<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Exchange ware at the second hand viz. Band, Ruffe, and Cuffe, lately out, and now newly dearned vp. Or a dialogue, acted in a shew in the famous Vniuersitie of Cambridge.</title>
            <title>Merrie dialogue, betweene Band, Cuffe, and Ruffe.</title>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1615</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 23 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 10 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2013-12">2013-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A03438</idno>
            <idno type="STC">STC 1356</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC S100661</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99836492</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99836492</idno>
            <idno type="VID">769</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A03438)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 769)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English Books, 1475-1640 ; 1164:01)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>Exchange ware at the second hand viz. Band, Ruffe, and Cuffe, lately out, and now newly dearned vp. Or a dialogue, acted in a shew in the famous Vniuersitie of Cambridge.</title>
                  <title>Merrie dialogue, betweene Band, Cuffe, and Ruffe.</title>
               </titleStmt>
               <editionStmt>
                  <edition>The second edition.</edition>
               </editionStmt>
               <extent>[24] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed by W. Stansby for Myles Partrich, and are to be sold at his shop neere Saint Dunstones Church-yard in Fleetstreet,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1615.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Signatures: A-C⁴.</note>
                  <note>The first leaf and the last leaf are blank.</note>
                  <note>Originally published earlier the same year as: A merrie dialogue, betweene Band, Cuffe, and Ruffe.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the Folger Shakespeare Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2012-08</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-08</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-11</date>
            <label>Mona Logarbo</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-11</date>
            <label>Mona Logarbo</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-02</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:769:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:769:1"/>
            <p>EXCHANGE WARE AT THE SECOND HAND, VIZ.</p>
            <p>Band, Ruffe, <hi>and</hi> Cuffe, <hi>lately out, and now newly</hi> dearned vp.</p>
            <p>OR <hi>A DIALOGVE, ACTED</hi> IN A SHEW IN THE famous Vniuerſitie of <hi>CAMBRIDGE.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The ſecond Edition.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON,</hi> Printed by <hi>W. Stansby</hi> for <hi>Myles Partrich,</hi> and are to be ſold at his ſhop neere Saint <hi>Dunſtones</hi> Church-yard in Fleetſtreet. 1615.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="poem">
            <pb facs="tcp:769:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:769:2"/>
            <head>RVFFE, CVFFE, AND BANDS COM<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>PLAINT AGAINST THE PRINTER.</head>
            <l>VVHen th' Printer read the copy of our <hi>Iarrs,</hi>
            </l>
            <l>He <hi>attacht</hi> vs ſtreight as authors of ſome <hi>warrs:</hi>
            </l>
            <l>And like a <hi>Iudge th'arraignment</hi> did begin,</l>
            <l>With <hi>guiltie (yea or no)</hi> of ſuch like ſin.</l>
            <l>We that had <hi>words,</hi> yet knew not how to <hi>crie,</hi>
            </l>
            <l>
               <hi>Not guiltie,</hi> Sir, <hi>condemned</hi> were to die:</l>
            <l>And ſince in <hi>ſilence</hi> thus our plea did reſt,</l>
            <l>According to the lawe hee'd haue vs <hi>preſt.</hi>
            </l>
         </div>
         <div type="poem">
            <pb facs="tcp:769:3"/>
            <head>THE OWNERS APPEALE FROM M. PRINTER HIS FALSE IVDGEMENT.</head>
            <l>PRinter, you are miſtaken in their <hi>fault,</hi>
            </l>
            <l>And though he ſweares, that <hi>Band, Cuffe, Ruffe</hi> are naught,</l>
            <l>Yet thus the cauſe hee'd have you vnderſtand,</l>
            <l>He was <hi>bewitch't</hi> by this ſame <hi>Cuffe, Ruffe, Band.</hi>
            </l>
            <l>To doe him <hi>Iuſtice,</hi> then he doth deſire,</l>
            <l>Condemne this <hi>Ruffe, Cuffe, Band,</hi> vnto the <hi>fire.</hi>
            </l>
            <l>So ſhall you ſee your <hi>Iudgement</hi> will proue right,</l>
            <l>And ſo their <hi>faults</hi> ſhall ſooner come to <hi>light.</hi>
            </l>
         </div>
         <div type="poem">
            <pb facs="tcp:769:3"/>
            <head>A <hi>Jurie</hi> of <hi>Seamſters,</hi> and their ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dit vpon <hi>Band, Ruffe,</hi> and <hi>Cuffe.</hi>
            </head>
            <div n="1" type="part">
               <head>1.</head>
               <l>I View'd my <hi>wares,</hi> and found <hi>Bands caſe</hi> was good,</l>
               <l>And <hi>Ruffe</hi> and <hi>Cuffe,</hi> if rightly vnderſtood.</l>
               <l>The fault the Printers was; for he miſtooke,</l>
               <l>And made a <hi>writ of Error</hi> in the <hi>booke.</hi>
               </l>
               <closer>
                  <signed>M. Pus.</signed>
               </closer>
            </div>
            <div n="2" type="part">
               <head>2.</head>
               <l>LEt <hi>Iudgement</hi> trie to whom the <hi>faults</hi> belong,</l>
               <l>'T wil ſay, the <hi>Printer</hi> did <hi>Ruffe, Cuffe, Band</hi> wrong.</l>
               <closer>
                  <signed>M. T.</signed>
               </closer>
            </div>
            <div n="3" type="part">
               <head>3.</head>
               <l>I See no <hi>fault</hi> for which I <hi>iudge</hi> it meet,</l>
               <l>That <hi>Ruffe, Cuffe, Band</hi> ſhould here ſtand in a ſheet.</l>
               <closer>
                  <signed>M. A.</signed>
               </closer>
            </div>
            <div n="4" type="part">
               <pb facs="tcp:769:4"/>
               <head>4.</head>
               <l>THe work's well <hi>viewd,</hi> each man in it doth pry,</l>
               <l>It cannot ſcape the very <hi>Needles eye:</hi>
               </l>
               <l>Yet this be ſure, if ought had beene o'reſlipt,</l>
               <l>The <hi>fault</hi> by me ſhould not haue ſcap't <hi>vnript.</hi>
               </l>
               <closer>
                  <signed>M. H.</signed>
               </closer>
            </div>
            <div n="5" type="part">
               <head>5.</head>
               <l>NOt for to <hi>cleare</hi> you, <hi>Ruffe, Cuffe, Band,</hi> come I</l>
               <l>Hither to th' Tearme: but rather here to buy</l>
               <l>A prohibition for to make no more,</l>
               <l>Leſt by this <hi>art,</hi> we <hi>Seampſters</hi> grow but poore.</l>
               <closer>
                  <signed>M. L.</signed>
               </closer>
            </div>
            <div n="6" type="part">
               <head>6.</head>
               <l>MY <hi>verdit's</hi> this, The <hi>accuſer</hi> is in <hi>fault:</hi>
               </l>
               <l>To <hi>picke</hi> a <hi>hole</hi> in <hi>Ruffe, Cuffe, Band,</hi> 'tis naught.</l>
               <closer>
                  <signed>M. O.</signed>
               </closer>
            </div>
            <div n="7" type="part">
               <pb facs="tcp:769:4"/>
               <head>7.</head>
               <l>THey <hi>preſſe Ruffe, Cuffe,</hi> &amp; <hi>Band:</hi> (what reaſon's in't)</l>
               <l>And yet deſire, they ſtill ſhould ſtand in <hi>print.</hi>
               </l>
               <closer>
                  <signed>M. B.</signed>
               </closer>
            </div>
            <div n="8" type="part">
               <head>8.</head>
               <l>THinke not your <hi>face</hi> ſo <hi>good,</hi> as <hi>need no band:</hi>
               </l>
               <l>Dare not to <hi>ſpoile</hi> great <hi>Ruffe;</hi> ſet not your <hi>hand,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Cuffe</hi> to diſgrace. All <hi>Linnen</hi> els will <hi>take</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Vp</hi> armes for <hi>Ruffe,</hi> and <hi>Cuffe,</hi> and <hi>Band,</hi> and make</l>
               <l>Their enemies like <hi>Friers, wool-ward</hi> to lie,</l>
               <l>Or <hi>weare</hi> a <hi>Diſhclout,</hi> yet afore they die.</l>
               <closer>
                  <signed>M. H.</signed>
               </closer>
            </div>
            <div n="9" type="part">
               <head>9.</head>
               <l>THe <hi>faults</hi> in <hi>Ruffe, Cuffe, Band,</hi> are whoſe, doe you thinke?</l>
               <l>The <hi>Printers?</hi> I. He ſpoild them with his <hi>Inke.</hi>
               </l>
               <closer>
                  <signed>M. I.</signed>
               </closer>
            </div>
            <div n="10" type="part">
               <pb facs="tcp:769:5"/>
               <head>10.</head>
               <l>WHat though the <hi>Printer Ruffe, Cuffe, Band</hi> hath ſtayn'd?</l>
               <l>Ile get it forth, or elſe let me be blam'd.</l>
               <l>For all his blacke <hi>foule</hi> fingers neuer feare,</l>
               <l>But that the <hi>Landreſſe</hi> ſhe can make them cleare.</l>
               <closer>
                  <signed>M. D.</signed>
               </closer>
            </div>
            <div n="11" type="part">
               <head>11.</head>
               <l>IF this <hi>Ruffe, Cuffe,</hi> and <hi>Band</hi> condemned are,</l>
               <l>Weele looke vnto the <hi>Linnen,</hi> that we weare.</l>
               <l>Did you deſire good <hi>Ware,</hi> you'd rather plead,</l>
               <l>The <hi>owner</hi> ſure hath <hi>ſpunne</hi> a <hi>goodly thread.</hi>
               </l>
               <closer>
                  <signed>M. D.</signed>
               </closer>
            </div>
            <div n="12" type="part">
               <head>12.</head>
               <l>WHe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> 
                  <hi>Cuffe</hi> at the <hi>Barre</hi> is forſt to hold his <hi>hand,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>And there condemned is with <hi>Ruffe</hi> &amp; <hi>Band,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>You that can ſee in them there's ſuch defects,</l>
               <l>High time it is to looke vnto your <hi>necks.</hi>
               </l>
               <closer>
                  <signed>M. E.</signed>
               </closer>
            </div>
         </div>
         <div type="poem">
            <pb facs="tcp:769:5"/>
            <head>The Owners deſire.</head>
            <l>THe <hi>faults</hi> that may in <hi>Ruffe, Cuffe, Band</hi> be nam'd,</l>
            <l>Will ſurely make the <hi>Owner</hi> more then blam'd;</l>
            <l>You will <hi>condemne</hi> him for what he miſtooke:</l>
            <l>Yet ſtill he craues, you'd let him haue <hi>his booke.</hi>
            </l>
         </div>
         <div type="poem">
            <head>
               <hi>M.</hi> Stitchwels ſentence.</head>
            <l>THe Printer ſeekes ſome way to bring about,</l>
            <l>That he the <hi>ſecond</hi> time might <hi>ſet Ruffe</hi> out,</l>
            <l>With <hi>Cuffe</hi> and <hi>Band.</hi> The <hi>Owner</hi> doth begin</l>
            <l>To ſeeke ſome way, that he may <hi>call</hi> them <hi>in.</hi>
            </l>
            <l>Thus to pleaſe both, &amp; grant them their requeſt,</l>
            <l>My <hi>ſentence</hi> is, The <hi>Booke</hi> ſhall be <hi>repreſt.</hi>
            </l>
         </div>
         <div type="poem">
            <head>Vpon the <hi>ſecond</hi> Edition.</head>
            <l>
               <hi>BAnd, Ruffe</hi> and <hi>Cuffe,</hi> at firſt ſo well did goe</l>
            <l>
               <hi>Through Stitch,</hi> as nought might added be therto.</l>
            <pb facs="tcp:769:6"/>
            <l>Yet in my mind they now ſeeme well enrich't,</l>
            <l>Since by the Printer, they haue bene <hi>double ſtitcht.</hi>
            </l>
            <closer>
               <signed>M. <hi>Burſe.</hi>
               </signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="poem">
            <l>
               <hi>WAre</hi> ne're the worſe for <hi>wearing?</hi> 'twas much afore.</l>
            <l>But now <hi>new waſht and ſtarcht,</hi> 'tis thus much more.</l>
            <l>You'le not loſe <hi>tweluepence</hi> by it (marke what you giue)</l>
            <l>
               <hi>Weare</hi> it and <hi>vſe't,</hi> as long as ere you liue.</l>
            <closer>
               <signed>M. <hi>Exchange.</hi>
               </signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="poem">
            <head>To the <hi>Cheapner.</hi>
            </head>
            <l>DOe you heare, Sir? one word more:</l>
            <l>Pray let me know,</l>
            <l>What is the vtmoſt <hi>farthing</hi> youle beſtow?</l>
            <l>To <hi>ſell</hi> at ſuch a <hi>rate,</hi> there's none can liue.</l>
            <l>But ſince no more y'are minded for to giue,</l>
            <l>Harke in your eare (I hope you'le not reueale it)</l>
            <l>It <hi>cost</hi> me ſo, or I in trouth did ſteale it.</l>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="dialogue">
            <pb facs="tcp:769:6"/>
            <head>A Merrie Dialogue betvveene BAND, CVFFE, and RVFFE.</head>
            <floatingText xml:lang="eng" type="dramatis_personae">
               <body>
                  <head>ACTORS.</head>
                  <list>
                     <item>Band,</item>
                     <item>Cuffe and</item>
                     <item>Ruffe.</item>
                  </list>
               </body>
            </floatingText>
            <stage>Enter BAND and CVFFE.</stage>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Band.</speaker>
               <p>CVFFE, where art thou?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Cuffe.</speaker>
               <p>Heere at <hi>hand.</hi>
               </p>
            </sp>
            <stage>ENTER RVFFE.</stage>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Ruffe.</speaker>
               <p>WHere is this <hi>Cuffe?</hi>
               </p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Cuffe.</speaker>
               <p>Almoſt at your <hi>Elbow.</hi>
               </p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <pb facs="tcp:769:7"/>
               <speaker>Ruffe.</speaker>
               <p>OH <hi>Band,</hi> art thou there? I thought thou haddeſt beene <hi>worne</hi> out of date by this time, or <hi>ſhrunke</hi> in the <hi>wetting</hi> at leaſt.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Band.</speaker>
               <p>What? doe you thinke I am afraid of your great words? no, you ſhall know that there be men of <hi>faſhion</hi> in place, as well as your ſelfe.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Cuffe.</speaker>
               <p>Good <hi>Band,</hi> doe not <hi>fret</hi> ſo.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Band.</speaker>
               <p>A ſcurvie <hi>ſhag-ragge</hi> Gentleman, new come out of the <hi>North,</hi> a <hi>Punie,</hi> a <hi>Freſhman,</hi> come vp hither to learne <hi>faſhions</hi> and ſeeke to expell me?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Cuffe.</speaker>
               <p>Nay: if you bee ſo <hi>broad</hi> with him, <hi>Band,</hi> we ſhall haue a <hi>fray</hi> preſently.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Ruffe.</speaker>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">He iuſtles <hi>B.</hi> and <hi>C.</hi> ſtayes him.</note>Sir, Ile pull downe you <hi>Coller</hi> from you.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Cuffe.</speaker>
               <p>It was fit time for mee to ſtay you vp, for I am ſure you were a <hi>falling Band.</hi>
               </p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Ruffe.</speaker>
               <p>Well, <hi>Band,</hi> for all you are ſo <hi>ſtiffe,</hi> Ile make you <hi>limber</hi> enough before I haue done with you.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Band.</speaker>
               <p>No, <hi>Hodge Poker,</hi> its more then you can doe.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Ruffe.</speaker>
               <p>Sfoot, let me come to him: well, <hi>Band,</hi> let mee catch you in another place, and I will make <hi>cut-worke</hi> of you.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Band.</speaker>
               <p>Ther's ne're a <hi>Spaniſh Ruffe</hi> of you all can doe it.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <pb facs="tcp:769:7"/>
               <speaker>Cuffe.</speaker>
               <p>Sfoot, if theſe two ſhould goe together by the eares and hurt one another, <hi>Cuffe</hi> would be in a fine <hi>plight:</hi> would he not?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Ruffe.</speaker>
               <p>Well, <hi>Band,</hi> looke to thy ſelfe, for if I meet thee, I will <hi>lace</hi> thee <hi>roundly.</hi>
               </p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Band.</speaker>
               <p>
                  <hi>Lace</hi> me? thou wouldeſt be <hi>laced</hi> thy ſelfe, <hi>Ruffe:</hi> for this is the very truth, thou art a <hi>plaine</hi> Knaue.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Cuffe.</speaker>
               <p>If they talke of <hi>lacing,</hi> I were beſt looke about my ſelfe.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Ruffe.</speaker>
               <p>Dareſt thou meet me in the field?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Band.</speaker>
               <p>In the field? why? thou art but an ef<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minate fellow, <hi>Ruffe;</hi> for all thou art ſo well <hi>ſet:</hi> but at what weapon?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Ruffe.</speaker>
               <p>Nay, I will giue thee that aduantage, bring thou what weapons thou wilt, I ſcorne to make any thing of thee, <hi>Band,</hi> but <hi>needle-worke.</hi>
               </p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Band.</speaker>
               <p>Sfoot, thou ſhalt know, a Gentleman and a Souldier ſcornes thy proffer.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Ruffe.</speaker>
               <p>A Souldier?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Cuffe.</speaker>
               <p>Did you not heare of the great <hi>Bands</hi> went ouer of late?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Ruffe.</speaker>
               <p>Where did you <hi>ſerue?</hi> in the Lowe Countries?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Cuffe.</speaker>
               <p>It may be ſo, for I am ſure he is a <hi>Hol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land Band.</hi>
               </p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Band.</speaker>
               <p>Where I haue ſerued, it is no matter: but I am ſure I haue beene <hi>preſſed</hi> oft.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Cuffe.</speaker>
               <p>Truely, his <hi>Landreſſe</hi> will beare him witneſſe thereof.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <pb facs="tcp:769:8"/>
               <speaker>Ruff.</speaker>
               <p>
                  <hi>Preſſe</hi> mee no <hi>preſsings:</hi> Ile make you know that <hi>Ruffe</hi> is <hi>ſteeled</hi> to the backe, if I had my <hi>ſticke</hi> here, you ſhould feele it.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Band.</speaker>
               <p>Nay, bragger, it is not your great words can carie it away ſo; giue <hi>Band</hi> but a <hi>hemme,</hi> and hee will be for you at any time, name the place, the time and houre of our meeting.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Ruffe.</speaker>
               <p>The place, the <hi>Paper-mills,</hi> where I wil teare thee into <hi>Rags,</hi> before I haue done with thee: the time, to morrow in the after-noone about one: but doe you heare? wee will fight <hi>ſingle,</hi> you ſhall not be <hi>double, Band.</hi>
               </p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Cuffe.</speaker>
               <p>Now I perceiue, the <hi>Spaniard</hi> and the <hi>Hollander</hi> will to it roundly.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Ruffe.</speaker>
               <p>But doe you heare? once more doe not ſay at our next meeting you forgot the time.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Cuffe.</speaker>
               <p>No, I dare warrant you, there is no man more carefull of the time then he: for I am ſure he hath alwayes at the leaſt a dozen <hi>Clockes</hi> about him.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Ruffe.</speaker>
               <p>Farewell then.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Band.</speaker>
               <p>Then farewell.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Cuffe.</speaker>
               <p>Nay, you ſhall not part ſo, you will go into the fieldes, and know not what fighting meanes: a couple of <hi>white liuered</hi> fellowes, your <hi>Landreſſe</hi> will make you both as <hi>white</hi> as a <hi>clout</hi> if ſhee liſt; If you lacke <hi>beating,</hi> ſhee'l <hi>beate</hi> you, Ile warrant you, ſhee'l ſo <hi>clap</hi> your ſides toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, that they ſhall bee <hi>beaten</hi> out in once or
<pb facs="tcp:769:8"/> twice ha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>dling; why? I haue known her leaue her <hi>markes</hi> behinde her a whole weeke after, ſheell quickely beate you <hi>Blacke</hi> and <hi>Blew,</hi> for I am ſure ſhee'll ſcarce <hi>waſh white</hi> before ſhee <hi>ſtarch.</hi>
               </p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Band.</speaker>
               <p>Well, remember the time and place, <hi>Ruffe.</hi>
               </p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Cuffe.</speaker>
               <p>Well, remember your ſelues and Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtris <hi>Stitchwel,</hi> one to whom you haue beene both beholding in your dayes.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Band.</speaker>
               <p>Who? Miſtris <hi>Stitchwell,</hi> by this light I know her not.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Cuffe.</speaker>
               <p>No, nor you neither?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Ruffe.</speaker>
               <p>Nor I, I ſweare by all the <hi>Gumme</hi> and <hi>Blew-ſtarch</hi> in Chriſtendome.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Cuffe.</speaker>
               <p>I thought ſo, why its the <hi>Sempſter,</hi> one that both you had beene <hi>vndone,</hi> had it not bene for her: but what talke I of your <hi>vndoing?</hi> I ſay Miſtris <hi>Stitchwel</hi> the <hi>Sempſter</hi> was the very <hi>maker</hi> of you both, yet thus little doe you re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gard her: but it is the common cuſtome of you all, when you come to bee ſo great as you are, you forget from what houſe you come.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Ruffe.</speaker>
               <p>Sfoote, <hi>Ruffe</hi> careth not a <hi>pinne</hi> for her.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Band.</speaker>
               <p>Nor <hi>Band</hi> a <hi>button.</hi>
               </p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Cuffe.</speaker>
               <p>Well, <hi>Band</hi> and <hi>Ruffe,</hi> you were beſt both of you to take heede of her, you knowe ſhee <hi>ſet</hi> you both in the <hi>Stockes</hi> once before, and if ſhee catch you againe, it is a hundreth to
<pb facs="tcp:769:9"/> one, if ſhe <hi>hang</hi> you not both vp, for ſhe hath got <hi>ſtrings</hi> already.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Ruffe.</speaker>
               <p>Meet me, if thou dareſt.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Band.</speaker>
               <p>The place the <hi>Paper-mils,</hi> the hower to morrow at one.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Cuffe.</speaker>
               <p>Since you will goe, goe; but heare me, if you goe, looke at me well; as little a fellow as I am, I will come and <hi>Cuffe</hi> you both out of the fields; if I doe not, ſay, <hi>Cuffe</hi> is no man of his <hi>hands.</hi>
               </p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Ruffe.</speaker>
               <p>Alas poore ſhrimpe, thou art nothing in my <hi>hands.</hi>
               </p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Cuffe.</speaker>
               <p>If you goe, you ſhall neuer ſay that <hi>Cuffe</hi> came of a <hi>ſleeueleſſe</hi> errand: Ile <hi>binde</hi> your <hi>hands</hi> (I warrant you) for ſtriking.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Band.</speaker>
               <p>Say and hold.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Ruffe.</speaker>
               <p>Remember the <hi>Paper-mils.</hi>
               </p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Cuffe.</speaker>
               <p>And you bee ſo chollericke, Ile euen <hi>pinne</hi> you both in, as ſoone as I come home: can you not decide the quarrell betweene your ſelues without a field? I had thought you had beene a little more milde, <hi>Ruffe.</hi> You were a horrible <hi>Puritane</hi> the other day, and very <hi>pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciſe, Ruffe.</hi>
               </p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Ruffe.</speaker>
               <p>Hang him, baſe Raſcall: would he not make any man mad, to ſee ſuch a — that durſt not (ſcarce) peepe out, before <hi>Collar</hi> came to Towne, now to ſwagger thus?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Cuffe.</speaker>
               <p>Come, you ſhall be friends, <hi>Band.</hi>
               </p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <pb facs="tcp:769:9"/>
               <speaker>Band.</speaker>
               <p>Friends with him? ſuch a baſe Raſcall? he is a very <hi>threed-bare</hi> fellow: I ſcorne, but my man <hi>Collar</hi> ſhould goe as well as hee euery day in the weeke, and be friends with him.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Ruffe.</speaker>
               <p>Thy man, <hi>Coller?</hi> thy <hi>Maſter,</hi> thou wouldeſt haue ſaid, I am ſure hee is thy <hi>vphol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der.</hi>
               </p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Cuffe.</speaker>
               <p>Nay, ſurely he is his <hi>Maſter,</hi> at leaſt his <hi>Maker:</hi> for <hi>Bands</hi> make <hi>rags; Rags</hi> make <hi>Paper, Paper</hi> makes <hi>Paſt-board,</hi> and <hi>Paſt-board</hi> makes <hi>Collar;</hi> and I thinke that this is a <hi>ſtiffe argument</hi> that he is his <hi>Maſter.</hi>
               </p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Ruffe.</speaker>
               <p>Well, be he what he will, if I catch his <hi>Collar,</hi> Ile <hi>cut</hi> him in <hi>iags,</hi> let me but claſpe him, and Ile make him for ſtirring.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Cuffe.</speaker>
               <p>But you ſhall not. Haue you not Friends and Neighbours ynow to end this con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trouerſie, but you muſt goe into the fields, and there cut the <hi>threed</hi> of your liues? wee'l haue none of that: come chooſe you an Vmpire, <hi>Band,</hi> for it ſhall be ſo.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Band.</speaker>
               <p>Since you will force me to it, if <hi>Ruffe</hi> be content, I am willing.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Cuffe.</speaker>
               <p>
                  <hi>Ruffe,</hi> you ſhall be content.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Ruffe.</speaker>
               <p>If I ſhall, then I muſt, let him name him.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Band.</speaker>
               <p>If I may chooſe, Ile haue Maſter <hi>Hand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kerchiefe.</hi>
               </p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Cuffe.</speaker>
               <p>Nay, ſtay there, he is a moſt filthy <hi>Sni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veling</hi>
                  <pb facs="tcp:769:10"/> fellow, &amp; a notable lawyer; he will <hi>wipe</hi> your <hi>Noſe</hi> of all, if you <hi>put</hi> the <hi>caſe</hi> to him: but what ſay you to <hi>Shirt?</hi>
               </p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Ruffe.</speaker>
               <p>He is a <hi>ſhifting</hi> knaue, and one, to whom <hi>Band,</hi> a little before hath beene much <hi>beholding.</hi> Why, they were <hi>ioyned</hi> a long time together in friendſhip.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Cuffe.</speaker>
               <p>Why, then goe to Maſter <hi>Cap,</hi> the <hi>headman</hi> of the Towne.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Band.</speaker>
               <p>No, I denie that, he is a very bad Iuſtice, you may haue him <hi>wrought</hi> on any <hi>ſide</hi> for mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nie.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Ruffe.</speaker>
               <p>Ile tell you what, then we will goe to my Lord <hi>Corpus</hi> himſelfe.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Band.</speaker>
               <p>He is not in Towne.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Ruffe.</speaker>
               <p>He is, for I ſaw <hi>Sock,</hi> his chiefe Foote<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man heere yeſterday.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Cuffe.</speaker>
               <p>Heer's adoe with you, and my Lord <hi>Corpus,</hi> indeed, I would you were both hanged about his necke for me. But I ſee, this ſtrife will neuer be ended, til I be Arbitrator my ſelfe, you know, I am equally allied to you both: ſhall I be Moderator betweene you?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Band and Ruffe.</speaker>
               <p>Content.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Cuffe.</speaker>
               <p>Well then, thus I pronounce. <hi>Ruffe</hi> ſhall be moſt accounted of amongſt the <hi>Clergie,</hi> for he is the grauer Fellow. (Although I know, the <hi>Puritans</hi> will not greatly care for him, hee hath ſuch a deale of <hi>ſetting,</hi> and they loue <hi>ſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding</hi>
                  <pb facs="tcp:769:10"/> better.) As for you, <hi>Band,</hi> you ſhall bee moſt made of amongſt the young <hi>Gallants</hi> (al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>though ſometimes they ſhall vſe <hi>Ruffe,</hi> for a <hi>fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhion,</hi> but not otherwiſe;) how euer, you neede not regard the giddie headed multitude, let them doe as they liſt, ſometimes reſpecting one, ſometimes the other: but when you come to the <hi>Counſailors,</hi> and men of <hi>Law,</hi> which know right from wrong, acknowledging both your <hi>Worths</hi> to be equall, they ſhall preferre neither, but vſe the kindneſſe of you both, wearing both a <hi>Band</hi> and a <hi>Ruffe;</hi> how ſay you, are you both content?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Band and Ruffe.</speaker>
               <p>We are.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Ruffe.</speaker>
               <p>Then goe before me to the next Ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerne, and Ile follow after with a <hi>Band</hi> of your friendſhip drawne, which I hope theſe Gentle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men will <hi>ſeale</hi> with their <hi>hands.</hi>
               </p>
            </sp>
            <stage>Exeunt Band and Ruffe.</stage>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Cuffe.</speaker>
               <l>Claw me, and Ile claw thee, the prouerb goes,</l>
               <l>Let it be true in that our Muſe here ſhoes,</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Cuffe</hi> graceth <hi>hand, Cuffes</hi> debtors <hi>hands</hi> remaine,</l>
               <l>Let <hi>hands</hi> clap me, and Ile <hi>Cuffe</hi> them againe.</l>
            </sp>
            <stage>Exit Cuffe.</stage>
         </div>
         <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
