<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Ben Ionson, his Case is alterd As it hath beene sundry times acted by the children of the Blacke-friers.</title>
            <title>Case is alterd</title>
            <author>Jonson, Ben, 1573?-1637.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1609</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 171 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 36 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-12">2011-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A04638</idno>
            <idno type="STC">STC 14757</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC S121512</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99856692</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99856692</idno>
            <idno type="VID">22306</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A04638)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 22306)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 757:03)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>Ben Ionson, his Case is alterd As it hath beene sundry times acted by the children of the Blacke-friers.</title>
                  <title>Case is alterd</title>
                  <author>Jonson, Ben, 1573?-1637.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[74] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed [by Nicholas Okes] for Bartholomew Sutton, dwelling in Paules Church-yard neere the great north doore of Paules Church,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>At London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1609.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Printer's name from STC.</note>
                  <note>Running title reads: A pleasant comedy, called The case is alterd.</note>
                  <note>Signatures: A-I⁴ K²  (-K2).</note>
                  <note>Imperfect; all after I3 lacking.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the British Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2009-06</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-07</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-12</date>
            <label>John Pas</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-12</date>
            <label>John Pas</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-06</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:22306:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:22306:1"/>
            <p>BEN: IONSON, <hi>HIS</hi> CASE IS ALTERD.</p>
            <p>As it hath beene ſundry times Acted by the Children of Blacke-friers.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>AT LONDON</hi> Printed for <hi>Bartholomew Sutton,</hi> dwelling in Paules Church-yard neere the great north doore of S. Paules Church. 1609.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="play">
            <pb facs="tcp:22306:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:22306:2"/>
            <head>A pleaſant Comedy called, the <hi>Caſe is Alterd.</hi>
            </head>
            <div n="1" type="act">
               <head>Actus primi,</head>
               <div n="1" type="scene">
                  <head>Scaena prima.</head>
                  <stage>
                     <hi>Sound? after a flouriſh:</hi> Iuniper <hi>a Cobler is diſcouered, ſitting at worke in his ſhoppe and ſinging.</hi>
                  </stage>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Iuniper, Onion, Antony Baladino.</speaker>
                     <l>
                        <seg rend="decorInit">Y</seg>OV <hi>wofull wights giue eare a while,</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>And marke the tenor of my ſtile,</hi>
                     </l>
                     <stage>Enter Onion in haſt.</stage>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Which ſhall ſuch trembling hearts vnfold</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>As ſeldome hath to fore bene told.</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Such chances rare and dolefull newes</hi>
                     </l>
                     <stage>
                        <hi>Oni.</hi> fellow <hi>Iuniper</hi>
                     </stage>
                     <l>Peace a Gods name.</l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>As may attempt your wits to muſe.</hi>
                     </l>
                     <stage>
                        <hi>Oni.</hi> Gods ſo, heere man.</stage>
                     <l>A pox a God on you.</l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>And cauſe ſuch trickling teares to paſſe,</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Except your hearts be flint or braſſe:</hi>
                     </l>
                     <stage>
                        <hi>Oni.</hi> Iuniper, Iuniper.</stage>
                     <l>
                        <hi>To heare the newes which</hi> I <hi>ſhall tell,</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>That in</hi> Caſtella <hi>once befell.</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>Sbloud, where didſt thou learne to corrupt a man in the midſt of a verſe, ha?</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Onion.</speaker>
                     <p>Gods lid man, ſeruice is ready to go vp man, you muſt ſlip on your coate and come in, we lacke waiters pitty<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fully.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Iunip.</speaker>
                     <p>A pittifull hearing, for now muſt I of a merry Cobler become mourning creature.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <stage>Exit Onion.</stage>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Onion.</speaker>
                     <p>Well youle come.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Iunip.</speaker>
                     <p>
                        <hi>Preſto.</hi> Go to, a word to the wiſe, away, flie? vaniſh: Lye there the weedes that I diſdaine to weare.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <pb facs="tcp:22306:3" rendition="simple:additions"/>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Anto.</speaker>
                     <p>God ſaue you Maiſter <hi>Iuniper.</hi>
                     </p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Iuni.</speaker>
                     <p>What <hi>Signior Antonio Balladino,</hi> welcome ſweet <hi>Ingle,</hi>
                     </p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Anto.</speaker>
                     <p>And how do you ſir?</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Iuni.</speaker>
                     <p>Faith you ſee, put to my ſhifts here as poore retainers be oftentimes, ſirrah <hi>Antony</hi> ther's one of my fellowes mighte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly enamored of thee, and I faith you ſlaue, now your come I'le bring you together, i'ts <hi>Peter Onion,</hi> the groome of the hal, do you know him.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Anto.</speaker>
                     <p>No not yet, I aſſure you.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Iuni.</speaker>
                     <p>O he is one as right of thy humour as may be, a plaine ſimple Raſcal, a true dunce, marry he hath bene anotable vilaine in his time: he is in loue, ſirrah, with awench, &amp; I haue preferd thee to him, thou ſhalt make him ſome prety <hi>Paradox</hi> or ſome <hi>Aligory,</hi> how does my coate ſit? well.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Anto.</speaker>
                     <p>I very well.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <stage>Enter Onion.</stage>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Oni.</speaker>
                     <p>Na Gods ſo, fellow <hi>Iuniper,</hi> come away.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Iun.</speaker>
                     <p>Art thou there mad ſlaue, I come with a powder?. Sirrah fellow <hi>Onion.</hi> I muſt haue you peruſe this Gentleman well, and doe him good offices of reſpect and kindneſſe, as in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtance ſhall be giuen.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Anto.</speaker>
                     <p>Nay good maiſter <hi>Onion</hi> what do you meane, I pray you ſir you are to reſpectue in good faith.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Onion</speaker>
                     <p>I would not you ſhould thinke ſo ſir, for though I haue no learning, yet I honour a ſcholer in any ground of the earth ſir,</p>
                     <p>Shall I requeſt your name ſir?</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Anto.</speaker>
                     <p>My name is <hi>Antonio Balladino.</hi>
                     </p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Oni,</speaker>
                     <p>
                        <hi>Balladino?</hi> you are not <hi>Pageant</hi> Poet to the City of <hi>Mil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>laine</hi> ſir<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> are you.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Anto.</speaker>
                     <p>I ſupply the place ſir: when aworſe cannot be had ſir.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Oni.</speaker>
                     <p>I crie you mercy ſir, I loue you the better for that ſir, by Ieſu you muſt pardon me, I knew you not, but Il'd pray to be better acquainted with you ſir, I haue ſeene of your works.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Anto.</speaker>
                     <p>I am at your ſeruice good Maiſter <hi>Onion,</hi> but concer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning this maiden that you loue ſir? what is ſhe,</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Onion.</speaker>
                     <p>O did my fellow <hi>Iuniper</hi> tell you? marry ſir, ſhe is
<pb facs="tcp:22306:3" rendition="simple:additions"/>as one may ſay, but a poore mans child indeede, and for mine owne part I am no Gentleman borne I muſt confeſſe, but <hi>my mind to me a kingdome is</hi> truly.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Anto.</speaker>
                     <p>Truly a very good ſaying.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Onion.</speaker>
                     <p>T'is ſomewhat ſtale, but that's no matter.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Anto.</speaker>
                     <p>O t'is the better, ſuch things euer are like bread, which the ſtaler it is, the more holeſome.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Onion.</speaker>
                     <p>This is but a hungry compariſon in my iudgement.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Anto.</speaker>
                     <p>Why, I'le tell you, <hi>M. Onion,</hi> I do vſe as much ſtale ſtuffe, though I ſay it my ſelfe, as any man does in that kind I am ſure. Did you ſee the laſt <hi>Pageant,</hi> I ſet forth?</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Onion.</speaker>
                     <p>No faith ſir, but there goes a huge report on't.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Anto.</speaker>
                     <p>Why, you ſhal be one of my <hi>Maecen-aſſes,</hi> I'le giue you one of the bookes, O you'le like it admirably.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Oni.</speaker>
                     <p>Nay that's certaine, I'le get my fellow <hi>Iuniper</hi> to read it.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Anto.</speaker>
                     <p>Reade it ſir, I'le reade it to you.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Onion.</speaker>
                     <p>Tut then I ſhall not chuſe but like it.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Anto.</speaker>
                     <p>Why looke you ſir, I write ſo plaine, and keepe that old <hi>Decorum,</hi> that you muſt of neceſſitie like it; mary you ſhall haue ſome now (as for example, in plaies) that will haue eue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry day new trickes, and write you nothing but humours: in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deede this pleaſes the Gentlemen: but the common ſort they care not for't, they know not what to make on't, they looke for good matter, they, and are not edified with ſuch toyes.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Onion.</speaker>
                     <p>You are in the right, I'le not giue a halfepeny to ſee a thouſand on'hem. I was at one the laſt Tearme, but &amp; euer I ſee a more roguiſh thing, I am a peece of cheeſe, &amp; no <hi>onion,</hi> nothing but kings &amp; princes in it, the foole came not out a lot.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Anto.</speaker>
                     <p>True ſir, they would haue me make ſuch plaies, but as I tell hem, and they'le giue me twenty pound a play, I'le not raiſe my vaine.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Onion.</speaker>
                     <p>No, it were a vaine thing, and you ſhould ſir.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Anto.</speaker>
                     <p>Tut giue me the penny, giue me the peny, I care not for the Gentlemen I, let me haue a good ground, no matter for the pen the plot ſhall carry it.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Onion.</speaker>
                     <p>Indeed that's right, you are in print already for the
<pb facs="tcp:22306:4"/>beſt plotter.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Anto.</speaker>
                     <p>I, I might as well ha bene put in for a dumb ſhew too.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Ont.</speaker>
                     <p>I marry ſir, I marle you were not, ſtand aſide ſir a while:</p>
                  </sp>
                  <stage>Enter an armd Sewer: ſome halfe dozen in mourning coates follow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing and paſſe by with ſeruice.</stage>
                  <stage>Enter Valentine.</stage>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Onion</speaker>
                     <p>How now friend, what are you there? be vncouered, Would you ſpeake with any man here?</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Valen,</speaker>
                     <p>I, or elſe I muſt Ira' returnd you no anſwer.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Oni.</speaker>
                     <p>Friend, you are ſomewhat to peremptory, let's craue your abſence: nay neuer ſcorne it, I am a little your better in this place.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Valen.</speaker>
                     <p>I do acknowledge it.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Onion.</speaker>
                     <p>Do you acknowledge it? nay then you ſhall go forth, Ile teach you how ſhall acknowledge it another time; go to, void, I muſt haue the hall purg'd, no ſetting vp of a reſt here, packe, begone.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Valen.</speaker>
                     <p>I pray you ſir is not your name <hi>Onion?</hi>
                     </p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Oni.</speaker>
                     <p>Your friend as you may vſe him, and <hi>M. Onion,</hi> ſay on.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Valen.</speaker>
                     <p>
                        <hi>M. Onion</hi> with a murraine, come come put off this Lyons hide, your eares haue diſcouered you, why <hi>Peter!</hi> do not I know you <hi>Peter?</hi>
                     </p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Onion.</speaker>
                     <p>Gods ſo, <hi>Valentine!</hi>
                     </p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Valen.</speaker>
                     <p>O can you take knowledge of me now ſir?</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Oni.</speaker>
                     <p>Good Lord, ſirra, how thou art altred with thy trauell?</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Valen.</speaker>
                     <p>Nothing ſo much as thou art with thine office, but ſirra, <hi>Onion</hi> is the <hi>Count Ferneze</hi> at home?</p>
                  </sp>
                  <stage>Exit Anthony.</stage>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Oni.</speaker>
                     <p>I <hi>Bully,</hi> he is aboue; and the Lord <hi>Paulo Ferneze,</hi> his ſon, and Maddam <hi>Aurelia,</hi> &amp; maddam <hi>Phaenixella,</hi> his daugh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters, But O <hi>Valentine?</hi>
                     </p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Valen.</speaker>
                     <p>How now man, how doſt thou?</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Oni.</speaker>
                     <p>Faith ſad, heauy, as a man of my coate ought to be.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Valen.</speaker>
                     <p>Why man, thou wert merry inough euen now.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Oni.</speaker>
                     <l>True, but thou knoweſt</l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>All creatures here ſoiorning, vpon this wretched earth,</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Sometimes haue a fit of mourning, as well as a fit of mirth.</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>O <hi>Valentine,</hi> mine old Lady is dead, man.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Valen.</speaker>
                     <p>Dead!</p>
                  </sp>
                  <pb facs="tcp:22306:4" rendition="simple:additions"/>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Oni.</speaker>
                     <p>I faith.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Valen.</speaker>
                     <p>When dyed ſhe?</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Onion.</speaker>
                     <p>Mary, to morrow ſhall be three months, ſhe was ſeene going to heauen they ſay, about ſome fiue weekes agone! how now? trickling teares, ha?</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Valen.</speaker>
                     <p>Faith thou haſt made me weepe with this newes.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Onion.</speaker>
                     <p>Faith thou haſt made me weepe with this newes.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Onion.</speaker>
                     <p>Why I haue done but the parte of an <hi>Onion,</hi> you muſt pardon me.</p>
                  </sp>
               </div>
               <div n="2" type="scene">
                  <head>Scaene. 2.</head>
                  <stage>
                     <hi>Enter the ſewer, paſſe by with ſeruice againe, the ſeruing-men take knowledge of</hi> Valentine <hi>as they goe.</hi> Iuniper <hi>ſalutes him.</hi>
                  </stage>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Iuni.</speaker>
                     <p>What <hi>Valentiue?</hi> fellow <hi>Onion,</hi> take my diſh I prithee you rogue ſirrah, tell me, how thou doſt, ſweet <hi>Ingle.</hi>
                     </p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Valen.</speaker>
                     <p>Faith, <hi>Iuniper,</hi> the better to ſee thee thus frolicke.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Iuni.</speaker>
                     <p>Nay, ſlid I am no changling, I am <hi>Iuniper</hi> ſtill.
<stage>Exit Oni.</stage> I keepe the priſtmate ha, you mad <hi>Hierogliphick,</hi> when ſhal we ſwagger.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Valen.</speaker>
                     <p>
                        <hi>Hierogliphick,</hi> what meaneſt thou by that.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Iuni.</speaker>
                     <p>Meane? Gods ſo, iſt not a good word man? what? ſtand vpon meaning with your freinds. <hi>Puh, Abſconde.</hi>
                     </p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Valen.</speaker>
                     <p>Why, but ſtay, ſtay, how long has this ſprightly humor haunted thee?</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Iuni.</speaker>
                     <p>Foe humour, a fooliſh naturall gift we haue in the <hi>Ae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quinoctiall.</hi>
                     </p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Valen.</speaker>
                     <p>Naturall, ſlid it may be ſupernaturall, this?</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Iuni.</speaker>
                     <p>
                        <hi>Valentine,</hi> I prithee ruminate thy ſelfe welcome. What <hi>fortuna de la Guerra.</hi>
                     </p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Valen.</speaker>
                     <l>O how pittifully are theſe words forc't.</l>
                     <l>As though they were pumpt out on's belly.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Iuni.</speaker>
                     <p>Sirrah <hi>Ingle,</hi> I thinke thou haſt ſeene all the ſtrange countries in Chriſtendome ſince thou wentſt?</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Valen.</speaker>
                     <p>I haue ſeene ſome <hi>Iuniper.</hi>
                     </p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Iuni.</speaker>
                     <p>You haue ſeene <hi>Conſtantinople?</hi>
                     </p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Valen.</speaker>
                     <p>I, that I haue.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <pb facs="tcp:22306:5"/>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Iuni.</speaker>
                     <p>And <hi>Ieruſalem,</hi> and the <hi>Indies,</hi> and <hi>Goodwine ſands,</hi> and the tower of <hi>Babylon,</hi> and <hi>Venice</hi> and all.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Valen.</speaker>
                     <p>I all; <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 words">
                           <desc>〈◊◊〉</desc>
                        </gap> and he haue a nimble tong, if he prac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſe to vault thus from one ſide of the world to another.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Iuni.</speaker>
                     <p>O it's a moſt heauenly thing to trauel, &amp; ſee countries, eſpecially at ſea, and a man had a pattent not to be ſicke.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Valen.</speaker>
                     <p>O ſea ſicke leſt, and full of the ſcuruie.</p>
                  </sp>
               </div>
               <div n="3" type="scene">
                  <head>Scaene 3.</head>
                  <stage>Enter Iuniper, Antonio, Sebaſtian, Martino, Vincentio, Balthaſar and Chriſtophero.</stage>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Seba.</speaker>
                     <p>
                        <hi>Valentine?</hi> welcome I faith how doſt ſirra?</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Mart.</speaker>
                     <p>How do you good <hi>Valentine.</hi>
                     </p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Vincen.</speaker>
                     <p>Troth, <hi>Valentine,</hi> I am glad to ſee you.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Balth.</speaker>
                     <p>Welcome ſweet rogue.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Sebaſt.</speaker>
                     <p>Before God he neuer lookt better in his life.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Balth.</speaker>
                     <p>And how iſt man? what, <hi>Alla Coragio.</hi>
                     </p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Valen.</speaker>
                     <p>Neuer better gentlemen I faith.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Iuni.</speaker>
                     <p>S'will here comes the ſteward.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Chriſt.</speaker>
                     <p>Why how now fellowes all here? and nobody to waight aboue now they are ready to riſe? looke vp one or two <hi>Signior Franceſco Colomia's man</hi> how doo's your good maiſter.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <stage>Exeunt Iuniper, Martino, Vincentio.</stage>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Valen.</speaker>
                     <p>In health ſir he will be here anon.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Chriſto.</speaker>
                     <p>Is he come home, then?</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Valen.</speaker>
                     <p>I ſir he is not paſt ſixe miles hence, he ſent me before to learne if <hi>Count Ferneze</hi> were here and returne him word.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Chriſto.</speaker>
                     <p>Yes, my Lord is here; and you may tel your maiſter he ſhal come very happily to take his leaue of Lord <hi>Paulo Fer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neze:</hi> who is now inſtantly to depart with other noble gentle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men, vpon ſpeciall ſeruice.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Valen.</speaker>
                     <p>I will tell him ſir.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Chriſto.</speaker>
                     <p>I pray you doe, fellowes make him drinke.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Valen.</speaker>
                     <p>Sirs, what ſeruice iſt they are imployed in?</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Sebaſt.</speaker>
                     <p>Why againſt the <hi>French</hi> they meane to haue a fling at <hi>Millaine</hi> againe they ſay.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <pb facs="tcp:22306:5" rendition="simple:additions"/>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Valen.</speaker>
                     <p>Who leades our forces, can you tell?</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Sebaſt.</speaker>
                     <p>Marry that do's Signior <hi>Maximilian?</hi> he is aboue, now.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Valen.</speaker>
                     <p>Who, <hi>Maximilian</hi> of <hi>Vicenza?</hi>
                     </p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Balt.</speaker>
                     <p>I he? do you know him?</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Valen.</speaker>
                     <p>Know him? O yes he's an excellent braue ſoldier.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Balt.</speaker>
                     <p>I ſo they ſay, but one of the moſt vaine glorious men in <hi>Europe.</hi>
                     </p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Valen.</speaker>
                     <p>He is indeed, marry exceeding valient.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Sebaſt.</speaker>
                     <p>And that is rare.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Balt.</speaker>
                     <p>What.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Sebaſt.</speaker>
                     <p>Why to ſee a vaineglorious man valient.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Valen.</speaker>
                     <p>Well he is ſo I aſſure you.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <stage>Enter Iuniper.</stage>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Iuni.</speaker>
                     <p>What no further yet, come on you precious raſcall, ſir <hi>Valentine,</hi> Ile giue you a health I faith, for the heauens you mad <hi>Capriceio,</hi> hold hooke and line.</p>
                  </sp>
               </div>
               <div n="4" type="scene">
                  <head>Scaene 4.</head>
                  <stage>Enter Lord Paulo Ferneze, his boy following him.</stage>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Pau.</speaker>
                     <p>Boy.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Boy.</speaker>
                     <p>My Lord.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Pau.</speaker>
                     <l>Sirrah go vp to <hi>Signior Angelio,</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>And pray him (if he can) deuiſe ſome meanes,</l>
                     <l>To leaue my father, and come ſpeake with me.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Boy</speaker>
                     <p>I will my Lord.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Pau.</speaker>
                     <l>Well heauen, be auſpicious in the euent;</l>
                     <l>For I do this againſt my <hi>Genius,</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>And yet my thoughts cannot propoſe a reaſon.</l>
                     <l>Why I ſhould feare, or faint thus in my hopes,</l>
                     <l>Of one ſo much endeered to my loue.</l>
                     <l>Some ſparke it is, kindled within the ſoule:</l>
                     <l>Whoſe light yet breaks not to the outward ſence,</l>
                     <l>That propagates this tymerous ſuſpect;</l>
                     <l>His actions neuer carried any face</l>
                     <l>Of change, or weaknes: then I iniury him?</l>
                     <l>In being thus cold conceited of his faith,</l>
                     <l>O here he comes.</l>
                     <stage>Enter Angels.</stage>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Ang.</speaker>
                     <p>How now ſweet Lord, whats the matter?</p>
                  </sp>
                  <pb facs="tcp:22306:6" rendition="simple:additions"/>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Pau.</speaker>
                     <l>Good faith his preſence makes me halfe aſhamd.</l>
                     <l>Of my ſtraid thoughts. <hi>Boy.</hi> Beſtow your ſelfe.</l>
                     <stage>Exit Boy.</stage>
                     <l>Where is my father, <hi>Signior Angelio.</hi>
                     </l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Ang.</speaker>
                     <p>Marry in the galery, where your Lordſhip left him.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Pau.</speaker>
                     <l>Thats well. Then <hi>Angelio</hi> I will be briefe.</l>
                     <l>Since time forbids the vſe of circumſtance,</l>
                     <l>How well you are receiued in my affection,</l>
                     <l>Let it appeare by this one inſtance, onely</l>
                     <l>That now I will deliuer to your truſt,</l>
                     <l>The deereſt ſecrets, treaſurd in my boſome,</l>
                     <l>Deare <hi>Angelio.</hi> You are not euery man,</l>
                     <l>But one, whome my election hath deſign'd,</l>
                     <l>As the true proper obiect of my ſoule:</l>
                     <l>I vrge not this t'inſinuate my deſert,</l>
                     <l>Or ſupple your tri'd temper, with ſoft phraſes;</l>
                     <l>True frendſhip lothes ſuch oyly complement:</l>
                     <l>But from th'aboundance of that loue, that flowes</l>
                     <l>Through all my ſpirits, is my ſpeech enforc'd.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Ang.</speaker>
                     <l>Before your Lordſhip do proceed too far,</l>
                     <l>Let me be bould to intimate thus much;</l>
                     <l>That what ſo ere your wiſedome hath t'expoſe,</l>
                     <l>Be it the waightieſt and moſt rich affaire,</l>
                     <l>That euer was included in your breaſt,</l>
                     <l>My faith ſhall poiſe it, if not—</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Pau.</speaker>
                     <l>O no more,</l>
                     <l>Thoſe words haue rapt me with their ſweet effects,</l>
                     <l>So freely breath'd, and ſo reſponſible,</l>
                     <l>To that which I endeuoured to extract,</l>
                     <l>Arguing a happy mixture of our ſoules.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Ange.</speaker>
                     <l>Why were there no ſuch <hi>ſympathy</hi> ſweete Lord?</l>
                     <l>Yet the impreſſure of thoſe ample fauours,</l>
                     <l>I haue deriu'd from your vnmatched ſpirit,</l>
                     <l>Would bind my faith to all obſeruances.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Pau.</speaker>
                     <l>How! fauours <hi>Angello,</hi> ô ſpeake not of them,</l>
                     <l>They are meere paintings, and import no merit,</l>
                     <l>Lookes my loue well? thereon my hopes are plac't:</l>
                     <pb facs="tcp:22306:6"/>
                     <l>Faith, that is bought with fauours, cannot laſt.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <stage>Enters Boy.</stage>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Boy.</speaker>
                     <p>My Lord.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Pau.</speaker>
                     <p>How now?</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Boy.</speaker>
                     <l>You are ſought for all about the houſe, within,</l>
                     <l>The <hi>Count</hi> your father cals for you.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Pau.</speaker>
                     <l>God, what croſſe euents do meet my purpoſes?</l>
                     <l>Now will he violently fret and grieue</l>
                     <l>That I am abſent. Boy, ſay I come preſently:</l>
                     <stage>Exit Boy.</stage>
                     <l>Sweet <hi>Angello,</hi> I cannot now inſiſt</l>
                     <l>Vpon particulars, I muſt ſerue the time</l>
                     <l>The maine of all this is, I am in loue.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Ange.</speaker>
                     <p>Why ſtarts your Lordſhip?</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Pau.</speaker>
                     <p>I thought I heard my father comming hither ward, liſt, ha?</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Ange.</speaker>
                     <p>I heare not any thing, it was but your imagination ſure.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Pau.</speaker>
                     <p>No?</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Ange.</speaker>
                     <p>No, I aſſure your Lordſhip.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Pau.</speaker>
                     <p>I would worke ſafely.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Ange.</speaker>
                     <p>Why, has he no knowledge of it then?</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Pau.</speaker>
                     <l>O no, no creature yet pertakes it but your ſelfe</l>
                     <l>In a third perſon, and beleeue me friend,</l>
                     <l>The world containes not now another ſpirit,</l>
                     <l>To whom I would reueile it. Harke, harke,</l>
                  </sp>
                  <stage>
                     <hi>Seruants. Signior Paulo.</hi> Lord <hi>Ferneze.</hi> within.</stage>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Ange.</speaker>
                     <l>A pox vpon thoſe brazen throated ſlaues,</l>
                     <l>What are they mad, trow?</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Pau.</speaker>
                     <l>Alas, blame not them,</l>
                     <l>Their ſeruices are (clock-like) to beſet,</l>
                     <l>Backward and forward, at their Lords command,</l>
                     <l>You know my father's wayward, and his humour</l>
                     <l>Muſt not receiue a check, for then all obiects,</l>
                     <l>Feede both his griefe and his impatience,</l>
                     <l>And thoſe affections in him, are like powder,</l>
                     <l>Apt to enflame with euery little ſparke,</l>
                     <pb facs="tcp:22306:7"/>
                     <l>And blow vp reaſon, therefore <hi>Angelo,</hi> peace.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <stage>within.
<sp>
                        <speaker>Count.</speaker>
                        <p>Why this is rare, is he not in the garden?</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Criſt.</speaker>
                        <p>I know not my Lord.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Count.</speaker>
                        <p>See, call him?</p>
                     </sp>
                  </stage>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Pau.</speaker>
                     <p>He is comming this way, let's withdraw a little.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <stage>Exeunt.</stage>
                  <stage>within. <hi>Seruants.</hi> Signior <hi>Paulo,</hi> Lord <hi>Ferneze,</hi> Lord <hi>Paulo.</hi>
                  </stage>
               </div>
               <div n="5" type="scene">
                  <head>Scaene 5.</head>
                  <stage>Enter Count Ferneze, Maximilian, Aurelia, Phoe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nixella, Sebaſt. Balthaſar.</stage>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Count.</speaker>
                     <p>VVHere ſhould he be, trow? did you looke in the armory?</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Sebaſt.</speaker>
                     <p>No my Lord.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Count.</speaker>
                     <p>No, why there? ô who would keepe ſuch drones?
<stage>Exeunt Sebaſt. and Baltha.</stage> How now, ha ye found him?</p>
                     <stage>Enter Martino.</stage>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Mart.</speaker>
                     <p>No my Lord.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Count.</speaker>
                     <l>No my Lord, I ſhall haue ſhortly all my family</l>
                     <l>Speake nought, but no my Lord, where is <hi>Chriſtophero,</hi>
                     </l>
                     <stage>Enter Chrriſtophero.</stage>
                     <l>Looke how he ſtands, you ſleep y knaue,</l>
                     <stage>Exit Martino.</stage>
                     <l>What is he not in the Garden?</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Chriſto.</speaker>
                     <p>No my good Lord.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Count.</speaker>
                     <p>Your good Lord, ô how this ſmels of fennell.
<stage>Enter Sebaſt Baltha.</stage> You haue bene in the garden it appeares, well, well.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Balth.</speaker>
                     <p>We cannot find him my Lord.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Sebaſt.</speaker>
                     <p>He is not in the armory.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Count.</speaker>
                     <p>He is not, he is no where, is he?</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Maxi.</speaker>
                     <p>Count <hi>Ferneze.</hi>
                     </p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Count.</speaker>
                     <p>Signior.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Maxi.</speaker>
                     <p>Preſerue your patience honorable <hi>Count.</hi>
                     </p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Count.</speaker>
                     <l>Patience? a Saint would looſe his patience to be croſt,</l>
                     <pb facs="tcp:22306:7"/>
                     <l>As I am with a ſort of motly braines,</l>
                     <l>See ſee, how like a neſt of Rookes they ſtand,</l>
                     <stage>Enter Onion.</stage>
                     <l>Gaping on one another! now <hi>Diligence,</hi> what news bring you?</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Oni.</speaker>
                     <p>Ant pleaſe your honour.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Count.</speaker>
                     <p>Tut, tut, leaue pleaſing of my honour <hi>Diligence,</hi> you double with we, come.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Oni.</speaker>
                     <p>How: does he find fault with <hi>Pleaſe his Honour.</hi> S'wounds it has begun a ſeruing mans ſpeech, euer ſince I be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>longd to the blew order: I know not how it may ſhew, now I am in blacke, but—</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Count.</speaker>
                     <p>Whats that, you mutter ſir? will you proceed?</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Oni.</speaker>
                     <p>Ant like your good Lordſhip.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Count.</speaker>
                     <p>Yet more; Gods precious.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Oni.</speaker>
                     <p>What, do not this like him neither?</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Count.</speaker>
                     <p>What ſay you ſir knaue?</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Oni.</speaker>
                     <p>Mary I ſay your Lordſhip were beſt to ſet me to ſchoole againe, to learne how to deliuer a meſſage.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Count.</speaker>
                     <p>What do you take exceptions at me then.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Oni.</speaker>
                     <p>Exception? I take no exceptions, but by Gods ſo your humours—</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Count.</speaker>
                     <p>Go to you are a Raskall, hold your tongue.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Oni.</speaker>
                     <p>Your Lordſhips poore ſeruant, I.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Count.</speaker>
                     <p>Tempt not my patience.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Oni.</speaker>
                     <p>Why I hope I am no ſpirit, am I?</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Maxi.</speaker>
                     <p>My Lord, command your Steward to correct the ſlaue.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Oni.</speaker>
                     <p>Correct him, S'bloud come you and correct him and you haue a minde to it, correct him, that's a good ieſt I faith, the Steward and you both, come and correct him.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Count.</speaker>
                     <p>Nay ſee, away with him, pull his cloth ouer his eares.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Oni.</speaker>
                     <p>Cloth? tell me of your cloth, here's your cloth, nay and I mourne a minute longer, I am the rotteneſt <hi>Onion</hi> that e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer ſpake with a tongue.</p>
                     <stage>They thruſt him out.</stage>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Maxi.</speaker>
                     <p>What call your hind's count <hi>Ferneze?</hi>
                     </p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Count.</speaker>
                     <p>His name is <hi>Onion</hi> Signior,</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Maxi.</speaker>
                     <p>I thought him ſome ſuch ſawcy companion.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <pb facs="tcp:22306:8"/>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Count.</speaker>
                     <p>Signior <hi>Maximillian.</hi>
                     </p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Maxi.</speaker>
                     <p>Sweet Lord.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Count.</speaker>
                     <l>Let me intreat you, you would not regard</l>
                     <l>Any contempt flowing from ſuch a ſpirit,</l>
                     <l>So rude, ſo barbarous.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Maxi.</speaker>
                     <p>Moſt noble <hi>Count</hi> vnder your fauour—</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Coun.</speaker>
                     <l>Why Ile tell you Signior,</l>
                     <l>Heele bandy with me word for word, nay more,</l>
                     <l>Put me to ſilence, ſtrike me perfect dumb;</l>
                     <l>And ſo amaze me, that oftentimes I know not,</l>
                     <l>Whether to check or cheriſh his preſumption:</l>
                     <l>Therefore good Signior.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Maxi.</speaker>
                     <p>Sweet Lord ſatisfie your ſelfe, I am not now to learn how to manage my affections, I haue obſeru'd, and know the difference betweene a baſe wretch and a true man, I can diſtinguiſh them, the property of the wretch is, he would hurt and cannot, of the man, he can hurt, and will not.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Coun.</speaker>
                     <l>Go to, my merry daughter, ô theſe lookes,</l>
                     <l>Agree well with your habit, do they not?</l>
                     <stage>Enter Iuniper.</stage>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Iunip.</speaker>
                     <p>Tut, let me alone. By your fauour, this is the Gen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tleman I thinke, Sir you appeare to be an honorable Gentle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man, I vnderſtand, and could wiſh (for mine owne part) that things were conden't otherwiſe then they are: but (the world knowes) a fooliſh fellow, ſomewhat procliue, and haſty, he did it in a preiudicate humour; mary now vpon better com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>putation, he wanes; he melts; his poore eyes are in a cold ſweat. Right noble <hi>Signior,</hi> you can haue but compunction, I loue the man, tender your compaſſion.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Maxi.</speaker>
                     <p>Doth any man here vnderſtand this fellow?</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Iunip.</speaker>
                     <p>O God ſir, I may ſay <hi>fruſtra</hi> to the comprehenſion of your intellection.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Maxi.</speaker>
                     <l>Before the Lord, he ſpeakes all riddle, I thinke.</l>
                     <l>I muſt haue a comment ere I can conceiue him.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Count.</speaker>
                     <l>Why he ſues to haue his fellow <hi>Onion</hi> pardon'd,</l>
                     <l>And you muſt grant it Signior.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Maxi.</speaker>
                     <p>O with all my ſoule my Lord, is that his motion?</p>
                  </sp>
                  <pb facs="tcp:22306:8" rendition="simple:additions"/>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Iunip.</speaker>
                     <p>I ſir, and we ſhall retort theſe kinde fauours with all allacrity of ſpirit, we can ſir, as may be moſt expedient, as well for the quality as the cauſe, till when in ſpight of this complement: I reſt a poore Cobler, ſeruant to my honorable Lord here, your friend and <hi>Iuniper.</hi>
                     </p>
                  </sp>
                  <stage>Exit.</stage>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Maxi.</speaker>
                     <p>How <hi>Iuniper?</hi>
                     </p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Count.</speaker>
                     <p>I Signior.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Maxi.</speaker>
                     <p>He is a ſweete youth, his tongue has a happy turne when he ſleepes.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <stage>Enter Paulo Ferneze, Franciſco, Colomea, Angelo, Valentine.</stage>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Count.</speaker>
                     <l>I for then it reſts, O Sir your welcome,</l>
                     <l>Why God be thanked you are found at laſt.</l>
                     <l>Signior <hi>Coloma</hi> truly you are welcome,</l>
                     <l>I am glad to ſee you ſir ſo well returned.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Fran.</speaker>
                     <l>I gladly thanke your honour, yet indeed</l>
                     <l>I am ſory for ſuch cauſe of heauineſſe,</l>
                     <l>As hath poſſeſt your Lordſhip in my abſence.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Count.</speaker>
                     <p>O <hi>Franciſco'</hi> you knew her what ſhe was!</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Fran.</speaker>
                     <p>She was a wiſe and honorable Lady.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Count.</speaker>
                     <l>I was ſhe not! well weepe not ſhe is gone,</l>
                     <l>Paſſons duld eye can make two grieues of one,</l>
                     <l>Whom death marke out, vertue, nor bluod can ſaue,</l>
                     <l>Princes, as beggers, all muſt feed the graue.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Max.</speaker>
                     <p>Are your horſe ready Lord <hi>Paulo,</hi>
                     </p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Pau.</speaker>
                     <p>I ſignior the ſtay for vs at the gate.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Max.</speaker>
                     <l>Well tis good. Ladies I will take my leaue of you,</l>
                     <l>Be your fortunes as your ſelues? faire. Come let vs to horſe,</l>
                     <l>Count <hi>Ferneze</hi> I beare a ſpirit full of thanks for all your hono<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable courteſies.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Count.</speaker>
                     <p>Sir I could wiſh the number and value of them more in reſpect of your deſeruings. But <hi>Signior Maximillian.</hi> I pay you a word in priuate.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Aur.</speaker>
                     <p>I Faith brother you are fitted for a generall yonder, Beſhrow my heart (If I had <hi>Fortunatus</hi> hat here) and I would not wiſh my ſelfe a man and go with you, only t'enioy his pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſence.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <pb facs="tcp:22306:9" rendition="simple:additions"/>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Pau.</speaker>
                     <p>Why do you loue him ſo well ſiſter.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Aur.</speaker>
                     <p>No by my troth, but I haue ſuch an odde prety appre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>henſion of his humour me thinks: that I am eene tickled with the conceite of it.</p>
                     <p>O he is a fine man.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Ang</speaker>
                     <p>And me thinks another may be as fine as he.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Aur.</speaker>
                     <p>O <hi>Angelio,</hi> do you thinke I do vrge any compariſon a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt you? no, I am not ſo ill bred, as to be a deprauer of your worthines: beleeue me, if I had not ſome hope of your abiding with vs, I ſhould neuer deſire to go out of black whilſt I liued: but learne to ſpeake i'the noſe, and turne puritan preſently.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Ang.</speaker>
                     <p>I thanke you Lady: I know you can flout.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Aur.</speaker>
                     <p>Come doe you take it ſo? I faith you wrong me.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Fran.</speaker>
                     <l>I, but Maddame,</l>
                     <l>Thus to diſclaime in all the effects of pleaſure,</l>
                     <l>May make your ſadneſſe ſeeme to much affected,</l>
                     <l>And then the proper grace of it is loſt.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Phoenix</speaker>
                     <l>Indeed ſir, if I did put on this ſadneſſe</l>
                     <l>Onely abroad, and in Society,</l>
                     <l>And were in priuate merry; and quick humor'd;</l>
                     <l>Then might it ſeeme affected and abhord:</l>
                     <l>But as my lookes appeare, ſuch is my ſpirit,</l>
                     <l>Drown'd vp with confluence of griefe, and melancholy,</l>
                     <l>That like to riuers run through all my vaines,</l>
                     <l>Quenching the pride and feruour of my bloud.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Max.</speaker>
                     <l>My honorable Lord? no more.</l>
                     <l>There is the honour of my bloud ingag'd,</l>
                     <l>For your ſonnes ſafety.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Count.</speaker>
                     <l>Signior, blame me not,</l>
                     <l>For tending his ſecurity ſo much,</l>
                     <l>He is mine onely ſonne, and that word onely,</l>
                     <l>Hath with his ſtrong, and reprecuſſiue ſound,</l>
                     <l>Stroke my heart cold, and giuen it a deepe wound.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Max.</speaker>
                     <p>Why but ſtay, I beſeech you, had your Lordſhip euer any more ſonnes then this.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Count.</speaker>
                     <p>Why haue not you knowen it <hi>Maximilian?</hi>
                     </p>
                  </sp>
                  <pb facs="tcp:22306:9"/>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Max.</speaker>
                     <p>Let my Sword faile me then.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Count.</speaker>
                     <l>I had one other yonger borne then this,</l>
                     <l>By twiſe ſo many how ers as would fill</l>
                     <l>The circle of a yeare, his name <hi>Camillo,</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>Whome in that blacke, and fearfull night I loſt,</l>
                     <l>(Tis now a nineteene yeares agone at leaſt,</l>
                     <l>And yet the memory of it fits as freſh</l>
                     <l>Within my braine as twere but yeſterday)</l>
                     <l>It was that night wherein the great <hi>Chamont,</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>The generall for <hi>France</hi> ſurpriſed <hi>Vicenza,</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>Me thinks the horrour of that clamorous ſhout</l>
                     <l>His ſouldiers gaue 'when they attaind the wall,</l>
                     <l>Yet tingles in mine eare, me thinkes I ſee</l>
                     <l>With what amazed lookes, diſtracted thoughts,</l>
                     <l>And minds confuſ'd, we, that were citizens,</l>
                     <l>Confronted one another: euery ſtreet</l>
                     <l>Was fild with bitter ſelfe tormenting cries,</l>
                     <l>And happy was that foote, that firſt could preſſe,</l>
                     <l>The flowry champaigne, bordering on <hi>Verona</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>Heere I (imploy'd about my deare wiues ſafety)</l>
                     <l>Whoſe ſoule is now in peace) loſt my <hi>Camillo.</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>Who ſure was murdered by the barbarous Souldiers,</l>
                     <l>Or elſe I ſhould haue heard—my heart is great.</l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Sorrow is faint? and paſſion makes me ſweat.</hi>
                     </l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Max</speaker>
                     <p>Grieue not ſweet <hi>Count:</hi> comfort your ſpirts, you haue a ſonne a noble gentleman, he ſtands in the face of ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour: For his ſafety let that be no queſtion. I am maiſter of my fortune, and he ſhall ſhare with me. Farewell my honorable Lord. Ladies once more adiew, for your ſelfe maddam you are a moſt rare creature, I tell you ſo, be not proud of it, I loue you: come Lord <hi>Paulo</hi> to horſe.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Pau.</speaker>
                     <p>Adiew good Signior <hi>Franceſco:</hi> farewell ſiſter.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <stage>Sound a tucket, and as they paſſe euery one ſeue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rally depart, Maximilian, Paulo Ferne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ze and Angelo remaine</stage>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Ang.</speaker>
                     <p>How ſhall we rid him hence.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <pb facs="tcp:22306:10"/>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Pau.</speaker>
                     <l>Why well inough? ſweet <hi>Signior Maximilian.</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>I haue ſome ſmall occaſion to ſtay:</l>
                     <l>If it may pleaſe you but take horſe afore</l>
                     <l>Ile ouer take you, ere your troopes be ranged.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Max.</speaker>
                     <p>Your motion hath taſt wel: Lord <hi>Ferneze</hi> I go</p>
                     <stage>Exit Max.</stage>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Pau.</speaker>
                     <l>Now if my loue faire <hi>Rachel,</hi> were ſo happy,</l>
                     <l>But to looke forth. See fortune doth me grace.</l>
                     <stage>Enter Rachel.</stage>
                     <l>Before I can demaund? how now loue.</l>
                     <l>Where is your father?</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Rach.</speaker>
                     <p>Gone abroad my Lord:</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Pau:</speaker>
                     <p>Thats well,</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Rach.</speaker>
                     <l>I but I feare heele preſently returne,</l>
                     <l>Are you now going my moſt honored Lord?</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Pau.</speaker>
                     <p>I my ſweet <hi>Rachel.</hi>
                     </p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Ang.</speaker>
                     <p>Before God, ſhe is a ſweet wench.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Pau.</speaker>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Rachel</hi> I hope I ſhall not need to vrge,</l>
                     <l>The ſacred purity of our effects,</l>
                     <l>As if it hung in triall or ſuſpence:</l>
                     <l>Since in our hearts, and by our mutuall vowes,</l>
                     <l>It is confirmd and ſeald in ſight of heauen.</l>
                     <l>Nay doe not weepe, why ſtarte you? feare not, <hi>Loue.</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>Your father cannot be returned ſo ſoone,</l>
                     <l>I prithee doe not looke ſo heauily</l>
                     <l>Thou ſhalt want nothing</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Rach.</speaker>
                     <l>No is your preſence nothing,</l>
                     <l>I ſhall want that, and wanting that, want all</l>
                     <l>For that is all to me.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Pau.</speaker>
                     <l>Content thee ſweet</l>
                     <l>I haue Made choiſe here of a conſtant friend</l>
                     <l>This gentleman? one, whoſe zealous loue</l>
                     <l>I doe repoſe more, then on all the world,</l>
                     <l>Thy beauteous ſelfe excepted: and to him,</l>
                     <l>Haue I committed my deere care of thee,</l>
                     <l>As to my genius, or my other ſoule.</l>
                     <l>Rsceiue hi gentle loue and what deffects,</l>
                     <pb facs="tcp:22306:10" rendition="simple:additions"/>
                     <l>My abſence proues, his preſence ſhall ſupply.</l>
                     <l>The time is enuious of our longer ſtay.</l>
                     <l>Farewell deere <hi>Rachel.</hi>
                     </l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Rach:</speaker>
                     <l>Moſt deere Lord, adew,</l>
                     <l>Heauen and honour crowne your deeds, and you,</l>
                  </sp>
                  <stage>Exit Rachel.</stage>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Pau.</speaker>
                     <p>Faiah tell me <hi>Angelio</hi> how doſt thou like her?</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Ang.</speaker>
                     <p>Troth well my Lord, but ſhall I ſpeake my mind.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Pan.</speaker>
                     <p>I prithee doe.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Ang.</speaker>
                     <l>She is deriud too meanely to be wife</l>
                     <l>To ſuch a noble perſon, in my iudgement.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Pau.</speaker>
                     <l>Nay then thy iudgement is to meene, I ſe<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>
                     </l>
                     <l>Didſt thou neare read in difference of good</l>
                     <l>Tis more to ſhine in vertue then in bloud.</l>
                     <stage>Enter Iaques.</stage>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Ang.</speaker>
                     <p>Come you are ſo ſententious my Lord.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Pau.</speaker>
                     <p>Here comes her father. How doſt thou good <hi>Iaques?</hi>
                     </p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Ang.</speaker>
                     <p>God ſaue thee <hi>Iaques.</hi>
                     </p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Iaq.</speaker>
                     <p>What ſhould this meane? <hi>Rachel</hi> open the dore.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <stage>Exit Iaques.</stage>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Ang.</speaker>
                     <l>Sbloud how the poore ſlaue lookes, as though</l>
                     <l>He had bene hauuted by the ſpirit <hi>Lar,</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>Or ſeene the ghoſt of ſome great <hi>Satrapas.</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>In an vnſauory ſheet.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Pru.</speaker>
                     <l>I muſe he ſpake no, belike he was amazd</l>
                     <l>Comming ſo ſuddenly and vnprepard? Well lets go:</l>
                  </sp>
                  <stage>Exeunt.</stage>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div n="2" type="act">
               <head>Actus ſecundi</head>
               <div n="1" type="scene">
                  <head>Scaena prima.</head>
                  <stage>Enter Iaques ſolus.</stage>
                  <l>SO now inough my heart, beat now no more;</l>
                  <l>At leaſt for this afright, what a could ſweat,</l>
                  <l>Flow'd on my browes, and ouer all my boſome!</l>
                  <l>Had I not reaſon? to behold my dore</l>
                  <l>Beſet with vnthrifts, and my ſelfe abroad?</l>
                  <l>Why <hi>Iaques?</hi> was their nothing in the houſe</l>
                  <l>Worth a continuall eye, a vigelent thought,</l>
                  <pb facs="tcp:22306:11"/>
                  <l>Whoſe head ſhould neuer nod, nor eyes once wincke?</l>
                  <l>Looke on my coate; my thoughts; worne quite thred bare,</l>
                  <l>That time could neuer couer with a nappe,</l>
                  <l>And by it learne, neuer with nappes of ſleepe,</l>
                  <l>To ſmother your conceipts of that you keepe.</l>
                  <l>But yet, I maruell, why theſe gallant youths</l>
                  <l>Spokeine ſo faire, and I eſteemd a beggar?</l>
                  <l>The end of flattery, is gaine, or lechery:</l>
                  <l>If they ſeeke gaine of me, they thinke me rich,</l>
                  <l>But that they do not: for their other obiect:</l>
                  <l>Tis in my handſome daughter, if it be.</l>
                  <l>And by your leaue, her handſomneſſe may tell them</l>
                  <l>My beggery counterfeits, and, that her neatneſſe,</l>
                  <l>Flowes from ſome ſtore of wealth, that breakes my coffers,</l>
                  <l>With this ſame engine, loue to mine owne breed.</l>
                  <l>But this is anſwered: <hi>Beggers will keepe fine,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Their daughters, being faire, though themſelues pine.</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>Well then, it is for her, I, t'is ſure for her,</l>
                  <l>And I make her ſo briske for ſome of them,</l>
                  <l>That I might liue alone once with my gold.</l>
                  <l>O t'is a ſweet companion! kind and true,</l>
                  <l>A man may truſt it when his father cheats him;</l>
                  <l>Brother, or friend, or wife, ô wondrous pelfe,</l>
                  <l>"<hi>That which makes all men falſe, is true it ſelfe.</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>But now this maid, is but ſuppos'd my daughter:</l>
                  <l>For I being Steward to a Lord of France,</l>
                  <l>Of great eſtate, and wealth, called Lord <hi>Chammount,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>He gone into the warres, I ſtole his treaſure,</l>
                  <l>(But heare not, any thing) I ſtole his treaſure,</l>
                  <l>And this his daughter, being but two yeares old,</l>
                  <l>Becauſe it lou'd me ſo, that it would leaue</l>
                  <l>The nurſe her ſelfe, to come into mine armes,</l>
                  <l>And had I left it, it would ſure haue dyed.</l>
                  <l>Now herein I was kinde, and had a conſcience;</l>
                  <l>And ſince her Lady mother that did dye</l>
                  <l>In child-bed of her, loued me paſſing well,</l>
                  <pb facs="tcp:22306:11" rendition="simple:additions"/>
                  <l>It may be nature faſhiond this affection,</l>
                  <l>Both in the child and her: but hees ill bred,</l>
                  <l>That ranſackes tombes, and doth deface the dead.</l>
                  <l>I'le therefore ſay no more: ſuppoſe the reſt,</l>
                  <l>Here haue I chang'd my forme, my name and hers.</l>
                  <l>And liue obſurely, to enioy more ſafe</l>
                  <stage>Enter Rachel.</stage>
                  <l>My deereſt treaſure. But I muſt abroad, <hi>Rachel.</hi>
                  </l>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Rach.</speaker>
                     <p>VVhat is your pleaſure ſir?</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Iaq.</speaker>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Rachel</hi> I muſt abroad.</l>
                     <l>Lock thy ſelfe in, but yet take out the key,</l>
                     <l>That whoſoeuer peepes in at the key-hole,</l>
                     <l>May yet imagine there is none at home.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Rach.</speaker>
                     <p>I will ſir.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Iaq.</speaker>
                     <l>But harke thee <hi>Rachel:</hi> ſay a theefe ſhould come,</l>
                     <l>And miſſe the key, he would reſoule indeede</l>
                     <l>None were at home, and ſo breake in the rather:</l>
                     <l>Ope the doore <hi>Rachel,</hi> ſet it open daughter;</l>
                     <l>But ſit in it thy ſelfe: and talke alowd,</l>
                     <l>As if there were ſome more in houſe with thee:</l>
                     <l>Put out the fire, kill the chimnies hart,</l>
                     <l>That it may breath no more then a dead man,</l>
                     <l>The more we ſpare my child, the more we gaine.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <stage>Exeunt.</stage>
               </div>
               <div n="2" type="scene">
                  <head>Scaene 2.</head>
                  <stage>Enter Chriſtophero, Iuniper and Onion.</stage>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>CHriſt.</speaker>
                     <p>What ſayes my fellow <hi>Onion?</hi> come on.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Oni.</speaker>
                     <p>All of a houſe ſir, but no fellowes, you are my Lords Steward, but I pray you what thinke you of loue, ſir?</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Chriſt.</speaker>
                     <p>Of loue <hi>Onion?</hi> Why it's a very honourable humor.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Oni.</speaker>
                     <p>Nay if it be but worſhipfull I care not.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Iunip.</speaker>
                     <p>Go to, it's honorable, checke not at the conceit of the Gentleman.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Oni.</speaker>
                     <l>But in truth ſir, you ſhall do well to think well of loue:</l>
                     <l>For it thinkes well of you, in me, I aſſure you.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <pb facs="tcp:22306:12"/>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Chriſ.</speaker>
                     <p>Gramercy fellow <hi>Onion:</hi> I do thinke well, thou art in loue, art thou?</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Oni.</speaker>
                     <p>Partly ſir, but I am aſham'd to ſay wholy.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Chriſ.</speaker>
                     <p>Well, I will further it in thee to any honeſt woman, or maiden, the beſt I can.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Iunip.</speaker>
                     <l>Why now you come neere him ſir, he doth vaile,</l>
                     <l>He doth remunerate, he doth chaw the cud in the kindneſſe</l>
                     <l>Of an honeſt imperfection to your worſhip.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Chriſ</speaker>
                     <p>But who is it thou loueſt fellow <hi>Onion?</hi>
                     </p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Oni.</speaker>
                     <p>Mary a poore mans daughter, but none of the honeſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eſt, I hope.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Chriſ.</speaker>
                     <p>Why, wouldſt thou not haue her honeſt?</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Oni.</speaker>
                     <p>O no, for then I am ſure ſhe would not haue me. T'is <hi>Rachel de Prie.</hi>
                     </p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Chriſ.</speaker>
                     <p>Why, ſhe hath the name of a very vertuous mayden.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Iunip.</speaker>
                     <p>So ſhee is ſir, but the fellow talkes in quiddits, he.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Chriſ.</speaker>
                     <p>What wouldſt thou haue me do in the matter?</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Oni.</speaker>
                     <p>Do nothing ſir, I pray you, but ſpeake for me.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Chriſ.</speaker>
                     <p>In what maner?</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Oni.</speaker>
                     <p>My fellow <hi>Iuniper</hi> can tell you ſir.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Iunip.</speaker>
                     <p>Why as thus ſir. Your worſhip may commend him for a fellow fit for conſanguinity, and that he ſhaketh with defire of procreation, or ſo.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Chriſ.</speaker>
                     <p>That were not ſo good, me thinkes.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Iunip.</speaker>
                     <p>No ſir, why ſo ſir? what if you ſhould ſay to her, correborate thy ſelfe ſweete ſoule, let me diſtinguiſh thy pappes with my fingers, diuine Mumps, prety <hi>Paſtorella?</hi> lookeſt thou ſo ſweet and bounteous? comfort my friend here.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Chriſ.</speaker>
                     <p>Well I perceiue you wiſh, I ſhould ſay ſomething may do him grace, and further his deſires, and that be ſure I will.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Oni.</speaker>
                     <p>I thanke you ſir, God ſaue your life, I pray God ſir.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Iunip.</speaker>
                     <p>Your worſhip is too good to liue long: youle con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taminate me no ſeruice.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <pb facs="tcp:22306:12"/>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Chriſ.</speaker>
                     <p>Command thou wouldeſt ſay, no good <hi>Iuniper.</hi>
                     </p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Iunip.</speaker>
                     <p>Health and wealth ſir.</p>
                     <stage>Exeunt Onion and Iuniper.</stage>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Chriſ.</speaker>
                     <l>This wench wil<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap> ſolicite for my ſelfe,</l>
                     <l>Making my Lord and maiſter priuy to it;</l>
                     <l>And if he ſecond me with his conſent,</l>
                     <l>I will proceede, as hauing long ere this,</l>
                     <l>Though her a worthy choyce to make my wife.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <stage>Exit.</stage>
               </div>
               <div n="3" type="scene">
                  <head>Scaene 3.</head>
                  <stage>Enter Aurelia, Phoenixella.</stage>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>AVre.</speaker>
                     <l>Roome for a caſe of matrons coloured blacke,</l>
                     <l>How motherly my mothers death hath made vs?</l>
                     <l>I would I had ſome girles now to bring vp;</l>
                     <l>O I could make a wench ſo vertuous,</l>
                     <l>She ſhould ſay grace to euery bit of meate,</l>
                     <l>And gape no wider then a wafers thickneſſe:</l>
                     <l>And ſhe ſhould make French curſies, ſo moſt low,</l>
                     <l>That euery touch ſhould turne her ouer backward.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Phoeni.</speaker>
                     <l>Siſter, theſe words become not your atrire,</l>
                     <l>Nor your eſtate: our vertuous mothers death</l>
                     <l>Should print more deepe effects of ſorrow in vs,</l>
                     <l>Then may be worne out in ſo little time.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Aure.</speaker>
                     <l>Siſter, faith you take too much Tobacco,</l>
                     <l>It makes you blacke within, as y'are without.</l>
                     <l>What true-ſtich ſiſter? both your ſides alike?</l>
                     <l>Be of a ſleighter worke: for of my word,</l>
                     <l>You ſhall be ſold as deere or rather deerer?</l>
                     <l>Will you be bound to <hi>cuſtomes</hi> and to <hi>rites?</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>Shed profitable teares, weepe for aduantage;</l>
                     <l>Or elſe, do all things, as you are enclynd.</l>
                     <l>Hate when your ſtomacke ſerues (ſaith the <hi>Phyſitian</hi>)</l>
                     <l>Not at <hi>eleuen</hi> and <hi>ſixe.</hi> So if your humour</l>
                     <l>Be now affected with this heauineſſe.</l>
                     <pb facs="tcp:22306:13"/>
                     <l>Giue me the reines and ſpare not, as I do,</l>
                     <l>In this my pleaſurable appetite,</l>
                     <l>It is <hi>Praeciſianiſme</hi> to alter that</l>
                     <l>With auſtere iudgement, that is giuen by nature.</l>
                     <l>I wept you ſaw too, when my mother dyed:</l>
                     <l>For then I found it eaſier to do ſo,</l>
                     <l>And fitter with my moode, then not to weepe.</l>
                     <l>But now tis otherwiſe, another time</l>
                     <l>Perhaps I ſhall haue ſuch deepe thoughts of her,</l>
                     <l>That I ſhall weepe a freſh, ſome twelue month hence,</l>
                     <l>And I will weepe, if I be ſo diſpos'd,</l>
                     <l>And put on blacke, as grimly then, as now;</l>
                     <l>Let the minde go ſtill with the bodies ſtature,</l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Iudgement is fit for Iudges, giue me nature.</hi>
                     </l>
                  </sp>
               </div>
               <div n="4" type="scene">
                  <head>Scaene. 4.</head>
                  <stage>Enter Aurelia, Phaenixella, Franciſco, Augelo.</stage>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Fran.</speaker>
                     <l>See Signior <hi>Angelo</hi> here are the Ladies,</l>
                     <l>Go you and comfort one, Ile to the other.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Ange.</speaker>
                     <l>Therefore I come ſir, I'le to the eldeſt.</l>
                     <l>God ſaue you Ladies, theſe ſad moodes of yours,</l>
                     <l>That make you chooſe theſe ſolitary walkes,</l>
                     <l>Are hurtfull for your beauties.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Aure.</speaker>
                     <p>If we had them.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Ange.</speaker>
                     <l>Come, that condition might be for your hearts,</l>
                     <l>When you proteſt faith, ſince we cannot ſee them.</l>
                     <l>But this ſame heart of beauty, your ſweet face</l>
                     <l>Is in mine eye ſtill.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Aure.</speaker>
                     <p>O you cut my heart with your ſharpe eye.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Ange.</speaker>
                     <p>Nay Lady thats not ſo, your heart's to hard.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Aure.</speaker>
                     <p>My beauties hart?</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Ange.</speaker>
                     <l>O no.</l>
                     <l>I meane that regent of affection, <hi>Maddam,</hi>
                     </l>
                     <pb facs="tcp:22306:13"/>
                     <l>That tramples on al loue with ſuch contempt <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>n this faire breaſt.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Aur.</speaker>
                     <l>No more, your drift is ſauour'd,</l>
                     <l>I had rather ſeeme hard hearted</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Ang.</speaker>
                     <l>Then hard fauour'd,</l>
                     <l>Is that your meaning, Lady?</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Aur.</speaker>
                     <l>Go too ſir.</l>
                     <l>Your wits are freſh I know, they need no ſpur,</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Ang.</speaker>
                     <p>And therefore you wil ride them.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Aur.</speaker>
                     <l>Say I doe.</l>
                     <l>They will not tire I hope?</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Ang.</speaker>
                     <p>No not with you, hark you ſweet Lady.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Fran.</speaker>
                     <l>Tis much pitty Maddam.</l>
                     <l>You ſhould haue any reaſon to retaine</l>
                     <l>This ſigne of griefe, much leſſe the thing diſignde.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Phoe.</speaker>
                     <l>Griefes are more fit for Ladies then their pleaſures.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Fran.</speaker>
                     <l>That is for ſuch as follow nought but pleaſures.</l>
                     <l>But you that temper them ſo wel with vertues,</l>
                     <l>Vſing your griefes ſo it would prooue them pleaſures.</l>
                     <l>And you would ſeeme in cauſe of griefes &amp; pleaſures equally pleaſant.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Phoe</speaker>
                     <l>Sir ſo I do now.</l>
                     <l>It is the exceſſe of either that I ſtriue</l>
                     <l>So much to ſhun in all my proou'd endeauours,</l>
                     <l>Although perhaps vnto a generall eye,</l>
                     <l>I may appeare moſt wedded to my griefes,</l>
                     <l>Yet doth my mind forſake no taſt of pleaſure,</l>
                     <l>I meane that happy pleaſure of the ſoule,</l>
                     <l>Deuine and ſacred contemplation</l>
                     <l>Of that eternall, and moſt glorious bliſſe.</l>
                     <l>Propoſed as the crowne vnto our ſoules.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Fran.</speaker>
                     <l>I will be ſilent, yet that I may ſerue</l>
                     <l>But as a <hi>Decade</hi> in the art of memory</l>
                     <l>To put you ſtil in mind of your owne vertues</l>
                     <l>When your too ſerious thoughts make you too ſad)</l>
                     <l>Accept me for your ſeruant honored Lady.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <pb facs="tcp:22306:14"/>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Phoen.</speaker>
                     <l>Thoſe cerimonies are too comon ſignior <hi>Francis,</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>For your vncommon grauitie, and iudgement,</l>
                     <l>And fits them onely, that are nought but cerimony.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Ang.</speaker>
                     <l>Come, I will not ſue, ſtally to be your ſeruant,</l>
                     <l>But a new tearme, will you be my refuge?</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Aur.</speaker>
                     <p>Your refuge, why ſir.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Ange.</speaker>
                     <p>That I might fly to you, when all elſe faile me.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Aur.</speaker>
                     <p>And you be good at flying, be my Plouer.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Ang.</speaker>
                     <p>Nay take away the P.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Aur.</speaker>
                     <p>Tut, then you cannot fly.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Ang.</speaker>
                     <p>Ile warrant you. Ile borrow <hi>Cupids</hi> wings.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Aur.</speaker>
                     <l>Maſſe then I feare me youle do ſtrange things:</l>
                     <l>I pray you blame me not, if I ſuſpect you,</l>
                     <l>Your owne confeſſion ſimply doth detect you,</l>
                     <l>Nay and you be ſo great in <hi>Cupids</hi> bookes,</l>
                     <l>T'will make me Iealous. you can with your lookes</l>
                     <l>(I warrant you) enflame a womans heart,</l>
                     <l>And at your pleaſure take loues golden dart,</l>
                     <l>And wound the breſt of any vertous maide.</l>
                     <l>Would I were hence: good Faith I am affraid,</l>
                     <l>You can conſtraine one ere they be aware,</l>
                     <l>To run mad for your loue?</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Ang.</speaker>
                     <p>O this is rate.</p>
                  </sp>
               </div>
               <div n="6" type="scene">
                  <head>Scaene 6.</head>
                  <stage>Aurelio, Phoenixella, Franciſco, Angelo, Count.</stage>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>COunt.</speaker>
                     <l>Cloſe with my daughters gentlemen? wel done,</l>
                     <l>Tis like your ſelues: nay luſty <hi>Angelo,</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>Let not my preſence make you bauke your ſport,</l>
                     <l>I will not breake a minute of diſcourſe</l>
                     <l>Twixt you and one of your faire Miſtreſſes.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Ang.</speaker>
                     <p>One of my miſtreſſes? why thinks your Lordſhip I haue ſo many</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Count.</speaker>
                     <l>Many? no <hi>Angelo.</hi>
                     </l>
                     <pb facs="tcp:22306:14"/>
                     <l>I do not thinke th'aſt many, ſome fourteene</l>
                     <l>I here thou haſt, euen of our worthieſt dames,</l>
                     <l>Of any note, in <hi>Millaine:</hi>
                     </l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Ang.</speaker>
                     <p>Nay good my Lord fourteene: it is not ſo.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Count.</speaker>
                     <l>By'th the Maſſe that iſt, here are their names to ſhew</l>
                     <l>Fourteene, or fifteene t'one. <hi>Good Angelo.</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>You need not be aſhamd of any of them,</l>
                     <l>They are gallants all.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Ang.</speaker>
                     <p>Sbloud you are ſuch a Lord.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Count.</speaker>
                     <l>Nay ſtay ſweet <hi>Angelo,</hi> I am diſpoſed</l>
                     <stage>Exit Ang:</stage>
                     <l>A little to be pleaſant paſt my couſtome,</l>
                     <l>He's gone? he's gone, I haue diſgraſt him ſhrewdly,</l>
                     <l>Daughters take heede of him, he's a wild youth,</l>
                     <l>Looke what he ſayes to you beleeue him not,</l>
                     <l>He will ſweare loue to euery one he ſees.</l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Franciſco,</hi> giue them councell, good <hi>Franciſco,</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>I dare truſt thee with both, but him with neither.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Fran.</speaker>
                     <p>Your Lordſhip yet may truſt both them with him.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <stage>Exunt.</stage>
               </div>
               <div n="7" type="scene">
                  <head>Scaene 7.</head>
                  <stage>Count. Chriſtopher,</stage>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Count.</speaker>
                     <l>Well goe your waies away; how now <hi>Chriſtopher,</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>What newes with you?</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Chriſt.</speaker>
                     <p>I haue an humble ſuit to your good Lordſhip.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Count.</speaker>
                     <p>A ſuit <hi>Chriſtopher?</hi> what ſuit I prithee?</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Chriſt.</speaker>
                     <l>I would craue pardon at your Lordſhips hands,</l>
                     <l>If it ſeeme vaine or ſimple in your ſight.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Count.</speaker>
                     <l>Ile pardon all ſimplicity, <hi>Chriſtopher,</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>What is thy ſuit?</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Chriſt.</speaker>
                     <l>Perhaps being now ſo old a batcheler,</l>
                     <l>I ſhall ſeeme halfe vnwiſe, to bend my ſelfe</l>
                     <l>In ſtrict affection to a poore yong maide.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Count.</speaker>
                     <l>What? is it touching loue <hi>Chriſtopher?</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>Art thou diſpoſt to marry, why tis well.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Chriſto.</speaker>
                     <l>I, but your Lordſhip may imagine now</l>
                     <l>That I being ſteward of your honours houſe.</l>
                     <pb facs="tcp:22306:15"/>
                     <l>If I be maried once, will more regard</l>
                     <l>The maintenance of my wife and of my charge,</l>
                     <l>Then the due diſcharge of my place and office.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Count.</speaker>
                     <p>No, no, <hi>Chriſtopher,</hi> I know thee honeſt.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Chriſto.</speaker>
                     <p>Good faith my Lord, your honour may ſuſpect it<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> but—</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Count.</speaker>
                     <l>Then I ſhould wrong thee, thou haſt euer been</l>
                     <l>Honeſt and true, and will be ſtill I knowe.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Chriſ.</speaker>
                     <l>I but this marriage alters many men:</l>
                     <l>And you may feare, it will do me my Lord,</l>
                     <l>But ere it do ſo? I will vndergoe</l>
                     <l>Ten thouſand ſeuerall deaths.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Count.</speaker>
                     <l>I know it man.</l>
                     <l>Who wouldſt thou haue I prithee?</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Chriſ.</speaker>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Rachel de prie,</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>If your good Lordſhip, graunt me your conſent.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Count.</speaker>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Rachel de prie?</hi> what the poore beggers daughter?</l>
                     <l>Shees a right handſome maide, how poore ſoeuer,</l>
                     <l>And thou haſt my conſent, with all my hart.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Chriſ.</speaker>
                     <p>I humbly thanke your honour. Ile now aſke her father.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <stage>Exit.</stage>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Count.</speaker>
                     <l>Do ſo <hi>Chriſtofero</hi> thou ſhalt do well.</l>
                     <l>Tis ſtrange (ſhe being ſo poore) he ſhould affect her,</l>
                     <l>But this is more ſtrange that my ſelfe ſhould loue her.</l>
                     <l>I ſpide her, lately, at her fathers doore,</l>
                     <l>And if I did not ſee in her ſweet face</l>
                     <l>Gentry and nobleneſſe, nere truſt me more:</l>
                     <l>But this perſwaſion, fancie wrought in me,</l>
                     <l>That fancie being created with her lookes,</l>
                     <l>For where loue is he thinke his baſeſt obiect</l>
                     <l>Gentle and noble: I am farre in loue,</l>
                     <l>And ſhall be forc'd to wrong my honeſt ſteward,</l>
                     <l>For I muſt ſue, and ſeeke her for my ſelfe;</l>
                     <l>How much my duetie to my late dead wife,</l>
                     <l>And my owne deere renowne ſo ere it ſwaies,</l>
                     <l>He to her father ſtraight. <hi>Loue hates delays.</hi>
                     </l>
                  </sp>
                  <stage>Exit.</stage>
               </div>
               <div n="8" type="scene">
                  <pb facs="tcp:22306:15"/>
                  <head>Scaene 8.</head>
                  <stage>Enter Onion, Iuniper, Valentine, Sebaſtian, Balthaſar, Martino.</stage>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Onion.</speaker>
                     <p>Come on Ifaith, lets to ſome exerciſe or other my hearts: Fetch the hilts fellow <hi>Iuniper,</hi> wilt thou play:</p>
                  </sp>
                  <stage>Exit Martino.</stage>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Iun.</speaker>
                     <p>I cannot reſolue you? tis as I am fitted with the inge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nuity, quantity, or quality of the cudgell.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Valen.</speaker>
                     <p>How doſt thou baſtinado the poore cudgell with tearmes?</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Iuni.</speaker>
                     <p>O <hi>Ingle,</hi> I haue the phraſes man, and the <hi>Anagrams</hi> and the <hi>Epitaphs,</hi> fitting the miſtery of the noble ſcience.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Oni.</speaker>
                     <p>Ile be hangd &amp; he were not misbegotten of ſome fen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cer.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Sebaſt.</speaker>
                     <p>Sirrah <hi>Valentine,</hi> you can reſolue me now, haue they their maiſters of defence in other countries as we haue here in <hi>Italy?</hi>
                     </p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Valen.</speaker>
                     <p>O Lord, I, eſpecially they in <hi>Vtopia,</hi> there they per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forme their prizes and chalenges, with as great cerimony as the <hi>Italian</hi> or any nation elſe.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Balt</speaker>
                     <p>Indeed? how is the manner of it (for gods loue) good <hi>Valeniine?</hi>
                     </p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Iuni.</speaker>
                     <p>
                        <hi>Ingle?</hi> I prithee make recourſe vnto vs, wee are thy friends and familiars: ſweet <hi>Ingle.</hi>
                     </p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Valen.</speaker>
                     <p>Why thus ſir.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Oni.</speaker>
                     <p>God a mercy good <hi>Valentine,</hi> nay go on.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Iuni.</speaker>
                     <p>
                        <hi>Silentium bonus ſocius Onionus,</hi> good fellow <hi>Onion</hi> be not ſo ingenious, and turbulent: ſo fir? and how? how ſweete <hi>Ingle?</hi>
                     </p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Valen.</speaker>
                     <p>Marry, firſt they are brought to the publicke <hi>Theater:</hi>
                     </p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Iuni.</speaker>
                     <p>What? ha? they <hi>Theater</hi> there</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Valen.</speaker>
                     <p>
                        <hi>Theaters?</hi> I and plaies to: both tragidy and comedy &amp; ſet foorth with as much ſtate as can be imagined?</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Iuni.</speaker>
                     <p>By Gods ſo; a man is nobody, till he has trauelled.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <pb facs="tcp:22306:16"/>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Sebaſt.</speaker>
                     <p>And how are their plaies? as ours are? extemporall?</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Valen.</speaker>
                     <p>O no? all premeditated things, and ſome of them ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry good I faith, my maiſter vſed to viſite them often when he was there.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Balth.</speaker>
                     <p>Why how are they in a place where any man may ſee them?</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Valen.</speaker>
                     <p>I, in the common <hi>Theaters,</hi> I tell you. But the ſport is at a new play to obſerue the ſway and variety of oppinion that paſſeth it. A man ſhall haue ſuch a confus'd mixture of iudgement, powr'd out in the throng there, as ridiculous, as laughter it ſelfe: one ſaies he likes not the writing, another likes not the plot, another not the playing. And ſometimes a fellow that comes not there paſt once in fiue yeare at a <hi>Parli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ament</hi> time or ſo, will be as deepe myr'd in cenſuring as the beſt, and ſweare by Gods foote he would neuer ſtirre his foote to ſee a hundred ſuch as that is.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Oni.</speaker>
                     <p>I muſt trauell to ſee theſe things, I ſhall nere think well of my ſelfe elſe.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Iunip.</speaker>
                     <p>Fellow <hi>Onion,</hi> Ile beare thy charges and thou wilt but pilgrimize it along with me, to the land of <hi>Vtopia.</hi>
                     </p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Sebaſt.</speaker>
                     <p>Why but me thinkes ſuch rookes as theſe ſhould be aſham'd to iudge.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Valen.</speaker>
                     <p>Not a whit? the rankeſt ſtinkard of them all, will take vpon him as peremptory, as if he had writ himſelfe <hi>in artibus magiſter.</hi>
                     </p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Sebaſt.</speaker>
                     <p>And do they ſtand to a popular cenſure for any thing they preſent.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Valen.</speaker>
                     <p>I euer, euer, and the people generally are very ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceptiue and apt to applaud any meritable worke, but there are two ſorts of perſons that moſt commonly are infectious to a whole auditory.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Balth.</speaker>
                     <p>What be they?</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Iunip.</speaker>
                     <p>I come lets know them.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Oni.</speaker>
                     <p>It were good they were noted.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Valen.</speaker>
                     <p>Marry? one is the rude barbarous crue, a people that haue no braines, and yet grounded iudgements, theſe will hiſſe
<pb facs="tcp:22306:16"/>any thing that mounts aboue their grounded capacities. But the other are worth the obſeruation, I faith.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Omnes.</speaker>
                     <p>What be they? what be they?</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Valen.</speaker>
                     <p>Faith a few <hi>Caprichious</hi> gallants.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Iunip.</speaker>
                     <p>
                        <hi>Caprichious?</hi> ſtay, that word's for me.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Valen.</speaker>
                     <p>And they haue taken ſuch a habit of diſlike in all things, that they will approue nothing, be it neuer ſo concei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted or elaborate, but ſit diſperſt, making faces, and ſpitting, wagging their vpright eares and cry filthy, filthy. Simply vtte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring their owne condition, and vſing their wryed countenan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces in ſtead of a vice, to turne the good aſpects of all that ſhall ſit neere them, from what they behold.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <stage>Enter Martino with cudgels.</stage>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Oni.</speaker>
                     <l>O that's well ſayd, lay them downe, come ſirs.</l>
                     <l>Who plaies, fellow <hi>Iuniper, Sebaſtian, Balthaſar:</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>Some body take them vp, come.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Iunip.</speaker>
                     <p>
                        <hi>Ingle Valentine?</hi>
                     </p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Valen.</speaker>
                     <p>Not I ſir, I profeſſe it not.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Iunip.</speaker>
                     <p>
                        <hi>Sebaſtian.</hi>
                     </p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Sebaſt.</speaker>
                     <p>
                        <hi>Balthaſar.</hi>
                     </p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Balth.</speaker>
                     <p>Who? I?</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Oni.</speaker>
                     <p>Come, but one bout, Ile giue hem thee, I faith.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Balth.</speaker>
                     <p>Why, heres <hi>Martino.</hi>
                     </p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Oni.</speaker>
                     <p>Foe he, alas he cannot play a whit, man.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Iunip.</speaker>
                     <p>That's all one: no more could you <hi>in ſtata quo prius, Martino,</hi> play with him, euery man has his beginning and conduction.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Mart.</speaker>
                     <p>Will you not hurt me fellow <hi>Onion?</hi>
                     </p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Oni.</speaker>
                     <p>Hurt thee, no? and I do, put me among pot-hearbs, And chop me to peeces, come on?</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Iunip.</speaker>
                     <p>By your fauor ſweet bullies giue them roome, back, ſo, <hi>Martino,</hi> do not looke ſo thin vpon the matter.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Oni.</speaker>
                     <p>Ha, well plaid, fall ouer to my legge now? ſo, to your guard againe, excellent, to my head now, make home your blow: ſpare not me, make it home, good, good a gaine.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Sebaſt.</speaker>
                     <p>Why how now <hi>Peter?</hi>
                     </p>
                  </sp>
                  <pb facs="tcp:22306:17"/>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Valen.</speaker>
                     <p>Gods ſo, <hi>Onion</hi> has caught a bruiſe.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Iunip.</speaker>
                     <p>Couragio? be not <hi>caprichious?</hi> what?</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Oni.</speaker>
                     <p>
                        <hi>Caprichious?</hi> not I, I ſcorn to be <hi>caprichious</hi> for a ſcrach, <hi>Martino</hi> muſt haue another bout, come.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Val. Seb. Balth.</speaker>
                     <p>No, no, play no more, play no more.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Oni.</speaker>
                     <p>Foe, tis nothing a philip, a deuiſe, fellow <hi>Iuniper</hi> pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thee get me a Plantan, I had rather play with one that had skil by halfe.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Mart.</speaker>
                     <p>By my troth, fellow <hi>Onion,</hi> twas againſt my will.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Oni.</speaker>
                     <l>Nay that's not ſo, twas againſt my head,</l>
                     <l>But come, weele ha one bout more.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Iunip.</speaker>
                     <p>Not a bout, not a ſtroke.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Omnes.</speaker>
                     <p>No more, no more.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Iunip.</speaker>
                     <p>Why Ile giue you demonſtration, how it came, Thou openeſt the dagger to falſifie ouer with the back ſword frick, and he interrupted, before he could fall to the cloſe.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Oni.</speaker>
                     <p>No, no, I know beſt how it was better the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> any man here, I felt his play preſently: for looke you, I gathered vpon him thus, thus do you ſee? for the double locke, and tooke it ſingle on the head.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Valen.</speaker>
                     <p>He ſayes very true, he tooke it ſingle on the head.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Sebaſt.</speaker>
                     <p>Come lets go.</p>
                     <stage>Enter Martino with a cob-web.</stage>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Mar.</speaker>
                     <p>Here fellow <hi>Onion,</hi> heres a cob-web.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Oni.</speaker>
                     <p>How? a cob-web <hi>Martino,</hi> I will haue another bout with you? S'wounds do you firſt breake my head, and then giue me a plaiſter in ſcorne? come to it, I will haue a bout.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Mart.</speaker>
                     <p>God's my witneſſe.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Oni.</speaker>
                     <p>Tut! your witneſſe cannot ſerue.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Iunip.</speaker>
                     <p>S'bloud? why what, thou art not lunatike, art thou? and thou bee'ſt auoide <hi>Mephoſtophiles.</hi> Say the ſigne ſhoud be in <hi>Aries</hi> now: as it may be for all vs, where were your life? An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwere me that?</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Sebaſt.</speaker>
                     <p>Hee ſayes well, <hi>Onion.</hi>
                     </p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Valen.</speaker>
                     <p>I indeed doo's he.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Iunip.</speaker>
                     <p>Come, come, you are a fooliſh <hi>Naturaliſt,</hi> go, get a white a of an egge, and a little flax, and cloſe the breach of the
<pb facs="tcp:22306:17"/>head, it is the moſt conducible thing that can be. <hi>Martino,</hi> do not inſinuate vpon your good fortune, but play an honeſt part and beare away the bucklers.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <stage>Exeunt.</stage>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div n="3" type="act">
               <head>Act. 3.</head>
               <div n="1" type="scene">
                  <head>Scaene 1.</head>
                  <stage>Enter Angelo ſolus.</stage>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>ANge.</speaker>
                     <l>My yong and ſimple friend, <hi>Paulo Ferneze,</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>Bound me with mighty ſolemne coniurations,</l>
                     <l>To be true to him, in his loue, to <hi>Rachel,</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>And to ſolicite his remembrance ſtill,</l>
                     <l>In his enforced abſence, much, I faith.</l>
                     <l>True to my friend in caſes of affection?</l>
                     <l>In womens caſes? what a ieſt it is?</l>
                     <l>How ſilly he is, that imagines it!</l>
                     <l>He is an aſſe that will keepe promiſe ſtricktly</l>
                     <l>In any thing that checkes his priuate pleaſure;</l>
                     <l>Chiefly in loue. S'bloud am not I a man?</l>
                     <l>Haue I not eyes that are as free to looke?</l>
                     <l>And bloud to be enflam'd as well as his?</l>
                     <l>And when it is ſo, ſhall I not purſue</l>
                     <l>Mine owne loues longings, but preferre my friends?</l>
                     <l>I tis a good foole, do ſo, hang me then,</l>
                     <l>Becauſe I ſwore, alas, who doo's not know,</l>
                     <l>That louers periuries are ridiculous?</l>
                     <l>Haue at thee <hi>Rachel:</hi> Ile go court her ſure:</l>
                     <l>For now I know her father is abroad.</l>
                     <stage>Enter Iaques.</stage>
                     <l>S'bloud ſee, he is here, ô what damn'd lucke is this?</l>
                     <l>This labour's loſt, I muſt by no meanes ſee him.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <stage>tau, dery, dery, Exit.</stage>
               </div>
               <div n="2" type="scene">
                  <head>Scaene 2.</head>
                  <stage>Iaques, Chriſtophero.</stage>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>IAq.</speaker>
                     <l>Miſchiefe and hell, what is this man a ſpirit,</l>
                     <l>Haunts he my houſes ghoſt? ſtill at my doore?</l>
                     <pb facs="tcp:22306:18"/>
                     <l>He has beene at my doore, he has beene in,</l>
                     <l>In my deere doore: pray God my gold be ſafe.</l>
                     <stage>Enter Chriſtophero.</stage>
                     <l>Gods pitty, heres another. <hi>Rachel, ho Rachel.</hi>
                     </l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Chriſ.</speaker>
                     <p>God ſaue you honeſt father.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Iaq.</speaker>
                     <p>
                        <hi>Rachel,</hi> Gods light, come to me, <hi>Rachel, Rachel!</hi>
                     </p>
                  </sp>
                  <stage>Exit.</stage>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Chriſ.</speaker>
                     <l>Now in Gods name what ayles he? this is ſtrange!</l>
                     <l>He loues his daughter ſo, Ile lay my life,</l>
                     <l>That hee's afraid, hauing beene now abroad,</l>
                     <l>I come to ſeeke her loue vnlawfully.</l>
                     <stage>Enter Iaques.</stage>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Iaq.</speaker>
                     <p>Tis ſafe, tis ſafe, they haue notrob'd my treaſure.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Chriſ.</speaker>
                     <p>Let it not feeme offenſiue to you ſir.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Iaq.</speaker>
                     <p>Sir, Gods my life, ſir, ſir, call me ſir.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Chriſ.</speaker>
                     <p>Good father here me.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Iaq.</speaker>
                     <l>You are moſt welcome ſir,</l>
                     <l>I meant almoſt; and would your worſhip ſpeake?</l>
                     <l>Would you abaſe your ſelfe to ſpeake to me?</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Chriſ.</speaker>
                     <l>Tis no abaſing father: my intent</l>
                     <l>Is to do further honour to you ſir</l>
                     <l>Then onely ſpeake: which is to be your ſonne.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Iaq.</speaker>
                     <l>My gold is in his noſtrels, he has ſmelt it,</l>
                     <l>Breake breaſt, breake heart, fall on the earth my entrailes,</l>
                     <l>With this ſame burſting admiration!</l>
                     <l>He knowes my gold, he knowes of all my treaſure,</l>
                     <l>How do you know ſir? whereby do you gueſſe?</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Chriſ.</speaker>
                     <p>At what ſir? what iſt you meane?</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Iaq.</speaker>
                     <l>I aske, an't pleaſe your Gentle worſhip, how you know?</l>
                     <l>I meane, how I ſhould make your worſhip know</l>
                     <l>That I haue nothing —</l>
                     <l>To giue with my poore daughter? I haue nothing:</l>
                     <l>The very aire, bounteous to euery man,</l>
                     <l>Is ſcant to me, ſir.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Chriſ.</speaker>
                     <p>I do thinke good father, you are but poore,</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Iaq.</speaker>
                     <l>He thinkes ſo, harke, but thinke ſo:</l>
                     <l>He thinkes not ſo, he knowes of all my treaſure.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <stage>Exit.</stage>
                  <pb facs="tcp:22306:18"/>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Chriſ.</speaker>
                     <l>Poore man he is ſo ouerioyed to heare</l>
                     <l>His daughter may be paſt his hopes beſtowed,</l>
                     <l>That betwixt feare and hope (if I meane ſimply)</l>
                     <l>He is thus paſſionate.</l>
                     <stage>Enter Iaques.</stage>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Iaq.</speaker>
                     <l>Yet all is ſafe within, is none without?</l>
                     <l>No body breake my walles?</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Chriſ.</speaker>
                     <p>What ſay you father, ſhall I haue your daughter?</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Iaq.</speaker>
                     <p>I haue no dowry to beſtow vpon her.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Chriſ.</speaker>
                     <p>I do expect none, father.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Iaq.</speaker>
                     <l>That is well,</l>
                     <l>Then I beſeech your worſhip make no queſtion</l>
                     <l>Of that you wiſh, tis too much fauour to me.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Chriſ.</speaker>
                     <l>Ile leaue him now to giue his paſſions breath,</l>
                     <l>Which being ſetled, I will fetch his daughter:</l>
                     <l>I ſhall but moue too much, to ſpeake now to him.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <stage>Exit Chriſtophero.</stage>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Iaq.</speaker>
                     <l>So, hee's gone, would all were dead and gone,</l>
                     <l>That I might liue with my deere gold alone.</l>
                  </sp>
               </div>
               <div n="3" type="scene">
                  <head>Scaene 3. <hi>Iaques, Count.</hi>
                  </head>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Count.</speaker>
                     <p>Here is the poore old man.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Iaq.</speaker>
                     <p>Out of my ſoule another, comes he hither?</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Count.</speaker>
                     <p>Be not diſmaid old man, I come to cheere you.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Iaq.</speaker>
                     <l>To me by heauen,</l>
                     <l>Turne ribs to braſſe, turne voice into a trumpet,</l>
                     <l>To rattle out the battels of my thoughts,</l>
                     <l>One comes to hold me talke, while th'other robbes me.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <stage>Exit.</stage>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Count.</speaker>
                     <l>He has forgot me ſure: what ſhould this meane?</l>
                     <l>He feares authority, and my want of wife</l>
                     <l>Will take his daughter from him to defame her:</l>
                     <l>He that hath naught on earth but one poore daughter,</l>
                     <l>May take this extaſie of care to keepe her.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <pb facs="tcp:22306:19"/>
                  <stage>Enter Iaques.</stage>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Iaq.</speaker>
                     <l>And yet tis ſafe: they meane not to vſe force,</l>
                     <l>But fawning comming. I ſhall eaſly know</l>
                     <l>By his next queſtion, if he thinke me rich,</l>
                     <l>Whom ſee I? my good Lord?</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Count.</speaker>
                     <l>Stand vp good father, I call thee not father for thy age,</l>
                     <l>But that I gladly wiſh to be thy ſonne,</l>
                     <l>In honoured marriage with thy beauteous daughter.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Iaq.</speaker>
                     <l>O, ſo, ſo, ſo, ſo, ſo, this is for gold,</l>
                     <l>Now it is ſure, this is my daughters neatneſſe,</l>
                     <l>Makes them beleeue me rich. No, my good Lord,</l>
                     <l>Ile tell you all; how my poore hapleſſe daughter</l>
                     <l>Got that attire ſhe weares from top to toe.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Count.</speaker>
                     <p>Why father, this is nothing.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Iaq.</speaker>
                     <p>O yes, good my Lord.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Count.</speaker>
                     <p>Indeed it is not.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Iaq.</speaker>
                     <l>Nay ſweet Lord pardon me? do not diſſemble,</l>
                     <l>Heare your poore beadſ-man ſpeake; tis requiſite</l>
                     <l>That I (ſo huge a beggar) make account</l>
                     <l>Of things that paſſe my calling: ſhe was borne</l>
                     <l>T'enioy nothing vnderneath the ſonne:</l>
                     <l>But that, if ſhe had more then other beggars</l>
                     <l>She ſhould be enuied: I will tell you then</l>
                     <l>How ſhe had all ſhe weares, her warme ſhooes (God wot)</l>
                     <l>A kind maide gaue her, ſeeing her go barefoot</l>
                     <l>In a cold froſty morning; God requite her;</l>
                     <l>Her homely ſtockings</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Count.</speaker>
                     <l>Father, Ile heare no more, thou mou'ſt too much</l>
                     <l>With thy too curious anſwere for thy daughter,</l>
                     <l>That doth deſerue a thouſand times as much,</l>
                     <l>Ile be thy Sonne in law, and ſhe ſhall weare</l>
                     <l>Th'attire of Counteſſes.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Iaq.</speaker>
                     <l>O good my Lord,</l>
                     <l>Mock not the poore, remembers not your Lordſhip,</l>
                     <l>That pouerty is the precious gift of God.</l>
                     <pb facs="tcp:22306:19"/>
                     <l>As well as riches, tread vpon me, rather</l>
                     <l>Then mocke my poorenes.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Count.</speaker>
                     <l>Riſe I ſay:</l>
                     <l>When I mocke poorenes, then heauens make me poore.</l>
                     <stage>Enter Nuntius.</stage>
                  </sp>
               </div>
               <div n="7" type="scene">
                  <head>Scaene 7. <hi>Nuncio, Count.</hi>
                  </head>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>NVn.</speaker>
                     <l>See heres the <hi>Count Ferneze,</hi> I will tell him</l>
                     <l>The hapleſſe accident of his braue ſonne,</l>
                     <l>That hee may ſeeke the ſooner to redeeme him,</l>
                     <stage>Exit Iaques.</stage>
                     <l>God ſaue your Lordſhip.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Count.</speaker>
                     <p>You are right welcome ſir.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Nun.</speaker>
                     <p>I would I brought ſuch newes as might deſerue it.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Count.</speaker>
                     <p>What, bring you me ill newes?</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Nun.</speaker>
                     <l>Tis ill my Lord,</l>
                     <l>Yet ſuch as vſuall chance of warre affoords,</l>
                     <l>And for which all men are prepar'd that vſe it,</l>
                     <l>And thoſe that vſe it not, but in their friends,</l>
                     <l>Or in their children.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Count.</speaker>
                     <l>Ill newes of my ſonne?</l>
                     <l>My deere and onely ſonne, Ile lay my ſoule,</l>
                     <l>Ay me accurs'd, thought of his death doth wound me,</l>
                     <l>And the report of it will kill me quite.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Nun.</speaker>
                     <p>Tis not ſo ill my Lord.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Count.</speaker>
                     <p>How then?</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Nun.</speaker>
                     <l>Hee's taken priſoner, and that's all.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Count.</speaker>
                     <l>That's enough, enough,</l>
                     <l>I ſet my thoughts on loue, on ſeruile loue,</l>
                     <l>Forget my vertuous wife, feele not the dangers,</l>
                     <l>The bands and wounds of mine owne fleſh and bloud,</l>
                     <l>And therein am a mad man: therein plagu'd,</l>
                     <l>With the moſt iuſt affliction vnder heauen.</l>
                     <pb facs="tcp:22306:20"/>
                     <l>Is <hi>Maximilian</hi> taken priſoner to?</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Nun.</speaker>
                     <p>My good my Lord, he is return'd with priſoners.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Count.</speaker>
                     <l>Iſt poſſible, can <hi>Maximilian?</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>Returne, and view my face without my ſonne,</l>
                     <l>For whom he ſwore ſuch care as for himſelfe?</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Nun.</speaker>
                     <p>My Lord no care can change the euents of war.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Count.</speaker>
                     <l>O! in what tempeſts do my fortunes ſaile,</l>
                     <l>Still wrackt with winds more foule and contrary,</l>
                     <l>Then any northen gueſt, or Southerne flawe?</l>
                     <l>That euer yet inforc't the ſea to gape,</l>
                     <l>And ſwallow the poore Marchants traffique vp?</l>
                     <l>Firſt in <hi>Vieenza,</hi> loſt I my firſt ſonne;</l>
                     <l>Next here in <hi>Millaine</hi> my moſt deere lou'd Lady:</l>
                     <l>And now my <hi>Paulo,</hi> priſoner to the <hi>French,</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>Which laſt being printed with my other griefes,</l>
                     <l>Doth make ſo huge a volume, that my breſt</l>
                     <l>Cannot containe them. But this is my loue<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
                     </l>
                     <l>I muſt make loue to <hi>Rachel,</hi> heauen hath throwne,</l>
                     <l>This vengeance on me moſt deſeruedly:</l>
                     <l>Were it for nought but wronging of my ſteward.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Nun.</speaker>
                     <l>My Lord ſince onely mony may redreſſe</l>
                     <l>The worſt of this miſfortune, be not griued,</l>
                     <l>Prepare his ranſome and your noble ſonne</l>
                     <l>Shall greete your cheered eyes, with the more honour.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Count.</speaker>
                     <l>I will prepare his ranſome: gratious heauen</l>
                     <l>Grant his impriſonment may be his worſt,</l>
                     <l>Honored and ſouldier-like impriſonment,</l>
                     <l>And that he be not manacled and made</l>
                     <l>A drudge to his proude foe. And here I vow,</l>
                     <l>Neuer to dreame of ſeeme-les amorous toyes,</l>
                     <l>Nor aime at other ioy on earth,</l>
                     <l>But the fruition of my onely ſonne.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <stage>Exunt</stage>
               </div>
               <div n="5" type="scene">
                  <pb facs="tcp:22306:20"/>
                  <head>Scaene 5.</head>
                  <stage>Enter Iaques with his gold and aſcuttle full of horſe-dung.</stage>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Iaq,</speaker>
                     <l>He's gone: I knew it; this is our hot louer,</l>
                     <l>I will beleeue them! I! they may come in</l>
                     <l>Like ſimple woers, and be arrant theeues,</l>
                     <l>And I not know them! tis not to be told,</l>
                     <l>What ſeruile villanies, men will do for gold,</l>
                     <l>O it began to haue a huge ſtrong ſmell,</l>
                     <l>Which lying ſo long together in a place;</l>
                     <l>Ile giue it vent, it ſhall ha ſhift inough,</l>
                     <l>And if the diuell, that enuies all goodneſſe,</l>
                     <l>Haue told them of my gold, and where I kept it,</l>
                     <l>Ile ſet his burning noſe once more a worke,</l>
                     <l>To ſmell where I remou'd it, here it is:</l>
                     <l>Ile hide and couer it with this horſe-dung:</l>
                     <l>Who will ſuppoſe that ſuch a precious ne<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>t</l>
                     <l>Is crownd with ſuch a dunghill excrement?</l>
                     <l>In my deere life, ſleepe ſweetly my deere child.</l>
                     <l>"Scarce lawfully begotten, but yet gotten,</l>
                     <l>"And thats enough. Rot all hands that come neere thee</l>
                     <l>Except mine owne. Burne out all eyes that ſee thee,</l>
                     <l>Except mine owne. All thoughts of thee be poyſon</l>
                     <l>To their enamor'd harts, except mine owne,</l>
                     <l>Ile take no leaue, ſweet Prince great Emperour,</l>
                     <l>But ſee thee euery minute, King of Kings,</l>
                     <l>Ile not be rude to thee, and turne my backe,</l>
                     <l>In going from thee, but go backward out:</l>
                     <l>With my face toward thee, with humble curteſies,</l>
                     <l>None is within. None ouerlookes my wall.</l>
                     <l>To haue gold, and to haue it ſafe, is all.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <stage>Exit.</stage>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div n="3" type="act">
               <pb facs="tcp:22306:21"/>
               <head>Actus 3.</head>
               <div n="1" type="scene">
                  <head>Scaene 1.</head>
                  <stage>Enter Maximilian, with ſouldiers Chamount, Camilla, Ferneze, Pacue.</stage>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Max.</speaker>
                     <p>Lord <hi>Chamount</hi> and your valient friend there, I can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not ſay welcome to Millaine: your thoughts and that word are not muſicall, but I can ſay you are come to <hi>Millaine.</hi>
                     </p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Pac.</speaker>
                     <p>Mort diew.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Cha.</speaker>
                     <p>Gar ſoone.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Max.</speaker>
                     <p>Gentlemen (I would cal an Emperour ſo) you are now my priſoners, I am ſorry, marry this, ſpit in the face of your fortunes, for your vſage ſhall be honorable.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Cam.</speaker>
                     <l>Wee know it ſignior <hi>Maximilian,</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>The fame of al your actions ſounds nought elſe,</l>
                     <l>But perfect honour from her ſwelling cheeks.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Max.</speaker>
                     <p>It ſhall do ſo ſtill I aſſure you, and I will giue you rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon, there is in this laſt action (you know) a noble gentleman of our party, &amp; a right valient; ſemblably priſoner to your gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral, as your honor'd ſelfe's to me, for whoſe ſafety, this tongue hath giuen warrant to his honorable father, the <hi>Count Ferneze.</hi> You conceiue me.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Cam.</speaker>
                     <p>I ſignior.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Max.</speaker>
                     <p>Well? then I muſt tell you your ranſomes be to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deeme him, what thinke you? your anſwer.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Cam.</speaker>
                     <l>Marry with my Lords leaue here I ſay ſignior,</l>
                     <l>This free &amp; ample offer you haue made,</l>
                     <l>Agrees well with your honour, but not ours:</l>
                     <l>For I thinke not but <hi>Chamount</hi> is aſwell borne</l>
                     <l>As is <hi>Ferneze,</hi> then if I miſtake not,</l>
                     <l>He ſcornes to haue his worth ſo vnderpriſed,</l>
                     <l>That it ſhould neede an adiunct, in exchange,</l>
                     <l>Of any equall fortune, Noble <hi>Signior?</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>I am a ſouldier, and I loue <hi>Chamount,</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>Ere I would bruſe his eſtimation,</l>
                     <l>With the leaſt ruine of mine owne reſpect,</l>
                     <l>In this vild kind, theſe legs ſhould rot with irons,</l>
                     <pb facs="tcp:22306:21"/>
                     <l>This body pine in priſon, till the fleſh</l>
                     <l>Dropt from my bones in flakes, like withered leaues,</l>
                     <l>In heart of <hi>Autumne,</hi> from a ſtubborne Oke.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Maxi.</speaker>
                     <p>Mounſieur <hi>Gaſper</hi> (I take it ſo is your name) miſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>priſe me not, I wil trample on the hart, on the ſoule of him that ſhall ſay, I will wrong you: what I purpoſe, you cannot now know; but you ſhall know, and doubt not to your content<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment. Lord <hi>Chamount,</hi> I will leaue you, whileſt I go in and preſent my ſelfe to the honorable <hi>Count,</hi> till my regreſſion ſo pleaſe you, your noble feete may meaſure this priuate, plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſant and moſt princely walke, Souldiers regard them and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpect them.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Pac.</speaker>
                     <p>
                        <hi>O Ver bon:</hi> excellenta gull, he tak'a my Lord <hi>Chamoun<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap>
                        </hi> for Mounſieur <hi>Gaſpra,</hi> &amp; Mounſieur <hi>Gaſpra</hi> for my Lord <hi>Cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mont,</hi> ô dis be braue for make a me laugh'a, <hi>ha, ha, ha,</hi> ô my heart tickla.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Cam.</speaker>
                     <l>I but your Lordſhip knowes not what hard fate</l>
                     <l>Might haue purſued vs, therefore howſoere</l>
                     <l>The changing of our names was neceſſary</l>
                     <l>And we muſt now be carefull to maintaine</l>
                     <l>This error ſtrongly, which our owne deuiſe,</l>
                     <l>Hath thruſt into their ignorant conceits,</l>
                     <l>For ſhould we (on the taſte of this good fortune)</l>
                     <l>Appeare our ſelues, t'would both create in them</l>
                     <l>A kinde of iealouſie, and perchaunce inuert</l>
                     <l>Thoſe honourable courſes they intend.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Cha.</speaker>
                     <l>True my deere <hi>Gaſper:</hi> but this hang by here,</l>
                     <l>Will (at one time or other) on my ſoule</l>
                     <l>Diſcouer vs: A ſecret in his mouth</l>
                     <l>Is like a wild bird put into a cage,</l>
                     <l>Whoſe doore no ſooner opens, but tis out.</l>
                     <l>But ſirra, if I may but know</l>
                     <l>Thou vtterſt it</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Pac.</speaker>
                     <p>Vtteria? vat Mounſieur?</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Cha.</speaker>
                     <p>That he is <hi>Gaſper,</hi> and I true <hi>Chamont.</hi>
                     </p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Pac.</speaker>
                     <l>O <hi>pardone moy,</hi> fore my tongue ſhall put out de ſecreta,</l>
                     <pb facs="tcp:22306:22"/>
                     <l>Shall breede <hi>de cankra</hi> in my mouth.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Count.</speaker>
                     <p>Speake not ſo loud <hi>Pacue.</hi>
                     </p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Pac.</speaker>
                     <p>Foe, you ſhall not heare foole, for all your long eare, Reguard Mounſieur: you be <hi>de Chamont, Chamont</hi> be <hi>Gaſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pra.</hi>
                     </p>
                  </sp>
                  <stage>Enter Count Ferueze, Maximilian, Franceſco, Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>relia, Phoenixella, Finio.</stage>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Cha.</speaker>
                     <p>Peace, here comes <hi>Maximilian.</hi>
                     </p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Cam.</speaker>
                     <p>O belike that's the <hi>Count Ferneze,</hi> that old man.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Cha.</speaker>
                     <p>Are thoſe his daughters, trow?</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Cam.</speaker>
                     <p>I ſure, I thinke they are.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Cha.</speaker>
                     <p>Fore God the taller is a gallant Lady.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Cam.</speaker>
                     <p>So are they both beleeue me.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Max.</speaker>
                     <p>True my honorable Lord, that <hi>Chamont</hi> was the fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther of this man.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Count.</speaker>
                     <l>O that may be, for when I loſt my ſonne,</l>
                     <l>This was but yong it ſeemes.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Fran.</speaker>
                     <l>Faith had <hi>Camillo</hi> liued,</l>
                     <l>He had beene much about his yeares, my Lord.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Count.</speaker>
                     <p>He had indeed, well, ſpeake no more of him.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Max.</speaker>
                     <p>Signior perceiue you the errour? twas no good of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fice in vs to ſtretch the remembrance of ſo deere a loſſe. <hi>Count Ferneze,</hi> let ſommer ſit in your eye, looke cheerefully ſweete <hi>Count,</hi> will you do me the honour to confine this noble ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit within the circle of your armes?</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Count.</speaker>
                     <l>Honor'd <hi>Chamont</hi> reach me your valiant hand,</l>
                     <l>I could haue wiſht ſome happier accident</l>
                     <l>Had made the way vnto this mutuall knowledge,</l>
                     <l>Which either of vs now muſt take of other,</l>
                     <l>But ſure it is the pleaſure of our fates,</l>
                     <l>That we ſhould thus be wrack't on Fortunes wheele,</l>
                     <l>Let vs prepare with ſteeled patience</l>
                     <l>To tread on torment, and with mindes confirm'd</l>
                     <pb facs="tcp:22306:22"/>
                     <l>Welcome the worſt of enuy.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Max.</speaker>
                     <p>Noble Lord, tis thus. I haue here (in mine honour) ſet this gentleman free, without ranſome, he is now himſelfe, his valour hath deſeru'd it, in the eye of my iudgement. Moun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſieur <hi>Gaſper</hi> you are deere to me: <hi>fortuna non mutuat genus.</hi> But to the maine, if it may ſquare with your Lordſhips li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king, and his loue, I could deſire that he were now inſtant<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly imployed to your noble Generall in the exchange of <hi>Fer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neze</hi> for your ſelfe, it is the buſineſſe that requires the tender hand of a friend.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Count.</speaker>
                     <l>I, and it would be with more ſpeed effected,</l>
                     <l>If he would vndertake it.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Max.</speaker>
                     <p>True my Lord. Mounſieur <hi>Gaſper,</hi> how ſtand you affected to this motion?</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Cha.</speaker>
                     <p>My duty muſt attend his Lordſhips will.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Max.</speaker>
                     <p>What ſayes the Lord <hi>Chamont?</hi>
                     </p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Cam.</speaker>
                     <p>My will doth then apprroue what theſe haue vrg'd.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Max.</speaker>
                     <p>Why there is good harmony, good muſicke in thise Mounſieur <hi>Gaſper,</hi> you ſhall protract no time, onely I will giue you a bowle of rich wine to the health of your Generall, another to the ſucceſſe of your iourney, and a third to the loue of my ſword. <hi>Paſſe.</hi>
                     </p>
                  </sp>
                  <stage>Exeunt all but Aurelia and Phoenixella.</stage>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Anre.</speaker>
                     <l>Why how now ſiſter in a motley muſe?</l>
                     <l>Go to, thers ſomewhat in the wind, I ſee.</l>
                     <l>Faith this browne ſtudy ſuites not with your blacke,</l>
                     <l>Your habit and your thoughts are of two colours.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Phoen.</speaker>
                     <p>Good faith me thinkes that this young Lord <hi>Cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mont</hi> fauours my mother, ſiſter, does he not?</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Aure.</speaker>
                     <l>A mothelry conceite, ô blind excuſe,</l>
                     <l>Blinder then loue himſelfe. Well ſiſter, well.</l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Cupid</hi> hath tane his ſtand in both your eyes, <hi>The caſe is al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terd.</hi>
                     </l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Phoen.</speaker>
                     <p>And what of that?</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Aure.</speaker>
                     <l>Nay nothing but a Saint.</l>
                     <pb facs="tcp:22306:23"/>
                     <l>Another <hi>Bridget,</hi> one that for a face</l>
                     <l>Would put downe <hi>Veſta,</hi> in whoſe lookes doth ſwim,</l>
                     <l>The very ſweeteſt creame of modeſty.</l>
                     <l>You to turne tippet? fie, fie, will you giue</l>
                     <l>A packing penny to Virginity.</l>
                     <l>I thought youl'd dwell ſo long in <hi>Cypres</hi> Ile,</l>
                     <l>You'd worſhip <hi>Maddam Venus</hi> at the length;</l>
                     <l>But come, the ſtrongeſt fall, and why not you?</l>
                     <l>Nay, do not frowne.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Phoen.</speaker>
                     <p>Go. go, you ſoole. Adiew.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Aure.</speaker>
                     <l>Well I may ieſt, or ſo: but <hi>Cupid</hi> knowes</l>
                     <l>My taking is as bad, or worſe then hers.</l>
                     <l>O Mounſieur <hi>Gaſper?</hi> if thou bee'ſt a man,</l>
                     <l>Be not affraid to court me, do but ſpeake,</l>
                     <l>Challenge thy right and weare it: for I ſweare</l>
                     <l>Till thou arriud'ſt, nere came affection here.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <stage>Exit.</stage>
                  <stage>Enter Pacue, Finio.</stage>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Fin.</speaker>
                     <l>Come on my ſweet finicall <hi>Pacue,</hi> the very prime</l>
                     <l>Of Pages, heres an excellent place for vs to practiſe in,</l>
                     <l>No body fees vs here, come lets to it.</l>
                     <stage>Enter Oniou.</stage>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Pac.</speaker>
                     <p>Contenta: Reguarde, vou le Preimer.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Oni.</speaker>
                     <p>Sirra <hi>Finio?</hi>
                     </p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Pac.</speaker>
                     <p>Mort deiu le peſant.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Oni.</speaker>
                     <p>Didſt thou ſee <hi>Valentine?</hi>
                     </p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Finio.</speaker>
                     <p>
                        <hi>Valentine?</hi> no.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Oni.</speaker>
                     <p>No?</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Fini.</speaker>
                     <p>No. Sirrah <hi>Onion,</hi> whither goeſt?</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Oni.</speaker>
                     <p>O I am vext, he that would truſt any of theſe lying trauellers.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Finio.</speaker>
                     <p>I prithee ſtay good <hi>Onion.</hi>
                     </p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Pac.</speaker>
                     <p>Mounſieur <hi>Onion,</hi> vene ca, come hidera, Ie vou prey. By gar me ha ſee two, tree, foure hundra towſand of your Couſan hang. Lend me your hand, ſhall prey for know you bettra.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <pb facs="tcp:22306:23"/>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Oni.</speaker>
                     <p>I thanke you good ſignior <hi>Parla vou?</hi> O that I were in an other world, in the <hi>Ingies,</hi> or ſome where, that I might haue roome to laugh.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Pac.</speaker>
                     <p>A we fort boon: ſtand? you be deere now, me come, Boon iour Mounſieur.</p>
                     <stage>Vnder the arme.</stage>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Fin.</speaker>
                     <p>God morrow good ſignior.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Pac</speaker>
                     <p>By gar, be muſh glad for ſee you.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Fin</speaker>
                     <p>I returne you moſt kind thanks ſir.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Oni.</speaker>
                     <p>How? how? Sbloud this is rare?</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Pac.</speaker>
                     <p>Nay, ſhall make you ſay rare by and by, Reguard Mounſieur <hi>Finio,</hi>
                     </p>
                     <stage>Theſhoulder</stage>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Fin.</speaker>
                     <p>Signior <hi>Pache.</hi>
                     </p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Pac.</speaker>
                     <p>Dieu vou gard Mounſieur.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Fin.</speaker>
                     <p>God ſaue you ſweet ſignior</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Pac.</speaker>
                     <p>Mounſieur <hi>On ion?</hi> is not fort boon.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Oni.</speaker>
                     <p>Beane? quoth he, would I were in debt of a pottle of beanes I could do as much.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Fin.</speaker>
                     <p>Welcome ſignior, whats next?</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Pac.</speaker>
                     <p>O here, Void de grand admiration, as ſhould meet per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chance Mounſieur <hi>Finio,</hi>
                     </p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Fin.</speaker>
                     <p>Mounſieur <hi>Pacue</hi>
                     </p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Pac.</speaker>
                     <p>Ieſu? by Gar who thinke wee ſhall meete here?</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Fin.</speaker>
                     <p>By this hand I am not a little proud of it, ſir</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Oni.</speaker>
                     <p>This trick is onely for the the chamber, it cannot be cleanly done abroad,</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Pac.</speaker>
                     <p>Well what ſay you for dis den? Mounſieur:</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Fin.</speaker>
                     <p>Nay pray, ſir.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Pac.</speaker>
                     <p>Par ma foy vou bein encounters?</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Fin</speaker>
                     <p>What doe you meane ſir, let your gloue alone.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Pac.</speaker>
                     <p>Comen, ſe porte la ſante.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Fin.</speaker>
                     <p>Faith exceeding well ſir.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Pac,</speaker>
                     <p>Trot, be muſh ioy for heire.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Fin.</speaker>
                     <p>And how iſt with you ſweet ſignior <hi>Pache.</hi>
                     </p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Pac.</speaker>
                     <p>Fat comme vou voyer.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Oni.</speaker>
                     <p>Yong gentlemen? ſpirits of bloud, if euer youle taſt of a ſweet peece of mutton, do <hi>Onion</hi> a good turne now.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <pb facs="tcp:22306:24"/>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Pac.</speaker>
                     <p>Que que, parla Mounſeir, what iſt.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Oni.</speaker>
                     <p>Faith teach me one of theſe tricks.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Pac.</speaker>
                     <p>O me ſhall doe preſently, ſtand you deere, you ſigni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>or deere, my ſelfe is here: ſo fort bein, now I parle to Moun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeir <hi>Onion, Onion</hi> pratla to you, you ſpeaka to me, ſo, and as you parle chang the bonet, Mounſeir <hi>Onion.</hi>
                     </p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Oni.</speaker>
                     <p>Mounſeiur <hi>Finio.</hi>
                     </p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Fin.</speaker>
                     <p>Mounſeur <hi>Pacue.</hi>
                     </p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Pac.</speaker>
                     <p>Pray be couera.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Oni.</speaker>
                     <p>Nay I beſeech you ſir.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Fin.</speaker>
                     <p>What do you meane.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Pac.</speaker>
                     <p>Pardon moy, ſhall be ſo,</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Oni</speaker>
                     <p>O God ſir.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Fin.</speaker>
                     <p>Not I in good faith ſir.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Pac.</speaker>
                     <p>By gar you muſt.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Oni:</speaker>
                     <p>It ſhall be yours.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Fin.</speaker>
                     <p>Nay then you wrong me,</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Oni.</speaker>
                     <p>Well and euer I come to be great.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Pac.</speaker>
                     <p>You be big enough for de <hi>Onion</hi> already,</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Oni.</speaker>
                     <p>I meane a great man.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Fin.</speaker>
                     <p>Then thou'dſt be a monſter.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Oni.</speaker>
                     <p>Well God knowes not what fortune may doe, com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maund me, vſe me from the ſoule to the crowne, and the crowne to the ſoule: meaning not onely from the crowne of the head, and the ſole of the foot, but alſo the foote of the mind and the crownes of the purſe, I cannot ſtay now yong gentle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men but — time was, time is, and time ſhall be.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <stage>Exeunt.</stage>
                  <stage>Enter Chamount, Camillo.</stage>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Cha.</speaker>
                     <l>Sweet <hi>Iaſper</hi> I am ſorry we muſt part,</l>
                     <l>But ſtrong neceſſity enforceth it.</l>
                     <l>Let not the time ſeeme long vnto my friend,</l>
                     <l>Till my returne for by our loue I ſweare</l>
                     <l>(The ſacred ſpheare wherein our ſoules are knit)</l>
                     <l>I will endeauour to effect this buſines</l>
                     <l>With all induſtrious care and happy ſpeed.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <pb facs="tcp:22306:24"/>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Cam.</speaker>
                     <l>My Lord theſe circumſtances would come well,</l>
                     <l>To one leſſe capable of your deſert</l>
                     <l>Then I: in whom your mirrit is confirmed</l>
                     <l>With ſuch authenticall and grounded proues.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Cha.</speaker>
                     <p>Well I will vſe no more. <hi>Gaſper</hi> adiew.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Cam.</speaker>
                     <p>Farewell my honored Lord.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Cha.</speaker>
                     <p>Commend me to the Lady, my good <hi>Gaſper.</hi>
                     </p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Cam.</speaker>
                     <p>I had remembred that had not you vrgd it.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Cha.</speaker>
                     <p>Once more adiew ſweet <hi>Gaſper.</hi>
                     </p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Cam.</speaker>
                     <p>My good Lord.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <stage>Exit Camillo,</stage>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Cha.</speaker>
                     <l>Thy vertues are more precious then thy name,</l>
                     <l>Kind gentleman I would not ſell thy loue,</l>
                     <l>For all the earthly obiects that mine eyes,</l>
                     <l>Haue euer taſted, ſure thou art nobly borne,</l>
                     <l>How euer fortune hath obſcurd thy birth:</l>
                     <l>For natiue honour ſparkles in thine eyes,</l>
                     <l>How may I bleſſe the time wherein <hi>Chamont</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>My honored father did ſurpriſe vicenza,</l>
                     <l>Where this my friend (knowen by no name) was found,</l>
                     <l>Being then a child and ſcarce of power to ſpeake,</l>
                     <l>To whom my father gaue this name of <hi>Gaſper,</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>And as his owne reſpected him to death,</l>
                     <l>Since when wee two haue ſhard our mutuall fortunes,</l>
                     <l>With equall ſpirits, and but deathes rude hand,</l>
                     <l>No violence ſhall diſſolue this ſacred band.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <stage>Exit.</stage>
                  <stage>Enter Iuniper in his ſhop ſinging: to him Onion.</stage>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Oni.</speaker>
                     <p>Fellow <hi>Iuniper,</hi> no more of thy ſongs and ſonets, ſweet <hi>Iuniper,</hi> no more of thy hymnes and madrigals, thou ſing'ſt, but I ſigh.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Iuni</speaker>
                     <p>Whats the matter <hi>Peter</hi> ha? what in an Academy ſtill, ſtill in ſable, and coſtly black array? ha?</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Oni.</speaker>
                     <p>Prithee riſe mount, mount ſweet <hi>Iuniper,</hi> for I goe downe the wind, and yet I puffe: for I am vext.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Iuni.</speaker>
                     <p>Ha Bully? vext? what intoxicate? is thy braine in a
<pb facs="tcp:22306:25"/>quinteſcence? an Idea? a metamorphoſis? an Apology? ha rogue? come this loue feeds vpon thee, I ſee by thy cheekes, and drinkes healthes of vermilion, teares I ſee by thine eyes.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Oni.</speaker>
                     <p>I confeſſe <hi>Cupids</hi> carouſe, he plaies ſuper negulum with my liquor of life</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Iuni.</speaker>
                     <p>Tut, thou art a gooſe to be <hi>Cupids</hi> gull, go to, no more of this contemplations, &amp; calculations, mourne not, for <hi>Rachels</hi> thine owne</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Oni.</speaker>
                     <p>For that let the higher powers worke: but ſweet <hi>Iuni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per,</hi> I am not ſad for her, and yet for her in a ſecond perſon, or <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>f not ſo yet in a third.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Iuni.</speaker>
                     <p>How ſecond perſon? away, away, in the crotchets al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ready Longitude and Latitude? what ſecond? what perſon? ha?</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Oni.</speaker>
                     <p>
                        <hi>Iuniper,</hi> Ile bewray my ſelfe before thee, for thy com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pany is ſweet vnto me, but I muſt entreat thy helping hand in the caſe.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Iuni.</speaker>
                     <p>Tut? no more of this ſurquedry; I am thine owne? ad vngem vpſie freeze: pell mell, come, what caſe? what caſe?</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Oni.</speaker>
                     <p>For the caſe it may be any mans caſe, aſwell as mine, <hi>Rachel</hi> I meane, but Ile medle with her anon, in the meane time, <hi>
                           <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                              <desc>••</desc>
                           </gap>lentine</hi> is the man hath wrongd me.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Iuni.</speaker>
                     <p>How my <hi>Ingle</hi> wrong thee, iſt poſſible?</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Oni.</speaker>
                     <p>Your <hi>Ingle,</hi> hang him infidell, well and if I be not re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uengd one him let <hi>Peter Onion</hi> (by the infernall Gods) be tur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned to al eeke or a ſcalion, I ſpake to him for a ditty for this handkerchier.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Iuni.</speaker>
                     <p>Why, has he not done it?</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Oni.</speaker>
                     <p>Done it, not a verſe by this hand.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Iuni.</speaker>
                     <p>
                        <hi>O in dichus illis,</hi> O prepoſterous, wel come be blith, the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>eſt iud<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2+ letters">
                           <desc>••…</desc>
                        </gap> of the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>l is ſomtimes dul, fellow <hi>Onion</hi> pardon mine <hi>Iugle:</hi> he is a man, has in pefections and declinations, as other men haue, his maſſe ſomtimes cannot carnet nor progniſticat and come of, as it ſhould, no matter, Ile hammer our a para<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>l<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1+ letters">
                           <desc>•…</desc>
                        </gap>raſe for thee my ſelfe.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Oni.</speaker>
                     <p>No ſweet <hi>Iuniper,</hi> no danger <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                           <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                        </gap> breed delay, loue
<pb facs="tcp:22306:25"/>makes me chollericke I can beare no longer.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Iuni.</speaker>
                     <p>Not beare? what my mad Meridian ſlaue? not be are? what?</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Oni.</speaker>
                     <p>
                        <hi>Cupids</hi> burden: tis to heauy, to tollerable, and as for the handkerchire and the poſie: I will not trouble thee: but if thou wilt goe with me into her fathers backſide, old <hi>Iaques</hi> backſide, and ſpeake for me to <hi>Rachel,</hi> I wil not being ratitude, the old man is abroad and all.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Iuni.</speaker>
                     <p>Art thou ſure on't.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Oni.</speaker>
                     <p>As ſure as an obligation.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Iuni.</speaker>
                     <p>Lets away then, come we ſpend time in a vaine cir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cumference, trade <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1+ letters">
                           <desc>•…</desc>
                        </gap>caſhire thee til to morrow, fellow <hi>Onion</hi> for thy ſake I fini<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                           <desc>••</desc>
                        </gap> this workiday.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Oni.</speaker>
                     <p>God a mercy, and for thy ſake Ile at any time make a holiday.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <stage>Exunt.</stage>
                  <stage>Enter Angelio, Rachel.</stage>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Ang.</speaker>
                     <p>Nay I prithee <hi>Rachel,</hi> I come to comfort thee, Be not ſo ſad.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Rach.</speaker>
                     <l>O ſignior <hi>Angelo,</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>No comfort but his preſence can remoue,</l>
                     <l>This ſadneſſe from my heart.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Ang.</speaker>
                     <l>Nay then y'are fond,</l>
                     <l>And want that ſtrength of iudgement and election,</l>
                     <l>That ſhould be attendent on your yeares and forme,</l>
                     <l>Will you, becauſe your Lord is taken priſoner,</l>
                     <l>Blubber and weepe and keepe a peeuiſh ſtirre,</l>
                     <l>As though you would turne turtle with the newes,</l>
                     <l>Come, come, be wiſe. Sblood ſay your Lord ſhould die:</l>
                     <l>And you goe marre your face as you begin,</l>
                     <l>What would you doe trow? who would care for you;</l>
                     <l>But this it is, when nature will beſtow</l>
                     <l>Her gifts on ſuch as know not how to vſe them,</l>
                     <l>You ſhall haue ſome that had they but one quarter</l>
                     <l>Of your faire beauty? they would make it ſhew</l>
                     <pb facs="tcp:22306:26"/>
                     <l>A little otherwiſe then you do this,</l>
                     <l>Or they would ſee the painter twice an hower,</l>
                     <l>And I commend them I, that can vſe art,</l>
                     <l>With ſuch iudiciall practiſe.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Rach.</speaker>
                     <l>You talke iedly,</l>
                     <l>If this be your beſt comfort keepe it ſtill,</l>
                     <l>My ſences cannot feede on ſuch ſower cates.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Ang.</speaker>
                     <p>And why ſweet heart.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Rach.</speaker>
                     <p>Nay leaue good ſignior.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Ang.</speaker>
                     <p>Come I haue ſweeter vyands yet in ſtore.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <stage>Enter Onion and Iuniper.</stage>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Iuni.</speaker>
                     <p>I in any caſe miſtres <hi>Rachel.</hi>
                     </p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Ang.</speaker>
                     <p>
                        <hi>Rachel?</hi>
                     </p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Rach.</speaker>
                     <p>Gods pitty ſignior <hi>Angelo,</hi> I here my father, away for Gods ſake.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Ang:</speaker>
                     <p>S'bloud, I am betwixt, I thinke, this is twice now, I haue been ſerued thus.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <stage>Exit</stage>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Rach.</speaker>
                     <p>Pray God he meet him not.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <stage>Exit Rechel.</stage>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Oni.</speaker>
                     <p>O braue? ſhe's yonder, O terrible ſhee's gone.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Iuni.</speaker>
                     <p>Yea? ſo nimble in your <hi>Dilemma</hi>'s, and your <hi>Hiperbole's</hi> Hay my loue? O my loue, at the firſt ſight: By the maſſe.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Oni.</speaker>
                     <p>O how ſhe ſkudded, O ſweet ſcud, how ſhe tripped, O delicate trip and goe.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Iuni.</speaker>
                     <p>Come thou art enamored with the influence of her profundity, but ſirrah harke a little.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Oni.</speaker>
                     <p>O rare, what? what? paſſing Ifaith, what iſt? what iſt?</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Iuni.</speaker>
                     <p>What wilt thou ſay now, if <hi>Rachel</hi> ſtand now, and play hity tity through the key hole, to behold the equipage of thy perſon:</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Oni.</speaker>
                     <p>O ſweet equipage, try good <hi>Iuniper,</hi> tickle her, talke, talke, O? rare</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Iuni.</speaker>
                     <p>Miſtris <hi>Rachel</hi> (watch then if her father come) <hi>Rachel? Madona? Rachel?</hi> No.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Oni.</speaker>
                     <p>Say I am here, <hi>Onion</hi> or <hi>Peter</hi> or ſo.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <pb facs="tcp:22306:26"/>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Iuni.</speaker>
                     <p>No, Ile knock, weele not ſtand vpon Horizons, and tricks, but fall roundly to the matter.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Oni.</speaker>
                     <p>Well ſaid ſweet <hi>Iuniper:</hi> Horizons? hang hem? knock, knock.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Rach.</speaker>
                     <p>Whoſe there? father.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Iuni.</speaker>
                     <p>Father no? and yet a father, if you pleaſe to be a mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Oni.</speaker>
                     <p>Well ſaid <hi>Iuniper,</hi> to her againe, a ſmack or two more of the mother</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Iuni.</speaker>
                     <p>Do you here? ſweet ſoule, ſweet radamant? ſweet ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thauell one word <hi>Melpomine?</hi> are you at leaſure.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Rach.</speaker>
                     <p>At leaſure? what to doe?</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Iuni.</speaker>
                     <p>To doe what, to doe nothing, but to be liable to the extaſie of true loues exigent, or ſo, you ſmell my meaning.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Oni.</speaker>
                     <p>Smell, filthy, fellow <hi>Iuniper</hi> filthy? ſmell? O moſt odi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Iuni.</speaker>
                     <p>How filthy.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Oni.</speaker>
                     <p>Filthy, by this finger? ſmell? ſmell a rat, ſmel a pudding, away theſe tricks are for truls, a plaine wench loues plaine dealing, ile vpon my ſelfe, ſmel to march paine wench.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Iuni.</speaker>
                     <p>With all my heart, Ile be legitimate and ſilent as anap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple-ſquire, Ile ſee nothing, and ſay nothing.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Oni.</speaker>
                     <p>Sweet hart, ſweet hart?</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Iuni.</speaker>
                     <p>And bag pudding, ha, ha, ha?</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Iaq.</speaker>
                     <p>What <hi>Rachel</hi> my girle what <hi>Rachel;</hi>
                     </p>
                     <stage>Within</stage>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Oni.</speaker>
                     <p>Gods lid<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
                     </p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Iaq.</speaker>
                     <p>What <hi>Rachel,</hi>
                     </p>
                     <stage>Within</stage>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Rach.</speaker>
                     <p>Here I am</p>
                     <stage>Within</stage>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Oni</speaker>
                     <p>What rakehell cals <hi>Rachel:</hi> O treaſon to my loue.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Iuni.</speaker>
                     <p>Its her father on my life, how ſhall wee entrench and edifie our ſelues from him?</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Oni.</speaker>
                     <p>O conni-catching<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> 
                        <hi>Cupid.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <stage>Enter Iaques.</stage>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Iaq.</speaker>
                     <l>How in my back ſide? where? what come they for?</l>
                     <stage>Onion gets vp into a tree.</stage>
                     <l>Where are they? <hi>Rachel?</hi> theeues, theeues?</l>
                     <l>Stay villaine ſlaue: <hi>Rachel?</hi> vntye my dog.</l>
                     <pb facs="tcp:22306:27" rendition="simple:additions"/>
                     <l>Nay theife thou canſt not ſcape.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Iuni.</speaker>
                     <p>I pray you ſir.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Oni.</speaker>
                     <p>A pitifull <hi>Onion,</hi> that thou hadſt a rope.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Iaq.</speaker>
                     <p>Why <hi>Rachel:</hi> when I ſay: let looſe my dog? garlique my maſtiue, let him looſe I ſay.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Iuni.</speaker>
                     <p>For Gods ſake here me ſpeake, keepe vp your cur.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Oni.</speaker>
                     <p>I feare not garlique, heele not bite <hi>Onion</hi> his kinſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man pray God he come out, and then theile not ſmell me.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Iaq.</speaker>
                     <p>well then deliuer, come deliuer ſlaue?</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Iuni.</speaker>
                     <p>What ſhould I deliuer?</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Iaq.</speaker>
                     <p>O thou wouldſt haue me tell thee? wouldſt thou ſhew me thy hands, what haſt thou in thy hands?</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Iuni.</speaker>
                     <p>Here be my hands.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Iaq.</speaker>
                     <p>Stay are not thy fingers ends begrimd with durt, no thou haſt wipt them.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Iuni.</speaker>
                     <p>Wipt them?</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Iaq.</speaker>
                     <p>I thou villaine? thou art a ſubtile knaue, put off thy ſhewes, come I will ſee them, giue me a knife here <hi>Rachel,</hi> Ile rip the ſoles.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Oni.</speaker>
                     <p>No matter he's a cobler, he can mend them.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Iuni.</speaker>
                     <p>What are you mad? are you deteſtable, would you make an Anatomy of me, thinke you I am not true Ortogra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phie?</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Iaq.</speaker>
                     <p>Ortographie, Anatomy?</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Iuni.</speaker>
                     <p>For Gods ſake be not ſo inuiolable, I am no ambuſca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>do, what predicament call you this, why do you intimate ſo much.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Iaq.</speaker>
                     <p>I can feele nothing.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Oni.</speaker>
                     <p>Bir Lady but <hi>Onion</hi> feeles ſomething.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Iaq.</speaker>
                     <p>Soft ſir, you are not yet gon, ſhake your legs, come, and your armes, be briefe, ſtay let me ſee theſe drums, theſe kil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derkins, theſe bombard ſlops, what is it crams hem ſo.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Iuni.</speaker>
                     <p>Nothing but haire.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Iaq.</speaker>
                     <p>Thats true, I had almoſt forgot this rug, this hedghogs neſt, this hay mowe, this beares ſkin, this heath, this firſbuſh.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Iuni.</speaker>
                     <p>O let me goe, you teare my haire, you reluolue my
<pb facs="tcp:22306:27"/>braines and vnderſtanding.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Iaq.</speaker>
                     <l>Heart, thou art ſomewhat eas'd? halfe of my feare</l>
                     <l>Hath tane his leaue of my, the other halfe</l>
                     <l>Still keepes poſſeſſion in diſpight of hope,</l>
                     <l>Vntill theſe amorous eyes, court my faire gold:</l>
                     <l>Deare I come to thee: friend, why art not gone?</l>
                     <l>Auoid my ſoules vexation, Sathan hence?</l>
                     <l>Why doeſt thou ſtare on me, why doeſt thou ſtay?</l>
                     <l>Why por'ſt thou on the ground with theeuiſh eyes?</l>
                     <l>What ſee'ſt thou there, thou curre? what gap'ſt thou at?</l>
                     <l>Hence from my houſe, <hi>Rachel,</hi> ſend garlick forth.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Iunip.</speaker>
                     <p>I am gone ſir, I am gone, for Gods ſake ſtay.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <stage>Exit Iuniper.</stage>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Iaq.</speaker>
                     <p>Pack, and thanke God thou ſcap'ſt ſo well away.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Oni.</speaker>
                     <p>If I ſcape this tree, deſtinies, I defie you.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Iaq.</speaker>
                     <l>I cannot ſee by any Characters</l>
                     <l>Writ on this earth, that any fellon foote</l>
                     <l>Hath tane acquaintance of this hallowed ground.</l>
                     <l>None ſees me: knees do homage to your Lord.</l>
                     <l>Tis ſafe, tis ſafe, it lyes and ſleepes ſo ſoundly,</l>
                     <l>Twould do one good to looke on't. If this bliſſe</l>
                     <l>Be giuen to any man that hath much gold,</l>
                     <l>Iuſtly to ſay tis ſafe, I ſay tis ſafe.</l>
                     <l>O what a heauenly round theſe two words dance</l>
                     <l>Within me and without me: Firſt I thinke hem,</l>
                     <l>And then I ſpeake hem, then I watch their ſound,</l>
                     <l>And drinke it greedily with both mine eares,</l>
                     <l>Then thinke, then ſpeake, then drinke their ſound againe,</l>
                     <l>And racket round about this bodies court.</l>
                     <l>Theſe two ſweet words: <hi>tis ſafe:</hi> ſtay I will feed</l>
                     <l>My other ſences, ô how ſweet it ſmels</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Oni.</speaker>
                     <p>I mar'le he ſmels not <hi>Onion,</hi> being ſo neere it.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Iaq.</speaker>
                     <l>Downe to thy graue againe, thou beauteous Ghoſt,</l>
                     <l>Angels men ſay, are ſpirits: Spirits be</l>
                     <l>Inuiſible, bright angels are you ſo?</l>
                     <l>Be you inuiſible to euery eye.</l>
                     <l>Saue onely theſe: Sleepe, Ile not breake your reſt,</l>
                     <l>Though you breake mine: Deare Saints adiew, adiew:</l>
                     <l>My feete part from you, but my ſoule dwels with you.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <stage>Exit.</stage>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Oni.</speaker>
                     <l>Is he gone? ô Fortune my friend, &amp; not fortune my foe,</l>
                     <l>I come downe to embrace thee, and kiſſe thy great toe.</l>
                     <stage>Enter Iuniper.</stage>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Iunip.</speaker>
                     <p>Fellow <hi>Onion? Peter.</hi>
                     </p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Oni.</speaker>
                     <p>Fellow <hi>Iuniper.</hi> What's the old panurgo gone? departed, coſmografied, ha?</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Oni.</speaker>
                     <p>O I, and harke Sirrah. Shall I tell him? no.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Iunip.</speaker>
                     <p>Nay, be briefe and declare, ſtand not vpon cono<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>drums now, thou knoweſt what contagious ſpeeches I haue ſufferd for thy ſake and he ſhould come againe and inuent me here.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Oni.</speaker>
                     <l>He ſaies true, it was for my ſake, I will tell him.</l>
                     <l>Sirra <hi>Iuniper?</hi> and yet I will not.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Iunip.</speaker>
                     <p>What ſayeſt thou ſweete <hi>Onion?</hi>
                     </p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Oni.</speaker>
                     <p>And thou hadſt ſmelt the ſent of me when I was in the tree, thou wouldeſt not haue ſaid ſo: but Sirra, <hi>The caſe is al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terd</hi> with me, my heart has giuen loue a box of the eare, made him kicke vp the heeles I faith.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Iunip.</speaker>
                     <p>Sayeſt thou me ſo, wad Greeke? how haps it? how chances it.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Oni.</speaker>
                     <p>I cannot hold it, <hi>Iuniper,</hi> haue an eye, looke, haue an eye to the doore, the old prouerb's true, I ſee: gold is but mucke. Nay Gods ſo <hi>Iuniper</hi> to the doore, an eye to the maine chance, here you ſlaue, haue an eye.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Iunip.</speaker>
                     <p>O inexorable! ô infallible! ô infricate deuine, and ſuperficiall fortune.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Oni.</speaker>
                     <p>Nay, it will be ſufficient anon, here, looke heere.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Iunip.</speaker>
                     <p>O inſolent good lucke! How didſt thou produce th'intelligence of the gold' mynerals.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Oni.</speaker>
                     <l>Ile tell you that anon, heere, make ſhift, conuey, cramme.</l>
                     <l>Ile teach you how you ſhall call for garlike againe I faith.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <pb facs="tcp:22306:28"/>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Iunip.</speaker>
                     <p>S'bloud what ſhall we do with all this? we ſhall nere bring it to a conſumption.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Oni.</speaker>
                     <p>Conſumption? why weele bee moſt ſumptuouſly at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tir'd, man.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Iunip.</speaker>
                     <p>By this gold, I will haue three or foure moſt ſtigma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticall ſuites preſently.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Oni.</speaker>
                     <p>Ile go in my foot-cloth, Ile turne Gentleman.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Iunip.</speaker>
                     <p>So will I.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Oni.</speaker>
                     <p>But what badge ſhall we giue, what culliſon?</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Iunip.</speaker>
                     <p>As for that lets vſe the infidelity and commiſeration of ſome harrot of armes, he ſhall giue vs a gudgeon.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Oni.</speaker>
                     <p>A gudgeon? a ſcutheon thou wouldſt ſay, man.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Iunip.</speaker>
                     <p>A ſcutcheon or a gudgeon, all is one.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Oni.</speaker>
                     <p>Well, our armes be good inough, lets looke to our legges.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Iunip.</speaker>
                     <p>Content, weele be iogging.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Oni.</speaker>
                     <p>
                        <hi>Rachel?</hi> we retire: garlike God boy ye.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Iunip.</speaker>
                     <p>Farewell ſweete <hi>Iaques.</hi>
                     </p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Oni.</speaker>
                     <p>Farewell ſweete <hi>Rachel,</hi> ſweet dogge adiew.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <stage>Exeunt.</stage>
                  <stage>Fnter Maximilian, Count Ferneze, Aurelia, Phoe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nixella, Pache.</stage>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Max.</speaker>
                     <p>Nay but ſweet <hi>Count.</hi>
                     </p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Count.</speaker>
                     <l>Away, Ile heare no more,</l>
                     <l>Neuer was man ſo palpably abuld,</l>
                     <l>My ſonne ſo baſely marted; and my ſelfe</l>
                     <l>Am made the ſubiect of your mirth and ſcorne.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Max.</speaker>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Count Ferneze</hi> you tread to hard vpon my patience,</l>
                     <l>Do not perſiſt I aduiſe your Lordſhip.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Count.</speaker>
                     <l>I will perſiſt, and vnto thee I ſpeake.</l>
                     <l>Thou. <hi>Maximilian</hi> thou haſt iniur'd me.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Max.</speaker>
                     <p>Before the Lord:</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Aur.</speaker>
                     <p>Sweet ſignior.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Phoe</speaker>
                     <p>O my father.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Mvx.</speaker>
                     <p>Lady let your father thank your beauty.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <pb facs="tcp:22306:29"/>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Pac.</speaker>
                     <l>By gar me ſhall be hang for tella dis ſame,</l>
                     <l>Metella madamoy ſelle, ſhe tell her ſadera.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Count.</speaker>
                     <l>The true <hi>Chamount</hi> ſet free, and one left here</l>
                     <l>Of no deſcent, clad barely in his name.</l>
                     <l>Sirrah boy come hither, and be ſure, you ſpeake the ſimple truth:</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Pac.</speaker>
                     <p>O pardone moy mounſieur,</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Count</speaker>
                     <l>Come leaue your pardons, and directly ſay.</l>
                     <l>What villaine is the ſame that hath vſurpt,</l>
                     <l>The honor'd name and perſon of <hi>Chamount:</hi>
                     </l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Pac</speaker>
                     <p>O Mounſieur, no point villaine, braue Cheualier, Mounſieur <hi>Gaſper.</hi>
                     </p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Count.</speaker>
                     <p>Mounſieur <hi>Gaſper,</hi> on what occaſion did they change their names, what was their policy, or their pretext.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Pac.</speaker>
                     <p>Me canno tell, par ma foy Mounſieur.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Max.</speaker>
                     <p>My honorable Lord.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Count.</speaker>
                     <p>Tut tut, be ſilent.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Max.</speaker>
                     <l>Silent? <hi>Count Ferneze,</hi> I tell thee if <hi>Amurath</hi> the great</l>
                     <l>Turke were here I would ſpeake, and he ſhould here me.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Count.</speaker>
                     <p>So will not I.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Max.</speaker>
                     <p>By my fathers hand, but thou ſhalt <hi>Count,</hi> I ſay till this inſtant, I was neuer toucht in my reputation: here me you ſhall knowe that you haue wrongd me, and I will make you ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>knowledge it, if I cannot my ſword ſhall.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Count.</speaker>
                     <l>By heauen I will not, I will ſtop mine eares,</l>
                     <l>My ſences loath the Sauiour of thy breath.</l>
                     <l>Tis poyſon to me, I ſay I will not heare.</l>
                     <l>What ſhall I know, tis you haue iniurd me,</l>
                     <l>What will you make? make me acknowledge it.</l>
                     <l>Fetch forth that <hi>Gaſper,</hi> that lewd counterfeit.</l>
                     <stage>Enter ſeruing with Camillo.</stage>
                     <l>Ile make him to your face approue your wrongs.</l>
                     <l>Come on falſe ſubſtance, ſhadow to <hi>Chamont:</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>Had you none elſe to worke vpon but me,</l>
                     <l>Was I your fitteſt proiect? well confeſſe,</l>
                     <l>What you intended by this ſecret plot.</l>
                     <pb facs="tcp:22306:29"/>
                     <l>And by whoſe policy it was contriu'd,</l>
                     <l>Speake truth, and be intreated courteouſly,</l>
                     <l>But double with me, and reſolue to proue</l>
                     <l>The extremeſt rigor that I can inflict.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Cam.</speaker>
                     <l>My honor'd Lord, heare me with patience,</l>
                     <l>Nor hope of fauour, not the feare of torment,</l>
                     <l>Shall ſway my tongue, from vttring of a truth.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Count.</speaker>
                     <p>Tis well, proceed then.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Cam.</speaker>
                     <l>The morne before this battell did begin,</l>
                     <l>Wherein my Lord <hi>Chamount</hi> and I were tane,</l>
                     <l>We vow'd one mutuall fortune, good or bad,</l>
                     <l>That day ſhould be imbraced of vs both,</l>
                     <l>And vrging that might worſt ſucceede our vow,</l>
                     <l>We there concluded to exchange our names.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Count.</speaker>
                     <p>Then <hi>Maximilian</hi> tooke you for <hi>Chamount.</hi>
                     </p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Cam.</speaker>
                     <p>True noble Lord.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Count.</speaker>
                     <l>Tis falſe, ignoble wretch,</l>
                     <l>Twas but a complot to betray my ſonne.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Max.</speaker>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Count,</hi> thou lyeſt in thy boſome, <hi>Count<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
                        </hi>
                     </l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Count.</speaker>
                     <p>Lye?</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Cam.</speaker>
                     <l>Nay I beſeech you honor'd gentlemen,</l>
                     <l>Let not the vntimely ruine of your loue,</l>
                     <l>Follow theſe ſleight occurents; be aſſured</l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Chamounts</hi> returne will heale theſe wounds againe,</l>
                     <l>And breake the points of your too piercing thoughts.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Count.</speaker>
                     <l>Returne? I when? when will <hi>Chamount</hi> returne?</l>
                     <l>Heele come to fetch you, will he? I tis like,</l>
                     <l>Youl'd haue me thinke ſo, that's your policy.</l>
                     <l>No, no, yong gallant, your deuice is ſtale,</l>
                     <l>You cannot feed me with ſo vaine a hope.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Cam.</speaker>
                     <l>My Lord, I feede you not with a vaine hope,</l>
                     <l>I know aſſuredly he will returne,</l>
                     <l>And bring your noble ſonne along with him.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Max.</speaker>
                     <p>I, I dare pawne my ſoule he will returne.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Count.</speaker>
                     <l>O impudent diriſion? open ſcorne?</l>
                     <l>Intollerable wrong? is't not inough?</l>
                     <pb facs="tcp:22306:30"/>
                     <l>That you haue plaid vpon me all this while;</l>
                     <l>But ſtill to mocke me, ſtill to ieſt at me?</l>
                     <l>Fellowes, away with him, thou ill-bred ſlaue,</l>
                     <l>That ſets no difference twixt a noble ſpirit,</l>
                     <l>And thy owne ſlauiſh humour, do not thinke</l>
                     <l>But ile take worthy vengeance on thee, wretch?</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Cam.</speaker>
                     <l>Alas, theſe threats are idle, like the wind,</l>
                     <l>And breed no terror in a guiltleſſe mind.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Count.</speaker>
                     <p>Nay, thou ſhalt want no torture, ſo reſolue, bring him away.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Cam.</speaker>
                     <l>Welcome the worſt, I ſuffer for a friend,</l>
                     <l>Your tortures will, my loue ſhall neuer end.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <stage>Exeunt.</stage>
                  <stage>Manent Maximillian, Aurelia, Phoenixella, Pacue.</stage>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Phoen.</speaker>
                     <l>Alas poore gentleman, my fathers rage</l>
                     <l>Is too extreame, too ſterne and violent</l>
                     <l>O that I knew with all my ſtrongeſt powers,</l>
                     <l>How to remoue it from thy patient breaſt,</l>
                     <l>But that I cannot, yet my willing heart,</l>
                     <l>Shall miniſter in ſpight of tyranny</l>
                     <l>To thy miſfortune, ſomething there is in him,</l>
                     <l>That doth enforce this ſtrange affection,</l>
                     <l>With more then common rapture in my breaſt:</l>
                     <l>For being but <hi>Gaſper,</hi> he is ſtill as deare</l>
                     <l>To me, as when he did <hi>Chamount</hi> appeare.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <stage>Exit Phoenixella.</stage>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Aure.</speaker>
                     <p>But in good ſadneſſe Signior, do you thinke <hi>Cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mount</hi> will returne?</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Max.</speaker>
                     <p>Do I ſee your face, Lady?</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Aure.</speaker>
                     <p>I ſure, if loue haue not blinded you.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Max.</speaker>
                     <p>That is a queſtion, but I will aſſure you no, I can ſee, and yet loue is in mine eye: well, the <hi>Count</hi> your father ſimply hath diſhonor'd me: and this ſteele ſhall engraue it on his burgonet.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Aure.</speaker>
                     <p>Nay, ſweet Signior.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Max.</speaker>
                     <l>Lady, I do preferre my reputation to my life,</l>
                     <l>But you ſhall rule me, come lets march.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <stage>Exit Maximillian.</stage>
                  <pb facs="tcp:22306:30"/>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Aure.</speaker>
                     <l>Ile follow Signior, ô ſweet Queene of loue!</l>
                     <l>Soueraigne of all my thoughts, and thou faire fortune,</l>
                     <l>Who (more to honour my affections)</l>
                     <l>Haſt thus tranſlated <hi>Gaſper</hi> to <hi>Chamount.</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>Let both your flames now burne in one bright ſpeare;</l>
                     <l>And giue true light to my a ſpiring hopes,</l>
                     <l>Haſten <hi>Chamounts</hi> returne, let him affect me,</l>
                     <l>Though father, friends, and all the world reiect me.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <stage>Exit.</stage>
                  <stage>Enter Angelo, Chriſtopher.</stage>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Ange.</speaker>
                     <l>Sigh for a woman, would I fould mine armes,</l>
                     <l>Raue in my ſleepe, talke idly being awake,</l>
                     <l>Pine and looke pale, make loue-walkes in the night,</l>
                     <l>To ſteale cold comfort from a day-ſtarres eyes.</l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Kit,</hi> thou art a foole, wilt thou be wiſe? then lad</l>
                     <l>Renounce this boy-gods nice idolatry,</l>
                     <l>Stand not on complement, and wooing trickes,</l>
                     <l>Thou loueſt old <hi>Iaques</hi> daughter, doeſt thou?</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Chriſ.</speaker>
                     <p>Loue her?</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Ange.</speaker>
                     <l>Come, come, I know't, be rul'd and ſhees thine owne,</l>
                     <l>Thou't ſay her father <hi>Iaques,</hi> the old begger,</l>
                     <l>Hath pawnd his word to thee, that none but thou,</l>
                     <l>Shalt be his ſonne in law.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Chriſ.</speaker>
                     <p>He has.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Ange.</speaker>
                     <l>He has? wilt thou beleeue him, and be made a kooke,</l>
                     <l>To waite on ſuch an antique wether cocke;</l>
                     <l>Why he is more inconſtant then the ſea,</l>
                     <l>His thoughts, <hi>Cameleon</hi>-like, change euery minute:</l>
                     <l>No <hi>Kit,</hi> worke ſoundly, ſteale the wench away,</l>
                     <l>Wed her, and bed her, and when that is done,</l>
                     <l>Then ſay to <hi>Iaques,</hi> ſhall I be your ſonne?</l>
                     <l>But come to our deuiſe, where is this gold?</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Chriſ.</speaker>
                     <p>Heere Signior <hi>Angelo.</hi>
                     </p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Ange.</speaker>
                     <l>Beſtow it, bid thy hands ſhed golden drops,</l>
                     <l>Let theſe bald french crownes be vncouered,</l>
                     <pb facs="tcp:22306:31"/>
                     <l>In open ſight, to do obeyſance</l>
                     <l>To <hi>Iaques</hi> ſtaring eyes when he ſteps forth,</l>
                     <l>The needy beggar will be glad of gold.</l>
                     <l>So, now keepe thou alooſe, and as he treades</l>
                     <l>This guilded path, ſtretch out his ambling hopes,</l>
                     <l>With ſcattring more &amp; more, &amp; as thou go'ſt, cry <hi>Iaques, Iaques</hi>
                     </l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Chriſ.</speaker>
                     <p>Tuſt, let me alone.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Ang.</speaker>
                     <p>Firſt ile play the ghoſt, Ile cal him out, <hi>Kit</hi> keep aloofe.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Chriſ.</speaker>
                     <p>But Signior <hi>Angelo.</hi> Where wil your ſelfe and <hi>Rachel</hi> ſtay for me, after the ieſt is ended?</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Ange.</speaker>
                     <p>Maſſe, that's true, at the old Priory behinde S. <hi>Foyes.</hi>
                     </p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Chriſ.</speaker>
                     <p>Agreed, no better place, ile meete you there.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Ange.</speaker>
                     <l>Do good foole, do, but ile not meet you there.</l>
                     <l>Now to this geere, <hi>Iaques, Iaques,</hi> what <hi>Iaques?</hi>
                     </l>
                  </sp>
                  <stage>within</stage>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Iaq.</speaker>
                     <p>Who cals? whoſe there?</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Ange.</speaker>
                     <p>
                        <hi>Iaques.</hi>
                     </p>
                  </sp>
                  <stage>within</stage>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Iaq.</speaker>
                     <p>Who cals?</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Ange.</speaker>
                     <p>Steward, he comes, he comes <hi>Iaques.</hi>
                     </p>
                  </sp>
                  <stage>Enter Iaques.</stage>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Iaq.</speaker>
                     <l>What voice is this? no body here, was I not cald? I was.</l>
                     <l>And one cride <hi>Iaques</hi> with a hollow voyce,</l>
                     <l>I was deceiu'd, no I was not deceiu'd,</l>
                     <l>See ſee, it was an Angell cald me forth,</l>
                     <l>Gold, gold, man<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> making gold, another ſtarre,</l>
                     <l>Drop they from heauen, no, no, my houſe I hope</l>
                     <l>Is haunted with a Fairy. My deere Lar,</l>
                     <l>My houſhold God, My Fairy on my knees.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Chriſt.</speaker>
                     <p>
                        <hi>Iaques.</hi>
                     </p>
                  </sp>
                  <stage>
                     <hi>Exit Chriſtopher<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>.</hi>
                  </stage>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Iaq.</speaker>
                     <l>My Lar doth call me, ô ſweet voyce.</l>
                     <l>Muſicall as the ſpheares, ſee, ſee, more gold.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <stage>within</stage>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Chriſ.</speaker>
                     <p>
                        <hi>Iaques.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <stage>Enter Rachel.</stage>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <stage>Iaq.</stage>
                     <p>What <hi>Rachel, Rachel,</hi> lock my doore, looke to my houſe.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <stage>within</stage>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Chriſ.</speaker>
                     <p>
                        <hi>Iaques.</hi>
                     </p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Iaq.</speaker>
                     <p>Shut faſt my doore, a golden crowne, <hi>Iaques</hi> ſhall be a king.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <stage>Exit.</stage>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Ange.</speaker>
                     <l>To a fooles paradice that path will bring</l>
                     <l>Thee and thy houſhold Lar.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Rach.</speaker>
                     <p>What means my father, I wonder what ſtrange humor.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <pb facs="tcp:22306:31"/>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Ange.</speaker>
                     <p>Come ſweete ſoule, leaue wondring, ſtart not, twas I laid this plot to get thy father forth.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Rach.</speaker>
                     <p>O <hi>Angelo.</hi>
                     </p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Ange.</speaker>
                     <l>O me no oo's, but heare, my Lord your loue,</l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Paulo Ferneze</hi> is returnd from warre,</l>
                     <l>Lingers at <hi>Pont Valeria,</hi> and from thence</l>
                     <l>By poſt at midnight laſt, I was coniur'd</l>
                     <l>To man you thither, ſtand not on replies,</l>
                     <l>A horſe is ſadled for you, will you go,</l>
                     <l>And I am for you, if you will ſtay, why ſo.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Rach.</speaker>
                     <p>O <hi>Angelo,</hi> each minute is a day till my <hi>Ferneze</hi> come, come weele away ſir.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Ange.</speaker>
                     <l>Sweet ſoule I gueſſe thy meaning by thy lookes,</l>
                     <l>At po<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>t <hi>Valerio</hi> thou thy loue ſhalt ſee,</l>
                     <l>But not <hi>Ferneze,</hi> Steward fare you well.</l>
                     <l>You wait for <hi>Rachel</hi> to, when can you tell?</l>
                  </sp>
                  <stage>Exeunt. Enter Iaq.</stage>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Iaq.</speaker>
                     <l>O in what golden circle haue I dan'ſt?</l>
                     <l>Millaine theſe od'rous and enfloured fields</l>
                     <l>Are none of thine, no heres <hi>Elizium,</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>Heere bleſſed ghoſts do walke, this is the Court</l>
                     <l>And glorious palace where the God of gold</l>
                     <l>Shines like the ſonne, of ſparkling maieſty;</l>
                     <l>O faire fethered, my red-breſted birds,</l>
                     <l>Come flye with me, ile bring you to a quier,</l>
                     <l>Whoſe conſort being ſweetned with your ſound:</l>
                     <l>The muſique will be fuller, and each hower</l>
                     <l>Theſe eares ſhall banquet with your harmony ô, ô, ô,</l>
                     <stage>Enter Chriſt.</stage>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Chriſ.</speaker>
                     <l>At the old priorie, behind Saint Foyes,</l>
                     <l>That was the place of our appointment ſure:</l>
                     <l>I hope he will not make me looſe my gold,</l>
                     <l>And mock me to, perhaps they are within: Ile knock.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Iaq.</speaker>
                     <p>O God, the caſe is alterd.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Chriſt.</speaker>
                     <p>
                        <hi>Rachel?</hi>
                     </p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Angelo?</speaker>
                     <p>Signior <hi>Angelo?</hi>
                     </p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Iaq.</speaker>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Angels?</hi> I where? mine <hi>Angels?</hi> wher's my gold?</l>
                     <l>Why <hi>Rachel?</hi> O thou theeuiſh <hi>Canibal,</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>Thou eateſt my fleſh in ſtealing of my gold.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <pb facs="tcp:22306:32"/>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Chriſ.</speaker>
                     <p>What gold?</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Iaq.</speaker>
                     <l>What gold? <hi>Rachel</hi> call help, come forth,</l>
                     <l>Ile rip thine entrailes, but ile haue my gold:</l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Rachel</hi> why comes thou not? I am vndone,</l>
                     <l>Ay me ſhe ſpeakes not, thou haſt ſlaine my child.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <stage>Exit</stage>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Chriſ.</speaker>
                     <l>What is the man poſſeſt trow? this is ſtrange,</l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Rachel</hi> I ſee is gone with <hi>Angelo:</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>Well ile once againe vnto the priory,</l>
                     <l>And ſee if I can meete them.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <stage>Exit Chriſtopher,</stage>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Iaq.</speaker>
                     <l>Tis too true,</l>
                     <stage>Enter Iaques</stage>
                     <l>Th'aſt made away my child, how haſt my gold:</l>
                     <l>O what <hi>Hienna</hi> cald me out of dores,</l>
                     <l>The theife is gone: my gold's gone, <hi>Rachels</hi> gone,</l>
                     <l>Al's gone? ſaue I that ſpend my cries in vaine,</l>
                     <l>But ile hence too, and die or end this paine.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <stage>Exit.</stage>
                  <stage>Enter Iuniper, Onion, Finio, Valentine.</stage>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Iuni.</speaker>
                     <l>Swonds, let me goe, hay catſo, catch him aliue,</l>
                     <l>I call, I call, boy, I come, I come ſweet heart.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Oni.</speaker>
                     <p>Page hold my rapier, while I hold my freind here.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Valen.</speaker>
                     <p>O heer's a ſweet metamorphoſis, a cupple of buz<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zards turn'd to a paire of peacocks.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Iuni.</speaker>
                     <p>Signior <hi>Onion,</hi> lend me thy boy to vnhang my rapier. <hi>On.</hi> Signior <hi>Iuniper</hi> for once or ſo, but troth is, you muſt inuei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gle, as I haue done, my Lords page here a poor folower of mine.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Iuni.</speaker>
                     <p>Hei ho, your page then ſha'not be ſuper intendent vpon me? he ſhall not be addicted? he ſhall not be incident? he ſhall not be incident? he ſhall not be incident, ſhall he?</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Fin.</speaker>
                     <l>O ſweet ſignior <hi>Iuniper.</hi>
                     </l>
                     <stage>He foynes</stage>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Iuni</hi> Sbloud ſtand away princocks? do not aggrauate my ioy.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Valen.</speaker>
                     <p>Nay good Maiſter. <hi>Onion.</hi>
                     </p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Oni.</speaker>
                     <p>Nay and he haue the heart to draw my bloud, let him come.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Iuni.</speaker>
                     <p>Ile ſlice you <hi>Onion,</hi> Ile ſlice you?</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Oni.</speaker>
                     <p>Ile cleaue you <hi>Iuniper.</hi>
                     </p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Valen.</speaker>
                     <p>Why hold, hold, hough? what do you meane?</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Iuni.</speaker>
                     <p>Let him come <hi>Ingle,</hi> ſtand by boy, his allebaſter blad
<pb facs="tcp:22306:32"/>cannot feare me.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Fin.</speaker>
                     <p>Why heare you ſweet ſignior, let not there be any conte<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tion, betweene my Maiſter &amp; you, about me, if you want a page ſir, I can helpe you to a proper ſtripling.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Iuni.</speaker>
                     <p>Canſt thou? what parentage? what anceſtry? what ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nealogy is he?</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Fin.</speaker>
                     <p>A french boy ſir.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Iuni.</speaker>
                     <p>Has he his French linguiſt? has he?</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Fin.</speaker>
                     <p>I, ſir.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Iuni.</speaker>
                     <p>Then tranſport him: her's a cruſado for thee.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Oni.</speaker>
                     <p>You will not, imbecell my ſeruant with your bene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uolence will you, hold boy their's a portmantu for thee.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Fin.</speaker>
                     <p>Lord ſir.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>On.</speaker>
                     <p>Do take it boy, its three pounds ten ſhill. a portmantu.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Fin.</speaker>
                     <p>I thanke your Lordſhip.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <stage>Exit Finio.</stage>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Iuni.</speaker>
                     <l>Sirrah <hi>Ningle:</hi> thou art a traueller, and I honour thee.</l>
                     <l>I prithee diſcourſe? cheriſh thy muſe? diſcourſe?</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Valen.</speaker>
                     <p>Of what ſir?</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Iuni.</speaker>
                     <p>Of what thou wilt. Sbloud? hang ſorrow?</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Oni.</speaker>
                     <p>Prithy <hi>Valentine</hi> aſſoile me one thing.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Valen.</speaker>
                     <p>Tis pitty to ſoile you ſir, your new apparell.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>On.</speaker>
                     <p>Maſſe thou ſaiſt true, aparel makes a man forget himſelf.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Iun.</speaker>
                     <p>Begin, find your tongue <hi>Ningle.</hi>
                     </p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Val.</speaker>
                     <l>Now will gull theſe ganders rarely:</l>
                     <l>Gentlemen hauing in my peregrinatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> through Meſopotamia.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Iun.</speaker>
                     <l>Speake legibly, this gam's gone, without the great mercy of God,</l>
                     <l>Heres a fine tragedy indeed. Thers a Keiſars royall.</l>
                     <l>By Gods lid, nor King nor Keiſar ſhall?</l>
                  </sp>
                  <stage>Enter Finio, Pacue, Balt. Martino.</stage>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Balt.</speaker>
                     <p>Where? where? <hi>Finio,</hi> where be they.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Iun.</speaker>
                     <p>Go to, ile be with you anon.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Oni.</speaker>
                     <p>O her's the page ſignior <hi>Iuniper:</hi>
                     </p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Iun.</speaker>
                     <p>What ſayth monſier <hi>Onion,</hi> boy.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Fin.</speaker>
                     <p>What ſay you ſir.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Iuni.</speaker>
                     <p>Tread out boy.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Fin.</speaker>
                     <p>Take vp, you meane ſir.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Iun.</speaker>
                     <p>Tread out I ſay, ſo, I thanke you, is this the boy.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <pb facs="tcp:22306:33"/>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Pac.</speaker>
                     <p>Aue mounſieur.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Iuni.</speaker>
                     <p>Who gaue you that name.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Pac.</speaker>
                     <p>Giue me de name, vat name:</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Oni.</speaker>
                     <p>He thought your name had been, we yong gentle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men, you muſt do more then his legges can do for him, beare with him ſir.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Iuni.</speaker>
                     <p>Sirrah giue me inſtance of your carriage? youle ſerue my turne, will you?</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Pac.</speaker>
                     <p>What? turne vpon the toe.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Fin.</speaker>
                     <p>O ſignior no.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Iuni.</speaker>
                     <p>Page will you follow me, ile giue you good exhibition.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Pac.</speaker>
                     <p>By gar, ſhal not alone follow you, but ſhal leade you to.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Oni.</speaker>
                     <p>Plaguie boy, he ſooths his humour? theſe french vil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>laines ha pockie wits.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Iuni.</speaker>
                     <p>Here? diſarme me? take my ſemitary.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Valen.</speaker>
                     <p>O rare, this would be a rare man, and he had a little trauell, <hi>Balthaſar, Martino,</hi> put off your ſhooes, and bid him coble them.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Iuni.</speaker>
                     <p>Freinds, friends, but pardon me for fellows, no more in occupation, no more in corporation, tis ſo pardon me, the caſe is alterd, this is law, but ile ſtand to nothing.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Pac.</speaker>
                     <p>Fat ſo me tinke.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Iuni.</speaker>
                     <p>Well then God ſaue the dukes Maieſty, is this any harme now? ſpeake, is this any harme now.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Oni.</speaker>
                     <p>No nor good neither, Sbloud?</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Iuni.</speaker>
                     <p>Do you laugh at me? do you laugh at me? do you laugh at me?</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Valen.</speaker>
                     <p>I ſir, we do.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Iunip.</speaker>
                     <p>You do indeed?</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Valen.</speaker>
                     <p>I indeed ſir.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Iuni.</speaker>
                     <p>Tis ſufficient, Page carry my purſe, dog me?</p>
                  </sp>
                  <stage>Exit.</stage>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Oni.</speaker>
                     <p>Gentlemen leaue him not, you ſee in what caſe he is, he is not in aduerſity, his purſe is full of money, leaue him not?</p>
                  </sp>
                  <stage>Enter Angelo with Rachel.</stage>
                  <stage>Exeunt</stage>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Ang.</speaker>
                     <p>Nay gentle <hi>Rachel?</hi>
                     </p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Rach.</speaker>
                     <l>Away? forbeare? vngentle <hi>Angelo,</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>Touch not my body, with thoſe impious hands,</l>
                     <l>That like hot Irons ſeare my trembling heart,</l>
                     <l>And <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                           <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                        </gap> it hiſſe, at your diſloyalty.</l>
                     <stage>Enter Chamount Paulo Ferneze.</stage>
                     <l>Wa<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap> 
                        <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                           <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                        </gap> your drift? to vſe <hi>Fernezes</hi> name?</l>
                     <gap reason="missing" extent="1 page">
                        <desc>〈1 page missing〉</desc>
                     </gap>
                     <pb facs="tcp:22306:33"/>
                     <l>Was he your fitteſt ſtale, ô wild diſhonor!</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Pau.</speaker>
                     <p>Stay noble ſir<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
                     </p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Ange.</speaker>
                     <l>Sbloud how like a puppet do you talke now?</l>
                     <l>Diſhonor? what diſhonor? come, come, foole,</l>
                     <l>Nay then I ſee y'are peeuiſh, S'heart diſhonor?</l>
                     <l>To haue you a toprieſt and marry you,</l>
                     <l>And put you in an honorable ſtate.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Rach.</speaker>
                     <l>To marry me? ô heauen, can it be?</l>
                     <l>That men ſhould liue with ſuch vnfeeling ſoules,</l>
                     <l>Without or touch or conſcience of religion,</l>
                     <l>Or that their warping appetites ſhould ſpoile</l>
                     <l>Thoſe honor'd formes, that the true ſeale of friendſhip</l>
                     <l>Had ſet vpon their faces.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Ange.</speaker>
                     <p>Do you heare? what needs all this? ſay, will you haue me, or no?</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Rach.</speaker>
                     <p>Il'e haue you gone, and leaue me, if you would.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Ange.</speaker>
                     <l>Leaue you? I was accurſt to bring you hither,</l>
                     <l>And make ſo faire an offer to a foole.</l>
                     <l>A pox vpon you, why ſhould you be coy,</l>
                     <l>What good thing haue you in you to be proud of?</l>
                     <l>Are y'any other then a beggars daughter?</l>
                     <l>Becauſe you haue beauty. O Gods light a blaſt.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Pau.</speaker>
                     <p>I <hi>Angelo.</hi>
                     </p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Ange.</speaker>
                     <p>You ſcornefull baggage, I lou'd thee not ſo much, but now I hate thee.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Rach.</speaker>
                     <l>Vpon my knees, you heauenly powers, I thanke you,</l>
                     <l>That thus haue tam'd his wild affections.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Ange.</speaker>
                     <l>This will not do, I muſt to her againe,</l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Rachel,</hi> ô that thou ſawſt my heart, or didſt behold,</l>
                     <l>The place from whence that ſcalding figh euented.</l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Rachel,</hi> by Ieſu I loue thee as my ſoule, <hi>Rachel,</hi> ſweet <hi>Rachel.</hi>
                     </l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Rach.</speaker>
                     <p>What againe returnd vnto this violent paſſion.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Ange.</speaker>
                     <p>Do but heare me, by heauen I loue you <hi>Rachel.</hi>
                     </p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Rach.</speaker>
                     <p>Pray forbeare, ô that my Lord <hi>Ferneze</hi> were but here.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Ange.</speaker>
                     <p>Sbloud and he were, what would he do.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Pau.</speaker>
                     <p>This would he do baſe villaine.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Rach.</speaker>
                     <p>My deere Lord,</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Pau.</speaker>
                     <l>Thou monſter, euen the ſoule of trechery!</l>
                     <l>O what diſhonord title of reproch,</l>
                     <l>May my tongue ſpit in thy deſerued face?</l>
                     <pb facs="tcp:22306:34"/>
                     <l>Me thinkes my very preſence ſhould inuert,</l>
                     <l>The ſteeled organs of thoſe traytrous eyes,</l>
                     <l>To take into thy heart, and pierce it through:</l>
                     <l>Turn'ſt thou them on the ground? wretch, dig a graue,</l>
                     <l>With their ſharp points, to hide th'abhorred head;</l>
                     <l>Sweet loue, thy wrongs haue beene too violent</l>
                     <l>Since my departure from thee, I perceiue:</l>
                     <l>But now true comfort ſhall againe appeare,</l>
                     <l>And like an armed angell guard thee ſafe</l>
                     <l>From all th'aſſaults of couered villany.</l>
                     <l>Come Mounſieur, let's go, &amp; leaue this wretch to his deſpaire.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Ange.</speaker>
                     <p>My noble <hi>Ferneze.</hi>
                     </p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Pau.</speaker>
                     <l>What canſt thou ſpeake to me, and not thy tongue,</l>
                     <l>Forc't with the torment of thy guilty ſoule</l>
                     <l>Breake that infected circle of thy mouth,</l>
                     <l>Like the rude clapper of a crazed bell.</l>
                     <l>I, that in thy boſome lodg'd my ſoule,</l>
                     <l>With all her traine of ſecrets, thinking them</l>
                     <l>To be as ſafe, and richly entertained,</l>
                     <l>As in a Princes court, or tower of ſtrength,</l>
                     <l>And thou to proue a traitor to my truſt,</l>
                     <l>And baſely to expoſe it, ô this world!</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Ange.</speaker>
                     <p>My honorable Lord.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Pau.</speaker>
                     <l>The very owle, who<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> other birds do ſtare &amp; wonder at,</l>
                     <l>Shall hoot at thee, and ſnakes in euery buſh</l>
                     <l>Shall deafe thine eares with their—</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Cha.</speaker>
                     <p>Nay good my Lord, giue end vnto your paſſions.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Ange.</speaker>
                     <p>You ſhall ſee, I will redeeme your loſt opinion.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Rach.</speaker>
                     <p>My Lord beleeue him.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Cha.</speaker>
                     <l>Come, be ſarisfied, ſweet Lord you know our haſte,</l>
                     <l>Let vs to horſe, the time for my engaged returne is paſt;</l>
                     <l>Be friends againe, take him along with you.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Pau.</speaker>
                     <p>Come ſignior <hi>Angelo,</hi> hereafter proue more true.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <stage>Exeunt.</stage>
                  <stage>Enter Count Ferneze, Maximillian, Franceſco.</stage>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Count.</speaker>
                     <l>Tut <hi>Maximillian,</hi> for your honor'd ſelfe,</l>
                     <l>I am perſwaded, but no words ſhall turne</l>
                     <l>The edge of purpoſd vengeance on that wretch,</l>
                     <l>Come, bring him forth to execution.</l>
                     <pb facs="tcp:22306:34"/>
                     <stage>Enter Camillo bound, withſeruants</stage>
                     <l>Ile hang him for my ſonne, he ſhall not ſcape,</l>
                     <l>Had he an hundred liues: Tell me vile ſlaue,</l>
                     <l>Thinkeſt thou I loue my ſonne? is he my fleſh?</l>
                     <l>Is he my bloud, my life? and ſhall all theſe be torturd for thy</l>
                     <l>ſake, and not reueng'd? truſſe vp the villaine.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Max.</speaker>
                     <l>My Lord, there is no law to confirme this action.</l>
                     <l>Tis diſhonorable.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Count.</speaker>
                     <l>Diſhonorable? <hi>Max imillian?</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>It is diſhonorable in <hi>Chamount,</hi> the day of his prefixt returne is paſt, and he ſhall pay fort.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Cam.</speaker>
                     <l>My Lord, my Lord,</l>
                     <l>Vſe your extreameſt vengeance, ile be glad</l>
                     <l>To ſuffer ten times more, for ſuch a friend.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Count.</speaker>
                     <p>O reſolute and peremptory wretch!</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Fran.</speaker>
                     <p>My honored Lord, let vs intreat a word.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Count.</speaker>
                     <l>Ile heare no more, I ſay he ſhall not liue,</l>
                     <l>My ſelfe will do it. Stay, what forme is this</l>
                     <l>Stands betwixt him and me, and holds my hand.</l>
                     <l>What miracle is this? tis my owne fancy,</l>
                     <l>Carues this impreſſion in me, my ſoft nature,</l>
                     <l>That euer hath retaind ſuch fooliſh pitty,</l>
                     <l>Of the moſt abiect creatures miſery,</l>
                     <l>That it abhorres it, what a child am I</l>
                     <l>To haue a child? Ay me, my ſon, my ſon.</l>
                     <stage>Enter Chriſtophero.</stage>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Chriſ.</speaker>
                     <l>O my deere loue, what is become of thee?</l>
                     <l>What vniuſt abſence layeſt thou on my breſt,</l>
                     <l>Like waights of lead, when ſwords are at my backe,</l>
                     <l>That run me through with thy vnkind flight,</l>
                     <l>My gentle diſpoſition waxeth wild,</l>
                     <l>I ſhall run frantike, ô my loue, my loue.</l>
                     <stage>Enter Iaques.</stage>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Iaq.</speaker>
                     <l>My gold, my gold, my life, my ſoule, my heauen,</l>
                     <l>What is become of thee? ſee, ile impart</l>
                     <l>My miſerable loſſe to my good Lord,</l>
                     <l>Let me haue ſearch my Lord, my gold is gone.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Count.</speaker>
                     <l>My ſonne, <hi>Chriſtophero,</hi> thinkſt it poſſible,</l>
                     <l>I euer ſhall behold his face againe.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Chriſ.</speaker>
                     <l>O father wher's my loue, were you ſo careleſſe</l>
                     <l>To let an vnthrift ſteale away your child.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Iaq.</speaker>
                     <l>I know your Lordſhip may find out my gold,</l>
                     <pb facs="tcp:22306:35"/>
                     <l>For Gods ſake pitty me, iuſtice, ſweet Lord.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Count.</speaker>
                     <l>Now they haue yong <hi>Chamount? Chriſtophero?</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>Surely they neuer will reſtore my ſonne.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Chriſ.</speaker>
                     <p>Who would haue thought you could haue beene ſo careleſſe to looſe your onely daughter.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Iaq.</speaker>
                     <l>Who would thinke,</l>
                     <l>That looking to my gold with ſuch hares eyes,</l>
                     <l>That euer open, I euen when thy ſleepe,</l>
                     <l>I thus ſhould looſe my gold, my noble Lord, what ſaies your</l>
                     <l>Lordſhip?</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Count.</speaker>
                     <p>O my ſonne, my ſonne.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Chriſ.</speaker>
                     <p>My deereſt <hi>Rachel?</hi>
                     </p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Iaq.</speaker>
                     <p>My moſt hony gold.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Count.</speaker>
                     <p>Heare me <hi>Chriſtophero.</hi>
                     </p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Chriſ.</speaker>
                     <p>Nay heare me <hi>Iaques.</hi>
                     </p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Iaq.</speaker>
                     <p>Heare me moſt honor'd Lord.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Max.</speaker>
                     <p>What rule is here?</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Count.</speaker>
                     <p>O God that we ſhould let <hi>Chamount</hi> eſcape.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <stage>Enter Aurelia, Phoenixella.</stage>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Chriſ.</speaker>
                     <p>I and that <hi>Rachel,</hi> ſuch a vertuous mayd, ſhould be thus ſtolne away.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Iaq.</speaker>
                     <p>And that my gold, being ſo hid in earth, ſhould bee found out.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Max.</speaker>
                     <p>O confuſion of languages, &amp; yet no tower of <hi>Babel!</hi>
                     </p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Fran.</speaker>
                     <p>Ladies, beſhrew me, if you come not fit to make a ian<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gling conſort, will you laugh to ſee three conſtant paſſions.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Max.</speaker>
                     <p>Stand by, I will vrge them, ſweet <hi>Count,</hi> will you be comforted.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Count.</speaker>
                     <l>It cannot be but he is handled the moſt cruelly,</l>
                     <l>That euer any noble priſoner was.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Max.</speaker>
                     <p>Steward, go cheere my Lord:</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Chriſ.</speaker>
                     <p>Well, if <hi>Rachel</hi> tooke her flight willingly?</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Max.</speaker>
                     <p>Sirrah, ſpeake you touching your daughters flight?</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Iaq.</speaker>
                     <p>O that I could ſo ſoone forget to know the thiefe a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gaine, that had my gold, my gold.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Max.</speaker>
                     <p>Is not this pure<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
                     </p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Count.</speaker>
                     <l>O thou baſe wretch, ile drag thee through the ſtreets.</l>
                     <stage>Enter Balthaſar, and whiſpers with him.</stage>
                     <l>And as a monſter, make thee wondred at, how now.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Phoen.</speaker>
                     <l>Sweet Gentleman? how too vnworthily</l>
                     <l>Art thou thus tortured, braue <hi>Maximillian,</hi>
                     </l>
                     <pb facs="tcp:22306:35"/>
                     <l>Pitty the poore youth and appeaſe my father,</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Count.</speaker>
                     <l>How, my ſonne returnd? O <hi>Maximillian,</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Franciſco,</hi> daughters? bid him enter here.</l>
                     <stage>Enter Chamount, Ferneze, Rachel, Angelo.</stage>
                     <l>Doſt thou not mocke me? O my deere <hi>Paulo</hi> welcome.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Max.</speaker>
                     <p>My Lord <hi>Chamount?</hi>
                     </p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Cha.</speaker>
                     <p>My <hi>Gaſper.</hi>
                     </p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Chriſ.</speaker>
                     <p>
                        <hi>Rachel.</hi>
                     </p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Iaq.</speaker>
                     <p>My gold <hi>Rachel?</hi> my gold?</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Count</speaker>
                     <p>Some body bid the begger ceaſe his noiſe.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Chriſ.</speaker>
                     <l>O ſignior <hi>Angelo,</hi> would you deceiue</l>
                     <l>Your honeſt friend, that ſimply truſted you?</l>
                     <l>Well <hi>Rachel:</hi> I am glad tho' art here againe.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Ang.</speaker>
                     <p>I faith ſhe is not for you ſteward.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Iaq.</speaker>
                     <p>I beſeech you maddam vrge your father.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Phoe.</speaker>
                     <p>I will anon? good <hi>Iaques</hi> be content.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Aur.</speaker>
                     <l>Now God a mercy fortune, and ſweet <hi>Venus,</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>Let <hi>Cupid</hi> do his part, and all is well.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Phoe.</speaker>
                     <p>Me thinks my heart's in heauen with this comfort.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Cha.</speaker>
                     <l>Is this the true <hi>Italian</hi> courteſie.</l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Ferneze</hi> were you torturd thus in France? by my ſoules ſafety.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Count:</speaker>
                     <p>My moſt noble Lord? I do beſeech your Lordſhip.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Cha.</speaker>
                     <l>Honored <hi>Count,</hi> wrong not your age with flexure of a knee,</l>
                     <l>I do impute it to thoſe cares and griefes,</l>
                     <l>That did torment you in your abſent ſonne.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Count.</speaker>
                     <l>O worthy gentlemen, I am a ſhamd</l>
                     <l>That my extreame affection to my ſonne,</l>
                     <l>Should giue my honour ſo vncur'd a maine,</l>
                     <l>But my firſt ſonne, being in <hi>Vicenza</hi> loſt.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Cha.</speaker>
                     <l>How in <hi>Vicenza?</hi> loſt you a ſonne there?</l>
                     <l>About what time my Lord?</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Count.</speaker>
                     <p>O the ſame night, wherein your noble father tooke the towne.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Cha.</speaker>
                     <p>How long's that ſince my Lord? can you remember.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Count.</speaker>
                     <p>Tis now well nie vpon the twentith yeare.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Cha.</speaker>
                     <p>And how old was he then?</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Count.</speaker>
                     <p>I cannot tel, betweene the yeares of three and ſoure, I take it.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <pb facs="tcp:22306:36"/>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Cha.</speaker>
                     <l>Had he no ſpeciall note in his attire,</l>
                     <l>Or otherwiſe, that you can call to mind.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Count</speaker>
                     <l>I cannot well remember his attire,</l>
                     <l>But I haue often heard his mother ſay:</l>
                     <l>He had about his necke a tablet,</l>
                     <l>Giuen to him by the Emperour <hi>Sigiſmund.</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>His Godfather, with this inſcription,</l>
                     <l>Vnder the figure of a ſiluer Globe: <hi>En minimo, mundus.</hi>
                     </l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Cha.</speaker>
                     <p>How did you call your ſonne my Lord?</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Count</speaker>
                     <p>
                        <hi>Camillo</hi> Lord <hi>Chamount.</hi>
                     </p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Cha.</speaker>
                     <l>Then no more my <hi>Gaſper?</hi> but <hi>Camillo,</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>Take notice of your father, gentlemen:</l>
                     <l>Stand not amazd? here is a tablet,</l>
                     <l>With that inſcription? found about his necke</l>
                     <l>That night, and in <hi>Vicenza</hi> by my father,</l>
                     <l>(Who being ignorant, what name he had)</l>
                     <l>Chriſtned him <hi>Gaſper,</hi> nor did I reueale,</l>
                     <l>This ſecret till this hower to any man.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Count.</speaker>
                     <p>O happy reuelation? ô bleſt hower? ô my <hi>Camillo.</hi>
                     </p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Phoe.</speaker>
                     <p>O ſtrange my brother.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Fran.</speaker>
                     <p>
                        <hi>Maximilion?</hi> behold how the aboundance of his ioy Drownds him in teares of gladneſſe.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Count.</speaker>
                     <p>O my boy? forgiue thy fathers late auſterity:</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Max.</speaker>
                     <p>My Lord? I deliuered as much before, but your ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour would not be perſwaded, I will heareafter giue more ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeruance to my viſions? I drempt of this.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Iaq.</speaker>
                     <l>I can be ſtill no longer, my good Lord,</l>
                     <l>Do a poore man ſome grace mongſt all your ioyes.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Count.</speaker>
                     <p>Why whats the matter <hi>Iaques.</hi>
                     </p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Iaq.</speaker>
                     <l>I am robd, I am vndone my Lord, robd and vndone:</l>
                     <l>A heape of thirty thouſand golden crownes,</l>
                     <l>Stolne from me in one minnte, and I feare:</l>
                     <l>By her confedracy, that cals me father,</l>
                     <l>But ſhe's none of mine, therefore ſweet Lord:</l>
                     <l>Let her be tortured to confeſſe the truth.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Max.</speaker>
                     <p>More wonders yet.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Count.</speaker>
                     <p>How <hi>Iaques</hi> is not <hi>Rachel</hi> then thy daughter.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Iaq.</speaker>
                     <p>No, I diſclaime in her, I ſpit at her,</p>
                  </sp>
                  <gap reason="missing" extent="1 page">
                     <desc>〈1 page missing〉</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <pb facs="tcp:22306:36"/>
               </div>
            </div>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
