<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>The tragedy of Nero, newly written</title>
            <title>Nero.</title>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1624</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 151 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 34 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2012-10">2012-10 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A08065</idno>
            <idno type="STC">STC 18430</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC S113150</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99848389</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99848389</idno>
            <idno type="VID">13479</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A08065)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 13479)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 967:13)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>The tragedy of Nero, newly written</title>
                  <title>Nero.</title>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[72] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>By Augustine Mathewes, and Iohn Norton, for Thomas Iones, and are to bee sold at the blacke Rauen in the Strand,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>Imprinted at London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1624.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>In verse.</note>
                  <note>Signatures: A-I⁴.</note>
                  <note>The first leaf and the last leaf are blank.</note>
                  <note>Running title reads: The tragedie of Nero.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in Yale University. Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Nero, --  Emperor of Rome, 37-68 --  Drama --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2011-11</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-11</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-01</date>
            <label>Jayanthi Reddy</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-01</date>
            <label>Jayanthi Reddy</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-05</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:13479:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:13479:1"/>
            <p>THE TRAGEDY OF NERO, <hi>Newly Written.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Imprinted at <hi>London</hi> by <hi>Auguſtine Mathewes,</hi> and <hi>Iohn Norton,</hi> for <hi>Thomas Iones,</hi> and are to bee ſold at the blacke Rauen in the Strand, 1624.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="play">
            <pb facs="tcp:13479:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:13479:2"/>
            <head>THE TRAGEDIE OF <hi>NERO.</hi>
            </head>
            <div n="1" type="act">
               <head>Astus Primus.</head>
               <stage>Enter <hi>Petronius, Arbyter, Antonius, Honoratus.</hi>
               </stage>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Petronius.</speaker>
                  <l>
                     <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>Vſh, take the wench</l>
                  <l>I ſhowed thee now, or elſe ſome other ſeeke;</l>
                  <l>What? can your choler no way be allayed?</l>
                  <l>But with Imperiall tytles?</l>
                  <l>Will you more tytles vnto <hi>Caeſar</hi> giue?</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Anto.</speaker>
                  <l>Great are thy fortunes <hi>Nero,</hi> great thy power</l>
                  <l>Thy Empyre lymited with natures bounds;</l>
                  <l>Vpon thy ground, the Sunne doth ſet, and ryſe;</l>
                  <l>The day, and night are thine:</l>
                  <l>Nor can the Planets, wander where they will:</l>
                  <l>See that proud Earth, that feares not <hi>Caeſars</hi> name,</l>
                  <l>Yet nothing of all this, I enuy thee;</l>
                  <l>But her, to whom the world, vnforſt, obayes,</l>
                  <l>Whoſe eyes more worth then all it lookes vpon:</l>
                  <l>In whom, all beautyes Nature hath encloſ'd,</l>
                  <l>That through the wide Earth, or Heauen are diſpoſ'd</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Petro.</speaker>
                  <l>Indeed the ſteales, and robs each part o'th world,</l>
                  <l>With borrowed beauties to enflame thine eye;</l>
                  <l>The Sea, to fetch her Pearle, is diu'd into:</l>
                  <l>The Diomond rocks are cut, to make her ſhine:</l>
                  <pb facs="tcp:13479:3"/>
                  <l>To plume her pryde, the Birds doe naked ſing</l>
                  <l>When my Enanthe, in a homely gowne.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Ant.</speaker>
                  <l>Homely I faith.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Petro.</speaker>
                  <l>I, homely in her gowne,</l>
                  <l>But looke vpon her face, and that's ſet out</l>
                  <l>With no ſmall grace, no vayled ſhadowes helpe;</l>
                  <l>Foole; that hadſt rather with falſe lights, and darke</l>
                  <l>Beguiled be, then ſee the ware thou buy eſt.</l>
               </sp>
               <stage>
                  <hi>Poppea</hi> royally attended, and paſſe ouer the Stage, in State.</stage>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Ant.</speaker>
                  <l>Great Queene, whom nature made to be her glory:</l>
                  <l>Fortune got eies, and came to be thy ſeruant,</l>
                  <l>Honour is proud to be thy tytle; Though</l>
                  <l>Thy beauties doe draw vp my ſoule; yet ſtill,</l>
                  <l>So bright, ſo glorious is thy Maieſtie,</l>
                  <l>That it beates downe againe my clyming thoughts.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Petro.</speaker>
                  <l>Why true;</l>
                  <l>And other of thy blindneſſes thou ſeeſt,</l>
                  <l>Such one to loue thou dar'ſt not ſpeake vnto.</l>
                  <l>Giue me a wench, that will be eaſily had,</l>
                  <l>Not woed with coſt; And, being ſent for, comes,</l>
                  <l>And when I haue her foulded in mine armes,</l>
                  <l>Then <hi>Cleopatra</hi> ſh<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>, or <hi>Lucres</hi> is:</l>
                  <l>Ile giue her any tytle.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Anto.</speaker>
                  <l>Yet not ſo much her greatneſſe, and eſtate</l>
                  <l>My hopes disharten, as her chaſtitie.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Pet.</speaker>
                  <l>Chaſtitie, foole a word not knowne in Courts:</l>
                  <l>Well may it lodge in meane, and countrey homes,</l>
                  <l>Where pouertie, and labour keepes them downe,</l>
                  <l>Short ſleepes, and hands made hard with <hi>Thuſcan</hi> Woll.</l>
                  <l>But neuer comes to great mens Pallaces,</l>
                  <l>Where eaſe, and riches, ſtirring thoughts beget,</l>
                  <l>Prouoking meates, and ſurfet wines Inflame:</l>
                  <l>Where all there ſetting forth's but to be wooed,</l>
                  <l>And wooed they would not be, but to be wonne.</l>
                  <l>Will one man ſerue <hi>Poppea?</hi> Nay, thou ſhalt</l>
                  <l>Make her, as ſoone, contented with an eye.</l>
               </sp>
               <stage>
                  <pb facs="tcp:13479:3"/>
                  <hi>Nimphidius</hi> to them.</stage>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Nim.</speaker>
                  <l>Whil'ſt <hi>Nero,</hi> in the ſtreetes, his Pageants ſhewes,</l>
                  <l>I, to his faire wiues chamber, ſent for am.</l>
                  <l>You gracious Starres, that ſmiled in my birth,</l>
                  <l>And thou bright ſtarre more powerfull then them all,</l>
                  <l>Whoſe fauouring ſmyles haue made me what I am</l>
                  <l>Thou ſhalt my God, my Fate, and fortune bee.
<stage>Ex. Nim.</stage>
                  </l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Ant.</speaker>
                  <l>How ſauſely you fellow.</l>
                  <l>Enters the Empreſſe chamber.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Pet.</speaker>
                  <l>I, and her too? <hi>Antonius</hi> knoweſt thou him?</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Ant.</speaker>
                  <l>What? knowes the onely fauorite of the Court?</l>
                  <l>Indeed, not many dayes agoe thou mighteſt,</l>
                  <l>Haue not vnlawfully askt that queſtion.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Pet.</speaker>
                  <l>Why? Is he rais'd?</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Ant.</speaker>
                  <l>That haue I ſought in him,</l>
                  <l>But neuer peece of good deſert could find:</l>
                  <l>Hee is <hi>Nimphidias</hi> ſonne, the free'd woman,</l>
                  <l>Which baſeneſſe to ſhake off, he nothing hath</l>
                  <l>But his owne pride</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Pet.</speaker>
                  <l>You Remember, when <hi>Gallus, Celſus,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>And others too, though now forgotten were</l>
                  <l>Great in <hi>Poppeas</hi> eyes.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Ant.</speaker>
                  <l>I doe, and did enterpret it in them</l>
                  <l>An honorable fauor, ſhe bare vertue,</l>
                  <l>Or parts like vertue.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Pet.</speaker>
                  <l>The cauſe is one of theirs, and this mans grace,</l>
                  <l>I once was great in wauering ſmiles of Court,</l>
                  <l>I fell becauſe I knew: Sence haue I giuen</l>
                  <l>My time to my owne pleaſures, and would now</l>
                  <l>Aduiſe thee too, to meane, and ſafe delights:</l>
                  <l>The thigh's as ſoft the ſheepes backe couereth</l>
                  <l>As that which crimſon, and with Gold adorn'd:</l>
                  <l>Yet cauſe I ſee, that thy reſtraind deſires.</l>
                  <l>Cannot their owne way chooſe, come thou with me</l>
                  <l>Perhapps Ile ſhew thee meanes of remedie.</l>
               </sp>
               <stage>Exeunt.</stage>
               <stage>
                  <pb facs="tcp:13479:4"/>Two <hi>Romans</hi> at ſeuerall dores.</stage>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>1 <hi>Rom.</hi>
                  </speaker>
                  <l>Whither ſo faſt man? whither ſo faſt?</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>2 <hi>Rom.</hi>
                  </speaker>
                  <l>Whither? but where your eares doe lead you;</l>
                  <l>To <hi>Neres</hi> Triumphs, and the ſhouts you heare.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>1 <hi>Ro.</hi>
                  </speaker>
                  <l>Why? comes he crown'd with <hi>Parthian</hi> ouerthrow.</l>
                  <l>And brings he <hi>
                        <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>
                        <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>legaeſus</hi> with him, chai'nd?</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>2 <hi>Ro.</hi>
                  </speaker>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Parthian</hi> ouerthrowne? why, he comes crownd</l>
                  <l>For victories which neuer Roman wonne;</l>
                  <l>For hauing Greece in her owne arts ouerthrowne;</l>
                  <l>In Singing, Dauncing, Horſe-raſe, Stage-playing.</l>
                  <l>Neuer, O Rome had neuer ſuch a Prince.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>1 <hi>Rom.</hi>
                  </speaker>
                  <l>Yet, I haue heard: our anceſtors were crown'd</l>
                  <l>For other Victories.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>2 <hi>Rom.</hi>
                  </speaker>
                  <l>None of our anceſtors, were ere like him.
<stage>within Nero, Apollo, Nero, Hercules.</stage>
                  </l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>1 <hi>Rom.</hi>
                  </speaker>
                  <l>Harke, how th'applauding ſhouts doe cleare th'ayre</l>
                  <l>This Idle talke will make me looſe the ſight.</l>
               </sp>
               <stage>Two <hi>Romans</hi> more to them.</stage>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>3 <hi>Rom.</hi>
                  </speaker>
                  <l>Whither goe you? alls done i'th Capytall,</l>
                  <l>And <hi>Nero,</hi> hauing there his tables hung,</l>
                  <l>And Garlands vp: is to the Pallace gone.</l>
                  <l>T'was beyond wonder; I ſhall neuer ſee,</l>
                  <l>Nay, I neuer looke, to ſee the like againe</l>
                  <l>Eighteene hundred and eight Crownes</l>
                  <l>For ſeuerall victories and the place ſet downe</l>
                  <l>Where, and in what, and whom he ouercame.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>4 <hi>Rom.</hi>
                  </speaker>
                  <l>That was ſet downe it'h tables, that were borne</l>
                  <l>Vpon the Souldiers ſpeares.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>1 <hi>Rom.</hi>
                  </speaker>
                  <l>O made, and ſometimes vſe to other ends.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>2 <hi>Rom.</hi>
                  </speaker>
                  <l>But did he winne them all with ſinging.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>3 <hi>Rom.</hi>
                  </speaker>
                  <l>Faith all with ſinging, and with ſtage-playing.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>1 <hi>Rom.</hi>
                  </speaker>
                  <l>So many Crownes got with a ſong.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>4 <hi>Rom.</hi>
                  </speaker>
                  <l>But, did you marke the Greeke Muſitians</l>
                  <l>Behinde his Chariot, hanging downe their heads?</l>
                  <pb facs="tcp:13479:4"/>
                  <l>Sham'd, and orecome, in their profeſsions,</l>
                  <l>O <hi>Rome</hi> was neuer honour'd ſo, before.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>3. <hi>Rom.</hi>
                  </speaker>
                  <l>But, what was he that rode'ith' Chariot with him?</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>4. <hi>Rom.</hi>
                  </speaker>
                  <l>That was <hi>Diodorus</hi> the Mynſtrill, that he fauours.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>3. <hi>Rom.</hi>
                  </speaker>
                  <l>Was there euer ſuch a Prince.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>2. <hi>Rom.</hi>
                  </speaker>
                  <l>O <hi>Nero Auguſtus,</hi> the true <hi>Auguſtus.</hi>
                  </l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>3. <hi>Rom.</hi>
                  </speaker>
                  <l>Nay, had you ſeene him as he rode along,</l>
                  <l>With an <hi>Olympicke</hi> Crowne vpon his head,</l>
                  <l>And with a <hi>Pithian</hi> on his arme: you would haue thought,</l>
                  <l>Looking on one he had <hi>Apollo</hi> ſeem'd,</l>
                  <l>On th'other <hi>Hercules.</hi>
                  </l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>2. <hi>Rom.</hi>
                  </speaker>
                  <l>I haue heard my father oft repeat the Triumphs,</l>
                  <l>Which in <hi>Auguſtus Caeſars</hi> tymes were ſhowne,</l>
                  <l>Vpon his Victorie ore the <hi>Jllirians;</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>But it ſeemes it was not li<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>e to this.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>3, &amp; 4. <hi>Rom.</hi>
                  </speaker>
                  <l>Puſh, it could not be like this.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>2, 3, &amp; 4.</speaker>
                  <l>O <hi>Nero, Apollo, Nero, Hercules.</hi>
                  </l>
               </sp>
               <stage>
                  <hi>Exeunt.</hi> 2, 3, &amp; 4. <hi>Rom.</hi>
               </stage>
               <stage>Manet Primus.</stage>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>1. <hi>Rom.</hi>
                  </speaker>
                  <l>Whether <hi>Auguſtus</hi> Tryumph greater was</l>
                  <l>I cannot tell; his Tryumphs cauſe I know</l>
                  <l>Was greater farre, and farre more Honourable.</l>
                  <l>What are wee People? or our flattering voyces,</l>
                  <l>That alwayes ſhame and fooliſh things applaud</l>
                  <l>Hauing no ſparke of Soule; All Eares, and eyes,</l>
                  <l>Pleas'd with vaine ſhowes, deluded by our ſenſes</l>
                  <l>Still enemies to wiſedome, and to goodneſſe.
<stage>exit.</stage>
                  </l>
               </sp>
               <stage>
                  <hi>Enter Nero, Poppea, Nimphidius, Tigellinus, Epaphro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ditus, Neophitus,</hi> and others.</stage>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Nero,</speaker>
                  <l>Now fayre <hi>Poppea,</hi> ſee thy <hi>Nero</hi> ſhine</l>
                  <l>In bright <hi>Achaias</hi> ſpoyles, and Rome in him.</l>
                  <l>The <hi>Capitall</hi> hath other Trophies ſeene</l>
                  <l>Then it was wont; Not ſpoyles with blood bedew'd,</l>
                  <l>Or the vnhappie obſequies of Death:</l>
                  <l>But ſuch, as <hi>Caeſars</hi> cunning, not his force,</l>
                  <l>Hath wrung from <hi>Greece;</hi> too bragging of her art.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Tigell.</speaker>
                  <l>And in this ſtrife, the glories all your owne,</l>
                  <l>Your Tribunes cannot ſhare this prayſe with you;</l>
                  <pb facs="tcp:13479:5"/>
                  <l>Here, your <hi>Centurions</hi> hath no part at all,</l>
                  <l>Bootleſſe your Armies, and your Eagles were;</l>
                  <l>No Nauies helpt, to bring away this conqueſt.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Nim.</speaker>
                  <l>Euen Fortunes ſelfe, Fortune the Queene of kingdomes</l>
                  <l>(That Warrs grim valour graceth with her deeds,)</l>
                  <l>Will claime no portion in this Victorie.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Nero.</speaker>
                  <l>Not <hi>Bacchus,</hi> drawne from Niſa downe with Tigers,</l>
                  <l>Curbing with viny raines, their wilfull heads,</l>
                  <l>Whil'ſt ſome doe gape vpon his Iuy Thirſe,</l>
                  <l>Some, on the dangling grapes, that Crowne his head,</l>
                  <l>All praiſe his beautie, and continuing youth:</l>
                  <l>So ſtrooke, amaſed India, with wonder.</l>
                  <l>As <hi>Neroes</hi> glories did the Greekiſh townes</l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Elis,</hi> and <hi>Piſa,</hi> and the rich <hi>Mic<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                           <desc>••</desc>
                        </gap>na,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Iunoman Argos,</hi> and yet <hi>Corinth</hi> proud</l>
                  <l>Of her two Seas; all which ore-come, did yeeld</l>
                  <l>To me their praiſe, and priſes of their games.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Poppea,</speaker>
                  <l>Yet, in your Greekiſh iourney, we do heare,</l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Sparta,</hi> and <hi>Athens,</hi> the two eyes of <hi>Greece,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>Neither beheld your perſon, nor your ſkill;</l>
                  <l>Whether, becauſe they did afford no games,</l>
                  <l>Or for their to much grauitie,</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Nero:</speaker>
                  <l>Why? what</l>
                  <l>Should I haue ſeene in them? but in the one,</l>
                  <l>Hunger, blacke-pottage, and men hot to di<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>,</l>
                  <l>Thereby to rid themſelues of miſerie:</l>
                  <l>And what in th'other? but ſhort Capes, long Beardes,</l>
                  <l>Much wrangling in things needleſſe to be knowne,</l>
                  <l>Wiſedome in words, and onely auſtere faces,</l>
                  <l>I will not be <hi>A<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>ecelans,</hi> nor <hi>Solon.</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Nero</hi> was there, where he might honour winn,</l>
                  <l>And honour hath he wonn, and brought from <hi>Greece,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>Thoſe ſpoyles which neuer Roman could obtaine,</l>
                  <l>Spoyles won by witt and <hi>Trophtis</hi> of his skill.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Nim.</speaker>
                  <l>What a thing he makes it to be a Minſtrill.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Pop.</speaker>
                  <l>I prayſe your witt, my Lord, that chooſe ſuch ſafe.</l>
                  <l>Honors, ſafe ſpoyles, wonn without duſt, on blood.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Nero:</speaker>
                  <l>What, mooke ye me <hi>Poppea?</hi>
                  </l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <pb facs="tcp:13479:5"/>
                  <speaker>Poppea:</speaker>
                  <l>Nay, in good Faith my Lord, I ſpeake in earneſt,</l>
                  <l>I hate that headie, and aduenturous crew,</l>
                  <l>That goe to looſe their owne, to purchaſe, but</l>
                  <l>The breath of others, and the common voyce,</l>
                  <l>Them that will looſe there hearing for a ſound;</l>
                  <l>That by death onely, ſeeke to get a liuing,</l>
                  <l>Make ſkarrs there beautie, and count loſſe of Limme<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>
                  </l>
                  <l>The commendation of a proper man,</l>
                  <l>And ſo, goe halting to immortalitie:</l>
                  <l>Such fooles I loue worſe then they doe their liues.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Nero:</speaker>
                  <l>But now <hi>Poppea,</hi> hauing laid apart</l>
                  <l>Our boaſtfull ſpoyles, and ornaments of Tryumph.</l>
                  <l>Come we, like <hi>Ione</hi> from <hi>Phlegra</hi> —</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Poppea:</speaker>
                  <l>O Giantlike compariſon.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Nero:</speaker>
                  <l>When, after all his Fiers, and wandring darts,</l>
                  <l>He comes to bath himſelfe, in <hi>Iunos</hi> Eyes:</l>
                  <l>But thou, (then wrangling <hi>Iuno,</hi>) farre more fayre,</l>
                  <l>Stayning the euening beauty of the Skie,</l>
                  <l>Or the dayes brightneſſe; ſhall make glad thy <hi>Caeſar,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>Shalt make him proud ſuch beauties to Inioy:
<stage>Exunt.</stage>
                  </l>
               </sp>
               <stage>Manet, Nimphidius ſolus.</stage>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Nimph:</speaker>
                  <l>Such beauties to inioy, were happineſſe,</l>
                  <l>And a reward ſufficient in it ſelfe,</l>
                  <l>Although no other end, or hopes were aim'd at:</l>
                  <l>But I haue other; Tis not <hi>Poppeas</hi> armes,</l>
                  <l>Nor the ſhort pleaſures of a wanton bed,</l>
                  <l>That can extinguiſh mine aſpiring thirſt</l>
                  <l>To <hi>Neroes</hi> Crowne; By her loue I muſt climbe,</l>
                  <l>Her bed is but a ſtep vnto his Throne.</l>
                  <l>Already, wiſe men laugh at him, and hate him;</l>
                  <l>The people, though his Mynſtrelſie doth pleaſe them<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
                  </l>
                  <l>They feare his Cruelty, hate his exactions,</l>
                  <l>Which, his need, ſtill, muſt force him to encreaſe.</l>
                  <l>The multitude, which cannot one thing long</l>
                  <l>Like, or diſlike, being cloy'd with vanitie,</l>
                  <l>Will hate their owne delights, though Wiſedome doe not,</l>
                  <l>Euen wearineſſe, at length, will giue them eyes,</l>
                  <pb facs="tcp:13479:6"/>
                  <l>Thus, I by <hi>Neroes,</hi> and <hi>Poppeas</hi> fauour,</l>
                  <l>Raiſ'd to the enuious height of ſecond place,</l>
                  <l>May gaine the firſt: Hate muſt ſtrike <hi>Nero</hi> downe.</l>
                  <l>Loue make <hi>Nimphidius</hi> way vnto a Crowne.</l>
               </sp>
               <stage>exit.</stage>
               <stage>
                  <hi>Enter Seneca, Sceninus, Lucan,</hi> and <hi>Flauius.</hi>
               </stage>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Sceu.</speaker>
                  <l>His firſt beginning was his Fathers death,</l>
                  <l>His brothers poyſoning, and wiues bloudy end</l>
                  <l>Came next, his mothers murther clos'd vp all:</l>
                  <l>Yet hitherto he was but wicked, when</l>
                  <l>The guilt of greater euills, tooke away the ſhame</l>
                  <l>Of leſſer, and did headlong thruſt him forth,</l>
                  <l>To be the ſcorne, and laughter to the world;</l>
                  <l>Then firſt, an Emperour came vpon the Stage,</l>
                  <l>And ſung to pleaſe Carmen, and Candle-ſellers,</l>
                  <l>And learnt to act, to daunce, to be a Fencer,</l>
                  <l>And in deſpight o'the Maieſtie of Princes,</l>
                  <l>He fell to wraſtling, and was ſoyl'd with duſt,</l>
                  <l>And tumbled on the Earth with ſeruile hands.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Seneca</speaker>
                  <l>He ſometimes trayned was in better ſtudies,</l>
                  <l>And had a Child-hood promis'd other hopes;</l>
                  <l>High fortunes, like ſtronge wines, do trie their veſſels.</l>
                  <l>Was not the Race, and Theater bigge enough,</l>
                  <l>To haue inclos'd thy follies heere at home?</l>
                  <l>O could not <hi>Rome,</hi> and <hi>Italie</hi> containe</l>
                  <l>Thy ſhame? but thou muſt croſſe the Seas to ſhew it?</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Scen.</speaker>
                  <l>And make them that had wont to ſee our Conſuls,</l>
                  <l>With conquering Eagles wauing in the field;</l>
                  <l>Inſtead of that; behold an Emperor dauncing,</l>
                  <l>Playing oth' ſtage, and what elſe, but to name</l>
                  <l>Were infamie.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Lucan.</speaker>
                  <l>
                     <hi>O Mummius, O Flaminius;</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>You, whom your Vertues haue not made more famous</l>
                  <l>Then <hi>Neros</hi> vices; You went ore to Greece,</l>
                  <l>But t'other warres, and brought home other conqueſts.</l>
                  <l>You Corinth, and <hi>Mic<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="3 letters">
                           <desc>•••</desc>
                        </gap>
                     </hi> ouerthrew;</l>
                  <l>And <hi>Perſeus</hi> ſelfe, the Great <hi>Achilles</hi> race</l>
                  <l>Ore came; hauing <hi>Mineruas</hi> ſtayned Temples.</l>
                  <pb facs="tcp:13479:6"/>
                  <l>And your ſlayne Anceſtors of Troy reueng'd</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Senec.</speaker>
                  <l>They ſtroue with Kings; and kinglike aduerſaries.</l>
                  <l>Were euen in their Enemies made happie;</l>
                  <l>The Macedonian Courage tryed of old,</l>
                  <l>And the new greatneſſe of the <hi>Syrian</hi> power:</l>
                  <l>But he for <hi>Phillip,</hi> and <hi>Antiochus,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>Hath found more eaſie enemies to deale with,</l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Turpuus, Pammenes,</hi> and a rout of Fidlers.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Sceuin:</speaker>
                  <l>Why all the begging Mynſtrills by the way,</l>
                  <l>He tooke along with him, and forc'd to ſtriue</l>
                  <l>That he might ouercome, Imagining</l>
                  <l>Himſelfe Imortall, by ſuch victories.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Flaui:</speaker>
                  <l>The Men he caried ouer were enough</l>
                  <l>T'haue put the <hi>Parthian</hi> to his ſecond flight</l>
                  <l>Or the proud Indyan, taught the Roman Yoke.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Sceuin:</speaker>
                  <l>But they were <hi>Neroes</hi> men, like <hi>Nero</hi> arm'd</l>
                  <l>With Luts, and Harpes, and Pipes, and Fiddle-caſes:</l>
                  <l>Souldyers to th ſhadow traynd, and not the field.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Flaui:</speaker>
                  <l>Therefore they brought ſpoyles of ſuch Soldyers worthy.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Luca:</speaker>
                  <l>But to throw downe the walls, and Gates of Rome,</l>
                  <l>To make an entrance for an Hobby-horſe;</l>
                  <l>To vaunt toth' people his rediculous ſpoyles;</l>
                  <l>To come with Lawrell, and with Olyues crown'd,</l>
                  <l>For hauing beene the worſt of all the Singers,</l>
                  <l>Is beyond Patience;</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Sceuin:</speaker>
                  <l>I and anger too,</l>
                  <l>Had you but ſeene him in his Chariot ryde.</l>
                  <l>That Chariot in which, <hi>Auguſtus</hi> late</l>
                  <l>His Triumphs ore' ſo many Nations ſhew'd,</l>
                  <l>And with him in the ſame a Minſtrell plac'd,</l>
                  <l>The whil'ſt the people, running by his ſide,</l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Hayle thou Olimpick Conqueror</hi> did crye,</l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>O haile thou Pithian,</hi> and did fill the skie</l>
                  <l>With ſhame, and voyces, Heauen would not haue heard.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Senec:</speaker>
                  <l>I ſaw't, but turn'd away my Eyes, and Eares,</l>
                  <l>Angry, they ſhould be priuie to ſuch ſights.</l>
                  <l>Why doe I ſtand relating of the ſtorie,</l>
                  <l>Which in the doing had enough to grieue me?</l>
                  <pb facs="tcp:13479:7"/>
                  <l>Tell on, and end the tale, you, whom it pleaſeth;</l>
                  <l>Mee mine owne ſorrow ſtops from further ſpeaking.</l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Nero,</hi> my loue doth make thy fault, and my griefe greater.
<stage>ex. Se.</stage>
                  </l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Sceuin:</speaker>
                  <l>I doe commend in <hi>Seneca</hi> this paſsion;</l>
                  <l>And yet me thinkes our Countries miſerie,</l>
                  <l>Doth at our hands craue ſomewhat more then teares.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Luca:</speaker>
                  <l>Pittie, though't doth a kind affection ſhow,</l>
                  <l>(If it end there) our weakeneſſe makes vs know.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Flaui:</speaker>
                  <l>Let children weepe, and men ſeeke remedie,</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Sceui:</speaker>
                  <l>Stoutly, and like a Souldier, <hi>Flauius:</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>Yet, to ſeeke remedie to a Princes ill,</l>
                  <l>Seldome, but it doth the Phiſitian kill.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Flaui:</speaker>
                  <l>And if it doe <hi>Sceuinus,</hi> it ſhall take</l>
                  <l>But a deuoted ſoule from <hi>Flauius,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>Which, to my Countrey, and the Gods of Rome,</l>
                  <l>Alreadie ſacred is, and giuen away,</l>
                  <l>Death is no ſtraunger vnto me, I haue</l>
                  <l>The doubtfull hazard in twelue Battailes throwne,</l>
                  <l>My chaunce was life.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Luca:</speaker>
                  <l>Why doe we goe to fight in Brittanie?</l>
                  <l>And end our liues vnder an other Sunne?</l>
                  <l>Seeke cauſeleſſe dangers out? The German might</l>
                  <l>Enioy his Woods, and his owne All is drinke,</l>
                  <l>Yet we walke ſafely in the ſtreets of Rome:</l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Bodinca</hi> hinders not, but we might liue,</l>
                  <l>Whom, we doe hurt; Them we call enemies,</l>
                  <l>And thoſe our Lords that ſpoyle, and murder vs.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Sceuin:</speaker>
                  <l>Nothing is hard to them that dare to die.</l>
                  <l>This Noble reſolution in you Lords,</l>
                  <l>Heartens me to diſcloſe ſome thoughts that I —</l>
                  <l>The matter is of waight and dangerous.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Luca:</speaker>
                  <l>I ſee you feare vs <hi>Seruinus.</hi>
                  </l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Sceuin</speaker>
                  <l>Nay, Nay, although the thing be full of feare.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Flaui:</speaker>
                  <l>Tell it to faithfull Eares, what eare it bee.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Sceuin:</speaker>
                  <l>Faith let it goe, it will but trouble vs,</l>
                  <l>Bee hurtfull to the ſpeaker, and the hearer.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Luca:</speaker>
                  <l>If our long friendſhip, or the opinion.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Sceuin:</speaker>
                  <l>Why ſhould I feare to tell them?</l>
                  <pb facs="tcp:13479:7"/>
                  <l>Why is he not a Parricide, a Player?</l>
                  <l>Nay <hi>Lucan</hi> is he not thine Enemie?</l>
                  <l>Hate not the Heauens, as well, as men, to ſee</l>
                  <l>That condem'd head: and you O righteous Gods</l>
                  <l>Whither ſo ere you now are fled, and will</l>
                  <l>No more looke downe vpon th'oppreſſed Earth;</l>
                  <l>O ſeuere anger of the higheſt Gods,</l>
                  <l>And thou ſterne power, to whom the Greekes aſsigne</l>
                  <l>Scourges, and ſwords to puniſh proud mens wrongs,</l>
                  <l>If you be more then names found out to awe vs,</l>
                  <l>And that we doe not vainely build you alters,</l>
                  <l>Aid that iuſt arme, that's bent to execute</l>
                  <l>What you ſhould doe.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Luca.</speaker>
                  <l>Stay, y'are caried too much away <hi>Sceuinus.</hi>
                  </l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Sceui.</speaker>
                  <l>Why, what will you ſay for him? hath h<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> not</l>
                  <l>Sought to ſuppreſſe your Poem, to bereaue</l>
                  <l>That honour euery tongue in duty paid it.</l>
                  <l>Nay, what can you ſay for him, hath he not</l>
                  <l>Broa'cht his owne wiues (a chaſt wiues) breaſt, and to<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ne</l>
                  <l>With Scithian hands his Mothers bowels vp,</l>
                  <l>The Inhoſpitable <hi>Caucaſus</hi> is milde:</l>
                  <l>The More, that, in the boyling deſert, ſeekes</l>
                  <l>With blood of ſtranger to imbrue his iawes</l>
                  <l>Vpbraides the Roman, now with barbarouſneſſe</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Luca:</speaker>
                  <l>You are to earneſt,</l>
                  <l>I neither can, nor will I ſpeake for him:</l>
                  <l>And, though he ſought my learned paynes to wrong,</l>
                  <l>I hate him not for that, My verſe ſhall liue</l>
                  <l>When <hi>Neroes</hi> body ſhall be throwne in Tiber,</l>
                  <l>And times to come ſhall bleſſe thoſe wicked armes;</l>
                  <l>I loue th'vnnaturall wounds, from whence did flow<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
                  </l>
                  <l>Another Ciria, a new Hellicon.</l>
                  <l>I hate him that he is Romes enemie,</l>
                  <l>An enemie to Vertue; fits on high</l>
                  <l>To ſhame the ſeate; And in that hate, my life,</l>
                  <l>And blood, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>le mingle on the earth with yours.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Flaui:</speaker>
                  <l>My de<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ds <hi>Sceuinus</hi> ſhall ſpeake my conſent.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Sceui.</speaker>
                  <l>Tis anſwerd, as I lookt for, noble Poet,</l>
                  <pb facs="tcp:13479:8"/>
                  <l>Worthy the double Lawrell; <hi>Flauius,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>Good lucke I ſee, doth vertuous meanings ayde,</l>
                  <l>And therefore haue the Heauens forborne their duties,</l>
                  <l>To grace our ſwords with glorious blood of Tyrants.</l>
               </sp>
               <stage>exeunt.</stage>
               <trailer>Finis Actus Primi.</trailer>
            </div>
            <div n="2" type="act">
               <head>Actus Secundus.</head>
               <stage>Enter Petronius Solus.</stage>
               <sp>
                  <l>HEre waites <hi>Poppea</hi> her <hi>Nimphidius</hi> comming,</l>
                  <l>And hath this garden, and theſe walkes choſe out,</l>
                  <l>To bleſſe her with more pleaſures then their owne:</l>
                  <l>Not onely Arras hangings, and ſilke beeds</l>
                  <l>Are guilty of the faults we blame them for:</l>
                  <l>Somewhat theſe Arbors, and you trees doe know,</l>
                  <l>Whil'ſt you kind ſhades, you to theſe night ſports ſhow.</l>
                  <l>Night ſports? Faith, they are done in open day,</l>
                  <l>And the Sunne ſee'th, and enuieth their play.</l>
                  <l>Hither haue I Loue-ſicke <hi>Antonius</hi> brought,</l>
                  <l>And thruſt him on occaſion ſo long ſought:</l>
                  <l>Shewed him the Empreſſe in a thicket by,</l>
                  <l>Her loues approach waiting with greedie Eye;</l>
                  <l>And told him, if he euer meant to proue,</l>
                  <l>The doubtfull iſſue of his hopeleſſe Loue;</l>
                  <l>This is the place, and time wherein to try it,</l>
                  <l>Women will heere the ſuite, that will deny it.</l>
                  <l>The ſuit's not hard that ſhe comes for to take;</l>
                  <l>Who (hott in luſt of men) doth difference make?</l>
                  <l>At laſt, loath, willing, to her did he pace;</l>
                  <l>Arme him <hi>Priapus,</hi> with thy powerfull Mace.</l>
                  <l>But ſee, they comming are; how they agree</l>
                  <l>Heere will I harken, ſhroud me gentle tree.</l>
               </sp>
               <stage>
                  <hi>Enter Poppea</hi> and <hi>Antonius.</hi>
               </stage>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Anto.</speaker>
                  <l>Seeke not to grieue that heart which is thine owne,</l>
                  <pb facs="tcp:13479:8"/>
                  <l>In Loues ſweete fires, let heat of rage burne out;</l>
                  <l>Theſe browes could neuer yet to wrinckle learne,</l>
                  <l>Nor anger out of ſuch faire eyes looke forth.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Poppea:</speaker>
                  <l>You may ſolicite your preſumptuous ſuites;</l>
                  <l>You duety may, and ſhame too layd aſide,</l>
                  <l>Diſturbe my priuacies, and I forſooth,</l>
                  <l>Muſt be afeard euen to be angry at you.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Anto:</speaker>
                  <l>What ſhame is't to be maſtred by ſuch beautie?</l>
                  <l>Who, but to ſerue you, comes, how wants he dutie?</l>
                  <l>Or if it be a ſhame, the ſhame is yours;</l>
                  <l>The fault is onely in your Eies, they drew me;</l>
                  <l>Cauſe you were louely, therefore did I loue:</l>
                  <l>O, if to Loue you, anger you ſo much,</l>
                  <l>You ſhould not haue ſuch cheekes, nor lips to touch,</l>
                  <l>You ſhould not haue your ſnow, nor currall ſpy'd;</l>
                  <l>If you but looke on vs, in vaine you chide,</l>
                  <l>We muſt not ſee your Face, nor heare your ſpeech:</l>
                  <l>Now, whilſt you Loue forbid, you Loue doe teach.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Pet.</speaker>
                  <l>He doth better then I thought he would.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Pop:</speaker>
                  <l>I will not learne my beauties worth of you,</l>
                  <l>I know you neither are the firſt, nor greateſt</l>
                  <l>Whom it hath mou'd: He whom the World obayes</l>
                  <l>Is fear'd with anger of my threatning Eyes.</l>
                  <l>It is for you a farre off to adore it,</l>
                  <l>And not to reach at it with ſawſie hands.</l>
                  <l>Feare, is the Loue that's due to Gods, and Princes</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Pet.</speaker>
                  <l>All this is but to edge his appetite.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Ant.</speaker>
                  <l>O doe not ſee thy faire in that falſe glaſſe</l>
                  <l>Of outward difference; Looke into my heart,</l>
                  <l>There, ſhalt thou ſee thy ſelfe, Inthroaned ſet</l>
                  <l>In greater Maieſty, then all the pompe</l>
                  <l>Of <hi>Rome,</hi> or <hi>Nero;</hi> Tis not the crowching awe,</l>
                  <l>And Ceremony, with which we flatter Princes,</l>
                  <l>That can to Loues true duties be compar'd.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Pop:</speaker>
                  <l>Sir, let me goe, or Ile make knowne your Loue</l>
                  <l>To them, that ſhall requite it, but with hate.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Pet.</speaker>
                  <l>On, on, thou haſt the goale, the fort is beaten,</l>
                  <l>Women are wonne when they begin to threaten.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <pb facs="tcp:13479:9"/>
                  <speaker>Anto.</speaker>
                  <l>Your Nobleneſſe doth warrant me from that,</l>
                  <l>Nor need you others helpe, to puniſh me,</l>
                  <l>Who, by your forehead am condem'd, or free.</l>
                  <l>They, that to be reuendg'd do bend their minde,</l>
                  <l>Seeke alwayes recompence, in that ſame kind</l>
                  <l>The wrong was done them; Loue was mine offence,</l>
                  <l>In that reuenge, in that ſeeke recompence.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Popp.</speaker>
                  <l>Further to anſwere, will ſtill cauſe replyes,</l>
                  <l>And thoſe as ill doe pleaſe me, as your ſelfe:</l>
                  <l>If you'le an anſwere take, that's breefe, and true,</l>
                  <l>I hate my ſelfe, If I be lou'd of you.
<stage>exit Popp.</stage>
                  </l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Petro.</speaker>
                  <l>What gone? but ſhe will come againe ſure, no;</l>
                  <l>It paſſeth cleane my cunning, all my rules;</l>
                  <l>For Womens wantonneſſe there is no rule.</l>
                  <l>To take her, in the itching of her Luſt,</l>
                  <l>A propper young-man putting forth himſelfe?</l>
                  <l>Why Fate; There's Fate and hidden prouidence</l>
                  <l>In cod piece matters.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Anto:</speaker>
                  <l>O vnhappie Man,</l>
                  <l>What comfort haue I now <hi>Petronius?</hi>
                  </l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Pet.</speaker>
                  <l>Counſell your ſelfe, Ile teach no more but learne.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Ant.</speaker>
                  <l>This comfort yet; He ſhall not ſo eſcape,</l>
                  <l>Who cauſeth my diſgrace, <hi>Nimphidius</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>Whom had I here.—Well, For my true-hearts loue</l>
                  <l>I ſee ſhe hates me; And ſhall I loue one</l>
                  <l>That hates me; and beſtowes what I deſerue</l>
                  <l>Vpon my riuall? no, Farewell <hi>Poppea,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>Farewell <hi>Poppea,</hi> and farewell all Loue;</l>
                  <l>Yet thus much ſhall it ſtill preuaile in me,</l>
                  <l>That I will hate <hi>Nimphidius</hi> for thee:</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Pet.</speaker>
                  <l>Farewell to her, to my <hi>Euanthe</hi> welcome,</l>
                  <l>Who, now, will to my burning kiſſes ſtoope,</l>
                  <l>Now, with an eaſie cruelty deny,</l>
                  <l>That, which ſhe, rather then the aſker, would</l>
                  <l>Haue forced from her, then begins her ſelfe.</l>
                  <l>Their loues, that liſt vpon great Ladies ſet;</l>
                  <l>I ſtill will loue the Wench that I can get.</l>
               </sp>
               <stage>Exeunt.</stage>
               <stage>
                  <pb facs="tcp:13479:9"/>
                  <hi>Enter Nero, Tigellinus, Epaphroditus</hi> and <hi>Neophilus.</hi>
               </stage>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Nero:</speaker>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Tigellinus,</hi> ſaid the villaine <hi>Proculus</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>I was throwne downe in running?</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Tigel:</speaker>
                  <l>My Lord, he ſaid that you were crown'd for that</l>
                  <l>You could not doe.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Nero,</speaker>
                  <l>For that I could not doe?</l>
                  <l>Why, <hi>Elis</hi> ſaw me doet, and doe't with wonder</l>
                  <l>Of all the Iudges, and the lookers on:</l>
                  <l>And yet, to ſee, A villane? could not doe't?</l>
                  <l>Who did it better? I warrant you he ſaid</l>
                  <l>I from the Chariot fell againſt my will.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Tigil:</speaker>
                  <l>He ſaid my Lord, you were throwne out of it,</l>
                  <l>All cruſht, and maim'd, and almoſt bruiſ'd to death.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Nero.</speaker>
                  <l>Malicious Rogue, when I fell willingly,</l>
                  <l>To ſhow of purpoſe, with what little hurt</l>
                  <l>Might a good rider beare a forced fall.</l>
                  <l>How ſayeſt thou? <hi>Tigillinus,</hi> I am ſure</l>
                  <l>Thou haſt in driuing as much skill as he.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Tigil:</speaker>
                  <l>My Lord, you greater cunning ſhew'd in falling,</l>
                  <l>Then had you ſate.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Nero,</speaker>
                  <l>I know I did; or bruiſed in my fall?</l>
                  <l>Hurt! I proteſt I felt no griefe in it.</l>
                  <l>Goe <hi>Tigillinus,</hi> fetch the villaines head,</l>
                  <l>This makes me ſee his heart in other things?</l>
                  <l>Fetch me his head, he nere ſhall ſpeake againe.
<stage>ex. Tigil.</stage>
                  </l>
                  <l>What doe we Princes differ, from the durt,</l>
                  <l>And baſeneſſe of the common Multitude,</l>
                  <l>If to the ſcorne of each malicious tongue</l>
                  <l>We ſubiect are: For that I had no skill;</l>
                  <l>Not he, that his farre famed daughter ſet</l>
                  <l>A priſe to victorie, and had bin crown'd</l>
                  <l>With thirteene Sutors deaths, till he at length</l>
                  <l>By fate of Gods, and ſeruants treaſon fell,</l>
                  <l>(Shoulder pack't <hi>Pelops</hi> glorying in his ſpoyles,)</l>
                  <l>Could with more skill his coupled horſes guide.</l>
                  <l>Euen as a Barke, that through the moouing Flood.</l>
                  <pb facs="tcp:13479:10"/>
                  <l>Her linnen wings, and the forc't ayre doe beare,</l>
                  <l>The Byllowes fome, ſhe ſmoothly cutts them through;</l>
                  <l>So paſt my burning Axeltree along,</l>
                  <l>The people follow, with their eyes and voyce,</l>
                  <l>And now the wind doth ſee it ſelfe outrun,</l>
                  <l>And the Clouds wonder to be left behind;</l>
                  <l>Whilſt the void ayre is fild with ſhoutes and noyſe</l>
                  <l>And <hi>Neroes</hi> name doth beate the braſen Skie,</l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Jubiter</hi> cruying, loath doth heare my praiſe:</l>
                  <l>Then there greene howes, and Crownes of <hi>Oliue</hi> wre'aths</l>
                  <l>The Conquerors praiſe, they giue me as my due,</l>
                  <l>And yet this Rogue ſayth no we haue no skill.</l>
               </sp>
               <stage>Enter a ſeruant to them.</stage>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Seruant,</speaker>
                  <l>My Lord, the Stage, and all the furnitures</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Nero:</speaker>
                  <l>I haue no skill to driue a Chariot:</l>
                  <l>Had he but robde me, broke my treaſurie,</l>
                  <l>The red-Sea's mine, mine are the <hi>Indian</hi> ſtones,</l>
                  <l>The Worlds mine owne, then, cannot I be robde?</l>
                  <l>But ſpightfully, to vndermine my fame,</l>
                  <l>To take away my arte; he would my life</l>
                  <l>As well, no doubt; could he tould how.</l>
               </sp>
               <stage>
                  <hi>Enter Tegillinus,</hi> with <hi>Proculus head.</hi>
               </stage>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Neoph:</speaker>
                  <l>My Lord,</l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Tegillinus</hi> is backe come with <hi>Proculus</hi> head
<stage>ſtrikes him.</stage>
                  </l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Nero,</speaker>
                  <l>O cry thee mercie good <hi>Neophitus;</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>Giue him fiue hundred ſeſterces for amends,</l>
                  <l>Haſt brought him <hi>Tegillinus?</hi>
                  </l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Tegil:</speaker>
                  <l>Heres his head my Lord.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Nero,</speaker>
                  <l>His tongue had bin enough,</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Tegil:</speaker>
                  <l>I did as you commanded me my Lord.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Nero,</speaker>
                  <l>Thou toldſt not me, though he had ſuch a Noſe.</l>
                  <l>Now are you quiet, and haue quieted me;</l>
                  <l>This tis to be commander of the World,</l>
                  <l>Let them extoll weake pittie that doe neede it,</l>
                  <l>Let meane men cry to haue Law, and Iuſtice done</l>
                  <l>And tell their griefes to <hi>Heauen,</hi> that heares them not</l>
                  <l>Kings muſt vpon the Peoples headleſſe courſes</l>
                  <l>Walke to ſecuritie, and eaſe of minde.</l>
                  <pb facs="tcp:13479:10"/>
                  <l>Why what haue we to doe with th'ayrie names</l>
                  <l>(That old age, and <hi>Philoſophers</hi> found out,)</l>
                  <l>Of <hi>Iuſtice,</hi> and ne're certaine Equitie;</l>
                  <l>The Gods reuenge themſelues, and ſo will we;</l>
                  <l>Where right is ſcand, Authoritie'is orethrowne,</l>
                  <l>We haue a high pre<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ogatiue aboue it;</l>
                  <l>Slaues may doe what is luſt, we, what we pleaſe,</l>
                  <l>The people will repine, and thinke it ill,</l>
                  <l>But they muſt beare, and prayſe too, what we will.</l>
               </sp>
               <stage>Enter Cornutus to them.</stage>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Neoph:</speaker>
                  <l>My Lord, <hi>Cornutus</hi> whom you ſent for's come.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Nero,</speaker>
                  <l>Welcome good <hi>Cornutus</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>Are all thigs ready for the Stage,</l>
                  <l>As I gaue charge.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Corn:</speaker>
                  <l>They onely ſtay your comming.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Nero,</speaker>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Cornutus,</hi> I muſt act to day <hi>Oreſtus.</hi>
                  </l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Cornu:</speaker>
                  <l>You haue done that alreadie; and too truely —
<stage>aſide</stage>
                  </l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Nero,</speaker>
                  <l>And when our Sceane is done, I meane beſides</l>
                  <l>To read ſome compoſitions of mine owne,</l>
                  <l>Which for the great opinion I my ſelfe,</l>
                  <l>And <hi>Rome</hi> In generall, of thy Iudgement, hath,</l>
                  <l>Before I publiſh them, Ile ſhew them thee.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Cornu:</speaker>
                  <l>My Lord, my diſabilities</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Nero:</speaker>
                  <l>I know thy modeſtie,</l>
                  <l>Ile onely ſhew thee, now, my works beginning:</l>
                  <l>Goe ſee <hi>Epaphroditus,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>Muſick made ready, I will ſing to day.
<stage>Exit Epa.</stage>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Cornutus</hi> I pray thee, come neere,</l>
                  <l>And let me heare thy Iudgement in my paynes;</l>
                  <l>I would haue thee more familiar good <hi>Cornutus,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Nero</hi> doth priſe deſert, and more eſteemes</l>
                  <l>Them, that in knowledge ſecond him then power,</l>
                  <l>Marke with what ſtyle, and ſtate my worke begins.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Cornu:</speaker>
                  <l>Might not my Interuption offend</l>
                  <l>Whats your workes name my Lord, what write you of?</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Nero,</speaker>
                  <l>I meane to write the deeds of all the <hi>Romans</hi>
                  </l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Cornu:</speaker>
                  <l>Of all the <hi>Romans?</hi> a huge argument</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Nero,</speaker>
                  <l>I haue not yet bethought me of a Title</l>
                  <pb facs="tcp:13479:11"/>
                  <l>
                     <hi>You Enthrall Powers which the wide Fortunes doome</hi> he reades</l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Of Empyre crown'd, ſeauen Mountaine-ſeated</hi> Rome</l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Full blowne; Inſpire me with</hi> Machlaean <hi>rage,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>That J may bellow out</hi> Romes <hi>Prentiſage,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>As when the</hi> Menades <hi>doe fill their Drums</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>And crooked hornes with</hi> Mimalonean <hi>humme:</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>And</hi> Ennion <hi>doe Ingeminate a round</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Which reparable Ecchoe doth reſound.</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>How doeſt thou like our Muſes paines <hi>Cornutus.</hi>
                  </l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Cornu:</speaker>
                  <l>The verſes haue more in them, then I ſee;</l>
                  <l>Your worke my Lord I doubt will be too long.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Nero,</speaker>
                  <l>Too long?</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Tigel:</speaker>
                  <l>Too long?</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Cornu:</speaker>
                  <l>I, If you write the deedes of all the <hi>Romans</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>How many Bookes thinke you t'include it in?</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Nero,</speaker>
                  <l>I thinke to write about foure hundred Bookes.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Cornu:</speaker>
                  <l>Foure hundred? why my Lord the'yle nere be read.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Nero,</speaker>
                  <l>Hah?</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Tigil:</speaker>
                  <l>Why he, whom you eſteeme ſo much <hi>Criſippus,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>Wrote many more.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Cornu:</speaker>
                  <l>But they were profitable to common life</l>
                  <l>And did Men, Honeſtie, and Wiſedome teach.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Nero:</speaker>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Tigillinus?</hi>
                     <stage>Exit Nero &amp; Tigeli.</stage>
                  </l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Cornu:</speaker>
                  <l>See with what earneſtneſſe he crau'd my Iudgment,</l>
                  <l>And now he freely hath it, how it likes him?</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Neoph:</speaker>
                  <l>The Prince is angry, and his fall is neere;</l>
                  <l>Let vs begon, leaſt we partake his ruines.</l>
               </sp>
               <stage>Exeunt omnes praeter Cornn,</stage>
               <stage>Manet Cornutus ſolus.</stage>
               <sp>
                  <l>What ſhould I doe at Court? I cannot lye;</l>
                  <l>Why didſt thou call me, <hi>Nero,</hi> from my Booke?</l>
                  <l>Didſt thou for flatterie of <hi>Cornutus</hi> looke?</l>
                  <l>No, let thoſe purple Fellowes that ſtand by thee,</l>
                  <l>(That admire ſhew, and things that <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>ou canſt giue,</l>
                  <l>Leaue to pleaſe Truth, and Vertue, to pleaſe thee.</l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Nero,</hi> there's nothing in thy power, <hi>Cornutus</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>Doth wiſh or feare.</l>
               </sp>
               <stage>
                  <pb facs="tcp:13479:11"/>
                  <hi>Enter Tigellinus to him.</hi>
               </stage>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Tigel:</speaker>
                  <l>Tis <hi>Neroes</hi> pleaſure that you ſtraight depart</l>
                  <l>To <hi>Giarae,</hi> and there remaine confin'd:</l>
                  <l>Thus he, out of his Princely Clemencie,</l>
                  <l>Hath Death, your due, turn'd but to baniſhment.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Cornu:</speaker>
                  <l>Why <hi>Tigellinus?</hi>
                  </l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Tigel:</speaker>
                  <l>I haue done, vpon your perill goe, or ſtay,
<stage>ex Ti.</stage>
                  </l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Cornu:</speaker>
                  <l>And why ſhould Death? or Baniſhment be due?</l>
                  <l>For ſpeaking, that which was requir'd, my thought;</l>
                  <l>O why doe Princes loue to be deceiu'd?</l>
                  <l>And, euen, doe force abuſes on themſelues?</l>
                  <l>There Eares are ſo with pleaſing ſpeech beguil'd,</l>
                  <l>That Truth they mallice, Flatterie, truth account,</l>
                  <l>And their owne Soule, and vnderſtanding loſt,</l>
                  <l>Goe (what they are) to ſeeke in other men.</l>
                  <l>Alas, weake Prince, how haſt thou puniſht me,</l>
                  <l>To baniſh me from thee? O let me goe</l>
                  <l>And dwell in <hi>Taurus,</hi> dwell in <hi>Ethiop<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>So that I doe not dwell at <hi>Rome,</hi> with thee.</l>
                  <l>The farther, ſtill, I goe from hence, I know,</l>
                  <l>The farther I leaue Shame and Vice behind.</l>
                  <l>Where can I goe, but I ſhall ſee thee, <hi>Sunne?</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>And <hi>Heauen</hi> will be as neere me, ſtill, as here.</l>
                  <l>Can they, ſo farre, a knowing ſoule exyle,</l>
                  <l>That her owne roofe ſhe ſees not ore her head?
<stage>Exit</stage>
                  </l>
               </sp>
               <stage>Enter Piſo, Sceuinus, Lucan Flauius.</stage>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Piſo,</speaker>
                  <l>Noble Gentlemen, what thankes, what recompence</l>
                  <l>Shall hee giue you, that giue to him the world;</l>
                  <l>One life to them, that muſt ſo many venture,</l>
                  <l>And that, the worſt of all, is too meane paye;</l>
                  <l>Yet can I giue no more; Take that, beſtow it</l>
                  <l>Vpon your ſeruice.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Lucan:</speaker>
                  <l>O <hi>Piſo,</hi> that vouchſafeſt,</l>
                  <l>To grace our headleſſe partie with thy name;</l>
                  <l>Whom, hauing our conductors, we need not</l>
                  <l>Haue fear'd to goe again the well try'd vallor</l>
                  <l>Of <hi>Iulius,</hi> or ſtayedneſſe of <hi>Auguſtus,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>Much leſſe the ſhame, and Womanhood of <hi>Nero;</hi>
                  </l>
                  <pb facs="tcp:13479:12"/>
                  <l>When we had once, giuen out, that our pretences</l>
                  <l>Were all for thee, our end, to make thee Prince,</l>
                  <l>They thronging came to giue their names, Men, Women,</l>
                  <l>Gentlemen, People, Soldiers, Senators,</l>
                  <l>The Campe, and Cittie, grew aſham'd that <hi>Nero,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>And <hi>Piſo</hi> ſhould be offered them together.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Sceu.</speaker>
                  <l>We ſeeke not now (as in the happy dayes</l>
                  <l>O'th common wealth they did, for libertie;</l>
                  <l>O you, deere aſhes, <hi>Caſſius</hi> and <hi>Brutus</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>That was with you entomb'd, there let it reſt,</l>
                  <l>We are contented with the galling yoke,</l>
                  <l>If they will only leaue vs necks to beare it;</l>
                  <l>We ſeeke no longer freedome, we ſeeke life</l>
                  <l>At leaſt, not to be murdred, let vs die</l>
                  <l>On Enemies ſwords; Shall we, whom neither</l>
                  <l>The <hi>Median</hi> Bow, nor <hi>Macedonian</hi> Speare</l>
                  <l>Nor the firce <hi>Gaule,</hi> nor painted <hi>Briton</hi> could</l>
                  <l>Subdue, lay downe our neckes to Tyrants axe?</l>
                  <l>Why doe we talke of Vertue, that obay</l>
                  <l>Weakeneſſe, and Vice.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Piſo:</speaker>
                  <l>Haue patience good <hi>Sceuinus</hi>
                  </l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Lucan:</speaker>
                  <l>Weakeneſſe, and ſeruile gouernment we hitherto</l>
                  <l>Obeyed haue, which, that we may no longer,</l>
                  <l>We haue our liues, and fortunes now ſet vp,</l>
                  <l>And haue our cauſe with <hi>Piſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>es</hi> credit ſtrengthned.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Flaui:</speaker>
                  <l>Which makes it doubtfull, whether loue to him</l>
                  <l>Or <hi>Neroes</hi> hatred, hath drawne more vnto vs.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Piſo:</speaker>
                  <l>I ſee the good thoughts you haue of me, Lords.</l>
                  <l>Lets now proceede to th' purpoſe of our meeting,</l>
                  <l>I pray you take your places.</l>
                  <l>Lets haue ſome Paper brought</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Sceuin:</speaker>
                  <l>Whoſe within</l>
               </sp>
               <stage>Enter Milichus to them.</stage>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Meli.</speaker>
                  <l>My Lord</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Sceu.</speaker>
                  <l>Some Inke, and Paper
<stage>Exit Meli—&amp; enter againe with Incke, and Paper.</stage>
                  </l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Flaui:</speaker>
                  <l>Whoſe that <hi>Sceuinus?</hi>
                  </l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Sceui:</speaker>
                  <l>It is my freed man <hi>Melichus.</hi>
                  </l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Luca:</speaker>
                  <l>Is he truſtie?</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <pb facs="tcp:13479:12"/>
                  <speaker>Sceuin:</speaker>
                  <l>I for as great matters, as we are about.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Piſo:</speaker>
                  <l>And thoſe are great ones.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Luca:</speaker>
                  <l>I aske not that we meane to neede his truſt.</l>
                  <l>Gaine hath great ſoueragintie ore ſeruile mindes.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Sceui:</speaker>
                  <l>O but my benifits haue bound him to me.</l>
                  <l>I, from abondman, haue his ſtate not onely</l>
                  <l>Aduanc't to freedome, but to wealth and credit.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Piſo:</speaker>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Meli.</hi> waire ith'next chamber tell we call.
<stage>abſcondit ſe</stage>
                  </l>
                  <l>The thing determinde on our meeting now,</l>
                  <l>Is of the meanes, and place, due circumſtance,</l>
                  <l>As to the doing of things t'is requir'd,</l>
                  <l>So done it names the action.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Melis:</speaker>
                  <l>I wonder,</l>
                  <l>What makes this new reſort to haunt our houſe,</l>
                  <l>When wonted <hi>Lucius Piſo</hi> to come hither?</l>
                  <l>Or <hi>Lucan,</hi> when ſo oft, as now of late.
<stage>aſide</stage>
                  </l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Piſo:</speaker>
                  <l>And ſince the field, and open ſhew of armes</l>
                  <l>Diſlike you, and that for the generall good,</l>
                  <l>You meane to end all ſtyrres, in end of him:</l>
                  <l>That, as the ground, muſt firſt be thought vpon.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Melic:</speaker>
                  <l>Beſides, this comming cannot be for forme,</l>
                  <l>Our viſitation, they goe aſide,
<stage>aſide</stage>
                  </l>
                  <l>And haue long conferences by themſelues.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Luca:</speaker>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Piſo,</hi> his comming to your houſe at <hi>Baiae</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>To bathe, and banquet, will fit meanes afford,</l>
                  <l>amidſt his cups, to end his hated life,</l>
                  <l>Let him die drunke, that nere liu'd ſoberly.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Piſa:</speaker>
                  <l>O be it farre, that I ſhould ſtaine my Table,</l>
                  <l>And Gods of Hoſpitalitie with blood;</l>
                  <l>Let not our cauſe (now Innocent) be ſoyld</l>
                  <l>With ſuch a blot, nor <hi>Piſoes</hi> name made hatefull.</l>
                  <l>What place can better fit our action</l>
                  <l>Then his owne houſe? that boundleſſe enuied heape,</l>
                  <l>Built with the ſpoyles, and blood of Cittizens</l>
                  <l>That hath taken vp the Citie, left no roome</l>
                  <l>For <hi>Rome</hi> to ſtand on; <hi>Romanes</hi> get you gone</l>
                  <l>And dwell at <hi>
                        <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ciae,</hi> If that <hi>Vciae</hi> too</l>
                  <l>This houſe ore runne not.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <pb facs="tcp:13479:13"/>
                  <speaker>Lucan.</speaker>
                  <l>But twill be hard to doe it in his houſe,</l>
                  <l>And harder to eſcape being done.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Piſo.</speaker>
                  <l>Not ſo,</l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>B<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>fus</hi> the Captaine of the Guard's with vs,</l>
                  <l>And diuers other oth' <hi>Preterian</hi> Band</l>
                  <l>Already made; many, though vnacquainted</l>
                  <l>With our intents, haue had diſgrace and wrongs,</l>
                  <l>Which grieue them ſtill; moſt will be glad of change,</l>
                  <l>And euen they that lou'd him beſt, when once</l>
                  <l>They ſee him gone, will ſmile o'th comming times,</l>
                  <l>Let goe things paſt, and looke to their owne ſafetie:</l>
                  <l>Beſides, th'aſtoniſhment and feare will be</l>
                  <l>So great, ſo ſodaine, that 'twill hinder them</l>
                  <l>From doing any thing.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Meli.</speaker>
                  <l>No priuate buſineſſe can concerne them all;
<stage>aſide.</stage>
                  </l>
                  <l>Their countenances are troubled, and looke ſad,</l>
                  <l>Doubt and Importance in their face is read.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Lucan.</speaker>
                  <l>Yet ſtill I thinke it were</l>
                  <l>Safer t'attempt him priuate, and alone.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Flaui.</speaker>
                  <l>But 'twill not carry that opinion with it,</l>
                  <l>Twill ſeeme more foule, and come from priuate malice.</l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Brutus,</hi> and they, to right the common cauſe,</l>
                  <l>Did chuſe a publike place.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Serui.</speaker>
                  <l>Our deed is honeſt, why ſhould it ſeeke corners?</l>
                  <l>Tis for the people done, let them behold it;</l>
                  <l>Let me haue them a witneſſe of my truth,</l>
                  <l>And loue toth' Common-wealth; The danger's greater,</l>
                  <l>So is the glory. Why ſhould our pale counſels</l>
                  <l>Tend whether feare, rather then vertue calls them:</l>
                  <l>I doe not like theſe cold conſiderings;</l>
                  <l>Firſt, let our thoughts looke vp to what is honeſt,</l>
                  <l>Next, to what's ſafe; If danger may deterre vs,</l>
                  <l>Nothing that's great, or good ſhall ere be done;</l>
                  <l>And, when we firſt gaue hands vpon this deed</l>
                  <l>Toth' commons ſafetie, we our owne gaue vp.</l>
                  <l>Let not man venture on a princes death,</l>
                  <l>How bad ſoeuer, with beliefe to eſcape;</l>
                  <l>Diſpaire muſt be our hope, fame, or reward.</l>
                  <l>To make the generall liking to concurre</l>
                  <pb facs="tcp:13479:13"/>
                  <l>With others, were euen to ſtrike him in his ſhame,</l>
                  <l>Or (as he thinks) his glory, on the Stage,</l>
                  <l>And ſo too truely make't a Tragedy;</l>
                  <l>When all the people cannot chuſe but clap</l>
                  <l>So ſweet a cloſe, and 'twill not <hi>Caeſar</hi> be</l>
                  <l>That ſhall be ſlaine, a <hi>Romane</hi> Prince:</l>
                  <l>Twill be <hi>Alemaeon,</hi> or blind <hi>Oedipus.</hi>
                  </l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Meli.</speaker>
                  <l>And if it be of publique matters, 'tis not
<stage>aſide.</stage>
                  </l>
                  <l>Like to be talke, or idle fault finding,</l>
                  <l>On which the coward onely ſpends his wiſedome:</l>
                  <l>Theſe are all men of action, and of ſpirit,</l>
                  <l>And dare performe what they determine on.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Luca.</speaker>
                  <l>What thinke you of <hi>Poppea, Tigellinus,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>And tho'ther odious Inſtruments of Court:</l>
                  <l>Were it not beſt at once to rid them all?</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Serui.</speaker>
                  <l>In <hi>Caeſars</hi> ruine, <hi>Anthony</hi> was ſpared:</l>
                  <l>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ets not our cauſe with needleſſe blood diſtaine,</l>
                  <l>One onely mou'd, the change will not appeare</l>
                  <l>When too much licence giuen to the ſword,</l>
                  <l>Though againſt ill, will make euen good men feare:</l>
                  <l>Beſides, things ſetled, you at pleaſure may</l>
                  <l>By Law, and publique Iudgement haue them rid.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Meli.</speaker>
                  <l>And if it be but talke oth'State, 'tis Treaſon,</l>
                  <l>Like it they cannot, that they cannot doe:</l>
                  <l>If ſeeke to mend it, and remooue the Prince,</l>
                  <l>That's higheſt Treaſon; change his Councellours,
<stage>aſide.</stage>
                  </l>
                  <l>That's alteration of the gouernment,</l>
                  <l>The common cloke that Treaſons mufled in;</l>
                  <l>If laying force aſide, to ſeeke by ſuite,</l>
                  <l>And faire petition, t'haue the State reform'd,</l>
                  <l>That's tutering of the Prince, and takes away,</l>
                  <l>Thone his perſon, this his Soueraigntie;</l>
                  <l>Barely in priuate talke to ſhew diſlike</l>
                  <l>Of what is done, is dangerous; therefore the action</l>
                  <l>Miſlike you, cauſe the doer likes you not?</l>
                  <l>Men are not fit to liue ith ſtate they hate.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Piſo.</speaker>
                  <l>Though we would all haue that imployment ſought,</l>
                  <l>Yet, ſince your worthy forwardneſſe, <hi>Seruinus,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <pb facs="tcp:13479:14"/>
                  <l>Preuents vs, And ſo Nobly beggs for danger:</l>
                  <l>Be this the choſen hand to doe the deed,</l>
                  <l>The fortune of the Empire ſpeed your ſword.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Sceui:</speaker>
                  <l>Vertue, and Heauen ſpeed it; O you homeborne</l>
                  <l>Gods of our countrey, <hi>Romulus,</hi> and <hi>Veſta,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>That <hi>Thuſcan Tiber,</hi> and <hi>Romes</hi> towers defends:</l>
                  <l>Forbid not yet at length a happie end</l>
                  <l>To former euils; Let this hand reuenge</l>
                  <l>The wronged world; enough we now haue ſuffered.
<stage>exeunt.</stage>
                  </l>
               </sp>
               <stage>Manet Melichus ſolus.</stage>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Meli</speaker>
                  <l>Tuſh, all this long Conſulting's more then words,</l>
                  <l>It ends not there; th'haue ſome attempt, ſome plot,</l>
                  <l>Againſt the ſtate: well, Ile obſerue it farther,</l>
                  <l>And if I find it, make my profit of it.
<stage>exeunt.</stage>
                  </l>
               </sp>
               <trailer>Finis Actus Secundus.</trailer>
            </div>
            <div n="3" type="act">
               <head>Actus Tertius.</head>
               <stage>Enter Poppea Solus.</stage>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>POppea:</speaker>
                  <l>I lookt <hi>Nimphidius</hi> would haue come ere this,</l>
                  <l>Makes he no greater haſt to our embraces?</l>
                  <l>Or, doth the eaſines abate his edge?</l>
                  <l>Or, ſeeme we not as faire ſtill as we did?</l>
                  <l>Or, is he ſo with <hi>Neroes</hi> playing wonne,</l>
                  <l>That he, before <hi>Poppea,</hi> doth preferre it?</l>
                  <l>Or doth he thinke to haue occaſion ſtill?</l>
                  <l>Sill, to haue time to waite on our ſtolne meetings?</l>
               </sp>
               <stage>Enter Nimphidius to her.</stage>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Poppe:</speaker>
                  <l>But ſee his preſence now doth end thoſe doubts,</l>
                  <l>What i'ſt <hi>Nimphidius</hi> hath ſo long detain'd you?</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Nimph:</speaker>
                  <l>Faith Lady, cauſes ſtrong enough,</l>
                  <l>High walls, bard dores, and guards of armed men.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Poppe:</speaker>
                  <l>Were you Impriſoned, then, as you were going</l>
                  <l>To the Theater.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Nimphi:</speaker>
                  <l>Not in my going Lady,</l>
                  <pb facs="tcp:13479:14"/>
                  <l>But, in the Theater, I was Impriſoned:</l>
                  <l>For, after he was once vpon the Stage,</l>
                  <l>The Gates were more ſeuerely lookt into</l>
                  <l>Then at a towne beſieg'd; No man, no cauſe</l>
                  <l>Was Currant, no, nor paſſant; At other ſights</l>
                  <l>The ſtriefe is only to get in, but here</l>
                  <l>The ſtirre was all, in getting out againe;</l>
                  <l>Had, we not bin kept to it ſo, I thinke</l>
                  <l>T'would nere haue bin ſo tedious, though I know,</l>
                  <l>'Twas hard to iudge, whether his doing of it</l>
                  <l>Were more abſur'd, then 'twas for time to doe it.</l>
                  <l>But wh<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap> we once were forc't to be ſpectators,</l>
                  <l>compel'd to that, which ſhould haue bin a pleaſure,</l>
                  <l>We could no longer beare the weariſomneſſe:</l>
                  <l>No paine ſo irkeſome, as a forc't delight;</l>
                  <l>Some fell downe dead, or ſeem'd at leaſt to doe ſo,</l>
                  <l>Vnder that colour, to be carried forth,</l>
                  <l>Then death firſt pleaſur'd men, the ſhape all feare</l>
                  <l>Was put on gladly, ſome clombe ore the walls,</l>
                  <l>And ſo, by falling caught in earneſt that,</l>
                  <l>Which th'other did diſſemble; There were women,</l>
                  <l>(That being not able to intreat the guard</l>
                  <l>To let them paſſe the gates,) were brought to bedde</l>
                  <l>Amid'ſt the throngs of men, and made <hi>Lucina</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>Bluſh, to ſee that vnwonted companie.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Poppe:</speaker>
                  <l>If 'twere ſo ſtraightly kept, how got you forth?</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Nimp:</speaker>
                  <l>Faith Lady I came, pretending haſt</l>
                  <l>In Face and Countenance, told them I was ſent</l>
                  <l>For things, bith' Prince forgot about the ſceane,</l>
                  <l>Which, both my credit made them to beleeue,</l>
                  <l>And <hi>Nero,</hi> newly whiſpered me before.</l>
                  <l>Thus did I paſſe the gates, the danger Ladie</l>
                  <l>I haue not yet eſcap't.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Poppe:</speaker>
                  <l>What danger meane you?</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Nim:</speaker>
                  <l>The danger of his anger, when he knowes</l>
                  <l>How I thus ſhrunke away, for there ſtood knaues</l>
                  <l>That put downe in their Tables all that ſtir'd,</l>
                  <l>And markt in each there cheerefulneſſe, or ſadneſſe.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <pb facs="tcp:13479:15"/>
                  <speaker>Poppe:</speaker>
                  <l>I warrant Ile excuſe you: But I pray,</l>
                  <l>Lett's be a little better for your ſight;</l>
                  <l>How did our Princely husband act <hi>Oreſtes?</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>Did he not wiſh againe his Mother liuing?</l>
                  <l>Her death would adde great life vnto his part:</l>
                  <l>But come I pray, the ſtorie of your ſight.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Nim:</speaker>
                  <l>O doe not driue me to thoſe hatefull paines;</l>
                  <l>Lady, I was too much in ſeeing vext,</l>
                  <l>Let it not be redoubled with the telling;</l>
                  <l>I now am well, and heare, my eares ſet free;</l>
                  <l>O be mercifull, doe not bring me backe</l>
                  <l>Vnto my priſon, at leaſt free your ſelfe,</l>
                  <l>It will not paſſe away, but ſtay the time;</l>
                  <l>Wracke out the houres in length; O giue me leaue,</l>
                  <l>as one that wearied with the toyle at ſea,</l>
                  <l>And now on wiſhed ſhore hath firm'd his foote;</l>
                  <l>He lookes about, and glads his thoughts and eyes,</l>
                  <l>With ſight oth' greene cloath'd ground, and leauy trees,</l>
                  <l>Of flowers that begge more then the looking on,</l>
                  <l>And likes theſe other waters narrow ſhores;</l>
                  <l>So let me lay my wearines in theſe armes,</l>
                  <l>Nothing but kiſſes to this mouth diſcourſe,</l>
                  <l>My thought be compaſt in thoſe circl'd Eyes;</l>
                  <l>Eyes on no obiect looke, but on thoſe Cheekes;</l>
                  <l>Be bleſt my hands with touch of thoſe round breſts,</l>
                  <l>Whiter and ſofter then the downe of Swans.</l>
                  <l>Let me of thee, and of thy beauties glory,</l>
                  <l>And endleſſe tell, but neuer wearying ſtory.
<stage>Exeunt.</stage>
                  </l>
               </sp>
               <stage>Enter Nero, Ephaproditus, Neophilus.</stage>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Nero:</speaker>
                  <l>Come Sirs, I faith, how did you like my acting?</l>
                  <l>What? waſt not as you lookt for?</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Epaph:</speaker>
                  <l>Yes my Lord, and much beyond.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Nero:</speaker>
                  <l>Did I not doe it to the life?</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Epaph:</speaker>
                  <l>The very doing neuer was ſo liuely</l>
                  <l>As now this counterfeyting.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Nero:</speaker>
                  <l>And when I came,</l>
                  <l>Toth' point of <hi>Agrippa, Cliteunneſtras</hi> death,</l>
                  <l>Did it not mooue the feeling auditory?</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <pb facs="tcp:13479:15"/>
                  <speaker>Epaph:</speaker>
                  <l>They had beene ſtones, whom that could not haue mon'd.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Nero:</speaker>
                  <l>Did not my voyce hold out well to the end?</l>
                  <l>And ſeru'd me afterwards afreſh to ſing with.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Neoph:</speaker>
                  <l>We know <hi>Apollo</hi> cannot match your voyce.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Epaph:</speaker>
                  <l>By <hi>Ioue,</hi> 
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> thinke you are the God himſelfe</l>
                  <l>Come from aboue, to ſhew your hidden arts;</l>
                  <l>And fill vs men with wonder of your skill.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Nero:</speaker>
                  <l>Nay faith ſpeake truely, doe not flatter me;</l>
                  <l>I know you need not: flattery's but where</l>
                  <l>Deſert is meane.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Epaph:</speaker>
                  <l>I ſweare by thee O <hi>Caeſar;</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>Then whom no power of Heauen I honour more,</l>
                  <l>No mortall voice can paſſe, or equall thine.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Nero:</speaker>
                  <l>They tell of <hi>Orpheus,</hi> when he tooke his Lute,</l>
                  <l>And moou'd the noble Iuory with his touch:</l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Hebrus</hi> ſtood ſtill, <hi>Pangea</hi> bow'd his head,</l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Oſſa</hi> then firſt ſhooke off his ſnowe, and came</l>
                  <l>To liſten to the moouings of his ſong;</l>
                  <l>The gentle <hi>Popler,</hi> tooke the Oake along.</l>
                  <l>And call'd the <hi>Pyne</hi> downe, from his Mountaine ſeate:</l>
                  <l>The <hi>Virgine Bay,</hi> although the Arts ſhe hates</l>
                  <l>Oth' <hi>Delphick</hi> God, was with his voice ore come,</l>
                  <l>He his twice-loſt <hi>Euridice</hi> bewailes,</l>
                  <l>And <hi>Proſerpines</hi> vaine gifts, and makes the ſhores</l>
                  <l>And hollow caues of forreſts now vntreed</l>
                  <l>Beare his griefe company, and all things teacheth</l>
                  <l>His loſt loues name: Then water, ayre, and ground</l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Euridice, Euridice,</hi> reſound.</l>
                  <l>Theſe are bould tales, of which the <hi>Greekes</hi> haue ſtore;</l>
                  <l>But if he could from Hell once more returne,</l>
                  <l>And would compare his hand and voice with mine,</l>
                  <l>I, though himſelfe were iudge, he then ſhould ſee,</l>
                  <l>How much the <hi>Latine</hi> ſtaines the <hi>Thracian</hi> lyar.</l>
                  <l>I oft haue walkt by <hi>Tibers</hi> flowing bankes,</l>
                  <l>And heard the Swan ſing her owne Epitaph</l>
                  <l>When ſhe heard me, ſhe held her peace and died.</l>
                  <l>Let others raiſe from earthly things their praiſe,</l>
                  <l>Heauen hath ſtood ſtill to heare my happy ayres</l>
                  <pb facs="tcp:13479:16"/>
                  <l>And ceaſt th'eternall Muſicke of the <hi>Spheares</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>To marke my voyce, and mend their tunes by mine.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Neoph:</speaker>
                  <l>O diuine voyce,</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Epaph:</speaker>
                  <l>Happy are they that heare it.</l>
               </sp>
               <stage>Enter Tigellinus to them.</stage>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Nero:</speaker>
                  <l>But here comes <hi>Tigellinus,</hi> come, thy bill,</l>
                  <l>Are there ſo many; I ſee I haue enemies.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Epaph:</speaker>
                  <l>Haue you put <hi>Caius</hi> in, I ſaw him frowne</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Neoph:</speaker>
                  <l>And, in the midſt oth' Emperors act on</l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Gallus</hi> laught out, and as I thinke in ſcorne.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Nero:</speaker>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Veſpaſian</hi> too a ſleepe; was he ſo drowſie?</l>
                  <l>Well, he ſhall ſleepe the Iron ſleepe of death</l>
                  <l>And did <hi>Thraſea</hi> looke ſo ſour<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ly on vs?</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Tigil:</speaker>
                  <l>He neuer ſmilde, my Lord, nor would vouchſafe</l>
                  <l>With one applauſe to grace your action.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Nero:</speaker>
                  <l>Our action needed not be grac'd by him,</l>
                  <l>Hee's our old enemie, and ſtill Malignes vs;</l>
                  <l>T'will haue an end, nay it ſhall haue an end.</l>
                  <l>Why, I haue bin too pittifull too remiſſe,</l>
                  <l>My eaſineſſe i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>laught at, and contemn'd,</l>
                  <l>But I will change it; Not, as heretofore,</l>
                  <l>By ſingling out them, one by one to death,</l>
                  <l>Each common man can ſuch reuenges haue;</l>
                  <l>A Princes anger muſt lay deſolate</l>
                  <l>Citties, Kingdomes conſume, Roote vp mankind.</l>
                  <l>O could I liue to ſee the generall end,</l>
                  <l>Behold the world en<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>rapt in funerall flame,</l>
                  <l>When, as the <hi>Sunne</hi> ſhall lend his beames to burne</l>
                  <l>What he before brought forth, and water ſerue,</l>
                  <l>Not to extinguiſh but to <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>uiſe the fire:</l>
                  <l>Then, like the <hi>Salamander,</hi> bathing me</l>
                  <l>In the laſt Aſhes of all mortall things</l>
                  <l>Let me giue vp this breath: <hi>Priam</hi> was happie,</l>
                  <l>Happie indeed, he ſaw his <hi>Troy</hi> burnt,</l>
                  <l>And <hi>Illion</hi> lye on heapes; Whil'ſt thy pure ſtreames,</l>
                  <l>(Diuine <hi>Scamander</hi>) did run <hi>Phrygian</hi> blood</l>
                  <l>And heard the pleaſant cries of <hi>Troian</hi> Mothers.</l>
                  <l>Could I ſee <hi>Rome,</hi> ſo?</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <pb facs="tcp:13479:16"/>
                  <speaker>Tigell:</speaker>
                  <l>Your Maieſtie may eaſily,</l>
                  <l>Without this trouble to your ſacred mind.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Nero:</speaker>
                  <l>What may I eaſily doe? kill thee, or him,</l>
                  <l>How may I rid you all? where is the Man</l>
                  <l>That will all others end, and laſt himſelfe?</l>
                  <l>O that I had thy Thunder in my hand,</l>
                  <l>Thou idle Rouer, Ile not ſhoote at trees,</l>
                  <l>And ſpend in woods my vnregarded vengeance,</l>
                  <l>Ile ſheuire them downe vpon thtir guilty roofes,</l>
                  <l>And fill the ſtreetes with bloody burials.</l>
                  <l>But 'tis not Heauen can giue me what I ſeeke;</l>
                  <l>To you, you hated kingdomes of the night,</l>
                  <l>You ſevere powers, that not like thoſe aboue,</l>
                  <l>Will with faire words, or childrens cryes be wonne,</l>
                  <l>That haue a ſtile beyond that Heauen is proud off,</l>
                  <l>Deriuing not from Art a makers Name,</l>
                  <l>But in deſtruction power, and terror ſhew:</l>
                  <l>To you I flye for ſuccour: you, whoſe dwellings</l>
                  <l>For torments are bely'de, muſt giue me eaſe;</l>
                  <l>Furies, lend me your fires, no they are here,</l>
                  <l>They muſt be other fires; materiall brands</l>
                  <l>That muſt the burning of my heat allay;</l>
                  <l>I bring to you no rude vnpractiz'd hands,</l>
                  <l>Already doe they reeke with mothers blood:</l>
                  <l>Tuſh that's but innocents, to what now I meane,</l>
                  <l>Alaſſe what euell could thoſe yeeres commit,</l>
                  <l>The world in this ſhall ſee my ſetled wit.
<stage>exeunt.</stage>
                  </l>
               </sp>
               <stage>Enter Seneca, Petronius.</stage>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Senec:</speaker>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Petroneus,</hi> you were at the <hi>Theater.</hi>
                  </l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Petron:</speaker>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Senica</hi> I was, and ſaw your kingly Pupyll</l>
                  <l>In Mynſtrils habit, ſtand before the Iudges,</l>
                  <l>Bowing thoſe hands, which the worlds Scepter hold,</l>
                  <l>And with great awe and reuerence beſeeching</l>
                  <l>Indifferent hearing, and an equall doome:</l>
                  <l>Then <hi>Caeſar</hi> doubted firſt to be oreborne,</l>
                  <l>And ſo he ioyn'd himſelfe to th'other ſingers,</l>
                  <l>And ſtraightly all other Lawes oth' Stage obſeru'd,</l>
                  <l>As not (though weary) to ſit downe, not ſpit;</l>
                  <pb facs="tcp:13479:17"/>
                  <l>Not wipe his ſweat off, but with what he wore;</l>
                  <l>Meane time how would he eye his aduerſaries,</l>
                  <l>How he would ſeeke t'haue all they did diſgrac't,</l>
                  <l>Traduce them priuily, openly raile at them:</l>
                  <l>And them he could not conquer ſo, he would</l>
                  <l>Corrupt with money, to doe worſe then he.</l>
                  <l>This was his ſinging part, his acting now.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Senec:</speaker>
                  <l>Nay euen end here, for I haue heard enough,</l>
                  <l>I haue a Fidler heard him, let me not</l>
                  <l>See him a Player, nor the fearefull voyce</l>
                  <l>Of <hi>Romes</hi> great Monarch, now command in Ieſt</l>
                  <l>Our Prince be <hi>Aegamemnon</hi> in a Play.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Petron:</speaker>
                  <l>Why <hi>Seneca,</hi> Tis better in Play</l>
                  <l>Be <hi>Aegamemnon,</hi> then himſelfe indeed;</l>
                  <l>How oft, with danger of the field beſet,</l>
                  <l>Or with home mutineys, would he vnbee</l>
                  <l>Himſelfe, or, ouer cruell alters weeping,</l>
                  <l>Wiſh, that with putting off a vizard, hee</l>
                  <l>Might his true inward ſorrow lay aſide;</l>
                  <l>The ſhowes of things are better then themſelues:</l>
                  <l>How doth it ſtirre this ayrye part of vs,</l>
                  <l>To heare our Poets tell imagin'd fights,</l>
                  <l>And the ſtrange blowes, that fained courage giues,</l>
                  <l>When I <hi>Achilles</hi> heare vpon the Stage</l>
                  <l>Speake Honour, and the greatneſſe of his ſoule;</l>
                  <l>Me thinkes I too, could on a <hi>Phrygian</hi> Speare</l>
                  <l>Runne boldly, and make tales for after times;</l>
                  <l>But when we come to act it in the deed,</l>
                  <l>Death mares this brauery, and the vgly feares</l>
                  <l>Of th'other world, ſit on the proudeſt browe,</l>
                  <l>And boaſting valour looſeth his red cheeke.</l>
               </sp>
               <stage>A Romane to them.</stage>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Rom:</speaker>
                  <l>Fire, fire, helpe, we burne.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>2. <hi>Rom:</hi>
                  </speaker>
                  <l>Fire, water, fire helpe fire.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Senec:</speaker>
                  <l>Fire, where?</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Petron:</speaker>
                  <l>Where? what fire.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Rom:</speaker>
                  <l>O round about, here, there, on euery ſide.</l>
                  <l>The girdling flame, doth with vnkind embraces</l>
                  <pb facs="tcp:13479:17"/>
                  <l>Compaſſe the Citie.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Petro:</speaker>
                  <l>How came this fire, by whom?</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Senec:</speaker>
                  <l>Waſt chance, or purpoſe?</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Petro:</speaker>
                  <l>Why is't not quencht?</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Rom:</speaker>
                  <l>Alas there are a many there with weapons,</l>
                  <l>Aod whether it be for pray, or by command,</l>
                  <l>They hinder: nay, they throwe on fire-brands.</l>
               </sp>
               <stage>Enter Antonius to them.</stage>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Anton:</speaker>
                  <l>The fire encreaſeth, and will not be ſtaid,</l>
                  <l>But like a ſtreame that tumbling from a hill,</l>
                  <l>Orewhelmes the fields, orewhelmes the hopefull toyle</l>
                  <l>Oth' husbandman, and headlong beares the woods;</l>
                  <l>The vnweeting Shepheard on a Rocke a farre,</l>
                  <l>Amazed, heares the fearefull noyſe; ſo here,</l>
                  <l>Danger and Terror ſtriue, which ſhall exceed,</l>
                  <l>Some cry, and yet are well, ſome are kild ſilent,</l>
                  <l>Some kindly runne to helpe their neighbours houſe,</l>
                  <l>The whileſt their own's a fire: ſome ſaue their goods,</l>
                  <l>And leaue their dearer pledges in the flame;</l>
                  <l>One takes his litle ſonnes with trembling hands,</l>
                  <l>Tother his houſe-Gods ſaues, which could not him,</l>
                  <l>All bann the doore, and with wiſhes kill</l>
                  <l>Their abſent murderer.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Petro:</speaker>
                  <l>What? are the <hi>Gaules</hi> returnd?</l>
                  <l>Doth <hi>Brenius</hi> brandiſh fire-brands againe.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Senec:</speaker>
                  <l>What can Heauen now vnto our ſuffrings adde.</l>
               </sp>
               <stage>Enter Another Romane to them.</stage>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Rom:</speaker>
                  <l>O all goes downe, <hi>Rome</hi> falleth from the Roofe,</l>
                  <l>The wind's aloft, the conquering flame turnes all</l>
                  <l>Into it ſelfe; Nor doe the Gods eſcape,</l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Pleidds</hi> burnes, <hi>Iupiter Stator</hi> burnes.</l>
                  <l>The Altar now is made a ſacrifice;</l>
                  <l>An <hi>Veſta</hi> mournes, to ſee her Virgin fires</l>
                  <l>Mingle with prophane aſhes.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Senec:</speaker>
                  <l>Heauen, haſt thou ſet this end, to <hi>Roman</hi> greatneſſe?</l>
                  <l>Were the worlds ſpoyles, for this, to <hi>Rome</hi> deuided,</l>
                  <l>To make but our fires bigger?</l>
                  <l>You Gods, whoſe anger made vs great, grant yet</l>
                  <pb facs="tcp:13479:18"/>
                  <l>Some change in miſery; We begge not now,</l>
                  <l>To haue our Conſull tread on <hi>Aſian</hi> Kings,</l>
                  <l>Or ſpurne the quiuerd <hi>Suſa</hi> at their feet;</l>
                  <l>This, we haue had before; we begg to liue,</l>
                  <l>At leaſt not thus to die; Let <hi>Cannos</hi> come,</l>
                  <l>Let <hi>Allius</hi> waters turne againe to blood.</l>
                  <l>To theſe will any miſeries be light.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Petro:</speaker>
                  <l>Why with falſe <hi>Auguries</hi> haue we bin deceiu'd?</l>
                  <l>Why was our Empire told vs, ſhould endure</l>
                  <l>With Sunne, and Moone, in time; in brightneſſe paſſe them,</l>
                  <l>And that our end ſhould be oth' world, and it.</l>
                  <l>What, can Celeſtiall Godheads double too?</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Senec:</speaker>
                  <l>O <hi>Rome,</hi> the enuy late,</l>
                  <l>But now, the pitie of the world thee gets,</l>
                  <l>The men of <hi>Choleos</hi> at thy ſufferings griue,</l>
                  <l>The ſhaggy dweller in the <hi>Scithian</hi> Rockes;</l>
                  <l>The moſt condemned to perpetuall ſnowe</l>
                  <l>That neuer wept at kindreds burials,</l>
                  <l>Suffers with thee, and feeles his heart to ſoften.</l>
                  <l>O, ſhould the <hi>Parthyan</hi> heare theſe miſeries,</l>
                  <l>He would, (his low and natiue hate apart)</l>
                  <l>Sit downe with vs. and lend an Enemies teare,</l>
                  <l>To grace the funerall fires of ending <hi>Rome.</hi>
                     <stage>Exeunt.</stage>
                  </l>
                  <stage>Soft Muſique, Enter Nero aboue alone with a Timbrell.</stage>
                  <l>I, now my <hi>Troy</hi> lookes beautious in her flames,</l>
                  <l>The <hi>Trirhnen</hi> Seas are bright with <hi>Roman</hi> fires,</l>
                  <l>Whileſt the amazed Marriner a farre,</l>
                  <l>Gazing on th'vnknowne light, wonders what starre</l>
                  <l>Heauen hath begot, to eaſe the aged Moone.</l>
                  <l>When <hi>Pirrhus,</hi> ſtryding ore the cynders, ſtood</l>
                  <l>On ground, where <hi>Troy</hi> late was; and with his Eye</l>
                  <l>Meaſur'd the height of what he had throwne downe,</l>
                  <l>A Citie, great in people, and in power:</l>
                  <l>Walls built with hands of Gods; He now forgiue</l>
                  <l>The ten yeares length, and thinkes his wounds well heald,</l>
                  <l>Bath'd in the blood of <hi>Priams</hi> fifty ſonnes.</l>
                  <l>Yet am not I appeas'd, I muſt ſee more</l>
                  <pb facs="tcp:13479:18"/>
                  <l>Then Towers, and Collomns tumble to the ground;</l>
                  <l>'Twas not the high built walles, and guiltleſſe ſtones</l>
                  <l>That <hi>Nero</hi> did prouoke; Themſelues muſt be the wood</l>
                  <l>To feed this fire, or quench it with their blood.</l>
               </sp>
               <stage>Enter a Woman with a burnt Child.</stage>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Wom:</speaker>
                  <l>O my deare Infant, O my Child, my Child;</l>
                  <l>Vnhappy comfort of my nine moneths paines;</l>
                  <l>And did I beare thee, onely for the fire,</l>
                  <l>Was I to that end made a Mother?</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Nero:</speaker>
                  <l>I, now begins the ſceane that I would haue.</l>
               </sp>
               <stage>Enter a Man bearing another dead.</stage>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Man:</speaker>
                  <l>O Father ſpeake yet; no, the mercileſſe blowe</l>
                  <l>Hath all bereft, ſpeech, motion, ſenſe, and life.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Wom:</speaker>
                  <l>O beauteous innocence, whitnes ill blackt,</l>
                  <l>How to be made a coale couldſt thou deſerue?</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Man:</speaker>
                  <l>O reuerend wrinckles, well becomming paleneſſe,</l>
                  <l>Why hath death now lifes colours giuen thee,</l>
                  <l>And mockes thee with the beauties of freſh youth?</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Wom:</speaker>
                  <l>Why wert thou giuen me, to be tane away</l>
                  <l>So ſoone, or could not Heauen tell how to puniſh</l>
                  <l>But firſt by bleſsing mee.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Man:</speaker>
                  <l>Why were thy yeares lengthned ſo long,</l>
                  <l>To be cut off vntimely?</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Nero:</speaker>
                  <l>Play on, play on, and fill the golden skies</l>
                  <l>With cryes, and pitie; with your blood; Mens Eyes.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Wom:</speaker>
                  <l>Where are thy flattering ſmiles, thy pretty kiſſes,</l>
                  <l>And armes, that wont to writhe about my necke?</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Man.</speaker>
                  <l>Where are thy Counſels, where their good example?</l>
                  <l>And that kind roughnes of a Fathers anger?</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Wom:</speaker>
                  <l>Whom haue I now to leaue my old age on?</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Man:</speaker>
                  <l>Who ſhall I now haue to ſet right my youth,
<stage>within.</stage>
                  </l>
                  <l>Gods if yee be not fled from Heauen helpe vs.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Nero:</speaker>
                  <l>I like this Muſique well; they like not mine:</l>
                  <l>Now in the teares of all men, let me ſing,
<stage>Cantat.</stage>
                  </l>
                  <l>And make it doubtfull to the Gods aboue;</l>
                  <l>Whether the Earth be pleas'd, or doe complaine.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Man:</speaker>
                  <l>But, may the man, that all this blood hath ſhed,</l>
                  <l>Neuer bequeath to th'earth, an old gray head;</l>
                  <pb facs="tcp:13479:19"/>
                  <l>Let him vntimely be cut off before,</l>
                  <l>And leaue a courſe like this all wounds and gore.</l>
                  <l>Be there no friend at hand, no ſtanders by,</l>
                  <l>In loue, or pittie mou'd, to cloſe that Eye.</l>
                  <l>O let him die the wiſh, and hate of all;</l>
                  <l>And not a teare to grace his Funerall.
<stage>exeunt.</stage>
                  </l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Wom:</speaker>
                  <l>Heauen, you will heare (that which the world doth ſcorne,)</l>
                  <l>The prayers of miſery, and ſoules forlorne:</l>
                  <l>Your anger waxeth by delaying ſtronger,</l>
                  <l>O now for mercy be diſpis'd no longer.</l>
                  <l>Let him, that makes ſo many Mothers childleſſe,</l>
                  <l>Make his vnhappy, in her fruitfulneſſe.</l>
                  <l>Let him no iſſue leaue to beare his name</l>
                  <l>Or ſome to right a Fathers wronged fame,</l>
                  <l>Our flames to quit; be righteous in your yre,</l>
                  <l>And when he dies, let him want funerall fire.
<stage>exeunt.</stage>
                  </l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Nero:</speaker>
                  <l>Let Heauen doe what it will this I haue done</l>
                  <l>Already: doe you feele my furies waight,</l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Rome</hi> is become a graue of her late greatnes;</l>
                  <l>Her clowdes of ſmoke haue tane away the day,</l>
                  <l>Her flames the night.</l>
                  <l>Now vnbeleeuing Eyes what craue you more?</l>
               </sp>
               <stage>Enter Neophilus to him.</stage>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Neoph:</speaker>
                  <l>O ſaue your ſelfe (my Lord) your Pallace burnes.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Nero:</speaker>
                  <l>My Pallace? how? what traiterous hand?</l>
               </sp>
               <stage>Enter Tigellinus to them.</stage>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Tigel:</speaker>
                  <l>O flie my Lord, and ſaue your ſelfe betimes,</l>
                  <l>The winde doth beate the fire vpon your houſe,</l>
                  <l>The eating flame deuoures your double gates,</l>
                  <l>Your pillars fall, your golden roofes doe melt,</l>
                  <l>Your antique Tables, and Greeke Imagery:</l>
                  <l>The fire beſets, and the ſmoake you ſee</l>
                  <l>Doth choake my ſpeech, O flie, and ſaue your life.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Nero:</speaker>
                  <l>Heauen, thou doſt ſtriue, I ſee, for victory.
<stage>exeunt.</stage>
                  </l>
               </sp>
               <stage>Enter Nimphideus ſolus.</stage>
               <sp>
                  <l>See how Fate workes vnto their purpos'd end;</l>
                  <l>And without all ſelfe-Induſtry will raiſe,</l>
                  <l>Whom they determine to make great and happy;</l>
                  <pb facs="tcp:13479:19"/>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Nero</hi> throwes downe himſelfe, I ſtirre him not,</l>
                  <l>He runnes vnto deſtruction ſtudies wayes</l>
                  <l>To compaſſed danger, and attaine the hate</l>
                  <l>Of all; Bee his owne wiſh is on his head:</l>
                  <l>Nor <hi>Rome</hi> with fire, mo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>e then reuenges burn<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>;</l>
                  <l>Let me ſtand ſtill, or lye, or ſl<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>epe, I <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>ſe.</l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Poppea</hi> ſome new fauour will ſeeke out</l>
                  <l>My wakings to ſalute, I cannot ſt<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>rre,</l>
                  <l>But meſſagers of new p<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>eferment meet me:</l>
                  <l>Now, ſhe hath made me Captaine of the Guard,</l>
                  <l>So well I beare me in theſe night Allar<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="3 letters">
                        <desc>•••</desc>
                     </gap>,</l>
                  <l>That ſhe imagin'd I was made for Armes;</l>
                  <l>I now command the Souldier, he the Citie,</l>
                  <l>If any chance doe turne the Prince aſide,</l>
                  <l>(As many hatreds, miſchiefes threaten him,)</l>
                  <l>Ours is his wife, his ſeat and throwne is ours.</l>
                  <l>He's next in right that hath the ſtrongeſt powers.
<stage>exit.</stage>
                  </l>
               </sp>
               <stage>Enter Sceuinus, Melechus.</stage>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Sceui:</speaker>
                  <l>O <hi>Troy,</hi> and O yee ſoules of our Forefathers,</l>
                  <l>Which in your countreys fires were offred vp,</l>
                  <l>How neere your Nephewes, to your fo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>tunes come:</l>
                  <l>Yet they were <hi>Grecian</hi> hands began your flame;</l>
                  <l>But that our Temples, and our houſes ſmoake,</l>
                  <l>Our Marble buildings turne to be our Tombes,</l>
                  <l>Burnt bones and ſpurnt at Cou<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ſes fill the ſtreets,</l>
                  <l>Not <hi>Pirrhus,</hi> nor thou <hi>Hanniball,</hi> art Autho<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>,</l>
                  <l>Sad <hi>Rome</hi> is ruin'd by a <hi>Romane</hi> hand.</l>
                  <l>But if to <hi>Neroes</hi> end, this onely way</l>
                  <l>Heauens Iuſtice hath choſe out, and peoples loue</l>
                  <l>Could not but by this feebling ills be mou'd;</l>
                  <l>We doe not then at all complaine our harmes,</l>
                  <l>On this condition pleaſe vs, let vs die,</l>
                  <l>And cloy the <hi>Parthian,</hi> with reuenge and pitie.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Melic:</speaker>
                  <l>My Maſter hath ſeald vp his Teſtament,</l>
                  <l>Thoſe bond-men which he liketh beſt ſet free,</l>
                  <l>Giuen money, and more liberally then he vs'd:</l>
                  <l>And now, as if a farewell to the world</l>
                  <l>Were meant, A ſumpteous banquet hath he made;</l>
                  <pb facs="tcp:13479:20"/>
                  <l>Yet not with countenance that feaſters vſe,</l>
                  <l>But che eres his friends the whileſt himſelfe lookes ſad.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Scen:</speaker>
                  <l>I haue from fortunes Temple tane this ſword,</l>
                  <l>May it be fortunate, and now at leaſt</l>
                  <l>Since it could not preuent, puniſh the Euill;</l>
                  <l>To <hi>Rome</hi> it had bin better done before,</l>
                  <l>But though leſſe helping now, they'le praiſe it more.</l>
                  <l>Great Soueraigne of all mortall actions</l>
                  <l>Whom onely wretched men, and Poets blame,</l>
                  <l>Speed thou the weapon, which I haue from thee.</l>
                  <l>'Twas not amidſt thy Temple Monuments</l>
                  <l>In vaine repos'd, ſomewhat I know 't hath done:</l>
                  <l>O with new honours let it be laid vp:</l>
                  <l>Strike bouldly, arme ſo many powerfull prayers</l>
                  <l>Of dead, and liuing houer ouer thee.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Melic:</speaker>
                  <l>And though ſometimes, with talke impertineur,</l>
                  <l>And idle fances, he would faine a mirth;</l>
                  <l>Yet is it eaſie ſeene, ſomewhat is here</l>
                  <l>The which, he dares not let his face make ſhew of.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Sceuin:</speaker>
                  <l>Long want of loſſe hath made it dull, and blunt:</l>
                  <l>See, <hi>Melichus,</hi> this weapon better edg'd.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Melic:</speaker>
                  <l>Sharpning of ſwords, when muſt wee then haue blowes,</l>
                  <l>Or meanes my Maſter, <hi>Cato</hi>-like, to exempt</l>
                  <l>Himſelfe from power of Fates, and cloy'd with life,</l>
                  <l>Giue the Gods backe their vnregarded gift,</l>
                  <l>But he hath neither <hi>Catoes</hi> minde, nor cauſe;</l>
                  <l>A man giuen ore to pleaſures, and ſoft eaſe:</l>
                  <l>Which makes me ſtill to doubt, how in affaires</l>
                  <l>Of Princes he dares meddle, or deſires?</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Sceuin:</speaker>
                  <l>We ſhall haue blowes on both ſides, <hi>Melichus;</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>Prouide me ſtore of cloathes to bind vp wounds;</l>
                  <l>What an't be heart, for heart, Death is the worſt;</l>
                  <l>The Gods ſure keepe it, hide from vs that liue</l>
                  <l>How ſweet death is, becauſe we ſhould goe on</l>
                  <l>And be their bailes: There are about the houſe</l>
                  <l>Some ſtones that will ſtanch blood, ſee them ſet vp:</l>
                  <l>This world I ſee hath no felicitie,</l>
                  <l>Ile trie the other.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <pb facs="tcp:13479:20"/>
                  <speaker>Melic:</speaker>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Neroes</hi> life is ſoft,</l>
                  <l>The ſword's prepar'd againſt anothers breaſt,</l>
                  <l>The helpe for his; it can be no priuate foe,</l>
                  <l>For then 'twere beſt to make it knowne, and call</l>
                  <l>His troupes of bond, and freed men to his aide:</l>
                  <l>Beſides his Counſellors, <hi>Seneca,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>And <hi>Lucan,</hi> are no Managers of quarrels.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Sceuin:</speaker>
                  <l>Me thinkes, I ſee him ſtruggling on the ground,</l>
                  <l>Heare his vnmanly outcries, and loſt prayers</l>
                  <l>Made to the Gods, which turne their heads away.</l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Nero,</hi> this day muſt end the worlds deſi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>es,</l>
                  <l>And head-long ſend thee, to vnquenched fires.
<stage>exit.</stage>
                  </l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Melic:</speaker>
                  <l>Why doe I further idly ſtand debating,</l>
                  <l>My proofes are but too many, and too pregnant,</l>
                  <l>And Princes Eares ſtill to ſuſpitions open:</l>
                  <l>Who euer, being but accus'd, was quit;</l>
                  <l>For States are wiſe, and cut of ylls that may be;</l>
                  <l>Meane men muſt die, that t'other may ſleepe ſound,</l>
                  <l>Chiefely, that rule, whoſe weaknes apt to feares,</l>
                  <l>And bad deſerts of all men, makes them know</l>
                  <l>There's none but is in heart, what hee's accus'd.
<stage>exit.</stage>
                  </l>
               </sp>
               <trailer>Finis Actus Tertij.</trailer>
            </div>
            <div n="4" type="act">
               <head>Actus Quartus.</head>
               <stage>Enter Nero, Poppaea, Nimphidius, Tigellinus, Neophitus, and Epaphroditus.</stage>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Nero:</speaker>
                  <l>THis kiſſe ſweet loue, Ile force from thee and this,</l>
                  <l>And of ſuch ſpoiles, and victories be prowder,</l>
                  <l>Then if I had the fierce <hi>Panonian,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>Or gray-eyd <hi>German</hi> ten times ouercome.</l>
                  <l>Let <hi>Iulius</hi> goe, and fight at end oth' world,</l>
                  <l>And conquer from the wilde inhabitants</l>
                  <l>Their cold, and pouerty; whileſt <hi>Nero,</hi> here,</l>
                  <l>Makes other warres, war<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>es where the conquerd gaines,</l>
                  <pb facs="tcp:13479:21"/>
                  <l>Where to ore-come, is to be priſoner.</l>
                  <l>O willingly, I giue my freedome vp;</l>
                  <l>And put on my owne chaines;</l>
                  <l>And am in loue with my captiuitie;</l>
                  <l>Such <hi>Venus</hi> is, when on the ſand ſhore</l>
                  <l>Of <hi>Xanthus</hi> or on <hi>Idas</hi> ple<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>n<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> greene</l>
                  <l>She leades the da<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>c<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>; Her, the Nimphes all are we,</l>
                  <l>And ſmyling graces doe accompany.</l>
                  <l>If <hi>Bacchus</hi> could his ſtragling Mynion</l>
                  <l>Grace, with a glorious wreath of ſhining S<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>arres;</l>
                  <l>Why ſhould not Heauen my <hi>Poppaea</hi> Crow<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>e?</l>
                  <l>The Northerne teeme ſhall moue into a round;</l>
                  <l>New conſtellations riſe, to honour thee;</l>
                  <l>The Earth ſhall wone thy fauours, and the Sea</l>
                  <l>Lay his rich ſhells, and treaſure at thy feete.</l>
                  <l>For thee, <hi>Hidaſpis</hi> ſhall throw vp his gold,</l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Pauchaia</hi> breath the rich delightfull ſmells,</l>
                  <l>The <hi>Seres,</hi> and the feather'd man of <hi>Inde</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>Shall their fine arts, and curious labours bring:</l>
                  <l>And where the Sunn's not knowne, <hi>Poppaeas</hi> name</l>
                  <l>Shall midſt their feaſts, and barbarous pompe be ſung.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Poppae:</speaker>
                  <l>I, now I am worthy to be Queene oth' world,</l>
                  <l>Fairer then <hi>
                        <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>enus,</hi> or the <hi>Bacchus</hi> loue:</l>
                  <l>But you'le anone, vnto your cutt-boy, <hi>S porus,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>Your new made woman; to whom, now I heare</l>
                  <l>You are wed led too.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Nero:</speaker>
                  <l>I wedded?</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Poppae:</speaker>
                  <l>I, you wedded;</l>
                  <l>Did you not heare the words oth' <hi>Auſpyces,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>Was not the boy in bride-like garm<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>n<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>s dreſt,</l>
                  <l>Marriage bookes ſeald, as 'twere for yſſue, to</l>
                  <l>Be had betweene you, ſolemne feaſts prepar'd;</l>
                  <l>While all the Court, with <hi>God-giue you Ioy,</hi> ſounds.</l>
                  <l>It had bin good <hi>Domitius</hi> your Father</l>
                  <l>Had nere had other wife:</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Nero:</speaker>
                  <l>Your froward foole, y'are ſtill ſo bitter, whoſe that?</l>
               </sp>
               <stage>Enter Melichus to them.</stage>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Nimph:</speaker>
                  <l>One that it ſeemes, my Lord, doth come in haſt.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <pb facs="tcp:13479:21"/>
                  <speaker>Nero:</speaker>
                  <l>Yet in his face he ſends his tale before him,</l>
                  <l>Bad newes thou telleſt.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Melic:</speaker>
                  <l>'Tis bad I tell, but good that I can tell it,</l>
                  <l>Therefore your Maieſtie will pardon me,</l>
                  <l>If I offend your eares to ſaue your life.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Nero:</speaker>
                  <l>Why, is my life indangerd?</l>
                  <l>How ends this circumſtance, thou wrackſt my thoughts.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Meli:</speaker>
                  <l>My Lord your life is conſpir'd againſt,</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Nero:</speaker>
                  <l>By whom?</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Meli;</speaker>
                  <l>I muſt be of the world excus'd in this,</l>
                  <l>If the great dutie to your Maieſtie:</l>
                  <l>Makes me all other leſſer to neglect.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Nero:</speaker>
                  <l>Th'art a tedious fellow, ſpeake, by whom?</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Melic:</speaker>
                  <l>By my Maſter.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Nero;</speaker>
                  <l>Who's thy Maſter?</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Meli:</speaker>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Sceuinus.</hi>
                  </l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Poppae:</speaker>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Sceuinus,</hi> why ſhould he conſpire?</l>
                  <l>Vnleſſe he thinke, that likeneſſe in conditions</l>
                  <l>May make him too, worthy oth' Empire thought.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Nero:</speaker>
                  <l>Who are elſe in it?</l>
                  <l>I thinke <hi>Natalis, Subius, Flauius,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Lucan, Seneca,</hi> and <hi>Lucius Piſo,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Aſper,</hi> and <hi>Quintilianus.</hi>
                  </l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Nero:</speaker>
                  <l>Ha done,</l>
                  <l>Thou'ilt reckon all <hi>Rome</hi> anone and ſo thou maiſt,</l>
                  <l>Th'are villaines all, Ile not truſt one of them;</l>
                  <l>O that the <hi>Romanes</hi> had but all one n<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>cke.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Poppae:</speaker>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Piſoes</hi> ſhe creeping into mens affections.</l>
                  <l>And popular arts, haue giuen long cauſe of doubt,</l>
                  <l>And th'others late obſeru'd diſcontents</l>
                  <l>Riſen from miſinterpre<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ed diſgraces,</l>
                  <l>May make vs credit this rel tion.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Nero:</speaker>
                  <l>Where are they? come they not vpon vs yet?</l>
                  <l>See the Guard doubted, ſee the Gates ſhut vp.</l>
                  <l>Why, the'yle ſurpriſe vs in our Court anon.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Meli:</speaker>
                  <l>Not ſo my Lord, they are at <hi>Piſoes</hi> houſe,</l>
                  <l>And thinke themſelues, yet ſafe, and vndiſcry'd.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Nero:</speaker>
                  <l>Lets thither then,</l>
                  <pb facs="tcp:13479:22"/>
                  <l>And take them in this falſe ſecurity;</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Tigel:</speaker>
                  <l>'Twere better firſt publiſh them traytors.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Nymph:</speaker>
                  <l>That were to make them ſo,</l>
                  <l>And force them all vpon their Enemies;</l>
                  <l>Now, without ſtirre, or hazard theyle be tane,</l>
                  <l>And boldly tryall dare, and law demaund;</l>
                  <l>Beſides, this accuſation may be forg'd</l>
                  <l>By mallice or miſtaking.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Poppe:</speaker>
                  <l>What likes you, doe <hi>Nimphidius,</hi> out of hand,</l>
                  <l>Two wayes diſtract, when either would preuaile;</l>
                  <l>If they ſuſpecting but this fellowes abſence,</l>
                  <l>Should try the Citie, and attempt their friends,</l>
                  <l>How dangerous might <hi>Piſoes</hi> fauour be.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Nimph:</speaker>
                  <l>I to himſelfe would make the matter cleare,</l>
                  <l>Which now vpon one ſeruants credit ſtands:</l>
                  <l>The Cities fauour keepes within the bonds</l>
                  <l>Of profit they'le loue none, to hurt themſelues;</l>
                  <l>Honour, and friendſhip they heare others name,</l>
                  <l>Themſelues doe neither feele, nor know the ſame;</l>
                  <l>To put them yet, (though needleſſe) in ſome feare,</l>
                  <l>Weele keepe their ſtreets with armed companies:</l>
                  <l>Then if they ſtirre, they ſee their wiues, and houſes</l>
                  <l>Prepar'd a pray to th' greedy Souldier.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Poppe:</speaker>
                  <l>Let vs be quicke then, you, to <hi>Piſoes</hi> houſe,</l>
                  <l>While I, and <hi>Tigellinus</hi> further ſift</l>
                  <l>This fellowes knowledge.
<stage>Ex. omnes Pretor Nero.</stage>
                  </l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Nero:</speaker>
                  <l>Looke to the gates, and walles oth' Citie, looke</l>
                  <l>The riuer be well kept, haue watches ſet</l>
                  <l>In euery paſſage, and in euery way;</l>
                  <l>But who ſhall watch theſe watches, what if they</l>
                  <l>Begin, and play the Traitors firſt? O where ſhall I</l>
                  <l>Seeke faith, or them that I may wiſely truſt?</l>
                  <l>The Citie fauours the conſpirators,</l>
                  <l>The Senate, in diſgrace, and feate hath liu'd;</l>
                  <l>The Ca<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>p, wh<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> moſt are ſouldiers that be named</l>
                  <l>Beſides, he knowes not all; and like a foole</l>
                  <l>I interrupted him, elſe had he named</l>
                  <l>Thoſe that ſtood by me; O ſecuritie.</l>
                  <pb facs="tcp:13479:22"/>
                  <l>Which we ſo much ſeeke after, yet art ſtill</l>
                  <l>To Courts a ſtranger, and doſt rather chooſe,</l>
                  <l>The ſmoaky reedes, and ſedgy cottages,</l>
                  <l>Then the proud roofes, and wanton coſt of Kings.</l>
                  <l>O ſweet diſpiſed ioyes of pouerty,</l>
                  <l>A happines vnknowne vnto the Gods:</l>
                  <l>Would I had rather in poore <hi>Gallij</hi> bin,</l>
                  <l>Or <hi>Vlubrae,</hi> a ragged Magiſtrate,</l>
                  <l>Sat as a Iudge of meaſures, and of corne,</l>
                  <l>Then the adored Monarke of the world.</l>
                  <l>Mother, thou didſt deſeruedly in this,</l>
                  <l>That from a priuate, and ſure ſtate, didſt raiſe</l>
                  <l>My fortunes, to this ſlippery hill of greatneſſe;</l>
                  <l>Where I can neither ſtand, nor fall with life.
<stage>Exit.</stage>
                  </l>
               </sp>
               <stage>Enter Piſo, Lucan, Sceuinus, Flauius.</stage>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Flau:</speaker>
                  <l>But ſince we are diſcouer'd, what remaines?</l>
                  <l>But put our liues vpon our hands, theſe ſwords</l>
                  <l>Shall try vs Traitors, or true Citizens.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Sceui:</speaker>
                  <l>And what ſhould make this hazard doubt ſucceſſe,</l>
                  <l>Stout men are oft with ſudden onſets danted,</l>
                  <l>What ſhall this Stage-player be?</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Luc:</speaker>
                  <l>It is not now,</l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Auguſtus</hi> grauitie, nor <hi>Tiberius</hi> craft,</l>
                  <l>But <hi>Tigellinus,</hi> and <hi>Criſogorus</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>Eunucke<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>, and women that we goe againſt.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Sceui:</speaker>
                  <l>This for thy owne ſake, this for ours we begg,</l>
                  <l>That thou wilt ſuffer him to be orecome;</l>
                  <l>Why ſhouldſt thou keepe ſo many vowed ſwords</l>
                  <l>From ſuch a hated throate?</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Flaui:</speaker>
                  <l>Or ſhall we feare,</l>
                  <l>To truſt vnto the Gods ſo good a cauſe.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Luca:</speaker>
                  <l>By this we may, our ſelues Heauens fauour promiſe,</l>
                  <l>Becauſe all nobleneſſe, and worth on earth</l>
                  <l>We ſee's on our ſide; Here the <hi>Faby's</hi> ſonne,</l>
                  <l>Here the <hi>Coruini</hi> are, and take that part;</l>
                  <l>There noble Fathers would, if now they liu'd;</l>
                  <l>There's not a ſoule that claimes Nobilitie</l>
                  <l>Either by his, or his fore-fathers merit,</l>
                  <pb facs="tcp:13479:23"/>
                  <l>But is with vs; with vs the gallant youth</l>
                  <l>Whom paſſed dangers, or hote bloud makes bould:</l>
                  <l>Staid men ſuſpect their wiſedome, or their faith,</l>
                  <l>To whom our counſels we haue not reueald.</l>
                  <l>And while (our party ſeeking to diſgrace)</l>
                  <l>They traitors call vs, Each man treaſon praiſeth,</l>
                  <l>And hateth faith, when <hi>Piſo</hi> is a traitor.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Sceui:</speaker>
                  <l>And at aduenturer what by ſtoutneſſe can</l>
                  <l>Befall vs worſe, then will by cowardiſe?</l>
                  <l>If both the people, and the ſouldier failde vs,</l>
                  <l>Yet ſhall we die at leaſt worthy our ſelues,</l>
                  <l>Worthy our anceſtors: <hi>O Piſo</hi> thinke,</l>
                  <l>Thinke on that day, when in the <hi>Parthian</hi> fields</l>
                  <l>Thou cryedſt to th' flying Legions to turne,</l>
                  <l>And looke Death in the face; he was not grim,</l>
                  <l>But faire and louely, when he came in armes.</l>
                  <l>O why, there di'd we not on <hi>Syrian</hi> ſwords?</l>
                  <l>Were we reſeru'd to priſons, and to chaines.</l>
                  <l>Behold the Galley-aſſes in euery ſtreet,</l>
                  <l>And euen now they come to clap on yrons;</l>
                  <l>Muſt <hi>Piſoes</hi> head be ſhewed vpon a pole?</l>
                  <l>Thoſe members torne; rather then <hi>Roman</hi>-like,</l>
                  <l>And <hi>Piſo</hi>-like, with weapons in our hands</l>
                  <l>Fighting, in throng of enemies to die:</l>
                  <l>And that it ſhall not be a ciuill warre</l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Nero</hi> preuents, whoſe cruelty hath left</l>
                  <l>Few Citizens; we are not Romans now,</l>
                  <l>But Moores, and Iewes, and vtmoſt Spaniards,</l>
                  <l>And <hi>Aſiaes</hi> refuge that doe fill the Citie.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Piſo:</speaker>
                  <l>Part of vs are already tak'n, the reſt</l>
                  <l>Amaz'd, and ſeeking holes; Our hidden ends</l>
                  <l>You ſee laid open, Court, and Citie arm'd,</l>
                  <l>And for feare ioyning to the part they feare.</l>
                  <l>Why ſhould we moue deſperate, and hopeleſſe armes</l>
                  <l>And vainely ſpill that noble bloud, that ſhould</l>
                  <l>Chriſtall <hi>Rubes,</hi> and the <hi>Median</hi> fields,</l>
                  <l>Not <hi>Tiber</hi> colour: And the more your ſhow be</l>
                  <l>Your loues, and readineſſe to looſe your liues,</l>
                  <pb facs="tcp:13479:23"/>
                  <l>The lother I am to aduenture them.</l>
                  <l>Yet am I proud, you would for me haue dy'd,</l>
                  <l>But liue, and keepe your ſelues to worthier ends;</l>
                  <l>No Mother but my owne ſhall weepe my death,</l>
                  <l>Nor will <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> make by ouerthrowing vs,</l>
                  <l>Heauen guiltie of more faults, yet from the hopes,</l>
                  <l>Your owne go<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>d wiſhes, rather then the thing</l>
                  <l>Doe make <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ou ſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>, this comfort I receiue</l>
                  <l>Of death vn<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>orſt. O friends, I would not die</l>
                  <l>When I can liue no longer; 'Tis my glory,</l>
                  <l>That free, and willing I giue vp this breath,</l>
                  <l>Leauing ſuch courages as you<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>s vntri'd.</l>
                  <l>But to belong in talke of dying, would</l>
                  <l>Shew a relenting, and a doubtfull mi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>d:</l>
                  <l>By this you ſhall my quiet though<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>s intend;</l>
                  <l>I blame nor Earth, nor H<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>auen for my end.
<stage>He dies.</stage>
                  </l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Lucan:</speaker>
                  <l>O that this noble courage had bin ſhewne,</l>
                  <l>Rather on enemies breaſts, then on thy owne.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Sceui:</speaker>
                  <l>But ſacred, and inviolate be thy will,</l>
                  <l>And let it lead, and I teach vs;</l>
                  <l>This ſword I could more willingly haue thruſt</l>
                  <l>Through <hi>Neroes</hi> breaſt; That, fortune deni'd me,</l>
                  <l>It now ſhall through <hi>Sceuinus.</hi>
                  </l>
                  <stage>Enter Tigellinus ſolus.</stage>
                  <l>What multitudes of villaines are here gotten</l>
                  <l>In a conſpiracy; which <hi>Hydra</hi> like,</l>
                  <l>Still in the cutting off, increaſeth more.</l>
                  <l>The more we take, the more are ſtill appeach,</l>
                  <l>And euery man brings in new company.</l>
                  <l>I wonder what we ſhall doe with them all,</l>
                  <l>The priſons cannot hold more then they haue,</l>
                  <l>The Iayles are full, the holes with Gallants ſtincke,</l>
                  <l>Strawe and gold lace together liue I thinke:</l>
                  <l>'Twere beſt euen ſhut the gates oth' Citie vp,</l>
                  <l>And make it all one Iayle; for, this I am ſure,</l>
                  <l>There's not an honeſt man within the walles:</l>
                  <l>And though the guilty doth exceed the free;</l>
                  <l>Yet through a baſe, and fatall cowardiſe,</l>
                  <pb facs="tcp:13479:24"/>
                  <l>They all aſsiſt, in taking one another,</l>
                  <l>And by their owne hands are to priſon led.</l>
                  <l>There's no condition, nor degree of men,</l>
                  <l>But here are met; Men of the ſword, and gowne,</l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Plebeans, Senators,</hi> and women too,</l>
                  <l>La<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ies that might haue ſlaine him with their Eye,</l>
                  <l>Would vſe their hands, Philoſophers,</l>
                  <l>And Polititians; Polititians?</l>
                  <l>Their plot was laid too ſhort; Poets would now,</l>
                  <l>Not onely write, but be the arguments</l>
                  <l>Of Tragedies: The Emperour's much pleas'd:</l>
                  <l>But ſome haue named <hi>Seneca,</hi> and I</l>
                  <l>Will haue <hi>Petroneus,</hi> one promiſe of pardon,</l>
                  <l>Or feare of torture, will accuſers find.
<stage>exit.</stage>
                  </l>
               </sp>
               <stage>Enter Nimphidius, Lucan, Sceninus, with a guard.</stage>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Nimph:</speaker>
                  <l>Though <hi>Piſoes</hi> ſuddenneſſe, and guilty hand</l>
                  <l>Preuented hath the death he ſhould haue had;</l>
                  <l>Yet you abide it muſt.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Luca:</speaker>
                  <l>O may the earth lye lightly on his Courſe,</l>
                  <l>Sprinckle his aſhes with your flowers and teares,</l>
                  <l>The loue and dainties of Mankind is gone.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Sceui:</speaker>
                  <l>What onely now we can, we'le follow thee</l>
                  <l>That way thou lead'ſt, and waite on thee in death,</l>
                  <l>Which we had done, had not theſe hindred vs.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Nimph:</speaker>
                  <l>Nay, other ends your grieuous crimes awaite,</l>
                  <l>Ends which the law and your deſerts exact.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Sceui:</speaker>
                  <l>What haue we deſerued?</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Nimph:</speaker>
                  <l>That puniſhment that traitors vnto Princes,</l>
                  <l>And enemies to the State they liue in merit.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Sceuin:</speaker>
                  <l>If by the State, this gouernment you meane,</l>
                  <l>I iuſtly am an enemy vnto it.</l>
                  <l>That's but to <hi>Nero,</hi> you, <hi>and Tigellinus:</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>That glorious world, that euen beguiles the wiſe,</l>
                  <l>Being lookt into, includes but three, or foure.</l>
                  <l>Corrupted men, which were they all remou'd,</l>
                  <l>'Twould for the common State much better be.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <pb facs="tcp:13479:24"/>
                  <speaker>Nimph:</speaker>
                  <l>Why, what can you ith' gouerment miſlike?</l>
                  <l>Vnleſſe it grieue you, that the world's in peace,</l>
                  <l>Or that our armes conquer without blood.</l>
                  <l>Hath not his power with forraine viſitations,</l>
                  <l>And ſtrangers honour more acknowldg'd bin,</l>
                  <l>Then any was afore him? Hath not hee</l>
                  <l>Diſpos'd of frontier kingdomes, with ſucceſſe,</l>
                  <l>Giuen away Crownes, whom he ſet vp, preuailing?</l>
                  <l>The riuall ſeat of the <hi>Arſacidae,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>That thought their brightneſſe equall vnto ours,</l>
                  <l>Is't crown'd by him by him, doth raigne?</l>
                  <l>If we haue any warre, it's beyond <hi>Rheme,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>And <hi>Euphrates,</hi> and ſuch whoſe different chances</l>
                  <l>Haue rather ſeru'd for pleaſure, and diſcourſe,</l>
                  <l>Then troubled vs; At home the Citie hath</l>
                  <l>Increaſt in wealth, with building bin adorn'd;</l>
                  <l>The arts haue flouriſht, and the Muſes ſung,</l>
                  <l>And that, his Iuſtice, and well tempred raigne,</l>
                  <l>Hath the beſt Iudges pleas'd, the powers diuine;</l>
                  <l>Their bleſsings, and ſo long proſperitie</l>
                  <l>Of th' Empire vnder him, enough declare.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Sceui:</speaker>
                  <l>You freed the State from warres abroad, but 'twas</l>
                  <l>To ſpoile at home more ſafely, and diuert</l>
                  <l>The <hi>Parthian</hi> enmitie on vs, and yet,</l>
                  <l>The glory rather, and the ſpoyles of warre</l>
                  <l>Haue wanting bin, the loſſe, and charge we haue.</l>
                  <l>Your peace is full of cruelty, and wrong,</l>
                  <l>Lawes taught to ſpeake to preſent purpoſes,</l>
                  <l>Wealth, and faire houſes dangerous faults become,</l>
                  <l>Much blood ith' Citie, and no common deaths,</l>
                  <l>But Gentlemen, and Conſulary houſes:</l>
                  <l>On <hi>Caeſars</hi> owne houſe looke, hath that bin free?</l>
                  <l>Hath he not ſhed the blood he calls diuine?</l>
                  <l>Hath not that neerenes which ſhould loue beget</l>
                  <l>Alwayes on him, bin cauſe of hate, and feare;</l>
                  <l>Vertue, and power ſuſpected, and kept downe:</l>
                  <l>They whoſe great anceſtors this Empire made,</l>
                  <pb facs="tcp:13479:25"/>
                  <l>Diſtruſted in the gouernment thereof;</l>
                  <l>A happy ſtate, where <hi>Decius</hi> is a traytor,</l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Narciſſus</hi> true, nor onely waſt vnſafe</l>
                  <l>T'offend the Prince, his freed men worſe were feard,</l>
                  <l>whoſe wrongs with ſuch inſulting pride were heard,</l>
                  <l>That euen the faultie it made innocent:</l>
                  <l>If we complain'd, that was it ſelfe a crime,</l>
                  <l>I, though it were to Caeſars benefit;</l>
                  <l>Our writings pry'd into, falce guiltines</l>
                  <l>(Thinking each taxing pointed out it ſelfe)</l>
                  <l>Our priuate whiſperings liſtned after; nay,</l>
                  <l>Our thoughts were forced out of vs, and puniſht:</l>
                  <l>And had it bin in you, to haue taken away</l>
                  <l>Our vnderſtanding, as you did our ſpeech,</l>
                  <l>You would haue made vs thought this honeſt too?</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Nimph:</speaker>
                  <l>Can malice narrow eyes,</l>
                  <l>See anything yet more it can traduce.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Sceui:</speaker>
                  <l>His long continued taxes I forbeare,</l>
                  <l>In which he chiefely ſhowed him to be Prince,</l>
                  <l>His robbing Alters, ſale of Holy things,</l>
                  <l>The Antique Goblets of adored ruſt,</l>
                  <l>And ſacred gifts of Kings, and people ſold.</l>
                  <l>Nor was the ſpoile more odious, then the vſe,</l>
                  <l>They were imployd on, ſpent on ſhame, and luſt</l>
                  <l>Which ſtill haue bin ſo endleſſe in their change,</l>
                  <l>And made vs know a diuers ſeruitude.</l>
                  <l>But that he hath bin ſuffered ſo long,</l>
                  <l>And proſpered, as you ſay: for that, to thee</l>
                  <l>O Heauen, I turne my ſelfe, and cry; No God</l>
                  <l>Hath care of vs, yet haue we our reuenge,</l>
                  <l>As much as Earth may be reueng'd on Heauen;</l>
                  <l>Their diuine honour <hi>Nero</hi> ſhall vſurpe,</l>
                  <l>And prayers, and feaſts, and adoration haue,</l>
                  <l>As well as <hi>Iupiter.</hi>
                  </l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Nimph:</speaker>
                  <l>Away blaſpheming tongue</l>
                  <l>Be euer ſilent for thy bitterneſſe,</l>
               </sp>
               <stage>Exeunt.</stage>
               <stage>
                  <pb facs="tcp:13479:25"/>
                  <hi>Enter Nero, Poppaea, Tigellinus, Flauius, Neophilus, Epaphroditus, and a yong man.</hi>
               </stage>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Nero:</speaker>
                  <l>What could cauſe thee,</l>
                  <l>Forgetfull of my benefits, and thy oath,</l>
                  <l>To ſeeke my life.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Plaui:</speaker>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Nero,</hi> I hated thee;</l>
                  <l>Nor was there any of thy ſouldiers</l>
                  <l>More faithfull, while thou faith deſeru'dſt then I,</l>
                  <l>Together did I leaue to be a ſubiect,</l>
                  <l>And thou a Prince, Caeſar was now become</l>
                  <l>A player on the Stage, a Waggoner,</l>
                  <l>A burner of our houſes, and of vs,</l>
                  <l>A Paracide of Wife, and Mother.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Tigel:</speaker>
                  <l>Villaine doſt know where, &amp; of whom thou ſpeakſt?</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Nero:</speaker>
                  <l>Haue you but one death for him, let it bee</l>
                  <l>A feeling one <hi>(Tigellinus)</hi> bee't</l>
                  <l>Thy charge, and let me ſee thee witty in't.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Tigell:</speaker>
                  <l>Come ſirrah</l>
                  <l>Weele ſee how ſtoutly you'le ſtretch out your necke.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Flaui:</speaker>
                  <l>Wold thou durſt ſtrike as ſtoutly,
<stage>Ex. Tig. &amp; Flau:</stage>
                  </l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Nero:</speaker>
                  <l>And what's hee th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>re?</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Epaph:</speaker>
                  <l>One that in whiſpering oreheard</l>
                  <l>What pitie 'twas, my Lord, that <hi>Piſo</hi> died.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Nero:</speaker>
                  <l>And why waſt pitie ſirrah, <hi>Piſo</hi> died?</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Yong:</speaker>
                  <l>My Lord 'twas pitie he deſeru'd to die.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Poppae:</speaker>
                  <l>How much this youth, my <hi>Otho</hi> doth reſemble;</l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Otho,</hi> my firſt, my beſt loue, who is now</l>
                  <l>(Vnder pretext of gouerning) exyl'd</l>
                  <l>To <hi>Lucitania,</hi> honourably baniſht.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Nero:</speaker>
                  <l>Well, if you be ſo paſsionate,</l>
                  <l>Ile make you ſpend your pitie on your Prince,</l>
                  <l>And good men, not on traytors.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Yong:</speaker>
                  <l>The Gods forbid my Prince ſhould pitie need.</l>
                  <l>Somewhat, the ſad remembrance did me ſtirre</l>
                  <pb facs="tcp:13479:26"/>
                  <l>Oth fraile and weake condition of our kind,</l>
                  <l>Somewhat his greatneſſe; then whom yeſterday,</l>
                  <l>The world, but <hi>Caeſar</hi> could ſhew nothing higher;</l>
                  <l>Beſides, ſome vertues, and ſome worth he had,</l>
                  <l>That might excuſe my pitie, to an end</l>
                  <l>So cruell, and vnripe.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Poppae:</speaker>
                  <l>I know not how this ſtranger moues my mind,</l>
                  <l>His face me thinkes is not like other mens,</l>
                  <l>Nor doe they ſpeake thus; Oh, his words inuade</l>
                  <l>My weakned ſenſes, and ouercome my heart.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Nero:</speaker>
                  <l>Your pitie ſhewes, your fauour and your will</l>
                  <l>Which ſide you are inclinde too, had your power,</l>
                  <l>You can but pitie, elſe ſhould <hi>Caeſar</hi> feare,</l>
                  <l>Your ill affection then ſhall puniſht bee.</l>
                  <l>Take him to execution, he ſhall die,</l>
                  <l>That the death pities of mine enemie.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Yong:</speaker>
                  <l>This benefit at leaſt.</l>
                  <l>Sad death ſhall giue, to free me from the power</l>
                  <l>Of ſuch a gouernment; and if I die</l>
                  <l>For pitying humane chance, and <hi>Piſoes</hi> end,</l>
                  <l>There will be ſome too, that will pitie mine.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Poppa:</speaker>
                  <l>O what a dauntleſſe looke, what ſparkling eyes,</l>
                  <l>Threating in ſuffering; ſure ſome noble blood</l>
                  <l>Is hid in ragges, feares argues a baſe ſpirit</l>
                  <l>In him what courage, and contempt of death,</l>
                  <l>And ſhall I ſuffer one I loue to die?</l>
                  <l>He ſhall not die? hands of this man, away,</l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Nero,</hi> thou ſhalt not kill this guiltleſſe man.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Nero:</speaker>
                  <l>He guiltleſſe, ſtrumpet.
<stage>Spurns her and Poppaa falls.</stage>
                  </l>
                  <l>She's in loue with the ſmo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>th face of the boy.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Neoph.</speaker>
                  <l>Alas my Lord you haue ſlaine her.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Epaph:</speaker>
                  <l>Helpe ſhe dies.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Nero:</speaker>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Poppaa, Poppaa,</hi> ſpeake, I am not angry,</l>
                  <l>I did not meane to hurt thee, ſpeake ſweet loue.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Neoph:</speaker>
                  <l>Shee's dead my Lord.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Nero:</speaker>
                  <l>Fetch her againe, ſhe ſhall not die,</l>
                  <l>Ile ope the Iron gates of hell,</l>
                  <pb facs="tcp:13479:26"/>
                  <l>And breake the impriſond ſhaddowes of the deepe,</l>
                  <l>And force from death this farre too worthy pray,</l>
                  <l>Shee is not dead.</l>
                  <l>The crimſon red, that like the morning ſhone,</l>
                  <l>When from her windowes, (all with Roſes ſtrewde,)</l>
                  <l>She peepeth forth forſakes not yet her ch<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ekes,</l>
                  <l>Her breath, that like a hony-ſuckle ſmelt</l>
                  <l>twining about the prickled Eglintine,</l>
                  <l>Yet moues her lipes; thoſe quicke, and piercing eyes,</l>
                  <l>That did in beautie challenge heauens eyes</l>
                  <l>Yet ſhine as they were wont: O no they doe not,</l>
                  <l>See how they grow obſcure: O ſee, they cloſe,</l>
                  <l>And ceaſe to take, or giue light to the world.</l>
                  <l>What ſtarres ſo ere you are aſſur'd to grace</l>
                  <l>The firmament, (for loe the twinkling fires</l>
                  <l>Together throng, and that cleare milky ſpace</l>
                  <l>Of ſtormes, and <hi>Phiades,</hi> and thunder void,</l>
                  <l>Prepares your roome,) doe not with wry aſpect</l>
                  <l>Looke on your <hi>Nero,</hi> who in blood ſhall mourne</l>
                  <l>Your luckleſſe fate; And many a breathing ſoule,</l>
                  <l>Send af<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>er you to waite vpon their Queene;</l>
                  <l>This ſhall begin, the reſt ſhall follow after,</l>
                  <l>And fill the ſtreets with outcryes, and with ſlaughter.
<stage>Ex.</stage>
                  </l>
               </sp>
               <stage>Enter Seneca, with two of his friends.</stage>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Senec:</speaker>
                  <l>What meanes your mourning, this vngratefull ſorrow?</l>
                  <l>Where are your precepts of <hi>Philoſophie?</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>Where our prepared reſolution,</l>
                  <l>So many yeeres fore-ſtudied againſt danger?</l>
                  <l>To whom is <hi>Neroes</hi> cruelty vnknowne?</l>
                  <l>Or what remained after mothers blood,</l>
                  <l>But his inſtructers death? Leaue, leaue theſe teares,</l>
                  <l>Death from me nothing takes, but what's a burthen,</l>
                  <l>A clog, to that free ſparke of Heauenly fire:</l>
                  <l>But that in <hi>Seneca,</hi> the which you lou'd,</l>
                  <l>Which you admir'd, doth, and ſhall ſtill remaine</l>
                  <l>Secure of death, vntouched of the graue.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <pb facs="tcp:13479:27"/>
                  <speaker>1. <hi>Friend.</hi>
                  </speaker>
                  <l>Weele not belie our teares, we waile not thee,</l>
                  <l>It is our ſelues, and our owne loſſe we grieue;</l>
                  <l>To thee, what loſſe in ſuch a change can bee,</l>
                  <l>Vertue is pai<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> her due, by death alone;</l>
                  <l>To our owne loſſes doe we giue theſe teares,</l>
                  <l>That looſe thy loue, thy boundleſſe knowledge looſe,</l>
                  <l>Looſe the vnpatternd ſample of thy vertue,</l>
                  <l>L<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>oſe whatſoeu'r may praiſe, or ſorrow moue;</l>
                  <l>In all theſe loſſes, yet of this we glory,</l>
                  <l>That 'tis thy happineſſe that makes vs ſorry.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>2. <hi>Friend.</hi>
                  </speaker>
                  <l>If there be any place for Ghoſts of good men,</l>
                  <l>If (as we haue bin long taught) great mens ſoules</l>
                  <l>Conſume not with their bodies, thou ſhalt ſee,</l>
                  <l>(Looking from out the dwellings of the ayre)</l>
                  <l>True duties to thy memorie perform'd;</l>
                  <l>Not in the outward pompe of funerall,</l>
                  <l>But in remembrance of thy deeds, and words,</l>
                  <l>The oft recalling of thy many vertues,</l>
                  <l>The Tombe, that ſhall th'eternall relickes keepe</l>
                  <l>Of <hi>Seneca,</hi> ſhall be his hearers hearts.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Senec:</speaker>
                  <l>Be not afraid my ſoule, goe cheerefully,</l>
                  <l>To thy owne Heauen, from whence it firſt let downe,</l>
                  <l>Thou loath by this impriſoning fleſh putſt on,</l>
                  <l>Now lifted vp, thou rauiſht ſhalt behold</l>
                  <l>The truth of things, at which we wonder here,</l>
                  <l>And fooliſhly doe wrangle on beneath;</l>
                  <l>And like a God ſhalt walke the ſpacious ayre,</l>
                  <l>And ſee what euen to conceit's deni'd.</l>
                  <l>Great ſoule oth' world, that through the parts defus'd</l>
                  <l>Of this vaſt All, guid'ſt what thou doſt informe;</l>
                  <l>You bleſſed mindes, that from the <hi>Pbeares</hi> you moue,</l>
                  <l>Looke on mens actions not with idle eyes;</l>
                  <l>And Gods we goe to, Aaid me in this ſtrife,</l>
                  <l>And combat of my fleſh, that ending, I</l>
                  <l>May ſtill ſhew <hi>Seneca,</hi> and my ſelfe die.</l>
               </sp>
               <stage>Exeunt.</stage>
               <stage>
                  <pb facs="tcp:13479:27"/>
                  <hi>Enter Antonius, Enanthe.</hi>
               </stage>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Anto:</speaker>
                  <l>Sure this meſſage of the Princes,</l>
                  <l>So grieuous and vnlookt for, will appall</l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Petronius</hi> much.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Enan:</speaker>
                  <l>Will not death any man?</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Anto:</speaker>
                  <l>It will; but him ſo much the more,</l>
                  <l>That hauing liu'd to his pleaſure; ſhall forgoe</l>
                  <l>So delicate a life, I doe not maruell</l>
                  <l>That <hi>Seneoa,</hi> and ſuch ſowre fellowes, can</l>
                  <l>Leaue that they neu'r taſted: But when we</l>
                  <l>That haue the <hi>Nectar</hi> of thy kiſſes felt,</l>
                  <l>That drinkes away the troubles of this life,</l>
                  <l>And but one banquet make of forty yeeres,</l>
                  <l>Muſt come to leaue this: but ſoft, here he is.</l>
               </sp>
               <stage>Enter Petroneus, and a Centurion.</stage>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Petron:</speaker>
                  <l>Leaue me a while, <hi>Centurion</hi> to my friends,</l>
                  <l>Let me my farewell take, and thou ſhalt ſee,</l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Neroes</hi> commandement quickly obaid in mee.
<stage>ex. Centurion.</stage>
                  </l>
                  <l>Come let vs drinke, and daſh the poſts with wine<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
                  </l>
                  <l>Here throwe your flowers; fill me a ſwelling bowle,</l>
                  <l>Such as <hi>Mecenas,</hi> or my <hi>Lucan</hi> dranke</l>
                  <l>On <hi>Virgills</hi> birth day.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Enan:</speaker>
                  <l>What meanes <hi>(Petroneus)</hi> this vnſeaſonable,</l>
                  <l>And cauſeleſſe mirth? Why, comes not from the Prince</l>
                  <l>This man to you, a meſſenger of death,</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Petro:</speaker>
                  <l>Here faire <hi>Enanthe,</hi> whoſe plumpe ruddy cheeke</l>
                  <l>Exceeds the grape, it makes this; here my g<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>yrle.
<stage>He drinks.</stage>
                  </l>
                  <l>And thinkſt thou death, a matter of ſuch harme,</l>
                  <l>Why, he muſt haue this pretty dimpling chin,</l>
                  <l>And will pecke out thoſe eyes that now ſo wound.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Enan:</speaker>
                  <l>Why, is it not th'extreameſt of all il<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>s?</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Petro:</speaker>
                  <l>It is indeed the laſt, and end of ills;</l>
                  <l>The Gods, before th'would let vs taſt deaths Ioyes,</l>
                  <pb facs="tcp:13479:28"/>
                  <l>Plac't vs ith toyle, and ſorrowes of this world,</l>
                  <l>Becauſe we ſhould perceiue th'amends, and thanke them,</l>
                  <l>Death, the grim knaue, but leades you to the doore,</l>
                  <l>Where entred once, all curious pleaſures come</l>
                  <l>To meete, and welcome you.</l>
                  <l>A troupe of beauteous Ladies from whoſe eyes,</l>
                  <l>Loue, thouſand arrowes, thouſand graces ſhootes;</l>
                  <l>Puts forth their faire hands to you, and inuites</l>
                  <l>To their greene arbours, and cloſe ſhadowed walles,</l>
                  <l>Whence, baniſht is the roughneſſe of our yeeres:</l>
                  <l>Onely the weſt wind blowes; Ith euer Spring,</l>
                  <l>And euer Sommer: There the laden bowes</l>
                  <l>Offer their tempting burdens to your hand,</l>
                  <l>Doubtfull your eye, or taſt inuiting more:</l>
                  <l>There euery man his owne deſires enioyes;</l>
                  <l>Faire <hi>Lucreſe</hi> lies, by luſty <hi>Tarquins</hi> ſide,</l>
                  <l>And wooes him now againe to rauiſh her.</l>
                  <l>Nor vs, (though <hi>Romane) Lais</hi> will refuſe,</l>
                  <l>To <hi>Corinth</hi> any man may goe; no maske,</l>
                  <l>No enuious garment doth thoſe beauties hide,</l>
                  <l>Which <hi>Nature</hi> made, ſo mouing, to be ſpide,</l>
                  <l>But in bright Chriſtall, which doth ſupply all,</l>
                  <l>And white tranſparent vailes they are attyr'd,</l>
                  <l>Through which the pure ſnowe vnderneath doth ſhine;</l>
                  <l>(Can it be ſnowe, from whence ſuch flames ariſe?)</l>
                  <l>Mingled with that faire company, ſhall we</l>
                  <l>On bankes of <hi>Violets,</hi> and of <hi>Hiacinths</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>Of loues deuiſing, ſit, and gently ſport,</l>
                  <l>And all the while melodious Muſique heare,</l>
                  <l>And Poets ſongs, that Muſique farre exceed</l>
                  <l>The old <hi>Anaicean</hi> crown'd with ſmyling flowers,</l>
                  <l>And amorous <hi>Sapho,</hi> on her Lesbian Lute</l>
                  <l>B<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ties ſweet Sca<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>res, and <hi>Cupids</hi> godhead ſing,</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Anto:</speaker>
                  <l>What, be not rauiſht with thy fancies, doe not</l>
                  <l>Court nothing nor make loue vnto our feares.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Petro:</speaker>
                  <l>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ſt nothing that I ſay?</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Anto:</speaker>
                  <l>But empty words.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <pb facs="tcp:13479:28"/>
                  <speaker>Petro:</speaker>
                  <l>Why, thou requir'ſt ſome inſtance of the eye,</l>
                  <l>Wilt thou goe with me then, and ſee that world?</l>
                  <l>Which either will returne thy old delights;</l>
                  <l>Or ſquare thy appetite anew to theirs.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Anto:</speaker>
                  <l>Nay; I had rather farre beleeue thee here,</l>
                  <l>Others ambition ſuch diſcoueries ſeeke;</l>
                  <l>Faith, I am ſatisfied with the baſe delights</l>
                  <l>Of common men; A wench, a houſe I haue,</l>
                  <l>And of my owne a garden, Ile not change,</l>
                  <l>For all your walkes, and Ladies, and rare fruits.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Petro:</speaker>
                  <l>Your pleaſures muſt of force reſigne to theſe,</l>
                  <l>In vaine you ſhunne the ſword, in vaine the ſea,</l>
                  <l>In vaine is <hi>Nero</hi> fear'd, or flatered;</l>
                  <l>Hether you muſt, and leaue your purchaſt houſes,</l>
                  <l>Your new made garden, and your blacke browd wife,</l>
                  <l>And of the trees thou haſt ſo quaintly ſet;</l>
                  <l>Not one, but the diſpleaſant Cipreſſe ſhall</l>
                  <l>Goe with thee.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Anton:</speaker>
                  <l>Faith 'tis true, we muſt at length,</l>
                  <l>But yet <hi>Petroneus,</hi> while we may, awhile</l>
                  <l>We would enoioy them, thoſe we haue, w'are ſure of,</l>
                  <l>When that you talke of 's doubfull, and to come.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Petro:</speaker>
                  <l>Perhaps thou thinkſt to liue yet twenty yeeres,</l>
                  <l>Which may vnlookt for be cut off, as mine,</l>
                  <l>If not, to endleſſe time compar'd, is nothing</l>
                  <l>What you endure muſt euer, endure now;</l>
                  <l>Nor ſtay not, to be laſt at table ſet,</l>
                  <l>Each beſt day of our life at firſt doth goe,</l>
                  <l>To them ſucceeds diſeaſed age, and woe;</l>
                  <l>Now die your pleaſures, and the dayes your pray</l>
                  <l>Your rimes, and loues, and ieſts will take away.</l>
                  <l>Therefore my ſweet, yet thou wilt goe with mee,</l>
                  <l>And not liue here, to what thou wouldſt not ſee.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Enan:</speaker>
                  <l>Would y'haue me then kill my ſelfe, and die,</l>
                  <l>And goe I know not to what places there.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Petro:</speaker>
                  <l>What places doſt thou feare?</l>
                  <l>The'll fauoured lake they tell thee thou muſt paſſe.</l>
                  <pb facs="tcp:13479:29"/>
                  <l>And thy blacke frogs that croake about the brim.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Enan:</speaker>
                  <l>O pardon Sir, though death affrights a woman;</l>
                  <l>Whoſe pleaſures, though you timely here diuine,</l>
                  <l>The paines we know, and ſee,</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Petron:</speaker>
                  <l>The paine is lifes, death rids that paine away,</l>
                  <l>Come boldly, there's no danger in this foord,</l>
                  <l>Children paſſe through it: If it be a paine,</l>
                  <l>You haue this comfort, that you paſt it are.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Enan:</speaker>
                  <l>Y<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>t all as w<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ll as I, are loath to die.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>
                     <hi>Petro<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>
                     </hi>
                  </speaker>
                  <l>Iudge them by deed, you ſee them doe't apace</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Enan:</speaker>
                  <l>I, but tis loathly, and againſt their wils.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Petro.</speaker>
                  <l>Yet, know you not that any being dead,</l>
                  <l>Repen<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ed them, and would haue liu'd againe,</l>
                  <l>They then there errors ſaw, and fooliſh prayers,</l>
                  <l>But you are blinded in the loue of life,</l>
                  <l>Death is but ſweet to them that doe approach it</l>
                  <l>To me as one that tak<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>n with <hi>Delphick</hi> rage,</l>
                  <l>When the diuining God his breaſt doth fill,</l>
                  <l>He ſees what others cannot ſtanding by,</l>
                  <l>It ſeemes a beauteous, and a pleaſant thing;</l>
                  <l>Where is my deaths Phiſitian?</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Phiſi:</speaker>
                  <l>Here my Lord.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Petro:</speaker>
                  <l>Art ready?</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Phiſi:</speaker>
                  <l>I my Lord.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Petro;</speaker>
                  <l>And I for thee:</l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Nero,</hi> my end ſhall mocke thy tyranny.
<stage>
                        <hi>Exeun<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                              <desc>••</desc>
                           </gap>
                        </hi>
                     </stage>
                  </l>
               </sp>
               <trailer>Finis Actus Quarti.</trailer>
            </div>
            <div n="5" type="act">
               <head>Actus Quintus.</head>
               <stage>Enter Nero, Nimphidius Tigellinus, Neophilus, Epaporoditus, and other attendants.</stage>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Nero:</speaker>
                  <l>ENough is wept, <hi>Poppaea,</hi> for thy death,</l>
                  <l>Enough is bled, ſo many teares of others</l>
                  <pb facs="tcp:13479:29"/>
                  <l>Wailing their loſſes haue wipt mine away</l>
                  <l>Who in the common funerall of the world</l>
                  <l>Can mourne on death?</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Tigell:</speaker>
                  <l>Beſides, your Maieſtie this benefit</l>
                  <l>In their diſerued puniſhment ſhall reape</l>
                  <l>From all attempts hereafter to be freed,</l>
                  <l>Conſpiracy is now for euer daſht,</l>
                  <l>Tumult ſuppreſt, rebellion out of heart;</l>
                  <l>In <hi>Piſoes</hi> death, danger it ſelfe did die.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Nimph:</speaker>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Piſo</hi> that thought to climbe by bowing downe,</l>
                  <l>By giuing a way to thriue, and raiſing others</l>
                  <l>To become great himſelfe, hath now by death</l>
                  <l>Giuen quiet to your thoughts, and feare to theirs</l>
                  <l>That ſhall from treaſon their aduancement plot;</l>
                  <l>Thoſe dangerous heads, that his ambition leand on,</l>
                  <l>And they by it crept vp, and from their meanneſſe</l>
                  <l>Thought in this ſtirre to riſe aloft, are off:</l>
                  <l>Now peace, and ſafetie waite vpon your throne;</l>
                  <l>Securitie hath wall'd your ſeat about,</l>
                  <l>There is no place for feare left.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Nero:</speaker>
                  <l>Why, I neuer feard them.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Nimph:</speaker>
                  <l>That was your fault.</l>
                  <l>Your Maieſtie muſt giue vs leaue to blame</l>
                  <l>Your dangerous courage, and that noble ſoule</l>
                  <l>Too prodigall of it ſelfe.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Nero:</speaker>
                  <l>A Princes mind knowes neither feare, nor hope,</l>
                  <l>The beames of royall Maieſtie are ſuch,</l>
                  <l>As all eyes are with it amaz'd, and weakened,</l>
                  <l>But it with nothing; I at firſt contemn'd</l>
                  <l>Their weake deuiſes, and faint enterpriſe:</l>
                  <l>Why, thought they againſt him to haue preuail'd,</l>
                  <l>Whoſe childhood was from <hi>Meſſalinas</hi> ſpight</l>
                  <l>By Dragons, (that the earth gaue vp) preſeru'd,</l>
                  <l>Such guard my cradle had; for fate had then</l>
                  <l>Pointed me out, to be what now I am.</l>
                  <l>Should all the Legions, and the prouinces</l>
                  <l>In one vnited, againſt me conſpire:</l>
                  <pb facs="tcp:13479:30"/>
                  <l>I could diſperce them withone angry eye.</l>
                  <l>My brow's an hoſt of men; Come <hi>Tigellinus,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>Let turne this bloody banquet, <hi>Piſo</hi> meant vs,</l>
                  <l>Vnto a merry feaſt, weele drinke and challenge</l>
                  <l>Fortune; whoſe that <hi>Neophilus?</hi>
                  </l>
               </sp>
               <stage>Enter a Roman.</stage>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Neoph:</speaker>
                  <l>A Currier from beyond the Alpes my Lord.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Nero:</speaker>
                  <l>Newes of ſome German victorie belike,</l>
                  <l>Or Britton ouerthrow.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Neoph:</speaker>
                  <l>The Letters come from France.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Nimp:</speaker>
                  <l>Why ſmiles your Maieſtie?</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Nero:</speaker>
                  <l>So I ſmile, I ſhould be afraid there's one</l>
                  <l>In Armes <hi>Nimphidius.</hi>
                  </l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Nimp:</speaker>
                  <l>What arm'd againſt your Maieſtie?</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Nero:</speaker>
                  <l>Our Lieuetenant of the Prouince, <hi>Iulius Vindex.</hi>
                  </l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Tigell:</speaker>
                  <l>Who, that guiddy French-man?</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Nimp:</speaker>
                  <l>His Prouince is diſarm'd my Lord, he hath</l>
                  <l>No legion, not a ſouldier vnder him.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Epaph:</speaker>
                  <l>One that by blood, and rapine would repaire</l>
                  <l>His ſtate conſum'd in vanities, and luſt.</l>
               </sp>
               <stage>Enter another Roman.</stage>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Tigell:</speaker>
                  <l>He would not find out three to follow him.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>A meſſ:</speaker>
                  <l>More newes my Lord.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Nero:</speaker>
                  <l>Is it of <hi>Vindex</hi> that thou haſt to ſay?</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Meſſ:</speaker>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Vindex</hi> is vp, and with him France in Armes.</l>
                  <l>The Noble men, and people throng to th' cauſe,</l>
                  <l>Money, and Armour, Cities doe conferre,</l>
                  <l>The contrey doth ſend in prouiſion</l>
                  <l>Yong men bring bodies, old men lead them forth,</l>
                  <l>Ladies doe coine their Iewels into pay,</l>
                  <l>The ſickle now is fram'd into a ſword,</l>
                  <l>And drawing horſes are to manage taught,</l>
                  <l>France nothing doth but warre, and fury breath.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Nero:</speaker>
                  <l>All this fierce talk's, but <hi>Vindex</hi> doth rebell,</l>
                  <l>And I will hang him.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Tigell.</speaker>
                  <l>How long came you forth after the former meſſenger.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Meſſ:</speaker>
                  <l>Foure dayes, but by the benefit of ſea,</l>
                  <pb facs="tcp:13479:30"/>
                  <l>and weather, am arriued with him.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Neoph.</speaker>
                  <l>How ſtrong was <hi>
                        <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>index</hi> at your comming forth?</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Meſſ:</speaker>
                  <l>He was eſteem'd a hundred thouſand.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Tigell:</speaker>
                  <l>Men enough,</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Nimph.</speaker>
                  <l>And ſouldiours few enough.</l>
                  <l>Tumultuary troopes, vndiſciplin'd,</l>
                  <l>Vntrain'd in ſeruice, to waſt victuals good,</l>
                  <l>But when they come to looke on warres blacke wounds,</l>
                  <l>And but a farre off ſee the face of death.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Nero:</speaker>
                  <l>It falles out for my empty coffers well,</l>
                  <l>The ſpoyle of ſuch a large and goodly Prouince,</l>
                  <l>Enricht with trade, and long enioyed peace.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Tigell:</speaker>
                  <l>What order will your Maieſtie haue taken</l>
                  <l>For leuying forces to ſuppreſſe this ſtirre?</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Nero:</speaker>
                  <l>What order ſhould we take? weele laugh, &amp; drinke,</l>
                  <l>Thinkſt thou it fit my pleaſures be diſturb'd</l>
                  <l>When any French-man liſt to breake his necke?</l>
                  <l>They haue not heard of <hi>Piſoes</hi> Fortune yet,</l>
                  <l>Let that Tale fight with them.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Nimph.</speaker>
                  <l>What order needs: your Maieſtie ſhall finde</l>
                  <l>This French heat quickly of it ſelfe grow cold.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Nero.</speaker>
                  <l>Come away.</l>
                  <l>Nothing ſhall come that this nights ſport ſhall ſtay.</l>
               </sp>
               <stage>Ex. Ner.</stage>
               <stage>Manet Neophilus, Epaphroditus.</stage>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Neoph.</speaker>
                  <l>I wonder what makes him ſo confident</l>
                  <l>In this reuolt now growne vnto a warre,</l>
                  <l>And enſignes in the field, when in the other,</l>
                  <l>Being but a plot of a conſpiracie,</l>
                  <l>He ſhew'd himſelfe ſo wretchedly diſmaid,</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Epaph.</speaker>
                  <l>Faith, the right nature of a coward to ſet light</l>
                  <l>Dangers that ſeeme farre off. <hi>Piſo</hi> was here,</l>
                  <l>Ready to enter at the Preſence doote,</l>
                  <l>And dragge him out of his abuſed chaire,</l>
                  <l>And then he trembled; <hi>Vindex</hi> is in France,</l>
                  <l>And many woods, and ſeas, and hills betweene.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Neoph.</speaker>
                  <l>Twas ſtrange that <hi>Piſo</hi> was ſo ſoone ſuppreſt,</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <pb facs="tcp:13479:31"/>
                  <speaker>Epaph:</speaker>
                  <l>Strange, ſtrange indeed, for had he but come vp,</l>
                  <l>And taken the Court, in that affright and ſtirre,</l>
                  <l>While vnreſolu'd for whom, or what to doe,</l>
                  <l>Each on the other had in iealouſie</l>
                  <l>(While as apaled Maieſtie not yet</l>
                  <l>Had time to ſet the countenance) he would</l>
                  <l>Haue hazarded the royall ſeat.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Neoph:</speaker>
                  <l>Nay, had it without hazard; all the Court</l>
                  <l>Had for him bin, and thoſe diſclos'd their loue,</l>
                  <l>And fauour in the cauſe, which now to hide,</l>
                  <l>And colour their good meanings ready were</l>
                  <l>To ſhew their forwardneſſe againſt it moſt.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Epaph:</speaker>
                  <l>But for a ſtranger with a naked prouince,</l>
                  <l>Without allies, or friends ith' ſta<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>e to challenge</l>
                  <l>A Prince vpheld with thirty Legions</l>
                  <l>Rooted in foure diſcents of Anceſtors,</l>
                  <l>And foureteene yeares continuance of raigne,</l>
                  <l>Why it is —</l>
               </sp>
               <stage>
                  <hi>Enter Nero, Nimphidius, Tigellinus to them.</hi>
                  <stage>ex Nor Nimph:</stage>
               </stage>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Nero:</speaker>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Galba</hi> and Spaine, what Spaine and <hi>Gala</hi> too?</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Epaph:</speaker>
                  <l>I pray thee <hi>Tigellinus,</hi> what furie's this?</l>
                  <l>What ſtrange euent, what accident hath thus</l>
                  <l>Orecaſt your countenances?</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Tigell.</speaker>
                  <l>Downe we were ſet at table, and began</l>
                  <l>With ſparckling bowles to chaſe our feares away,</l>
                  <l>And mirth and pleaſure lookt out of our eyes;</l>
                  <l>When loe a breathleſſe meſſenger comes in</l>
                  <l>And tells how <hi>Vindex,</hi> and the powers of France</l>
                  <l>Haue <hi>Segius Galba</hi> choſen Emperor,</l>
                  <l>With what applauſe the Legions him receiue,</l>
                  <l>That Spaines reuolted; Portingale hath ioyn'd;</l>
                  <l>As much ſuſpected is of Germany;</l>
                  <l>But <hi>Nero,</hi> not abiding out the end,</l>
                  <l>Orethrew the tables, daſht againſt the ground</l>
                  <l>The cuppe which he ſo much you know eſteem'd;</l>
                  <l>Teareth his haire, and with incenſed rage</l>
                  <l>Curſeth falſe men, and Gods the lookers on.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <pb facs="tcp:13479:31"/>
                  <speaker>Neoph:</speaker>
                  <l>His rage we ſaw was wild and deſperate.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Epaph:</speaker>
                  <l>O you vnſearched wiſedomes, which doe laugh,</l>
                  <l>At our ſecuritie, and feares alike;</l>
                  <l>And plaine to ſhew our weakeneſſe, and your power</l>
                  <l>Make vs contemne the harmes, which ſureſt ſtrike</l>
                  <l>When you our glories, and our pride vndoe,</l>
                  <l>Our ouerthrow you make rediculous too.
<stage>exeunt.</stage>
                  </l>
                  <stage>Enter Nimphidius ſolus.</stage>
                  <l>Slow making counſels, and the ſliding yeere</l>
                  <l>Haue brought me to the long foreſeene deſtruction</l>
                  <l>Of this miſled yong man; his State is ſhaken,</l>
                  <l>And I will puſh it on; reuolted France;</l>
                  <l>Nor the coniured Prouinces of Spaine,</l>
                  <l>Nor his owne guilt, ſhall like to me oppreſſe him;</l>
                  <l>I to his eaſie yeelding feares proclaime</l>
                  <l>New German mutenys, and all the world</l>
                  <l>Rowſing it ſelfe in hate of <hi>Neroes</hi> name;</l>
                  <l>I his diſtracted counſels doe diſperce</l>
                  <l>With freſh deſpaires, I animate the Senate</l>
                  <l>And the people, to ingage them paſt recall</l>
                  <l>In preiudice of <hi>Nero,</hi> and in briefe,</l>
                  <l>Periſh he muſt, the fates and I reſolue it;</l>
                  <l>Which to effect, I preſently will goe,</l>
                  <l>Proclaime a <hi>Donatiue</hi> in <hi>Galbaes</hi> name.</l>
               </sp>
               <stage>Enter Antoneus to him.</stage>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Anton:</speaker>
                  <l>Yonders <hi>Nimphidius</hi> our Commander, now,</l>
                  <l>I with reſpect muſt ſpeake, and ſmooth my brow;</l>
                  <l>Captaine all <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>aile.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Nimp:</speaker>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Antoneus</hi> well met,</l>
                  <l>Your place of <hi>Tribune</hi> in this Anarchi.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Anton:</speaker>
                  <l>This Anarchy my Lord, i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> 
                     <hi>Nero</hi> dead?</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Nimph:</speaker>
                  <l>This Anarchy, this yet vnſtiled time,</l>
                  <l>While <hi>Galba</hi> is vn eaſed of the Empire</l>
                  <l>Which <hi>Nero</hi> h<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>h forſooke.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Anton:</speaker>
                  <l>Hath <hi>Nero</hi> then reſign'd the Empire?</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Nimph:</speaker>
                  <l>In effect he hath, for he's fled to <hi>Egypt.</hi>
                  </l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Anton:</speaker>
                  <l>My Lord you tell ſtrange newes to me,</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <pb facs="tcp:13479:32"/>
                  <speaker>Nimph:</speaker>
                  <l>But nothing ſtrange to mee,</l>
                  <l>Who euery moment, knew of his deſpaires,</l>
                  <l>The Curriers came ſo faſt with freſh alarmes</l>
                  <l>Of new reuolts, that he vnable quite</l>
                  <l>To beare his feares, which he had long conceal'd,</l>
                  <l>Is now reuoulted from himſelfe, and fled.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Anto:</speaker>
                  <l>Thruſt with reports, and rumours from his ſeat.</l>
                  <l>My Lord you know the Campe depends on you</l>
                  <l>As you determine.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Nimph:</speaker>
                  <l>There it lies <hi>Antonius,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>What ſhould we doe, it boots not to relie</l>
                  <l>On <hi>Neroes</hi> ſtinking fortunes, and to ſit</l>
                  <l>Securely looking on, were to receiue</l>
                  <l>An Emperor from Spaine; which how diſgracefull</l>
                  <l>It were to vs, who if we waigh our ſelues</l>
                  <l>The moſt materiall acceſsions are</l>
                  <l>Of all the Roman Empire, which diſgrace</l>
                  <l>To couer we muſt ioyne our ſelues betimes,</l>
                  <l>And thereby ſeeme to haue created <hi>Gabba;</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>Therefore Ile ſtraight proclaime a <hi>Donatiue,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>Of thirty thouſand ſiſterces a man.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Anto:</speaker>
                  <l>I thinke ſo great a gift was neuer heard of.</l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Galba</hi> they ſay is frugally inclinde,</l>
                  <l>Will he avow ſo great a gift as this?</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Nimph:</speaker>
                  <l>How ere he like of it, he muſt avow it,</l>
                  <l>If by our promiſe he be once ingaged;</l>
                  <l>And ſince the ſouldiers care belongs to mee,</l>
                  <l>I will haue care of them, and of their good.</l>
                  <l>Let them thanke me, if I through this occaſion</l>
                  <l>Procure for them ſo great a donatiue.
<stage>Ex: Nimp:</stage>
                  </l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Anton:</speaker>
                  <l>So you be thankt, it skils not who preuaile,</l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Galba,</hi> or <hi>Nero,</hi> traitor to them both;</l>
                  <l>You giue it out that <hi>Neroes</hi> fled to <hi>Egypt,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>Who with the frights of your repotts amaz'd,</l>
                  <l>By our deuice, doth lurke for better newes,</l>
                  <l>Whilſt you ineuitably doe betray him,</l>
                  <l>Workes he all this for <hi>Galba</hi> then? not ſo</l>
                  <pb facs="tcp:13479:32"/>
                  <l>I haue long ſeene his climbing to the Empire</l>
                  <l>By ſecret practiſes of gracious women,</l>
                  <l>And other inſtruments of the late Court,</l>
                  <l>That was his loue to het that me refus'd;</l>
                  <l>And now by this he would giue the ſouldiers fauour;</l>
                  <l>Now is the time to quit <hi>Poppaeas</hi> ſcorne,</l>
                  <l>And his rivallity; Ile ſtraight reueale</l>
                  <l>His treacheries, to <hi>Galbaes</hi> agents here.
<stage>Exit:</stage>
                  </l>
               </sp>
               <stage>Enter Tigellinus with the Guard.</stage>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Tigell:</speaker>
                  <l>You ſee what iſſue things doe ſort vnto,</l>
                  <l>Yet may we hope not onely impunitie,</l>
                  <l>But with our fellowes part oth' guift proclaim'd.</l>
               </sp>
               <stage>Nero meets them.</stage>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Nero:</speaker>
                  <l>Whether goe you, ſtay my friends;</l>
                  <l>'Tis <hi>Caeſar</hi> calles you, ſtay my louing friends.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Tigell:</speaker>
                  <l>We were his ſlaues, his footſtooles, and muſt crouch;</l>
                  <l>But now, with ſuch obſeruance to his feet,</l>
                  <l>It is his miſery that calles vs friends.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Nero.</speaker>
                  <l>And moues you not the miſery of a Prince?</l>
                  <l>O ſtay my friends, ſtay, harken to the voyce</l>
                  <l>Which once yee knew.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Tigell:</speaker>
                  <l>Harke to the peoples cryes,</l>
                  <l>Harke to the ſtreets, that <hi>Galba, Galba</hi> ring.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Nero:</speaker>
                  <l>The people may forſake me without blame,</l>
                  <l>I did them wrong to make you rich, and great,</l>
                  <l>I tooke their houſes to beſtow on you:</l>
                  <l>Treaſon in them hath name of libertie,</l>
                  <l>Your fault hath no excuſe, you are my fault,</l>
                  <l>And the excuſe of others treachery.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Tigell:</speaker>
                  <l>Shall we with ſtaying ſeeme his tyrannies</l>
                  <l>T' vphold, as if we were in loue with them?</l>
                  <l>We are excus'd vnleſſe we ſtay too long,</l>
                  <l>As forced Miniſters, and apart of wrong.
<stage>ex. preter Nero.</stage>
                  </l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Nero:</speaker>
                  <l>O now I ſee the vizard from my face</l>
                  <l>So louely, and ſo fearefull is fall'n off</l>
                  <l>That vizard, ſhadow, nothing (Maieſtie)</l>
                  <l>(Which like a child acquainted with his feares,</l>
                  <pb facs="tcp:13479:33"/>
                  <l>But now men trembled at, and now contemne<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Nero</hi> forſaken is of all the world.</l>
                  <l>The world of truth; O fall ſome vengeance downe</l>
                  <l>Equall vnto their falſehoods, and my wrongs;</l>
                  <l>Might I accept the Chariot of the Sunne.</l>
                  <l>And like another <hi>Phaeton</hi> conſume</l>
                  <l>In flames of all the world; a pile of Death</l>
                  <l>Worthy the ſtate, and greatneſſe I haue loſt.</l>
                  <l>Or were I now but Lord of my owne fires,</l>
                  <l>Wherein falſe Rome yet once againe might ſmoake,</l>
                  <l>And periſh, all vnpitied of her Gods,</l>
                  <l>That all things in their laſt deſtruction might</l>
                  <l>Performe a funerall honour to their Lord.</l>
                  <l>O loue diſſolue with <hi>Caeſar, Caeſars</hi> world;</l>
                  <l>Or you whom <hi>Nero</hi> rather ſhould inuoake</l>
                  <l>Blacke <hi>Chaes,</hi> and you fearefull ſhapes beneath,</l>
                  <l>That with a long, and not vaine enuy haue</l>
                  <l>Sought to deſtroy this worke of th'other Gods;</l>
                  <l>Now let your darkeneſſe ceaſe the ſpoyles of day,</l>
                  <l>And the worlds firſt contention end your ſtrife.</l>
               </sp>
               <stage>Enter two Romanes to him.</stage>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>1 <hi>Rom:</hi>
                  </speaker>
                  <l>Though others, bound with greater benefits</l>
                  <l>Haue left your changed fortunes and doe runne</l>
                  <l>Whither new hopes doe call them, yet come we.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Nero:</speaker>
                  <l>O welcome, come you to aduerſitie,</l>
                  <l>Welcome true friends, why there is faith on earth.</l>
                  <l>Of thouſand ſeruants, friends, and followers;</l>
                  <l>Yet two are left: your countenance me thinkes</l>
                  <l>Giues comfort, and new hopes</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>2 <hi>Rom:</hi>
                  </speaker>
                  <l>Doe not deceiue your thoughts,</l>
                  <l>My Lord we bring no comfort, would we could;</l>
                  <l>But the laſt duty to performe, and beſt</l>
                  <l>We euer ſhall, a free death to perſwade,</l>
                  <l>To cut off hopes of fearcer cruelty,</l>
                  <l>And ſcorne, more cruell to a worthy ſoule.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>1 <hi>Rom:</hi>
                  </speaker>
                  <l>The Senate haue decreed you're puniſhable,</l>
                  <l>After the faſhion of our anceſtors;</l>
                  <pb facs="tcp:13479:33"/>
                  <l>Which is; your necke being locked in a forke</l>
                  <l>You muſt be naked whipt, and ſcourg'd to death.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Nero:</speaker>
                  <l>The Senate thus decreed? they that ſo oft</l>
                  <l>My vertues flattered haue, and guifts of mine,</l>
                  <l>My gouernment prefert'd to ancient times,</l>
                  <l>And challenge <hi>Numa</hi> to compare with me;</l>
                  <l>Haue they ſo horrible an end ſought out?</l>
                  <l>No, here I beare which ſhall preuent ſuch ſhame,</l>
                  <l>This hand ſhall yet from that deliuer me,</l>
                  <l>And faithfull be alone vnto his Lord.</l>
                  <l>Alaſſe how ſharpe, and terrible is death;</l>
                  <l>O muſt I die, muſt now my ſenſes cloſe,</l>
                  <l>For euer die, and nere returne againe,</l>
                  <l>Neuer more ſee the Sunne, nor Heauen, nor Earth?</l>
                  <l>Whither goe I? what ſhall I be anone;</l>
                  <l>What horred iourney wandreſt thou my ſoule,</l>
                  <l>Vnder th'earth, in darke, dampe, duskie vaults?</l>
                  <l>Or ſhall I now to nothing be reſolu'd?</l>
                  <l>My feares become my hopes, O would I might.</l>
                  <l>Me thinkes I ſee the boyling <hi>Phlegeton,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>And the dull poole, feared of them we feare,</l>
                  <l>The dread, and terror of the Gods themſelues,</l>
                  <l>The furies arm'd with linkes, with whippes, with ſnakes,</l>
                  <l>And my owne furies farre more mad then they;</l>
                  <l>My mother, and thoſe troopes of ſlaughtred friends,</l>
                  <l>And now the Iudge is brought vnto the throne,</l>
                  <l>That will not leaue vnto authoritie,</l>
                  <l>Nor fauour the oppreſsions of the great</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>1 <hi>Rom:</hi>
                  </speaker>
                  <l>Theſe are the idle terrors of the night,</l>
                  <l>Which wiſe men (though they teach, doe not beleeue)</l>
                  <l>To curbe our pleaſures faine, and aide the weake.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>2 <hi>Rom:</hi>
                  </speaker>
                  <l>Deaths wrongfull defamation, which would make</l>
                  <l>Vs ſhunne this happy hauen of our reſt,</l>
                  <l>This end of euils; as ſome fearefull harme.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>1 <hi>Rom.</hi>
                  </speaker>
                  <l>Shadowes, and fond imaginations,</l>
                  <l>Which now you ſee on earth; but children feare.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>2 <hi>Rom:</hi>
                  </speaker>
                  <l>Why ſhould our faults feare puniſhment from them,</l>
                  <pb facs="tcp:13479:34"/>
                  <l>What doe the actions of this life concerne</l>
                  <l>The tother world, with which is no commerce?</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>1 <hi>Rom:</hi>
                  </speaker>
                  <l>Would Heauen, and Starres, neceſsitie compell</l>
                  <l>Vs to doe that, which after it would puniſh?</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>2 <hi>Rom:</hi>
                  </speaker>
                  <l>Let vs not after our liues end beleeue</l>
                  <l>More then you felt before it.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Nero:</speaker>
                  <l>If any words haue made me confident,</l>
                  <l>And boldly doe, for hearing others ſpeake,</l>
                  <l>Boldly this night; But will you by example</l>
                  <l>Teach me the truth of your opinion,</l>
                  <l>And make me ſee that you beleeue your ſelues,</l>
                  <l>Will you by dying, teach me to beare death</l>
                  <l>With courage?</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>1 <hi>Rom:</hi>
                  </speaker>
                  <l>No neceſsitie of death</l>
                  <l>Hangs ore our heads, no dangers threatens vs,</l>
                  <l>Nor Senates ſharpe decree, nor <hi>Galbaes</hi> armes.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>2 <hi>Rom:</hi>
                  </speaker>
                  <l>Is this the thankes then thou doſt pay our loue?</l>
                  <l>Die baſely as ſuch a life deſeru'd;</l>
                  <l>Reſerue thy ſelfe to puniſhment, and ſcorne</l>
                  <l>Of Rome, and of thy laughing enemies.
<stage>exeunt.</stage>
                  </l>
               </sp>
               <stage>Manet Nero.</stage>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Nero:</speaker>
                  <l>They hate me, cauſe I would but liue, what was't</l>
                  <l>You lou'd kind friends, and came to ſee my death;</l>
                  <l>Let me endure all torture, and reproach</l>
                  <l>That earth, or <hi>Galbaes</hi> anger can inflict:</l>
                  <l>Yet hell, and <hi>Rodamanth</hi> are more pittileſſe.</l>
               </sp>
               <stage>The firſt Romane to him.</stage>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Rom:</speaker>
                  <l>Though not deſeru'd, yet once <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>gaine I come,</l>
                  <l>To warne thee to take pitie on thy ſelfe;</l>
                  <l>The troupes by the Senate ſent, diſcend the hill</l>
                  <l>And come.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Nero:</speaker>
                  <l>To take me, and to whip me vnto death:</l>
                  <l>O whither ſhall I flye?</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Rom:</speaker>
                  <l>Thou haſt no choice.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Nero:</speaker>
                  <l>O hither muſt I flye, hard is his happe,</l>
                  <l>Who from death onely muſt by death eſcape,</l>
                  <l>Where are they yet? O may I not a little</l>
                  <pb facs="tcp:13479:34"/>
                  <l>Bethinke my ſelfe?</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Rom:</speaker>
                  <l>They are at hand; harke, thou maiſt heare the noiſe.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Nero:</speaker>
                  <l>O <hi>Rome</hi> farewell farewell you Theaters,</l>
                  <l>Where I ſo oft, with popular applauſe</l>
                  <l>In ſong; and action; O they come I die.
<stage>He fals on his ſword.</stage>
                  </l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Rom:</speaker>
                  <l>So baſe an end all iuſt commiſeration</l>
                  <l>Doth take away, yet what we doe now ſpurne,</l>
                  <l>The morning Sunne ſaw fearefull to the world.</l>
               </sp>
               <stage>Enter ſome of Galbaes friends, Antoneus and others, with Nimphidius bound.</stage>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Gal:</speaker>
                  <l>You both ſhall die together, Traitors both,</l>
                  <l>He to the common wealth, and thou to him,</l>
                  <l>And worſe, to a good Prince; what, is he dead?</l>
                  <l>Hath feare encourag'd him, and made him thus,</l>
                  <l>Preuent our puniſhment; then die with him.</l>
                  <l>Fall thy aſpyring at thy Maſters feete.
<stage>He kils Nimph:</stage>
                  </l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Anton:</speaker>
                  <l>Who though he iuſtly periſht, yet by thee</l>
                  <l>Deſeru'd it not, nor ended there thy treaſon;</l>
                  <l>But euen thought oth' Empire, thou conceiu'ſt</l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Galbaes</hi> diſgrace in receiuing that</l>
                  <l>Which the ſonne of <hi>Nimphidia</hi> could hope.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Rom:</speaker>
                  <l>Thus great bad men aboue them finde a rod:</l>
                  <l>People depart, and ſay there is a God.</l>
               </sp>
               <stage>Exeunt.</stage>
            </div>
            <trailer>FJNJS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
