<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>A right godly rule how all faithfull Christians ought to occupie and exercise themselues in their dayly prayers.</title>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1602</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 164 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 189 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2013-12">2013-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A11180</idno>
            <idno type="STC">STC 21446.7</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC S105748</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99841474</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99841474</idno>
            <idno type="VID">6059</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A11180)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 6059)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 717:06)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>A right godly rule how all faithfull Christians ought to occupie and exercise themselues in their dayly prayers.</title>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[382] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>By F. Kyngston,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>Imprinted at London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1602.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Largely based on prayers in STC 16060: An vniforme and catholyke prymer in Latin and Englishe.</note>
                  <note>Identified as STC 21056b on UMI microfilm.</note>
                  <note>Running title reads: Godly prayers.</note>
                  <note>Signatures: A-2A(-2A8).</note>
                  <note>Some print blurred; A1-3 mutilated at lower right corner; 2A7 partly torn, with some loss of text.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the Folger Shakespeare Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Prayer --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Christian life --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2012-06</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-06</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-08</date>
            <label>Colm MacCrossan</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-08</date>
            <label>Colm MacCrossan</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-02</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:6059:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:6059:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>RIGHT GODLY RVLE; How all faithfull Chriſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans ought to occupie and <hi>exerciſe themſelues in their</hi> dayly prayers.</p>
            <q>
               <bibl>
                  <hi>Luke.</hi> 22. <hi>Matth</hi> 26.</bibl>
               <p>Chriſt teacheth vs in his Goſpel <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> Watch and pray, leaſt yee f<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="3 letters">
                     <desc>•••</desc>
                  </gap> into temptation.</p>
            </q>
            <p>Imprinted at London by F. Kingſton. 1602</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="prayers">
            <pb facs="tcp:6059:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:6059:2"/>
            <head>GODLY PRAYERS.</head>
            <div type="prayer">
               <head>
                  <hi>For Munday.</hi> Morning Prayer.</head>
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">O</seg> Moſt louing God and gracious fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther in Chriſt, wee thanke thee for that ſweete ſleepe and comfortable reſt, that thou haſt giuen vs this night: and foraſmuch as thou ha<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>t commaunded vs by thy <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> w<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>rd, that no man ſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> bee idle, but alwaies oc<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>pied
<pb facs="tcp:6059:3"/> in vertuous exerciſes, euerie man according to his calling: wée moſt humblie beſéech thée, that thine eies may attend vs dayly, and defend vs, and in ſorrowe ſuccour, cheriſh, and comfort vs. And ſo gouerne (good Lord) all our counſailes, ſtudies, and labours, that wee may ſpend this day ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to thy moſt bleſſed <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>ll, without hurting of our <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="4 letters">
                     <desc>••••</desc>
                  </gap>hbour, yea that <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap> diligently and warily
<pb facs="tcp:6059:3"/> eſchew and auoyd all things that ſhould diſpleaſe thée, ſet thée alwayes before our eyes, and liue in thy feare, and euer worke thou ſo in vs, that wee may bee found continent, pure of liuing, temperate, and acceptable before thy diuine Maieſtie, vnto the praiſe of thy moſt holy &amp; bleſſed name, through Ieſu Chriſt our Lord and Sauiour. Amen.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="prayer">
               <pb facs="tcp:6059:4"/>
               <head>
                  <hi>For Tueſday.</hi> Morning Prayer.</head>
               <p>SEeing that thou (oh hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uenly Father) art that one and alone Almightie God, which art in euerie place, &amp; beholdeſt the coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſailes, deuices and workes, yea the very thoughts of all men, and giueſt to euery one <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>cording to their déedes: wee humbly beſeech thee for Chriſt Ieſus his ſake, to
<pb facs="tcp:6059:4"/> giue vs this grace, that for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>aſmuch as thou haſt graci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſlie preſerued vs this night paſt, wee may not ſpend this day preſent, nor any other day of our liues, after our owne mindes and pleaſure, which is alway e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uil and wicked, but more earneſtly looke vpon and di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligently follow thy fatherly will, thy euerlaſting coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſaile, thy faithfull word and pleaſure, which is alwaies good, perfite and holy, and
<pb facs="tcp:6059:5"/> performe y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſame w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> cheare<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fulnes, that thy diuine name may alway bee ſanctified both now and euermore of vs miſerable ſinners, tho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rough thy dearely beloued Son Ieſus Chriſt our Lord and Sauiour. Amen.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="prayer">
               <head>
                  <hi>For Wedneſday.</hi> A Morning prayer.</head>
               <p>
                  <hi>O</hi> Lord Ieſus Chriſt, which art the bright Sun of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> world, euer riſing,
<pb facs="tcp:6059:5"/> neuer falling, which w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> thy wholeſome looke, preſerueſt, nouriſheſt, and makeſt ioy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full all thinges that are in heauen and earth: ſhine fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uourablie, I beſéech thée, in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to my ſpirite, that the night of ſinnes, and miſts of er<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rors, being driuen away by thy inward light, I may walke this day, and all the daies of my life without ſtumbling or offe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce: comely as in y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> day time, being pure fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the works of darkneſſe.
<pb facs="tcp:6059:6"/> Grant this (O Lord) which liueſt &amp; raigneſt with God the Father in vnitie of the holy Ghoſt, world without end. Amen.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="prayer">
               <head>
                  <hi>For Thurſday.</hi> Morning Prayer.</head>
               <p>
                  <hi>O</hi> Lord Ieſu Chriſt, to whom &amp; before whom all things are manifeſt and plaine, which alſo ſuffereſt not a Sparrow to light on the grounde without thy
<pb facs="tcp:6059:6"/> prouidence: and which in times paſt, by thy holy Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit diddeſt guide our forefa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers Abraham, Iſaac and Iacob, in thy pathes and waies, &amp; in a ſtrange coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trey didſt appoint the ſame thy bleſſed Spirit and meſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſenger to bee their guide: Graunt me this day moſt wretched ſinner (whom by thy word thou doeſt encou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rage to call vpon thee in all time of neede &amp; neceſſities) that I may haue the ſame
<pb facs="tcp:6059:7"/> thy holie Spirit to direct my pathes and waies this day, that I may walke according to thy godly will and plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure, to the profite of my neighbour, and glorie of thy name, which liueſt and raigneſt world without end, Amen.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="prayer">
               <head>
                  <hi>For Friday.</hi> A Morning prayer.</head>
               <p>
                  <hi>O</hi> Mercifull Lord God &amp; heauenly Father, I
<pb facs="tcp:6059:7"/> render moſt high lande, praiſe and thanks vnto thée, for y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> thou haſt preſerued me both this night and all the time and daies of my life he<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>therto vnder thy defence, &amp; haſt ſuffered me to liue vnto this preſent hower: I be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſéech thée heartilie that thou wilt vouchſafe to receiue me this day, and the reſidue of my whole life from hence<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>foorth into thy tuition, ruling and gouerning mee with thy holie Spirite,
<pb facs="tcp:6059:8"/> that ſo all manner of darke<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes, of miſbeliefe, infideli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie, carnall luſtes, and affe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctions, may bee vtterly cho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed &amp; driuen out of my heart, and that I may be iuſtified and ſaued both body &amp; ſoule, through a right and ſtedfaſt faith, and ſo walke in the light of thy moſt godly truth, to thy glorie &amp; praiſe, and to the profit and furthe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rance of my neighbour, through Ieſus Chriſt our Lord and Sauiour. Amen.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="prayer">
               <pb facs="tcp:6059:8"/>
               <head>
                  <hi>For Saturday.</hi> Morning Prayer.</head>
               <p>
                  <hi>O</hi> Heauenlie Father, which like a diligent watchman, attendeſt al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>waies vpon thy faithfull people, whether they wake or ſleepe, and mightily de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fendeſt the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, not only fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>than y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> old enemie of man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kind, but alſo fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> al their ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerſaries; ſo that through thy godly power they bee
<pb facs="tcp:6059:9"/> preſerued harmeleſſe: I hu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>bly thanke thee, for that it hath pleaſed thy goodneſſe ſo to take care for me thy vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>profitable ſerua<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t, this night paſt, that thou haſt both ſafely kept me from all mine enemies, and alſo giuen mée ſwéete ſléepe, vnto the great comfort of my bodie. I far<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther entirely beſeech thée moſt mercifull and ſwéete father, to ſhewe the like kindneſſe towardes me this day in preſeruing my bodie &amp;</p>
               <gap reason="missing" resp="#OXF" extent="2 pages">
                  <desc>〈2 pages missing〉</desc>
               </gap>
            </div>
            <div type="prayer">
               <pb facs="tcp:6059:9"/>
               <head>For Sunday, or the Sabboth. <hi>Morning Prayer.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>
                  <hi>O</hi> Gracious Lord God, and heauenly Father, I humblie beſéech thée in Chriſt ſo to ſanctifie me tho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>roughout in body, ſoule, and ſpirit, that I may religiouſly kéep and ſanctifie this Sab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bath vnto thee, according to thy holy word, not thinking therein mine own thoughts, nor ſpeaking mine owne words, nor doing mine own works, but thinking, ſpeak<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing
<pb facs="tcp:6059:10"/> and doing that which is agréeable to thy bleſſed will: Giue me grace, carefully to frequent the publike aſſem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>blies of thy Saints, and dili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gently to profite by all holy exerciſes there. Graunt me a religious heart to conſent to the praiers of the Church, and an attentiue minde, to heare and vnderſtand the good things of truth and life, that ſhalbe deliuered to mee out of thy word. And aſſiſt me ſo further, y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> when I ſhal
<pb facs="tcp:6059:10"/> depart from thy people, I may call mine owne heart to account in the thinges I haue heard, and may con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fer chriſtianlie with others, for the ſtrengthening of our faith in our hearts, and for a glorious confeſſion of the ſame with our mouthes, to y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> euerlaſting praiſe of thy glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rious name, and the eternall ſaluation of our ſoules, through Ieſus Chriſt thy deare ſon, &amp; our only media<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tor and aduocate. So be it.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="prayer">
               <pb facs="tcp:6059:11"/>
               <head>A generall Morning prayer.</head>
               <p>
                  <hi>O</hi> Almightie God and our moſt mercifull fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther in Ieſus Chriſt, I con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſe and acknowledge that I am a miſerable &amp; a wret<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ched ſinner, and haue mani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fold waies moſt grieuouſly tranſgreſſed thy moſt godly and bleſſed commaunde<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mentes, through wicked thoughts, vngodly luſtes,
<pb facs="tcp:6059:11"/> ſinfull words and déedes, all my whole life.</p>
               <p>In ſinne was I concei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued and borne, and there is no goodneſſe in mée, inſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>much that if thou ſhouldeſt enter into thy narrow iudg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment with mée, iudging mée according vnto the ſame, I were not able to ſuffer or a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bide it, but muſt needes pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſh, and be damned for euer. So little helpe, comfort, or ſucour is there either in me, or in any other creature
<pb facs="tcp:6059:12"/> whatſoeuer. Only this is my co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>fort, O heauenly father, y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> thou diddeſt not ſpare thy only &amp; dearely beloued Son, but diddeſt giue him vp vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the moſt bitter &amp; moſt vile and ſlaunderous death of the Croſſe for mee, that ſo hee might in his obedience pay the ranſome for my ſinnes, ſatisfie thy iudgement, ſtill and pacifie thy wrath, reco<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cile mée vnto thée againe, &amp; purchaſe mée thy grace and fauour, and euerla<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſting life.</p>
               <pb facs="tcp:6059:12"/>
               <p>Wherefore through the merites of his moſt bitter death and paſſion, &amp; through his innocent bloudſhedding, I beſéech thee, O heauenly Father, that thou wilt vouchſafe to bee gracious &amp; mercifull vnto mee, to for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giue and pardon me all my ſinnes, to lighten my heart with thy holy Spirit, to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>new, confirme and ſtreng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>then mee with a right and ſtedfaſt faith, and to enflame mee in loue towardes thee
<pb facs="tcp:6059:13"/> and my neighbour for thy ſake, that I may henceforth with a willing and a glad heart walke as it becom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>meth mee, in the obedience of thy moſt godly and moſt bleſſed Commandements, and ſo glorifie and praiſe thée euerlaſtingly, and alſo that I may with a frée con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcience, &amp; a quiet ſpirit in al manner of temptations, af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>flictions and neceſſities, and euen in the very pangs of death, boldly &amp; faithfully ſay:</p>
               <pb facs="tcp:6059:13"/>
               <p>I beleeue in God the Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther almighty, maker of hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen and earth. And in Ie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſus Chriſt his onely Sonne our Lord, which was con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiued by the holy Ghoſt, borne of the virgin Mary. Suffered vnder Ponce Pi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>late. Was crucified, dead, and buried. Hée deſcended into hell. The third day hée roſe againe from the dead. Hee aſcended into Heauen, and ſitteth on the right hand of God the Father almigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie,
<pb facs="tcp:6059:14"/> from thence he ſhal come to iudge the quicke and the dead. I beléeue in the holy Ghoſt. The holy Catho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>like Church. The commu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nion of Saints. The for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giueneſſe of ſinnes. The re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſurrection of the bodie. And the life euerlaſting. Amen.</p>
               <p>But (O Lord) heauenly Father, to comfort my ſelfe in afflictions &amp; temptations, w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> aſſured féeling of theſe Articles of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Chriſtia<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> faith it is not in my power: for
<pb facs="tcp:6059:14"/> faith is thy gift. And there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore foraſmuch as thou wilt be praied vnto, and called vpon for it, I come vnto thée to pray and beſéech thée, both for that &amp; for al my other ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſities, bodily and ſpiritu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>all, euen as thy dearely be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>loued ſonne our Sauiour Chriſt Ieſus himſelfe hath taught vs, and from the very bottome of my heart, I cry and ſay vnto thée.</p>
               <p>Our Father, which art in heaue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, halowed be thy name.</p>
               <pb facs="tcp:6059:15"/>
               <p>Thy kingdome come.</p>
               <p>Thy will bée done, in earth as it is in heauen.</p>
               <p>Giue vs this day our dailie bread.</p>
               <p>And forgiue vs our treſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paſſes, as we forgiue them that treſpaſſe againſt vs.</p>
               <p>And lead vs not into temp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tation.</p>
               <p>But deliuer vs from euill.</p>
               <p>For thine is the kingdome, the power, and the glorie, for euer and euer, Amen.</p>
               <gap reason="missing" resp="#OXF" extent="2 pages">
                  <desc>〈2 pages missing〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb facs="tcp:6059:15"/>
               <p>vnto the lappe of thy pitie. For loe thou art my hope and truſt, in whom I onely repoſe my ſelfe, hauing in thee ful confidence and faith, ſo that now I may ſay with a very faithfull heart, tru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſting in thy mercie: I be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>léeue in thee, O God the Father, in thee O God the Sonne, and in thee O God the holy Ghoſt, thrée per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons and one true, and alſo verie God, beſides whom I acknowledge none other
<pb facs="tcp:6059:16"/> God in heauen aboue, nor in earth beneath: And yet I poore ſinner cannot but accuſe my ſelfe vnto thee (deare Father) that I haue fore and grieuouſly offended thy almightie goodneſſe and Maieſtie, in the committing of mine exceeding grieuous and manifold ſins and wic<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kednes. For I haue not kept the leaſt of thy moſt godly and bleſſed com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maundementes, like as thy righteouſnes may require &amp;
<pb facs="tcp:6059:16"/> indéed doth dema<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſame of me, I haue not (I ſay) honou<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>red thee like my God, dread thée like my Lord, loued thée like my father, nor truſted in thee like my creator &amp; my ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uiour. Thy holy and dread<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful name, vnto which al glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry &amp; honour belongeth, haue I vſed in vaine. I haue not ſanctified the Sabboth day with workes which bee ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceptable to thée, nor inſtruc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted my neighbour in vertue accordingly. I haue not ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nored
<pb facs="tcp:6059:17"/> my parents, nor bin obedient vnto the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, through whom (as by an inſtrume<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t) thou haſt wrought my com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ming into this world.</p>
               <p>The high powers and rulers, which receiue au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thoritie of thee, I haue not willingly obeyed. I haue not kept my heart pure and cleane from malice and manſlaughter: yea, had not thy grace and mercy defended mee the better, I ſhould haue committed the
<pb facs="tcp:6059:17"/> verie deede alſo. I likewiſe am not pure from theft, nor from adulterie, nor fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> falſe witneſſe bearing, but haue in my heart and mind wiſhed and deſired my nighbours goods and thinges: I haue followed the great Prince of this Worlde Sathan, which hath been a lyer from the beginning, in concu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piſcence of the fleſh, in pride of liuing, in deceiptfulnes, in lecherie, in hatred, and al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo enuie, in backbiting, in
<pb facs="tcp:6059:18"/> deſpaire, and alſo miſbeléefe. And as I haue abuſed my will &amp; vnderſtanding, which are faculties and powers of my ſoule: ſo my ſenſes alſo, which thou haſt giuen mee to vſe to thy glorie, and my neighbours good, and mine own lawfull delight, I haue miſuſed and miſpent, in hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring, ſéeing, ſmelling, taſting, and feeling alſo, things that I ſhould not, or elſe ſuffring the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> to be too viole<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tly caried to things I might haue vſed.</p>
               <pb facs="tcp:6059:18"/>
               <p>But in what manner ſoe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer that I haue offended and ſinned againſt thy eternall Maieſtie, (for no man kno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>weth throughly his ſinnes, as the Prophet witneſſeth) whether it hath béen by day or elſe by night, yea euen from my childhood vnto this day, were it in workes, wordes, or thoughts, ſecret<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, or openly, O my merci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full God, I am ſorie for it, euen from the very bottome of my heart, yea my ſoule
<pb facs="tcp:6059:19"/> mourneth for very ſorowe, moſt mercifull Father, that I am not a thouſand times more ſorie than I am: how<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>beit, in token of great repen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tance, though all hearts bée knowne well enough vnto thée, I doe knocke &amp; ſtrike my breaſt, and ſay in bitter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe of heart and ſoule, Lord GOD the Father, Sonne, and holy Ghoſt, haue mercie. Spare mee of thine infinite mercie (deare Lord) now and all the daies
<pb facs="tcp:6059:19"/> of my life, &amp; let me bee made partakers of thine abundant grace, in ſuch ſort that I may chaunge my ſinfull life, and put thou out of mee the olde man, w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> al his concupiſences and luſtes: graunting mee grace dayly to die vnto the world, and that the world may bée crucified vnto mee and I ſo dayly goe forward in newnes of life. Streng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>then mee O Lord, in a true humble heart, in ſound loue, hope, and truſt in thée: giue
<pb facs="tcp:6059:20"/> my ſoule grace to deſire, in thée onely to reioyce and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe my ſelfe, &amp; that I may vtterly renounce and for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſake the vaine aſſiſtance of this world, ſo y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> thou mayſt finde me readie to méete thée in ioy, and the right vſe of al thy gifts, with the good ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uant in y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> mid night of death which ſhall ſuddenly ſteale vpon me like a theefe, ere I beware. Be thou to me at that time of neede (O Lord) a tower of ſtrength, a place
<pb facs="tcp:6059:20"/> of refuge, and a God to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fend mee euery manner of way, and namely againſt y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> face of the feend, who like a roring lion will be then rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy to deuoure me, &amp; againſt deſperation, which then wil be ready to grieue &amp; aſſault me.</p>
               <p>Let the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> thy comfort cleaue faſt vnto mee, thy mercie kéepe mée, and thy grace guide me. Then eſpecially recouer againe Lord God the Father, that which thy
<pb facs="tcp:6059:21"/> puiſſant might hath ſhapen. Fetch then againe Lord GOD the Sonne, that which thou haſt ſo wiſely gouerned, and bought with thy precious bloud. Take againe thou Lord God holy Ghoſt, that which thou haſt kept &amp; preſerued ſo louing<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly in this region of ſinne and vale of miſerie, three perſo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s and one very GOD, vnto whom be praiſe and honour for euer and euer. Amen,</p>
            </div>
            <div type="prayer">
               <pb facs="tcp:6059:21"/>
               <head>A Pſalme wherein the ſinner deſireth ot bee heard of God.</head>
               <p>HOwe long (O Lord) ſhall my mind be preſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed downe with painefull ſorrowes?</p>
               <p>How long (O God) wilt thou reiect my prayers which daylie I powre out before thée? wilt thou Lord heare me at no time, or wilt thou now ceaſe to ſhew mercie?</p>
               <p>Haſt thou (O Lord) caſt
<pb facs="tcp:6059:22"/> me away for euer, and wilt thou neuer hereafter bee pleaſed with me?</p>
               <p>Thy hand is not weakned but it may helpe, and thine eares are not ſtopped that they ſhould refuſe to heare.</p>
               <p>I beſéech thée (O my God) for Ieſus Chriſtes ſake to regard y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> teares that fall: &amp; let the ſighings and inward deſires of my heart, mooue &amp; incline thée to heare mee, I haue béen a ſtubborne &amp; fro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward childe to thée, I haue
<pb facs="tcp:6059:22"/> not feared thée, but haue béen euer diſobedient &amp; ſtub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>borne againſt thee.</p>
               <p>I am in priſon and bound in fetters of ſorrow, and ſo ſhalbe til thou with thy gra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cious preſence ſhalt vouch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſafe to viſite mee, and bring me againe to libertie &amp; ioy.</p>
               <p>Keepe thy mercie there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore for me always, O Lord, and y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> couenant which thou haſt made with mée, oh let it be ſurely performed.</p>
               <p>Keepe mee, Lord, from
<pb facs="tcp:6059:23"/> ſinne, and ſo ſhall I dread neither death nor hell; and as thou haſt béen alwayes mercifull to penitent ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ners, ſo now good Lord for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giue me my ſinnes.</p>
               <p>Keepe my heart to thee, and then ſhall it reioyce in thy mercie, becauſe thou haſt looked on mee, and haſt regarded my ſoule in my great diſtreſſe.</p>
               <p>Let mee neuer hereafter goe away from thy waies, and leaue me not now in the
<pb facs="tcp:6059:23"/> déepenes of my troubles.</p>
               <p>Loe now be the daies of health and grace, now is the accepted time, for in death who remembreth thee O Lord? or in hell who ſhall praiſe thee?</p>
               <p>Lord beholde therefore my weakneſſe and frailneſſe beſt knowne vnto thee: and looke downe from heauen vpon the ſorrow and heaui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes of me thy poore creature.</p>
               <p>Mollifie my heart (O Lord GOD) that I may
<pb facs="tcp:6059:24"/> returne to thee, and walke in thy waies: for I haue wandred too long in the way of ſinners.</p>
               <p>Make a perpetuall league with me that thou wilt put thy feare into my heart, that I neuer ſwarue from thée againe.</p>
               <p>O Lord my prayers be e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer vnto thee, let thy anger bee turned from mee, that I may finde fauour in thy ſight.</p>
               <p>O Lord, looke thou not
<pb facs="tcp:6059:24"/> vpon y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> hardnes of my hart, but as thou art a mercifull God, ſo now bee merci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full vnto me, and forgiue me that wherein I haue offen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded thée.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="prayer">
               <head>A Prayer.</head>
               <p>MOſt righteous God, and merifull father in Chriſt, for thy great mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cie ſake hearken to theſe my humble prayers which I make before thée, and conſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>der
<pb facs="tcp:6059:25"/> Lorde, the deſires and thoughts of my hart. Let my loud cryings come vnto thée, &amp; let mine vnfained prayers enter into thine eares. Heare me (O Lord) for I am deſtitute of thy helpe. Take care for my ſoule, ſaue me thy ſeruant which wholly truſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth in thee. Haue mercie O Lord, haue mercie vpon me, for I will neuer ceaſe cry<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing vnto thée for thy helpe and mercie. In the day time <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ll I call on thee, and in
<pb facs="tcp:6059:25"/> the night my crie ſhall not be hid from thee.</p>
               <p>O thou God of the Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uens, and maker of all crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures, heare me a moſt wret<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ched ſinner, calling on thee, and take away from mee all my ſinnes, and make ſtedfaſt my faith and confidence in thée, &amp; in thy merciful pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſes, y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> I putting my truſt in them, may haue, as thou haſt promiſed, euerlaſting life, thorough Chriſt Ieſus thy Son our Lord. Amen.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="prayer">
               <pb facs="tcp:6059:26"/>
               <head>A Pſalme that may bee ſayd. <hi>For Euening Prayer.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>COnſider and heare mee (O Lord my God) lighten the eies of my ſoule, that I ſléepe not in death: for if I bee caſt downe, they that trouble me, wil reioyce at it.</p>
               <p>Defend mee therefore (O God) from the way of the vngodly, and out of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> hands of the vnrighteous and cru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> man, deliuer me.</p>
               <pb facs="tcp:6059:26"/>
               <p>Euen in thy feare doe I worſhip (O Lord) toward thy holy temple: bee merci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full vnto me, and heare the requeſt of my heart.</p>
               <p>For happy are they whom thou heareſt, and regardeſt in the needfull time of trou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble.</p>
               <p>Haue mercy vpon me (O God) haue merce vpon me: euen as thou haſt promiſed to them that loue thy name.</p>
               <p>I will call on thée, O Lord my ſtrength, I <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <pb facs="tcp:6059:27"/> truſt in thée, O thou ground of my ſaluation.</p>
               <p>Keepe thy ſeruant there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore (O Lord) from preſump<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuous ſins, leſt they get the dominion ouer mee: and ſo ſhall I be vndefiled, &amp; inno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cent from the great offence.</p>
               <p>Let I beſéech thee (O Lord) the words of my mouth, and the meditation of my heart bee alwaies acceptable in thy ſight, O Lord God my ſtrength and my redéemer.</p>
               <p>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>t my prayers bee ſet
<pb facs="tcp:6059:27"/> forth in thy ſight as the in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cenſe, and let the lifting vp of my hands be an euening ſacrifice.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>O</hi> Lord graunt mee thy light, that I being de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liuered from the darkneſſe of ſinne, may come to the very light which is Chriſt.</p>
               <p>Turne thee vnto mee (O Lord) and ſhew mee the light of thy countenance.</p>
               <p>Yea Lord heare my praier alſo I beſéech thée. And let my crie come vnto thée.</p>
               <pb facs="tcp:6059:28"/>
               <p>
                  <hi>O</hi> Lord God, I beſéech thée for Chriſt Ieſus ſake to lighten my darknes, both outward and inward, &amp; of thy great goodneſſe to deliuer me from all the dan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gers of this night either bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dily or ſpirituall, that thou being my ſauiour in watch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, and my kéeper in ſlee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ping, I may wake in Chriſt, and reſt in peace, through thy ſonne Ieſu Chriſt, who liueth and raigneth with thee in vnitie of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> holy ghoſt
<pb facs="tcp:6059:28"/> world without end. Amen.</p>
               <p>O Lord, into thy handes I commend my ſpirit, for thou haſt redeemed mee (O Lord) thou God of truth.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="prayer">
               <head>A prayer of a ſinner to be ſayd dayly before hee goeth about any worldly buſines.</head>
               <p>
                  <hi>O</hi> My celeſtiall Father, be now mercifull vnto mée thy repentant ſinfull ſeruant, fled from mine ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies to thy helpe and ſuc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cour. Impute not vnto me
<pb facs="tcp:6059:29"/> my ſinnes for Chriſts ſake, for I haue heard thy Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>therly voyce, and yet it ſoun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deth daylie in my eares out of heauen, promiſing mee, and affirming co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſtantly thy ſelfe to be appeaſed, pleaſed, and at one with mee for thy Sonnes ſake, whome thou commandeſt me to heare and beléeue, whom I am ſure is made of thee, my righteouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes, my ſatiſfactio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, my recon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciliation, my peace maker, my mediator &amp; interceſſor,
<pb facs="tcp:6059:29"/> with his praier, my fulfiller of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> law, my deliuerer, &amp; my whole holy acco<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>pliſher of all my iuſt deſires, &amp; my Sauior Chriſt Ieſus, God &amp; man, in whoſe name this day I at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tempt &amp; take in hand all my iuſt doings according to my vocation, for his glory: &amp; my neighbours profit, deſiring thy gracious goodnes moſt merciful Lord and father for thy dearly beloued ſons ſake to proſperit, &amp; to giue it hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pie encreaſe, &amp; whatſoeuer
<pb facs="tcp:6059:30"/> I take in hand according to thy will, graunt me grace to finiſh the ſame. O holy fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, bleſſe all things I take in hand, with thy bleſſed in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>creaſe, and let mee not ſéeke mine owne will, but euer to pray that thy will be fulfil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led in all thinges, now and for euer. So be it.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Thou maieſt, if thou wilt, af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter this ſay the Lords Prayer. And ſo hauing co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mended thy ſelfe to almighty God, maieſt
<pb facs="tcp:6059:30"/> fall to ſome honeſt and vertu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous exerciſe according to thy calling: but whatſoeuer thou doeſt, doe it with purenes of heart, and with ſinglenes of eie, yea ſo doe it, as though God were preſent and looked vppon thee, as vndoubtedly he doth.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div type="prayer">
               <head>A Prayer.</head>
               <p>HEare vs O heauenly King, Father of mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cie, our life, our ſwéetnes, our hope: for vnto thée doe we crie euen we which are the baniſhed children of <hi>Eua,</hi>
                  <pb facs="tcp:6059:31"/> vnto thee doe we ſigh, wée<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ping and wayling in this vale of lamentation: come therefore our aduocate, caſt vpon vs thoſe mercifull eyes of thine, and after this our baniſhment, ſhew to vs the glorious light in thy hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uenly kingdome. O merci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full, O holy, O ſwéete Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uiour, in all our troubles, and heauineſſe, O Ieſu our health and glorie, ſuccour vs. Amen.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="prayer">
               <pb facs="tcp:6059:31"/>
               <head>Another Prayer.</head>
               <p>
                  <hi>O</hi> Ieſu Chriſt the Son of God, our Redéemer, which deiectedſt and hum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bledſt thy ſelfe from that glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rious ſtate and ſhape of thy Godhead, to the ſhape of our vile ſeruitude, becauſe thou wouldeſt reconcile vs (be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the children of wrath and damnation) to thy fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, &amp; ſo make vs the chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren of grace: wee beſéech thée graunt vs ſuch an excel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lent meaſure of thy grace
<pb facs="tcp:6059:32"/> that wee may euer followe euen thée thy ſelfe in all bleſſed obedience, and may euer finde and féele thée to be our preſent mediator before our father, for all ghoſtly giftes, whom wee acknow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge with perfect faith to be our Sauiour, which art the liuing God with the fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther and the holy Ghoſt, li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing and raigning without end. Amen.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="prayer">
               <pb facs="tcp:6059:32"/>
               <head>A Prayer.</head>
               <p>
                  <hi>O</hi> Pitifull Lord God, al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wayes ſhewing thy mercie vpon me a grieuous ſinner, I humblie acknow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge the ſame, yet Lord notw<hi rend="sup">t</hi>ſtanding I cannot but hartily pray thée to heare my prayer: though I haue bin a ſinner, I am now tho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rough thy grace ſorie there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore, and purpoſe by thy goodnes &amp; aſſiſtance to take no more pleaſure therein,
<pb facs="tcp:6059:33"/> but am glad and willing to exerciſe the trueth, and to forſake all vaineglorie. Wherefore therein I hum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bly pray thée to fortifie mée with thy grace, to withſta<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d my ſecret enemie in all my temptations: and to aſſiſt mee ſo, that thy moſt holy ſpirit of ſapience and vnder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding, may haue conti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nuall dwelling in mee, direct mee vnto the obedience of thy pleaſure and will, that ſo I may at the laſt inherite
<pb facs="tcp:6059:33"/> thine eternall reſt.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="prayer">
               <head>Another Prayer.</head>
               <p>OMnipotent and mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cifull God, Father e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ternall, which doeſt not de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpiſe ſinners, bewayling with contrite heart the of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fences, which they haue committed againſt thy high Maieſtie, wée pray thée by thy grace to drawe vs néere to thée and heare our pray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers, and forgiue vs our of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fences, comfort vs in our af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>flictions:
<pb facs="tcp:6059:34"/> and forgiue Lord them that oppreſſe vs, and graunt that our ghoſtly e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nemie haue no power to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uour vs, as he deſireth, but that we ſtrongly withſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding his fraudes and ſnares to our comfort, may die in the true Catholique faith, and reſt with thée eternally our Lord Ieſu Chriſt. Amen.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="prayer">
               <head>Sundrie holy petitions to our Sauiour Ieſus Chriſt.</head>
               <pb facs="tcp:6059:34"/>
               <p>LOrd Ieſu haue mercie on mée, and forgiue mee my great offences, which I haue done in thy ſight.</p>
               <p>Grant mée grace alſo for the loue of thée, to deſpiſe all ſinne, and worldly vanitie. Lord Ieſu inable mee to w<hi rend="sup">c</hi>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtand and to ouercome the temptation of ſinne, and the malice of my Ghoſtly ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mie, to ſpend my time in vertue and labour accepta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble to thée.</p>
               <p>Lord Ieſu ſtrengthen me
<pb facs="tcp:6059:35"/> in ſoule and bodie, to per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forme the works of godly<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes and vertue, to the glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry and praiſe of thy name, and that afterwards I may come to euerlaſting ioy and felicitie.</p>
               <p>Graunt me a ſtedfaſt pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe, mercifull Ieſus, to a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mend my life, and recom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pence thoſe yeares which I haue miſpent, to the diſplea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure of thée, in euil thoughts, delectations, conſentings, words, workes, and euill
<pb facs="tcp:6059:35"/> cuſtomes, and alſo in b<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king thy lawes: whereby I haue deſerued damnation.</p>
               <p>And good Lord inlighten me ſo with thy ghoſtly wiſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome, that I may knowe thy goodnes, &amp; thoſe things which are moſt acceptable to thée: and confirme me ſo with thy grace, that I may giue good examples to all men. Make me profitable that none be hurt by mee: &amp; guide me to help thoſe with good counſaile which haue
<pb facs="tcp:6059:36"/> offended thee: make me pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceede from vertue to vertue, vntill I ſhall cléerely ſée thée in thy Maieſtie. Let mee not returne to any of my wonted ſinnes, ſpecially thoſe ſinnes which I haue ſorrowed for, and by con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſion haue iuſtly accuſed my ſelfe of.</p>
               <p>Let not the horrible ſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tence of endleſſe death, nor the terrible iudgement of damnation, nor thy wrath, ire, and indignation (mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cifull
<pb facs="tcp:6059:36"/> Lord) fall vpon mée. But let thy mercie and me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rits (my Sauiour) euer bée betwéene them and me.</p>
               <p>Lord Ieſu graunt mee grace to flie euill company, and when I come among them, for thy paſſion I be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſéech thée to preſerue mee, that no occaſion of any ey<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther mine owne, or their ſin ouercome mée, and ſend mée ghoſtly comfort &amp; ſtrength by y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> true loue of thy worde, and power of thy ſpirit, ſhed
<pb facs="tcp:6059:37"/> abroad into my heart. Kéepe my mouth (good Lord) from ſlaunderous ſpeaking, ly<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, falſe witneſſe bearing, curſing, ſwearing, vncha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritable chidinges, diſſolute laughing &amp; words of vanity, make me, bleſſed Lord, with child-like reuere<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce to reme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber, that thou preſently heareſt mee, which of al my words ſhalt iudge me.</p>
               <p>Lord Ieſu make me to per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeuer in the bleſſed ſeruice of thée, in religious exerciſe, &amp;
<pb facs="tcp:6059:37"/> all holie and vertuous af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>faires. Lord keepe my ſoule and bodie, make me flée ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full delectation, and patient<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly to ſuffer iniuries and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bukes, as which my diſobe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dient heart to thée haue de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerued more the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> all men can inflict or lay vpo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> me: prouide (good Lord) that ſtate of life for mee, which thou knoweſt ſhall moſt tend to thy honour and my eternall felicitie.</p>
               <p>Lord Ieſu graunt mee
<pb facs="tcp:6059:38"/> grace at all times, but ſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cially in the time of prayer to fixe my minde on thée, &amp; then alſo effectually to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>member my wretchedneſſe, &amp; faithfully to call for helpe of thée. Yea, good Lord, giue me grace to order my life, and y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> workes of my body &amp; ſoule with actuall intent to pleaſe thée, that through thy merites and mercie, at the end I may obtaine the reward of thy infinite ioy, and eternall felicitie. Let
<pb facs="tcp:6059:38"/> the water and bloud which can from thy bleſſed heart, bee powerfull to waſh my ſoule from ſinne and iniqui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie, and to purchaſe mee a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bunda<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce of thy grace, faith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fully to ſerue thée. O my Lord, my might, my life, my light, lead me, féede me, and ſpéede me in the pilgrimage of this mortalitie: graunt me (O Lord) by the merits of thy paſſion, and power of thy moſt excellent and glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rious godhead, whatſoe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer
<pb facs="tcp:6059:39"/> thy Wiſedome knoweth moſt expedie<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t for me, which howſoeuer in my miſerable life I am moſt vnworthy of, yet vouchſafe them vnto me, all the time of my pil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>grimage, but ſpecially at the houre of death; when I ſhall be accuſed before thée, haue mercie on mee, breake my froward heart, and make it obedient to thée. Preſerue me alſo good Lord, from ſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>daine and vnprouided death, and of thy owne ſingular
<pb facs="tcp:6059:39"/> grace and goodneſſe, graunt mee theſe ſupplications in this prayer, which now I haue made to thée according to thy will. Yea by thine owne mediation, purchaſe for mee, and beſtow vpon mee a holy life, and bleſſed ending, and grant I beſéech thée, after my bodily death, euerlaſting life with end<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſſe bliſſe and felicitie, tho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>row thy merites and bitter paſſion: O Lord Ieſu, who with the Father and the ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly
<pb facs="tcp:6059:40"/> Spirit, liueſt and raigneſt euer one God, world with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out end.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Holy Trinitie one very God, haue mercie on me. Amen.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div type="prayer">
               <head>A deuout prayer to our Lord Ieſu Chriſt.</head>
               <p>
                  <hi>O</hi> My ſoueraigne Lord Ieſu, the very ſonne of almightie God, and of the moſt cleane, and glorious virgin Marie, who ſufferedſt bitter death for my ſake, and all mankind, and diddeſt riſe
<pb facs="tcp:6059:40"/> againe the third day: I be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeech thée Lord haue mercie vpon me, that am a wret<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ched ſinner, but yet thy crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture: and for thy precious paſſion ſaue mee, and kéepe me from al perils bodily and ghoſtly, and ſpecially from all things that might turne to thy diſpleaſure. And with all my heart I thanke thee moſt mercifull Lord, for thy great mercies that thou haſt ſhewed me in the great dan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gers that I haue béen in, as
<pb facs="tcp:6059:41"/> well in my ſoule as in my bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy: and that thy grace and endleſſe mercie hath euer kept me, ſpared me, and ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued me, from the houre of my birth to this preſent time. For theſe I ſay, and al other thy mercies, I humb<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lie thanke thée, Lord Ieſus Chriſt, further deſiring thée that thy mercie may pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerue me alway. And I crie thée mercie with all my whole heart, for my great offences, for my great vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kindnes,
<pb facs="tcp:6059:41"/> &amp; for all my wret<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ched and ſinfull life, and for this in particular, that I haue not, or cannot leade my ſelfe as becommeth thy ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uant. I thanke thée alſo with all my heart my moſt gracious Lord, for the bene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fites and graces that thou haſt giuen mee ſo largely in this world afore many o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther of thy creatures, vpon whom (if it had béene ſo thy good pleaſure) thou mighteſt a thouſand times better
<pb facs="tcp:6059:42"/> haue beſtowed them, than vpon me. But moſt graci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous Lord, I wot and know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge verily, that it com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>meth of thée: wherefore with all my heart I thanke thee continually crying and ſaying: all honour, praiſe, and glorie bee vnto thée O Ieſu, with the Father and the holy Ghoſt, for euer and euer. Amen.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="prayer">
               <head>Another prayer for an houſeholder.</head>
               <pb facs="tcp:6059:42"/>
               <p>
                  <hi>O</hi> Lord GOD almigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie, moſt mercifull and heauenly father, thorough Chriſt I fréely confeſſe, that thou art my life, my ſoule and my bodie: yea al the good which I haue and all what<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoeuer is mine, haſt thou gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen vnto me, &amp; that of thine owne ſingular grace and goodnes. Now ſith of thee I haue receiued it, and in me there is corruption to abuſe it, make vpright and order thou (O Lord God of hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen)
<pb facs="tcp:6059:43"/> all that is in my houſe. And teach mee and mine to handle and guide all theſe outward things, after thy godlie will, we being there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by more and more prouoked to loue thée, and in thée, and for thée, euery one of vs to profit another. I ſay vnto thée, I beléeue, Lorde helpe my vnbeléefe. And yet in this weakenes I cannot but intreate thée, not to forſake me, nor my wife, my chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren, nor any of my houſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>holde.
<pb facs="tcp:6059:43"/> Defend vs Lord from ſin before thée, from ſhame in the world, and from ſick<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes in our ſelues, according to thy good pleaſure. Send vs thy holy Angell to guide and guarde vs, that ſo wee may be defended in y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> whole courſe of our liues, and may be lead forth the right way, ſo as we may not talke, doe, or thinke any thought a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt thy holy commaun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dements and will, but there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>after to liue, worſhipping
<pb facs="tcp:6059:44"/> thée, and praiſing thée for e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uermore, thorough Chriſt Ieſus our Lord thy onely welbeloued Sonne. Amen.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Bleſſed be the Father, the Son and the holy Ghoſt. Let vs praiſe him and exalt him world without end. Amen.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div type="prayer">
               <head>An other Prayer.</head>
               <p>ALmightie GOD our heauenly Father in Ieſus Chriſt: wée vnfeined<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly confeſſe before thée that thy mercie and goodnes to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards
<pb facs="tcp:6059:44"/> vs is infinite, and without meaſure.</p>
               <p>It is thy mercie and no goodnes that is in vs or of vs which mooued thée to ſend into the worlde thine onely begotten and eternall Sonne, to take our nature vpon him, and therein to worke the myſterie of our redemption and ſaluation, as thou hadſt appointed, and ſpoken before by y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> mouthes of all thy Prophets which were from the beginning.
<pb facs="tcp:6059:45"/> And likewiſe it was thy bleſſed will, thy mercie and goodnes towardes vs, that thy heauenly Sonne did ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fer perſecution, trouble, and aduerſitie, was betraied of his owne friend and diſciple Iudas, traiterouſly taken &amp; caried awaie, to bée falſly ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuſed, and vniuſtly condem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned, to bee cruelly beaten &amp; ſcourged, and finally, with moſt ſcornefull rebukes, to be put to the moſt painfull &amp; ſhamefull death that could
<pb facs="tcp:6059:45"/> bée deuiſed. All this (O hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uenly Father) was doone through thy mercy and bleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed will for our ſakes, &amp; that not only to anſwere and ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſfie thy iuſt wrath and an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger which we had deſerued, and dayly doe deſerue, both for the offences of our firſt parents, &amp; our actuall tranſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>greſſing of thy holy comma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dements, but alſo to reſtore vs againe to thy grace and fauour, to indue vs with thy heauenly gifts, that wée
<pb facs="tcp:6059:46"/> might ſerue thée in holynes and righteouſnes all the dayes of our life: And fi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nally to make vs by the be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nefite of thy dearely beloued Sonnes paſſion, and alſo through y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> price of his moſt precious bloud, partners w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> him of his infinite, and vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpeakeable glory and bliſſe in heauen. Wherefore, O heauenly Father, wee bée<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſéech thée powre vppon vs thy holy ſpirit and make vs in our hearts clearely to ſée,
<pb facs="tcp:6059:46"/> comfortably to féele, and moſt ſtedfaſtly to beléeue this thine infinit gracious goodnes, ſhewed and giuen vnto vs in thine owne ſonne our Sauiour Ieſus Chriſt: and with this beliefe make vs to put all our confidence and hope of ſaluation in him alone, whom thou haſt ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pointed to bee our onely re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>déemer and Sauiour. Make vs alway readie and able to render vnto thée moſt hum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble and heartie thankes, for
<pb facs="tcp:6059:47"/> this thine incomprehenſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble mercy and goodnes to<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>wardes vs: finally, ſo to make vs profeſſe the death of thy dearely beloued Son, that wee renounce and for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſake all ſinne, yea, that wée may alwaies féele it in our ſelues, and plainely ſhew it forth to others, that wee a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſe with him in newnes of life, in righteouſnes, inno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cencie, and all true holines, &amp; after this life may raigne with him in euerlaſting glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie:
<pb facs="tcp:6059:47"/> heare vs O heauenly Father, for our Lord Ieſus Chriſtes ſake. Amen.</p>
               <p>ALmightie God our heauenly Father, wée beſéech thy gracious good<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes now and at all times ſo to aſſiſt vs, that like as thy onely begotten, and deare<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly beloued ſonne our Saui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>our Ieſus Chriſt, according to his bleſſed will, ſuffered death willingly, and bitter paſſion for our redemption,
<pb facs="tcp:6059:48"/> and ſaluation, hauing there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of foreſight, &amp; perfect know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge: ſo in like maner when it ſhall pleaſe thée ſo lay any croſſe, and afflictions vpon our backs, that we may both willinglie vndergoe it, &amp; pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiently beare it, &amp; powerfully ouercome it, to thy euerlaſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing glorie, other mens ſpiri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuall benefit, and our owne endleſſe ſaluation through Chriſt. Heare vs herein, O heaue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ly father, for our Lord Ieſus Chriſts ſake. Amen.</p>
               <pb facs="tcp:6059:48"/>
               <p>
                  <hi>O</hi> Our Sauiour and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>déemer Ieſus Chriſt, which in thy laſt Supper with the Apoſtles, didſt giue thy bleſſed bodie &amp; blood vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der the viſible elements of bread and wine, graunt vs grace wee beſéech thée, euer ſtedfaſtly to beléeue, and ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerely to acknowledge in this moſt bleſſed Sacrame<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t not onely thine infinite and Almightie power, but alſo thine incomprehenſible loue towards vs, yea aſſiſt ſo, that
<pb facs="tcp:6059:49"/> when we come to the parti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cipation of theſe bleſſed my<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſteries we may alway wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thily receiue the ſame, ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to thy holy ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nances in ſuch ſort, as that thereby we may alwaies ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine ſtrength of faith in the truth of thy promiſes, &amp; encreaſe of holines by the vniting of the ſpirit with thee our head, and by thee and thy ſpirite, with all the company of them that bee truely thine, which bee thy
<pb facs="tcp:6059:49"/> ſpirituall and myſticall bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>die, and our ſpirituall, and Chriſtian brethren.</p>
               <p>Herein heare vs O Chriſt our Sauiour for thy names ſake. Amen.</p>
               <p>ALmighty GOD and our moſt louing Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther in Chriſt, whoſe holy Apoſtle Peter preſuming of his owne power &amp; ſtrength did miſerably fall not onely in the deniall of his maiſter Chriſt, for feare of an hand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maide,
<pb facs="tcp:6059:50"/> but alſo in ſorſwea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring, and curſing himſelfe, if euer he knew him: grant vs grace we beſeech thee merci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cifull Father, that we neuer preſume of our own might &amp; power, but that being in our own harts humble &amp; lowly, and acknowledging our in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firmitie, frailtie, and weake<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes, we may euer in all our affaires, receiue at thy hand outward &amp; inward ſtrenght &amp; co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>fort alſo, and may there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by bée inabled vnto the ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceptable
<pb facs="tcp:6059:50"/> performance of thy holy and bleſſed will. Heare vs O heauenly Father, for our Lorde Ieſus Chriſts ſake. Amen.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>O</hi> Our bleſſed Sauiour Ieſus Chriſt, which in that great heauines of thy ſoule &amp; intolerable anguiſh, which thou ſuſtainedſt be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore thy paſſion, diddeſt fall down vpo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> thy face in praier vnto thy heauenly Father, giue vs grace alſo, &amp; the aide of thy holy ſpirite, that wee
<pb facs="tcp:6059:51"/> likewiſe in all heauineſſe of minde, and troubles of this world, may run euer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>more by moſt humble and conſtant prayer, vnto the onely ayd, ſtrength and com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fort of thée our heauenly fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, heare vs our Sauiour Chriſt, for thy names ſake. Amen.</p>
               <p>ALmighty God eternal father, we doe remem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber that in the condemnati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of thy onely and deare<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly
<pb facs="tcp:6059:51"/> beloued innocent Lambe, our Sauiour Ieſus Chriſt, the Iudge did ſitte, witneſſe was brought, Chriſt him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe was preſented and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demned, and all truth there was troden vnder foote, all vnrighteouſnes did raigne, and innocencie comdemned. In conſideration whereof we cannot but intreat thée, O moſt gracious Lord and Father, to graunt vnto our heads and rulers ſuch a no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>table meaſure of grace and
<pb facs="tcp:6059:52"/> aſſiſtance euen from thine owne ſelfe, that they may e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer in all their iudgements, iudge according to true iu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtice and equitie, without corruption, partialitie, and wicked diſſimulation, and that to the beating down of wickednes and ſinne, and to the maintenance of thine e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerlaſting truth, iuſtice, ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour and glorie. Heare vs our heauenly Father, for our Lord Ieſus Chriſts ſake. Amen.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="prayer">
               <pb facs="tcp:6059:52"/>
               <head>A prayer for truſt in God.</head>
               <p>
                  <hi>O</hi> Moſt gracious &amp; moſt wiſe guide, and our almightie Sauiour Ieſus Chriſt, who doeſt lead them the right way to immortall bleſſednes, which truly and vnfainedly truſting in thee, commit themſelues to thée, grant vs grace we pray thée, not only to ſée this, that we be blinde and féeble indeede, but alſo that we may ſo take and repute our ſelues: that
<pb facs="tcp:6059:53"/> ſo wee may not preſume of our ſelues, to ſée to our ſelues, but may alwaies wholie commit our ſelues vnto thee, to bee guyded by thee, and from thee may bee inabled ſo far to ſée, that al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>way wee may haue thée be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore our eies, to follow thee being our guide, to be ready at thy call moſt obediently, and to commit our ſelues wholy vnto thée, that thou which onely knoweſt the way, and art alone the
<pb facs="tcp:6059:53"/> way indéed mayeſt lead vs the ſame way to all heauen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly deſires. To thée with the Father and the holy Ghoſt, be glory for euer. Amen.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="prayer">
               <head>A prayer of any captiue, according to the forme of Dauid, when he was hid in the caue.</head>
               <p>WIth my voyce I crie to thée, afore thée I open my lamentati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, in thy boſome I diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cloſe
<pb facs="tcp:6059:54"/> the ſecret words of my heart, my dolours and griefs I ſhew vnto thee, my heart is almoſt like to bruſt, ſo great is my diſcomfiture. Thou knoweſt all my faſhi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons (O Lord) and thou ſéeſt well enough how y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> vngodly haue laid their ſnares for me.</p>
               <p>Loe, I caſt mine eyes on this ſide &amp; that ſide, as well on my friends as kinſfolkes: but all is in vaine, none of them all helpeth me. And a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gaine, I cannot run away, I
<pb facs="tcp:6059:54"/> am ſo laden and ouercharged with yrons. O Lord my ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ker, and father, vnto thée I crie, thou art mine onely ſhot-anker, defence &amp; helpe. Thou art my portion &amp; he<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritage in all countries, yea, I haue none other poſſeſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on but thée onely. To thee therefore I ſticke altoge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, knowing certainly that nothing can goe a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſſe with mee, when I am vnder the ſhadowe of thy wings, and thou guideſt me.
<pb facs="tcp:6059:55"/> Conſider then my lamenta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble complaint, behold howe I am lowe brought by the cruell purſuers, which bee much more of power than I am, defend me, deliuer me from all this priſon, &amp; hor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rible feare of ſinne &amp; death, y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> I may ſet out thy name. This once obtained, the godly folke ſhall flocke a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bout me, and ſhall not ſtint to giue thee thankes, when they ſée that thou riddeſt me forth of theſe dangers to the
<pb facs="tcp:6059:55"/> high praiſe of thy name.</p>
               <p>Lord bee mercifull vnto vs, take part with vs, then we ſhall for euer lift vp and magnify thy glorious name Amen.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="prayer">
               <head>A prayer for patience in trouble.</head>
               <p>HOw haſt thou O Lord humbled and plucked me downe? I dare now vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neath make my prayers vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to thée, for thou art angrie with me, but not without
<pb facs="tcp:6059:56"/> my deſeruing. Certainely I haue ſinned, Lord I will co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fes it, I wil not deny it. But O god pardo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> my treſpaſſes, releſe my debts, make me to féele again, and y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> effectually &amp; continually alſo thy grace within me, ſtop my wounds for I am all to plagued and beaten, yet Lord this not<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>withſtanding, I do abide pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiently, and giue my atten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>da<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce on thée, co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tinually wai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting for helpe at thy hands, &amp; that, not without ſom know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge
<pb facs="tcp:6059:56"/> &amp; beléefe of thy truth, for I haue receiued a token of thy fauour and grace to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wardes mée, I meane thy word of promiſe concerning Chriſt, who for me was of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fered on the Croſſe, for a ranſome, ſacrifice, and price for my ſins. Wherfore ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to that thy promiſe, defend mee Lord by thy right hand, and giue a gra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cious eare to my requeſtes, bee thou my ſtay in perils, for all mens ſtayes are but
<pb facs="tcp:6059:57"/> vaine. Beate downe there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore my enemies, thine own ſelfe with thy power, which art mine onely ayd and pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tector, O Lord God al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mighty. Amen.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="prayer">
               <head>The humble confeſſion of Iob in his moſt grieuous ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerſitie, and loſſe of goods, children and all. Iob. 1.</head>
               <p>NAked I came out of my Mothers wombe, and naked ſhall I returne againe: the Lord gaue, and
<pb facs="tcp:6059:57"/> the Lord hath taken away, as it hath pleaſed the Lord, ſo is it done: now bleſſed be y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> name of the Lord. Amen.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="prayer">
               <head>In great trouble of con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcience. Pſal. 143.</head>
               <p>LOrd heare my prayer, receiue my ſupplication, hearken to my plaint for thy righteouſnes.</p>
               <p>Trie not the law with thy ſeruants, for truly then ſhal no liuing man be found vnguiltie, yea, not one of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi>
                  <pb facs="tcp:6059:58"/> ſaints ſhould eſcape quit at the bar, vnleſſe thou graunt him thy gracious pardon, in ſo much as the very ſtarres be not pure and faulties be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore thée, in the Angels thou foundedſt ſin. O Lord mine enemies grieuouſly hunt my ſoule, they beate &amp; driue it downe, they thruſt it in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to darke dungeons, where fello<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s (conuict and condem<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ned to death) were wont to be kept, my ſpirit is ſorow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full, my heart is heauy &amp; ſad
<pb facs="tcp:6059:58"/> within my breaſt, to thée I hold vp my hands, requiring thee of mercie. For like as the dry ground longeth for a ſhower of raine, ſo my ſoule thinketh long til it hath thy help and ſuccour, heare mee therefore ſpéedily: if thou do not, I am in deſpaire, my ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit is all weary of this bon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dage. I haue bidden my life fare well. Wherefore (O God) hyde not thy face that I bee not likened to thoſe that be hurled into the pit
<pb facs="tcp:6059:59"/> of damnation: after this night of miſerie ouerpaſſed, let the pleaſant morning of comfort graciouſly ſhine vppon mee, that betimes I may heare and féele thy goodnes, for in thée is al my truſt: point me the way that I ſhall walke in, for if thou bee not my guide, I muſt néedes wander and ſtray out of the way.</p>
               <p>To thée (Lord) I lift vp my ſoule, and that with all mine heart. I beſéech thée
<pb facs="tcp:6059:59"/> take mee foorth of mine ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies handes.</p>
               <p>Thou onely art my ſuc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cour and ſauegard, teach me to worke whatſoeuer ſhall be thy pleaſure, for thou art my God, let thy good ſpirite conduct mée into the land of the liuing, raiſe vp my ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rite within mee: for thy names ſake bring me foorth of all theſe troubles, for thy righteouſnes deliuer mee: deſtroy mine enemies as thou art gracious &amp; fauou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable
<pb facs="tcp:6059:60"/> towards me.</p>
               <p>Thoſe that wil worke me any ſorrow or griefe, pluck foorth of the way, for I am thy ſerua<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t, for thy ſake ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fer I al this hurly burly. As thou art God almighty and moſt mercifull, ſo helpe thou me, thy vnworthy ſeruant, who ſtand in neede of al ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>portation from thee.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="prayer">
               <head>A prayer in aduerſity.</head>
               <p>
                  <hi>O</hi> Lord God, without whoſe will and plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure,
<pb facs="tcp:6059:60"/> a ſparrow doth not fall on the ground, ſeeing it is thy wil and bleſſed ordina<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce that I ſhould be in this mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerie and aduerſitie, ſeeing alſo thou doſt puniſh mee with aduerſitie, not to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtroy and caſt me away, but to call me to repentance and ſaue me: for whom thou doſt loue, him doſt thou chaſten. Furthermore, ſéeing afflicti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on &amp; aduerſitie worketh pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce, &amp; who ſo patie<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tly hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reth tribulatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, is made like
<pb facs="tcp:6059:61"/> vnto our Sauiour Chriſt our head. Finally, ſéeing that in all trubulation and aduerſitie, wee are in aſſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rance of comfort at thy gra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cious hands, for thou com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mandeſt mee to call vpon thée in y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> time of tribulation haſt promiſed to heare and ſuccour me: graunt me ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore (O almighty God) and mercifull father, in al trou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble and aduerſitie general<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, and euen in this particu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>larlie to bee quiet without
<pb facs="tcp:6059:61"/> diſcouragement, and pati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ent without diſtruſtfulnes, that ſo I may haue grace to praiſe and magnifie thée and to put my whole truſt and confidence in thee: becauſe thou neuer forſakeſt them that truſt in thee-but wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>keſt all for the beſt to them that loue thee, and ſeeke the glorie of thy name. To thee be glorie for euer. Amen.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="prayer">
               <pb facs="tcp:6059:62"/>
               <head>A thankſgiuing, and pray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er alſo to be vſed, in the time of proſperitie.</head>
               <p>
                  <hi>I</hi> Giue thankes vnto thee (O God almighty) which not onely haſt endued mee, with the giftes of nature, as reaſon, power and ſtrength, but alſo haſt plenteouſly gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen me the ſubſtance of this worlde. I acknowledge (O Lord) that theſe are thy giftes, and confeſſe with the holy Apoſtle Saint Iames that there is no perfect nor
<pb facs="tcp:6059:62"/> good gift but it commeth fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> thee (O Father of light) which giueſt freely, and ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſteſt no man in the téeth: yea I further in particular ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>knowledge with the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phet Aggeus, that gold and ſiluer is thine, and to whom it pleaſeth thee thou giueſt it, to y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> godly, y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> they may be thy diſpoſers &amp; diſtributers thereof, and to the vngodly to heape vp their damnation withall. Wherefore ſith I feele in mine owne heart an
<pb facs="tcp:6059:63"/> inclination, to abuſe theſe as other good things, I can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not but humblie beſeech and deſire thée moſt mercifull God, and louing father to frame in mee with thy holy ſpirite a faithfull heart, and ready hand to diſtribute theſe thy gifts according to thy pleaſure, that ſo I may not lay vp treaſure here, where théeues may rob, and moathes corrupt, but may lay vp treaſure in thy hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uenly kingdome, where nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther
<pb facs="tcp:6059:63"/> théeues may ſteale, nor moathes corrupt, and that onely to mine owne com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fort, whom of thy mercie thou haſt promiſed to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>warde, therefore neither yet alone to the good example of the humble and meeke of thy congregation, but alſo to the glorie of thy name, to whom bee all honor and praiſe world without ende. Amen.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="prayer">
               <pb facs="tcp:6059:64"/>
               <head>The prayer of Manaſſes King of Iuda.</head>
               <p>
                  <hi>O</hi> Lord almightie, God of our fathers Abra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ham, Iſaac, and Iacob, and of the iuſt ſeede of them: which haſt made heauen and earth, with all the or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>naments thereof, which <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>aſt ordained the ſea by the word of thy commaunde<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, which haſt ſhut vppe the déepe, and haſt ſealed it for thy fearefull and lauda<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble name dreaded of all men,
<pb facs="tcp:6059:64"/> and honorable before the face of thy power, the firie anger of thy threatning is aboue all meaſure heauie to ſinners, but the mercie of thy promiſe is great and vnſearchable, for thou art the Lord God moſt high a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>boue all the earth, long ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fering, and excéeding merci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full, and ſorie for the malice of men, I haue prouoked thine anger, and haue done euill before thee, in com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitting abominations, and
<pb facs="tcp:6059:65"/> multiplying of offences. And now I bowe the knées of my heart, requiring good<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes of thee: O Lord I haue ſinned, Lord, I haue ſinned, and knowe my wicked<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe, I deſire thee by pray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er, O Lord, forgiue mee, O Lord, forgiue me, and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtroy me not with mine ini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quities, neither doe thou al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wayes remember my euils, to puniſh them: but ſaue me (which am vnworthie) after thy great mercie, and I wil
<pb facs="tcp:6059:65"/> praiſe thee euerlaſtingly, all the dayes of my life: for all the power of heauen pray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeth thée, and vnto thée be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>longeth all glorie, world without ende. Amen.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="prayer">
               <head>A prayer of Ieremy. Iere. 17.</head>
               <p>HEale me (O Lord) and I ſhall be whole, ſaue thou me, and I ſhall bee ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued: for thou art my praiſe. Be not thou terrible vnto me (O Lord) for thou art he in whom I hope. When I
<pb facs="tcp:6059:66"/> am in perill, let my perſecu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tors be confounded, but not me. Thou ſhalt bring vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on them the time of their plague, and ſhalt deſtroy them right ſoone. Amen.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="prayer">
               <head>A prayer of Ephraim or Iſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rael in the Prophet Ieremie. Ierem. 31.</head>
               <p>
                  <hi>O</hi> Lord, thou haſt cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtened me, and thy cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtening haue I receiued as an vntamed calfe, conuert thou me, and I ſhall be con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerted, for thou art my Lord
<pb facs="tcp:6059:66"/> God: for as ſoone as thou diddeſt turne me, I repented my ſelfe: and when I vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtood, I ſmote vpon my thigh, I confeſſed and was aſhamed, becauſe I ſuffered the reproach of my youth.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="prayer">
               <head>The prayer of Ieſus the ſonne of Sirach, in neceſſitie, and for wiſedome. Eccleſ. the laſt chap.</head>
               <p>
                  <hi>I</hi> Thanke thee (O Lorde and King) and praiſe thée O God my Sauiour, I will yéeld praiſes vnto thy name.
<pb facs="tcp:6059:67"/> Thou haſt deliuered my bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy from deſtruction, for thou art my defender and helper, from the ſnare of the falſe tongue, and from them that are occupied in lyes. Thou haſt béene my helper from ſuch as roſe againſt me, and haſt deliuered me according to thy great mercie, and thy holy names ſake: thou haſt deliuered mee from the roa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring of them that prepared themſelues to deuoure me, out of the hands of ſuch as
<pb facs="tcp:6059:67"/> ſought after my life, from the multitude of them that trouble me, and went about to ſet fire vpon me on eue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie ſide, ſo that I was not brent in the middeſt of the fire. From the déepe of hell thou deliueredſt mee, from the vncleane tongue, from lying words, from the wic<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ked iudge, and from the vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>righteous tongue. My ſoule ſhall praiſe the Lord vnto the death, for my life drew neere vnto hel downeward,
<pb facs="tcp:6059:68"/> they compaſſed mee round a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bout on euery ſide, and there was no man to helpe mee: I looked about mee if there were any man that would ſuccour mee, and there was none. Then thought I vpon thy mercie (O Lord) and vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on the acts that thou haſt done of olde, namely, that thou deliuereſt ſuch as put their truſt in thée, and rid<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deſt them out of the handes of the falſe Paynimes. Thus lifted I vp my prayer from
<pb facs="tcp:6059:68"/> the earth, and prayed for de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liuerance from death, I cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led vpon the Lord my Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, that hée would not leaue mee without help in the day of my trouble, and in the time of the proude, I will praiſe thy name con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinually, yéelding honour and thankes vnto it, and ſo my prayer was heard. Thou ſauedſt me from deſtruction and deliueredſt me from the vnrighteous time. There<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore will I acknowledge
<pb facs="tcp:6059:69"/> and praiſe thee, and magni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fie the name of the Lord.</p>
               <p>When I was but young ere euer I went aſtray, I deſired wiſedome openly in prayer. I came therefore be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore the temple and ſought it very buſily, and I will ſéeke for it to my laſt houre. Then will it flouriſh vnto me as a grape that is ſoone ripe. My heart reioyced in it, then went my feate the right way: yea, from my youth vp, ſought I after it,
<pb facs="tcp:6059:69"/> I bowed downe mine eare a little and receiued it: I found in myſelfe much wiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome, and proſpered greatly in it.</p>
               <p>Therefore will I giue the glorie vnto him that gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ueth me wiſedome, for I am aduiſed to doe thereafter. I will be iealous to cleaue vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to that that is good, ſo ſhal I not be confounded. My ſoule hath wreſtled with it, I lifted vp my hands on high, then was my ſoule lighte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned
<pb facs="tcp:6059:70"/> through wiſedome, that I acknowledged my foo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſhnes: I ordered my ſoule after it, I found her in cleaneneſſe, I had my heart in it from the beginning, and therefore ſhall not I be for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſaken. My hart longeth af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter it, and therefore I got a good treaſure. Through it the Lord hath giuen mee a new tongue, werewith I will praiſe him: Oh come vnto me yee vnlearned, and dwell in the houſe of diſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pline,
<pb facs="tcp:6059:70"/> withdraw not your ſelues from it, but commune on theſe things, for your ſoules are very thirſtie. I opened my mouth and ſpake, O come and buy wiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome without money, and bowe downe your necke vnder her yoke, and let your ſoule receiue diſcipline, it is euen at hand, and readie to be found. Behold with your eyes, how I haue had but little labour, and yet haue much reſt. Oh receiue wiſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome,
<pb facs="tcp:6059:71"/> and you ſhall receiue plentie of ſiluer and golde in your poſſeſſion: let your minde reioyce in her mercie, and be not aſhamed of her praiſe, worke your worke betimes, and ſhee ſhall giue you your reward in due time.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="prayer">
               <head>A prayer to our Lord Ieſus Chriſt.</head>
               <p>MOſt mercifull Lorde Ieſus Chriſt, which waſt ſent from the moſt higheſt tower of the father
<pb facs="tcp:6059:71"/> almightie, into this world to relieue ſinners, to gather together them that were ſcattered abroade, to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deeme them which were puniſhed, to looſe them that were in priſon, to their countrie againe, to heale them that were ſore, to comfort them that were wayling and ſorrowful. Vouchſafe I beſeech thée of thy ſingular goodnes to comfort mee in the puniſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment that I am in. And thou
<pb facs="tcp:6059:72"/> Lord Ieſu Chriſt, that did<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deſt reſtore mankind in peace and concord, to the high inheritance of Para<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dize, whom thou boughteſt with thy precious bloud, and diddeſt make peace be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>twéene God &amp; men, vouch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſafe to aſſure euen thy ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gular mercie towards me, &amp; cauſe me to féele reconcilia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion betwéene me and mine enemies, and vouchſafe to ſhew thy glorie vpon mee, and to quench the anger of
<pb facs="tcp:6059:72"/> them al, and put away from me their hatred, and ceaſe the malice that they beare againſt mee, and as thou diddeſt not onelie allaie Eſau his malice againſt his brother Iacob, but alſo diddeſt deliuer Iacob from the ſame: ſo aſſwage the rage of my enemies, and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liuer me with thine almigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie power, from them that owe mee malice, and from their laying await and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſires, as thou diddeſt deliuer
<pb facs="tcp:6059:73"/> Abraham from the hands of the Chaldées, and Ioſeph from the hands of his bre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thren: Lot, from the citie of Sodome: thy ſeruants Moſes and Aaron, from the power of Pharao, and from the bondage of Egypt: King Dauid from the power of Saul, and Goliah the Gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ant: Daniel from the den of lions: the thrée children from the fornace of flaming fire: Peter from hands. Euen ſo vouchſafe to deli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer
<pb facs="tcp:6059:73"/> me thy ſeruant from all troubles and anguiſhes, in which preſently I am: yea deliuer mee from all my ſinnes, which haue pulled downe vpon mee all theſe myſeries, and frée me from the laying awaite, and from the deſires of all mine ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies vſible, and inuiſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble. And thou Lord Ieſus Chriſt of thy ſingular good<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes, diddeſt ſaue that which the olde ſerpent did hurt, and deſtroy by ſuggeſtions and
<pb facs="tcp:6059:74"/> wicked councell vouchſafe mee ſuch a notable meaſure of thy grace and defence that I may auoyde from the di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uelliſh counſell which mine enemies haue done &amp; would doe againſt mee: and fru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrate and auoyde all their euill counſailes, as thou did<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deſt ouerthrowe the coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſels of Achitophell, which gaue counſell to Abſolon a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt his father Dauid: Amen.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="prayer">
               <pb facs="tcp:6059:74"/>
               <head>A fruitfull meditation not to bee ſayde with the mouth lightlie, but to be cried with heart, and minde, oft and mightilie.</head>
               <p>
                  <hi>O</hi> Moſt excellent good<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes, withdrawe not thou thy mercie from mee, O moſt mightie maker, de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpiſe not me, which am the work that thine own hands haue made. O moſt prudent redéemer, ſuffer not to pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſh that which thou haſt
<pb facs="tcp:6059:75"/> bought with ſo deare a price O moſt holy and heauen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly hoſt and gueſt, both pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rifie, ſaue, dreſſe, and keepe thy houſe, and dwelling place, the which thou haſt ſanctified and dedicated to thy ſelfe, by thy word and ſpirit.</p>
               <p>When ſhall I loue thee? when ſhall I bee ſorie and contrite for my ſins? when ſhall I turne to thee by grace? when ſhall I re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>member thy benefits, thy
<pb facs="tcp:6059:75"/> méeknes, thy pouertie, and thy painfull and bitter paſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion, thy patience, thy obe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dience, thy loue and thy cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritie? when ſhall I ſancti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fie, worſhip, magnifie, and loue thée? If thou be moſt dreadful, where is my dread O Ieſus Chriſt? If thou bee a moſt louing father, where is my loue? If thou be my Lord, and redeemer, where is my ſeruice? If thou be mine hoſt, and dwel in my ſoule by thy grace and
<pb facs="tcp:6059:76"/> mercie, where is my holi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes and cleanneſſe, accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to ſuch an hoſt? Now therefore good Lord Ieſus Chriſt, drawe my hart after thée, with the ſound loue and féeling of thy ſufferings, moyſten my mind with thy moſt precious bloud, that whitherſoeuer I turne me, I may behold about me and féele within me the merites of thy death, that thus behol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding thée, I may not with de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>light fixe my ſight in any
<pb facs="tcp:6059:76"/> thing but only in thée, which liueſt and raigneſt God, world without end. Amen.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="prayer">
               <head>A godly and deuout prayer.</head>
               <p>GRaunt mee mercifull Lorde God to deſire feruently, to ſearch wiſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, to knowe truly, to per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forme effectually all things that thou haſt giuen mee in charge, by thy holy word: and giue mee grace to doe them ſimply and onely, for
<pb facs="tcp:6059:77"/> the glorie and lawde of thy holy name, good Lord direct and order the ſtate and ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner of my liuing. And all things thou wouldeſt I ſhould doe, grant (I beſéech thée) that I may know it, will it, and haue power to doe it, and giue me grace to execute it, as I ſhould doe and as it is expedient for thy glorie, and the comfort of my ſoule. My way to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards thee, let it be faire, right, and well performed,
<pb facs="tcp:6059:77"/> not fayling, nor wauering betwixt proſperitie, and ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerſitie, but guide me ſo good Lord that in proſperitie I may continually and vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fainedly giue thée thankes, and may bee inabled by thée to hold patience in aduerſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie; in all eſtates ſo carrying my ſelfe that I bee not exal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted in any pride, when pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſperitie aboundeth, neither in the dayes of danger and diſtreſſe be depreſſed by any deiection or heauines of
<pb facs="tcp:6059:78"/> minde aboue that is meete. Let mee inwardly ioy in nothing but in that, that ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ueth and promoteth vnto thée: neither ſuffer me to be ſorie for any thing but that, that leadeth and withdraw<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>eth from thée: let me couet to pleaſe no man but in thée, nor feare to diſpleaſe any for thy ſake, but onely thée: let all tranſitorie things be vile vnto me, good Lord, for thy ſake, and all things that be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>long to thee, let them bee
<pb facs="tcp:6059:78"/> daintie and deare vnto mee, and thou good Lord God moſt deare of all other. Let mee bee wearie of that ioy that is without thee, and al reſt and quiet that is not in thee, let it bee tedious and painfull vnto me: grant me moſt to addreſſe and direct my hart to thée, and when I doe amiſſe, giue me grace to know and conſider it, yea worke in mee for it a godly ſorrowe with a full purpoſe and intent of amendment
<pb facs="tcp:6059:79"/> of life. Make me now ſweet Lord Ieſu, méeke without any fayning, glad and chéer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full without diſſolutenes, ſorrie without exceſſiue hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uines or diſtruſt, ſad and ſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber without hypocriſie, quiet, and merry without lightnes, truſting in thée without preſumption rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>die alwayes to tell my neighbour his fault without neglect of mine owne, and without diſſimulation and feare, as in regard of
<pb facs="tcp:6059:79"/> him, labouring alwayes in charitie to edifie him in word and deede.</p>
               <p>Make me obedient with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out contradiction, patient without murmuring, con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tent with mine owne with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out couetouſneſſe. Giue me (moſt louing Father and God) a waking, and a dili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gent heart, that no vaine or vncleane cogitation with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wrawe it from thée: giue me a noble heart that no vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>worthie affection plucke it
<pb facs="tcp:6059:80"/> downewardes to earthly things, giue me a firme and conſtant heart alwayes la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bouring to breake, or ouer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come euill: giue mee a frée heart, yea, a heart of ſuch li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bertie, y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> no wicked thought, or euill thing, hold it at any time in bondage or ſlauerie. Grant to me my ſweet Lord God, vnderſtanding, that I may know thée, diligence, y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> I may ſéeke thée, wiſdome y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> I may find thée, conuerſatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, that I may pleaſe thée, long
<pb facs="tcp:6059:80"/> perſeuerance, that truſtily I may abide for thée, and ſure hope, that finally I may em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brace thée. Grant y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> I be not here ſo afflicted with paines, and torments in the way of this life, y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> I ſhould any ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner of way be drawen from thee: but ſo Lord let mee haue the vſe of thy benefits here by grace, that alſo I may haue fruition of thy ioyes and rewards in thy heauenly kingdome &amp; euer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>laſting glorie, thorow Ie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſus
<pb facs="tcp:6059:81"/> Chriſt. Amen.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="prayer">
               <head>A godly prayer to deſire the life to come.</head>
               <p>THis my body is the ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie darke and filthie priſon of my ſoule, this world is an exile and a ba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſhment, this life is care and miſerie. But where thou art O Lord, there is the very countrey and king<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome of libertie and euer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>laſting bleſſedneſſe: ſtirre our mindes therefore con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinually
<pb facs="tcp:6059:81"/> to remember ſo great felicitie: powre into our hearts a deſire of ſuch precious things, and of all things moſt to bee deſired. Giue quicknes vnto our minde, and grant that euen in this life wee may haue a good taſte of euerlaſting ioyes, whereby theſe things of the world may ſéeme fil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thie and be loathſome vnto vs. And howſoeuer we doe now too earneſtly and too gréedily ſéeke for the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, yea ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>count
<pb facs="tcp:6059:82"/> them as if it were our ſtrong rocke, yet giue vs grace in reſpect of thée and eternall bleſſednes to refuſe and deſpiſe theſe bitter and filthie things, and moſt fer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uently to deſire the ſwéet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes of thy familiaritie, in the which all goodneſſe is contained. To thée be ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour and glorie for euer. Amen.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="prayer">
               <pb facs="tcp:6059:82"/>
               <head>A thankes giuing, and alſo an interceſſion and prayer vnto our Sauiour Ieſus Chriſt.</head>
               <p>
                  <hi>O</hi> Moſt mercifull Ieſu, my ſwéet ſauiour, and moſt gratious Lord God, I thanke thee hartily for that thou haſt created and made me of nought, &amp; for thy manifold benefits and gra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces that thou haſt giuen vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to me here in this world be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore many other, not onely
<pb facs="tcp:6059:83"/> preſeruing me from vile and loathſome ſickneſſe, from ſhame, and many grieuous daungers beſides, but alſo giuing to me moſt vnwor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thie, many great and irre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>compenſible, yea and in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>comprehenſible gifts alſo. All which gifts, moſt ſwéete Ieſus, I know full well, and méekely acknowledge to come of thy goodnes on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, and nothing of my deſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing, nay, indeede without yea contrarie to my deſerts.
<pb facs="tcp:6059:83"/> Wherefore moſt mightie Lord God my creator, my redéemer, and moſt merci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full Sauiour Ieſus Chriſt, which when wee were loſt, boughteſt and redéemedſt vs againe with thy owne moſt precious bloud, haue mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cie on mee moſt vnworthie wretch, which haue com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitted, and done many great ſinnes and treſpaſſes againſt thy mercifull good<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe, and haue miſpent thy giftes of grace, that thou ſo
<pb facs="tcp:6059:84"/> louingly and bountifully diddeſt giue to me, and I for my part haue ſo vnkindly behaued my ſelfe to thée, that ſurely I am much vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>worthie to bee called thy ſonne: yet moſt benigne Ieſu, thou art ſo bountifull of thy mercy and pittie, that notwithſtanding mine vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kindnes towards thee, yet thou wilt ſtill haue mercie, and during my life, wilt al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo I hope aſſiſt me to put all my whole truſt and confi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence
<pb facs="tcp:6059:84"/> in thy mercy. O Lord thou commandeſt (I wot) to cry and call vpon thee, that thou thereby mighteſt haue occaſion to giue vnto vs thy moſt gracious gifts. Wherefore moſt glorious Ieſu, which forſakeſt no ſinner, but gladly receiueſt to thy mercie all them that will méekely call for it: giue me euer grace in earneſtnes and feruencie of heart to call vpon thee for thy goodneſſe. And aſſiſt me ſo, that I may
<pb facs="tcp:6059:85"/> continually dread thee, loue thee, and ſerue thee with all my heart and minde, with all my will and reaſon, with all my might, power, and ſtrength of body and ſoule, and graunt mee grace good Lord, that of all my acts and deedes done to thy will and pleaſure, I may render all the honor and praiſe vnto thee, as to whom alone of verie dutie it belongeth: And further I beſéech thee (gracious Lord) of thine in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>finit
<pb facs="tcp:6059:85"/> mercie, that all my miſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pent life in times paſt may bee forgotten before thee, which I cannot but confeſſe that I haue conſumed and ſpent very euill, and yet I pray thee pardon and paſſe by it for Ieſus Chriſt ſake, aſſiſting me to walke in bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter courſes euer hereafter: yea worke in me the gift of good perſeuerance in ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuous liuing, that I may now from henceforth order my life here in this world
<pb facs="tcp:6059:86"/> to thy pleaſure. Alſo (my ſwéete Sauiour) graunt me not onely time and ſpace heere to repent, before I de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>part out of this world, but alſo that I may truly re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pent, and that ſo, I may be aſſured that I am thy ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uant to the comfort and ſal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uation of my ſinfull ſoule. And (moſt mercifull Ieſu) I humbly pray thee to pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerue mee from ſodaine death, and ſo to ſtand by me, at my departing, out of
<pb facs="tcp:6059:86"/> this tranſitorie world, that I may not onely haue a ſtayed memorie and fruit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full vtterance, but alſo may bee indued with ſtedfaſt faith, very true hope, and feruent charitie: and moſt ſwéete Lord Ieſu Chriſt, giue me now whileſt I liue, thy mercifull ayde, and grace to purſue and followe alwayes thy will and com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mandements, and ſo to eſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chew mine owne fraile will and wicked deſires, and the
<pb facs="tcp:6059:87"/> diuels falſe inticements, that in thy ſight I may ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peare and be found to be (as I am named) thy ſonne, and a true Chriſtian man, and after this preſent life I may come to the ſight of thy moſt glorious face in heauen. A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men.</p>
               <p>We worſhip thée Chriſt, with praiſe and benediction, for thou redéemeſt the world through thy paſſion.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="prayer">
               <pb facs="tcp:6059:87"/>
               <head>Another Prayer vnto our Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uiour Ieſus Chriſt.</head>
               <p>
                  <hi>O</hi> Maker of heauen and earth, King of Kings, and Lord of Lords, which of nothing in compariſon diddeſt make mee to thy image and likenes, and did<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deſt redéeme me with thine owne precious blood, whom I a ſinner, am not worthie to name, neither call vpon, neither with my heart to thinke vpon: humbly I de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſire
<pb facs="tcp:6059:88"/> thée, and méekly I pray thée, that graciouſly thou wouldeſt behold mee thy wicked ſeruant, and haue mercie on me, which had<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deſt mercie on the woman of Canaan, and Mary Mag<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dalen, which diddeſt for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giue the Publicane, and the théefe hanging on the Croſſe, vnto thee I confeſſe (moſt holy father) my ſins, which (if I would) I can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not hide from thee, becauſe all things are naked before
<pb facs="tcp:6059:88"/> thee, with whom I haue to deale: haue mercie therfore on mee, Lord Ieſu Chriſt, for I a wretch haue ſore offended thee, in pride, in couetouſnes, in gluttonie, in lecherie, in vaine glorie in hatred, in enuie, in adul<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>terie, in theft, in lying, in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>backbiting, in ſporting, in diſſolute and wanton laugh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, in idle words, in hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring, in taſting, in touch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, in thinking, in ſléep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, in working, yea euery
<pb facs="tcp:6059:89"/> manner of way, in which I (fraile man and moſt wretched ſinner) might ſin. My default, my moſt grie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uous default, I vnfainedly confeſſe before thee, and doe humbly pray and beſeech thee, which for my health deſcendedſt from heauen, to haue mercie vpon me mi<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſerable wretch that I am. And as thou diddeſt forgiue Peter that did for ſake thee. So vouchſafe graciouſly to pardon and paſſe by my
<pb facs="tcp:6059:89"/> grieuous iniquities. Thou art my creator and my hel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per, my maker, my redéemer and gouernour, my father, my Lord, my God, and my King. Thou art my hope, my truſt, my gouernour, my helpe, my ſtrength, my defence, my redemption, my life, my health, and my reſurrection, thou art my ſtedfaſtnes, my refuge or ſuccour, my light and my helpe. Therefore I moſt humbly and hertily deſire
<pb facs="tcp:6059:90"/> and pray thée helpe me, de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fend mee, make me ſtrong and comfort me, make mee ſtedfaſt, make me ioyful and cheareful, giue me light and viſite me, reuiue me againe which am dead: for I am thy making and thy worke (O Lord) therefore deſpiſe me not, I am thy ſeruant I confeſſe it and thy bond<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>: although euil, although vnworthy and a ſinner. But whatſoeuer I am, whether I be good or bad, I am euer
<pb facs="tcp:6059:90"/> thine. Therfore to who<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſhal I flée except I flée vnto thée. If thou caſt me off, who ſhal or will receiue me? If thou deſpiſe mee, &amp; turne thy face fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> me, who ſhall looke vpon me? therefore recogniſe and knowledge mee, for thine owne, although vnworthie, co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ming to thée, yea although I be vile and vncleane? For though I be vile &amp; vncleane, yet y<hi rend="sup">u</hi> canſt make me cleane. Though I bee ſicke, thou canſt heale me. Though I
<pb facs="tcp:6059:91"/> bee dead and buried, thou canſt reuiue mee. For thy mercie is much more then mine iniquitie. Thou canſt forgiue me more then I can offend. Therefore (O Lord) do not conſider nor haue re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpect to y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> number of my ſins and to y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> grieuouſnes therof, but according to the great<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes of thy mercie, forgiue mee, and haue mercie on me moſt wretched ſinner. Say vnto my ſoule, I am thy ſal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uation, and the rather ſpeak
<pb facs="tcp:6059:91"/> this again becauſe thou haſt ſaid and alwayes performed it, I will not the death of a ſinner, but rather that hee liue and bee conuerted, and turne to me. O Lord, be not angrie with me, I pray thée moſt meeke father, for thy great mercie ſake: yea I moſt humbly beſeech thée, that thou wouldeſt for Chriſt Ieſus ſake vouchſafe to bring me to bliſſe that ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer ſhall ceaſe. Amen.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="prayer">
               <pb facs="tcp:6059:92"/>
               <head>Another Prayer.</head>
               <p>
                  <hi>O</hi> Bountifull Ieſu, O ſweete Ieſu, O Ieſu, the ſonne of the pure Virgin Mary, full of mercie and truth, after thy great mercy haue pittie on mee. I pray thée by the ſame precious bloud, which for vs miſera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble ſinners thou waſt con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tent to ſhed on the altar of the croſſe, that thou wilt vouchſafe cleane to remoue and take away all my wic<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kednes,
<pb facs="tcp:6059:92"/> and not to deſpiſe mee, I humbly requiring this, and that in, and for thy moſt holy and bleſſed name, O Lord Ieſus. This name of thine, Ieſus, is the name of health: what is Ieſus, but a Sauiour? O my Sauiour Ieſus Chriſt that haſt cre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ated and redéemed me with thy precious bloud, ſuffer me not to be damned, whom thou haſt made of naught, and whom thou haſt redée<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med with a moſt precious
<pb facs="tcp:6059:93"/> ranſome. Oh let not my wickedneſſe deſtroy, that thy almightie goodnes hath made and formed. Lord Ieſu reknowledge, that which is thine indéed, and wipe cleane away that which withdraweth or withhol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deth me from thée. Now and in all time of mercie haue mercie one mee and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>found not me in the time of thy terrible iudgeme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t. And though I wretched ſinner for my moſt grieuous of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fences,
<pb facs="tcp:6059:93"/> haue by thy very iuſtice deſerued eternall paine, yet I doe appeale from that exact righteouſneſſe of thine, to thy ſingular good<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe, and ſtedfaſtly truſt in thine vnſpeakeable mercie: wherefore I pray thée, as a louing father and merci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full Lord to take pittie on me. Lord Ieſu, what profit is my bloud, ſéeing I muſt deſcend into eternall cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ruption eternally? They that bee dead ſhall not mag<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nifie
<pb facs="tcp:6059:94"/> thee, nor likewiſe all they that go to hell. O moſt mercifull Ieſu, haue mercie on me therefore, and deliuer me, yea, be alwayes comfor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>table vnto me and accept me a wretched ſinner into the number of them that ſhall be ſaued. And fith thou art the health of all them that truſt in thee, and thou haſt giuen grace in ſome mea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure to beléeue, haue mercie on me: endue me with thy grace, wiſedome, charitie,
<pb facs="tcp:6059:94"/> chaſtitie, and humilitie: yea and in all mine aduerſities vphold me with ſtedfaſt pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tience, ſo that I may ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerely loue thee, and in thée waite and looke to be glori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fied, and haue mine onely delight in thee, world with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out end. Amen.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="prayer">
               <head>Another Prayer.</head>
               <p>
                  <hi>O</hi> Glorious King, which among thy Saints art praiſed, and neuertheleſſe incomparable, thou art in
<pb facs="tcp:6059:95"/> vs Lord, and thy name hath béene called vpon by vs. Therefore doe not forſake vs Lord God, and in the day of iudgement vouchſafe to glorifie vs among thy ſaints and elect. O bleſſed King. Amen.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="prayer">
               <head>If thou be ſicke, or in tribula<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, ſay thus.</head>
               <p>LOrd God which doeſt puniſh and ſcourge thy people, not after their de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeruing, neither yet to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtroy
<pb facs="tcp:6059:95"/> them, but to conuert them mercifully to thée: and yet notwithſtanding knoweſt, that thorough our frailties, wee are readie in the middeſt of thy correcti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons to fall away, graunt vs we pray thée, and that for Ieſus Chriſts ſake, the ſtrength and comfort of thy bleſſed ſpirit, that to the glorie of thy name, other mens good, and our owne conſolation, wee may both patiently beare, and graci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſly
<pb facs="tcp:6059:96"/> profit by, and at the laſt bee mightily deliuered from this maladie, which worthily wee doe ſuffer, as the chaſtiſement of our ſinne, and the time of faith. Amen.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="prayer">
               <head>A very godly and neceſſarie prayer to bee ſayde moſt ſpecially at the houre of death.</head>
               <p>
                  <hi>O</hi> LORD Ieſu Chriſt, which art the health of all men liuing, and euer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>laſting
<pb facs="tcp:6059:96"/> life to them that be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>léeue in thée, and dye in thy faith, I wretched ſinner giue ouer and ſubmit my ſelfe wholy vnto thy moſt bleſſed will, I being ſure by the promiſes of thy worde, and the pledge of thy ſpirit, that the thinge cannot pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſh which is committed to thy mercie. In full perſwa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion whereof, O Lord giue me grace, that willingly I may leaue this fraile and wretched fleſh, in hope of
<pb facs="tcp:6059:97"/> the reſurrection, which in moſt perfect manner ſhall reſtore it mee againe. And further I beſéech thée moſt mercifull Lord, that thou wilt by thy grace make ſtrong my ſoule againſt all temptations. And that thou wilt ſo couer and defend mée with the buckler of mercie againſt all aſſaultes of the Diuel, that he may not any manner of way preuaile vpon me. I ſee and acknow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge, there is in my ſelfe no
<pb facs="tcp:6059:97"/> hope of ſaluation, but all my confidence, hope and truſt is in thy moſt merci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full goodnes, I haue no me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rites nor good workes at all which I may any manner of way alleadge before thée: ſinnes and euill workes, alas I ſée a great, yea an in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>numerable and infinite heape: notwithſtanding through thy mercie I truſt to be in the number of them to whom thou wilt not im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pute their ſinnes, but take
<pb facs="tcp:6059:98"/> and accept me for righteous and iuſt, and to be the inhe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritour of euerlaſting life in and by the obedience of thy ſonne, and my Sauiour, who was borne for my ſake, who did ſuffer both hunger and thirſt for my ſake, who did both preach and teach for my ſake, who did pray and faſt for my ſake, who did all good workes and déedes for my ſake, who ſuffered moſt grieuous and painfull torments for my ſake, and
<pb facs="tcp:6059:98"/> finally, who gaue his moſt precious body to dye, and bloud to bee ſhed vpon the croſſe for my ſake.</p>
               <p>Now therefore moſt mercifull Sauiour, I hum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bly beſéech thee, which haſt giuen thy ſelfe for mee to make all theſe things, and euery other grace of thine, which thou haſt fréely giuen me, profitable to me, and powerfull in me: Let thy bloude clenſe mee, and waſh away the ſpottes and foule<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes
<pb facs="tcp:6059:99"/> of my ſinnes. Let thy righteouſnes hide and couer my vnrighteouſnes, by the merits of thy paſſion and bloud which I acknowledg to be the onely price of ſatiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>faction for my ſins &amp; offen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces. Strengthen me ſo good Lord, by thy grace, that my faith and ſaluation in thy bloud wauer not in me, but may euer bée firme and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtant: Lord let not the hope of thy mercie and life euer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>laſting euer decay in mee,
<pb facs="tcp:6059:99"/> but let it alwayes reſt and be felt pourefully in me, and that euen to and in the laſt gaſpe. And graunt further I pray thée, that charitie ware not cold in me: final<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, that the weaknes of my fleſh bée not ouercome with the feare of death, or any o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther temptation whatſoe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer. Yea graunt me merci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full Sauiour, I humbly be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſéech thee, that, when death hath ſhut vp the eyes of my bodie, yet that the eyes of
<pb facs="tcp:6059:100"/> my ſoule may ſtill beholde and looke vpon thée, and may aſſuredly féele thée in my ſelfe, for my ſelfe, to bee the mightie conqueror of death and the deuil, ſinne and hell, and all other enemies of mine whatſoeuer, ſo that when death hath taken a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>way the vſe of my tongue and ſpéech, yet that my heart may cry and ſay vnto thée:</p>
               <p>O Lord, into thy hands I giue and commend my ſpirit.</p>
               <pb facs="tcp:6059:100"/>
               <p>Lord Ieſus, receiue my ſoule vnto thée. Amen.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="prayer">
               <head>The prayer of Salomon for to obtaine wiſedome. 1, King. 2.</head>
               <p>THOU haſt ſhewed, Lord, vnto thy ſeruant Dauid my Father, great mercie, when hee walked in thy ſight in truth, and iu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtice, and in vprightnes of heart with thée. Thou ſheweſt vnto him thy great mercie, and gaueſt him a
<pb facs="tcp:6059:101"/> ſonne, ſitting vpon his throne, as it is at this day. And now, Lord God, thou haſt made thy ſeruant to raigne in the roome of Dauid my Father. I am a very babe, and know not how to goe out and in. And thy ſeruant is in the middeſt of an infinite number, which thou haſt choſen, which can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not bee numbred nor coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted for multitude. Where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore giue to thy ſeruant an heart apt to bee taught, and
<pb facs="tcp:6059:101"/> full of vnderſtanding, to iudge thy people, that I may diſcerne betwéene good and bad. For who is able to iudge this thy mightie peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="prayer">
               <head>A prayer for obtaining of wiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome. <hi>Sapient.</hi> 9.</head>
               <p>GOd of our fathers, and Lord of mercie, thou haſt made all things with thy word, and ordained man through thy wiſedome, that hee ſhould haue dominion
<pb facs="tcp:6059:102"/> ouer the creatures which thou haſt made, that hee ſhould order the world ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording vnto equitie and righteouſnes, and execute iudgement with a true heart, giue mee wiſedome, which is euer among the children of Iſrael. For I thy ſeruant, and ſonne of thy handmaide, am a féeble per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon, of a ſhort time, and too young to the vnderſtanding of thy iudgements, and though a man bee neuer ſo
<pb facs="tcp:6059:102"/> perfect among the children of men, yet if thy wiſedome be not with him, he ſhall be nothing worth: Oh ſend thy wiſedome out of thy ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly heauens, and from the throne of thy Maieſtie, that ſhe may be with me, and la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bour with me, that I may knowe what is acceptable in thy ſight: for ſhe know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth and vnderſtandeth all things, and ſhe ſhall conduct me right ſoberly in all my workes, and preſerue mee
<pb facs="tcp:6059:103"/> in her power, ſo ſhall my workes bee acceptable. A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="prayer">
               <head>A prayer for a competent li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing. <hi>Prouerb.</hi> 30.</head>
               <p>TWo things Lord I de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mand, that thou wilt not deny mee vntill I dye: vanitie and words of lea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſings remoue farre from me, pouertie or riches giue me not: onely giue me that is neceſſarie for my liuing, leaſt being in full abun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dance,
<pb facs="tcp:6059:103"/> I might be prouoked to denie thée, and ſay, Who is the Lord? or being com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pelled by neceſſitie, I might ſteale and forſweare the name of God.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="prayer">
               <head>Another Prayer.</head>
               <p>GOod Lord God and ſwéete Sauiour Ieſus Chriſt, the ſonne of the euer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>laſting God, grant vnto me moſt fraile ſinner, and miſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable wretch this grace and mercie, that I may euer
<pb facs="tcp:6059:104"/> haue preſent before the eyes of my ſoule, thy holy life, thine example and behaui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>our, and that according to any meaſure of mercie thou haſt béen pleaſed, or ſhalt be pleaſed to beſtowe vpon me: I may in liuing and manners follow the ſame. And cauſe mee good Lord to profite, grow, and increaſe therein to ſuch a notable meaſure, as may be accepta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble vnto thée, being thine own grace, and comfortable
<pb facs="tcp:6059:104"/> to my ſelfe, as comming from thée for the ſaluation of my ſoule. Lighten Lord, and make cleere and bright my heart, with the glorious light of thy grace, that it euer may goe before mee, and follow mee in all my acts, ſo that by thy grace and power conducting and guiding, I may accompliſh and fulfill al that may pleaſe thy goodnes, and vtterly eſchue and auoide all, that in any wiſe ſhould diſpleaſe
<pb facs="tcp:6059:105"/> the ſame. Vouchſafe ſweete Sauiour, I beſéech thée, to direct and order all my co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gitations and thoughts, all my ſpéech and wordes, all mine acts and déedes in thy law and commaundements, in thy monitions and coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſels, and take me good Lord wholly ſo vnto thée, that here in all things doing thy will, I by grace may bee one of the ſoules that thou haſt appointed to euerla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſting ſaluation thorough
<pb facs="tcp:6059:105"/> Chriſt Ieſus. Amen.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="prayer">
               <head>A deuout prayer to our Lord God.</head>
               <p>
                  <hi>O</hi> LORD which haſt vouchſafed of thy vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpeakeable goodnes to make me, and ordaine me thy crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture to liue in this tranſito<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie life, giuing me a reaſona<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble ſoule by the which in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lightned with the truth of thy word, I know thée to be my Lord, my God, and my maker, which alſo I may
<pb facs="tcp:6059:106"/> in ſome ſort well perceiue by the viſible ſight of thy wonderfull workes, as by heauen, the earth, and the creatures in them contained together with the commodi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties &amp; bleſſings y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> we daylie receiue by them at thy hand, all which declare the great loue that thou hadeſt in our firſt creation, and alſo doe expreſſe the ſingular care and prouidence, that yet ſtill thou haſt for vs, and fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther doe declare to vs, thée
<pb facs="tcp:6059:106"/> to be the only God and Lord ouer all, and that there is none aboue thée, and that there is no wiſdome, know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge, power, or ſtrength of value beſides thée: and yet further alſo thou knowing our neceſſarie néede, of thy holy, of thy moſt louing fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uour, haſt not diſdained to ſay to me, and to other thy people by thine owne moſt bleſſed word, to the great comfort of all our conſcien<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces: Aſke, and it ſhall bee
<pb facs="tcp:6059:107"/> giuen: ſéeke, and yee ſhall finde: knocke, and it ſhall be opened to you. And yet for further declaration of thy great loue toward vs, haſt moſt familiarly ſayde, If we that be euill, can giue vnto our children when they aſke good things: how much more then ſhall our heauenly Father giue his holy ſpirit to them that ear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſtly deſire it. What a ſwéete and comfortable ſay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing is this? In confidence
<pb facs="tcp:6059:107"/> of this truth, O moſt bleſſed Lord, I wretched ſinner, doe aſke at thy hands mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cie and grace, confeſſing my ſelfe to bee a moſt wicked and abominable ſinner in thy ſight, moſt weake of all other to ſtand to or in thy truth, moſt fraile to fall, and readie to breake all thy holy commandements: by the kéeping of which, we are knowne to bee thy true ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uants. O moſt mercifull Lord God, I acknowledge
<pb facs="tcp:6059:108"/> my ſelfe daylie and hourely to breake the ſame: but where I haue thus offended thy diuine Maieſtie, I hum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>blie for Chriſt Ieſus ſake aſke of thee mercie and for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giuenes, minding by thy moſt mightie aſſiſtance ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer hereafter to offend in the ſame. And Lord, that I may bee the better perſwa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded of the aſſured perfor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mance of the ſame, I hum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bly aſke, and deſire thy ſtrength continually to
<pb facs="tcp:6059:108"/> make me ſtand faſt in faith: thy knowledge and power from thée to worke thy bleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed will: thy might to reſiſt all errour and wicked ima<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ginations: thy wiſedome to know the truth. For I con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſe and knowe, O Lord, that all worldly wit, policie, knowledge and ſtrength, is but fooliſhnes in thy ſight. Therefore I aſke and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinually craue, good Lord, that helpe, and moſt humbly deſire that thy holy ſpirit
<pb facs="tcp:6059:109"/> may guide all the imaginati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, thoughts, and deſires of my heart, not onely alte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring in me my fleſhly minde, but alſo inabling me in bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy, ſoule, and ſpirit, to ſerue thy bleſſed maieſtie: for this I know the moſt perfect amongſt men, lacking thy wiſedome are nothing worth. And great reaſon, becauſe the thoughts of mortall men are miſerable, and our forecaſtes are vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>certaine. And why? Our
<pb facs="tcp:6059:109"/> nature ſurely is ſo vitiated, and our will ſo depraued, and our vnderſtanding ſo corrupted, that it muſeth moſt, yea altogether on vaine things. Therefore good Lord, I beſéech thée comfort my ſicke ſoule, that it may walke in thy lawes and wayes, and worke thy will. And Lord like as thou knoweſt the ſecrets of my heart, and the deſires of the ſame, and ſéeſt indéede that I would verie earneſtly
<pb facs="tcp:6059:110"/> walke in thy trueth, and worke the workes of the ſame truth: ſo Lord I be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeech thee refreſh my ſoule according to thy mercifull calling, where thou ſaidſt, Come to me all that labour and are laden (and lowly of heart) and you ſhall finde reſt to your ſoules, and I ſhall refreſh you.</p>
               <p>O Lord, I miſerable ſinner would gladly labour in acceptable wayes, and haue ſome care that my good
<pb facs="tcp:6059:110"/> will and deſire might not ſwarue from thée, but bee wholy bent towardes thée, and like as thou knoweſt the ſame to bee vnfained in mee becauſe it is thine own worke: So Lord refreſh me with thy mercifull grace, that now and for euer I may bée ſtedfaſt in the true faith, and that I may be al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wayes obedient vnto thy lawes and commaunde<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments, and that I may ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer ſwarue from the holy
<pb facs="tcp:6059:111"/> and bleſſed ordinances of thy true and catholike Church, which is thy ſpouſe, and for the moſt part ſpeak<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth thy words of truth and life, but that I may vſe them, receiue them, and ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour thée in them ſo farre forth as they concerne thy worſhip, and are according vnto thy moſt holy will and pleaſure, as in things which thou haſt left to declare thy loue vnto vs, and by them to aſſure our hope, and to
<pb facs="tcp:6059:111"/> exerciſe our faith, that it ſhould not bee idle nor wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uering: whereunto howſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>euer I bee proue, thorough the corruption of my na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, and Satans malice againſt me (as I am on the other ſide vnwilling and vnable to doe that which is good) yet O Lord ſith all things are poſſible with thée, though they ſéeme ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer ſo vnpoſſible to vs, help and reach out thy moſt mightie and mercifull hand.
<pb facs="tcp:6059:112"/> O moſt louing father I know that by my ſins, I am not worthie thy bleſſed com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fort: nay I am moſt worthie to be depriued of that and all other fauours: but Lord ſith thou haſt ſaid, that in what houre ſoeuer a ſinner doth repent him of his ſins, thou wouldeſt no more re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>member them: and alſo thou wouldeſt not deſpiſe the ſighing of a contrite heart, I am bold in confi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence and truſt of thy mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cie
<pb facs="tcp:6059:112"/> méekly and with a lowly heart to call to thée for grace and helpe in this troublous time of temptation, and trying of our faith. I am as one laden, yea ouer laden with ignorance, not know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the height of thy hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uenly miſteries, nor the de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceitfull déepnes of the craftie and ſubtill arguments and perſwaſions of my ghoſtly enemies, which daylie doe aſſault my ſinfull ſoule, and ſo burden the ſame that it
<pb facs="tcp:6059:113"/> can finde no reſt. Therefore O Lord, like as thou know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eſt my will and heartie de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſire is to ſerue thée notwith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding theſe ſuggeſtions within me and without me, and that I haue a deſire to liue and dye in thy moſt holy faith: ſo Lord I beſéech thée, neuer ſuffer the ſubtill perſwaſions contrarie to thy truth to take place or roote in my heart. But like, Lord, as thou haſt created my heart, and giuen me in
<pb facs="tcp:6059:113"/> ſom meaſure a will to or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der the ſame according to thy bleſſed will: ſo Lord I humbly yéeld the ſame a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gaine into thy hands, de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiring thée by thy holy ſpirit ſo to direct my wayes, words, and workes, that now and alwayes they may be accepcable in thy ſight. And good Lord, ſuffer not my ſoule to periſh, which thou haſt bought ſo dearely with thy moſt precious bloud, for the which great
<pb facs="tcp:6059:114"/> mercie ſake, of thine here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tofore ſhewed vnto mee, haue mercie on me continu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ally, and mak mee poore in ſpirit, and low of heart, and content with my vocation, ſubmitting my ſelfe wholy into thy hands, ſo that my deſire may bee to thy will, and that no deſire remaine in me, but onely to doe thy will and pleaſure: And grant I beſéech thée that I may haue none other truſt but only in thée, which
<pb facs="tcp:6059:114"/> art onely to be truſted, and all truſt it ſelfe, and none beſides thée. Graunt fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther O Lord, that my poore ſoule may reſt in thée, yea in thée alone, for thou haſt ſayd, they ſhall neuer be con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>founded that put their truſt in thée: which truſt Lord graunt me neuer to forſake, for any vaine truſt, or temp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tation, or tribulation that may any manner of way fal out to vexe my poore ſoule: but graunt me thy holy ſpirit
<pb facs="tcp:6059:115"/> to comfort and defend mee from all things that ſhould procure thy diſpleaſure. As thou art in Trinitie one God and Lord ouer all, which liueſt and raigneſt world without end. To thée bee all honour, glorie, and praiſe for euer. Amen.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="prayer">
               <head>A prayer that wee may haue the feare of God before our eyes in all our doings.</head>
               <p>
                  <hi>O</hi> Almightie, and euer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>laſting God, thy holy
<pb facs="tcp:6059:115"/> word teacheth vs, that thou art not onely a father, but alſo a Lord, not onely a for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giuer, but alſo a reuenger, not onely a Sauiour, but al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo a iudge: and as thou be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing a father, a forgiuer, and a Sauiour, doeſt pardon and ſhewe mercie; ſo thou being a Lord, a reuenger and a iudge, puniſheſt and condemneſt. Neither doth thy holy ſcripture onely ſet foorth vnto vs a Goſpell which comforteth vs, quick<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neth
<pb facs="tcp:6059:116"/> vs, ſheweth vs glad and ioyfull tidings, forgi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ueth our ſinnes, and quie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teth our conſciences, and bringeth vs vnto euerla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſting life: but alſo a law which reproueth, accuſeth, condemneth vs, woundeth and ſlayeth our conſcience, yea, and throweth vs down headlong into the déepe dungeon of hell. And as the holy Goſpell lifteth vs vppe and maketh vs glad with the hope of remiſſion, and
<pb facs="tcp:6059:116"/> forgiuenes of our ſinnes: ſo doth the lawe plucke vs downe, and almoſt driue vs vnto deſperation for feare of thy plagues, and euerla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſting puniſhments: ſo that we not onely loue thée, as a father, a forgiuer, a Saui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>our, but alſo feare thée as a Lord, a reuenger, a iudge. For aſmuch therefore, O moſt gracious God, and merciful Sauiour, and moſt righteous iudge, as this doth ſo mightily put away ſinne,
<pb facs="tcp:6059:117"/> and make vs to walke in the way of thy commaunde<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments, namely, reuerently to feare thée, and to ſtand in awe of thy iudgement and heauie diſpleaſure: wée moſt entirely pray thée to giue vs that feare which thou re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quireſt of vs thy children in thy holy ſcriptures, and whereunto thou haſt pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſed, ſo many large and bounteous bleſſings: that we may not onely loue thée as a Sauiour, honour thée
<pb facs="tcp:6059:117"/> as a father, but alſo reue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rence thée as a Lord, and feare thée as a iudge. But yet with that feare and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerence good Lord, that be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>longeth to children, and not to ſlaues, otherwiſe it will do vs ſmall good.</p>
               <p>O Lord, all things are open to thy eyes, neither is any thing hid from thée, which ſéeſt the very ſecrets and moſt inward thoughts of our hearts. Giue vs ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore grace, that in all our
<pb facs="tcp:6059:118"/> enterpriſes, we may euer ſet thée, and thy feare be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore our eyes, and ſo ſtand in awe of thée and of thy righteous iudgement, that we attempt nothing where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by wee ſhould prouoke thy heauie diſpleaſure againſt vs, but ſo walke in thy feare, and thy holy ordinan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces, that we may at all times loue thée as a moſt gracious Sauiour, honour thée as a moſt louing father, reue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rence thée as a ſoueraigne
<pb facs="tcp:6059:118"/> Lord, and feare thée as an vpright, yet moſt mercifull iudge. So ſhall it come to paſſe, that wee reuerently fearing thée, as a childe doth his father, ſhall not onely auoyde all ſuch euils, as might make thée our heauie Lord and fierce iudge: but alſo embrace thoſe vertues, which ſhall both euidently declare our faithfull loue, true honour, vnfained reue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rence, and humble feare towards thee, and alſo
<pb facs="tcp:6059:119"/> cauſe thée that art our lo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing Father, and moſt mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cifull Sauiour, through Ieſus Chriſt our Lord, to acknowledge thine owne grace in vs, and to crowne it at the length with euerla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſting glorie, through Chriſt Ieſus. Amen.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="prayer">
               <head>A prayer againſt the enemies of Chriſts truth. <hi>Pſal.</hi> 140.</head>
               <p>DEliuer mee, O Lord from the vngodly, and ſtifnecked perſons, for thou
<pb facs="tcp:6059:119"/> ſéeſt howe in their hearts they imagine miſchiefe, and haue great pleaſure to picke quarrels: their tongues be ſharper then any adders ſting, and vnder their lips lyeth poyſon of adders: but O mercifull Lord, let mee not fall into their hands, leaſt they handle mee after their owne luſts.</p>
               <p>Thou onely art my God, that muſt heare my piteous plaints, Lord, that ruleſt altogether, that art the
<pb facs="tcp:6059:120"/> ſtrength and power of my defence, be thou as a helmet vpon my head, whereſoeuer the vngodly ſhall aſſault me, and ſuffer thou not the wicked thus to proſper in their matters. Suffer not their cankred and malitious ſtomackes to increaſe and ſpightfully to reuile me.</p>
               <p>Looke vpon thy poore wretches cauſe, and rid mee out of theſe daily grieuan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces: then ſhall I with an vpright heart, and pleaſant
<pb facs="tcp:6059:120"/> countenance, extoll and magnifie thy holy name. A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="prayer">
               <head>A prayer to keepe the tongue and to eſchew the affectio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of the world. <hi>Pſal.</hi> 141.</head>
               <p>TO thee I cry, O Lord, heare mee ſpeedily: let my prayer bee as a ſweete taſt and ſauour in thy pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſence, and the lifting vp of my hands as an euening ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crifice.</p>
               <p>Lord ſet a watch before
<pb facs="tcp:6059:121"/> my mouth, kéepe my lips, and my tongue alſo that they ſpeake nothing amiſſe, as doth the vngodly, who can ſpeake nothing ſaue euill; but that they call pure<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly and heartily vpon thee, and report thy worthie praiſes.</p>
               <p>Bow not my heart to laſt after euill, nor to fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low the faſhion of the wic<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ked, and abominable ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ners, leaſt I happen to cloake my wickednes with
<pb facs="tcp:6059:121"/> other ſinnes, as hypocrites doe. Let me not liue as they would haue mee to doe, but rather as it ſhall beſt pleaſe thée. Let mee not approue their counſailes, nor their déedes, though they carry neuer ſo goodly a ſhow, and faire face to the world. Let me not hearken to the enti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing and ſwéete baits of the vngodly, which counſaile me to filthie and vncleane thinges, but rather let mee giue good eare to the righte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous
<pb facs="tcp:6059:122"/> and godly man, though hée ſharpely correct and chide me. Let me alwayes haue a readie eye towardes thée, onely in thée to truſt alway and to apply my ſelfe vnto thée continually. Caſt not away my ſoule, neither ſuffer it to periſh: keepe me, that I be not tangled with the ſnares of the vngodly: and from the priuie traps of malitious perſons ſaue me: deliuer me, O Lord, through thy grace, for in all
<pb facs="tcp:6059:122"/> our owne deuiſes and workes, can nothing bee found ſure for vs to truſt vpon.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="prayer">
               <head>A Prayer of the Church a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt ſinne. <hi>Sapi.</hi> 1<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
               </head>
               <p>THou, O our God, art ſwéete, long ſuffering, and true, and with mercie ordereſt thou all things, for if wée ſinne, yet are wée thine, becauſe though ſinne in it one nature ſeparate be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>twéene thée and vs, yet doth
<pb facs="tcp:6059:123"/> thy goodneſſe ſurmount all iniquitie: ſo excelle<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t I know thy greatnes to bee. And if we ſinne not in ſo high a meaſure (for otherwiſe who liueth and ſinneth not?) yet are wee ſure that with thée wee are allowed, for to know thée, is perfect righte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſnes, and power is the roote of immor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>talitie.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="prayer">
               <pb facs="tcp:6059:123"/>
               <head>In the time of warres, a pray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er of King Aſa. 2. <hi>Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral.</hi> 14.</head>
               <p>LOrd, it is all one with thée, to helpe them that haue néede, with fewe, or with many: helpe vs, O Lord our God, for we truſt in thée, and in thy name we be come againſt this multi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tude, thou art the Lord our God, let no man preuaile a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt thée.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="prayer">
               <pb facs="tcp:6059:124"/>
               <head>A Prayer for keeping of a good name.</head>
               <p>THAT wiſe man which was priuie of thy ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crets, O heauenly Father, taught vs, that an honeſt name is a treaſure right pre<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>cious when he ſaith: better it is to haue a good name, than precious oyntments. But this ſo excellent and good thing, wée neither can get, but by thy goodnes; nor kéepe, but by thy grace, aide
<pb facs="tcp:6059:124"/> and helpe. Now ſurely the well and fountaine of a good name, is a faultles life: this therefore in eſpeciall, wee demaund and craue of thée, O Lord almightie, and that for Ieſus Chriſts ſake. Yet neuertheleſſe, for as much as oftentimes, innocencie and faultleſſe liuing is not ynough, neither yet a ſure buckler, and defence, name<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly againſt ſuch as vnder their lippes beare the poy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon of ſerpents: yea and of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tentimes,
<pb facs="tcp:6059:125"/> it hapneth that when wee ſuppoſe to be a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mong our truſtie friends, we dwell as <hi>Ezechiell</hi> did a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mongſt ſcorpions and vene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mous ſerpents, we crie with thy holy prophet, O Lord deliuer my ſoule from wic<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ked lippes, and a guilefull tongue. But if neuertheleſſe it ſéeme good to thée, to ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>erciſe vs thy ſeruants alſo in this affliction, to the in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tent they may bee better brought to godlines before
<pb facs="tcp:6059:125"/> thée, and bée bettered in this world, then graunt we pray thée, that with <hi>Paul</hi> thy moſt valiant champion, wee may by reproch &amp; glory, by infa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mie and good name, abide ſtill in thy commaunde<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments, through Ieſus Chriſt, which alſo himſelfe (when he walked here on earth) was reuiled, ſlandred, euill ſpoken of, and called to his face a Samaritane, a wine drinker, a deceiuer of the people, and one that
<pb facs="tcp:6059:126"/> had a diuel, and yet the ſame now raigneth with thée in glory, whither alſo wee be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeech thee, in good time to bring vs, and that together with the reſt, whom thou haſt put apart to euerla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſting bleſſednes through Chriſt Ieſus. Amen.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="prayer">
               <head>A Prayer againſt worldly carefulnes.</head>
               <p>
                  <hi>O</hi> Moſt deare and ten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der father, our defen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der and nouriſher, endue vs
<pb facs="tcp:6059:126"/> with thy grace, that wee may caſt off the great blind<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes of our minds, and care<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fulnes of worldly thinges, and may imploy our whole ſtudie and care in kéeping of thy holy lawes: and yet that wee may trauaile and labour, for our neceſſities in this life, like the birdes of the aire, and the lillies of the field, without carefulneſſe: for thou haſt promiſed to be carefull for vs, and haſt commanded that vpon thée,
<pb facs="tcp:6059:127"/> we ſhould caſt all our care, which liueſt and raigneſt world without ende. Amen.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="prayer">
               <head>A Prayer againſt the diuel.</head>
               <p>IEſu Chriſt our Lord, which by the mouth of thy holy Apoſtle S. Peter didſt ſay, that our aduerſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie the diuell goeth about like a roring lyon ſéeking whom hee may deuour, wee know the truth of this by our owne experience, and
<pb facs="tcp:6059:127"/> féele that hee is buſie and fierce and breaketh in vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on vs: ſo that if thou helpe not, hee will ſoone deceaue vs with his craft, ouer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turne vs with his might and with his crueltie teare vs in péeces. But if thou which haſt vanquiſhed him wilt appeare, but as it were a farre off, thou wilt make him afraide, and with thy onely looke, put him to ſlight.</p>
               <p>Vouchſafe (O Lord) to
<pb facs="tcp:6059:128"/> receiue vs into thy tuition, being but infants, weake, féeble, and vnſkilful, leſt the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="3 letters">
                     <desc>•••</desc>
                  </gap>rce and cruell beaſt all to teare vs: yea, giue vs grace alwayes, not onely to beare before vs the ſworde of the ſpirit in our ſight, and to tarrie it in our hands, but alſo couragiouſly to vſe it, as from thée, that ſo our ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies may well, know that we doe our buſines by thy counſaile, aid, and ſtrength and in thy power may bee
<pb facs="tcp:6059:128"/> put to flight, to thy glorie, and our euerlaſting comfort through Chriſt. Amen.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="prayer">
               <head>A thankeſ-giuing vnto God for all his benefites.</head>
               <p>WE verie humbly in Chriſt thanke thée, O heauenly Father, for thy manifold and ineſtimable benefits, which thou haſt giuen to vs, both for our ſoules and bodies, yea and that fréely of thine owne goodnes not onely without,
<pb facs="tcp:6059:129"/> but contrarie to our deſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing. We thanke thée, that it hath pleaſed thee of thy great mercie, firſt, to cre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ate and make vs according to thine owne image and likenes, and to place vs in ioyfull Paradiſe, where we ſhould haue continually re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mained in a bleſſed and quiet ſtate, if through the ſubtile and deceitfull ſuggeſtions of Satan, our old enemie, we had not tranſgreſſed thy holy commandements. We
<pb facs="tcp:6059:129"/> thanke thee alſo, O moſt gentle Father, for thy lo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing kindnes, which thou ſhewedſt to vs, when wee were all periſhed and loſt through the ſinne of our firſt parents Adam and Heua.</p>
               <p>For when thou mighteſt iuſtly haue condemned vs, and caſt vs into perpetuall damnation, thou like a fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther of ſingular great loue hadſt pitty on vs, and ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uedſt vs by the death and paſſion of thy welbeloued
<pb facs="tcp:6059:130"/> ſonne our Lord and ſauiour Ieſus Chriſt, who gaue himſelfe a ranſome for all our ſinnes, and payed a ſufficient price by his pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cious bloud, for all the wic<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kedneſſe that wee at any time heretofore haue com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitted, or hereafter ſhall commit through our frailtie and weakenes, ſo that wee beléeue thy promiſes, and repent and amend our liues. Neither waſt thou thus contented, that hee onely
<pb facs="tcp:6059:130"/> ſhould die for our ſinnes, but alſo diddeſt raiſe him vp againe for our iuſtification, and to make vs righteous in thy ſight. Moreouer after that he had ſhewed himſelfe vnfainedly to liue to his A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſtles, by manifeſt and e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uident tokens certainelie through the power of his Godhead hee aſcended vp in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to heauen, perfect God and perfect man, where he now ſitteth on thy right hande, and maketh interceſſion for
<pb facs="tcp:6059:131"/> vs, being our alone media<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tor and aduocate: from thence we looke for him to come againe at the day of iudgement, not as a feare<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full Iudge to condemne and caſt vs away, but as a moſt louing Lord and gen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tle Sauiour, to carry vs with him into euerlaſting glorie, there world with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out end to remaine in ſuch ioyes, as eye hath not ſeene, nor eare hath not heard, nor yet any heart
<pb facs="tcp:6059:131"/> is able to thinke.</p>
               <p>For theſe thy moſt boun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teous giftes, and for all o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther thy benefites which thou daylie giueſt to vs of thy great mercie, both for our body and ſoule, wee humbly thanke thee, moſt mercifull Father, beſéech<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing thee to giue vs grace through thy holy ſpirit, not to bee either vnmind full of them, or vnthankefull for them, but to walke worthy of this thy kindnes, and ſo
<pb facs="tcp:6059:132"/> behaue our ſelues all our life time in this wretched world, according to thy holy will, that at the laſt day we may bee found in the num<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber of them, to whom thy onely begotten ſoone ſhall ſay, Come ye bleſſed of my father, poſſeſſe the king<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome prepared for you from the beginning of this world. Lord let it ſo come to paſſe euen for Chriſt Ieſus ſake. Amen.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="prayer">
               <pb facs="tcp:6059:132"/>
               <head>A deuout Prayer to bee day<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lie ſayd.</head>
               <p>
                  <hi>O</hi> Almighty and eternal God which vouchſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fedſt that wee (as it were) heauenly children, ſhould euery one of vs call thee our heauenly father. Grant that among vs by purenes and example of innocent life, thy moſt holy name may bee ſanctified, that all other nations beholding our goodneſſe, and vertuous li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing
<pb facs="tcp:6059:133"/> that thou workeſt in vs, may bee ſtirred to hal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low and glorifie thée. Grant (O Lord) that the king<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome of thy grace and mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cie in this life may ſo rule and raigne continually in our hearts, that we may bee by thée accepted and ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>counted, as worthie in Chriſt to bee partakers of thy kingdome of glorie and maieſtie, in the life to come. Grant that vnto the very death, yea and in death it
<pb facs="tcp:6059:133"/> ſelfe alſo, wee refuſe not to follow thy diuine will, but that wee according to the example of the celeſtiall ci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tizens, agréeing together quietly, vnited in ſpirit, all controuerſie in opinions contrarie to thy holy truth, being laide apart, and the luſt of the fleſh being ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dued, and the flattering aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſaults of the world and the diuell ouercome, we may willingly, faithfully, and conſtantly, obey thy bleſſed
<pb facs="tcp:6059:134"/> will in all things. Graunt O Lord, for our bodie ſuch a meaſure of neceſſarie and néedefull ſuſtenance, that thereby we may be the bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter enabled, more freely and hearefully to ſerue thée, and abound in all good workes, towards thy ſaints and ſeruants here vpon earth, knowing that our goodneſſe reacheth not to thee, but to the excellent that are in the world, whom wee beſeech thée make vs
<pb facs="tcp:6059:134"/> more and more to delight in, and to loue for thy ſake.</p>
               <p>Giue me grace, O Lord, not onely patiently to beare and ſuffer our enemies, and ſuch as hate vs, together with the iniuries, which they doe lay vpon vs, ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king good vſe of them, for thy glorie and our inſtructi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, but alſo vnfaignedly to forget and forgiue, what<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoeuer they haue deuiſed, ſayd or done againſt vs euen as wee our ſelues would
<pb facs="tcp:6059:135"/> gladly obtayne at thy mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cifull hands, and féele in our ſelues the frée pardon and full forgiueneſſe of all our tranſgreſſions. And for ſuch temptations to euill, as from the corruption of our nature ariſe vppe in our hearts, giue vs grace firſt clearely to diſcerne and diſcouer them; then coura<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giouſly to ſtand vp againſt them, and ſoundly to loath and leaue them, that we bée not in the ſtrength of them,
<pb facs="tcp:6059:135"/> as it were in the middeſt of a violent tempeſt, carried headlong into ſinne, and by meanes thereof into euer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>laſting deſtruction.</p>
               <p>Eſpecially ſtrengthen vs (good Lord) againſt the ſuggeſtions of Satan, whoſe maruellous malice, wilie ſubtilties and verie great power againſt vs, wee are not ignorant of: as not vnacquainted neither with our owne weakenes and diſability to withſtand:
<pb facs="tcp:6059:136"/> What ſay wee? more with our proneneſſe and readi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe to yeeld: and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore cannot but in both theſe reſpects, againe and againe intreate thée, that art the God of our ſtrength to cauſe thy grace to bee ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficient for vs and in vs, and to make thy power perfect through our infirmitie, that ſo hauing fought valiant<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, and mightily ouercome through thy ſtrength, wee may through thy goodneſſe
<pb facs="tcp:6059:136"/> and mercie, for euermore liue with thée, in that hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uenly citie, where and a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt which, as alſo againſt ſuch citizens of thine, as are gathered into it, no man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner of temptation ſhall aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſayle, much leſſe bee able to preuaile, and there for e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer haue the full fruition of celeſtiall delectation, not on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly accompanied with An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gels and bleſſed Saints, but enioying the moſt comfor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>table ſight of thy glorious
<pb facs="tcp:6059:137"/> countenance, in whoſe pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſence is the fulnes of ioy, and at thy right hand there are pleaſures for euermore, which vouchſafe vnto vs, for Ieſus Chriſts ſake thy déere ſonne, and our all and on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly ſufficient Sauiour. A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="prayer">
               <head>Another Prayer to our Lord God.</head>
               <p>
                  <hi>O</hi> Heauenly Father, God almighty, I pray and beſéech thée in mercie,
<pb facs="tcp:6059:137"/> graciouſly to behold me thy vnworthie ſeruant, that I may, by the giftes of thy ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly ſpirit, feruently deſire thy kingdome, and by the light of thy word, may ſoundly knowe thy will, and faith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fully worke and walke thereafter. Giue mee, O Lord, wiſedome, euen the wiſedome that is from a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>boue. Make mee conſtant in thy truth, patient in tri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bulation, and ſtrong in thée vnto the ende. Keepe mee
<pb facs="tcp:6059:138"/> Lord, from the ſleightie in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uaſion of the olde wily ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pent. Defend mee from the counſailes and curſings of euill tongues. Let thy mightie arme bee my con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinuall ſhield againſt all the malignity and miſchiefe of this wicked world: Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>member not Lord my offen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces: inſtruct and prepare me to repent, and teach mee to be truly ſorrowfull for my ſinnes. Make me to loue iuſtice and hate wrong, to
<pb facs="tcp:6059:138"/> doe good, and abſteine from all euils, that ſo the fruits of my faith, may pledge vp to my conſcience, that thou haſt graciouſly called me to be thy child. To thée there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore bée glory and honor for euer and euer. Amen.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="prayer">
               <head>A deuout Prayer.</head>
               <p>HEarken Lord to my wordes, conſider the thoughts of my heart. Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hold how loud I cry to thée, Let my iuſt prayer enter
<pb facs="tcp:6059:139"/> into thine eares, which vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fainedly commeth from my heart. Heare me Lord, for I am poore and deſtitute of mans helpe. Take care for my ſoule. Saue me thy ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uant which wholy truſt in thee. Haue mercie vpon me, O Lord, for I will neuer ceaſe crying to thee for help, for thou art mild and more mercifull, than my tongue is able to expreſſe, yea than my heart is able to thinke. As often as aduerſitie aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſaileth
<pb facs="tcp:6059:139"/> me, I will crie and call for helpe vnto thée: I will call vpon thée in the day time, and in the night my cry ſhall not bee hid from thée; O thou God of the heauens, maker of the waters, and Lord of all creatures, heare me a poore ſinner calling vpon thée, and putting my whole truſt in thy mercie, haue mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cie vpon me, O Lord God, haue mercie vpon mée, and for thy manifold mercies
<pb facs="tcp:6059:140"/> ſake forgiue mee all my offences. Amen.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="prayer">
               <head>A prayer for meekenes and chaſtitie.</head>
               <p>
                  <hi>O</hi> Lord, thou father and God of my life, let mee not haue a proud looke, but turne away all voluptuouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes from mee. Take from mee the luſtes of the body, let not the deſires of vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cleaneneſſe take hold vpon me, and giue me not ouer in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to an vnſhamefaſt and ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtinate mind. Amen.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="prayer">
               <pb facs="tcp:6059:140"/>
               <head>A prayer of Eſay in the 6. and 64. Chap.</head>
               <p>LOrd looke downe from heauen, and behold from thy holy habitations, and from the ſeate of thy glorie: where is thy ſtrength? where is the plenteous rich multitude of thy mercies? are al theſe hardned againſt vs? verily thou art our Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther: Abraham now know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth vs not, nor Iſrael knoweth vs not, but thou
<pb facs="tcp:6059:141"/> Lord art our father, thou art our redeemer, thy name is from the beginning. Wherefore haſt thou made vs Lord to erre from thy wayes? haſt thou hardned our hearts leaſt wee ſhould feare thée? Turne thee to thy promiſe made to thy ſeruants, for the tribes of thy heritage: for few of thy people haue enioyed the poſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeſſion of their land, and that but a little while. Our ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies haue ſpoyled thy holy
<pb facs="tcp:6059:141"/> place, and troden it vnder féete. And wee were regar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded ſo vile, as if thou hadſt neuer béen Lord ouer vs, as though thy glorious name had neuer béen called vpon by vs, and ſhewed ouer vs. I would that thou wouldeſt all too breake the heauens and come downe once, that theſe hilles might melt a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>way at thy preſence, like as at a hot fire, and that the malicious might boyle a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>way, as doth the water vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on
<pb facs="tcp:6059:142"/> the fire, that thy name might be knowne to thy e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nemies, and theſe vngodly might bee ſhamed and trou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bled at thy preſence. When thou wroughteſt for vs marueilous things, then we looked not for them: thou camſt downe, and the hilles waſted away with trem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bling before thy face, and from the beginning hearde they not, nor perceiued with their eares, neither with any eye was there
<pb facs="tcp:6059:142"/> ſéene any beſides thee, that wrought ſuch marueilous things, and that to men, which waited not for thée: ſometime thou méeteſt with them that gladly did righte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſneſſe, and thought vpon thee in thy wayes. But now Lord, thou art angry, becauſe wee are ſinners, and euer haue béen in ſinne, al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>though wee were deliuered from perils. And all we are wrapped in filthie vnclean<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe, yea all our righte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſnes
<pb facs="tcp:6059:143"/> is ſpotted like the cloathes of a me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſtruous wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man, and all wee are taken away like leaues, and our iniquities haue caried vs a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>way like a whirle-winde, and there is none left that will call for helpe in thy name, and not one that will riſe vp and holde thée with prayer, for thou haſt hid thy face from vs, and haſt dried vs vp in the hand of our ini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quitie. But now Lord thou art our Father, wee are but,
<pb facs="tcp:6059:143"/> clay, and thou art our pot<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, and all wee are the works of thy hands, bee not angry, O Lord, for euer, and remember not all our wickednes. Loe, beholde we beſéech thee, all wee are thy people, the cities of thy holy places are forſaken, Syon is turned into a de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſert, Ieruſalem is deſolate, the houſe of holines and prayer and of our glory, in which our fathers praiſes thée, is turned into an he<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>e
<pb facs="tcp:6059:144"/> of fire and all things that we delighted in, into a wil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dernes. Wilt thou, Lord, be auenged of theſe things? Wilt thou holde thy peace, and ſcourge vs euer ſo grie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uouſly?</p>
            </div>
            <div type="prayer">
               <head>Before the receiuing of the Sacrament, ſay thus.</head>
               <p>LOrd, although I be not worthy to receiue thee into the houſe of my ſoule, for mine innumerable offen<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ces and ſinnes done againſt
<pb facs="tcp:6059:144"/> thy great goodnes, yet tru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſting in thy great pity, and infinite mercie, I come to receiue thy bleſſed body, not groſſely and carnally as the blinde ſuppoſe, but ſpiritu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ally and by faith, together with all the fruits and ef<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fects of thy ſufferings, yea as a ſicke creature to thee, that art the health of life: vncleane to thée, that art the well of mercie and holy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes: blinde by ignorance to thee, that art the light
<pb facs="tcp:6059:145"/> euerlaſting: needy of grace and power, yea of will to any good thing to thée, that art the King of heauen and earth and workeſt therein whatſoeuer pleaſeth thée: naked of good works, to thée, that art the author of all grace. I come as a wretch to thée my Lord and maker, all deſolate and comfortles, to thee my refuge and ſuc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cour, for beſides thée there is no conſolation. I come as a ſinner to thée, that art
<pb facs="tcp:6059:145"/> the mediator betwéene God and man. I come as a caitife to thée my moſt mercifull Sauiour. I come all ſinfull to thee, granter of remiſſion and pardon: I that am dead by ſin, come to thee, the re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtorer of life, euill to thee, that art all goodneſſe: hard hearted, to bée relieued by the infuſion of thy ſupera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>boundant grace: deſiring thée to heale mine infirmitie and ſicknes, to waſh away my ſinne and filthines, to
<pb facs="tcp:6059:146"/> lighten my blindnes, to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duce me to the right way, when I am out thereof, to comfort me deſolate of good<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe. Haue mercie on my wretchedneſſe, pardon my ſinfulnes, giue me the light of grace thus buried in ſin, that I may receiue thee to be the ſpirituall foode and nouriſhment of my ſoule: and that with ſuch chaſtitie of body, with ſuch purenes and cleannes of ſoule, with ſuch contrition of heart,
<pb facs="tcp:6059:146"/> and abundance of wéeping teares, with ſuch ſpirituall ioy and gladnes, with ſuch dread and reuerence, with ſuch ſtrong faith, ſtedfaſt hope and vnfeigned chari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie, with ſuch obedience and humilitie, with ſuch loue, deuotion, faithfulneſſe, and thankefulneſſe, as it is be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſéeming for ſuch a Lord to be entertained and receiued withall, and that to the comfort of my conſcience in this life, and my endleſſe
<pb facs="tcp:6059:147"/> ſaluation at the laſt.</p>
               <p>And be not diſpleaſed good Lord, that I a ſinner, with an vncleane heart, and pol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>luted minde, (or ſure I am not ſo ſanctified outwardly and inwardly, as were fit) come hither this day to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiue the bleſſed ſacrament of thy precious body and bloud, by a liuely faith: but remember mercifull Lord, that thou refuſedſt not the ſinfull Magdalene being penitent, from the kiſſing
<pb facs="tcp:6059:147"/> of thy moſt bleſſed féete. And in likewiſe deſpiſe mee not, ne put thou me away as vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>worthie, from this bleſſed Sacrament, for my ſinnes and vnkindnes, though I confeſſe thou maiſt iuſtly doe ſo, and doe me no iniu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie: but graunt thou mee godly ſorrow of heart, plen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie of vnfaigned teares, to teſtifie vnto my heart, the waſhing away of my ſinnes and wickednes: ſo that with a pure heart, and cleane
<pb facs="tcp:6059:148"/> conſcience, I may this day come to, and be partaker of the holy Communion, to thy glory and the comfort of my ſoule and conſcience, whileſt I receiue therein an effectuall pledge of euer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>laſting life, with all holy ſaints in heauens glory, and of the fellowſhip of thy peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple in this preſent life, theſe things being wrought in mee, by thy holy ſpirit in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wardly, as well as offered vnto me by the outward
<pb facs="tcp:6059:148"/> and viſible elements. Grant mee bleſſed Ieſu, ſo reue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rently and religiouſly to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiue the Sacrament of thy fleſh and bloud, that there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by I may aſſuredly feele my ſelfe incorporated into thy Church, as a ſound member of thy body here on earth: and though as yet I be not méete or fit, by reaſon of my filthineſſe, to bee numbred among the ſimpleſt and loweſt of thy ſeruants, but rather to be reiect for my
<pb facs="tcp:6059:149"/> ſinfulnes: yet good Lord, of thine infinite power I knowe thou canſt, and of thy ſingular goodneſſe I hope thou wilt, and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore am alſo the more bold humbly to intreate thee, to make me equall, and like to thine elect and choſen ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uants.</p>
               <p>Come thou father of the fatheries, come comfort of the comfortles, come I be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſéech thee, and cleanſe my ſoule from contagiouſnes
<pb facs="tcp:6059:149"/> of ſinne: for it is not con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uenient, and according, that there ſhould bee any vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cleannes, where thou then, the fountaine of all true ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lines, yea holines it ſelfe, ſhouldeſt come in and dwel. Come therefore good Lord, and apparell my ſoule and body both with ſuch orna<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments of vertue and grace, that it may delight thee therein to abide.</p>
               <p>And as thou diſdainedſt not to touch the ſore Lea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pers
<pb facs="tcp:6059:150"/> with thy holy hands: ſo good Lord vouchſafe to annoynt my ſinfull ſoule with the oyntment of remiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion and pardon of ſinnes, and ſo to repleniſh it with ſtrength and power againſt ſinne, and to fill it with a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bilitie to doe good duties, that in this life, by ſtedfaſt hope, firme faith, and vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feigned charitie, I may ſo encreaſe in vertue from day to day, that I may attaine to the glorious fruition of
<pb facs="tcp:6059:150"/> thy Godhead in the king<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome of heauen, where I may ſee thee face to face, world without ende. A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="prayer">
               <head>After the receiuing of the Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crament, ſay thus.</head>
               <p>
                  <hi>I</hi> Thank thée, good Lord, of thine infinit goodnes for y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> this day y<hi rend="sup">u</hi> haſt vouchſafed to féed me with thy bleſſed bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy in this holy Sacrament of thine, and that by a liuely faith, thou haſt made me
<pb facs="tcp:6059:151"/> a fruiteful partaker thereof, humbly deſiring thée, fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther to graunt, that this thy bleſſed Sacrament, which I haue receiued, may bee powerfull in mee, to leſſen in me, and purge from mee the power of my particular iniquities, and to fit mee to all good workes of bleſſed obedience, yea make it in me a fortitude, and a ſpiri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuall ſtrength againſt my frailtie, a ſure defence a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt worldly troubles and
<pb facs="tcp:6059:151"/> aduerſitie, a ſure ſeale of grace and pardon: a medi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cine of life, and a continuall remembrance in my minde and heart of thy bleſſed paſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion, ſo that in the way it may conduct and guide me, and when I am out of the way, it may reduce mee: when I ſtumble, it may vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>holde mee, and when I am falling, it may raiſe me: ſo that by this and other gra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cious helpes that thou haſt ordained, and by good con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinuance,
<pb facs="tcp:6059:152"/> and daily growth in the obedience of thy will I may be brought to euerla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſting glorie. And during my life vpon earth, vouchſafe ſo to order the tallage and taſte of my heart, that I neuer féele other ſwéetenes but thee, that I neuer ſeeke o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther but thee, that I care not for any other delight but thee, neither that I re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gard any other honor but thine. And giue me ſuch a ſound loue towards thee,
<pb facs="tcp:6059:152"/> and in thee, and for thee, to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards my brethren, that in it, I may continually and comfortably féele, that I am tranſlated out of darknes into light, and be well aſſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red, that thou wilt grati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſly deliuer mee from all tribulations of body and ſoule, captiuitie, anguiſh, and perils, together with all the elect and choſen. A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="prayer">
               <pb facs="tcp:6059:153"/>
               <head>A deuout Prayer</head>
               <p>
                  <hi>O</hi> My Lord Ieſu, with al my mind, with all my might I do laude thee, and praiſe thée for thine innume<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>rable benefites which thou haſt ſhewed vnto mee here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tofore, and ſheweſt daily: but alas, good Lord, ſure I am of this, that I cannot praiſe thée as I would, and as my dutie requireth: wherefore I méekely be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſéech thee, both to accept this
<pb facs="tcp:6059:153"/> my bounden dutie and ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uice, and alſo to ſupplie and fulfill mine inſufficiencie, ſo that thy abſolute righte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſneſſe and obedience may for mee be acceptable before thy father, and may to mee, and in me, bee comfortable to my ſoule. O ſwéete Ieſu, I loue thée as my God, my maker, and my redéemer: what though I loue thee not ſo feruently, as I ought to doe? yet I humbly beſéech thée, to accept me according
<pb facs="tcp:6059:154"/> to that I haue, and not ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to that I haue not, and the rather, becauſe that I haue, is thine, which I pray thée ſo to acknowledge and daylie more and more increaſe, that my peace in hee, and loue towards thée, may more and more a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bound. O ſweete Saui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>our heare me here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>: euen ſo be it.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="prayer">
               <pb facs="tcp:6059:154"/>
               <head>The complaint of a penitent ſinner, which is ſore trou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bled and ouercome with ſinnes.</head>
               <p>
                  <hi>O</hi> Lord God mercifull and patient, and of much mercifulneſſe and truth, which of thy abun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dant charitie, and according to thy great mercie, haſt taken vs out from the pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er of darknes, and haſt ſaued vs by the fountaine of rege<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neration, and new birth,
<pb facs="tcp:6059:155"/> and the renewing of the ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly Ghoſt: whom thou haſt ſhed vpon vs aboundantly by Ieſus Chriſt our Saui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>our.</p>
               <p>If I haue found grace and fauour in thy ſight, ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fer me to ſpeake a word vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to thée, and be not diſpleaſed with me.</p>
               <p>Why doſt thou euer for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>get me and leaueſt me in the midſt of my troubles and evils?</p>
               <p>Where is become thy
<pb facs="tcp:6059:155"/> zeale and ſtrength? where is the multitude of thy ten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der affections, and of thy mercies?</p>
               <p>O Lorde, may not hee which is fallen, riſe vp a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gaine? Or may not hee which hath gone away from thee, returne vnto thée a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gaine?</p>
               <p>Shall my ſorrow <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>er indure? ſhall my <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ound be vncurable and neuer hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led?</p>
               <p>How commeth it to paſſe,
<pb facs="tcp:6059:156"/> that I ſtill turne away from thee, ſurely Satans malice and mine owne corruption carie me violently. But ſtay me O Lord, and turne me, yea cauſe me to turne, for of my ſelfe I cannot re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turne.</p>
               <p>In aſmuch as it is not gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen to man to direct his <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap> wayes, neither to <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> perfect his owne pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceedings.</p>
               <p>For in thy hand is the life of euery liuing thing:
<pb facs="tcp:6059:156"/> and the ſpirit alſo of euery man.</p>
               <p>Thou ſheweſt thy mercy to whom thou wilt, and thou art gracious to them, whom thou fauoureſt.</p>
               <p>Thou doeſt kill, and thou doeſt quicken, thou leadeſt downe to Hell gate, and bringeſt vp againe.</p>
               <p>Thy eyes beholde the wayes of euery man, and thou ſearcheſt the hearts of men.</p>
               <p>There is no place ſo ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cret
<pb facs="tcp:6059:157"/> or darke, wherein ſins may hide themſelues from thee.</p>
               <p>Nor any man may ſo lurke and hide themſelfe in Caues, but thou ſhalt ſée him, which doeſt fulfill both heauen and earth in euery pa<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>t.</p>
               <p>Why haſt thou caſt me away from thy preſence, and <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>eſt me for thine ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mie?</p>
               <p>Why haſt thou layd vpon my head the heauie
<pb facs="tcp:6059:157"/> weight of my ſinnes, ſéeing no man is able to beare thy diſpleaſure?</p>
               <p>What meaneth it that thou ſheweſt thy power a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt a wretch? why de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtroyeſt thou me for the ſins of my youth?</p>
               <p>If I haue ſinned, what ſhall I doe to thée? and if my ſins be encreaſed what ſhall I doe?</p>
               <p>If I do iuſtly, what ſhal I giue to thée? or what ſhalt thou receiue a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> my hand?</p>
               <pb facs="tcp:6059:158"/>
               <p>My wickedneſſe ſhall hurt my ſelfe, and my righ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teouſneſſe ſhall not profit me.</p>
               <p>The life of man is a temptation vpon the earth, and if I haue ſinned (as all m<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> ha<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>e) what may I <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap>?</p>
               <p>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>hall <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> man be found <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap> without ſinne <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap> or ſhall any man <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> withou<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> fault in his deedes?</p>
               <p>How may a mortall m<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <pb facs="tcp:6059:158"/> be pure of ſinne in thy ſight? or how may hee which is borne of a woman, be righ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teous?</p>
               <p>Remember, O Lord, I beſeech thee, that thou haſt made me of the earth, and that thou ſhalt bring mee againe into the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>uſt of death.</p>
               <p>My dayes pa<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> and v<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>niſh away like <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap> waſte daily, there is no ta<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>y<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing.</p>
               <p>My life flieth, as the
<pb facs="tcp:6059:159"/> winde, and conſidereth not that which is good.</p>
               <p>I was but lately borne in this world, and ſhortly I ſhall be taken away hence by death, I neuer continue ſtill in one ſtate.</p>
               <p>The dayes of my life bee few, and ſhort, thou haſt appoynted an end, which I ſhall not paſſe.</p>
               <p>Naked and bare I came out of my mothers wombe, and naked and bare I ſhall returne againe, truly all
<pb facs="tcp:6059:159"/> men liuing are but vani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie.</p>
               <p>Haue pitie O Lord, on them that are in miſerie, and deſpiſe not the workes of thy hands.</p>
               <p>Though we ſin, yet are we vnder thée, for we know thy power and ſtrength: and if we ſinne not, then are we ſure that thou regardeſt vs.</p>
               <p>Ceaſe thy indignation, O Lord, and turne it from mee: and caſt all my <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>nes
<pb facs="tcp:6059:160"/> behind thy backe.</p>
               <p>Take away thy plagues from mee: for thy puniſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment hath made mee both feeble and faint.</p>
               <p>For when thou chaſtiſeſt a man for his ſinnes, thou cauſeſt him by and by to conſume and pine away.</p>
               <p>Whatſoeuer is delecta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble in him, periſheth like vnto the cloth that is eaten with moaths.</p>
               <p>Would God I had one <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> defend me a while, vntill
<pb facs="tcp:6059:160"/> thy anger were turned a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>way, or that thou wouldeſt remember me.</p>
               <p>I am cleane caſt away from thy preſence: ſhall I neuer hereafter ſee thy face againe?</p>
               <p>Beholde I haue opened the griefs of my ſoule, the day of my ſorrowes haue taken me.</p>
               <p>The flouds of tribulati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on compaſſe mee round a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bout, and the ſtreames of thy fury run ouer me.</p>
               <pb facs="tcp:6059:161"/>
               <p>And I cry vnto thée, O Lord God, but thou heareſt me not: I aſke mercie, but thou reiecteſt my prayers.</p>
               <p>Why thruſteſt thou downe a poore wretch from thy preſence? or why for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſakeſt thou mee ſo longe time?</p>
               <p>Why takeſt thou not a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>way mine in<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>uitie? and why putteſt th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> not away the wickedneſſe of my heart?</p>
               <p>Ariſe and tary no longer,
<pb facs="tcp:6059:161"/> O Lord, ariſe, and reiect me not for euer.</p>
               <p>Haue mee in remem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brance I beſéech thée, for I throughlie tremble and ſhake for feare.</p>
               <p>Yet will I not holde my tongue, but cry ſtil vnto thée with a mourning and an heauie hear<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>.</p>
               <p>Turne away the ſtroke of thy ve<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>eance from me and bring my <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> out of troubles into reſt.</p>
               <p>I am here no long con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinuer,
<pb facs="tcp:6059:162"/> but a pilgrime and a ſtranger, as all other mor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tall men be.</p>
               <p>And what is man that thou ſhouldeſt bee angrie with him? or what is man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kinde, that thou ſhouldeſt bee ſo heauie Lord vnto vs?</p>
               <p>What, wilt thou bring ſorrow vppon ſorrow? I pant for paine, and finde no reſt.</p>
               <p>My ſorrow grieueth me, when I ſhould eate, and ſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>daine
<pb facs="tcp:6059:162"/> ſighes ouerwhelme my heart.</p>
               <p>I am as if my bones were all to broken, when I heare my enemies raile vpon me, and ſay to mee day by day where is thy God?</p>
               <p>Why turneſt thou thy face from theſe thinges, O Lord, why haſt thou no re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gard of my trouble?</p>
               <p>I earneſtly make my prayers daily in thy ſight, and the heauines of my hart I doe ſhew vnto thée.</p>
               <pb facs="tcp:6059:163"/>
               <p>My ſpirit is carefull and troubled within mee: and deſperation hath entred into my heart.</p>
               <p>Is it thy pleaſure, O Lord God, to caſt away thine own handie workes?</p>
               <p>Deliuer my ſoule from <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>rruption, and my life from euerlaſting darknes.</p>
               <p>What auaileth it mee, that euer I was borne, if thou caſt mee ſtraight into damnation: ſéeing that the dead ſhall not praiſe thée, nor
<pb facs="tcp:6059:163"/> any of them which go down to hell?</p>
               <p>I haue ſinned, what ſhal I doe to thée? why haſt thou put me to be contrarie to thée? I am wearie of mine owne ſelfe.</p>
               <p>Why ſearcheſt thou out my ſinnes ſo narrowly? when there is no man that can eſcape out of thy hands?</p>
               <p>If I would ſay that I were righteous and with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out ſinne, then thou migh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſt
<pb facs="tcp:6059:164"/> worthily condemne me to the fire prepared for the diuell and his angels.</p>
               <p>But I confeſſe that I am a ſinner, and doe hum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble my ſelfe here in thy ſight.</p>
               <p>Surely if a man would <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>and with thee in iudge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, he ſhall not bee able to anſwere one word to a thouſand things where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>with thou mighteſt charge him.</p>
               <p>This maketh me to feare
<pb facs="tcp:6059:164"/> all my deedes, knowing that thou ſpareſt not him that offendeth.</p>
               <p>If I looke vppon thy power, O how mightie and ſtrong art thou? If I ſhall call for iudgement, who ſhall defend my matter, or ſpeake for me?</p>
               <p>To thee O Lord, I call and crie, to thee my God I make my humble ſute.</p>
               <p>Turne away thine an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger from mee, that I may know that thou art more
<pb facs="tcp:6059:165"/> mercifull to mee than my ſinnes deſerue.</p>
               <p>What is my ſtrength that I may endure? or what is the ende of my trouble, that my ſoule may patiently abide it?</p>
               <p>My ſtrength is not a ſtony ſtrength, and my fleſh is not made of braſſe.</p>
               <p>There is no helpe in my ſelfe, and alſo my ſtrength flieth away from me.</p>
               <p>Although thou hide theſe things in my heart, yet I
<pb facs="tcp:6059:165"/> know that thou wilt re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>member me at length.</p>
               <p>For thou art true and iuſt, O Lord God, thou doeſt not condemne vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iuſtly, which rewardeſt man according to his de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerts.</p>
               <p>All this is come vnto me becauſe I haue forgotten thee, and not vſed my ſelfe truely in thy teſtimo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nies.</p>
               <p>My heart hath turned backeward, and I haue fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowed
<pb facs="tcp:6059:166"/> the deſires of my fleſh.</p>
               <p>And thou haſt ſurely knowne this thing, which knoweſt the ſecrets of the heart.</p>
               <p>Lay not againſt mee, O Lord, the ſinnes of my youth: nor haue in remem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brance my old iniuries done againſt thee.</p>
               <p>Daily ſorrow <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>meth me, and ſadnes poſſeſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeth my heart.</p>
               <p>I looke after peace, but I
<pb facs="tcp:6059:166"/> cannot haue it: I looke for a time of health, but my griefe continueth ſtill.</p>
               <p>When the time of thine anger is paſt, let mercie come, yet am I vnhappie more and more.</p>
               <p>Woe and alas that euer I ſinned: my heart there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore mourneth and is ſad, al mirth and ioy is vaniſhed from me.</p>
               <p>How am I waſted? how miſerably am I confoun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded, becauſe I haue forſaken
<pb facs="tcp:6059:167"/> and caſt away thy law.</p>
               <p>Death hath aſcended by the windowes, pearcing the inward parts of my heart</p>
               <p>W<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="3 letters">
                     <desc>•••</desc>
                  </gap> I daily one while muſt ſecretly with my ſelfe: another while with loud voyce crye out and com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plaine, the meane time my life draweth néere to the pit.</p>
               <p>Who ſhall giue mee a place to reſt in, from all my griefts and troubles?</p>
               <pb facs="tcp:6059:167"/>
               <p>And I will forſake all men and get away from them.</p>
               <p>Who ſhall giue me wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter to my head, and a foun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine of teares to mine eyes, that I may bewaile my ſinnes both night and day?</p>
               <p>And I will looke for him which may ſaue me, and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liuer me from the wrath to come.</p>
               <p>I haue no truſt neither in life nor death, but I feare
<pb facs="tcp:6059:168"/> thy iudgement, O Lord, and the paines prepared for ſinners.</p>
               <p>The feare of my ſinne maketh mee carefull: and the burden of my conſcience oppreſſeth me ſore.</p>
               <p>O God which tenderly loueſt mankind, and art a moſt righteous Iudge, ſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>are mee now I beſéech mee, and ſhewe mee ſome fauour while time is. For<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giue that which I feare, put away that which I
<pb facs="tcp:6059:168"/> dread, before I depart hence and ſhall not returne againe.</p>
               <p>My ſinnes doe vexe and trouble mee ſore, they bee ſo great that none can be grea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter.</p>
               <p>Alas my fall, alas my miſerie, alas the griefe of my plague, and ſtroke: cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tainly my ſinne is the cauſe of all this, and ſo I will take it, and ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fer it.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="prayer">
               <pb facs="tcp:6059:169"/>
               <head>A Pſalme in which he giueth thankes to God, that his enemies haue not gotten the vpper hand of him.</head>
               <p>
                  <hi>I</hi> Wil magnifie and praiſe thee, O Lord God, for thou haſt exalted me and ſet me vp, and mine enemies haue not gotten the vpper hand of me.</p>
               <p>O Lord of ho<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> I haue cried vnto thee and thou haſt ſaued me.</p>
               <p>Th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>aſt brought my
<pb facs="tcp:6059:169"/> ſoule out of hell: thou haſt holden mee vp from falling into the déepe Lake, from whence no man returneth.</p>
               <p>Thou haſt not cloſed me vp in the hands of mine ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies: but thou haſt ſet my féete in a place both wide and broade.</p>
               <p>I haue ſought thée, and thou haſt heard mee, thou haſt brought me into liber<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie out of great diſtreſſe.</p>
               <p>Thou ha<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>urned my ſorrowe into <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <pb facs="tcp:6059:170"/> haſt ceaſed my mourning, and compaſſed mee round a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bout with mirth.</p>
               <p>Thou haſt declared thy great magnificence in help<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing thy ſeruant.</p>
               <p>Thou haſt <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>ne mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uailouſly with me in my mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeries.</p>
               <p>Thou haſt regarded the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>ne of the poore: thou haſt not turned away thy face from me.</p>
               <p>I will bee ſinging and ſpeaking of thy mercies:
<pb facs="tcp:6059:170"/> and I will publiſh to other thy fidelitie and truth, ſo long as I ſhall liue.</p>
               <p>My mouth ſhall neuer ceaſe to ſpeake of thy righ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teouſnes, and of thy bene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fits: which be ſo many, that I cannot number them.</p>
               <p>But I will giue thee thankes till death take mee away, I will ſing in the praiſe of thée, ſo long as I ſhall continue.</p>
               <p>I will triumph and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ioyce in thy mercie, for thou
<pb facs="tcp:6059:171"/> haſt looked vpon my neceſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſities, and regarded my ſoule in diſtreſſe.</p>
               <p>Thou haſt béene my ſure refuge, and the ſtrength of my truſt and hope.</p>
               <p>I thanke thee Lorde of thy goodneſſe alway: and for thy excéeding mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cie.</p>
               <p>Thou haſt béen my com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>or<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>n the time of my trou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble, thou haſt been merciful vnto me, O Lord, and haſt reuenged the wronges that
<pb facs="tcp:6059:171"/> mine enemies haue done to me.</p>
               <p>According to the multi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tude of the heauie thoughts that I had in my minde, thy comforts haue cheared and lightned my heart.</p>
               <p>Thou haſt ſent me now ioyes, for the dayes where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in I was in ſorrowe, and for the yeares in which I ſuffered many a painefull ſtorme.</p>
               <p>Thou haſt called to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>membrance the rebuke that
<pb facs="tcp:6059:172"/> thy ſeruant hath beene put to, and how furiouſly mine enemies haue perſecuted me.</p>
               <p>O Lord God of hoſts, who may bee compared vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to thée? thou art great, and greatly to be praiſed.</p>
               <p>Thou art high vpon all <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> earth, thou art exalted fa<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> all gods.</p>
               <p>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>orie and honor is <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> thy face: holines, and magnificence is in thy Sanctuarie.</p>
               <pb facs="tcp:6059:172"/>
               <p>With iuſtice and iudge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment thy royall throne is eſtabliſhed, mercie and trueth goe before thy face.</p>
               <p>Bleſſed art thou, O Lord, which haſt not holden backe thy mercie from thy ſeruant.</p>
               <p>After that I had long looked for thée, O Lord <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> the laſt thou didſt attend vpon mee, and hearof <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>rye.</p>
               <p>Thou haſt taken me out of the Lake of miſerie, &amp; ſet
<pb facs="tcp:6059:173"/> my féete vpon a rocke, and made my ſteps ſure?</p>
               <p>Thou haſt giuen me my deſire, I haue ſéene thy ioy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full countenance.</p>
               <p>Thou haſt ſtriken all my aduerſaries, and haſt abated their ſtrength.</p>
               <p>Thou haſt rebuked the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ablement of them that vex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed me, and haſt plucked me forth of their hands.</p>
               <p>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>hou haſt caſt them h<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="5 letters">
                     <desc>•••••</desc>
                  </gap>ng into their owne <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap>, their féete bee wrapped
<pb facs="tcp:6059:173"/> in the net which they laide priuily for me.</p>
               <p>Mine enemies are re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>coyled backe, they are fallen downe and deſtroyed from thy ſight.</p>
               <p>Thou haſt been the poore mans defence, and his hel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per in tribulation, when moſt néede was.</p>
               <p>Thou haſt executed iudg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment for me: thou haſt de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fended my cauſe againſt mine accuſers.</p>
               <p>And although thou were
<pb facs="tcp:6059:174"/> very angry with mee a lit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tle, yet now I liue through thy mercie and goodnes.</p>
               <p>Verily I ſuppoſed with my ſelfe that I was cleane caſt out of thy fauour.</p>
               <p>But thou haſt heard my prayers and according to thy great mercie haſt taken me againe into thy <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="3 letters">
                     <desc>•••</desc>
                  </gap>our.</p>
               <p>O Lord of th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> owne <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap> haſt <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>rength <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap> when the<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap> from me, O Lord
<pb facs="tcp:6059:174"/> how greatly aſtonied was I?</p>
               <p>When I was in aduerſity, then I cried vnto thee, and thou didſt aunſwere me: When my ſoule was in great anguiſh and trouble then O Lord, I remembred thee.</p>
               <p>I haue taſted and ſéene how ſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>eet thou art: truly bleſſed i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>he ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> that truſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> in th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>rding to thy <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap> thy commen<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <pb facs="tcp:6059:175"/> and praiſe, but thy coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſailes touching vs, be with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out example, and greater then with wordes can bee expreſſe<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
               </p>
               <p>Dominion, power and glory he thine, for thou haſt made all things, and becauſe thy w<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ll is ſo, they doe ſtill <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ontin<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="3 letters">
                     <desc>•••</desc>
                  </gap>
               </p>
               <p>Thy name <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> bleſſed, p<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>iſed, and m<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>nified both <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap> wo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ld with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>men.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="prayer">
               <pb facs="tcp:6059:175"/>
               <head>A Pſalme of the benefites of God with thankes for the ſame.</head>
               <p>MY ſoule praiſeth thee, O Lord, and all that is within mee, praiſeth thy holy name.</p>
               <p>My ſoule giueth thee humble thankes, and thy benefites <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> will neuer for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>get.</p>
               <p>Wh<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> for <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap> ſinnes <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> heal<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="3 letters">
                     <desc>•••</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap> infirmties.</p>
               <pb facs="tcp:6059:176"/>
               <p>Which haſt ſaued my life from deſtruction, and ſhew<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed in me thy grace and mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cie.</p>
               <p>Which haſt ſatisfied my de<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>e with good things, and ſhall once reſtore my youth againe.</p>
               <p>Thou haſt intreated me mercifully at all times, and haſt reuenged me of my ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies.</p>
               <p>Thou ha<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>éen a defence to m<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> O Lord, and a ſure foundation of my wealth.</p>
               <pb facs="tcp:6059:176"/>
               <p>Thou haſt guided mee with thy counſaile, and ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken me vnto thee through thy mercie.</p>
               <p>Thou haſt many wayes declared in mee thy great might and power, and after thy anger hath béene paſt, thou haſt turned again, and comforted me.</p>
               <p>Thou haſt ſent me many grieuous troubles, but at the le<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>gth thou haſt brought mee out of the bottomes héepenes.</p>
               <pb facs="tcp:6059:177"/>
               <p>Thou haſt made me pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uie to thy wayes, &amp; haſt not hid thy counſails from me.</p>
               <p>Thou art full of mercy and grace O Lord, ſlow to wrath &amp; readie to goodnes.</p>
               <p>Thy diſpleaſure laſteth not alway, and thou kéepeſt not backe thy mercies in thine anger for euer.</p>
               <p>Thou rewardeſt vs not after our ſins, nor puniſheſt vs according <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> our deſerts.</p>
               <p>Looke how high the hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen is in compariſon of the
<pb facs="tcp:6059:177"/> earth, ſo great is thy mercy towarde vs.</p>
               <p>How far as the Eaſt is diſtant from the Weſt: ſo far, O Lord, remoue our ſinnes from vs.</p>
               <p>Like as a naturall father hath pitie vpon his chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren, euen ſo, O Lord God, thou haſt had compaſſion vpon vs.</p>
               <p>Thou haſt not forgotten thy creature, thou remem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>breſt that we are fleſh, yea all men liuing are vanitie.</p>
               <pb facs="tcp:6059:178"/>
               <p>And that the age of man is like vnto graſſe, and may be compared to the flowers of the field, which as ſoone as the ſharpe winde hath blowne vpon them with his blaſts, wither away, and die: ſo that no man can tell where thy did grow.</p>
               <p>But thy mercie O Lord, and louing kindnes is al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>waies vpon the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> that feare thée, and thy righteouſnes endureth for euer.</p>
               <p>So that we kéep our pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſe,
<pb facs="tcp:6059:178"/> and couenant with thée, and ſo remember thy commaundements that we doe them indeede.</p>
               <p>O Lord thou haſt ſtabli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhed thy throne in heauen, thou gouerneſt al things by thy imperiall power.</p>
               <p>I will magnifie thee, O Lord, and land thy name world without end. I will giue thankes alway, &amp; make thy name glorious for euer.</p>
               <p>O Lord thou art puiſſant and great, and thy magnifi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cence
<pb facs="tcp:6059:179"/> is vnſearchable.</p>
               <p>One generation ſhall ſhew to another thy works, and they ſhall declare thine ancient noble acts.</p>
               <p>They ſhall euer praiſe the magnificence of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> glory of thy holines, and the me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>morie of thy great goodnes. For thou art good <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>d gra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cious to al men, &amp; thy mercy excéedeth all thy workes.</p>
               <p>The e<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="3 letters">
                     <desc>•••</desc>
                  </gap> of all things be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>holde <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> fruite vpon thee, that thou ſhouldſt giue the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <pb facs="tcp:6059:179"/> their ſuſtenance in time con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uenient.</p>
               <p>Thou openeſt thy hand, and ſilleſt euery liuing crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture with food neceſſarie.</p>
               <p>O Lord thou art right<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full in all thy wayes, and holy in all thy deedes.</p>
               <p>Thou keepeſt all them that lo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> thée, and the tor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of malice ſhall not touch them.</p>
               <p>My mou<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>h ſhall ſprake thy glory and praiſe, and all liuing creatures ſhall honor
<pb facs="tcp:6059:180"/> thy holy name for euer.</p>
               <p>Praiſe our Lord, O yee his angels mighty in power which doe his commaunde<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments, and obey the voice of his word.</p>
               <p>Praiſe yee altogether God, O al ye hoſts, you his miniſters that due his will and pleaſure.</p>
               <p>Praiſe our Lord as I do, and let vs <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>gnifie his name together.</p>
               <p>Pr<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="3 letters">
                     <desc>•••</desc>
                  </gap> our Lord, O ye al his ſaints, for his name is
<pb facs="tcp:6059:180"/> glorious, and his praiſe a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>boue heauen and earth.</p>
               <p>Praiſe our Lord toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, O ye al his workes, e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uery thing that liueth, praiſe our Lord. Amen.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="prayer">
               <head>The complaint of a ſinner.</head>
               <p>MY God, my God, why haſt thou forſaken mee? it ſemeth that I ſhall not obtaine deliuerance, though I ſeeke it with loud cries.</p>
               <p>My God, I wil; cry all the day long, but thou wilt
<pb facs="tcp:6059:181"/> not anſwere, and all the night long, without taking any reſt.</p>
               <p>The meane time, thou moſt holieſt, ſéemeſt to ſit ſtill, not caring for y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> things that I ſuffer, which ſo oft hath helped mee heretofore, and haſt giuen to thy people Iſrael ſufficient arguments and matter to praiſe thée with ſonges wherewith they haue <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> thankes to thee for thy benefites.</p>
               <p>Our forefathers were
<pb facs="tcp:6059:181"/> wont to put their truſt in thée, and as often as they did ſo, thou diddeſt deliuer them.</p>
               <p>As oft as they cryed for helpe to thée, they were de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liuered, as oft as they com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitted themſelues to thée, they were not put to ſhame.</p>
               <p>But as for me<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>, I ſéeme rather to be a worme than a man, the dunghill of Adam, the outcaſt of the vulgar people.</p>
               <p>As many as haue ſéene me haue laughed me to ſcorne,
<pb facs="tcp:6059:182"/> and reuiled me, and ſhaking their heades in deriſion at mee, haue caſt mee in the téeth ſaying:</p>
               <p>He is wont to boaſt and glory that he is great in fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uour with God, wherefore let God now deliuer him, if he loue him ſo well.</p>
               <p>By thy procurement, O Lord, I came out of my mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers wombe and thou ga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ueſt me good comforte, euen when I ſucked my mothers breaſtes.</p>
               <pb facs="tcp:6059:182"/>
               <p>Through thy meanes I came into this world, and as ſoone as I was borne, I was left to thy tuition, yea thou waſt my God when I was yet in my mothers wombe. Wherefore go not far away fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> me: for danger is euen now at hand, &amp; I ſée no man that will help me.</p>
               <p>Many b<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>lles haue cloſed me in, both ſtrong and fat, they haue compaſſed mee round about.</p>
               <p>They haue opened their
<pb facs="tcp:6059:183"/> mouthes againſt mee, like vnto a lyon that gapeth vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on his praye, and roreth for hunger.</p>
               <p>I am poured out like wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, and al my limmes looſed one from another: and my heart is melted within mee as it were waxe.</p>
               <p>Al my ſtrength is gone &amp; dried vp like to a tileſtone, my tongue cleaueth to the roofe of my mouth: &amp; at the laſt, I ſhall be buried in the earth, as the dead be wont.</p>
               <pb facs="tcp:6059:183"/>
               <p>For dogges haue com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paſſed me round about, and the moſt wicked haue con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpired againſt me, they haue made hoales through my hands and my féete.</p>
               <p>I was ſo vngently in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>treated of the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, that I might eaſily number al my bones: and after all the paine and torment that they did to me with grieuous countena<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce, they ſtared &amp; looked vpo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> me.</p>
               <p>They deuided my clothes among them, and caſt
<pb facs="tcp:6059:184"/> lottes for my coate.</p>
               <p>Wherefore Lord I be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſéech thée, goe not far from me, but for as much as thou art my power and ſtrength, make haſt to helpe me.</p>
               <p>Deliuer my ſoule from danger of the ſworde, and kéepe my life deſtitute of all mans helpe, from the vio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lence of the dog.</p>
               <p>Saue me from the mouth of the L<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="3 letters">
                     <desc>•••</desc>
                  </gap> and take mee from the hornes of the Vni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cornes.</p>
               <pb facs="tcp:6059:184"/>
               <p>I will ſhew vnto my bre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thren the maieſtie of thy name, and when the people be moſt aſſembled together, I wil praiſe &amp; ſet foorth thy moſt worthy acts &amp; deedes.</p>
               <p>And all that worſhip our Lord, praiſe him, all the po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſterity of Iacob magnifie him, al ye that be of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſtocke of Iſrael with reuerence ſerue and honor him.</p>
               <p>For he hath not deſpiſed and ſet at naught the poore man, becauſe of his miſerie,
<pb facs="tcp:6059:185"/> neither hath he diſdaineful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly turned away his face from him; but rather as ſoone as the poore man cryed to him for helpe, hee heard him by and by.</p>
               <p>I will praiſe thée with ſongs openly in the multi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tude of thy people, and will performe my vowes in the ſight of the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> that honor thée.</p>
               <p>The po<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="3 letters">
                     <desc>•••</desc>
                  </gap> ſhall eate and be ſatiſfi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>hey ſhall praiſe our Lord that ſtudie to pleaſe, and as many of you
<pb facs="tcp:6059:185"/> as continue ſtill ſuch, your hearts ſhall liue.</p>
               <p>All the ends of the world ſhall conſider theſe things and be turned to our Lord, and all heathen nations ſhal ſubmit themſelues, and doe homage vnto thée.</p>
               <p>For our Lord hath a po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wer royall, and an imperial dominion ouer the heathen.</p>
               <p>The moſt mightie and greateſt of all them that dwell on the earth haue ea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten, and after that they haue
<pb facs="tcp:6059:186"/> taſted the ſpirituall giftes of our Lord, they haue ſubmit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted themſelues, and made humble ſuite vnto him: yea and all the dead which are buried in the earth, ſhall knéele and make reuerence in his honour, becauſe hee hath not diſdained to ſpend his owne life for them.</p>
               <p>They that ſhal come after vs, ſhall honor &amp; ſerue him.</p>
               <p>Theſe <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>hings ſhall bee written of our Lord: that our poſteritie may know
<pb facs="tcp:6059:186"/> and vnderſtand them.</p>
               <p>That they alſo may come and ſhew theſe things to the people that ſhall be borne of them, that our Lord hath done theſe things which be ſo marueilous.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="prayer">
               <head>A Pſalme of thankeſ-giuing.</head>
               <p>REioyce and ſing in the honor of God, all yee that liue on the earth.</p>
               <p>Worſhip and ſerue our Lord with gladnes, come vnto his ſight and preſence
<pb facs="tcp:6059:187"/> with ioy and mirth.</p>
               <p>Acknowledge you, and confeſſe that our Lord is that God which hath crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted and made vs: for truly we made not our ſelues, but we bee his people and his flocke, which he nouriſheth and féedeth continually.</p>
               <p>Go ye through his gates to giue him thankes for the innumerable benefits which ye haue receiued of him, and to ſing through his courtes his worthy acts and deedes,
<pb facs="tcp:6059:187"/> praiſe him, and highly com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mend his name.</p>
               <p>For our Lord is both good and gracious, and his mercy is infinite: he is moſt conſtant in kéeping of pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſes, not to one generati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on onely, but euen to all.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="prayer">
               <head>A Prayer for the night.</head>
               <p>
                  <hi>O</hi> Lord God and my heauenly father, for as much as by thy diuine ordinance, the night ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>procheth and darknes be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ginneth to ouerwhelme the
<pb facs="tcp:6059:188"/> earth, and time requireth that wee giue our ſelues to bodily reſt and quietnes: I render vnto thée moſt harty thanks for thy louing kind<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes, which haſt vouchſafed to preſerue me this day fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the danger of mine enemies to giue mee my health, to féede mee and to ſend mee al things neceſſarie for the comforte of this my poore and néedy l<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>fe, I moſt hum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bly beſéech thée for Ieſus Chriſts ſake, that thou wilt
<pb facs="tcp:6059:188"/> mercifully forgiue mee all y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> I haue this day committed againſt thy fatherly good<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes, either in word, déede, or thought, and that thou wilt vouchſafe, to ſhadowe mee this night vnder the com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fortable wings of thy al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mightie power, and defend mee from Sathan, and from all his crafty aſſaultes, that neither he nor any of his mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſters haue pe<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="3 letters">
                     <desc>•••</desc>
                  </gap> ouer ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther my body or my ſoule: but that although my body
<pb facs="tcp:6059:189"/> through thy benefit enioy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth ſweet and pleaſant ſléep, yet my ſoule may continual<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly watch vnto thée, thinke of thée, delight in thée, and euermore praiſe thée: that when the ioyful light of the day returneth according to thy godly appointment, I may riſe again with a faith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful ſoule, and vndefiled body and ſo afterward behaue my ſelfe all my life time, accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to thy bleſſed will and commaundement, by caſting
<pb facs="tcp:6059:189"/> away <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap> ſée<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap> there<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>rifie thée <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ther, which <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap> begotten Son, I <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap> our onely Sau<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap> ſwéete comforter, liue<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> raigneſt one true and eu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>laſting God, world with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out end. Amen.</p>
            </div>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
