<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>The shepheards holy-day A pastorall tragi-comædie. Acted before both their Maiesties at White-Hall, by the Queenes Servants. With an elegie on the death of the most noble lady, the Lady Venetia Digby. Written by J.R.</title>
            <author>J. R. (Joseph Rutter), fl. 1635-1640.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1635</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 171 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 56 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-04">2011-04 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A11205</idno>
            <idno type="STC">STC 21470</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC S116288</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99851505</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99851505</idno>
            <idno type="VID">16779</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A11205)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 16779)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 936:10)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>The shepheards holy-day A pastorall tragi-comædie. Acted before both their Maiesties at White-Hall, by the Queenes Servants. With an elegie on the death of the most noble lady, the Lady Venetia Digby. Written by J.R.</title>
                  <author>J. R. (Joseph Rutter), fl. 1635-1640.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[112] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed by N[icholas] and I[ohn] Okes, for Iohn Benson, and are to be sold at his shop in St. Dunstans Church-yard in Fleetstreet,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1635.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Dedication signed: Jos. Rutter.</note>
                  <note>In verse.</note>
                  <note>Signatures: A⁴ B-G H⁴.</note>
                  <note>The last leaf is blank.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the Henry E. Huntington Library and Art Gallery.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2009-05</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-06</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-07</date>
            <label>Zev Berger</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-07</date>
            <label>Zev Berger</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-09</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:16779:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:16779:1"/>
            <p>THE SHEPHEARDS HOLY-DAY. A PASTORALL TRAGI-COMAEDIE. ACTED BEFORE BOTH THEIR MAIESTIES AT WHITE-HALL, by the Queenes Servants. <hi>WITH</hi> AN ELEGIE ON THE DEATH of the moſt noble Lady, the Lady VENETIA DIGBY.</p>
            <p>
               <q>
                  <bibl>
                     <hi>VIR.</hi>
                  </bibl>
Nec erubuit Sylvas habitare Thalia.</q> 
               <hi>WRITTEN BY</hi> J. R.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON:</hi> Printed by <hi>N.</hi> and <hi>I. Okes,</hi> for <hi>Iohn Benſon,</hi> and are to be ſold at his ſhop in St. <hi>Dunſtans</hi> Church-yard in <hi>Fleetſtreet.</hi> 1635.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="dedication">
            <pb facs="tcp:16779:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:16779:2" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <head>TO THE TRVELY NOBLE Sir KENELME DIGBY, K<hi rend="sup">t</hi>.</head>
            <opener>
               <salute>SIR,</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg>T is ſayd, that all things naturally affect their place of birth. Fire fain'd to be ſtolne from Heauen, of its owne Nature tends upwards. The Soule of Man deſires to be united with the Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vine Eſſence from whence it is derived. Tis then but reaſon that theſe Poems ſhould of themſelves returne to you, by whoſe influence they were con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceived; Both of them being borne in your houſe: The one whilſt I admir'd the ſerenity, and ſweetneſſe of your diſpoſition: the other when I kept time with your greife, which you tooke for the loſſe of that noble Lady, your deare wife: So that now I doubt whether I may call my ſelfe the Author, or you. At leaſt, if this be my worke, I am yours: And
<pb facs="tcp:16779:3"/>
could my capacity have reacht thoſe Heroique vertues, which in the time of my attendance I be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>held in you, I might perhaps have dar'd a higher flight, and from the hu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ble ſtraine of ſhepheards, have growne up to you, as you are, the ſubiect of all morall vertues: I ſhouldh ha' then deſcrib'd your <hi>valour, Induſtry,</hi> and <hi>Prudence</hi> in your actions at ſea, your <hi>Bounty</hi> ſtill exerciſed in the right place, your <hi>Piety</hi> in the memory of your deceaſed Lady, of whom, (be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſides the Monument you have erected to her,) the ſtatues and pictures you have, and what ever elſe might render her, teſtifie what a value you ſet on the originall. <hi>Vxorem enim vivam amare voluptas eſt, defunctam religio.</hi> But theſe aymes are too high for me, yet may you ſomewhat raiſe my thoughts, if you deſcend to keepe theſe in your eſteeme, and with them,</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>Your true ſervant, JOS. RVTTER.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="encomium">
            <pb facs="tcp:16779:3"/>
            <head>To my deare Sonne, and right-learned Friend, Maſter <hi>JOSEPH RVTTER.</hi>
            </head>
            <l>YOu looke, my <hi>Joſeph,</hi> I ſhould ſomething ſay</l>
            <l>Unto the <hi>world,</hi> in praiſe of your <hi>firſt Play:</hi>
            </l>
            <l>And truely, ſo I would, could I be heard.</l>
            <l>You know, I never was of <hi>Truth</hi> a feard,</l>
            <l>And leſſe aſham'd; not when I told the crowd</l>
            <l>How well I lov'd <hi>Truth:</hi> I was ſcarce allow'd</l>
            <l>By thoſe deepe-grounded, underſtanding men,</l>
            <l>That ſit to cenſure <hi>Playes,</hi> yet know not when,</l>
            <l>Or why to like; they found, it all was new,</l>
            <l>And newer, then could pleaſe them, by-cauſe trew.</l>
            <l>Such men I met withall, and ſo have you.</l>
            <l>Now, for mine owne part, and it is but due,</l>
            <l>(You haue deſerv'd it from me) I have read,</l>
            <l>And weigh'd your <hi>Play:</hi> untwiſted ev'ry thread,</l>
            <l>And know the woofe, and warpe thereof; can tell</l>
            <l>Where it runs round, and even: where ſo well,</l>
            <l>So ſoft, and ſmooth it handles, the whole piece,</l>
            <l>As it were ſpun by nature, off the fleece:</l>
            <l>This is my cenſure. Now there is a new</l>
            <l>Office of Wit, a Mint, and (this is true)</l>
            <l>Cry'd up of late: Whereto there muſt be firſt</l>
            <l>A <hi>Maſter-worker</hi> call'd, th'old ſtanderd burſt</l>
            <l>Of wit, and a new made: a <hi>Warden</hi> then,</l>
            <l>And a <hi>Comptroller,</hi> two moſt rigid men</l>
            <l>For order, and for governing the pixe,</l>
            <l>A <hi>Say-maſter,</hi> hath ſtudied all the tricks</l>
            <l>
               <pb facs="tcp:16779:4"/>Of <hi>Fineneſſe,</hi> and <hi>alloy:</hi> follow his hint,</l>
            <l>Yo' have all the <hi>Myſteries</hi> of <hi>Wits new Mint,</hi>
            </l>
            <l>The <hi>valuations, mixtunes,</hi> and the ſame</l>
            <l>Concluded from a <hi>Carract</hi> to a <hi>dramme.</hi>
            </l>
            <closer>
               <signed>Ben. Ionſon.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="encomium">
            <head>To my much reſpected Friend, Maſter <hi>Ioſeph Rutter<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
               </hi> upon his Paſtorall.</head>
            <l>WHy ſhould I vainely ſtrive to vindicate</l>
            <l>Thy fame, or feare thy well-writ Poems fate?</l>
            <l>Why ſhould I wrong the age, to thinke a ſtraine</l>
            <l>So clearely ſweete, ſo elegantly plaine,</l>
            <l>Should be miſtaken? that a Reader, though</l>
            <l>Not of the beſt, who judge becauſe they know,</l>
            <l>But of the venturing ranke, ſhould therefore ceaſe</l>
            <l>To praiſe, becauſe he underſtands with eaſe?</l>
            <l>Becauſe he is not puzled, but may finde</l>
            <l>A quicke delight, ſuch as ſhould moove the minde</l>
            <l>In Playes or Paſtoralls, whoſe gentle ſtraines.</l>
            <l>Should not perplexe, but recreate the braines?</l>
            <l>Can unjuſt ignorance offer ſo much</l>
            <l>Wrong to it ſelfe? yet I have heard that ſuch,</l>
            <l>For whom no language can be plaine enough,</l>
            <l>Praiſe nought but intricate and clouded ſtuffe,</l>
            <l>As if that conſcious to their owne weake ſence,</l>
            <l>Becauſe they know not perfect Eloquence,</l>
            <l>And yet would ſeeme; they thinke that beſt muſt be,</l>
            <l>That's fartheſt off from their capacity.</l>
            <l>Let ſuch, if ſuch there be, have their deſire;</l>
            <l>And, though nor pleas'd, nor profited, admire.</l>
            <l>I wiſh who ere ſhall read thy ſweeteſt ſtraine,</l>
            <l>May love the Authours skill that made it plaine,</l>
            <l>And ſo be juſt both to himſelfe, and thee:</l>
            <l>But I'le no more anticipate, nor be</l>
            <l>Tedious in cenſure; to that Worthy's breaſt,</l>
            <l>To whom thou ſend'ſt thy Booke, I leave the reſt.</l>
            <closer>
               <signed>Thomas May.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="play">
            <div type="prologue">
               <pb facs="tcp:16779:4"/>
               <l>TO this faire <hi>Company</hi> I am to ſay,</l>
               <l>You're Welcome all, to a well meaning play,</l>
               <l>For ſuch our Author made it, with intent</l>
               <l>To defame none. <hi>His</hi> Muſe is innocent,</l>
               <l>A Virgin yet, that has not found the wayes</l>
               <l>Out of foule crimes to raiſe her ſelfe a prayſe;</l>
               <l>And therefore <hi>She</hi> deſires, you would excuſe</l>
               <l>All bitter ſtraines, that ſuite a Satyr Muſe:</l>
               <l>And that which ſo much takes the Vulgar Eare,</l>
               <l>Looſenes of ſpeech, which they for jeſts do heare;</l>
               <l>She hopes none ſuch are here, therfore ſhe dares</l>
               <l>Venter this ſtory, purg'd from lighter ayres:</l>
               <l>A piece intire, without or patch, or maime,</l>
               <l>Round in it ſelfe, and euery where the ſame.</l>
               <l>And if there be not in't, what they call wit,</l>
               <l>There might haue bin, had it bin thought ſo fit.</l>
               <l>A Shepheards Muſe gently of loue does ſing,</l>
               <l>And with it mingles no impurer thing.</l>
               <l>Such ſhe preſents vnto your eares, and eyes,</l>
               <l>And yet your Chriſtian freedome not denies</l>
               <l>Of liking, or diſliking what you will,</l>
               <l>You may ſay this is well, or that is ill,</l>
               <l>Without diſpute; for why ſhould you that pay</l>
               <l>For what you haue, be taught what you ſhould ſay,</l>
               <l>Or made to judge by any ſquare, or rule,</l>
               <l>As if you came not to a Stage, but Schoole?</l>
               <l>
                  <pb facs="tcp:16779:5"/>No, he that made it, ſayes, if you will eate,</l>
               <l>He will not force your ſtomackes, there's your meat,</l>
               <l>Which if you like tis well, if not, all's one,</l>
               <l>There muſt be difference in opinion:</l>
               <l>Beſides, he's ſure what ever hee could wiſh,</l>
               <l>Your taſte, and not his Art muſt praiſe the diſh.</l>
            </div>
            <div type="dramatis_personae">
               <head>The Perſons of the Play.</head>
               <list>
                  <item>Thyrſis, <hi>the Lover of</hi> Sylvia.</item>
                  <item>Hylas, <hi>the Lover of</hi> Nerina.</item>
                  <item>Mirtillus, <hi>the common Lover.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>Daphnis, <hi>the rich Shepheard.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>Montanus, <hi>an ancient Shepheard.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>Charinus, <hi>Father to</hi> Nerina.</item>
                  <item>Alcon, <hi>an ancient Shepheard.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>Nuntius.</item>
               </list>
               <list>
                  <head>Chorus of <hi>Shepheards.</hi>
                  </head>
                  <item>Sylvia, <hi>belov'd of</hi> Thyrſis.</item>
                  <item>Nerina, <hi>a huntreſſe, belov'd of</hi> Hylas <hi>&amp; of</hi> Daphnis</item>
                  <item>Dorinda, <hi>enamored of</hi> Daphnis.</item>
                  <item>Delia, <hi>a Court Lady.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>Euarchus, <hi>King of</hi> Arcady.</item>
                  <item>Eubulus, <hi>his Counſellor.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>Cleander, <hi>Sonne to</hi> Eubulus.</item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Attendants.</hi>
                  </item>
               </list>
               <p>
                  <hi>The Scene</hi> Arcady.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="body_of_play">
               <pb facs="tcp:16779:5"/>
               <head>THE SHEPHEARDS HOLY-DAY.</head>
               <div n="1" type="act">
                  <head>ACTVS. 1.</head>
                  <div n="1" type="scene">
                     <head>SCENA 1.</head>
                     <stage>Thyrſis, Montanus.</stage>
                     <lg>
                        <l>HEre in this Grove I left her, here amongſt</l>
                        <l>Theſe Poplars, Laurells, and theſe Sycamors,</l>
                        <l>Guilty of her ſad loſſe: And yet behold</l>
                        <l>They doe appeare as freſh and full of verdure,</l>
                        <l>As when my Love cloth'd in her cleareſt lookes,</l>
                        <l>Did give them grace and luſtre: Why do we</l>
                        <l>Poore ſilly men bred up in cares, and feare,</l>
                        <l>The Nurſe of our Religion, ſtoope to Nature,</l>
                        <l>That onely knowes to forme, not to preſerve</l>
                        <l>What ſhe has made, ſince careleſſe of her worke,</l>
                        <l>She leaves to giddy Fortune the whole power</l>
                        <l>Of ruling us: Theſe ſenſeleſſe Trees ſtand ſtill,</l>
                        <l>And flouriſh too, and in their pride upbraide</l>
                        <l>My loſſe to me; but my deare <hi>Sylvia</hi> being</l>
                        <l>
                           <hi>Natures</hi> beſt peece, made to excuſe the reſt</l>
                        <l>Of all her vulgar formes, ay me! was left</l>
                        <l>To deſolation, till ſome horrid Satyr</l>
                        <l>Bred in theſe Woods, and furious in his luſts</l>
                        <l>
                           <pb facs="tcp:16779:6"/>Made her his prey, and now has carried her</l>
                        <l>Into his darke retirings, or ſome Cave</l>
                        <l>Where her poore <hi>Thyrſis</hi> never more ſhall ſee her.</l>
                     </lg>
                     <lg>
                        <l>But I will be reveng'd, this Wood that now</l>
                        <l>Is ſo bedeckt with leaves and freſh array,</l>
                        <l>Ile levell with the ground, untill it be</l>
                        <l>As deſolate as I.</l>
                     </lg>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Mon.</speaker>
                        <p>Alas poore ſhepheard!</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Thy.</speaker>
                        <l>It ſhall affoord no ſhade to any thing</l>
                        <l>That hither us'd to come for its releife;</l>
                        <l>But henceforth be for ever infamous:</l>
                        <l>That when ſome gentle ſhepheard paſſes by,</l>
                        <l>And ſees this ground rent with the crooked plough,</l>
                        <l>Here, he may ſay, here 'twas that <hi>Sylvia</hi>
                        </l>
                        <l>Was loſt, and then ſhall turne another way.</l>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Mon.</speaker>
                        <l>Good <hi>Thyrſis,</hi> do not make ſo much of griefe,</l>
                        <l>Y'have fed it with too many teares already,</l>
                        <l>Take comfort now.</l>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Thy.</speaker>
                        <l>What has my preſent ſtate</l>
                        <l>To doe with comfort? if you ſee the trees</l>
                        <l>Widdow'd of leaves, the earth growne hard, and ſpoild</l>
                        <l>Of the greene mantles which ſhe wont to weare,</l>
                        <l>You wonder not if winter then appeare.</l>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Mon.</speaker>
                        <p>By theſe we know that ſeaſon.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Thy.</speaker>
                        <l>And muſt I,</l>
                        <l>When ſhe is gone, whoſe Sun-like eyes did cheriſh</l>
                        <l>An everlaſting Summer in my life,</l>
                        <l>Feele any ſpring of joy to comfort me?</l>
                        <l>
                           <pb facs="tcp:16779:6"/>No father, griefe with me is beſt in ſeaſon.</l>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Mon.</speaker>
                        <p>But whilſt you mourne thus, who looks to your flock?</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Thy.</speaker>
                        <l>All as the ſhepheard is, ſuch be his flocks,</l>
                        <l>So pine and languiſh, they, as in deſpaire</l>
                        <l>He pines and languiſhes, their fleecy locks</l>
                        <l>Let hang diſorder'd, as their Maſters haire,</l>
                        <l>Since ſhe is gone that deskt both him, and them.</l>
                        <l>And now what beauty can there be to live</l>
                        <l>When ſhe is loſt that did all beauty give?</l>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Mon.</speaker>
                        <l>But yet, mee thinks, for one that is a ſtranger,</l>
                        <l>Scarce knowne to any here, but by her name,</l>
                        <l>Theſe plaints are overmuch: beſides there are</l>
                        <l>In fruitfull <hi>Arcady</hi> as faire as ſhe,</l>
                        <l>I'me ſure more rich and wiſe, make out of them</l>
                        <l>A choiſe. <hi>Nerina</hi> is as faire as ſhe,</l>
                        <l>
                           <hi>Dorinda's</hi> flocks are more then <hi>Silvia's,</hi>
                        </l>
                        <l>And carry on their backs more wooll then hers.</l>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Thy.</speaker>
                        <l>Let ſuch baſe Peſants, as the Gods, do hate,</l>
                        <l>Admire their wealth, and them, for what they have,</l>
                        <l>Their bodies, and their ſoules materiall</l>
                        <l>Alike, of droſſie ſubſtance are compounded,</l>
                        <l>And can contemplate nothing but the earth.</l>
                        <l>No, <hi>Silvia,</hi> whom ſome better God (perhaps</l>
                        <l>For the reward of my well tuned pipe)</l>
                        <l>Sent downe to me made up of ayre, and fire,</l>
                        <l>Though ſince, becauſe I knew not how to uſe</l>
                        <l>With faire reſpect a gift ſo great as ſhe,</l>
                        <l>Has juſtly reft her from me, is ſo much,</l>
                        <l>
                           <pb facs="tcp:16779:7"/>So great a part of me, that in her abſence,</l>
                        <l>Amidſt my griefe I feele ſome little joy,</l>
                        <l>To ſee how much of me each minute waſteth,</l>
                        <l>And gives me hope that when I ſhall diſſolve</l>
                        <l>This earthly ſubſtance, and be pure as ſhe</l>
                        <l>(For ſure the Gods have taken her undefil'd)</l>
                        <l>I may injoy her lookes, and though it be</l>
                        <l>Prophane to touch a hallowed thing like her,</l>
                        <l>I may adore her yet, and recompence</l>
                        <l>With my religion the proud thoughts I had</l>
                        <l>once to injoy her.</l>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Mo.</speaker>
                        <l>See how fond you are</l>
                        <l>T'embrace a ſhadow, and to leave the ſubſtance.</l>
                        <l>The love of <hi>Hylas</hi> to <hi>Nerina</hi> has</l>
                        <l>More hopes then yours; though ſhe be yong and coy</l>
                        <l>Yet whilſt <hi>Nerina</hi> is, and <hi>Hylas</hi> too,</l>
                        <l>One time or other, they may both haue joy</l>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Thy.</speaker>
                        <l>May they prove happy in each others love,</l>
                        <l>And nothing pleaſe, but what each other do,</l>
                        <l>For ſo liv'd <hi>Thirſis</hi> and his <hi>Silvia,</hi>
                        </l>
                        <l>Whilſt <hi>Silvia</hi> was, and <hi>Thirſis</hi> was her loue,</l>
                        <l>What ever <hi>Thirſis</hi> pip'd pleaſd <hi>Silvia,</hi>
                        </l>
                        <l>
                           <hi>Thirſis</hi> admird what ever <hi>Sylvia</hi> ſung</l>
                        <l>And both their joyes were equall, or but one,</l>
                        <l>Well I can now remember (and it is</l>
                        <l>Some comfort to remember what I moane)</l>
                        <l>That when our loves began, how firſt I gaz'd</l>
                        <l>On her,, and ſhe was pleaſd that I ſhould looke</l>
                        <l>
                           <pb facs="tcp:16779:7"/>Till greedily I had devour'd the hooke.</l>
                        <l>Love gave me courage then to ſpeake my thoughts,</l>
                        <l>And gave her pitty to receive my words,</l>
                        <l>They linkt our hearts together: from that time</l>
                        <l>When ere ſhe ſaw me ſtrike the furious Boare,</l>
                        <l>(Though then my caſe ſhe ru'd, and ſigh'd full oft)</l>
                        <l>Yet was ſhe pleas'd to ſee my victory,</l>
                        <l>And I receiv'd my vigour from her eye.</l>
                        <l>Then would ſhe make me Chaplets of the beſt</l>
                        <l>And choiceſt flowers to adorne my head:</l>
                        <l>Which when I wore, methought I then did graſpe</l>
                        <l>The Empire of the world; but what of that?</l>
                        <l>The more I then enjoy'd of heavenly bliſſe,</l>
                        <l>The more my preſent griefe and paſſion is.</l>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Mon.</speaker>
                        <l>Well <hi>Thyrſis,</hi> ſince my words doe but renew</l>
                        <l>The ſtory of your griefe, I'le leave to uſe</l>
                        <l>Perſwaſions to you; for 'tis time I ſee,</l>
                        <l>And not my words, muſt cure your maladie</l>
                     </sp>
                     <stage>Exit.</stage>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Thy.</speaker>
                        <l>That time muſt put a period to my life,</l>
                        <l>Or elſe it never will unto my griefe:</l>
                        <l>Come Boy, and under this ſame hanging bow,</l>
                        <l>The note which thou attemperſt to my words,</l>
                        <l>Sing, and be happier then thy Maſter, Boy.</l>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Boy.</speaker>
                        <lg type="song">
                           <lg n="1">
                              <head>1.</head>
                              <l>SHall I becauſe my Love is gon,</l>
                              <l>Accuſe thoſe golden darts</l>
                              <l>
                                 <pb facs="tcp:16779:8"/>Which to a bleſſed union</l>
                              <l>Strooke our two loving hearts,</l>
                              <l>Since Fortune, and not Love hath caus'd my moane?</l>
                           </lg>
                           <lg n="2">
                              <head>2.</head>
                              <l>No, her pure Image I ſhall prize,</l>
                              <l>Imprinted in my breſt,</l>
                              <l>More then the faireſt Miſtreſſe eyes</l>
                              <l>That ever Swaine poſſeſt,</l>
                              <l>Which in eternall bonds my fancie tyes.</l>
                           </lg>
                           <lg n="3">
                              <head>3.</head>
                              <l>Come then you ſharpeſt griefes, and try</l>
                              <l>If you can pierce my heart,</l>
                              <l>But uſe, if you would have me dye,</l>
                              <l>The beſt you can of Art,</l>
                              <l>To wound a breaſt ſo arm'd with conſtancy.</l>
                           </lg>
                        </lg>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Thy.</speaker>
                        <l>Enough: I'le ſigh the reſt out: Goe my boy,</l>
                        <l>Be carefull of thy tender Lambes, whilſt I</l>
                        <l>Seeke out ſome hidden place to pine and dye.</l>
                     </sp>
                  </div>
                  <div n="2" type="scene">
                     <head>SCENA SECUNDA.</head>
                     <stage>Hylas, Mirtillus.</stage>
                     <l>BEleeve <hi>Mirtillus,</hi> never any love</l>
                     <l>Was bought with other price then love alone,</l>
                     <l>Since nothing is more precious then it ſelfe.</l>
                     <l>It being the pureſt abſtract of that fire,</l>
                     <l>Which wiſe <hi>Prometheus</hi> firſt indu'd us with;</l>
                     <l>
                        <pb facs="tcp:16779:8"/>And he muſt love that would be lov'd againe.</l>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Mi.</speaker>
                        <l>Why? who can ſay <hi>Mirtillus</hi> does not love,</l>
                        <l>
                           <hi>Mirtillus,</hi> he who has imploy'd his youth</l>
                        <l>Ever in ſervice of the faireſt Nymphs.</l>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Hy.</speaker>
                        <p>
                           <hi>Mirtillus</hi> cannot love.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Mi.</speaker>
                        <l>No, gentle <hi>Hylas?</hi>
                        </l>
                        <l>This Ribband, and this haire you ſee me weare</l>
                        <l>Are they not enſignes of a lover? ſay</l>
                        <l>What ſhepheardeſſe whom ever Swaine thought faire,</l>
                        <l>Has not <hi>Mirtillus</hi> courted, and obtaind</l>
                        <l>Some favour from? but you will thinke becauſe</l>
                        <l>I do not fold my armes, and ſigh, and ſpend</l>
                        <l>The dayes the Gods have given me to rejoice,</l>
                        <l>In whining paſſion, walking ſtill alone,</l>
                        <l>Now proud with hopes, then caſt downe with deſpaire,</l>
                        <l>Unequall to my ſelfe in every thing,</l>
                        <l>I cannot love. No, <hi>Hylas,</hi> know I love</l>
                        <l>
                           <hi>Dorinda, Cloris, Amarillis,</hi> all</l>
                        <l>Whom ever love did to his Altars call:</l>
                        <l>And when this Miſtreſſe frownes, I am content</l>
                        <l>To take another, when that flame is ſpent</l>
                        <l>By time, or put out by a Rivall, ſtraite</l>
                        <l>A third ſupplies her place, perhaps more worthy,</l>
                        <l>If leſſe, becauſe ſhe loves, Ile thinke her ſo.</l>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Hy.</speaker>
                        <l>Alas, <hi>Mirtillus,</hi> I doe pitty thee,</l>
                        <l>Pittie the error which thou wandreſt in,</l>
                        <l>That thinkſt thou lov'ſt, and know'ſt not what it is,</l>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Mi.</speaker>
                        <p>Why what is love ſay you, if mine be not?</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <pb facs="tcp:16779:9"/>
                        <speaker>Hy.</speaker>
                        <l>I know <hi>Mirtillus,</hi> that no lover yet</l>
                        <l>Purchaſ'd a laſting pleaſure without griefe;</l>
                        <l>For love has gall in it, as well as honie,</l>
                        <l>And ſo compounded, that who ſo ere will taſte</l>
                        <l>The ſweetes of it, muſt take the bitter too,</l>
                        <l>Out of both which is made our conſtancy,</l>
                        <l>You that embrace the falſe delights alone,</l>
                        <l>Are a faign'd lover, or more truly none.</l>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Mi.</speaker>
                        <l>I know not what you meane by conſtancy,</l>
                        <l>I'me ſure I loue the faireſt.</l>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Hy.</speaker>
                        <l>Still you erre,</l>
                        <l>For if you lov'd the faireſt, none had bin</l>
                        <l>The object of your choiſe but my <hi>Nerina,</hi>
                        </l>
                        <l>
                           <hi>Nerina,</hi> ſhe the glory of theſe woods</l>
                        <l>The only ſubject of all ſhepheards ſong.</l>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Mi.</speaker>
                        <l>She has her ſhare of beautie with the reſt,</l>
                        <l>And I confeſſe ſhe's fit for love as any;</l>
                        <l>But why ſhe onely ſhould take up your breaſt,</l>
                        <l>And ſhut out all that have a right as good,</l>
                        <l>Whoſe equall, or tranſcendent beautie pleades</l>
                        <l>As juſt a title to't, as hers can do,</l>
                        <l>I cannot reach the reaſon, but admire</l>
                        <l>Your faith, and what you praiſe, your conſtancie.</l>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Hy.</speaker>
                        <l>
                           <hi>Mirtillus,</hi> though I know your ſtubborn heart</l>
                        <l>Could never entertaine a lovers thought,</l>
                        <l>Yet did I thinke you would have bin more tender</l>
                        <l>How you prophan'd a name ſo ſacred as</l>
                        <l>
                           <hi>Nerina's</hi> is, whom never any Swaine</l>
                        <l>
                           <pb facs="tcp:16779:9"/>Nor rurall God, nor Satyr, though he be</l>
                        <l>Of ſavage kinde would ever violate;</l>
                        <l>
                           <hi>Nerina</hi> in whoſe forme love ever dwells</l>
                        <l>Attended by the Graces, which do range</l>
                        <l>Themſelves in order 'bout her comely face,</l>
                        <l>Whoſe breaſts without are hills of whiteſt ſnow,</l>
                        <l>Within the ſeate of blameleſſe modeſtie,</l>
                        <l>Regard of honor, and pure chaſtity</l>
                        <l>Nor may a looſe thought ever harbor there</l>
                        <l>To tempt ſuch lovers as you ſeeme to be.</l>
                        <l>Is it for that you ſlight her?</l>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Mi.</speaker>
                        <l>No, I loue her</l>
                        <l>As I do others, with whom I compare her.</l>
                        <l>But you that loue with ſuch intemperance,</l>
                        <l>Make of your love a glaſſe, wherein you ſee</l>
                        <l>Each thing much greater then indeed it is:</l>
                        <l>My loves too cold you ſay, but I am ſure</l>
                        <l>Yours is too hot for any to endure:</l>
                        <l>A meane perhaps 'twixt theſe I might approve</l>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Hy.</speaker>
                        <p>You might, if there were any meane in love.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Mi.</speaker>
                        <l>But whilſt we talke thus, ſee, the flame has caught you,</l>
                        <l>your beauteous flame <hi>Nerina</hi> is at hand</l>
                        <l>
                           <hi>Dorinda</hi> with her, dare you ſtay th'encounter.</l>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Hy.</speaker>
                        <p>No let's with draw, and watch her where ſhe gos.</p>
                     </sp>
                  </div>
                  <div n="3" type="scene">
                     <head>SCENA III.</head>
                     <stage>Merina, Dorinda.</stage>
                     <l>
                        <hi>DOrinda,</hi> I have miſt the chaſe to day,</l>
                     <l>Such is my chance, and he that lodg'd the deere,</l>
                     <l>
                        <pb facs="tcp:16779:10"/>Told me it was the faireſt in theſe Woods.</l>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Do.</speaker>
                        <l>The Gods doe love you ſure, that have left</l>
                        <l>Your thoughts ſo free for ſport; mine are not ſo.</l>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Ne.</speaker>
                        <p>Thou art in love, I warrant, art thou not?</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Do.</speaker>
                        <l>That angry God purſues me in his fury,</l>
                        <l>And forces me to love where I am ſcorn'd.</l>
                        <l>Hapleſſe <hi>Dorinda,</hi> why ſhould he deſpiſe thee?</l>
                        <l>Many a Swaine, and many a rurall God</l>
                        <l>Have ſought thy favors, and have ſought in vaine,</l>
                        <l>Now thou art juſtly puniſht with diſdaine.</l>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Ne.</speaker>
                        <l>Truſt me Sweet-heart, I cannot chooſe but wonder,</l>
                        <l>To thinke that one of ſuch a comely grace</l>
                        <l>(I doe not flatter you) could ſue to any</l>
                        <l>For love, who are much fitter to be lov'd:</l>
                        <l>Scorne him aſmuch as he does thee, for men</l>
                        <l>Love us no more, when we love them agen.</l>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Do.</speaker>
                        <l>Ah good <hi>Nerina,</hi> you have ſpoken truth:</l>
                        <l>It may warne other Nymphs by my example</l>
                        <l>How they profeſſe their loves to any man:</l>
                        <l>I'me paſt the cure, he that wounded me,</l>
                        <l>Has left me quite diſarm'd, and robb'd me of</l>
                        <l>All thoſe defenſive arts which men will ſay</l>
                        <l>Are naturall and proper to our ſexe:</l>
                        <l>I cannot change a face, or weepe one teare,</l>
                        <l>Or laugh againſt my will, ſo violently</l>
                        <l>My Fate hath thruſt me to this love, that all</l>
                        <l>My faculties confeſſe their weakneſſe, and</l>
                        <l>My flame is got ſo much above my reach,</l>
                        <l>
                           <pb facs="tcp:16779:10"/>
                           <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                              <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                           </gap> can not put it out, nor ſmother it.</l>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Me.</speaker>
                        <l>Alas poore wench, tell me who is the man</l>
                        <l>Made up of ſo much rigid cruelty,</l>
                        <l>That I may ſhun him whereſoere I goe.</l>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Do.</speaker>
                        <p>Do not you know him?</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Me.</speaker>
                        <p>No.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Do.</speaker>
                        <l>I heare he boaſts</l>
                        <l>To every ſhepheard, and to every Nymph,</l>
                        <l>How much I love him.</l>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Me.</speaker>
                        <p>Then it muſt be <hi>Daphnis.</hi>
                        </p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Do.</speaker>
                        <l>
                           <hi>Venus</hi> forgive me, if I do diſcloſe him,</l>
                        <l>But he will do't himſelfe: Tis he <hi>Nerina.</hi>
                        </l>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Me.</speaker>
                        <l>
                           <hi>Daphnis,</hi> that woes my father to win me,</l>
                        <l>He is my daily ſuitor, now I know</l>
                        <l>How much he owes to pitty, and to thee:</l>
                        <l>Untill he pay that debt, I ſhall deſpiſe him.</l>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Do.</speaker>
                        <p>Why, do not you love him as much as I?</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Me.</speaker>
                        <l>Love him? I know no greater miſery,</l>
                        <l>Then to love one that's not of humane race,</l>
                        <l>A Tyger rather, but a Tyger is</l>
                        <l>More milde then he.</l>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Do.</speaker>
                        <l>For loves ſake ſay not ſo.</l>
                        <l>He has a manly feature, and does ſhew</l>
                        <l>As much of grace in his comportment, as</l>
                        <l>The beſt of ſhepheards can him <hi>Titan</hi> made</l>
                        <l>Of better clay, then he did other men:</l>
                        <l>Although his heart be flint, and hardeſt rocke.</l>
                        <l>Yet is his heart ſo hard, or are my parts</l>
                        <l>
                           <pb facs="tcp:16779:11"/>Rather unequall to his high deſerts?</l>
                        <l>For he can love I ſee, ſince you he loves,</l>
                        <l>And you deſerve it: had he thought me worthy,</l>
                        <l>He would have lov'd me too; but as I am</l>
                        <l>Worthleſſe <hi>Dorinda,</hi> I am made his ſcorne,</l>
                        <l>And I had rather be ſo, then <hi>Nerina</hi>
                        </l>
                        <l>Should want a ſervant ſuch as <hi>Daphnis</hi> is.</l>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Me,</speaker>
                        <l>Prethee no more of him, I hate his name</l>
                        <l>As much, as I would do the loſſe of honor,</l>
                        <l>Which he injuriouſly would rob me off,</l>
                        <l>No, no, <hi>Dorinda,</hi> if by love I be</l>
                        <l>In<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap>hrald to any, <hi>Daphnis</hi> is not he.</l>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Do.</speaker>
                        <p>Why, is there any can deſerve you more?</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Me.</speaker>
                        <l>Yes many, that I could tell how to love</l>
                        <l>Rather then him: for why ſhould I love him</l>
                        <l>Whilſt <hi>Hylas</hi> lives and languiſhes for me?</l>
                        <l>
                           <hi>Hylas</hi> who lov'd me in my infancy,</l>
                        <l>And being then a boy was never well</l>
                        <l>If I was abſent, nor indeed was I</l>
                        <l>Content with any but his company.</l>
                        <l>Our flocks ſtill fed together, I on him,</l>
                        <l>And he on me did feed his greedie eyes.</l>
                        <l>Since though his yeares have ſtild him man, he has</l>
                        <l>Continu'd that firſt love with ſuch reſpects,</l>
                        <l>So full of innocence and ſimple truth,</l>
                        <l>That howſoere my outward coyneſſe is,</l>
                        <l>My heart within tells me, 'tis onely his:</l>
                        <l>Ay me! my father! prithee let's away.</l>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <pb facs="tcp:16779:11"/>
                        <speaker>Do.</speaker>
                        <p>But <hi>Daphnis</hi> comes with him, for loves ſake ſtay.</p>
                     </sp>
                  </div>
                  <div n="4" type="scene">
                     <head>SCENA QVARTA.</head>
                     <stage>Hylas, Mirtillus, Charinus, Daphnis.</stage>
                     <l>
                        <hi>PAn</hi> be as cruell to his flocks and him,</l>
                     <l>As he has bin to me.</l>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Mi.</speaker>
                        <l>Go, leave your curſing,</l>
                        <l>And follow her, let me alone with him.</l>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Cha.</speaker>
                        <l>Ha! have I found you? Hoh! <hi>Nerina,</hi> ſtay,</l>
                        <l>Your father calls you; was not that my daughter</l>
                        <l>That made away ſo faſt?</l>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Mi.</speaker>
                        <l>Who, ſhe thats gon?</l>
                        <l>
                           <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap>eleeve your eies no more, they are falſe to you.</l>
                        <l>Could you take one for her, thats nothing like her.</l>
                        <l>Twas <hi>Cloris</hi> went from us.</l>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Cha.</speaker>
                        <p>Iſt poſſible?</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Mi.</speaker>
                        <p>Tis true.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Da.</speaker>
                        <p>I thought, that it had bin my love.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Cha.</speaker>
                        <l>I durſt have ſworne that ſhe had bin my daughter,</l>
                        <l>What made ſhe here? 'Twill nere be otherwiſe;</l>
                        <l>Young women will be chatting with young men,</l>
                        <l>What ere their father ſay. It was not ſo</l>
                        <l>When I was young, a boy, as you are, ſhepheards.</l>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Mi.</speaker>
                        <p>Wee are not men with him, till after fiftie.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Cha.</speaker>
                        <l>We never durſt keepe company with women,</l>
                        <l>Nor they with us, each one did carefully</l>
                        <l>
                           <pb facs="tcp:16779:12"/>Attend his charge: And when the time was come</l>
                        <l>That we grew ripe in yeares, and were ſtaid youths,</l>
                        <l>Our Fathers would provide us wives: we did not</l>
                        <l>Carve for our ſelves, as now a daies they doe:</l>
                        <l>But now our children thinke themſelves as wiſe,</l>
                        <l>Nay wiſer then their Fathers, and will rule 'em:</l>
                        <l>They can no ſooner peepe out of the ſhell,</l>
                        <l>But they muſt love forſooth; I would faine know,</l>
                        <l>Whether 'twere fit a Maide ſhould be in love,</l>
                        <l>(I ſpeak now of that skittiſh girle my daughter</l>
                        <l>Before ſhe aske her Fathers leave and liking?</l>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Da.</speaker>
                        <l>Tis true <hi>Charinus,</hi> 'twere not fit indeed:</l>
                        <l>Who ſhould beſtow the daughter, but the Father?</l>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Mi.</speaker>
                        <l>But Shepheards did you never heare, that once</l>
                        <l>There was an Age, the neareſt to the Gods:</l>
                        <l>An age we rather praiſe then imitate;</l>
                        <l>When no mans will, nor womans was inforc'd,</l>
                        <l>To any bent, but its owne motion:</l>
                        <l>Each follow'd Natures lawes, and by inſtinct</l>
                        <l>Did love the faireſt, and injoy'd their wiſhes;</l>
                        <l>Love then not ty'd to any intereſt</l>
                        <l>Of blood or fortune, haſtned to his end,</l>
                        <l>Without controll, nor did the Shepheard number</l>
                        <l>Her ſheepe that was his choice, but every grace</l>
                        <l>That did adorne her beauteous minde or face;</l>
                        <l>Riches with love then were not valued,</l>
                        <l>Pure uncompounded love, that could deſpiſe</l>
                        <l>The whole worlds riches for a Miſtreſſe eyes.</l>
                        <l>
                           <pb facs="tcp:16779:12"/>Pray tell me <hi>Daphnis,</hi> you are young and handſome,</l>
                        <l>The lover of our faireſt Nymph <hi>Nerina:</hi>
                        </l>
                        <l>Would you for all that fruitfull <hi>Sicilie</hi>
                        </l>
                        <l>Can yeeld, or all the wealth of <hi>Perſia,</hi>
                        </l>
                        <l>Change one poore locke of your faire Miſtreſſe haire,</l>
                        <l>Whilſt ſhe is yours, and you her ſhepheard are.</l>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Da.</speaker>
                        <p>Would ſhe were mine, I'de aske no portion.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Mi.</speaker>
                        <p>Spoke like a Lover of the ancient ſtampe.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Cha.</speaker>
                        <l>Sonne, ſonne, ſhe ſhall be yours: why? am not I</l>
                        <l>Her Father, ſhe my daughter; may not I</l>
                        <l>Beſtow her where I pleaſe?</l>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Mi.</speaker>
                        <l>Yes if ſhe like</l>
                        <l>The man, ſhe will beſtow her ſelfe, ne're feare it.</l>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Cha.</speaker>
                        <l>What? ſhe beſtow herſelfe without my leave?</l>
                        <l>No, no, <hi>Mirtillus,</hi> you miſtake my daughter.</l>
                        <l>I cannot get her once to thinke of marriage,</l>
                        <l>And truely I do muſe to ſee a wench,</l>
                        <l>That in all other things (although I ſay it)</l>
                        <l>Has wit at will, can pin her ſheepe in fold</l>
                        <l>As well as any, knowes when to drive them home:</l>
                        <l>And there ſhe can do twenty things as well:</l>
                        <l>Yet when I ſpeake to her of marriage,</l>
                        <l>She turnes the head, ſhee'le be a <hi>Dryade,</hi> ſhe</l>
                        <l>Or one of thoſe fond Nymphs of <hi>Dians</hi> traine.</l>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Mi.</speaker>
                        <l>Old man, beleeve her not, ſhe meanes not ſo,</l>
                        <l>She loves to keepe the thing for which ſhe is</l>
                        <l>So much belov'd, I meane her Maidenhead;</l>
                        <l>Which, whilſt ſhe has, ſhe knowes to play the Tyrant,</l>
                        <l>
                           <pb facs="tcp:16779:13"/>And make us ſlaves unto her ſcornefull lookes:</l>
                        <l>For beauty then it ſelfe moſt juſtifies,</l>
                        <l>When it is courted, if not lov'd, it dies.</l>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Cha.</speaker>
                        <l>Well, we will thinke of this: Come <hi>Daphnis,</hi> come,</l>
                        <l>I ſee you love my daughter, and you onely</l>
                        <l>Shall have her, it is I that tell you ſo,</l>
                        <l>That am her Father.</l>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Da.</speaker>
                        <l>Thanke you good <hi>Charinus:</hi>
                        </l>
                        <l>But I had rather ſhe had told me ſo.</l>
                     </sp>
                  </div>
               </div>
               <div n="2" type="act">
                  <head>ACTUS SECUND.</head>
                  <div n="1" type="scene">
                     <head>SCENA PRIM.</head>
                     <stage>Thyrſis, Montanus.</stage>
                     <stage>
                        <hi>To them</hi> Mirtillus.</stage>
                     <l>THis day the Sunne ſhot forth his beames as faire</l>
                     <l>As ere he did, and through the trembling aire</l>
                     <l>Coole <hi>Zephyrus</hi> with gentle murmuring</l>
                     <l>Breath'd a new freſhneſſe on each Tree and Plant:</l>
                     <l>My Kids as game ſome too, as ere they were;</l>
                     <l>All ſhew a face of gladneſſe but my ſelfe.</l>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Mon.</speaker>
                        <p>And why not you aſwell by their example?</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Thy.</speaker>
                        <l>Not in this life, here joy would be untimely:</l>
                        <l>The Gods reſerve for me their comforts in</l>
                        <l>Th' <hi>Elyzian</hi> fields, or elſe they mocke my ſorrows.</l>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Mon.</speaker>
                        <p>O ſay not ſo, they're juſt and pittifull.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Thyr.</speaker>
                        <l>They are, but Father, (ſo I ſtill muſt call you)</l>
                        <l>
                           <pb facs="tcp:16779:13"/>When in the ſadneſſe of my ſoule I askt</l>
                        <l>Before the Altar of our great <hi>Apollo,</hi>
                        </l>
                        <l>What ſhould become of me, or where my love</l>
                        <l>Bright <hi>Silvia</hi> was, whether alive or dead,</l>
                        <l>Why ſhould the Oracle reply, <hi>Goe home,</hi>
                        </l>
                        <l>
                           <hi>Thou ſhalt enjoy thy Silvia?</hi>
                        </l>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Mon.</speaker>
                        <l>What more could you</l>
                        <l>Deſire to heare?</l>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Th.</speaker>
                        <l>I, but when greedily</l>
                        <l>I askt the time, the anſwere was, <hi>That day</hi>
                        </l>
                        <l>
                           <hi>Thou art not Thirſis, nor ſhe Silvia.</hi>
                        </l>
                        <l>Then in this life I'me ſure it muſt not be,</l>
                        <l>For I was <hi>Thyrſis</hi> ever call'd, and ſhe</l>
                        <l>Knowne by no other name then <hi>Sylvia.</hi>
                        </l>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Mon.</speaker>
                        <l>It may be for your importunity</l>
                        <l>You might deſerve this anſwere, or elſe is it</l>
                        <l>Becauſe the Gods ſpeake not their myſteries</l>
                        <l>To be conceiv'd by every vulgar ſence?</l>
                        <l>I now remember what <hi>Acriſius,</hi>
                        </l>
                        <l>The wiſe and vertuous <hi>Acriſius</hi>
                        </l>
                        <l>Was wont to ſay.</l>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Th.</speaker>
                        <l>Why? what ſaid he?</l>
                        <l>Does it concerne me ought?</l>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Mon.</speaker>
                        <l>It may do ſonne,</l>
                        <l>He bid us flie all curioſitie.</l>
                        <l>Seeking to know what future time may bring</l>
                        <l>To us, which onely Gods above do know,</l>
                        <l>And if at any time they do impart</l>
                        <l>
                           <pb facs="tcp:16779:14"/>This knowledge unto us, it is inwrapt</l>
                        <l>In ſuch a miſt, as we ſhall neere ſee through it:</l>
                        <l>Becauſe, ſaid he, we have enough to doe</l>
                        <l>With what is preſent: the celeſtiall powers</l>
                        <l>Would not cut of our hopes, nor multiply</l>
                        <l>Our cares, by ſhewing us our deſtinie.</l>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Thy.</speaker>
                        <l>Oh this diſcourſe to a deſpairing lover,</l>
                        <l>What comfort does it bring? for heavens ſake leave it,</l>
                        <l>And me; for I am beſt, I finde, alone:</l>
                        <l>Yet ſtay, there's ſomething that I faine would aske you:</l>
                        <l>You ſaid this Circle here about my necke</l>
                        <l>Has ſo continu'd from my infancie,</l>
                        <l>When firſt you tooke me up.</l>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Mon.</speaker>
                        <l>Tis true, that Circle</l>
                        <l>Hung looſely then about your necke, which ſince</l>
                        <l>Is filld with it. I left it there, becauſe</l>
                        <l>I ſaw ſome letters that were wrought about it.</l>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Thy.</speaker>
                        <p>And may they not be read?</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Mon.</speaker>
                        <l>I thinke they may:</l>
                        <l>But I could never finde ſo greate a Clerke,</l>
                        <l>As could tell how t'expound the meaning of them.</l>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Thy.</speaker>
                        <l>My life is nothing but a Myſtery;</l>
                        <l>That which I was, and that which I ſhall be,</l>
                        <l>Is equally unknowne. Now, if you'le leave me</l>
                        <l>Unto my thoughts, they'le keepe me companie.</l>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Mon.</speaker>
                        <p>I will, but here is one come to ſupplie me.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <stage>Enter to him Mirtillus.</stage>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Mi.</speaker>
                        <l>I, let me alone.</l>
                        <pb facs="tcp:16779:14"/>
                        <stage>Sings.</stage>
                        <lg type="song">
                           <l>HE that mournes for a Miſteris,</l>
                           <l>When he knows not where ſhe is,</l>
                           <l>Let him kiſſe her ſhaddow faire,</l>
                           <l>Or ingender with the ayre;</l>
                           <l>Or ſee if with his teares he can</l>
                           <l>Swell at an ebb the Ocean:</l>
                           <l>Then, if he had not rather die,</l>
                           <l>Let him love none, or all as I.</l>
                        </lg>
                        <l>This is the doctrine that I ever taught you,</l>
                        <l>And yet you profit not; theſe ſcurvy paſſions</l>
                        <l>Hang on you ſtill: You that are yong and active,</l>
                        <l>That may have all our Nymphs at your devotion,</l>
                        <l>To live a whining kind of life as this,</l>
                        <l>How ill it does become you?</l>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Th.</speaker>
                        <l>True <hi>Mirtillus.</hi>
                        </l>
                        <l>And yet I doe not envie thee the pleaſure,</l>
                        <l>Thou haſt in thy diſpers'd affections.</l>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>M.</speaker>
                        <l>You would, if your head were right once; but love,</l>
                        <l>Your love does make an Aſſe of all your reaſon.</l>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Th.</speaker>
                        <l>Sure, a true lover is more rationall</l>
                        <l>Then you, that love at randome every where.</l>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Mi.</speaker>
                        <l>I doe not thinke ſo; all the reaſon love</l>
                        <l>Has left you, to imploy in this diſcourſe,</l>
                        <l>Will hardly bring me to confeſſe it to you.</l>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Th.</speaker>
                        <l>Why? all mens actions have ſome proper end,</l>
                        <l>Whereto their meanes and ſtrict endeavours tend:</l>
                        <l>
                           <pb facs="tcp:16779:15"/>Elſe there would be nought but perplexitie</l>
                        <l>In humane life, and all uncertaintie.</l>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Mi.</speaker>
                        <p>Well, what will you inferre on this?</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Thy.</speaker>
                        <l>That you,</l>
                        <l>Who know no end at all of wild deſire,</l>
                        <l>Muſt in your wandring fancie ſee this way</l>
                        <l>Leads unto madneſſe, when too late you finde</l>
                        <l>That nothing ſatisfies a boundleſſe minde.</l>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Mi.</speaker>
                        <l>I, but I do confine my ſelfe to two,</l>
                        <l>Or three at moſt; in this varietie</l>
                        <l>I pleaſe my ſelfe, for what is wanting in</l>
                        <l>One, I may finde it in another.</l>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Th.</speaker>
                        <l>No.</l>
                        <l>Not in another, one is the onely Centre</l>
                        <l>The line of love is drawne to, muſt have all</l>
                        <l>Perfections in her, all that's good and faire,</l>
                        <l>Or elſe her Lover muſt beleeve her ſo.</l>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Mi.</speaker>
                        <l>I, there's your error, that's the ground of all</l>
                        <l>Your teares, and ſighs, your fruitleſſe hopes and feares,</l>
                        <l>When ſhe perhaps has not ſo much t'adorne her</l>
                        <l>As the leaſt grace your thoughts beſtow upon her.</l>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Th.</speaker>
                        <l>Well, be it ſo; and yet this faire <hi>Idea</hi>
                        </l>
                        <l>Which I have fram'd unto my ſelfe, does argue</l>
                        <l>Vertue in me; ſo that if ſhe be loſt,</l>
                        <l>Or dead, (ay me! the ſad remembrance of</l>
                        <l>My <hi>Sylvia</hi> cauſes this) yet I muſt love,</l>
                        <l>Becauſe the Character is indelible,</l>
                        <l>Writ in my heart, and heaven is witneſſe to it.</l>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <pb facs="tcp:16779:15"/>
                        <speaker>Mi.</speaker>
                        <l>Well, I'le no more of this, I'le be converted,</l>
                        <l>Rather then call this griefe to your remembrance.</l>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Th.</speaker>
                        <l>Why? doſt thou thinke I ever ſhall forget her?</l>
                        <l>Or that where ere I ſet my carefull foote,</l>
                        <l>As in this place, will it not tell me, that</l>
                        <l>Here <hi>Sylvia</hi> and I walkt hand in hand,</l>
                        <l>And here ſhe pluckt a flower, and anon</l>
                        <l>She gave it me; and then we kiſs't, and here</l>
                        <l>We mutually did vow each others love?</l>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Mi.</speaker>
                        <l>Nay leave good <hi>Thyrſis,</hi> I did come to tell you,</l>
                        <l>This holy-day our Royall Prince <hi>Euarchus</hi>
                        </l>
                        <l>Being remov'd to his houſe here neere adjoyning,</l>
                        <l>Sent to command us to attend his perſon,</l>
                        <l>With all our ſports and wonted merriment,</l>
                        <l>Wherein you alwaies bore the chiefeſt part.</l>
                        <l>And I have heard, ('tis not to make you bluſh)</l>
                        <l>The Princeſſe has commended your rare Art</l>
                        <l>And hanſome graces, which you gave your Muſicke.</l>
                        <l>Come, you muſt goe with us, for <hi>Hylas</hi> is</l>
                        <l>So farre ingag'd in love, and neere his hopes,</l>
                        <l>He will not ſtirre unleſſe his Miſtreſſe goe.</l>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Thy.</speaker>
                        <l>Alas <hi>Mirtillus,</hi> I have broke my Pipe,</l>
                        <l>My ſighs are all the muſicke which I now</l>
                        <l>Can make, and how unfit I am t'attend</l>
                        <l>So great an expectation, you may ſee.</l>
                        <l>Yet give me leave to thinke on it, at night</l>
                        <l>Perhaps Ile goe with you.</l>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Mi.</speaker>
                        <l>Till then farewell.</l>
                        <l>
                           <pb facs="tcp:16779:16"/>The gentleſt youth that ever plaid on Pipe:</l>
                        <l>But ſee, who's here? oh, 'tis my other Lover,</l>
                        <l>His Miſtreſſe with him, I will not diſturbe him.</l>
                     </sp>
                  </div>
                  <div n="2" type="scene">
                     <head>SCENA SECUNDA.</head>
                     <stage>Nerina, Hylas, Mirtillus.</stage>
                     <p>SHepheard, I would you'd leave to follow me.</p>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Hy.</speaker>
                        <p>How can I ſweeteſt, when my heart is with you?</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Ne.</speaker>
                        <l>With me? then tell me where, and ſee how ſoone</l>
                        <l>I ſhall reſtore it you.
<stage>Aſide.</stage>
                        </l>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Mi.</speaker>
                        <p>Oh, this is fine.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Hy.</speaker>
                        <l>It hangs upon your eies, where being ſcorcht</l>
                        <l>With their diſdaine, and dazel'd with their luſtre,</l>
                        <l>It flies for eaſe unto your roſie lips.</l>
                        <l>But beaten thence with many a harſh deniall,</l>
                        <l>Faine would it come for better harbour here,</l>
                        <l>But here for ever it muſt be an Exile:</l>
                        <l>For pittie then faire Nymph, receive it you;</l>
                        <l>And if you can, teach it the hardneſſe of</l>
                        <l>Your owne, and make it marble as yours is.</l>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Mi.</speaker>
                        <l>I ſee he is not ſuch a Novice as
<stage>Aſide.</stage>
                        </l>
                        <l>I tooke him for; he can tell how to ſpeake.</l>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Ne.</speaker>
                        <l>Well, if my heart be ſuch as you will make it,</l>
                        <l>I am ſo much the gladder; that it is</l>
                        <l>Of ſtrength to be a fence unto my honour.</l>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Hy.</speaker>
                        <l>In vaine a fence is made to guard the ſheep,</l>
                        <l>
                           <pb facs="tcp:16779:16"/>Where no wolfe ever came.</l>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Ne.</speaker>
                        <l>What if within</l>
                        <l>It keepe a dog of prey, would they be ſafe?</l>
                        <l>For my part Ile not cheriſh in my breaſt,</l>
                        <l>The man that would undoe my chaſtitie.</l>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Hy.</speaker>
                        <l>Then cheriſh me, for you beſt know, I never</l>
                        <l>Attempted any thing to caſt a ſpot</l>
                        <l>On that white Innocence, to which I am</l>
                        <l>A moſt religious votary.</l>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Mi</speaker>
                        <l>More foole you;
<stage>Aſide.</stage>
                        </l>
                        <l>It may be if you had, it needed not</l>
                        <l>Ha' come to this.</l>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Ne.</speaker>
                        <l>Yes, yes, you may remember,</l>
                        <l>I bluſh to tell it you, when firſt my thoughts</l>
                        <l>Were pure and ſimple, (as I hope they are</l>
                        <l>Still, and will ſo continue, whilſt I flie</l>
                        <l>Such companie as you) I thought you one</l>
                        <l>Whom never any flame impure had toucht:</l>
                        <l>Then we converſt without ſuſpect together.</l>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Hy.</speaker>
                        <l>And am I not ſo ſtill? why do you now</l>
                        <l>Flie from me thus?</l>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Ne.</speaker>
                        <l>The cauſe I ſhall tell you,</l>
                        <l>Since you will not remember; though it be</l>
                        <l>Unfit for me to ſpeake, yet you ſhall know</l>
                        <l>How juſt my anger is.</l>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Hy</speaker>
                        <l>Ay me! moſt wretched!</l>
                        <l>What have I don?</l>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Ne.</speaker>
                        <l>When tending of my flocks</l>
                        <l>
                           <pb facs="tcp:16779:17"/>Under the ſhade of yonder Mirtle tree.</l>
                        <l>(Which beares the guilt of your ſoule miſdemeanour)</l>
                        <l>My maide <hi>Coriſca</hi> cried out for my helpe,</l>
                        <l>Becauſe a bee had ſtung her in the face:</l>
                        <l>You heard me ſpeake in pittie of her ſmart,</l>
                        <l>A charme, my mother taught me, (that being ſaid</l>
                        <l>Cloſe to the place affected, takes away</l>
                        <l>The paine) which gave her eaſe, but you uncivill,</l>
                        <l>Turning my courteſie to your vile ends,</l>
                        <l>Fain'd you were ſtung too, and cried out, your lips</l>
                        <l>Had from the ſame ſharpe point receiv'd a wound;</l>
                        <l>Prayd me to ſay the ſame charme over there.</l>
                        <l>I charitably lent my helpe to you,</l>
                        <l>Miſtruſting nothing of your purpoſes,</l>
                        <l>When with ungentle hands you held me faſt,</l>
                        <l>And for my thanks gave me a luſtfull kiſſe,</l>
                        <l>Canſt thou remember this, and yet not bluſh?</l>
                        <l>O impudence!</l>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Hy.</speaker>
                        <l>You will excuſe the heate</l>
                        <l>Of my deſires; ſtill I feele that ſting</l>
                        <l>But dare not aske the cure, nor did I then</l>
                        <l>Do any hurt, but ſince you thinke it was</l>
                        <l>A fault, I do repent it, and am ſorry</l>
                        <l>I did offend you ſo.</l>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Mi.</speaker>
                        <l>Better, and better</l>
                        <l>He'le cry anon, he has already askt</l>
                        <l>Forgiveneſſe of her.
<stage>Aſide.</stage>
                        </l>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Ne.</speaker>
                        <l>Well ſhepheard looke</l>
                        <l>
                           <pb facs="tcp:16779:17"/>You never ſee me more, I cannot love</l>
                        <l>At all, or if at all, not you: let this</l>
                        <l>Settle your thoughts.</l>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Hy.</speaker>
                        <l>Oh, it diſtracts them more:</l>
                        <l>But ſince my preſence is offenſive to you,</l>
                        <l>I muſt obey, yet if I thought you would,</l>
                        <l>When I am dead, the Martyr of your beautie,</l>
                        <l>Shed one poore teare on my untimely grave,</l>
                        <l>And ſay that <hi>Hylas</hi> was unfortunate</l>
                        <l>To love, where he might not be lov'd againe,</l>
                        <l>My aſhes would find reſt, and ſo farewell</l>
                        <l>The faireſt, but the cruellſt <hi>Nymph</hi> alive.</l>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Mi.</speaker>
                        <p>What will you leave her thus?</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Hy.</speaker>
                        <l>I prithee, come,</l>
                        <l>The ſentence of my baniſhment is paſt,</l>
                        <l>Never to be recall'd.</l>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Mi.</speaker>
                        <l>Are theſe the hopes</l>
                        <l>You fed upon? O what a thing in Nature</l>
                        <l>Is a coy woman! or how great a foole</l>
                        <l>The man is, that will give her leave to rule.</l>
                     </sp>
                  </div>
                  <div n="3" type="scene">
                     <head>SCENA TERTIA.</head>
                     <stage>Nerina.</stage>
                     <l>ALas my <hi>Hylas,</hi> my beloved ſoule,</l>
                     <l>Durſt ſhe, whom thou haſt call'd cruell <hi>Nerina,</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>But ſpeake her thoughts, thou wouldſt not thinke her ſo,</l>
                     <l>
                        <pb facs="tcp:16779:18"/>To thee ſhe is not cruell, but to her ſelfe:</l>
                     <l>That law which Nature hath writ in my heart,</l>
                     <l>Taught me to love thee, <hi>Hylas,</hi> and obey</l>
                     <l>My father too; who ſaies I muſt not love thee?</l>
                     <l>Oh diſproportiond love and duty, how</l>
                     <l>Do you diſtract me? if I love my choiſe,</l>
                     <l>I muſt be diſobedient; if obedient</l>
                     <l>I muſt be linkt to one I cannot love.</l>
                     <l>Then either love give me my libertie,</l>
                     <l>Or nature from my duty ſet me free.
<stage>Exit.</stage>
                     </l>
                  </div>
                  <div n="4" type="scene">
                     <head>SCENA QUARTA.</head>
                     <stage>Daphnis.</stage>
                     <l>
                        <hi>NErina,</hi> ſince nor teares nor praiers can move</l>
                     <l>Thy ſtubborne heart, Ile ſee what gifts can do:</l>
                     <l>They of my ranke, whom moſt do deeme unworthy</l>
                     <l>Of any virgins love, being rough, and bred</l>
                     <l>To mannage the eſtates our fathers left us,</l>
                     <l>Unskild in thoſe hid myſteries, which loues</l>
                     <l>Profeſſors onely know, have yet a way</l>
                     <l>To gaine our wiſhes: firſt we get the father,</l>
                     <l>He knowes our pleaſures, and gives his conſent:</l>
                     <l>The daughters eies being blinded with our gifts</l>
                     <l>Cannot ſo ſoone ſpie our deformities,</l>
                     <l>But we may catch her to: This <hi>Alcon</hi> ſaies,</l>
                     <l>A man whom age and obſervation taught</l>
                     <l>
                        <pb facs="tcp:16779:18"/>What I muſt learne; yet though moſt women be</l>
                     <l>Such as he has deliver'd, my <hi>Nerina</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>Seemes not to have regard to what I give,</l>
                     <l>But holds me and my gifts both at one rate.</l>
                     <l>What can I hope then out of this poore preſent,</l>
                     <l>A looking-glaſſe, which though within our Plaines</l>
                     <l>'Tis ſeldome ſeene; yet I have heard in Citties,</l>
                     <l>They are as common as a locke of wooll:</l>
                     <l>However, if ſhe take it, I am happy,</l>
                     <l>So <hi>Alcon</hi> tells me; and he knowes full well,</l>
                     <l>(He gave it me) that whoſoe're ſhall looke</l>
                     <l>Her face in it, ſhall be at my diſpoſe:</l>
                     <l>In confidence of this I will preſent it,</l>
                     <l>And ſee my Fortune; ſure I muſt needs ſpeed:</l>
                     <l>My friend, her father comes along with her.</l>
                     <l>But oh my Fate! is not that Nymph <hi>Dorinda</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>Which keepes them company? Yes, ſure 'tis ſhe;</l>
                     <l>A curſe light on her importunitie.</l>
                     <l>Her father urges ſomething, and I hope</l>
                     <l>On my behalfe; let me obſerve a little.</l>
                  </div>
                  <div n="5" type="scene">
                     <head>SCENA QUINTA.</head>
                     <stage>Charinus, Nerina, Dorinda, Daphnis.</stage>
                     <l>ANd as I oft have told you, I doe wiſh</l>
                     <l>To ſee you wiſe.</l>
                     <sp>
                        <pb facs="tcp:16779:19"/>
                        <speaker>Do.</speaker>
                        <l>Is ſhe not ſo <hi>Charinus?</hi>
                        </l>
                        <l>Does ſhe ſay any thing that's out of reaſon?</l>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Cha.</speaker>
                        <l>Do not tell me of reaſon; I would heare</l>
                        <l>Of her obedience, therefore I ſay, be wiſe,</l>
                        <l>And doe as I would have you.</l>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Do.</speaker>
                        <l>What would you</l>
                        <l>Have her to doe? you ſee ſhe anſwers not</l>
                        <l>To contradict you.</l>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Cha.</speaker>
                        <l>I will have her anſwer</l>
                        <l>To what I now demand, that is, to marry</l>
                        <l>
                           <hi>Daphnis,</hi> and I will have her love him too.</l>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Do.</speaker>
                        <l>Love him <hi>Charinus?</hi> that you cannot do.</l>
                        <l>Her body you may linke i'th' rights of <hi>Hymen,</hi>
                        </l>
                        <l>Her will ſhe muſt beſtow her ſelfe, not you.</l>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Da.</speaker>
                        <p>Oh, ſhe was borne to be a plague unto me.
<stage>Aſide.</stage>
                        </p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Cha.</speaker>
                        <l>Why ſhould ſhe wiſh or hope for any thing,</l>
                        <l>But what I'de have her wiſh or hope for onely?</l>
                        <l>Come, to be ſhort, anſwere me, and directly;</l>
                        <l>Are you content to marry <hi>Daphnis,</hi> ſay?</l>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Ne.</speaker>
                        <p>What is your pleaſure Father?</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Cha.</speaker>
                        <l>You do not heare</l>
                        <l>It ſeemes, but what you liſt; I aske you once</l>
                        <l>Againe, if you will marry <hi>Daphnis,</hi> ſpeake?</l>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Ne.</speaker>
                        <l>Sir, I would marry whom you pleaſe to give me:</l>
                        <l>I neither can, nor ought to make my choice,</l>
                        <l>I would referre that to you: But you know</l>
                        <l>My inclination never lay to marry.</l>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Cha.</speaker>
                        <p>I know you ſhal do that which I command.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <pb facs="tcp:16779:19"/>
                        <speaker>Ne.</speaker>
                        <l>Now heaven forbid, that I who have thus long</l>
                        <l>Vow'd to <hi>Diana</hi> my Virginitie,</l>
                        <l>To follow her a Huntreſſe in theſe Woods,</l>
                        <l>Should yeeld my ſelfe to the impure delights</l>
                        <l>Of <hi>Hymen,</hi> and ſo violate my faith.</l>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Cha.</speaker>
                        <l>A fine devotion, is it not? to make</l>
                        <l>A vow, and never aske your Father leave;</l>
                        <l>The Lawes will not permit it to be ſo.</l>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Do.</speaker>
                        <l>The vow <hi>Charinus,</hi> is not made to men:</l>
                        <l>The Lawes have not to doe with that which is</l>
                        <l>Seal'd and recorded in the Court of Heaven.</l>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Cha.</speaker>
                        <l>Do not tell me of vowes, I'le have her marry;</l>
                        <l>And marry <hi>Daphnis:</hi> Is he not rich and handſome?</l>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Do.</speaker>
                        <l>Ay me! I would he were nor rich, nor handſome,</l>
                        <l>It may be then he would regard my ſufferings.
<stage>Aſide.</stage>
                        </l>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Cha.</speaker>
                        <l>No, Daughter, do not you beleeve, you can</l>
                        <l>Catch me with ſhifts and tricks: I ſee, I tell you,</l>
                        <l>Into your heart.</l>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Ne.</speaker>
                        <l>Alas, I would you did,</l>
                        <l>Then your diſcourſe would tend another way.</l>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Cha.</speaker>
                        <l>Yes, you have made a vow I know, which is,</l>
                        <l>Whilſt you are young, you will have all the Youth</l>
                        <l>To follow you with lies and flatteries.</l>
                        <l>Foole, they'le deceive you, when this colour fades,</l>
                        <l>Which will not alwaies laſt, and you goe crooked,</l>
                        <l>As if you ſought your beautie loſt i'th' ground:</l>
                        <l>Then they will laugh at you, and finde ſome other</l>
                        <l>Fit for their love; where if you doe as I</l>
                        <l>
                           <pb facs="tcp:16779:20"/>Command you, I have one will make you happie.</l>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Ne.</speaker>
                        <p>Ay me moſt miſerable!</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Da.</speaker>
                        <l>Now I'le come in,</l>
                        <l>And ſee what I can doe with this my gift.</l>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Cha.</speaker>
                        <l>Looke now, as if the Fates would have it ſo,</l>
                        <l>He comes juſt in the nicke of my diſcourſe:</l>
                        <l>Come, uſe him kindly now, and then you ſhall</l>
                        <l>Redeeme what you have loſt, my good opinion.</l>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Ne.</speaker>
                        <l>O moſt ungratefull chance! how I doe hate</l>
                        <l>The ſight of him!</l>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Do.</speaker>
                        <l>Were it to me he came,</l>
                        <l>How happie would this faire encounter be!</l>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Cha.</speaker>
                        <l>
                           <hi>Daphnis,</hi> you're welcome, very welcome to me,</l>
                        <l>And to my Daughter: what is that you have there?</l>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Da.</speaker>
                        <p>A preſent, which I meane to give my love.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Cha.</speaker>
                        <l>See but how true a lover <hi>Daphnis</hi> is;</l>
                        <l>His hand is never emptie when he comes:</l>
                        <l>Welcome him Daughter, looke what he has for you.</l>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Da.</speaker>
                        <l>O good <hi>Charinus,</hi> none muſt looke in it,</l>
                        <l>But ſhe herſelfe to whom it is preſented.</l>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Cha.</speaker>
                        <l>I am an old man, I, and therefore care not</l>
                        <l>To ſee my wither'd face, and hoarie haire:</l>
                        <l>Give it that young thing, ſhe knows what to doe with it.</l>
                        <l>Daughter, come hither, uſe him courteouſly,</l>
                        <l>And kindly too: (Be ſure you take his gift.)</l>
                        <l>
                           <hi>Daphnis,</hi> I'le leave you both together here;</l>
                        <l>My ſheepe are ſhearing, I can ſtay no longer.</l>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Da.</speaker>
                        <p>Farewell old man; health to my deareſt Miſtreſſe</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <pb facs="tcp:16779:20"/>
                        <speaker>Ne.</speaker>
                        <p>And to you ſhepheard.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Do.</speaker>
                        <l>
                           <hi>Daphnis</hi> am not I</l>
                        <l>Worthy to have a ſhare in your ſalute?</l>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Do.</speaker>
                        <l>How can I give thee part of that, whereof</l>
                        <l>I have no ſhare my ſelfe?</l>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Do.</speaker>
                        <l>If you would love</l>
                        <l>There, where you are belov'd againe, you might</l>
                        <l>Make your content ſuch, as you would your ſelfe.</l>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Da.</speaker>
                        <l>If you, <hi>Nerina,</hi> would vouchſafe to love</l>
                        <l>Him that loves you, and ever will, you might</l>
                        <l>Make your content ſuch as you would your ſelfe.</l>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Ne.</speaker>
                        <l>Shepheard, I oft have wiſht you not to trouble</l>
                        <l>Me and your ſelfe with words: I cannot love you.</l>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Da.</speaker>
                        <l>As oft <hi>Dorinda</hi> have I ſpoke to you,</l>
                        <l>To leave to trouble me: I cannot love you.</l>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Do.</speaker>
                        <p>Will you then ſlight my love, becauſe 'tis offer'd?</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Da.</speaker>
                        <p>Will you then ſlight my love, becauſe 'tis offer'd?</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Ne.</speaker>
                        <p>Some body elſe may love you, I cannot.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Da.</speaker>
                        <p>Some body elſe may love you, I cannot.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Do.</speaker>
                        <p>O cruell words; how they do peirce my heart!</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Da.</speaker>
                        <p>O cruell words, how they do peirce my heart!</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Ne.</speaker>
                        <l>How can I helpe it, if your deſtinie</l>
                        <l>Lead you to love, where you may not obtaine?</l>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Da.</speaker>
                        <l>How can I helpe it, if your deſtinie</l>
                        <l>Leade you to love, where you may not obtaine.</l>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Do.</speaker>
                        <l>It is not deſtinie that injures me,</l>
                        <l>It is thy cruell will, and marble heart.</l>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Da.</speaker>
                        <l>It is not deſtinie that injures me,</l>
                        <l>
                           <pb facs="tcp:16779:21"/>It is thy cruell will, and marble heart.</l>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Ne.</speaker>
                        <l>No <hi>Daphnis,</hi> 'tis not hardnes of my heart,</l>
                        <l>Nor any crueltie that cauſes this.</l>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Da.</speaker>
                        <p>Then 'tis diſdaine of me.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Ne.</speaker>
                        <l>Nor is it that:</l>
                        <l>I do not ſee in <hi>Daphnis</hi> any thing</l>
                        <l>To cauſe diſdaine.</l>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Do.</speaker>
                        <l>Why do you not replie</l>
                        <l>In thoſe ſame words to me, malicious Eccho?</l>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Da.</speaker>
                        <l>Pray leave me, I have other buſineſſe now</l>
                        <l>To trouble me; if you diſdaine me not,</l>
                        <l>Faire Nymph, as you pretend, receive my offer.</l>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Ne.</speaker>
                        <p>What's that?</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Da.</speaker>
                        <p>My heart.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Do.</speaker>
                        <p>I will gentle <hi>Daphnis.</hi>
                        </p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Da.</speaker>
                        <p>O importunitie!</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Ne.</speaker>
                        <l>Give her thy heart,</l>
                        <l>She has deſerv'd it, for ſhe loves thee, <hi>Daphnis.</hi>
                        </l>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Da.</speaker>
                        <p>Firſt I would teare it peecemeale here before you.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Do.</speaker>
                        <p>O me unfortunate! O cruell man!</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Ne.</speaker>
                        <p>Stay good <hi>Dorinda,</hi> I'le goe with thee, ſtay.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Da.</speaker>
                        <l>Let her goe where ſhe will, behold ſweete ſaint</l>
                        <l>This Mirror here, the faithfull repreſenter</l>
                        <l>Of that which I adore, your beautious forme,</l>
                        <l>When you do ſee in that how how lovely are</l>
                        <l>your lookes, you will not blame my love.</l>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Ne.</speaker>
                        <l>If I refuſe it,</l>
                        <l>My father will be angrie, let me ſee it:</l>
                        <l>
                           <pb facs="tcp:16779:21"/>Here take thy glaſſe againe: what ailes my head?</l>
                        <l>I know not where I am, it is ſo giddie:</l>
                        <l>And ſomething like a drouſineſſe has ſeiz'd</l>
                        <l>My vitall ſpirits.</l>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Da.</speaker>
                        <p>How do you love? not well?</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Ne.</speaker>
                        <p>Heavy o'th ſuddaine; Ile goe home, &amp; ſleepe.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Da.</speaker>
                        <l>So, let her goe, and let this worke awhile.</l>
                        <l>Shee caſt an eye upon me as ſhe went,</l>
                        <l>That by its languiſhing did ſeeme to ſay,</l>
                        <l>
                           <hi>Daphnis</hi> I'me thine, thou haſt o'recome at laſt:</l>
                        <l>
                           <hi>Alcon,</hi> th'haſt made me happy by thy art.</l>
                     </sp>
                  </div>
               </div>
               <div n="3" type="act">
                  <head>ACTUS, 3.</head>
                  <div n="1" type="scene">
                     <head>SCENA 1.</head>
                     <stage>Sylvia, Delia.</stage>
                     <sp>
                        <lg type="song">
                           <lg n="1">
                              <l>
                                 <hi>Q.</hi> TEll me what you thinke on earth</l>
                              <l>The greateſt bliſſe?</l>
                              <l>
                                 <hi>A.</hi> Riches, honor, and high birth.</l>
                              <l>
                                 <hi>Q.</hi> Ah, what is this?</l>
                              <l>If love be baniſhed the heart,</l>
                              <l>The joy of Nature, not of Art?</l>
                           </lg>
                           <lg n="2">
                              <head>2.</head>
                              <l>What's honor worth, or high deſcent?</l>
                              <l>Or ample wealth,</l>
                              <l>If cares do breed us diſcontent,</l>
                              <l>Or want of health?</l>
                              <l>
                                 <pb facs="tcp:16779:22"/>
                                 <hi>A.</hi> It is the order of the Fates,</l>
                              <l>That theſe ſhould waite on higheſt ſtates.</l>
                           </lg>
                           <lg n="3">
                              <head>3.</head>
                              <l>
                                 <hi>Cho.</hi> Love onely does our ſoules refine,</l>
                              <l>And by his skill</l>
                              <l>Turnes humane things into divine,</l>
                              <l>And guides our will.</l>
                              <l>Then let us of his praiſes ſing,</l>
                              <l>Of love, that ſweetens every thing.</l>
                           </lg>
                        </lg>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Del.</speaker>
                        <p>Madam, you're overheard.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Sy.</speaker>
                        <l>I care not <hi>Delia.</hi>
                        </l>
                        <l>Although my libertie, and free diſcourſe</l>
                        <l>Be here denide me, yet the Aire is common:</l>
                        <l>To it then will I utter my complaints,</l>
                        <l>Or to thee, friend, to whom my love will dare</l>
                        <l>To ſhew the ſecrets of my heart, for others</l>
                        <l>I do not care, nor feare; ſo thou be faithfull.</l>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Del.</speaker>
                        <l>Madam, I have no life, but what I wiſh</l>
                        <l>May be imploy'd to do your beauties ſerice;</l>
                        <l>My tongue is rul'd by yours: what you would have</l>
                        <l>It ſpeake, it ſhall; elſe further then my thoughts</l>
                        <l>Nothing ſhall venter, that you leaue to me:</l>
                        <l>And thoſe my thoughts, Ile keepe to ſuch reſtraint,</l>
                        <l>As they ſhall never come within my dreames,</l>
                        <l>Leſt they betray your counſells: this I vow</l>
                        <l>Religiouſly by—</l>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Syl.</speaker>
                        <l>Hold, I will not</l>
                        <l>
                           <pb facs="tcp:16779:22"/>Have thee to ſweare, nor would I thou ſhouldſt thinke,</l>
                        <l>That I ſo much ſuſpect thee, as to urge</l>
                        <l>An Oath; I know thou haſt too much of goodneſſe</l>
                        <l>(That's bred within thee) to betray a truſt:</l>
                        <l>And therefore without further circumſtance,</l>
                        <l>I'le let thee know my fortunes, part of which</l>
                        <l>I'me ſure th' haſt heard already.</l>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Del.</speaker>
                        <l>Madam, I have,</l>
                        <l>And wiſht that they had ſorted to your wiſhes.</l>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Syl.</speaker>
                        <l>I thanke thee <hi>Delia,</hi> but my evill Genius,</l>
                        <l>That has purſu'd my innocence with hate,</l>
                        <l>Brought me from thence where I had ſet my heart,</l>
                        <l>Unto this curſed Court, which, though it be</l>
                        <l>My place of birth and breeding, I doe finde</l>
                        <l>Nothing but torment, and affliction in it.</l>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Del.</speaker>
                        <l>I gueſſe the cauſe ſweet Madam, but that's paſt</l>
                        <l>And now forgotten: if you cleere your looks,</l>
                        <l>Your Father will inlarge you, and ne're thinke</l>
                        <l>On what you did, but that you are his daughter.</l>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Syl.</speaker>
                        <l>Alas my <hi>Delia,</hi> thou doſt miſtake,</l>
                        <l>My liberty is of no worth to me,</l>
                        <l>Since that my love, I feare, will ne're be free:</l>
                        <l>Nor doe I care what idle Ladies talke</l>
                        <l>Of my departure, or my ſtrange diſguiſe,</l>
                        <l>To colour my intents; I am above</l>
                        <l>Their envie or their malice:</l>
                        <l>But for th' unluckie chance that ſent to me</l>
                        <l>The over-curious eyes of him I hate,</l>
                        <l>
                           <pb facs="tcp:16779:23"/>Thou know'ſt the man.</l>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>De.</speaker>
                        <l>Yes, you meane <hi>Cleander,</hi>
                        </l>
                        <l>Sonne to <hi>Eubulus,</hi> who is now your keeper:</l>
                        <l>What Starre directed him to finde you out?</l>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Syl.</speaker>
                        <l>His love forſooth, for ſo he colour'd his</l>
                        <l>Unſeaſon'd boldneſſe, told me, he was not able</l>
                        <l>To want my ſight: and ſo, when every one</l>
                        <l>Had given o're their ſtrict enquirie of me,</l>
                        <l>He onely with too much officiouſneſſe,</l>
                        <l>Obſerv'd me in the Woods, walking alone:</l>
                        <l>And when I would have ſhunn'd him (which perhaps</l>
                        <l>Had I not done, he had not ſo well knowne me)</l>
                        <l>He came, and utter'd, as his manner was,</l>
                        <l>His tedious complaints; untill at length</l>
                        <l>He brought me with him, making no reſiſtance:</l>
                        <l>And to ingratiate himſelfe the more,</l>
                        <l>He ſaid he would convey me where my Father</l>
                        <l>Should have no knowledge of me: I refuſed it;</l>
                        <l>Willing however to be ridde of him.</l>
                        <l>And now you know, it is a full Moneth ſince</l>
                        <l>I did returne to Court, but left my heart</l>
                        <l>Behinde me in thoſe fields, wherein I joy'd.</l>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Del.</speaker>
                        <l>Madam, has not the Court more pleaſure in it,</l>
                        <l>Then the dull Countrie, which can repreſent</l>
                        <l>Nothing, but what does taſte of ſolitude?</l>
                        <l>'Twas ſomething elſe that carried you away.</l>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Syl.</speaker>
                        <l>Tis true my <hi>Delia;</hi> for though thou wert</l>
                        <l>Privie to my departure, yet the cauſe</l>
                        <l>
                           <pb facs="tcp:16779:23"/>Thou couldſt not tell, which I will now unfold,</l>
                        <l>And thinke I truſt my honor in thy hands,</l>
                        <l>And maiden modeſtie: 'twas love that did it.</l>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Del.</speaker>
                        <l>Love Madam? ſure it is impoſſible</l>
                        <l>You ſhould finde any thing there worth your love.</l>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Syl.</speaker>
                        <l>Thou know'ſt the ſhepheards, that do dwell about</l>
                        <l>This place (which for their entertainements onely</l>
                        <l>The King my father built) did uſe to come,</l>
                        <l>As now they do, being ſent for unto Court:</l>
                        <l>I ever lik't their ſports, their harmeleſſe mirth,</l>
                        <l>And their contentions, which were voide of malice,</l>
                        <l>And wiſht I had bin borne juſt ſuch a one.</l>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Del.</speaker>
                        <p>Your ſtate is better Madam as you are.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Syl.</speaker>
                        <l>But I confeſſe the rather, cauſe there was</l>
                        <l>One amongſt them, of a more comely grace</l>
                        <l>(Though none of them did ſeeme uncomely to me)</l>
                        <l>Call'd <hi>Thyrſis;</hi> and with him me thought I could</l>
                        <l>Draw out my life, rather then any other,</l>
                        <l>Such things my fancie then ſuggeſted to me:</l>
                        <l>So well he ſung, ſo paſſionate his love</l>
                        <l>Shew'd in his verſe, thereto ſo well expreſt,</l>
                        <l>As any one would judge it naturall:</l>
                        <l>Yet never felt he flame, till this of me:</l>
                        <l>Often he came, and oftner was deſir'd</l>
                        <l>Of me, nor did I ſhame in publique there</l>
                        <l>Before my father, to commend his graces;</l>
                        <l>Which when I did, the whole Court, as they uſe,</l>
                        <l>Conſented with me, and did ſtrive to make them</l>
                        <l>
                           <pb facs="tcp:16779:24"/>Greater then I, or any elſe could thinke them:</l>
                        <l>At laſt I was ſurpriz'd, I could not helpe it;</l>
                        <l>My Fate with love conſenting, ſo would have it.</l>
                        <l>Then did I leave the Court, I've told thee all.</l>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Del.</speaker>
                        <l>Tis ſtrange, but Madam, though in that diſguiſe,</l>
                        <l>How could you hope, a ſtranger, to be lov'd</l>
                        <l>Of him you held ſo deare?</l>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Syl.</speaker>
                        <l>I fain'd my ſelfe</l>
                        <l>Of <hi>Smyrna,</hi> and from thence ſome Goats I had,</l>
                        <l>And Sheepe, with them a rich commoditie.</l>
                        <l>Neare him I bought me land to feed them; he</l>
                        <l>Seem'd glad of it, and thinking me a ſtranger,</l>
                        <l>Us'd me with ſuch civilitie and friendſhip,</l>
                        <l>As one would little looke for of a ſhepheard;</l>
                        <l>And did defend me from the avarice</l>
                        <l>Of the old ſhepheards, which did thinke to make</l>
                        <l>A prey of what I had. At length I ſaw,</l>
                        <l>He did addreſſe himſelfe with feare to me,</l>
                        <l>Still gazing on me: knowing my love to him,</l>
                        <l>I eaſily beleev'd he lov'd me too:</l>
                        <l>For love, alas, is ever credulous.</l>
                        <l>And though I was reſolv'd, having my end,</l>
                        <l>(Which was no more, then to diſcourſe with him)</l>
                        <l>Nev<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap>r to let him know what flame I felt:</l>
                        <l>Yet when I ſaw his teares, and heard his vowes,</l>
                        <l>(Perſwaſive ſpeakers for affection)</l>
                        <l>I could not chooſe but open to his view</l>
                        <l>My loving heart; yet with this caution,</l>
                        <l>
                           <pb facs="tcp:16779:24"/>That he ſhould ever beare reſpect unto</l>
                        <l>My honor, and my virgin chaſtitie:</l>
                        <l>Which then he vow'd, and his ambition</l>
                        <l>Never was more then to attaine a kiſſe,</l>
                        <l>Which yet he hardly got: thou ſeeſt, ſweete <hi>Delia,</hi>
                        </l>
                        <l>How willingly I dwell upon this Theame.</l>
                        <l>But canſt thou helpe me now, that I have open'd</l>
                        <l>My wound unto thee.</l>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Del.</speaker>
                        <l>Alas, I would I could</l>
                        <l>Invent the way to cure you; I ſhould ſoone</l>
                        <l>Apply my helpe: yet ſtay, this day it is</l>
                        <l>The ſhepheards come to Court.</l>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Syl.</speaker>
                        <l>'Tis true, they come;</l>
                        <l>But what is that to me, if <hi>Thyrſis</hi> come not?</l>
                        <l>Or if he come, how ſhall he know me his,</l>
                        <l>Or I injoy his companie?</l>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Del.</speaker>
                        <l>Let me alone</l>
                        <l>To worke out that.</l>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Syl.</speaker>
                        <p>Thou dreamſt, thou canſt not do it.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Del.</speaker>
                        <l>Ile undertake it, but how ſhall I know him</l>
                        <l>Without inquiring, which muſt breede ſuſpition.</l>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Syl.</speaker>
                        <l>True, and beware thou aske; the Majeſtie</l>
                        <l>Which ſits upon his brow, will ſay 'tis he,</l>
                        <l>
                           <hi>Thyrſis</hi> my love; but yet perhaps at this time,</l>
                        <l>If I my ſelfe not flatter, thou ſhalt know him,</l>
                        <l>By his eies caſt downe, and folding of his armes,</l>
                        <l>And often ſighs, that interrupt his words.</l>
                        <l>For if his ſorrow weares the liveries,</l>
                        <l>
                           <pb facs="tcp:16779:25"/>Which mine does for his abſence, by theſe ſignes</l>
                        <l>Thou ſhalt deſcrie him.</l>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Del.</speaker>
                        <l>Theſe are ſilent markes:</l>
                        <l>Yet will I not deſpaire to finde him out.</l>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Syl.</speaker>
                        <l>But when thou haſt, what wilt thou ſay to him?</l>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Del.</speaker>
                        <l>Give me but leave to uſe my mother wit,</l>
                        <l>You would be gone together, would you not?</l>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Syl.</speaker>
                        <l>Thou ſpeak'ſt my thoughts: do this, and I will crowne</l>
                        <l>Thy faith, thou ſhalt be Queene in ſteed of me.</l>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Del.</speaker>
                        <l>If you could crowne me with your vertues Madam,</l>
                        <l>I ſhould be a Queene indeed; in the meane time,</l>
                        <l>As I am <hi>Delia,</hi> Ile do this buſines.</l>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Sil.</speaker>
                        <l>Do it, and when th' haſt don, the God of love</l>
                        <l>Reward thee with thine owne deſires for this.</l>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Del.</speaker>
                        <p>Madam withdraw, I heare your keepers comming.</p>
                     </sp>
                  </div>
                  <div n="2" type="scene">
                     <head>SCENA 2.</head>
                     <stage>Cleander, Eubulus.</stage>
                     <l>SIr you have put a bridle on my paſſions,</l>
                     <l>And given my ſoule the libertie it wiſht:</l>
                     <l>I now intreate your pardon, for beginning</l>
                     <l>A thing of ſo great conſequence without</l>
                     <l>Leave and advice from you.</l>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Eu.</speaker>
                        <l>Tis well <hi>Cleander,</hi>
                        </l>
                        <l>It will behove you then to be reſerv'd,</l>
                        <l>And locke this ſecret up: for 'tis no jeſting</l>
                        <l>
                           <pb facs="tcp:16779:25"/>With Kings that may command our lives and fortunes:</l>
                        <l>You now perceive her whom we call the Princeſſe,</l>
                        <l>To be your ſiſter, and the love you beare her,</l>
                        <l>Muſt be a brothers freindſhip, not a lovers</l>
                        <l>Paſſionate heate; but yet ſhe muſt not know,</l>
                        <l>That I her father am, and you her brother:</l>
                        <l>And truſt me ſon, had I not ſeene deſpaire</l>
                        <l>Of life in you, which this love brought you too,</l>
                        <l>I ſhould not have reveal'd, what now you know.</l>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Cle.</speaker>
                        <l>It was a comfort Sir, I doe confeſſe,</l>
                        <l>That came in time to reſcue me from death,</l>
                        <l>So great her ſcorne was, and my love ſo violent.</l>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Eu.</speaker>
                        <p>Now you're at peace, I hope.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Cle.</speaker>
                        <l>I am: but if</l>
                        <l>I be too curious in asking where</l>
                        <l>The Kings ſon is, I ſhall deſire your pardon:</l>
                        <l>For ſure it were injuſtice to deprive</l>
                        <l>So great a Prince, of that which he was borne too.</l>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Eu.</speaker>
                        <l>You are too far inquiſitive; yet becauſe</l>
                        <l>I have ingag'd you in a ſecret of</l>
                        <l>As great importance, this I will not hide.</l>
                        <l>The King, I told you, when his wife grew neere</l>
                        <l>The time of her deliverie, ſent to know</l>
                        <l>Of our great Oracle, whether the childe ſhould be</l>
                        <l>Female, or Male, and what ſhould be their fortune.</l>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Cle.</speaker>
                        <p>What ſaid the Oracle? have you the anſwere?</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Eu.</speaker>
                        <l>It onely was imparted unto me,</l>
                        <l>And this it is which I have never ſhewen</l>
                        <l>
                           <pb facs="tcp:16779:26"/>To any but the Queene: here take and reade it.</l>
                        <q>
                           <l>If ere thy iſſue male thou live to ſee,</l>
                           <l>The childe thou thinkst is thine, thine ſhall not be,</l>
                           <l>His life ſhall be obſcure: twice ſhall thy hate</l>
                           <l>Doome him to death. Yet ſhall he ſcape that Fate:</l>
                           <l>And thou ſhalt live to ſee that not long after,</l>
                           <l>Thy onely ſon ſhall wed thy onely daughter.</l>
                        </q>
                        <l>This Oracle is full of myſterie.</l>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Eu.</speaker>
                        <l>It is; and yet the King would needs interpret</l>
                        <l>That ſhould it prove a man-childe, twas a Baſtard:</l>
                        <l>And being loth that one not of his blood</l>
                        <l>(As he conceiv'd by this) ſhould be his heire,</l>
                        <l>Told me in private, that if it were Male,</l>
                        <l>He would not have it live, yet fearing moſt</l>
                        <l>To publiſh his diſhonor, and his wives,</l>
                        <l>He charg'd me not reveale it unto any,</l>
                        <l>But take the childe, and ſee it made away,</l>
                        <l>And make the world beleeve it was ſtill borne.</l>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Cle.</speaker>
                        <p>And did you ſo?</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Eu.</speaker>
                        <l>No, for indeed I durſt not</l>
                        <l>For any thing, become a murderer.</l>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Cle.</speaker>
                        <p>How did you then?</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Eu.</speaker>
                        <l>I went unto the Queene,</l>
                        <l>Shew'd her the ſtate ſhe was in, and beſought her</l>
                        <l>To be as carefull of me, as I was</l>
                        <l>Of her, and we would worke a better end</l>
                        <l>
                           <pb facs="tcp:16779:26"/>Then ſhe expected, ſo we both agree'd;</l>
                        <l>That if the Childe ſhe then did labour with,</l>
                        <l>Prov'd to be Male, I ſhould with care conceale</l>
                        <l>The birth of it, and put a female childe</l>
                        <l>Inſteed of it, which I was to looke out.</l>
                        <l>It fortun'd that your Mother then was ready</l>
                        <l>To be deliver'd of your ſiſter, and</l>
                        <l>Time and good fortune did conſpire to ſave</l>
                        <l>The Kings child, and to make my daughter Princeſſe.</l>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Cle.</speaker>
                        <p>But what did then become of the yong Prince?</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Eu.</speaker>
                        <l>The Queene proteſting to me, that it was</l>
                        <l>The Kings owne Childe, conjur'd me to preſerve it,</l>
                        <l>Which as mine owne I could not; for already</l>
                        <l>Many tooke notice that my childe was female:</l>
                        <l>And therefore I was faine to publiſh her</l>
                        <l>As dead, and buried an emptie coffin.</l>
                        <l>I rode forth with the childe a full nights journey,</l>
                        <l>With purpoſe to deliver it to ſome</l>
                        <l>Plaine honeſt man, that would be carefull of it,</l>
                        <l>And not inquiſitive to know whoſe childe</l>
                        <l>It was, but give it breeding as his owne:</l>
                        <l>When being frighted with the noiſe of Armes</l>
                        <l>Of ſome out-lawed theeves, that did infeſt</l>
                        <l>The place, I made all haſte I could to ſcape 'em,</l>
                        <l>Conſidering my charge; for that I knew</l>
                        <l>If I were taken, though they ſpar'd my life,</l>
                        <l>The charge I had, muſt needs betray me to</l>
                        <l>The King, and then I could not hope for mercy:</l>
                        <l>
                           <pb facs="tcp:16779:27"/>I laid it downe there cover'd cloſely o're,</l>
                        <l>A circle 'bout his necke, wherein was writ,</l>
                        <stage>Archigenes Sonne of Euarchus and Eudora,</stage>
                        <l>In characters knowne onely to my ſelfe,</l>
                        <l>And to the King; in which I us'd to cloath</l>
                        <l>Secret diſpatches, when I writ to him</l>
                        <l>From forraigne States, and within the Circle</l>
                        <l>I grav'd the Kings leſſe Seale, which then I kept.</l>
                        <l>Some Gold beſides, and Jewels there I left,</l>
                        <l>That whoſoe're ſhould finde him, might with that</l>
                        <l>Defray the charge of his education;</l>
                        <l>Howe're, next day I purpos'd to returne</l>
                        <l>With ſpeede, and carrie it to ſome abode.</l>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Cle.</speaker>
                        <p>But did the Queene know this?</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Eu.</speaker>
                        <l>She did not,</l>
                        <l>Till my returne next day: then when I told her,</l>
                        <l>The childe was thence remov'd where I had left him,</l>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Cle.</speaker>
                        <p>Belike thoſe theeves had carried him away.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Eu.</speaker>
                        <p>'Tis probable.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Cle.</speaker>
                        <l>How could the Queene take this</l>
                        <l>So ſad a ſtorie?</l>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Eu.</speaker>
                        <l>With ſuch impatience,</l>
                        <l>That being weake before, ſhe ſhortly di'd.</l>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Cle.</speaker>
                        <l>But yet ſir, with your favour might you not</l>
                        <l>Have made inquirie after him?</l>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Eu.</speaker>
                        <l>I durſt not,</l>
                        <l>For feare of being diſcover'd; on your life</l>
                        <l>
                           <pb facs="tcp:16779:27"/>Take heed how you reveale this.</l>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Cle.</speaker>
                        <p>I am charm'd.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Eu.</speaker>
                        <l>Then let us watch my daughter, for I feare</l>
                        <l>The flight ſhe made was for ſome other end,</l>
                        <l>Then for retirement which ſhe does pretend.</l>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Cle.</speaker>
                        <l>Henceforth I ſhall obey her as my Princeſſe,</l>
                        <l>And love her as my ſiſter, not my Miſtreſſe.</l>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Eu.</speaker>
                        <p>You ſhall do well: Come, let us to the King.</p>
                     </sp>
                  </div>
                  <div n="3" type="scene">
                     <head>SCENA 3.</head>
                     <stage>Hylas, Mirtillus, Chorus of Shepheards and Shepheardeſſes, repreſenting Paris, Oe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>none, <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>enus, and the Graces.</stage>
                     <l>IT was my dreame, and I will ſend it to her;</l>
                     <l>Though I my ſelfe by her too cruell ſentence,</l>
                     <l>Muſt never ſee her face.</l>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Mi.</speaker>
                        <l>What paper's that?</l>
                        <l>Love-verſes, as I live; what's here, a Dreame?</l>
                        <l>Nay, I will read 'em, therefore ſtand aſide.</l>
                        <stage>Mirtillus <hi>reades.</hi>
                        </stage>
                        <q>
                           <lg>
                              <l>SLeepe, thou be calmer of a troubled ſprîte,</l>
                              <l>Which leadſt my fancy to that ſweet delight,</l>
                              <l>Wherein my ſoule found reſt, when thou didſt ſhow</l>
                              <l>Her ſhadow mine, whoſe ſubſtance is not ſo:</l>
                              <l>
                                 <pb facs="tcp:16779:28"/>Wrappe up mine eyes in an eternall night.</l>
                              <l>For ſince my day ſprings onely from that light</l>
                              <l>Which ſhe denies me; I account the beſt</l>
                              <l>Part of my life is that which gives me reſt.</l>
                           </lg>
                           <lg>
                              <l>And thou more hard to be intreated, then</l>
                              <l>Sleepe to the heated eyes of franticke men;</l>
                              <l>Thou that canſt make my joyes eſſentiall,</l>
                              <l>Which are but ſhadowes now, be liberall,</l>
                              <l>And out-doe ſleepe, let me not dreame in vaine,</l>
                              <l>
                                 <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nleſſe thou mean'ſt I ne're ſhall ſleepe againe.</l>
                           </lg>
                        </q>
                        <l>Alas poore foole! will ſhe not let thee ſleepe?</l>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Hy.</speaker>
                        <l>I knew I ſhould be mock't, but I'le divert him;</l>
                        <l>What are theſe thou haſt brought along with thee?</l>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Mi.</speaker>
                        <l>The Maſquers, <hi>Hylas,</hi> theſe are they muſt trip it</l>
                        <l>Before the King: doſt like their properties?</l>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Hy.</speaker>
                        <p>What <hi>Paris,</hi> and <hi>Oenone,</hi> the old ſtorie?</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Mi.</speaker>
                        <l>But newly made, and faſhion'd to my purpoſe;</l>
                        <l>Brought hither to make good my owne poſitions</l>
                        <l>Againſt the company of puling lovers;</l>
                        <l>Which if I doe not, and with good effect,</l>
                        <l>Let me be one my ſelfe; and that's a torture</l>
                        <l>Worſe then <hi>Apollo</hi> laid upon the Satyr,</l>
                        <l>When the rude villaine durſt contend with him:</l>
                        <l>Looke this way <hi>Hylas,</hi> ſee <hi>Oenone</hi> here,</l>
                        <l>The faireſt Nymph that ever <hi>Ida</hi> bleſt,</l>
                        <l>Court her departing ſhepheard, who is now</l>
                        <l>Turning his loue unto a fairer object;</l>
                        <l>
                           <pb facs="tcp:16779:28"/>And for his judgement in varietie</l>
                        <l>See how the ſeaborne Goddeſſe, and the Graces</l>
                        <l>Preſent their darling <hi>Helena</hi> to him.</l>
                        <l>Be happy in thy choiſe, and draw a war</l>
                        <l>On thee, and thine, rather then ſet thy heart</l>
                        <l>Upon a ſtale delight: Do, let her weepe,</l>
                        <l>And ſay thou art inconſtant. Be ſo ſtill;</l>
                        <l>The Queene of love commands it: you that are</l>
                        <l>The old companions of your <hi>Paris</hi> here,</l>
                        <l>Moue in a well pac'd meaſure, that may ſhew</l>
                        <l>The Goddeſſe, how you are content for her</l>
                        <l>Faire ſake to leave the honor of your woods:</l>
                        <l>But firſt let her, and all the Graces ſing</l>
                        <l>The Invitation to your offering.</l>
                     </sp>
                     <stage>
                        <hi>Venus,</hi> and the Graces ſing.</stage>
                     <sp>
                        <lg type="song">
                           <lg>
                              <l>COme lovely boy unto my Court,</l>
                              <l>And leave theſe uncouth woods, and all</l>
                              <l>That feed thy fancy with loves gall,</l>
                              <l>But keepe away the honey, and the ſport.</l>
                              <l>
                                 <hi>Cho.</hi> Come unto me,</l>
                              <l>And with varietie</l>
                              <l>Thou ſhalt be fed, which Nature loves, and I.</l>
                           </lg>
                           <lg n="2">
                              <head>2.</head>
                              <l>There is no Muſique in a voice,</l>
                              <l>That is but one, and ſtill the ſame.</l>
                              <l>Inconſtancy is but a name,</l>
                              <l>
                                 <pb facs="tcp:16779:29"/>To fright poore lovers from a better choice.</l>
                              <l>
                                 <hi>Cho.</hi> Come then to me, &amp;c.</l>
                           </lg>
                           <lg n="3">
                              <head>3</head>
                              <l>
                                 <hi>Orpheus,</hi> that on <hi>Euridice</hi>
                              </l>
                              <l>Spent all his love, on others ſcorne,</l>
                              <l>Now on the bankes of <hi>Heber</hi> torne,</l>
                              <l>Findes the reward of fooliſh conſtancy.</l>
                              <l>
                                 <hi>Cho.</hi> Come then to me, &amp;c.</l>
                           </lg>
                           <lg n="4">
                              <head>4</head>
                              <l>And ſigh no more for one love loſt,</l>
                              <l>I have a thouſand <hi>Cupids</hi> here,</l>
                              <l>Shall recompence with better cheere</l>
                              <l>Thy miſ-ſpent labours, and thy bitter coſt.</l>
                              <l>
                                 <hi>Cho.</hi> Come then to me, &amp;c.</l>
                           </lg>
                        </lg>
                     </sp>
                     <stage>The Dance ended.</stage>
                     <stage>Enter a Meſſenger.</stage>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Nun.</speaker>
                        <l>Shepheards, if you have any pittie, come,</l>
                        <l>And ſee a woefull ſpectacle.</l>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Mi.</speaker>
                        <l>What is't</l>
                        <l>That can be worth the breaking of our ſports?</l>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Nun.</speaker>
                        <p>The gentle Nymph <hi>Nerina.</hi>
                        </p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Hy.</speaker>
                        <p>What of her?</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Nun.</speaker>
                        <l>The laſt of her I thinke, ſhe lies a dying,</l>
                        <l>And calls to ſpeake with you.</l>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Hy.</speaker>
                        <l>Curſe of your follies;</l>
                        <l>
                           <pb facs="tcp:16779:29"/>Do I live here whilſt ſhe is dying there?</l>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Mi.</speaker>
                        <l>But ſhepheard, what diſeaſe is't that ſo ſoone</l>
                        <l>Could ſpend his force upon her? ſhe was well</l>
                        <l>This morning, when ſhe made poore <hi>Hylas</hi> ſicke.</l>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Mun.</speaker>
                        <l>I know not, I am ſent unto the well</l>
                        <l>Of <hi>Aeſculapius</hi> to fetch ſome water</l>
                        <l>For her recovery. I muſt be gone.</l>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Mi.</speaker>
                        <l>Shepheards here let us end. I thinke we are</l>
                        <l>Perfect in all the reſt: This night the King</l>
                        <l>Muſt ſee't, reſolve on that.</l>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Cho.</speaker>
                        <p>We are all ready.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Mi.</speaker>
                        <l>Then lets away, and ſee what will betide</l>
                        <l>This gentle Nymph <hi>Nerina.</hi>
                        </l>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Cho.</speaker>
                        <p>We'le goe with you.</p>
                     </sp>
                  </div>
                  <div n="4" type="scene">
                     <head>SCENA. 4.</head>
                     <stage>Charinus, Nerina, Dorinda, Hylas, Mirtillus, Nuntius.</stage>
                     <l>HOld up thy head good childe, ſee he is come;</l>
                     <l>Bring me the water quickly, whilſt there is</l>
                     <l>Some life in her: now chafe her good <hi>Dorinda.</hi>
                     </l>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Ne.</speaker>
                        <l>All is in vaine, I cannot live; deare father</l>
                        <l>Farewell: what ſhepheard's that lies on the ground?</l>
                        <l>Is it not <hi>Hylas?</hi>
                        </l>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Do.</speaker>
                        <p>Yes, it is he, <hi>Nerina.</hi>
                        </p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Ne.</speaker>
                        <l>Alas poore ſhepheard, tis my greateſt griefe,</l>
                        <l>
                           <pb facs="tcp:16779:30"/>That I have grieved him, I would beg life</l>
                        <l>For nothing but to make him ſatisfaction.</l>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Mi.</speaker>
                        <l>
                           <hi>Hylas,</hi> what on the ground? looke up and ſpeake</l>
                        <l>Alas, he's dead.</l>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Ne.</speaker>
                        <l>It cannot be: good father</l>
                        <l>Let me goe to him, and but touch his eare,</l>
                        <l>It may be that my voice may have more vertue.</l>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Cha.</speaker>
                        <l>Do what thou wilt ſweete heart: ſee my poore child</l>
                        <l>How charitable ſhe is, being halfe dead</l>
                        <l>Her ſelfe, ſhe pities others.</l>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Ni.</speaker>
                        <l>Marke her fineneſſe,</l>
                        <l>Now at the brimm of death: ſhe kiſſes him:</l>
                        <l>And tooke this way to mock her ſimple father;</l>
                        <l>O fine invention! ſure a womans wit,</l>
                        <l>Does never faile her.</l>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Ne.</speaker>
                        <l>
                           <hi>Hylas, Hylas,</hi> ſpeake,</l>
                        <l>
                           <hi>Nerina</hi> calls thee; ſpeake to thy <hi>Nerina.</hi>
                        </l>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Mi.</speaker>
                        <l>What cannot love doe? It revives the dead,</l>
                        <l>He's come to himſelfe againe.</l>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Hy.</speaker>
                        <l>What God is it,</l>
                        <l>That has the power to returne my ſoule</l>
                        <l>From the <hi>Elyſian</hi> fields?</l>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Mi.</speaker>
                        <l>It is no God,</l>
                        <l>A Goddeſſe rather, <hi>Hylas.</hi> 'Tis <hi>Nerina,</hi>
                        </l>
                        <l>Looke where ſhe is.</l>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Hy.</speaker>
                        <l>Ah then I do not wonder</l>
                        <l>I cannot die, when my beſt ſoule comes to me:</l>
                        <l>Shall wee live ever thus?</l>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <pb facs="tcp:16779:30"/>
                        <speaker>Ne.</speaker>
                        <l>How faine I would</l>
                        <l>Forthy ſake, <hi>Hylas,</hi> but it cannot be:</l>
                        <l>I feele a heavy ſleepe ſit on my head,</l>
                        <l>And my ſtrength failes me, helpe me ſweet <hi>Dorinda,</hi>
                        </l>
                        <l>Farewell for ever: oh I die, I die.</l>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Hy.</speaker>
                        <l>And muſt I then be call'd to life againe,</l>
                        <l>To ſee my life expire before my face?</l>
                        <l>You Fates, if you will take a ranſome for her,</l>
                        <l>Then take my life: but you are ſure of that</l>
                        <l>Youle ſay already: for in her one death</l>
                        <l>Two lives are forfeit: <hi>Nerina,</hi> gentle Nymph,</l>
                        <l>The cauſe why now I live, open theſe eyes</l>
                        <l>Once more, and I ſhall flouriſh like thoſe plants</l>
                        <l>The ſunne gives life to: elſe I fall, and wither,</l>
                        <l>Leaving behinde naught but a worthleſſe ſtemme:</l>
                        <l>Speake to thy <hi>Hylas,</hi> ſweete <hi>Nerina,</hi> ſpeake.</l>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Cha.</speaker>
                        <l>Ay me! my daughter, hadſt thou liv'd, perhaps,</l>
                        <l>I might have ſeene thee married to <hi>Daphnis,</hi>
                        </l>
                        <l>Now we muſt ſee thee buried: Ay me!</l>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Ne.</speaker>
                        <p>
                           <hi>Hylas.</hi>
                        </p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Hy.</speaker>
                        <l>She lives, give me ſome more of that,</l>
                        <l>That water there, ſee now ſhe comes againe:</l>
                        <l>O gentle deſtinies, but ſpare this thred,</l>
                        <l>And cut a thouſand courſer, ſpeake <hi>Nerina,</hi>
                        </l>
                        <l>Give me ſome comfort, give thy father ſome,</l>
                        <l>Or elſe behold three lives fall in thy death.</l>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Ne.</speaker>
                        <l>You Fates, that keepe th' accompt of all our daies,</l>
                        <l>Adde but one minute to my life, that I</l>
                        <l>
                           <pb facs="tcp:16779:31"/>May quit my ſoule of thoſe two heavy burthens</l>
                        <l>Which now oppreſſe it: Dry your eyes good father,</l>
                        <l>Remember that the Gods doe ſend us nothing</l>
                        <l>But for our good; and if my journey be</l>
                        <l>Shorter then yours, the leſſe will be my trouble:</l>
                        <l>Will you forgive me father, that I have not</l>
                        <l>Paid ſo much duty to you; as I ow'd you:</l>
                        <l>Take my good will, I pray, inſteed of it.</l>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Cha.</speaker>
                        <l>See her good Nature: I childe, 'tis enough,</l>
                        <l>Thou alwaies wert obedient.</l>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Ne.</speaker>
                        <l>Shall I dare</l>
                        <l>To ſpeake my thoughts, and ſo diſcharge my ſoule</l>
                        <l>Of one loade yet?</l>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Cha.</speaker>
                        <p>I, doe my childe, ſpeake freely.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Ne.</speaker>
                        <l>I've heard you ſay, that no ſinne was ſo heavy</l>
                        <l>As is ingratitude.</l>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Cha.</speaker>
                        <l>'Tis true, <hi>Nerina,</hi>
                        </l>
                        <l>How ſhe remembers what her father ſaid!</l>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Ne.</speaker>
                        <l>Then be not angry, if I now muſt tell you,</l>
                        <l>That this poore ſhepheard, whoſe ſwolne eyes you ſee</l>
                        <l>Cover'd with teares, for many yeares now paſt</l>
                        <l>Has courted me: but ſtill with ſuch a love,</l>
                        <l>So full of truth and gentle ſervices,</l>
                        <l>That ſhould I not requite him with my love,</l>
                        <l>I ſhould be guilty of ingratitude:</l>
                        <l>Therefore before I die, ſpray give leave</l>
                        <l>That he may have my dying heart, which living,</l>
                        <l>I ſtill debar'd him of. <hi>Hylas,</hi> thy hand.</l>
                        <l>
                           <pb facs="tcp:16779:31"/>O ſtay a little death: here, take thou mine,</l>
                        <l>And ſince I cannot live the wife of <hi>Hylas,</hi>
                        </l>
                        <l>Yet let me die ſo: Sir, are you content?</l>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Cha.</speaker>
                        <p>I am, with any thing that pleaſeth thee.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Ne.</speaker>
                        <p>Tell me, are you ſo <hi>Hylas?</hi>
                        </p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Hy.</speaker>
                        <l>O my love,</l>
                        <l>Aske me if I would live amongſt the Gods,</l>
                        <l>But aske not this: Sir, have we your conſent?</l>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Cha.</speaker>
                        <l>You have, it is in vaine now to denie it:</l>
                        <l>You ſee, <hi>Dorinda,</hi> what her vow's come to.</l>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Ne.</speaker>
                        <l>Then let me die, take me into thy Armes,</l>
                        <l>Sweet love, you'le ſee my coffin ſtrew'd with flowers,</l>
                        <l>And you <hi>Dorinda,</hi> will you make a garland?</l>
                        <l>I die a virgine, though I die his wife.</l>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Do.</speaker>
                        <p>Alas, ſhe's gon.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Hy.</speaker>
                        <p>She's dead, and do I live?</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Cha.</speaker>
                        <p>Looke to the ſhepheard there: oh my <hi>Nerina!</hi>
                        </p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Do.</speaker>
                        <l>Vexe not her ſoule, I pray, with often calling,</l>
                        <l>You ſee ſhe's dead.</l>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Cha.</speaker>
                        <l>Then there is no hope left:</l>
                        <l>Pray helpe us ſhepheards now to beare her hence;</l>
                        <l>You'le come I hope to ſee her in her grave.</l>
                     </sp>
                  </div>
               </div>
               <div n="4" type="act">
                  <head>ACT. 4.</head>
                  <div n="1" type="scene">
                     <head>SCENA 1.</head>
                     <stage>Thyrſis, Delia.</stage>
                     <l>HEre I am come unto a place, where griefe</l>
                     <l>
                        <pb facs="tcp:16779:32"/>They ſay has no abode. In Princes Courts,</l>
                     <l>I've heard there is no roome for loves laments:</l>
                     <l>For either they enjoy, or elſe forget,</l>
                     <l>Thrice happy men, to whom love gives ſuch leave:</l>
                     <l>It may be that this place, or people may</l>
                     <l>Worke ſo with me, and melt this frozen heart:</l>
                     <l>Ah foole, that canſt beleeve the change of place,</l>
                     <l>Or ayre, can change thy minde; the love thou bearſt,</l>
                     <l>Is woven ſo within thy thoughts, that as</l>
                     <l>Out of this piece thy <hi>Sylvia</hi> wrought for thee,</l>
                     <l>Thou canſt not take her name forth, but withall</l>
                     <l>Thou muſt deface the whole: ſo <hi>Thyrſis</hi> thinke</l>
                     <l>The winde that here may riſe, or heat, or raine</l>
                     <l>Thou maiſt auoide, thy love will ſtill remaine,</l>
                     <l>And when thou dieſt, then may it die with thee;</l>
                     <l>Till then reſolve to endure thy miſery.</l>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Del.</speaker>
                        <l>This is the garden, which I ſaw him go to,</l>
                        <l>And that is he, for all the markes ſhe gave me</l>
                        <l>To know him by, he beares.</l>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Thy.</speaker>
                        <l>A heavineſſe</l>
                        <l>Weighs downe my head, and would invite me to</l>
                        <l>Repoſe my ſelfe; Ile take the offer, here</l>
                        <l>Ile reſt awhile, for I have need of it.</l>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Del.</speaker>
                        <l>How if I be deceiv'd, and this ſhould proove</l>
                        <l>Another man: what then? I can excuſe it;</l>
                        <l>He's layd already, and I feare, aſleepe,</l>
                        <l>Ile ſtay untill he wake, but then ſuppoſe</l>
                        <l>That any body come, and take me here,</l>
                        <l>
                           <pb facs="tcp:16779:32"/>What will they thinke of me? Beſt wake him: ſhepheard:</l>
                        <l>It is a hanſome youth, ſee what a grace</l>
                        <l>Shewes it ſelfe in his feature, ſuch a face</l>
                        <l>Might take the heart of any Lady living,</l>
                        <l>I, though ſhe were a Princeſſe: ſhepheard: what</l>
                        <l>Not yet? his ſleepes are ſound.</l>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Thy.</speaker>
                        <l>Ah <hi>Sylvia,</hi>
                        </l>
                        <l>Preſerve thy life, oh let me die; Alas</l>
                        <l>I do but dreame; me thought I ſaw my ſelfe</l>
                        <l>Condemn'd to die, and <hi>Sylvia</hi> to ſave me,</l>
                        <l>Offerd her ſelfe, and would needs die for me:</l>
                        <l>'Twas a ſweet ſhadow, let me court this dreame.</l>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Del.</speaker>
                        <p>He muſt not ſleepe againe: ſhepheard looke up.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Thy.</speaker>
                        <l>Who envies me this ſmall repoſe, indeed</l>
                        <l>I do not often ſleepe; ha, who are you?</l>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Del.</speaker>
                        <l>Sent to thee, from thy <hi>Sylvia,</hi> ſhepheard riſe</l>
                        <l>And follow me.</l>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Thy.</speaker>
                        <l>Doe I dreame ſtill? what are you?</l>
                        <l>Came you from heaven where my <hi>Sylvia</hi> is,</l>
                        <l>And muſt I thither? whoſo ere you are,</l>
                        <l>An Angell, or a feind, in ſuch a name</l>
                        <l>You come, as I'me conjurd to follow you:</l>
                        <l>But I muſt die firſt: Here is to be with thee.</l>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Del.</speaker>
                        <l>Stay, hold thy hand, I live, thy <hi>Sylvia</hi> lives</l>
                        <l>To make thee happy, if thou wilt goe to her.</l>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Thy.</speaker>
                        <l>You're habited like thoſe I've ſeene at Court,</l>
                        <l>And courtiſie they ſay is ever there,</l>
                        <l>Yet mingled with deceit: if you do meane</l>
                        <l>
                           <pb facs="tcp:16779:33"/>T'abuſe me for your ſport, this way will prove</l>
                        <l>Too ſad to raiſe mirth out of. There's no ill</l>
                        <l>That I have done to you, or any elſe,</l>
                        <l>Unleſſe my conſtancy be here a ſinne.</l>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Del.</speaker>
                        <l>His griefes have made him wilde, I have no time</l>
                        <l>Left me to uſe perſwaſions, or to make</l>
                        <l>This truth apparant to you; on my word</l>
                        <l>You ſhall be ſafe, and if you dare beleeve me,</l>
                        <l>Ile bring you where your love is; follow me.</l>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Thy.</speaker>
                        <l>Why ſhould I doubt, or feare to goe with her?</l>
                        <l>Ill does he call for phyſicke, whom the Law</l>
                        <l>Has doom'd to die: There's no condition</l>
                        <l>Can prove worſe to me then my preſent one.</l>
                        <l>Pray lead me where you pleaſe, I'me ſure of this,</l>
                        <l>To one that's deſperate, no way's amiſſe.</l>
                     </sp>
                  </div>
                  <div n="2" type="scene">
                     <head>SCENA 2.</head>
                     <stage>Euarchus, Eubulus, Cleander, Attendants.</stage>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Ev.</speaker>
                        <l>ALl leave the roome. <hi>Eubulus,</hi> I'me reſolv'd</l>
                        <l>To hold an eaſier hand over my daughter</l>
                        <l>Then I was wont: Therefore I ſent <hi>Cleander</hi>
                        </l>
                        <l>To bring her to my preſence, though ſhe have</l>
                        <l>Wrong'd her great birth and breeding by her follies,</l>
                        <l>Yet I conſider that ſhe is my daughter,</l>
                        <l>And this reſtraint cannot but harden her</l>
                        <l>In her fond reſolutions: have you ſought</l>
                        <l>
                           <pb facs="tcp:16779:33"/>By all the meanes you can to ſift the cauſe</l>
                        <l>Of her departure?</l>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Eub.</speaker>
                        <l>Sir, I have tryed,</l>
                        <l>By all the waies that fit a ſubject, to</l>
                        <l>Enquire a truth of one that is his Princeſſe.</l>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Eu.</speaker>
                        <p>And what have you diſcover'd?</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Eub.</speaker>
                        <l>Nothing more</l>
                        <l>Then what my ſon <hi>Cleander</hi> did before.</l>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Eu.</speaker>
                        <l>I have heard his relation: but I wonder</l>
                        <l>How for a whole moneths time, ſhe ſhould abide</l>
                        <l>Within our confines, when ſo great a ſearch,</l>
                        <l>Through all our Countryes, and lowd proclamations</l>
                        <l>Were made for her recovery.</l>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Eub.</speaker>
                        <l>Tis true.</l>
                        <l>She herein was ingenuous, and confeſt,</l>
                        <l>That ſhe foreſaw what ſearch would be made for her,</l>
                        <l>Therefore with ſome about her ſhe had plotted,</l>
                        <l>To hire a barke, that might convey her hence,</l>
                        <l>In a diſguiſe to <hi>Smyrna,</hi> where ſhe ſtayd,</l>
                        <l>Till time did fit her; that with ſafety</l>
                        <l>She might returne in habite of a Nymph,</l>
                        <l>Unto the place, where then <hi>Cleander</hi> found her:</l>
                        <l>But why ſhe left the Court, ſhe will not tell.</l>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Eu.</speaker>
                        <l>I will not force her to't: ſome little time</l>
                        <l>Perhaps may make diſcovery of that ſecret:</l>
                        <l>But unto thee my faithfull Counſellor.</l>
                        <l>(As unto one my heart hath ſtill bin open)</l>
                        <l>I will diſcover what my purpoſe is,</l>
                        <l>
                           <pb facs="tcp:16779:34"/>In ſending for theſe ſhepheards to my Court.</l>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Eub.</speaker>
                        <l>I ſhould beleeve, they' reſent for to delight</l>
                        <l>Your Majeſty, as they were wont.</l>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Eu.</speaker>
                        <l>No <hi>Eubulus,</hi>
                        </l>
                        <l>But for a greater end; I feare my daughter,</l>
                        <l>And therefore I have ſent for her to ſee</l>
                        <l>Theſe ſports, with purpoſe to obſerve her lookes,</l>
                        <l>For I ſuſpect ſhe loves ſome ſhepheard there.</l>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Eub.</speaker>
                        <l>It cannot be: ſhe will not ſtaine her birth</l>
                        <l>With ſuch ignoble love; yet I confeſſe,</l>
                        <l>Revolving all the cauſes of her ſtrange</l>
                        <l>Departure, I could fixe on none but that.</l>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Eub.</speaker>
                        <l>Well, if ſhe do ſo, I will let her forth,</l>
                        <l>Forth of my blood, and whoſoere he be</l>
                        <l>Whoſe fortune markt him out to be the object</l>
                        <l>Of this her love, ſhall finde <hi>Ixions</hi> Fate,</l>
                        <l>He ſhall embrace a ſhadow; by my life</l>
                        <l>They both ſhall die.</l>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Eub.</speaker>
                        <l>O my gracious Lord,</l>
                        <l>Remember ſhe's your daughter.</l>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Eu.</speaker>
                        <l>I, thou ſtill</l>
                        <l>Doſt plead for her, but yet am I her King</l>
                        <l>As well as father, private men reſpect</l>
                        <l>Their profits, and their private intereſts</l>
                        <l>Of kindred, but the actions of a King,</l>
                        <l>To honor, and renowne muſt be directed:
<stage>Cleander enters.</stage>
                        </l>
                        <l>Conſider that, and then thou wilt forget her.</l>
                        <l>
                           <hi>Cleander,</hi> welcome, how does <hi>Calligone?</hi>
                        </l>
                        <l>
                           <pb facs="tcp:16779:34"/>Is ſhe not glad to come unto our preſence?</l>
                        <l>Why doſt not anſwere? art thou frighted man?</l>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Cle.</speaker>
                        <l>I know not how to anſwere any thing,</l>
                        <l>Unleſſe your Majeſty will ſigne my pardon.</l>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Eu.</speaker>
                        <p>Why what's the matter, ſpeake, and ſpeak it freely</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Cle.</speaker>
                        <l>Then know great ſoveraigne that when I went</l>
                        <l>As full of joy, as ſpeed, with your glad meſſage,</l>
                        <l>I found the Princeſſe.</l>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Eu.</speaker>
                        <p>What, not dead, I hope?</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Cle.</speaker>
                        <p>Dead to her honor.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Eu.</speaker>
                        <p>Ha!</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Cle.</speaker>
                        <l>In ſhort my Lord,</l>
                        <l>I found her walking in the garden with</l>
                        <l>A ſhepheard, (more of him I cannot tell)</l>
                        <l>But ſhe was habited in that attire</l>
                        <l>She wore, when from the woods I brought her home,</l>
                        <l>I ſlipt away, not being ſeene by them,</l>
                        <l>And if you pleaſe to goe, perhaps great Sir,</l>
                        <l>You ſtill may finde them there.</l>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Eu.</speaker>
                        <l>How now <hi>Eubulus,</hi>
                        </l>
                        <l>Are my preſages true? ſhall I then ſleepe</l>
                        <l>With this diſgrace, and let my neighbour Princes</l>
                        <l>Mocke at my humble fortunes, when they heare</l>
                        <l>The daughter of <hi>Euarchus</hi> matcht her ſelfe</l>
                        <l>With a baſe ſhepheard? Goe <hi>Eubulus</hi> quickly,</l>
                        <l>Here take my ſignet, let this be your warrant</l>
                        <l>To put them both to death.</l>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Eub.</speaker>
                        <p>How? both my Lord?</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <pb facs="tcp:16779:35"/>
                        <speaker>Eu.</speaker>
                        <p>I, both.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Eub.</speaker>
                        <p>Your daughter too?</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Eu.</speaker>
                        <l>Why do you queſtion me?</l>
                        <l>Haue I not ſaid they both ſhall die: diſpatch.</l>
                        <l>Let me not ſee thee, till they both be dead.
<stage>Exit.</stage>
                        </l>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Eub.</speaker>
                        <l>What haſt thou done? thou raſh inhumane boy?</l>
                        <l>Depriv'd thy father of a childe, thy ſelfe</l>
                        <l>Of thine owne ſiſter, whom but now thou knewſt.</l>
                        <l>Well may the King take that deare life away,</l>
                        <l>Which he did never give: I will goe tell him,</l>
                        <l>I am her father: but I looſe my life</l>
                        <l>If I do that, as guilty of a treaſon.</l>
                        <l>Go Murderer, hadſt thou no pittie in thee?</l>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Cle.</speaker>
                        <l>Sir I do feele ſo much of griefe within me,</l>
                        <l>For this my act, that if my blood will ſerve</l>
                        <l>To ſave her life, Ile make no price of it:</l>
                        <l>Yet could I not imagine, that the King</l>
                        <l>Would have bin ſo inrag'd; or if he would,</l>
                        <l>I had no time to thinke of it before.</l>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Eu.</speaker>
                        <l>No time? who bid thee haſten to the ruine</l>
                        <l>Of thy poore father, and thy family?</l>
                        <l>The meſſages which come to do us hurt,</l>
                        <l>Are ſpeedy: but the good come ſlowly on,</l>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Cle.</speaker>
                        <l>But Sir, remember what a ſtraight we're in:</l>
                        <l>It will concerne us, to invent ſome way</l>
                        <l>To ſave my ſiſter, though the ſhepheard die;</l>
                        <l>He will deſerve it for his bold attempt.</l>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Eub.</speaker>
                        <l>Go take thy way, whither thou wilt thy ſelfe,</l>
                        <l>
                           <pb facs="tcp:16779:35"/>That way is beſt, which leads me to my grave.
<stage>Exit.</stage>
                        </l>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Cle.</speaker>
                        <l>What luck is this? This is more haſte then ſpeed:</l>
                        <l>I am reſolv'd (though my life lie at ſtake)</l>
                        <l>To ſtand the fury of th'inraged King:</l>
                        <l>Who knowes but he may be as ſorry for</l>
                        <l>His ſuddaine act, as I for mine. 'Tis here</l>
                        <l>To ſave her, though it coſt her lover deare.</l>
                     </sp>
                  </div>
                  <div n="3" type="scene">
                     <head>SCENA 3.</head>
                     <stage>Sylvia, Thyrſis, Cleander.</stage>
                     <l>NAy ſtay a little <hi>Thyrſis,</hi> we are ſafe,</l>
                     <l>My warie keepers now are with the King.</l>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Thy.</speaker>
                        <l>Madam, for my poore ſelfe I doe not feare,</l>
                        <l>But when I thinke on you, and how your name,</l>
                        <l>And ſtate that is ſo eminent, muſt needs</l>
                        <l>Receive a certaine ſcandall, and foule blot,</l>
                        <l>If we be ſeene together, blame me not,</l>
                        <l>Though I do feare or doubt: What cruell fate</l>
                        <l>Angry with men, that gave us hearts alike,</l>
                        <l>And fortunes ſo aſunder; you're a Cedar,</l>
                        <l>I a poore ſhrub, that may looke up unto you</l>
                        <l>With adoration, but ne're reach your height.</l>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Syl.</speaker>
                        <l>But <hi>Thyrſis</hi> I do love you; love and death</l>
                        <l>Do not much differ, they make all things equall:</l>
                        <l>The Monuments of Kings may ſhew for them</l>
                        <l>What they have bin, but looke upon their duſt,</l>
                        <l>
                           <pb facs="tcp:16779:36"/>The color, and the weight of theirs, and beggers,</l>
                        <l>You'le finde the ſame: and if 'mongſt living men</l>
                        <l>Nature has printed in the face of many,</l>
                        <l>The characters of nobleneſſe and worth,</l>
                        <l>Whoſe fortune envies them a worthy place,</l>
                        <l>In birth, or honor. When the greateſt men</l>
                        <l>Whom ſhe has courted, beare the marks of ſlaves,</l>
                        <l>Love ſure will looke on thoſe, and lay aſide</l>
                        <l>The Accidents of wealth and noble blood,</l>
                        <l>And in our thoughts wil equall them with Kings.</l>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Thy.</speaker>
                        <l>'Tis true divineſt Lady, that the ſoules</l>
                        <l>Of all men are alike, of the ſame ſubſtance</l>
                        <l>By the ſame maker into all infus'd,</l>
                        <l>But yet the ſeverall matters which they worke on,</l>
                        <l>How different they are I neede not tell you:</l>
                        <l>And as theſe outward Organs give our ſoules</l>
                        <l>Or more, or leſſe roome, as they are contriv'd,</l>
                        <l>To ſhew their luſtre; ſo againe comes fortune,</l>
                        <l>And darkens them, to whom the Gods have given</l>
                        <l>A ſoule divine, and body capable</l>
                        <l>Of that divinity, and excellence:</l>
                        <l>But 'tis the order of the Fates, whoſe cauſes</l>
                        <l>We muſt not looke into: But you deare Madam,</l>
                        <l>Nature, and fortune have conſpir'd to make</l>
                        <l>The happieſt alive.</l>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Syl.</speaker>
                        <l>Ay me moſt wretched!</l>
                        <l>What pleaſure can there be in higheſt ſtate,</l>
                        <l>Which is ſo croſt in love, the greateſt good,</l>
                        <l>
                           <pb facs="tcp:16779:36"/>The Gods can tell how to beſtow on men?</l>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Thy.</speaker>
                        <l>Yet ſome do reckon it the greateſt ill,</l>
                        <l>A paſſion of the minde, form'd in the fancy,</l>
                        <l>And bred to be the worſt diſeaſe of reaſon.</l>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Syl.</speaker>
                        <l>They that thinke ſo, are ſuch as love excludes,</l>
                        <l>Men full of age, or foule deformitie.</l>
                        <l>No <hi>Thyrſis,</hi> let not us prophane that deity:</l>
                        <l>Love is divine, the ſeed of every thing,</l>
                        <l>The cauſe why now we live, and all the world.</l>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Thy.</speaker>
                        <l>Love is divine, for if religion</l>
                        <l>Binds us to love, the Gods who never yet</l>
                        <l>Reveald themſelves in any thing to us</l>
                        <l>But their bright Images, the faireſt creatures,</l>
                        <l>Who are our daily objects; loving them,</l>
                        <l>Wee exerciſe religion: let us not</l>
                        <l>Be ſcrupulous, or feare; the Gods have care</l>
                        <l>Of us, and of our piety.</l>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Syl.</speaker>
                        <l>But take heed,</l>
                        <l>We cannot be too warie: many things</l>
                        <l>Oppoſe our wills, yet if you thinke it fit,</l>
                        <l>And this nights ſilence will ſo favour us,</l>
                        <l>Weele goe together: if we quit this Countrie,</l>
                        <l>It is no matter, all the world to me</l>
                        <l>Will be <hi>Arcadia,</hi> if I may injoy</l>
                        <l>Thy company, my love.</l>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Thy.</speaker>
                        <l>No <hi>Sylvia,</hi>
                        </l>
                        <l>(Pardon mee deare, if ſtill I call you ſo)</l>
                        <l>Enjoy your fortunes, thinke how much your honor</l>
                        <l>
                           <pb facs="tcp:16779:37"/>Muſt ſuffer in this act: For me I finde,</l>
                        <l>It is enough that I have ever lov'd you:</l>
                        <l>Now let me at the light of your bright eie,</l>
                        <l>Burne like the bird whoſe fires renew her neſt,</l>
                        <l>I ſhall leave you behind me to the world,</l>
                        <l>The Phenix of true love and conſtancy:</l>
                        <l>Nor is that bird more glorious in her flames,</l>
                        <l>Then I ſhall be in mine, though they conſume me.</l>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Syl.</speaker>
                        <l>It muſt not be, for know my deareſt ſhepheard,</l>
                        <l>I ſhall not tell one minute after thee;</l>
                        <l>I finde my ſoule ſo linkt to thine, that death</l>
                        <l>Cannot divide us.</l>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Thy.</speaker>
                        <l>What then ſhall we do?</l>
                        <l>Shall we reſolve to live thus, till we gaze</l>
                        <l>Our eies out firſt, and then loſe all our ſenſes</l>
                        <l>In their ſucceſſion? ſhall we ſtrive to leave</l>
                        <l>Our ſoules breath'd forth upon each others lips?</l>
                        <l>Come let us practiſe: this our envious Fates</l>
                        <l>Cannot deny us.
<stage>Cleander enters.</stage>
                        </l>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Cle.</speaker>
                        <l>What a ſight were this</l>
                        <l>To meete her father? This would make him mad</l>
                        <l>Indeed, and execute his rage himſelfe.</l>
                        <l>Madam, your father's here.</l>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Syl.</speaker>
                        <l>Ha <hi>Delia!</hi>
                        </l>
                        <l>
                           <hi>Cleander,</hi> is it thou? then I'me betraid</l>
                        <l>The ſecond time, but muſt thy fortune make thee</l>
                        <l>The inſtrument of my undoing ſtill?</l>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Cla.</speaker>
                        <l>Shepheard, I will not honor thee ſo much</l>
                        <l>
                           <pb facs="tcp:16779:37"/>As to enquire thy name) thou haſt don that</l>
                        <l>Thou wilt pay deare for: And I hope thy death</l>
                        <l>Will take away the blot of this diſgrace</l>
                        <l>Th'haſt laid upon the Princeſſe.</l>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Thy.</speaker>
                        <l>If you do this,</l>
                        <l>Youle make me happy, it was this I lookt for,</l>
                        <l>My triviall acts of life, this of my death</l>
                        <l>Will recompence with glory; I ſhall die</l>
                        <l>To ſave my Princeſſe, and whats more, to ſave</l>
                        <l>The life of her life, her unſpotted honor.</l>
                        <l>Bleſt Lady, though you are as innocent</l>
                        <l>And chaſte as pureſt Virgins, that have yet</l>
                        <l>Seene nothing in a dreame to warme their blood,</l>
                        <l>Yet the malicious world, the cenſuring people,</l>
                        <l>That haſte to caſt durt on the faireſt things,</l>
                        <l>Will hardly ſpare you, if it once be knowne</l>
                        <l>That we were here together: As for me,</l>
                        <l>My life is nothing but variety</l>
                        <l>Of griefe and troubles, which with conſtancy</l>
                        <l>I have borne yet: tis time that now I die,</l>
                        <l>Before I do accuſe the Gods that have</l>
                        <l>Brought me to this, and ſo pull on my death</l>
                        <l>A puniſhment. Will you be mercifull,</l>
                        <l>And end me quickly?</l>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Cle.</speaker>
                        <l>Shepheard, know for this</l>
                        <l>Thy reſolution, which in noble bloods</l>
                        <l>I ſcarce have found, I willingly would grant</l>
                        <l>What thou deſir'ſt. But ſomthing muſt be knowne</l>
                        <l>
                           <pb facs="tcp:16779:38"/>Before that time either from you, or you.</l>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Syl.</speaker>
                        <l>I know <hi>Cleander,</hi> it is me you aime at:</l>
                        <l>I do confeſſe this ſhepheard is my love;</l>
                        <l>For his ſake I did leave the Court, and thee,</l>
                        <l>Unworthy as thou art, to be his Rivall.</l>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Cle.</speaker>
                        <l>Madam, my duty bids me ſpeake to you,</l>
                        <l>Not as a lover now; but as you are</l>
                        <l>My Princeſſe, and the daughter of my King.</l>
                        <l>I would not for the world have thoſe deſires</l>
                        <l>Which I had then; for ſure my bolder love</l>
                        <l>Would have tranſgreſt the limits of all duty,</l>
                        <l>And would have dar'd to tell you, that this ſhepheard</l>
                        <l>Was not a match for great <hi>Arcadias</hi> heire,</l>
                        <l>Nor yet one fit for my Competitor.</l>
                        <l>'Tis not his outward feature, (which how faire</l>
                        <l>It is I do not queſtion) that can make him</l>
                        <l>Noble, or wiſe: Whereas my birth, deriv'd</l>
                        <l>From ancient Kings, and yeares not far unſuiting</l>
                        <l>Thoſe of your owne; to theſe my education</l>
                        <l>(To you well knowne,) perhaps might make me worthy</l>
                        <l>Of being your ſervant.</l>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Syl.</speaker>
                        <l>Canſt thou looke on this,</l>
                        <l>This piece <hi>Cleander,</hi> and not bluſh to boaſt</l>
                        <l>Thy follies thus, ſeeking to take away</l>
                        <l>From his full vertue, if but this one act</l>
                        <l>Of his appeare unto the world? (as know</l>
                        <l>It ſhall; for Ile not ſhame to publiſh him,</l>
                        <l>Though I die for it) will it not devoure</l>
                        <l>
                           <pb facs="tcp:16779:38"/>Thy empty glories, and thy puft up nothings,</l>
                        <l>And like a grave will burie all thy honors?</l>
                        <l>Do, take his life, and glory in that act,</l>
                        <l>But be thou ſure, in him thou ſhalt kill two.</l>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Cle.</speaker>
                        <p>What meane you, madam?</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Syl.</speaker>
                        <l>Not to live a minute,</l>
                        <l>After his death.</l>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Gle.</speaker>
                        <p>That all the Gods forbid.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Syl.</speaker>
                        <l>No, they command it rather, that have made</l>
                        <l>Our ſoules but one: <hi>Cleander,</hi> thou wert wont</l>
                        <l>To be more courteous; and I do ſee</l>
                        <l>Some pitie in thee: if not for pitties ſake,</l>
                        <l>Yet for thine owne good ſpare this life, and take</l>
                        <l>Mine; for thou knowſt, when I am dead, this kingdome</l>
                        <l>Thy father will inherit, or thy ſelfe.</l>
                        <l>Tis but the waiting of an old mans death,</l>
                        <l>Who cannot long out-live me: will you do't?</l>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Thy.</speaker>
                        <l>Sir, you are noble, I do ſee you are,</l>
                        <l>You lov'd this Lady once: by that dear love</l>
                        <l>(With me it was a conjuration</l>
                        <l>To draw my ſoule out, whilſt I was ſo happy)</l>
                        <l>I do beſeech you ſpare her noble life,</l>
                        <l>Her death will ſit full heavie on your ſoule,</l>
                        <l>And in your height of Kingly dignities</l>
                        <l>Diſturbe that head, which crownes will give no reſt to.</l>
                        <l>To take my life is juſtice.</l>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Syl.</speaker>
                        <l>Rather mine;</l>
                        <l>I have offended in firſt loving him,</l>
                        <l>
                           <pb facs="tcp:16779:39"/>And now betraying him unto his end.</l>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Thy.</speaker>
                        <l>Be not ſo cruell madam to your ſelfe</l>
                        <l>And me, to envy me a death ſo noble.</l>
                        <l>Sir, as you hope your love ſhall ever proſper,</l>
                        <l>Your great deſignes, your fights, (what ere they are)</l>
                        <l>As you do hope for peace in your laſt houre,</l>
                        <l>And that the earth may lightly cloath your aſhes,</l>
                        <l>Diſpatch me quickly, ſend me to my death.</l>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Cle.</speaker>
                        <l>A ſtrange contention! Madam will you pleaſe</l>
                        <l>A little to retire: Tis your honor</l>
                        <l>That I do ſtrive to ſave, as well as life:</l>
                        <l>Pray do not croſſe my purpoſe, I ſhall do</l>
                        <l>Something that you may thanke me for.</l>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Syl.</speaker>
                        <l>
                           <hi>Cleander,</hi>
                        </l>
                        <l>Save but the ſhepheard, and Ile crowne thy merit.</l>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Cle.</speaker>
                        <p>Will you be pleaſd to enter here?</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Syl.</speaker>
                        <l>But ſweare</l>
                        <l>That thou wilt ſave him.</l>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Cle.</speaker>
                        <l>I ſhall do my beſt,</l>
                        <l>I dare not ſweare, for tis not in my power</l>
                        <l>To do what you command.</l>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Syl.</speaker>
                        <l>But will you ſweare</l>
                        <l>To let me know of it before he die?</l>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Cle.</speaker>
                        <p>I will by heaven.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Syl.</speaker>
                        <l>Then I take my leave.</l>
                        <l>And <hi>Thyrſis</hi> be thou ſure, what ever Fate</l>
                        <l>Attends thy life, the ſame does governe mine:</l>
                        <l>One kiſſe I muſt not be deny'd.</l>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <pb facs="tcp:16779:39"/>
                        <speaker>Cle.</speaker>
                        <l>Fy Madam,</l>
                        <l>How low is this in you?</l>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Syl.</speaker>
                        <l>Then thus we part,</l>
                        <l>To meete againe, I hope.</l>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Thy.</speaker>
                        <l>Downe ſtubborne heart,</l>
                        <l>Wilt thou not breake yet? In my death I finde</l>
                        <l>Nothing that's terrible, but this Farewell</l>
                        <l>Preſents my ſoule with all the paines of hell.</l>
                     </sp>
                  </div>
                  <div n="4" type="scene">
                     <head>SCENA 4.</head>
                     <stage>Mirtillus, Chorus of ſhepheards.</stage>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>1 <hi>ſhep.</hi>
                        </speaker>
                        <p>I'me ſorry that this buſines went not forward.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>2 <hi>ſhep.</hi>
                        </speaker>
                        <p>So am not I, we're rid of ſo much trouble.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>2 <hi>ſhep.</hi>
                        </speaker>
                        <l>Yet it is ſtrange the King ſhould ſend for us,</l>
                        <l>And when we were come, command us to returne.</l>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Mi.</speaker>
                        <l>No, 'tis not ſtrange, it was his will to do ſo:</l>
                        <l>But if you have an itch of dancing, friends,</l>
                        <l>Next holy-day we'le ha't amongſt our ſelves,</l>
                        <l>And every man ſhall dance with his owne ſweetheart:</l>
                        <l>What ſay you ſhepheards, wil't not be as well?</l>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>1 <hi>ſhep.</hi>
                        </speaker>
                        <p>It will be very fine. But where is <hi>Thyrſis?</hi>
                        </p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>2. <hi>ſhep.</hi>
                        </speaker>
                        <l>I, where is he! you went along with him,</l>
                        <l>Where did you leave him?</l>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Mi.</speaker>
                        <l>Walking in a garden,</l>
                        <l>Where when I came to call him, he was gon.</l>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>2 <hi>ſhep.</hi>
                        </speaker>
                        <p>It ſeemes he cares not for our company.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <pb facs="tcp:16779:40"/>
                        <speaker>Mi.</speaker>
                        <p>Neither for yours nor any mans beſides.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>1 <hi>ſhep.</hi>
                        </speaker>
                        <l>He is much alter'd, ſince his love was loſt;</l>
                        <l>Methinks he is nothing like the man he was.</l>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Mi.</speaker>
                        <l>Well then beware my friends how you ingage</l>
                        <l>Your ſelves in love: He is a faire example,</l>
                        <l>And <hi>Hylas</hi> too, he's drooping for his miſtreſſe;</l>
                        <l>
                           <hi>Daphnis</hi> is mad, they ſay; if you have a minde</l>
                        <l>To die, or to runne mad, then be in love.</l>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>2 <hi>ſhep.</hi>
                        </speaker>
                        <p>See where he comes, in what a fume he is.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Mi.</speaker>
                        <p>I do not like his fumes: pray let's away.</p>
                     </sp>
                  </div>
                  <div n="5" type="scene">
                     <head>SCENA 5.</head>
                     <stage>Daphnis, to him Dorinda.</stage>
                     <l>HE will not now be found the Traitor: but</l>
                     <l>Where e're he be, nor heaven, nor hell ſhall ſave him</l>
                     <l>From my revenge. To take away the life</l>
                     <l>Of that ſweet innocent, without whoſe ſight</l>
                     <l>He knew I could not live, and to do this</l>
                     <l>Under the name of freindſhip: O you Gods,</l>
                     <l>What age can parallell ſo great a miſcheife?</l>
                     <l>This is his Magicke glaſſe, which had the vertue</l>
                     <l>To make her mine, but ſent her to the Gods.</l>
                     <l>Bleſt ſoule, I will revenge thy death, and then</l>
                     <l>Ile follow thee my ſelfe.</l>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Do.</speaker>
                        <l>
                           <hi>Daphnis,</hi> my love,</l>
                        <l>
                           <pb facs="tcp:16779:40"/>Whither ſo faſt?</l>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Da.</speaker>
                        <l>Now love deliver me;</l>
                        <l>And muſt you come to trouble me? Be gon;</l>
                        <l>I cannot ſtay to heare thy tedious follies.</l>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Do.</speaker>
                        <l>Were all your vowes then made but to abuſe me?</l>
                        <l>Are there not paines to puniſh perjur'd men?</l>
                        <l>And will they not ore'take you?</l>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Da.</speaker>
                        <l>'Las poore foole,</l>
                        <l>The Gods doe laugh at ſuch ſlight perjuries</l>
                        <l>As come from lovers.</l>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Do.</speaker>
                        <l>Yet it was no conqueſt</l>
                        <l>To deceive one that would be credulous,</l>
                        <l>A ſimple maide that lov'd you.</l>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Da.</speaker>
                        <l>Then I ſee.</l>
                        <l>There is no end of womens reaſoning;</l>
                        <l>Or elſe this might ſuffice thee, that I cannot</l>
                        <l>No nor I will not love thee.</l>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Do.</speaker>
                        <p>Never?</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Da.</speaker>
                        <p>Never.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Do.</speaker>
                        <l>Goe cruell man, and if the God of love</l>
                        <l>Will heare my prayers, thou in thy love ſhalt thrive,</l>
                        <l>As I in mine: that when thou art forlorne,</l>
                        <l>Thou maiſt remember her thou now doeſt ſcorne.</l>
                     </sp>
                  </div>
               </div>
               <div n="5" type="act">
                  <pb facs="tcp:16779:41"/>
                  <head>ACT. 5.</head>
                  <div n="1" type="scene">
                     <head>SCENA 1.</head>
                     <stage>Hylas.</stage>
                     <l>IT was the cruell practiſe of my Fate,</l>
                     <l>That lifted me unto the height of bliſſe,</l>
                     <l>To make my fall the greater: for no ſooner</l>
                     <l>Did I injoy the love of my <hi>Nerina,</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>But in a moment ſhe was taken from me:</l>
                     <l>A love ſo dearely bought with ſighs and teares,</l>
                     <l>So many yeares ſpent in the gaining her,</l>
                     <l>And loſt in one poore minute: It is better</l>
                     <l>Alwaies to live a miſerable life,</l>
                     <l>Then once to have bin happy: ſhe is dead,</l>
                     <l>And I alive that cannot live without her:</l>
                     <l>Tis fit that I die too; but by what meanes?</l>
                     <l>By violence? No, that the Gods forbid.</l>
                     <l>A lingring greife, I neede not feare, will kill me,</l>
                     <l>When every day I ſhall repaire, as now,</l>
                     <l>Unto her tombe, and conſecrate my teares,</l>
                     <l>And tearing ſighs unto her bleſſed Ghoſt,</l>
                     <l>Some pittying God, when I'me diſolv'd away</l>
                     <l>Upon her aſhes, will congeale thoſe teares,</l>
                     <l>That they may cloath her duſt: whilſt ſome kinde ſhepheard</l>
                     <l>Paſſing this way does write this on her grave.</l>
                     <q>
                        <l>See here <hi>Nerina,</hi> that from <hi>Hylas</hi> eyes</l>
                        <l>Fed her faire flame, now in their dew ſhe lies.</l>
                     </q>
                     <l>Thus I will have it, ſo the words ſhall runne.</l>
                  </div>
                  <div n="2" type="scene">
                     <pb facs="tcp:16779:41"/>
                     <head>SCENA 2.</head>
                     <stage>
                        <hi>Daphnis, Alcon, Nerina:</hi> to them <hi>Hylas, Montanus, Carinus, Mirtillus.</hi>
                     </stage>
                     <l>IT ſhall not ſerve thy turne, malicious ſhepheard,</l>
                     <l>Though thou haſt tane my love away by tricks,</l>
                     <l>Yet all thy cunning, and thy practiſes</l>
                     <l>Shall not ſecure thee from my revenge.</l>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Al.</speaker>
                        <l>Are theſe the thanks I have for that rich jewell</l>
                        <l>Which I beſtowd on thee, ungratefull man?</l>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Da.</speaker>
                        <p>Yes, for a poyſond glaſſe, a precious jewel.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Al.</speaker>
                        <p>I do confeſſe 'twas poyſond.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Da.</speaker>
                        <l>Do you ſo?</l>
                        <l>And to do me a courteſie, you kild her.</l>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Al.</speaker>
                        <l>Yet heare me, ſhe is not dead; and if ſhe be,</l>
                        <l>
                           <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                              <desc>••</desc>
                           </gap>e pay my life for hers.</l>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Da.</speaker>
                        <l>Be ſure thou ſhalt:</l>
                        <l>But canſt thou hope for ſuch a ſtrong illuſion</l>
                        <l>To mocke my ſence? did I not ſee her dead?</l>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Al.</speaker>
                        <l>She did appeare ſo: what you thought was death,</l>
                        <l>
                           <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap>s but a lethargie: though I profeſſe not</l>
                        <l>To draw the Moone downe from the ſphere ſhe is in,</l>
                        <l>Or make the ſunne looke bloody by my Arte,</l>
                        <l>Yet am I well informd in everything</l>
                        <l>This glaſſe is made of, and I know th'effects</l>
                        <l>
                           <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap>t workes, and can dicourſe 'em.</l>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <pb facs="tcp:16779:42"/>
                        <speaker>Da.</speaker>
                        <p>Let me heare them.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Al.</speaker>
                        <l>Have patience, and you ſhall; the Glaſſe you ſee</l>
                        <l>Of this rare Mirrour which I gave you, is</l>
                        <l>Made of a Memphian ſtone, that has the power</l>
                        <l>To bring a deadly ſleepe on all the ſenſes:</l>
                        <l>With it, to make th'effects more ſtrong, is mingled</l>
                        <l>The Quinteſſence, extracted in a Limbecke,</l>
                        <l>Of the <hi>Torpedo,</hi> which has ſuch a quality,</l>
                        <l>That if the Fiſher touch it with his hooke,</l>
                        <l>A poiſon ſtraite will creepe through all his veines,</l>
                        <l>Till it benumme his ſenſes: This compounded,</l>
                        <l>And made into a glaſſie metall, ſoone</l>
                        <l>Reflects upon the eyes of him that lookes in't</l>
                        <l>A ſleepie poiſon, which will ſtupifie</l>
                        <l>The vitall parts. Yet, he that gave it me,</l>
                        <l>Taught me the Cordiall water, which he us'd</l>
                        <l>To reſtore ſpirits and heate unto thoſe vitalls;</l>
                        <l>And I have brought it with me for our purpoſe.</l>
                        <l>What have I wrong'd you now? or is my preſent</l>
                        <l>Worthy the thankes you give me?</l>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Da.</speaker>
                        <l>Yet you were</l>
                        <l>Too blame, that you'd not tell me this before</l>
                        <l>I gave it her.</l>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Al.</speaker>
                        <l>In that I ſhew'd my love;</l>
                        <l>For I did feare your reſolution,</l>
                        <l>Though I were certaine of recovering her.</l>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Da.</speaker>
                        <p>And what muſt now be done?</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Al.</speaker>
                        <l>Here, where you found me,</l>
                        <l>
                           <pb facs="tcp:16779:42"/>
                           <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                              <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                           </gap> ſaw her laid, and buried in the clothes</l>
                        <l>
                           <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                              <desc>••</desc>
                           </gap>e wont to weare, her father ſo would have it:</l>
                        <l>
                           <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                              <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                           </gap> waited on the funerall, with purpoſe</l>
                        <l>
                           <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap>o ſee the ſtone laid hollow on her grave,</l>
                        <l>
                           <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap>or feare of hurting her.</l>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Da.</speaker>
                        <p>It was well don.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Al.</speaker>
                        <l>Here Ile apply my medicine; you ſhall ſee</l>
                        <l>Whether I lie or no.</l>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Da.</speaker>
                        <l>Let's loſe no time.</l>
                        <l>
                           <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                              <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                           </gap> long to ſee my love alive againe.</l>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Al.</speaker>
                        <l>Then helpe to lift this ſtone; ſee where ſhe lies,</l>
                        <l>
                           <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap>he ſame <hi>Nerina?</hi>
                        </l>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Da.</speaker>
                        <p>She is dead, I ſee.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Al.</speaker>
                        <p>Love is ſtill full of feares: give me the water.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Da.</speaker>
                        <p>Here, but take heede it do not ſpoile her face.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Al.</speaker>
                        <l>If ſhe be dead, you neede not feare the change</l>
                        <l>Of any color; what a childe is love?</l>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Da.</speaker>
                        <l>The Gods, I ſee, will not let beautie die:</l>
                        <l>
                           <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap>he breathes, ſhe ſtirs, her eies begin to open</l>
                        <l>As after ſleepe. O miracle!</l>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Al.</speaker>
                        <l>How now?</l>
                        <l>
                           <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap>s ſhe alive? will you beleeve your ſence?</l>
                        <l>Now I have put her in your hands, be ſure</l>
                        <l>You do not let her goe, and loſe no time.</l>
                        <l>If you give credit to her words, you're loſt.</l>
                        <l>What cannot womens words and flatteries</l>
                        <l>Effect with ſimple lovers? thinke on that,</l>
                        <l>Be confident: Ile leave you to your Fate.</l>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <pb facs="tcp:16779:43"/>
                        <speaker>Ne.</speaker>
                        <l>You Gods where am I now? what place is this?</l>
                        <l>What light is this I ſee? are the ſame things</l>
                        <l>Seene in this new world, as they are in th' other?</l>
                        <l>Or in the grave do men ſee waters, trees,</l>
                        <l>As I do now, and all things as I liv'd?</l>
                        <l>But ſure I live ſtill: if I doe, why then</l>
                        <l>Was I here buried amongſt theſe flowers?</l>
                        <l>Sure I am dead; but yet I walke and ſpeake,</l>
                        <l>And I have heard that thoſe who once are dead,</l>
                        <l>Can never uſe their voice, or action:</l>
                        <l>But who is this I ſee here? <hi>Daphnis,</hi> ha!</l>
                        <l>Are you dead too, as well as I?</l>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Da.</speaker>
                        <l>No ſweet,</l>
                        <l>I live to be the ſervant of <hi>Nerina.</hi>
                        </l>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Ne.</speaker>
                        <p>I, ſo ſaid <hi>Hylas,</hi> whil'ſt I liv'd with him.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Da.</speaker>
                        <p>She thinks of <hi>Hylas</hi> ſtill, what ſhall I do?</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Ne.</speaker>
                        <p>But tell me <hi>Daphnis,</hi> in what place am I?</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Da.</speaker>
                        <p>In <hi>Daphnis</hi> heart you live, and ever did.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Ne.</speaker>
                        <p>And ſo ſaid <hi>Hylas,</hi> when we liv'd together.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Da.</speaker>
                        <l>O Gods againe? <hi>Nerina</hi> thinke not on him,</l>
                        <l>You muſt love me.</l>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Ne.</speaker>
                        <l>Muſt they in this new world,</l>
                        <l>As they have chang'd their lives, ſo change their loves,</l>
                        <l>I never ſhall do that.</l>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Da.</speaker>
                        <l>You are deceiv'd.</l>
                        <l>You are not dead.</l>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Ne.</speaker>
                        <p>Not dead? how came I hither then?</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Da.</speaker>
                        <p>By my device to keepe me company.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <pb facs="tcp:16779:43"/>
                        <speaker>Ne.</speaker>
                        <p>But will you not declare, how I came hither?</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Da.</speaker>
                        <p>Aske me not that, but goe along with me.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Ne.</speaker>
                        <p>Stay ſhepheard, whither would you have me goe?</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Da.</speaker>
                        <p>Where love and ſilence ſhall befriend us beſt.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Ne.</speaker>
                        <p>But tell me <hi>Daphnis,</hi> was not I once dead?</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Da.</speaker>
                        <p>You were, but I your ſervant chang'd that death <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap>nto a ſleepe.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Ne.</speaker>
                        <l>I know not what you meane,</l>
                        <l>Can you change death into a ſleepe?</l>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Da.</speaker>
                        <l>I can,</l>
                        <l>And did for love of you.</l>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Ne.</speaker>
                        <l>This is a riddle,</l>
                        <l>Pray let me know what you do meane by it.</l>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Da.</speaker>
                        <p>Come with me, and you ſhall.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Ne.</speaker>
                        <p>Nay, tell me firſt.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Da.</speaker>
                        <l>Then know faire ſhepheardeſſe, that when I ſaw</l>
                        <l>My love, my ſervices, my gifts, my vowes,</l>
                        <l>Did all returne to me without your love,</l>
                        <l>I had recourſe unto this Artifice,</l>
                        <l>A pleaſent one of loves Invention,</l>
                        <l>Which you may well remember.</l>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Ne.</speaker>
                        <p>What was that?</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Da.</speaker>
                        <p>I did preſent you with a looking glaſſe.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Ne.</speaker>
                        <p>You did, but what of that?</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Da.</speaker>
                        <l>Nothing at all.</l>
                        <l>Pray goe this way with me.</l>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Ne.</speaker>
                        <p>But tell me firſt.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Da.</speaker>
                        <l>That caſt you into this deepe lethargie:</l>
                        <l>
                           <pb facs="tcp:16779:44"/>Such was the Magicke of it.</l>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Ne.</speaker>
                        <l>To what purpoſe</l>
                        <l>Did you do this?</l>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Da.</speaker>
                        <p>To make you mine.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Ne.</speaker>
                        <l>Yours, <hi>Daphnis?</hi>
                        </l>
                        <l>How could you hope that without my conſent?</l>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Da.</speaker>
                        <l>My ſervices I thought would merit it,</l>
                        <l>Beſides the world not dreaming but you were</l>
                        <l>Dead, and here buried, we two might liue</l>
                        <l>Together without being knowne to any.</l>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Ne.</speaker>
                        <l>But could you practiſe tricks on thoſe you love?</l>
                        <l>Now you are paid with your owne Artifice:</l>
                        <l>For know, ther's none that can diſpoſe of me</l>
                        <l>But <hi>Hylas,</hi> who has long preſerv'd my heart,</l>
                        <l>And now my father, (whom I did reſolve</l>
                        <l>For ever to obey) has made him mine,</l>
                        <l>By giving his conſent, which had not bin</l>
                        <l>But for this tricke of yours.</l>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Da.</speaker>
                        <l>Why then it ſeemes</l>
                        <l>You do not love me.</l>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Ne.</speaker>
                        <l>Love you? know I had</l>
                        <l>Rather embrace my death againe, then thee.</l>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Da.</speaker>
                        <l>Then 'tis no time to dally, come along,</l>
                        <l>Or I will force you.</l>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Ne.</speaker>
                        <p>Helpe me ſhepheards, helpe.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Da.</speaker>
                        <p>Foole, ſtop your mouth, no humane helpe ſhal ſave thee</p>
                     </sp>
                     <stage>Enter Hylas.</stage>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Hy.</speaker>
                        <l>This is the place where I am come to pay</l>
                        <l>
                           <pb facs="tcp:16779:44"/>My teares firſt ſacrifice, upon this tombe</l>
                        <l>That glories in the ſpoiles of all my wealth.</l>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Ne.</speaker>
                        <l>
                           <hi>Hylas,</hi> come helpe me, ſee'ſt thou not that <hi>Daphnis</hi>
                        </l>
                        <l>Will raviſh me?</l>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Hy.</speaker>
                        <l>Ha, what doe I heare?</l>
                        <l>The voice of my <hi>Nerina?</hi> ſo ſhe ſpake</l>
                        <l>When ſhee did live; but now, alas, ſhee's dead:</l>
                        <l>Some Devill mockes me with a viſion,</l>
                        <l>And voice unto it.</l>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Ne.</speaker>
                        <l>Will you ſee me raviſht</l>
                        <l>Before your face? O <hi>Hylas!</hi> oh my Love!</l>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Hy.</speaker>
                        <l>Tis ſhe, it is no viſion<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> hold Raviſher,</l>
                        <l>My love thou canſt not take without my life.</l>
                     </sp>
                     <stage>Enter Mirtillus, Montanus, Charinus.</stage>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Mi.</speaker>
                        <p>What noiſe is this?</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Mo.</speaker>
                        <p>Some ſhreike much like a womans.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Ne.</speaker>
                        <p>Oh helpe my love, <hi>Mirtillus.</hi>
                        </p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Mi.</speaker>
                        <l>Shepheard, hold,</l>
                        <l>Let goe this Nymph.</l>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Da.</speaker>
                        <l>Or death, or victory</l>
                        <l>Shall crowne my enterprize.</l>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Cha.</speaker>
                        <p>Who makes this out-cry?</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Mi.</speaker>
                        <p>Sir, I ſhall coole you, if you be ſo hot.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Cha.</speaker>
                        <l>My daughter here? was ſhee not buried?</l>
                        <l>Away foule ſpirit, away; let's part theſe ſhepheards.</l>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Ne.</speaker>
                        <l>O father, do you thinke that I am dead,</l>
                        <l>I am alive, as you are; touch me, ſee.</l>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <pb facs="tcp:16779:45"/>
                        <speaker>Cha.</speaker>
                        <p>She is alive indeede: how cam'ſt thou hither?</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Ne.</speaker>
                        <l>
                           <hi>Daphnis,</hi> whom you would have to be my husband,</l>
                        <l>Brought me to this ſuppoſed death and grave.</l>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Cha.</speaker>
                        <p>By what ſtrange meanes, <hi>Nerina?</hi>
                        </p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Ne.</speaker>
                        <l>By the glaſſe</l>
                        <l>You bid me I ſhould take: he has confeſt</l>
                        <l>To mee that it was poiſon'd.</l>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Cha.</speaker>
                        <l>Can it be?</l>
                        <l>Can <hi>Daphnis</hi> doe this? he had little reaſon.</l>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Da.</speaker>
                        <l>She was a foole to crie, I ſhould ha' pleas'd her</l>
                        <l>Ere this perhaps.</l>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Cha.</speaker>
                        <l>Here <hi>Hylas,</hi> take my daughter,</l>
                        <l>For ſhe is thine: you <hi>Daphnis,</hi> I did further</l>
                        <l>In all I could, till you would finde a tricke</l>
                        <l>To put your ſelfe beſide her.</l>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Ne.</speaker>
                        <l>I forgive him:</l>
                        <l>For though it was ill meant, yet did it ſort</l>
                        <l>By accident unto my good.</l>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Mo.</speaker>
                        <l>But will</l>
                        <l>Our Lawes permit a Raviſher to live?</l>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Hy.</speaker>
                        <l>No, no <hi>Montanus:</hi> let him live, and envie</l>
                        <l>Our preſent happineſſe.</l>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Da.</speaker>
                        <l>Cover, you Gods,</l>
                        <l>The world in publique ruine, or elſe ſhew me</l>
                        <l>A way to hide my ſhame.</l>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Mo.</speaker>
                        <p>What will he doe?</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Mi.</speaker>
                        <l>He will go hang himſelfe: what plots hee had</l>
                        <l>To foole himſelfe with!</l>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <pb facs="tcp:16779:45"/>
                        <speaker>Mo.</speaker>
                        <l>They that practiſe tricks</l>
                        <l>Finde them as jades, that throw 'em firſt, then kick 'em</l>
                        <l>As his has don.</l>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Cha.</speaker>
                        <l>Come ſhepheards, lets away,</l>
                        <l>And ſolemnize theſe nuptials.</l>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Mi.</speaker>
                        <l>Stay <hi>Montanus,</hi>
                        </l>
                        <l>Did the King ſend for you?</l>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Mo.</speaker>
                        <p>He did.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Mi.</speaker>
                        <p>And how?</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Mo.</speaker>
                        <p>The meſſage came from <hi>Thyrſis.</hi>
                        </p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Ni.</speaker>
                        <l>I'le goe with you:</l>
                        <l>'Tis ſtrange the King ſhould ſend for you: pray heaven</l>
                        <l>
                           <hi>Thyrſis</hi> have done no miſchiefe there, he's hanſome,</l>
                        <l>Of a good grace, and moving eloquence:</l>
                        <l>Perhaps ſome Lady may have taken him</l>
                        <l>Up for her ſelfe, and he, Ile lay a wager,</l>
                        <l>Will be ſo ſqueamiſh, that if <hi>Sylvia</hi>
                        </l>
                        <l>Come in his minde, he ne're will do her reaſon,</l>
                        <l>And then her plot will be how to betray him:</l>
                        <l>Would I were in his place.</l>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Mo.</speaker>
                        <l>I would thou wert,</l>
                        <l>So he were ſafe.</l>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Mi.</speaker>
                        <l>I would comply, ne're feare it;</l>
                        <l>They live a heavenly life of love in Court,</l>
                        <l>To that which we do here; a Miſtreſſe there</l>
                        <l>Will ſatisfie the longings of her lover,</l>
                        <l>And never trouble <hi>Hymen</hi> for the matter:</l>
                        <l>Then if they like not, they may looke elſe-where,</l>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <pb facs="tcp:16779:46"/>
                        <speaker>Mo.</speaker>
                        <p>Thou wilt be puniſht one day for thy miſchiefe.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Mi.</speaker>
                        <p>The miſchiefe's in my tongue, I ne're do any.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Mo.</speaker>
                        <l>No, I have heard that <hi>Stella</hi> was with childe</l>
                        <l>By thee, and thou muſt father it.</l>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Mi.</speaker>
                        <l>Who, I?</l>
                        <l>Take me at that once, fathering of children,</l>
                        <l>And make me common father of them all:</l>
                        <l>A child's a prettie thing, and I ſhould joy</l>
                        <l>To ſee one of mine owne. Ile tell thee truth</l>
                        <l>
                           <hi>Montanus,</hi> by this hand I never lay</l>
                        <l>With any woman in my life.</l>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Mo.</speaker>
                        <l>How then?</l>
                        <l>You' have courted all; who is it that <hi>Mirtillus</hi>
                        </l>
                        <l>Has not profeſt to love?</l>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Mi.</speaker>
                        <l>I do confeſſe it,</l>
                        <l>And that is all I could do; for before</l>
                        <l>I could get earneſt of any ones love,</l>
                        <l>To whom I made addreſſe; even ſhe would ſay,</l>
                        <l>You have another miſtreſſe, go to her,</l>
                        <l>I wil not be her ſtale: and ſo by this meanes,</l>
                        <l>Nor this, nor that would do me any reaſon.</l>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Mo.</speaker>
                        <p>You had ill lucke, it ſeemes, 'twas not your fault.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Mi.</speaker>
                        <l>No, for if they would beleeve me, I did ſweare</l>
                        <l>I had no other. Pray, <hi>Montanus,</hi> tell me,</l>
                        <l>For you have knowne the ſeverall waies of wooing,</l>
                        <l>Which is the beſt, and ſafeſt?</l>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Mo.</speaker>
                        <l>O <hi>Mirtillus,</hi>
                        </l>
                        <l>Gray haires have put the wilder thoughts of love</l>
                        <l>
                           <pb facs="tcp:16779:46"/>Out of my head; cold blood and frozen limbes,</l>
                        <l>Fright all thoſe heates away, in place of which</l>
                        <l>Diſcretion and ſobriety ſhould come.</l>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Mi.</speaker>
                        <p>But I have heard, old men doe ſometimes love.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Mo.</speaker>
                        <l>They dote, <hi>Mirtillus,</hi> give it the right name;</l>
                        <l>In old mens bloods <hi>Cupid</hi> does quench his flames.</l>
                        <l>But as we goe, Ile tell thee, not to love</l>
                        <l>At all is beſt; but if you needs muſt love,</l>
                        <l>Love one, and ſeeke no further, thou wilt finde</l>
                        <l>Enough of her, if once ſhe prove unkinde.</l>
                     </sp>
                  </div>
                  <div n="3" type="scene">
                     <head>SCENA 3.</head>
                     <stage>
                        <hi>Daphnis, Alcon.</hi> To <hi>Daphnis, Dorinda.</hi>
                     </stage>
                     <l>THere is no way to avoide the ſhame of this:</l>
                     <l>Each ſhepheards boy that ſings unto his flocke,</l>
                     <l>Will make me the ſcorn'd ſubject of his ſong.</l>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Al.</speaker>
                        <l>Had you bin ſuddaine as I counſail'd you,</l>
                        <l>You had not faild: but you young men doe never</l>
                        <l>Goe through with any thing.</l>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Do.</speaker>
                        <l>For heavens ſake,</l>
                        <l>Call not that wicked deede to my remembrance.</l>
                        <l>I do repent me, that I e're beganne it:</l>
                        <l>I would not for a world have ended it:</l>
                        <l>
                           <hi>Nerina's</hi> chaſte, and faire, and I a villaine.</l>
                        <l>Leave me, I pray, for ſomething tells me, you</l>
                        <l>Did firſt adviſe me to this damned act.</l>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <pb facs="tcp:16779:47"/>
                        <speaker>Al.</speaker>
                        <l>Nay, if you prize my friendſhip at this rate,</l>
                        <l>I'le leave you to your pennance.
<stage>Exit.</stage>
                        </l>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Da.</speaker>
                        <l>This old man</l>
                        <l>Is full of malice, nothing troubles him;</l>
                        <l>The ills that he has done, flie from his thoughts,</l>
                        <l>And he rejoyces that he did, them queintly:</l>
                        <l>I have begun my youth, as if I meant</l>
                        <l>To have my age ſo puniſht as his is,
<stage>Enter Dorinda.</stage>
                        </l>
                        <l>Who's this? <hi>Dorinda?</hi> I have done her wrong:</l>
                        <l>I ſu'de for love to her firſt, which obtain'd,</l>
                        <l>I ſtucke diſgraces on her; let me aske</l>
                        <l>Forgiveneſſe now, for 'twere too much to hope,</l>
                        <l>That ſhe ſhould love one ſtain'd with ſuch a deed</l>
                        <l>As I have done, ſo foule and impious.</l>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Do.</speaker>
                        <l>Great love, if yet thou art not ſatiſfied</l>
                        <l>With all the wrongs I have ſuſtain'd for thee:</l>
                        <l>My blood, I hope thy anger will appeaſe,</l>
                        <l>Which thou maiſt glut thy ſelfe with.</l>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Da.</speaker>
                        <p>Gentle Nymph.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Do.</speaker>
                        <l>I've beene too gentle, doe not mocke me with't:</l>
                        <l>O <hi>Daphnis,</hi> is it you? this is not well,</l>
                        <l>To mocke me thus; your looks when arm'd with frownes,</l>
                        <l>Gave not my heart ſo deepe a wound as this.</l>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Da.</speaker>
                        <l>I meane no ſcorne, I come to aske your pardon</l>
                        <l>For what I've done already, not to heape</l>
                        <l>More ſinnes upon my head.</l>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Do.</speaker>
                        <p>'Tis very ſtrange.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Da.</speaker>
                        <l>But true <hi>Dorinda,</hi> will you ſpit upon me?</l>
                        <l>
                           <pb facs="tcp:16779:47"/>Take your revenge, for I have well deſerv'd it.</l>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Do.</speaker>
                        <l>But is this ſerious <hi>Daphnis?</hi> oh take heed,</l>
                        <l>Cracke not my heart with ſuch a loade of griefe</l>
                        <l>And ſcorne, ſo preſt as this is; if you doe,</l>
                        <l>The Gods will puniſh it: for though they have</l>
                        <l>Neglected me thus long, they will revenge</l>
                        <l>Such injuries as theſe.</l>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Da.</speaker>
                        <l>My many ills</l>
                        <l>Diſcredit my repentance: if my words</l>
                        <l>Can finde no faith with you, beleeve my teares,</l>
                        <l>Indeed they are not feign'd.</l>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Do.</speaker>
                        <l>Even ſo you look't</l>
                        <l>When firſt you ſtole my heart: but I forgive you,</l>
                        <l>What ere become of me; I ſtill muſt love you.</l>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Da.</speaker>
                        <l>Forgive me firſt, and then I will beginne</l>
                        <l>By my endeavours and true ſervices</l>
                        <l>To deſerve ſomething of you, if not love.</l>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Do.</speaker>
                        <l>There is not that hard heartedneſſe in man</l>
                        <l>Which I did thinke, for he repents I ſee:</l>
                        <l>O <hi>Daphnis,</hi> if thou mean'ſt not this as ſcorne,</l>
                        <l>Take me into thine armes, and I will be</l>
                        <l>Thy ſlave.</l>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Da.</speaker>
                        <l>O ſay not ſo, let me</l>
                        <l>Rather be thine; it will be pride in me</l>
                        <l>To be ambitious of it.</l>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Do.</speaker>
                        <l>Oh my heart!</l>
                        <l>What ſuddaine joy thou ſtrik'ſt into it now!</l>
                        <l>But yet methinkes I feare thou doſt not love me.</l>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <pb facs="tcp:16779:48"/>
                        <speaker>Da.</speaker>
                        <l>Why ſhould you feare? by <hi>Pan</hi> you are to me</l>
                        <l>What ere you can imagine; equall, above</l>
                        <l>All that I ere thought faire; and if you be</l>
                        <l>Content to hide my faults, and take me to</l>
                        <l>Your nuptiall bed, (which yet I dare not hope)</l>
                        <l>But if you will, when ere that day ſhall come,</l>
                        <l>Th'embraces of my love and me, ſhall be</l>
                        <l>Such as the <hi>Cyprian</hi> boy from our abundance,</l>
                        <l>Shall take his fires to kindle other hearts,</l>
                        <l>Yet leave with us a flame, which we will cheriſh,</l>
                        <l>And keepe alive unto eternitie.</l>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Do.</speaker>
                        <l>Women are ever credulous moſt then,</l>
                        <l>When knowledge of the truth would but afflict them:</l>
                        <l>I dare not now diſtruſt you, though I knew,</l>
                        <l>What you have ſaid, were falſe, it has a ſemblance</l>
                        <l>Of ſuch a pleaſing truth: Give me thy hand,</l>
                        <l>And take thou mine; whilſt we walke thus intwin'd</l>
                        <l>I ſhall thinke <hi>Daphnis</hi> never was unkind.</l>
                     </sp>
                  </div>
                  <div n="4" type="scene">
                     <head>SCENA 4.</head>
                     <stage>Eubulus, Cleander: to them Thyrſis, Sylvia.</stage>
                     <l>WHat, are they dead? Is the Kings will obey'd?</l>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Cle.</speaker>
                        <l>No Sir, they live, and <hi>Hymen</hi> in his bands</l>
                        <l>Has ty'd them both; the happieſt knot that ere</l>
                        <l>Knit two ſuch equall hearts, and loves together:</l>
                        <l>Oh I am raviſh'd with the newes, my joy</l>
                        <l>Is greater now, then if ſh'had beene the daughter</l>
                        <l>Unto our King, and I had married her.</l>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Eu.</speaker>
                        <p>I am amaz'd; pray <hi>Jove</hi> thou beeſt not mad.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <pb facs="tcp:16779:48"/>
                        <speaker>Cle.</speaker>
                        <l>Somewhat exalted, Sir, beyond my my ſelfe,</l>
                        <l>But yet not mad: Goe, Sir, unto the King,</l>
                        <l>Tell him, <hi>Cleander</hi> lives to make him happy.</l>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Eu.</speaker>
                        <l>Sure thou wilt come unto thy ſelfe anon,</l>
                        <l>Prethee bethinke thee.</l>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Cle.</speaker>
                        <l>Yes Sir, I doe thinke,</l>
                        <l>And know that I have newes to make him live,</l>
                        <l>And you an age yet longer.</l>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Eu.</speaker>
                        <p>This is ſtrange.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Cle.</speaker>
                        <p>Tis true.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Eu.</speaker>
                        <p>But what is true?</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Cle.</speaker>
                        <l>Tis true, my Siſter</l>
                        <l>Shall be a Queene.</l>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Eu.</speaker>
                        <l>If ſhe doe live, I thinke</l>
                        <l>She will; but yet you know we were commanded</l>
                        <l>To cut that life off.</l>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Cle.</speaker>
                        <l>But your haſtie ſonne,</l>
                        <l>That came ſo ſpeedy with a fatall meſſage,</l>
                        <l>Was not ſo forward now; they both doe live,</l>
                        <l>And both are married.</l>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Eu.</speaker>
                        <p>
                           <hi>Jupiter</hi> forbid.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Cle.</speaker>
                        <l>The Fates command it, 'tis their proper worke<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
                        </l>
                        <l>The Shepheard is a Prince, your Prince, and mine,</l>
                        <l>And married to my Siſter,</l>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Eu.</speaker>
                        <l>Ha! what's that?</l>
                        <l>Prithee digeſt thy troubled thoughts, and tell me</l>
                        <l>What Prince is this thou mean'ſt?</l>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Cle.</speaker>
                        <p>
                           <hi>Archigenes.</hi>
                        </p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Eu.</speaker>
                        <p>Thou dream'ſt, it cannot be.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Cle.</speaker>
                        <l>No, then come forth</l>
                        <l>You royall paire, and teſtifie your ſelves.
<stage>Enter Thyrſis and Sylvia.</stage>
                        </l>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Syl.</speaker>
                        <p>Father, your bleſſing.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Eu.</speaker>
                        <p>Ha!</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Cle.</speaker>
                        <l>Nay, I've told all.</l>
                        <l>
                           <pb facs="tcp:16779:49"/>She knowes ſhe is your daughter: looke Sir here;</l>
                        <l>Here we muſt place our reverence.</l>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Eu.</speaker>
                        <p>Who's this?</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Cle.</speaker>
                        <l>Not yet? then looke upon this Circle, that</l>
                        <l>You know for certaine, though you know not him.</l>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Eu.</speaker>
                        <l>'Tis it, it is the ſame: <hi>Archigenes</hi>
                        </l>
                        <l>
                           <hi>Sonne of Euarchus and Eudora:</hi>
                        </l>
                        <l>This is my character, and this my ſeale.</l>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Thy.</speaker>
                        <l>Sir, I have heard that by your piety,</l>
                        <l>My infant life was ſav'd: now by the goodneſſe</l>
                        <l>Deriv'd from you, unto your ſonne, I have</l>
                        <l>Not onely found my life, but my content,</l>
                        <l>The ſumme of all my hopes, this Lady here,</l>
                        <l>Without whoſe love my life had bin a torment.</l>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Syl.</speaker>
                        <l>And I the happieſt maide that ever was</l>
                        <l>Conducted by the power of ſimple love,</l>
                        <l>Have found in place of him I thought a ſhepheard,</l>
                        <l>A Princely lover.</l>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Eu.</speaker>
                        <l>Riſe <hi>Calligone:</hi>
                        </l>
                        <l>The Gods are juſt I ſee, that favoring</l>
                        <l>My innocence, have brought this match about.</l>
                        <l>But ſay <hi>Cleander,</hi> what Fate guided thee</l>
                        <l>To this diſcovery?</l>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Cle.</speaker>
                        <l>Sir, ſhould I tell you,</l>
                        <l>How many waies I caſt to ſave my ſiſter</l>
                        <l>After the fatall meſſage which I brought,</l>
                        <l>I ſhould be tedious, and keepe you from</l>
                        <l>What you do long to heare: In ſhort I ſoone</l>
                        <l>
                           <pb facs="tcp:16779:49"/>Reſolv'd to make away this royall ſhepheard.</l>
                        <l>And knowing that in this affaire, to keepe it</l>
                        <l>Secret, diſpatch was needefull, I commanded</l>
                        <l>A ſervant, of whoſe faith and courage I</l>
                        <l>Was well aſſur'd, to kill him in my preſence.</l>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Eu.</speaker>
                        <p>'Tis ſtrange, thou ſhould'ſt be preſent at a murder.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Cle.</speaker>
                        <l>'Twas a neceſſity was laid upon me,</l>
                        <l>Becauſe I would be ſure to ſee him dead,</l>
                        <l>I bad him chooſe his death, when manfully</l>
                        <l>He ſaid, he car'd not how, ſo he might die.</l>
                        <l>I knew to ſtrangle him, was the readieſt way,</l>
                        <l>Which death himſelfe was ready to embrace:</l>
                        <l>This his ſo noble reſolution,</l>
                        <l>Did ſtande me from mine; my ſervants hands</l>
                        <l>Trembled for feare,</l>
                        <l>Preſaging what a ſinne they were to act:</l>
                        <l>He bad him be aſſur'd he would not ſtart,</l>
                        <l>And often call'd him to diſpatch him quickly.</l>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Syl.</speaker>
                        <l>What man could have a heart for ſuch a deed,</l>
                        <l>And ſee his face.</l>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Cle.</speaker>
                        <l>The Prince, before he came</l>
                        <l>To put the fatall twiſt about his necke,</l>
                        <l>Beſought me, as I ever hop't for peace,</l>
                        <l>I ſhould preſerve the Princeſſe: this I promis'd,</l>
                        <l>And whatſoever elſe he would deſire:</l>
                        <l>He anſwered, nothing now, but haſty death,</l>
                        <l>Then ſtripping off his doublet, I eſpide</l>
                        <l>With a quick eye this golden Circle here,</l>
                        <l>
                           <pb facs="tcp:16779:50"/>When haſtily I bid my ſervant hold,</l>
                        <l>And let him goe. He ask't me why I ſtaid,</l>
                        <l>I told him that about his necke was <hi>Sacred,</hi>
                        </l>
                        <l>He would have rent it off, but I forbad it.</l>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Eu.</speaker>
                        <p>What did you then?</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Cle.</speaker>
                        <l>Sir, I did well remember</l>
                        <l>What I had heard of th' Oracle and you,</l>
                        <l>Which with the computation of his yeares,</l>
                        <l>I found agreeing to make up a truth</l>
                        <l>Which you before aſſur'd me; then I ask't him,</l>
                        <l>Whether he would be married to the Princeſſe</l>
                        <l>Before he died; he thought that I had mockt him,</l>
                        <l>And ſaid, I practis'd Tyrannie upon him:</l>
                        <l>Then went I to my ſiſter, and deſir'd</l>
                        <l>The ſame of her; in fine, I ſaw them both</l>
                        <l>Joyne hands and hearts together, but the Prince</l>
                        <l>Thought this a dreame of life, which certaine death</l>
                        <l>Would wake him from, untill I did aſſure him</l>
                        <l>Of his great State, and that his love, whom now</l>
                        <l>He thought to be the Princeſſe, was my Siſter,</l>
                        <l>All which I did referre unto your knowledge.</l>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Eu.</speaker>
                        <l>This day for ever let it holy be,</l>
                        <l>And you whom love has brought through deepe deſpaire,</l>
                        <l>Unto the haven of your happineſſe,</l>
                        <l>Enjoy each other freely. Of you brave ſhepheard,</l>
                        <l>(But now my Prince) I ſhall enquire anon</l>
                        <l>Where, and with whom you liv'd.</l>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Thy.</speaker>
                        <l>Sir, the ſhepheard,</l>
                        <l>
                           <pb facs="tcp:16779:50"/>
                           <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap>hom I call father, ſtayes without; <hi>Montanus</hi>
                        </l>
                        <l>
                           <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap>s name is, by whoſe gentle hands, (as he</l>
                        <l>as often told me) I was reſcu'd firſt</l>
                        <l>
                           <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap>om cold and death, ſince under his kind roofe</l>
                        <l>
                           <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap>oſterd, and bred as his.</l>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Eu.</speaker>
                        <l>Goe call him in,
<stage>Enter Montanus, Mirtillus.</stage>
                        </l>
                        <l>
                           <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap>ou're welcome both, you may applaud your fortune</l>
                        <l>
                           <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap>hat brought you ſuch a Shepheard: ſtay all here,</l>
                        <l>Whilſt I goe to the King. This day will adde</l>
                        <l>
                           <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap>ore yeares unto his life, when he ſhall ſay,</l>
                        <l>
                           <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap>o day ſhone brighter on <hi>Arcadia.</hi>
                           <stage>Exit.</stage>
                        </l>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Mon.</speaker>
                        <l>We are both come to doe our duties to you.</l>
                        <l>as being ſent for, and <hi>Mirtillus</hi> with me,</l>
                        <l>
                           <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap>o celebrate your joyes: within a while</l>
                        <l>
                           <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap>he Shepheards and the Nymphs will all be here.</l>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Thy.</speaker>
                        <l>My old companions ſhall be welcome all,</l>
                        <l>
                           <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap>s you are now; I never ſhall forget</l>
                        <l>
                           <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap>our courteſie, nor theirs.</l>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Syl.</speaker>
                        <l>Nor I the Nymphs</l>
                        <l>
                           <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap>nce my deare fellowes; but you <hi>Mirtillus,</hi>
                        </l>
                        <l>
                           <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap>hough you did ſcorne to love, yet could you ſing</l>
                        <l>
                           <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap>ell, if you liſted of it.</l>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Cle.</speaker>
                        <l>Can ſhepheards then</l>
                        <l>
                           <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap>eſpiſe that Deity which we adore?</l>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Mi.</speaker>
                        <l>Madam, I reverence it in you,</l>
                        <l>
                           <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap>he perfect'ſt patterne of a conſtant lover,</l>
                        <l>
                           <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap>nd in the honour of your Nuptialls</l>
                        <l>
                           <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                              <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                           </gap> have a Song, which if your Grace will heare,</l>
                        <l>
                           <pb facs="tcp:16779:51"/>'Twill entertaine the time.</l>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Syl.</speaker>
                        <p>Let it be ſung.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <lg type="song">
                           <head>Song.</head>
                           <lg>
                              <l>
                                 <hi>Hymen,</hi> God of marriage bed,</l>
                              <l>Be thou ever honoured:</l>
                              <l>Thou, whoſe torches purer light,</l>
                              <l>Deaths ſad tapers did affright,</l>
                              <l>And inſteed of funerall fires,</l>
                              <l>Kindled lovers chaſt deſires:</l>
                              <l>May their love</l>
                              <l>Ever prove</l>
                              <l>True and conſtant: let not age</l>
                              <l>Know their youthfull heate t'aſſwage.</l>
                           </lg>
                           <lg n="2">
                              <head>2.</head>
                              <l>Maides prepare the Genial bed,</l>
                              <l>Then come night, and hide that red</l>
                              <l>Which her cheekes, his heart does burne:</l>
                              <l>Till the envious day returne,</l>
                              <l>And the luſty bridegroome ſay,</l>
                              <l>I have chac'd her feares away,</l>
                              <l>And inſteed</l>
                              <l>Of virgin head,</l>
                              <l>Given her a greater good,</l>
                              <l>Perfection, and womanhood.</l>
                           </lg>
                        </lg>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Thy.</speaker>
                        <l>Thanks good <hi>Mirtillus,</hi> this indeed was proper</l>
                        <l>Unto your ſubject.</l>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <pb facs="tcp:16779:51"/>
                        <speaker>Mi.</speaker>
                        <l>Your thrice happy match,</l>
                        <l>
                           <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap>eing but now come to my knowledge, made me</l>
                        <l>
                           <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap>ontract my ſelfe into a ſtraiter roome,</l>
                        <l>
                           <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap>hen the large ſubject might afford.</l>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Cle.</speaker>
                        <p>The King.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <stage>To theſe, Euarchus, Eubulus.</stage>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Eu.</speaker>
                        <l>Although I wonder, yet I doe beleeve thee,</l>
                        <l>
                           <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap>y faithfull Councellor.</l>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Eub.</speaker>
                        <l>Your Majeſty</l>
                        <l>
                           <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap>as found me alwaies reall, but this truth</l>
                        <l>
                           <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap>he Oracles accompliſhment will prove,</l>
                        <l>
                           <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap>hat did foretell their match.</l>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Eu.</speaker>
                        <l>Reade it, <hi>Eubulus,</hi>
                        </l>
                        <l>
                           <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap>nce more; and then call in my ſonne and daughter.</l>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>
                           <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap>ub.</speaker>
                        <q>
                           <l>
                              <hi>If ere thy Iſſue Male thou liv'ſt to ſee,</hi>
                           </l>
                           <l>
                              <hi>The childe thou thinkst is thine, thine ſhall not bee.</hi>
                           </l>
                        </q>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Eu.</speaker>
                        <p>
                           <hi>Calligone</hi> is not my childe, proceed.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>
                           <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap>ub.</speaker>
                        <q>
                           <l>
                              <hi>His life ſhall be obſcure, twice ſhall thy hate</hi>
                           </l>
                           <l>
                              <hi>Doome him to death, yet ſhall he ſcape that Fate.</hi>
                           </l>
                        </q>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Eu.</speaker>
                        <l>'Tis true, that twice I did command his death,</l>
                        <l>
                           <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap>irſt thinking him a baſtard, then a ſhepheard,</l>
                        <l>
                           <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap>or his offence; the Gods are juſt: Goe on.</l>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>
                           <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap>ub.</speaker>
                        <q>
                           <l>
                              <hi>And thou ſhalt live to ſee that not long after</hi>
                           </l>
                           <l>
                              <hi>Thy onely ſonne ſhall wed thy onely daughter.</hi>
                           </l>
                        </q>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <pb facs="tcp:16779:52"/>
                        <speaker>Eu.</speaker>
                        <l>This was a riddle ever till this day,</l>
                        <l>Their marriage has made it plaine. <hi>Eubulus,</hi>
                        </l>
                        <l>Call in <hi>Archigenes,</hi> and call thy daughter</l>
                        <l>The faire <hi>Calligone,</hi> that I may powre</l>
                        <l>My bleſſings on them: And I long to ſee</l>
                        <l>Thoſe characters, thou writſt about his necke,</l>
                        <l>That I may call him mine.</l>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Eub.</speaker>
                        <p>See where they are.</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Eu.</speaker>
                        <l>
                           <hi>Archigenes</hi> come neerer, for thou art</l>
                        <l>A ſtranger yet, although thou be my ſonne:</l>
                        <l>The Character is plaine, it is the ſame</l>
                        <l>
                           <hi>Eubulus</hi> writ to me: you heavenly powers</l>
                        <l>Give me a heart that may be large enough</l>
                        <l>T'expreſſe my joy for theſe, and thanks to you.</l>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Thy.</speaker>
                        <l>My royall father, (for I am inſtructed</l>
                        <l>To call you ſo) If I have don amiſſe</l>
                        <l>In haſting to this match, I aske your pardon.</l>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Syl.</speaker>
                        <l>And I for daring to aſpire ſo high</l>
                        <l>Without your leave.</l>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Eu.</speaker>
                        <l>Riſe both, you have my bleſſing.</l>
                        <l>But who are theſe?</l>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Thy.</speaker>
                        <l>This is the ſhepheard Sir,</l>
                        <l>Who tooke me up firſt, whom till now I call'd</l>
                        <l>Father, and he deſerv'd it for his care.</l>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Eu.</speaker>
                        <p>
                           <hi>Eubulus,</hi> this is he, <hi>Montanus,</hi> iſt not?</p>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Eub.</speaker>
                        <l>He is deliverd to me for the ſhepheard,</l>
                        <l>Of whom your Majeſty may if you pleaſe</l>
                        <l>Be well inform'd of all thoſe paſſages,</l>
                        <l>
                           <pb facs="tcp:16779:52"/>I left untold.</l>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Eu.</speaker>
                        <l>Some other time we'le heare them.</l>
                        <l>Let him be well rewarded.</l>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Thy.</speaker>
                        <l>Sir, theſe ſhepheards</l>
                        <l>Are come to entertaine your Majeſtie,</l>
                        <l>With their devices, as their cuſtome is,</l>
                        <l>In which ſometimes, untill my fortune chang'd,</l>
                        <l>I bore apart.</l>
                     </sp>
                     <sp>
                        <speaker>Eu.</speaker>
                        <l>Let them be feaſted all,</l>
                        <l>And ſtuddy ſomething new to celebrate</l>
                        <l>Theſe Nuptials, which I will have proclaim'd</l>
                        <l>Throughout my kingdome: and <hi>Eubulus,</hi> ſee</l>
                        <l>That every thing be fitted for their honor.</l>
                        <l>Come let us to the Temple, that we may</l>
                        <l>With holy ſacrifice appeaſe the Gods,</l>
                        <l>Whoſe great decrees, though we did ſtrive to hinder,</l>
                        <l>Yet are they now fulfill'd. It is in vaine,</l>
                        <l>T'oppoſe the Fates, whoſe lawes do all conſtraine.
<stage>Exeunt</stage>
                        </l>
                     </sp>
                  </div>
               </div>
               <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
            </div>
            <div type="epilogue">
               <pb facs="tcp:16779:53"/>
               <head>The Epilogue to the KING and QVEENE.</head>
               <l>TO you moſt royall paire, whoſe lives have brought</l>
               <l>Vertue in faſhion, and the world have taught,</l>
               <l>That chaſt innocuous ſports become the ſtage</l>
               <l>No leſſe then civill manners do the age:</l>
               <l>We dedicate this Piece, but yet with feares,</l>
               <l>To have diſpleas'd ſo chaſt, ſo tender eares;</l>
               <l>Which, if you free us from, we'le call this play</l>
               <l>No more the <hi>Shepheards,</hi> but our <hi>Holy-day.</hi>
               </l>
            </div>
         </div>
         <div type="elegy">
            <pb facs="tcp:16779:53"/>
            <head>THYRSIS. A Paſtorall Elegie in the perſon of Sir <hi>Kenelme Digby,</hi> on the Death of his Noble Lady, the Lady <hi>Venetia Digby.</hi>
            </head>
            <lg>
               <l>THe gentleſt Swaine that <hi>Arcady</hi> ere bred,</l>
               <l>Who <hi>Thyrſis</hi> hight, the ſaddeſt of that name,</l>
               <l>Cloſe by a Rivers ſide his heavy head</l>
               <l>Laid downe, as he with teares would fill the ſame,</l>
               <l>Regarding nought that might him pleaſance give,</l>
               <l>Since what was his delight, had left to live.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>And whilſt that other Shepheards of his ranke,</l>
               <l>(If any Shepheard of his ranke might be)</l>
               <l>Plaid on their merry Pipes upon ſome banke,</l>
               <l>Making the hills reſound their jollity,</l>
               <l>Hee in ſad plight his woefull daies did ſpend,</l>
               <l>Their joyous ſports caring not to attend.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>There as hee by that ſilent water lay,</l>
               <l>Regardleſſe of his youth, and luſty head,</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <pb facs="tcp:16779:54"/>
               <l>His ſwelling griefe in vaine he did aſſay</l>
               <l>To vent in grievous plaints, which more it fed,</l>
               <l>Whilſt to the ruthleſſe waves he did relate</l>
               <l>The ſtory of his loſſe, and heavy Fate.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>You Nymphs (if any doe inhabite here)</l>
               <l>(And I have heard that Nymphs in waters dwell,)</l>
               <l>Lend to my carefull Verſe a gentle eare,</l>
               <l>Whilſt I, the ſaddeſt wight that ere did tell</l>
               <l>His owne miſhaps, unfold to you my caſe</l>
               <l>In this your balefull place.</l>
               <l>If to the Sea, of which you branches are,</l>
               <l>I ever honour did, when liſt me change</l>
               <l>My Shepheards ſtaffe, to ſeeke adventures farre</l>
               <l>In the wide <hi>Ocean,</hi> where I long did range,</l>
               <l>And brought renowne home to my native ſoyle,</l>
               <l>The glory of my toyle.</l>
               <l>Doe not miſtake, nor offer to compare</l>
               <l>Thoſe dayes with theſe, wherein my griefe exceeds</l>
               <l>The joy, which once I had, to ſee my faire</l>
               <l>Welcome me home, and gratulate my deeds,</l>
               <l>Which to atchieve, her grace as well did move,</l>
               <l>As did my countries love.</l>
               <l>But now with her thoſe graces all are gone,</l>
               <l>Weepe with me waters to make up my moane.</l>
               <l>
                  <pb facs="tcp:16779:54"/>Gone is my Love: and why then doe I ſee</l>
               <l>Nature the ſame, as ere ſhee was before,</l>
               <l>Since to her making all her forces ſhee</l>
               <l>Wiſely imploy'd, and ſhe could give no more?</l>
               <l>Though ſhee ſhould frame the moſt caeleſtiall mould</l>
               <l>That ere the Earth did hold,</l>
               <l>To draw from all the heads of noble blood</l>
               <l>The beſt, and to infuſe it into one,</l>
               <l>To make a mixture of all faire and good.</l>
               <l>Rare <hi>Symmetry,</hi> and ſweete <hi>proportion,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>Was it to ſhew that ſuch a thing might be</l>
               <l>Without eternitie?</l>
               <l>It was, and wee are taught how fraile the truſt</l>
               <l>Is, that wee give unto mortality,</l>
               <l>How ſoone ſhee is reſolved into duſt,</l>
               <l>Whom erſt the world ſo beautifull did ſee.</l>
               <l>But you were juſt that tooke her, though unkinde</l>
               <l>In leaving me behinde:</l>
               <l>Alas! why was I left thus all alone?</l>
               <l>Weepe with mee waters to make up my moane.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Shee's gone, and I am here; yet doe I finde</l>
               <l>With ſome ſmall joy the languiſhing decay</l>
               <l>Of th'other halfe, which ſhe has left behind<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
               </l>
               <l>For halfe of me with her ſhee bore away</l>
               <l>
                  <pb facs="tcp:16779:55"/>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nto thoſe fields, where ſhee immortall is,</l>
               <l>Heaped with heavenly bliſſe.</l>
               <l>I ſee her faire ſoule in that bleſſed place,</l>
               <l>Where joy for ever dwells: and now I know,</l>
               <l>How in a dreame ſhe ſaw an Angells face,</l>
               <l>And it admiring, wiſht ſhe might be ſo:</l>
               <l>Which the celeſtiall powers would not deny,</l>
               <l>So did ſhee ſleeping dye.</l>
               <l>So did ſhee breake the bonds of heavy night,</l>
               <l>And when ſhee wak't, wak't to eternall day:</l>
               <l>Where ſhee in formes Angelicke now is dight,</l>
               <l>And ſees her maker, and ſhall ſee for aye.</l>
               <l>O happy ſoule, I will not thee envy,</l>
               <l>O let me rather flye</l>
               <l>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nto that bleſſed place, where thou art gone,</l>
               <l>Then waters, weepe no more, but end your moane</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>I come; yet ſomething does retard me here,</l>
               <l>The pledges of our love thou left'ſt with me:</l>
               <l>Thoſe whom thou living didſt account ſo deare,</l>
               <l>Who ſtill with mee preſerve thy memory;</l>
               <l>For their lov'd ſakes yet muſt I longer ſtay,</l>
               <l>Then will I poſte away.</l>
               <l>Then to thy laſting name I have uprear'd</l>
               <l>A Monument, which time ſhall ne're deface,</l>
               <l>
                  <pb facs="tcp:16779:55"/>And made the world, which as yet have not heard</l>
               <l>Of thy rare vertues, and thy honour'd race,</l>
               <l>Know who thou wert, and that thou wentſt from hence</l>
               <l>At Natures great expence.</l>
               <l>Then world farewell, you I have ſeene enough,</l>
               <l>And know how to deſpiſe your vanity:</l>
               <l>Your painted glories are of baſer ſtuffe,</l>
               <l>Made to delude thoſe that with halfe eyes ſee:</l>
               <l>He that's abſtracted from you, ſtands much higher,</l>
               <l>And greater things admire.</l>
               <l>'Tis you I leave, to goe where ſhee is gone,</l>
               <l>Then waters weepe no more, here end your moane.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>This to the empty winds and waters, hee</l>
               <l>Alas, in vaine, (they car'd not for his teares)</l>
               <l>Did thus unfold to eaſe his miſery:</l>
               <l>When loe, the Meſſenger of night appeares;</l>
               <l>For the falne Sun (which warn'd him to be gone)</l>
               <l>Chang'd to the light uncertaine of the Moone.</l>
            </lg>
         </div>
         <div type="epitaph">
            <pb facs="tcp:16779:56"/>
            <head>DE TVMVLO PER ILLVS<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>triſſimum Dominum <hi>Kenelmum Digby</hi> lectiſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mae conjugiſuae ſtructo, ejuſque memoriae <hi>dicato</hi> EPIGRAMMA.</head>
            <l>HAc tua chara jacet <hi>Digbeie, Venetia</hi> terrâ,</l>
            <l>Quae pietate tuâ nobile marmor habet:</l>
            <l>En Parios lapides, atque hac in mole repertum</l>
            <l>Quod <hi>Phidiae</hi> potuit, <hi>Praxiteliſve</hi> manus.</l>
            <l>Aſpicis ut vivunt ſtatuae, caelataque doctâ</l>
            <l>Aera manu, quin ut vertice &amp; ipſa micat:</l>
            <l>Gloria defunctos ſi tangit, poſſe videtur</l>
            <l>Credibile hoc illam velle cubare modo,</l>
            <l>Quaerenti cineres reſpondent, corde jacebo</l>
            <l>Conjugis, &amp; tumulo nobiliore tegar.</l>
            <closer>
               <dateline>
                  <hi>Obijt</hi>
                  <date>1. <hi>Maij,</hi> 1633.</date>
               </dateline>
            </closer>
            <pb facs="tcp:16779:56"/>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
