<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Torquato Tassos Aminta Englisht To this is added Ariadne's complaint in imitation of Anguillara; written by the translater of Tasso's Aminta</title>
            <title>Aminta. English</title>
            <author>Tasso, Torquato, 1544-1595.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1628</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 142 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 47 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-12">2011-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A13384</idno>
            <idno type="STC">STC 23696</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC S118131</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99853340</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99853340</idno>
            <idno type="VID">177232</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A13384)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 177232)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 941:4)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>Torquato Tassos Aminta Englisht To this is added Ariadne's complaint in imitation of Anguillara; written by the translater of Tasso's Aminta</title>
                  <title>Aminta. English</title>
                  <author>Tasso, Torquato, 1544-1595.</author>
                  <author>Reynolds, Henry, fl. 1627-1632.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[94] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed by Aug: Mathewes for William Lee, and are to bee sold at the signe of the Turkes Head in Fleetstreet,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1628.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>A translation, by Henry Reynolds, of: Aminta.</note>
                  <note>In verse.</note>
                  <note>The words "Torquato Tassos Aminta Englisht" on title page are incorporated into a pictorial engraving.</note>
                  <note>Signatures: A-M⁴ (-M4).</note>
                  <note>A3 is a cancel.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the Harvard University. Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2011-02</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-02</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-03</date>
            <label>Susie Lorand</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-03</date>
            <label>Susie Lorand</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-06</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:177232:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:177232:1"/>
            <figure>
               <figDesc>engraved title page</figDesc>
            </figure>
            <p>To this is added ARIADNE<hi>'S</hi> Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plaint in imitation of ANGVILLARA; Written by the Tranſlater of TASSO'S AMINTA.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Meglio è il poco terreno ben coltuiare, che'l molto laſciar per mal gouerno miſeramente imboſchire. <choice>
                     <abbr>Sannaz<hi rend="sup">o</hi>.</abbr>
                     <expan>Sannazaro</expan>
                  </choice>
               </hi>
            </p>
            <p>LONDON, Printed by AVG: MATHEWES for WILLIAM LEE, and are to bee ſold at the Signe of the <hi>Turkes Head</hi> in <hi>Fleetſtreet.</hi> 1628.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="dramatis_personae">
            <pb facs="tcp:177232:2"/>
            <head>The Speakers are</head>
            <list>
               <item>CVPID, <hi>in Shepherds weedes.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>DAPHNE, <hi>companion of</hi> SILVIA.</item>
               <item>SILVIA, <hi>beloued of</hi> AMINTA.</item>
               <item>AMINTA, <hi>louer of</hi> SILVIA.</item>
               <item>THIRSIS, <hi>companion of</hi> AMINTA.</item>
               <item>SATYR, <hi>in loue with</hi> SILVIA.</item>
               <item>NERINA, <hi>Nymphe.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>ERGASTVS, <hi>Shepherd.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>ELPINE, <hi>Shepherd.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>CHORVS, <hi>of Shepherds.</hi>
               </item>
            </list>
         </div>
         <div type="prologue">
            <pb facs="tcp:177232:2"/>
            <head>The Prologue.</head>
            <sp>
               <speaker>CVPID</speaker>
               <stage>in habit of a Shepheard.</stage>
               <l>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">W</seg>Ho would beleeue that in this human forme,</l>
               <l>And vnder theſe meane Shepherds weedes,</l>
               <l>A god head? nor yet of the lower ranke,</l>
               <l>But the moſt mighty 'mong the gods; whoſe powre were hid</l>
               <l>Makes oft the bloudy Sword of angry <hi>Mars</hi>
               </l>
               <l>Fall from his hand; ſterne <hi>Neptune</hi> hurle away</l>
               <l>His powerfull trident; and great <hi>Ioue</hi> lay by</l>
               <l>His thunderbolt: and thus attyr'de, I hope</l>
               <l>My mother <hi>Venus</hi> ſhall haue much adoe</l>
               <l>To find her <hi>Cupid.</hi> For the troth to tell,</l>
               <l>Sh'has made me play the run-away with her:</l>
               <l>Becauſe (forſooth) ſhee will ſole miſtreſſe bee,</l>
               <l>And to her pleaſure binde my ſhafts and mee;</l>
               <l>And (vaine ambitious woman as ſhee is)</l>
               <l>Would tye me to liue ſtil 'mongſt Crownes, &amp; Scep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters,</l>
               <l>And to high Courts confine my power and me;</l>
               <l>And to my vnder-followers graunts to liue</l>
               <pb facs="tcp:177232:3"/>
               <l>Here in theſe woods; and to aduance their powres,</l>
               <l>Ore ſilly Shepherds breſts; but I that am</l>
               <l>No childe, (though childiſh be my gate and lookes)</l>
               <l>Will for this once, doe as ſhall pleaſe me beſt:</l>
               <l>For not to her, but me allotted were</l>
               <l>The euer awfull brande, and goulden bowe:</l>
               <l>Therefore I purpoſe to conceale my ſelfe,</l>
               <l>And runne from her entreates; (for other powre</l>
               <l>Then to intreate, ſhee ſhall not haue ore me:)</l>
               <l>I heare ſhee haunts theſe groues, and promiſeth</l>
               <l>Vnto the Nymphes and Shepherds, which of them</l>
               <l>Will bring me to her, kiſſes for their paines,</l>
               <l>And more then kiſſes too; and cannot I</l>
               <l>To them ſhall hide me from her, liberall be</l>
               <l>Of kiſſes, and more too as well as ſhee?</l>
               <l>The Nymphes I know will like my kiſſes beſt,</l>
               <l>When I ſhall woe them that am god of loue:</l>
               <l>Therefore my mother doth but looze her paine,</l>
               <l>Here's none will bring her home her ſonne againe.</l>
               <l>But to be ſurer, that ſhe may not know</l>
               <l>Or finde me out by the vſd'e markes I beare,</l>
               <l>I'ue layd my quiuer, bowe, and wings from me;</l>
               <l>Yet come I not hither vnarm'de; this rodd</l>
               <l>I carry is my brand transformed thus,</l>
               <l>And breathes out vnſeene flame at eu'ry pore;</l>
               <l>And this dart (though it haue no goulden head)</l>
               <l>Of heu'nly temper is; and where it lytes</l>
               <pb facs="tcp:177232:3"/>
               <l>Inforceth loue; and eu'ne this day ſhall make</l>
               <l>A deepe and cureleſſe wound in the hard breſt</l>
               <l>Of the moſt cruell Nymph, that euer yet</l>
               <l>Hath bin a follower of <hi>Dianas</hi> traine;</l>
               <l>Nor will I pitty <hi>Siluia</hi> more, (for ſo</l>
               <l>Th'obdurate ſtony-breſted Nymph is call'd)</l>
               <l>Then erſt I did the gentle-hearted Swaine</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Aminta,</hi> many winters ſince, when he</l>
               <l>(Poore wretch) then young, follow'd her younger ſtepps</l>
               <l>From wood to wood in eu'ry game and ſport:</l>
               <l>And for more ſure effecting my intent,</l>
               <l>I'le pauſe a while till ſome remorſe and pitty</l>
               <l>Of the poore Shephedrs ſufferings, haue a little</l>
               <l>Thawde the hard yce congeal'd about her breſt</l>
               <l>With mayden peeuiſhneſſe; and when I finde</l>
               <l>She growes more plyant, will I launch her breſt:</l>
               <l>And this to doe with better eaſe and arte,</l>
               <l>Amongſt the feaſting troopes of the crown'd Shep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>herds</l>
               <l>That hither come to ſport o'hollydayes,</l>
               <l>I'le put my ſelfe; and heere, euen in this place</l>
               <l>I'le giue the ſpeeding blow vnſeene, vnknowne.</l>
               <l>To day theſe Woods ſhall heare another voyce</l>
               <l>Of loue then ere before, and more refin'de;</l>
               <l>My god head heere ſhall in it ſelfe appeare</l>
               <l>Preſent no longer in my Miniſters:</l>
               <l>I'le breath ſoft thoughts into their courſer breſts,</l>
               <l>And make their tungs in ſmootheſt nu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>bers moue;</l>
               <pb facs="tcp:177232:4"/>
               <l>For whereſoere I am, ſtill am I <hi>Loue;</hi>
               </l>
               <l>No leſſe in Shepherds then in greateſt Peeres;</l>
               <l>And inequallity in people, I</l>
               <l>Can temper as I pleaſe, ſuch is my power.</l>
               <l>The Rurall ſound of homely Shepherds reede</l>
               <l>I can make equall with the learned'ſt lyre,</l>
               <l>And if my mother (which diſdaines forſooth</l>
               <l>To ſee me heere) be ignorant of this,</l>
               <l>Shee's blinde, not I</l>
               <l>Whom the blind world reputes blinde wrongfully.</l>
            </sp>
         </div>
         <div type="errata">
            <head>To the Reader.</head>
            <p>
               <hi>ERe thou readeſt farther, let mee intreat thee Reader (in fauour of</hi> Taſſo, <hi>the great Author of this ſmall Poeme) to correct theſe fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowing faults eſcaped in the Printing.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>In <hi>Act. Pri: Scen: Pri</hi> for theenes, read <hi>theeues.</hi> In the next line for whice, r. <hi>which.</hi> In <hi>Act. Prim. Sce. ſecund.</hi> for giddy Bees, read <hi>greedy Bees.</hi> In the firſt <hi>Chorus,</hi> for Was then, read, <hi>Was not then.</hi> And in the ſame <hi>Chorus,</hi> for Liue wee while, read <hi>Loue wee while.</hi> In <hi>Act. ſecund. Scen. prim.</hi> for eyelids fault, read <hi>eyelids foult.</hi> In the ſecond <hi>Chorus,</hi> for read'ſt thine, read <hi>readeſt thy.</hi> In <hi>Act. Ter. Scen. Pri.</hi> for foft beſt, r. <hi>ſoft breſt.</hi> In the next page for he went, r. <hi>he wont.</hi> In the end of the Scene for they it may, r. <hi>that it may.</hi> In the third <hi>Chorus</hi> for Lone no price, read <hi>Loue no price.</hi> In <hi>Act. Quint. Scen. Pri.</hi> for tenter lap, r. <hi>tender lapp.</hi> In VE<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>NVSSES <hi>Search,</hi> for your hears keyes, r. <hi>your hearts keyes.</hi>
            </p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="play">
            <pb facs="tcp:177232:4"/>
            <div n="1" type="act">
               <head>Actus Primus. </head>
               <div n="1" type="scene">
                  <head>Scen: Prima.</head>
                  <stage>Daphne. Siluia.</stage>
                  <sp>
                     <l>I'ſt poſsible (Siluia) thou canſt reſolue</l>
                     <l>To ſpend the faire houres of thy flowring youth</l>
                     <l>With ſuch contempt of <hi>Venus,</hi> and her Sonne;</l>
                     <l>And haſt no more deſire to be a mother,</l>
                     <l>And leaue a part of thee (when thou art dead)</l>
                     <l>Liuing behinde thee? Change (young fondling) change</l>
                     <l>Thy minde; and do not leade a life ſo ſtrange.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Sil.</speaker>
                     <l>Daphne, let others pleaſure take in loue,</l>
                     <l>(If in ſuch thraledome any pleaſure bee;)</l>
                     <l>The life I leade contents me well enough;</l>
                     <l>To chaſe the flying Deere ouer the lawne</l>
                     <l>With Hounde, or well-aym'de Flight, and while I finde</l>
                     <l>
                        <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>hafts in my quiuer, and beaſts for my pray,</l>
                     <l>Ile want no ſport to paſſe the time away.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Da:</speaker>
                     <l>Fine ſports no doubt, and ſure a goodly life</l>
                     <l>For ſilly mindes that neuer taſted other,</l>
                     <l>And for that cauſe alone it pleaſes thee:</l>
                     <l>
                        <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>o duller ages heretofore could thinke</l>
                     <l>
                        <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>cornes and water the beſt meate and drinke,</l>
                     <l>
                        <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>efore the vſe of corne and wine was founde,</l>
                     <l>
                        <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>ut now th'are onely eate and drunke by beaſtes:</l>
                     <pb facs="tcp:177232:5"/>
                     <l>And hadſt thou but once proou'd the thouſand part</l>
                     <l>Of the deare joyes thoſe happy louers feele,</l>
                     <l>That truely loue, and are belou'd againe,</l>
                     <l>Thou wouldſt with ſighes repent thy time miſpent,</l>
                     <l>And onely call a louers life Content.</l>
                     <l>And ſay, O my paſt ſpringtyde, how in vaine</l>
                     <l>Spent I thy widowy nights? how many dayes</l>
                     <l>In fruitleſſe loneneſſe, which I now be waile?</l>
                     <l>Why knew I not loues ſweetes haue this condition</l>
                     <l>To bring new ioyes with eu'ry repetition?</l>
                     <l>Change, change thy minde (young ſilly one) and knowe</l>
                     <l>Too late repentance is a double woe.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Sil.</speaker>
                     <l>When I repent the thoughts I carry now,</l>
                     <l>Or ſay ſuch words as theſe thou fayning framest</l>
                     <l>To ſport thy ſelfe withall; the Floulds ſhall runne</l>
                     <l>Backe to their Springs, the Wolfe ſhall fearing flye</l>
                     <l>The ſilly Lambe, and the young Leurett ſhall</l>
                     <l>Purſue the ſpeedy Grayhound ore the playne,</l>
                     <l>The Beare ſhall in the toyling Ocean breede,</l>
                     <l>And finny Dolphine on the mountaines feede.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Da:</speaker>
                     <l>I ſo, iuſt ſuch another peeuiſh thing</l>
                     <l>Like thee was I, when I was of thy yeares;</l>
                     <l>So look'd, ſo pac'de, ſo goulden trest', ſo ruddy</l>
                     <l>My tyſing lipp, ſo in my riſing cheeke</l>
                     <l>The damaske roſe was blowne; and I remember</l>
                     <l>Iuſt ſuch as thine is now, my minde was then,</l>
                     <l>And eu'ne ſuch ſilly paſtimes as thine be</l>
                     <pb facs="tcp:177232:5"/>
                     <l>I likewiſe vſd'e; as with lim'd twiggs to catch</l>
                     <l>Vnwares the fethred ſingers in the wood,</l>
                     <l>Track the Deeres footing, till I had intrapt them</l>
                     <l>And ſuch like; when a gentle louer woode me,</l>
                     <l>With ſuch a peeuiſh grace hang downe the head</l>
                     <l>And bluſh for ſcorne I would, as oft thou doe'ſt;</l>
                     <l>And that vnſeemely forme me thought became mee,</l>
                     <l>Nay eu'ne diſlik'd what others lik'de in me,</l>
                     <l>So much I counted it a fault, and ſhame</l>
                     <l>To be deſir'de or lou'de of any one;</l>
                     <l>But what cannot time bring to paſſe? and what</l>
                     <l>Cannot a true and faithfull louer do</l>
                     <l>With importunity, deſert and loue?</l>
                     <l>And I confeſſe plainely the troth to thee</l>
                     <l>So was I vanquiſht; nor with other armes</l>
                     <l>Then humble ſuff'rance, ſighes, and pitty crauing:</l>
                     <l>But then I ſoone found in one ſhort nights ſhade,</l>
                     <l>What the broade light of many hundred dayes</l>
                     <l>Could neuer teach me; then I could recall</l>
                     <l>My ſelfe, ſhake off my blinde ſimplicitie,</l>
                     <l>And ſighing ſay, here Cinthia take thy bowe,</l>
                     <l>Quiuer, and horne, for I renounce thy life.</l>
                     <l>And I hope yet to ſee another day</l>
                     <l>Thy wilde thoughts bridled too, and thy hard breſt</l>
                     <l>Yeeld, and growe ſofter at Aminta's plaints.</l>
                     <l>Is he not young and freſh, and louely too?</l>
                     <l>Does he not loue thee dearely', and thee alone?</l>
                     <pb facs="tcp:177232:6"/>
                     <l>For though belou'de of many Nymphes, he neuer</l>
                     <l>For others loue, or thy hate, leaues to loue thee.</l>
                     <l>Nor canſt thou thinke him to meane borne for thee;</l>
                     <l>For (be thou daughter of Cidippe faire,</l>
                     <l>Whoſe ſire was god of this our noble floud)</l>
                     <l>Yet is Aminta ould Siluanus heire,</l>
                     <l>Of the high ſeed of Pan the Shepherds god.</l>
                     <l>The ſleeke-browd' Amarillis (if ere yet</l>
                     <l>In any fountaines glaſſe thou ſaw'ſt thy ſelfe)</l>
                     <l>Is not a whit leſſe louely then thou art;</l>
                     <l>Yet all her ſweet alurements he reiects,</l>
                     <l>And madly dotes on thy diſpightfull loathings.</l>
                     <l>Well, but ſuppoſe now, (and the heau'ns forbid</l>
                     <l>It come to more then ſuppoſition)</l>
                     <l>That he falling from thee, his minde remooue,</l>
                     <l>And cleaue to her, that ſo deſerues his loue;</l>
                     <l>What will become of thee then? with what eye</l>
                     <l>Wilt thou behould him in an others armes</l>
                     <l>Happily twyn'de, and thy ſelfe laught to ſcorne?</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Sil:</speaker>
                     <l>Be it to' Aminta and his loues, as beſt</l>
                     <l>Shall like himſelfe; I'me at a point for one;</l>
                     <l>And ſo he be not mine, be' he whoſe he liſt.</l>
                     <l>But mine he cannot be againſt my will,</l>
                     <l>Nor yet though he were mine, would I be his.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Da:</speaker>
                     <l>Fye, whence grows this thy hate?</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Sil:</speaker>
                     <l>Why from his loue.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Da:</speaker>
                     <l>Too ſoft a ſyre to breed ſo rough a Sonne;</l>
                     <l>But who ere ſawe Tygars of milde Lambes bred,</l>
                     <pb facs="tcp:177232:6"/>
                     <l>Or the blacke Rau'ne hatcht of a ſiluer Doue?</l>
                     <l>Thou doſt but mocke me Siluia, doſt thou not?</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Sil:</speaker>
                     <l>I hate his loue, that doth my honour hate;</l>
                     <l>And lou'de him, whilſt he ſought what I could graunt.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Da:</speaker>
                     <l>Tis thou offend'ſt thy ſelfe; he doth but crane</l>
                     <l>The ſame for thee, that he deſires to haue.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Sil:</speaker>
                     <l>I pre'thee Daphne either ſpeake no more,</l>
                     <l>Or ſomwhat elſe that I may anſwer to.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Da:</speaker>
                     <l>See fondling ſee</l>
                     <l>How ill this peeuiſhneſſe of youth becomes thee;</l>
                     <l>Tell me but this yet, if ſome other lou'de thee,</l>
                     <l>Is this the welcome thou wouldſt giue his loue?</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Sil:</speaker>
                     <l>Such and worſe welcome they deſerue, that ar</l>
                     <l>Theſe theenes of ſilly maydes virginities,</l>
                     <l>Whice you call louers, and I enimies.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Da:</speaker>
                     <l>Is the ramme then to th'ewe an enimy,</l>
                     <l>The bull to th' bayfer, is the turtle too,</l>
                     <l>An enemy to' his mate that loues him ſo?</l>
                     <l>And is the Spring the ſeaſon of debate,</l>
                     <l>That (ſweetly ſmiling) leades to coupling bands</l>
                     <l>The beaſt, the fiſh, the fowle, women and men?</l>
                     <l>And ſee'ſt thou not that e'ury thing that is,</l>
                     <l>Breathes now a ſoueraign ayre of loue, and ſweetneſſe,</l>
                     <l>Pleaſure, and health? behold that Turtle there</l>
                     <l>With what a wooing murmur he ſighes loue</l>
                     <l>To his belou'de; harke of yon Nitingall</l>
                     <l>That hops from bough to bough,</l>
                     <pb facs="tcp:177232:7"/>
                     <l>Singing I loue I loue; nay more then theſe,</l>
                     <l>The ſpeckled Serpent layes his venim by,</l>
                     <l>And greedy runnes to' imbrace his loued one;</l>
                     <l>The Tygar loues, and the proud Lion too;</l>
                     <l>Thou onely ſauadge more then ſauadge beaſts</l>
                     <l>Barr'ſt againſt loue thy more-then-yron breſt.</l>
                     <l>But what ſpeake I of Lions, Tygars, Snakes,</l>
                     <l>That ſenſible ar? why all theſe trees doe loue;</l>
                     <l>See with what amorous and redoubled twinings</l>
                     <l>The louing Vine her husband faire intangles;</l>
                     <l>The Beech tree loues the Beech, the Pine the Pine,</l>
                     <l>The Elme the Elme loues, and the Willows too</l>
                     <l>A mutuall languiſh for each other feele.</l>
                     <l>That Oake that ſeemes ſo rough and ſo impenitrable,</l>
                     <l>Doth no leſſe feele the force of amorous flame;</l>
                     <l>And hadſt thou but the ſpirit and ſence of loue,</l>
                     <l>His hidden language thou wouldſt vnderſtand.</l>
                     <l>Wilt thou be leſſe and worſe then trees and plants,</l>
                     <l>In being thus an enimy to Loue?</l>
                     <l>Fye ſilli'one fie; theſe idle thoughts remooue.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Sil:</speaker>
                     <l>When I heare trees ſighe (as belike they do)</l>
                     <l>I'le be content to bee a louer too.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Da:</speaker>
                     <l>Well, mock my words, laugh my aduice to ſcorne,</l>
                     <l>(Deaffe to Loues ſound, and ſimple as thou art)</l>
                     <l>But goe thy wayes; be ſure the time will come</l>
                     <l>When thou ſhalt flye from the now-loued fount</l>
                     <l>Where thou behold'ſt and ſo admyr'ſt thy ſelfe;</l>
                     <pb facs="tcp:177232:7"/>
                     <l>Fearing to view thy ſelfe ſo wrinkled fowle</l>
                     <l>
                        <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>s age will make thee; but I note not this</l>
                     <l>
                        <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>o thee aboue the reſt, for though age be</l>
                     <l>
                        <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>uill, 'tis ſo to all as well as thee.</l>
                     <l>Heard'ſt thou what Elpine ſpake this other day,</l>
                     <l>The reu'rend Elpine to the faire Licoris,</l>
                     <l>Licoris whoſe eyes wrought vpon him that</l>
                     <l>Which his ſongs ſhould haue wrought vpon her heart,</l>
                     <l>
                        <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>f Loue could learne but to giue each his due)</l>
                     <l>He tould it (Batto' and Thirſis being by,</l>
                     <l>
                        <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>hoſe two learn'd louers) in Auroras denne,</l>
                     <l>
                        <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                           <desc>••</desc>
                        </gap>er whoſe doore is writt—<hi>hence yee prophane,</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>
                           <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap>ye yee farre hence,</hi> which words he writt (ſayd he)</l>
                     <l>
                        <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>hat in that high pitch ſang of loues and armes,</l>
                     <l>
                        <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>nd when he dyed bequeath'd his pipe to him;</l>
                     <l>
                        <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>here was (he ſaid) lowe in th'infernall lake</l>
                     <l>A dungeon darke, aye fill'd with noyſom fumes</l>
                     <l>
                        <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>reath'd from the furnaces of Acaron,</l>
                     <l>
                        <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>nd there all cruell and ingratefull women</l>
                     <l>
                        <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                           <desc>••</desc>
                        </gap>ue in eternall horror, and ar fedd</l>
                     <l>With onely their owne booteleſſe plaints and cryes.</l>
                     <l>
                        <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>ooke to't betimes, or I am ſore afraide</l>
                     <l>
                        <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>here muſt a roome be taken vp for you,</l>
                     <l>
                        <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                           <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                        </gap> quite this cruelty to others vſd'e.</l>
                     <l>
                        <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>nd 'twere but iuſtice, that thoſe fumes ſhould drawe</l>
                     <l>
                        <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap> ſea of ſorrow from thoſe eyes of thine,</l>
                     <l>
                        <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>hat pitty could ne're make to ſhed a teare:</l>
                     <pb facs="tcp:177232:8"/>
                     <l>Well, runne on thine owne courſe, and marke the ende.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Sil:</speaker>
                     <l>But what did then Licoris (pre'thee tell me)</l>
                     <l>What reply did ſhee make to Elpine's words?</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Da:</speaker>
                     <l>How curious th' art in other folkes affaires,</l>
                     <l>And careleſſe quite in what concernes thy ſelfe?</l>
                     <l>Why, with her eyes Licoris anſwer'd him.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Sil:</speaker>
                     <l>How could ſhee anſwer only with her eyes?</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Da:</speaker>
                     <l>Yes; her faire eyes wrapt in a ſunny ſmile,</l>
                     <l>Tould Elpine this; Her heart and we are thine;</l>
                     <l>More cannot ſhe giue, nor muſt thou deſire.</l>
                     <l>This were alone enough to ſatis ſie</l>
                     <l>And ſerue for full reward to a chaſt louer,</l>
                     <l>That held her eyes as true as they were faire,</l>
                     <l>And put entire and harty truſt in them.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Sil:</speaker>
                     <l>But wherfore does not he then truſt her eyes?</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Da:</speaker>
                     <l>I'le tell thee; know'ſt thou not what Thirſis wri<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>
                     </l>
                     <l>When hurryed ſo with loue, and loues diſdaine</l>
                     <l>He wont to wander all about the woods,</l>
                     <l>In ſuch a ſort, as pitty moou'de, and langhter</l>
                     <l>Mong'ſt the young Swaines and Nymphes that gaz'de o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap> him?</l>
                     <l>Yet writ he nought that laughter did deſerue,</l>
                     <l>Though many things he did, deſeru'd no leſſe.</l>
                     <l>He writ it on the barkes of ſundry trees,</l>
                     <l>And as the trees, ſo grew his verſe. 'Twas this—</l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Deluding eyes, falſe mirhors of the heart,</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Full well I finde how well yee can deceiue:</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>But what auailes, if loue inforce my will</hi>
                     </l>
                     <pb facs="tcp:177232:8"/>
                     <l>
                        <hi>To'imbrace your harmes, and dote vpon you ſtill?</hi>
                     </l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Sil:</speaker>
                     <l>Well thus we waſt the time in ydle chatt,</l>
                     <l>And I had halfe forgot, that 'tis to day</l>
                     <l>We did appoint to meet in th'Oaken groue,</l>
                     <l>To hunt an houre; I pre'thee if thou wilt,</l>
                     <l>Stay for me till I haue in yon freſh fount</l>
                     <l>
                        <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>ayd off the ſweat and duſt that yeſterday</l>
                     <l>
                        <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>ſoyld me with, in chaſe of a ſwift Doe,</l>
                     <l>That at the length I ouertooke, and kill'de.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Da:</speaker>
                     <l>I'le ſtay for thee, and perhaps waſh me too,</l>
                     <l>But firſt I'le home a while, and come againe,</l>
                     <l>
                        <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>or the daye's younger then it ſeemes to be.</l>
                     <l>Goe then, and ſtay there for me till I come;</l>
                     <l>
                        <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>nd in the meane time, thinke on my aduice,</l>
                     <l>
                        <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>hat more imports thee, then the chaſe, or fount;</l>
                     <l>
                        <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>nd if thou doſt not thinke ſo, thou muſt know</l>
                     <l>Thou little know'ſt; and ought'ſt thy iudgement bowe</l>
                     <l>To their direction that know more then thou.</l>
                  </sp>
               </div>
               <div n="2" type="scene">
                  <head>Actus Primus. Scen: Secunda.</head>
                  <stage>Aminta. Thirſis.</stage>
                  <sp>
                     <l>AT my laments I'ue heard the rocks, the waters</l>
                     <l>For pitty anſwer; and at my complaint</l>
                     <l>
                        <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>he leau'de boughes murmur, as they grieu'd for me;</l>
                     <l>
                        <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                           <desc>••</desc>
                        </gap>t neuer ſaw, nor euer hope to ſee</l>
                     <pb facs="tcp:177232:9"/>
                     <l>Pitty in the faire and cruell (ſhall I ſay</l>
                     <l>Woman or) tygar? for a woman ſhee</l>
                     <l>Denyes to be, in thus denying me</l>
                     <l>The pitty this my miſerable ſtate</l>
                     <l>Drawes from things ſenceleſſe, and inanimate.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Thir:</speaker>
                     <l>Lambes on the graſſe, the Wolfe feedes on th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap> Lambe<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>
                     </l>
                     <l>Loue (cruelleſt of things) with teares is fedd.</l>
                     <l>And though he euer feedes, is neuer full.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Am:</speaker>
                     <l>Alas alas, loue hath bin with my teares</l>
                     <l>Long ſince full fedd, and now thirſts onely for</l>
                     <l>My bloud; and long it ſhall not be, ere he</l>
                     <l>And the faire Cruell drinke it with their eyes.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Thi:</speaker>
                     <l>Ay me, what ſayſt thou' Aminta? Fye no more</l>
                     <l>Of this ſtrange dotage; be of comfort man</l>
                     <l>And ſeeke ſome other; others thou mayeſt finde</l>
                     <l>As true, as this is cruell, and vnkinde.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Am:</speaker>
                     <l>Alas how weary'a worke were it for me</l>
                     <l>Other to ſeeke, that cannot finde my ſelfe;</l>
                     <l>And hauing loſt my ſelfe, what can I gaine</l>
                     <l>With buſie'ſt ſearch that ſhall requite the paine?</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Thi:</speaker>
                     <l>Diſpaire not yet, vnhappy though thou bee,</l>
                     <l>Shee may in time relent, and pitty thee:</l>
                     <l>Time makes the Tygar and the Lion tame.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Am:</speaker>
                     <l>O but ſo long to hope and be delaid,</l>
                     <l>Is worſe then death to one in miſerie.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Thi:</speaker>
                     <l>Perhaps thy ſuffrance ſhall not long endure;</l>
                     <l>For mayds ſo' inconſtant ar of diſpoſition,</l>
                     <pb facs="tcp:177232:9"/>
                     <l>That as th'ar ſoone at odds, th'ar as ſoone wonne;</l>
                     <l>Vncertaine as the leafe Howne with each winde,</l>
                     <l>And flexible as is the bladed graſſe.</l>
                     <l>But gentle Shepherd, let me craue to know</l>
                     <l>More throughly thy loues hard condition;</l>
                     <l>For though I'ue often heard thee ſay thou lou'ſt,</l>
                     <l>Thou neuer tould'ſt me yet, who 'twas thou lou'ſt;</l>
                     <l>And well it fitts the neareneſſe of our liues,</l>
                     <l>And frendſhip, that ſuch counſayls ſhould be none</l>
                     <l>Betweene vs two, but free to both, as one.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Am:</speaker>
                     <l>Thirſis, I am content to ope to thee</l>
                     <l>What the woods, hills, and flouds ar priuy to,</l>
                     <l>But no man knowes: ſo neere alas I finde</l>
                     <l>Th'approaching period of this loathed breath,</l>
                     <l>That reaſon 'tis I leaue ſome one behinde,</l>
                     <l>That may relate th'occaſion of my death,</l>
                     <l>And leaue it written on ſome Beech-tree barke,</l>
                     <l>Neere where my bloudleſſe carkaſſe ſhall be lay'd;</l>
                     <l>That as the cruell Faire ſhall paſſe along,</l>
                     <l>She may at pleaſure ſpurne with her proud foote</l>
                     <l>The vnhappy bones,</l>
                     <l>And ſmiling ſay; loe here, loe where he lyes;</l>
                     <l>The triumph and the trophey of mine eyes;</l>
                     <l>And (to encreaſe her fame,) reioyce to ſee</l>
                     <l>In my ſad ende her beauties victory</l>
                     <l>Knowne to the Nimphes, and Shepherds farr and neere,</l>
                     <l>Whom the report may thither guide: perhaps</l>
                     <l>(Ab hopes too high) ſhee may beſtow a ſigh,</l>
                     <pb facs="tcp:177232:10"/>
                     <l>And though too late, with ſome compaſsion rue</l>
                     <l>The loſse of him dead, whom ſhee liuing ſlue,</l>
                     <l>And wiſh he liu'd againe. But I digreſse.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Thi:</speaker>
                     <l>On with thy ſtory, for I long to heare't;</l>
                     <l>Perhaps to better ende then thou ſuppoſeſt.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Am:</speaker>
                     <l>Being but a Lad, ſo young as yet ſcarſe able</l>
                     <l>To reach the fruit from the low-hanging boughes</l>
                     <l>Of new growne trees; Inward I grew to bee</l>
                     <l>With a young mayde, fulleſt of loue and ſweetneſse,</l>
                     <l>That ere diſplay'd pure gold treſſe to the winde;</l>
                     <l>Thou know'ſt her mother hight Cidippe; no?</l>
                     <l>Montano the rich Goteheard is her father:</l>
                     <l>Siluia, faire Siluia 'tis I meane, the glory</l>
                     <l>Of all theſe woods, and flame of euery heart;</l>
                     <l>'Tis ſhee, 'tis ſhe I ſpeake of; long alas</l>
                     <l>Liu'd I ſoneare her, and then lou'de of her,</l>
                     <l>As like two turtles each in other joy'de;</l>
                     <l>Neere our abodes, and neerer were our bearts;</l>
                     <l>Well did our yeares agree, better our thoughts;</l>
                     <l>Together woue we netts t'intrapp the fiſh</l>
                     <l>In flouds and ſedgy fleetes; together ſett</l>
                     <l>Pitfalls for birds; together the pye'd Buck</l>
                     <l>And flying Doe ouer the plaines we chac'de;</l>
                     <l>And in the quarry', as in the pleaſure ſhar'de:</l>
                     <l>But as I made the beaſts my pray, I found</l>
                     <l>My heart was loſt, and made a pray to other.</l>
                     <l>By little' and little in my breaſt beganne</l>
                     <l>To ſpring, I know not from what hidden roote</l>
                     <pb facs="tcp:177232:10"/>
                     <l>(Like th'her be that of it ſelfe is ſeene to growe)</l>
                     <l>A ſtrange deſire, and loue ſtill to be neere</l>
                     <l>And hourely drinke from the faire Siluias eyes</l>
                     <l>A ſweetneſſe paſt all thought, but it had ſtill</l>
                     <l>(Me thought) a bitter farewell; oft I ſigh'd,</l>
                     <l>Yet knew no cauſe I had to ſigh; and ſo</l>
                     <l>Became betimes a louer, ere I knewe</l>
                     <l>What loue meant; but alas I knewe too ſoone;</l>
                     <l>And in what ſort, marke, and I'le tell thee</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Thir:</speaker>
                     <l>Onn.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Am:</speaker>
                     <l>All in the ſhade of a broad Beech-tree ſitting,</l>
                     <l>Siluia, Phillis, and my ſelfe together;</l>
                     <l>A Bee, that all about the flowry mede</l>
                     <l>Had hunny gathred; flow to Phillis cheeke;</l>
                     <l>The roſie cheeke miſtaking for a roſe,</l>
                     <l>And there (belike) his little needle left:</l>
                     <l>Phillis cryes out, impatient of the paine</l>
                     <l>Of her ſharp ſting; but th' euerlouely Siluia</l>
                     <l>Bad her be patient; Phillis (ſaid ſhee) peace,</l>
                     <l>And with a word or two I'le heale thy hurt,</l>
                     <l>And take the ſting, and ſoone the griefe away;</l>
                     <l>This ſecret erst the graue Aretia taught mee,</l>
                     <l>And her I gaue (in recompence) the horne</l>
                     <l>Of Yuory tipt with gould I wont to were;</l>
                     <l>This ſaid, the libs of her faire ſweeteſt mouth</l>
                     <l>Vpon th' offended cheeke ſhee laid; and ſtraite,</l>
                     <l>(O ſtrange effect) whether with the ſound it were</l>
                     <l>Of her ſoft murmur'd verſe of Magick powre,</l>
                     <l>Or rather (as I rather doe beleeue)</l>
                     <pb facs="tcp:177232:11"/>
                     <l>The vertue of her mouth,</l>
                     <l>That what it toucheth, cures, Phillis was cur'de;</l>
                     <l>And with the paine ſoone was the ſwelling gone.</l>
                     <l>I, that till then ne're dream't of more delight,</l>
                     <l>Then on the ſhine of her bright eyes to gaze,</l>
                     <l>And ioy to heare her ſpeake, (muſique more ſweete,</l>
                     <l>Then makes the murmur of a ſlow pac'de brooke,</l>
                     <l>When tis with thouſand little pebbles croſt;</l>
                     <l>Or the winde pratling' mongst the wanton leaues)</l>
                     <l>Gan then, eu'n then to feele a new deſire</l>
                     <l>Poſſeſſe me, of touching thoſe deare lips with mine;</l>
                     <l>And growne more ſuttle then I was before,</l>
                     <l>(So loue perhaps th'imagination whets,)</l>
                     <l>I found this new deceipt, whereby to 'aspire</l>
                     <l>With greater eaſe to th'end of my deſire;</l>
                     <l>I faynde my ſelfe ſtung on the nether lip,</l>
                     <l>In like ſort with a Bee as Phillis was;</l>
                     <l>And in ſuch manner gan to moane myſelfe,</l>
                     <l>As th'helpe my tongue crau'd not, my lookes implored;</l>
                     <l>The harmleſſe Siluia, pittying ſtratt my caſe,</l>
                     <l>Offred her ready cure to my fayn'd hurt;</l>
                     <l>But th' vnfayn'd wound I bleede of, deeper made,</l>
                     <l>And farre more deadly, when thoſe corall twinnes</l>
                     <l>On mine ſhee layd. Nor do the giddy Bees</l>
                     <l>Gather from any flowre honey ſo ſweete,</l>
                     <l>As I did from thoſe freſheſt roſes gather;</l>
                     <l>Though baſhfull ſhame, and feare had taught to barre,</l>
                     <l>Hot kiſſes from deſire to preſſe too farre,</l>
                     <pb facs="tcp:177232:11"/>
                     <l>T'imbathe themſelues; and did their heate withholde</l>
                     <l>And kill, or made them ſlower and leſſe bolde.</l>
                     <l>But while downe to my beart that ſweetneſſe glided,</l>
                     <l>Mixt with a ſecret poyſon, ſuch delight</l>
                     <l>I inly felt, that faigning ſtill the griefe</l>
                     <l>Of the ſting had not left me yet; ſo dealt,</l>
                     <l>That ſhee the charme repeated ſundry times:</l>
                     <l>Since when till now, ſtill more and more I finde,</l>
                     <l>For all her charme, ſhe'has left the ſting behinde.</l>
                     <l>Whoſe paine ere ſince hath ſo increas'd vpon me,</l>
                     <l>As my loue-labouring breaſt could hold no longer,</l>
                     <l>But that vpon a time, when diuers Nymphes</l>
                     <l>And Shepherds of vs in a ring were ſitting,</l>
                     <l>Whilſt the play was, each one ſhould ſoftly whiſper</l>
                     <l>Some word in th'eare of her that next him ſat;</l>
                     <l>Siluia (quoth I ſoft in her eare) for thee</l>
                     <l>I pine, and dye, vnleſſe thou pitty mee.</l>
                     <l>No ſooner heard ſhe this, but downe ſhe hangs</l>
                     <l>The faire looke, whence I might perceiue to breake</l>
                     <l>A ſuddaine and vnwonted ruddineſſe,</l>
                     <l>That ſeem'd to breat he forth anger mixt with ſhame;</l>
                     <l>Nor would ſhee' in other language anſwer mee,</l>
                     <l>Then ſuch a troubled ſilence, as appear'd</l>
                     <l>Threatning and deadly; nor ſince then would euer</l>
                     <l>Willingly ſee, or heare me: Thriſe the Sunne</l>
                     <l>His yearly courſe hath runne, thriſe the greene fields</l>
                     <l>Hath the nak'd Sythman barb'd; and three times hath</l>
                     <l>The Winter rob'd the trees of their greene lockes;</l>
                     <pb facs="tcp:177232:12"/>
                     <l>That I haue tryde all meanes I could, t'appeaſe her,</l>
                     <l>And nought remaines, but that I dye to pleaſe her;</l>
                     <l>And gladly would I dye, were I but ſure</l>
                     <l>'Twould either pleaſe, or but drawe pitty from her;</l>
                     <l>Each were a bleſsing to mee, though no doubt</l>
                     <l>Her pitty were of both the greater meede,</l>
                     <l>And worthyer recompenſe for all my loue,</l>
                     <l>And for my death; yet I were loth to wiſh</l>
                     <l>Ought, that too rudely might thoſe eyes moleſt,</l>
                     <l>Or do the leaſt offence to that deare breſt.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Thi:</speaker>
                     <l>Did ſhe but heare thus much from thee, beleeu'ſt thou</l>
                     <l>It would not make her loue, or pitty thee?</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Am:</speaker>
                     <l>I neither knowe, nor can I hope ſo much:</l>
                     <l>Shee flyes my ſpeech, as th' Adder doth the charme,</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Thi:</speaker>
                     <l>Well be of comfort; my minde giues mee yet,</l>
                     <l>Wee'll finde a meane that ſhe ſhall heare thee ſpeak</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Am:</speaker>
                     <l>'Twill come to nought; to begg ſuch grace were vaine,</l>
                     <l>For mee to ſpeake, where ſpeech no grace will gaine.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Thi:</speaker>
                     <l>For ſhame diſpaire not thus.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Ami:</speaker>
                     <l>Alas iuſt cauſe</l>
                     <l>Bids mee diſpaire; my cruell deſtinie</l>
                     <l>Was read by the graue Mopſo long agon,</l>
                     <l>Mopſo that knowes the hid language of birds,</l>
                     <l>And vnderſtands the force of herbes and founts.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Thi:</speaker>
                     <l>What Mopo's this thou ſpeak'ſt on? is't not he</l>
                     <l>That carryes honey in his ſupple tongue,</l>
                     <l>And friendly ſmiles for all he lookes vpon,</l>
                     <l>But in his heart deceipt, and hidden beares</l>
                     <l>Vnder his coate a raſor? ſhame befall him;</l>
                     <pb facs="tcp:177232:12"/>
                     <l>The vilde vnlucky doomes he lewdly ſells</l>
                     <l>To ſilly fooles with that graue looke, and grace,</l>
                     <l>Ar farr from trueth; take't of my word, and triall.</l>
                     <l>I'le rather hope (and ſure my hope will thriue)</l>
                     <l>That from this fellowes ydle auguryes</l>
                     <l>Much happyer fate will to thy loue ariſe.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Am:</speaker>
                     <l>If ought by proofe thou know'ſt of him, good ſwayne</l>
                     <l>Hyde it not from me?</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Thir:</speaker>
                     <l>Ile tell thee willingly.</l>
                     <l>When firſt my hap led mee to know theſe woods,</l>
                     <l>I knew this fellow, and eſteemed him</l>
                     <l>As thou do'ſt: So it fortun'd once, I had</l>
                     <l>Deſire and bus'neſſe to go ſee that great</l>
                     <l>Wonder of Citties, at whoſe ancient feete</l>
                     <l>The broad-fam'd riuer runnes; and him I made</l>
                     <l>Acquainted with my purpoſe: he replyes,</l>
                     <l>And thus began to preach; My ſonne beware</l>
                     <l>Now thou art going to that ſeate of fame,</l>
                     <l>Where thoſe deceiptfull crafty Cittizens,</l>
                     <l>And euill minded Courtiers liue, and wont</l>
                     <l>To ſcoffe at vs, and hould in ſuch a ſcorne</l>
                     <l>Our plaine diſtrnſtleſſe homely carriage;</l>
                     <l>Be well aduiz'd (my ſonne) and preſſe not there</l>
                     <l>Where the freſh colour'd robes with gould ar wrought,</l>
                     <l>Gay plumes, and dayly-varied dreſsings ſhine;</l>
                     <l>But aboue all, beware accurſed Fate,</l>
                     <l>Or thy youths iollity conduct thee not</l>
                     <l>Vnto that magazine of reſtleſſe chatt,</l>
                     <l>But flye that curſed and inchaunted place.</l>
                     <pb facs="tcp:177232:13"/>
                     <l>What place is that (quoth I?) 'tis there (ſaid he)</l>
                     <l>Where dwell th'inchantreſſes that haue the powre</l>
                     <l>And arte to make men, and their minds tranſparent;</l>
                     <l>And what ſo Diamonds ſeeme, and fineſt gold,</l>
                     <l>But glaſſe and copper ar; thoſe ſiluer cheſtes</l>
                     <l>That ſeeme full of rich treaſor, ar no more</l>
                     <l>Then kennells full of filth, and cozen men;</l>
                     <l>The walles ar built too with that wondrous arte,</l>
                     <l>That they will ſpeake, and anſwer them that ſpeake;</l>
                     <l>Nor in halfe words, and ſuch imperfect ſounds,</l>
                     <l>As wont the Eccos that heere haunt our grounds,</l>
                     <l>But eu'ry word whole, and entyre repeating:</l>
                     <l>Nay more then this, the tables, chaires, and ſtooles,</l>
                     <l>Hangings, and all that to each roome belongs,</l>
                     <l>Haue toung and voice, and neuer ſilent ar;</l>
                     <l>Falſe lyes there, formde into the ſhape of babes,</l>
                     <l>Ar hopping all about; and be he dumbe</l>
                     <l>That enters there, findes ſtraite a tongue to prate</l>
                     <l>And lye with; but there is yet worſe then this,</l>
                     <l>May happen thee; thou mayſt perhaps be turn'd</l>
                     <l>Into a beaſt, a tree, a floud, a flame,</l>
                     <l>Into a floud of teares, a fire of ſighes.</l>
                     <l>All this he tould mee; and I forward went</l>
                     <l>To ſee the Cittie with this falſe beliefe;</l>
                     <l>And (as good happ would haue it,) chaunc'd to paſse</l>
                     <l>Along the place where ſtands that bleſsed dwelling,</l>
                     <l>Whence I might heare breath out ſuch melody,</l>
                     <l>By Swans, and Nimphes, and heau'nly Syrens made,</l>
                     <pb facs="tcp:177232:13"/>
                     <l>With voyce ſo ſhrill, ſo ſweet and full of pleaſure,</l>
                     <l>That all amaz'd, I ſtay'd to gaze, and liſten:</l>
                     <l>Before the doore there ſtood (mee ſeem'd) as guard</l>
                     <l>Of the faire ſhowes within, a man in ſhowe</l>
                     <l>And of proportion ſtout, and knightly hue;</l>
                     <l>Such as (for what he ſeem'd me) made me doubt</l>
                     <l>Whether for Armes he were, or counſaile fitter:</l>
                     <l>With a benigne, and milde, though graue aſpect,</l>
                     <l>He highly-faire beſpake, and led me in;</l>
                     <l>He great in place, mee poore and homely man:</l>
                     <l>But then, what did I ſee? what did I heare?</l>
                     <l>Celeſtiall goddeſſes, and louely Nimphes,</l>
                     <l>New lights, new <hi>Orpheuſſes;</hi> and others too</l>
                     <l>Vnuayl'd vnclouded, as the virgin-morne,</l>
                     <l>When ſiluer dewes her golden rayes adorne.</l>
                     <l>There <hi>Phaebus</hi> ſhone, inlightning all about,</l>
                     <l>With all his ſiſter Muſes; among whom</l>
                     <l>Satt Elpine; at which ſight, all in a trice</l>
                     <l>I felt my ſelfe growe greater then my ſelfe,</l>
                     <l>Full of new powre, full of new diety?</l>
                     <l>And ſang of warres, and Knightly deedes in Armes,</l>
                     <l>Scorning the rurall Songs I wont to make;</l>
                     <l>And though I after did (for others pleaſure)</l>
                     <l>Turne to theſe woods againe, yet I retaynde</l>
                     <l>Part of that Spirit; nor yet ſounds my pipe</l>
                     <l>So lowly as before, but ſhriller farr.</l>
                     <l>And through the woods rings with a trumpets voyce.</l>
                     <pb facs="tcp:177232:14"/>
                     <l>Afterward Mopſo heard me'; and with ſo vilde,</l>
                     <l>And ſowre a count'nance greeted mee, that I</l>
                     <l>Became ſtraite hoarce, and was a long time mute;</l>
                     <l>When all the Shepherds ſaid, ſure I had bin</l>
                     <l>Scar'd with the Wolfe; but Mopſo was the Wolfe.</l>
                     <l>This I haue tould thee, that thou mayſt beleeue</l>
                     <l>How little this mans words deſerue beliefe;</l>
                     <l>And out of doubt, th'haſt the more cauſe to hope,</l>
                     <l>For that this fellow bids thee not to hope.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Am:</speaker>
                     <l>I'me glad to heare this troth of him; but now</l>
                     <l>I leaue my life, and my liues care to you.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Thi:</speaker>
                     <l>Feare not 'tis all my care to cure thy paine:</l>
                     <l>Within this boure ſee thou be here againe.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Chorus.</speaker>
                     <l>O Happy Age of Gould; happy' houres;</l>
                     <l>Not for with milke the riuers ranne,</l>
                     <l>And hunny dropt from eu'ry tree;</l>
                     <l>Nor that the Earth bore fruits, and flowres,</l>
                     <l>Without the toyle or care of Man,</l>
                     <l>And Serpents were from poyſon free;</l>
                     <l>Nor for th' Ayre (euer calme to ſee)</l>
                     <l>Had quite exil'de the lowring Night;</l>
                     <l>Whilſt clad in an eternall Spring</l>
                     <l>(Now fiery hott, or elſe freezing)</l>
                     <l>The cheekes of heau'n ſmil'de with cleare light;</l>
                     <l>Nor that the wandring Pine of yore</l>
                     <l>Brought neither warres, nor wares from forraine ſhore;</l>
                     <pb facs="tcp:177232:14"/>
                     <l>But therefore only happy Dayes,</l>
                     <l>Becauſe that vaine and ydle name,</l>
                     <l>That couz'ning I doll of vnreſt,</l>
                     <l>(Whom the madd vulgar firſt did raize,</l>
                     <l>And call'd it <hi>Honour,</hi> whence it came</l>
                     <l>To tyrannize or'e eu'ry breſt,)</l>
                     <l>Was then ſuffred to moleſt</l>
                     <l>Poore louers hearts with new debate;</l>
                     <l>More happy they, by theſe his hard</l>
                     <l>And cruell lawes, were not debar'd</l>
                     <l>Their innate freedome; happy ſtate;</l>
                     <l>The goulden lawes of Nature, they</l>
                     <l>Found in their breſts; and then they did obey.</l>
                     <l>Amidd the ſiluer ſtreames and floures,</l>
                     <l>The winged <hi>Genii</hi> then would daunce,</l>
                     <l>Without their bowe, without their brande;</l>
                     <l>The Nymphes ſate by their Paramours,</l>
                     <l>Whiſpring loue-ſports, and dalliance,</l>
                     <l>And ioyning lips, and hand to hand;</l>
                     <l>The faireſt Virgin in the land.</l>
                     <l>Nor ſcorn'de, nor glor'yed to diſplaye</l>
                     <l>Her cheekes freſh roſes to the eye,</l>
                     <l>Or ope her faire breſts to the day,</l>
                     <l>(Which now adayes ſo vailed lye,)</l>
                     <l>But men and maydens ſpent free houres</l>
                     <l>In running Riuers, Lakes, or ſhady Bowres.</l>
                     <l>Thou <hi>Honour,</hi> thou didſt firſt deuize</l>
                     <l>To maske the face of Pleaſure thus;</l>
                     <pb facs="tcp:177232:15"/>
                     <l>Barr water to the thirſt of Loue,</l>
                     <l>And lewdly didſt inſtruct faire eyes</l>
                     <l>They ſhould be nyce, and ſcrupulous,</l>
                     <l>And from the gazing world remooue</l>
                     <l>Their beauties; thy hands new netts woue</l>
                     <l>T'intrap the wilde curles, faire diſpred</l>
                     <l>To th'open ayre; thou mad'ſt the ſweet</l>
                     <l>Delights of Loue ſeeme thus vnmeete;</l>
                     <l>And (teaching how to looke, ſpeake, tread,)</l>
                     <l>By thy ill lawes this ill haſt left,</l>
                     <l>That what was firſt Loues gift, is now our theft.</l>
                     <l>Nor ought thy mighty working brings,</l>
                     <l>But more annoyes, and woe to vs;</l>
                     <l>But thou (of Nature and of Loue</l>
                     <l>The Lord, and ſcourge of mighty Kings,)</l>
                     <l>Why do'ſt thou ſhrowde thy greatneſſe thus</l>
                     <l>In our poore cells? hence, and remooue</l>
                     <l>Thy powre; and it diſplay aboue.</l>
                     <l>Diſturbing great ones in their ſleepe;</l>
                     <l>And let vs meaner men alone</l>
                     <l>T'inioye againe, (when thou art gone)</l>
                     <l>And lawes of our Forefathers keepe.</l>
                     <l>Liue we in loue, for our liues houres</l>
                     <l>Haſt on to death, that all at length deuoures.</l>
                     <l>Liue we while we may; the wayne</l>
                     <l>Of Heau'n can ſet, and riſe againe;</l>
                     <l>But we (when once we looze this light)</l>
                     <l>Muſt yeeld vs to a neuer ending Night.</l>
                  </sp>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div n="2" type="act">
               <pb facs="tcp:177232:15"/>
               <head>Actus Secundus.</head>
               <div n="1" type="scene">
                  <head>Scena Prima.</head>
                  <stage>
                     <hi>Satyr</hi> ſolus.</stage>
                  <sp>
                     <l>SMall is the Bee; but yet with his ſmall ſting</l>
                     <l>Does greater miſchiefe, then a greater thing.</l>
                     <l>But what of all things can be leſſe then Loue,</l>
                     <l>That through ſo narrow paſſages can pierce,</l>
                     <l>And in ſo narrow roome lye hid? ſometime</l>
                     <l>Vnder the ſhaddow of an eye-lids fault,</l>
                     <l>Now in the ſmall curle of a ſhining treſſe,</l>
                     <l>Now in the little pitts which forme ſweet ſmiles</l>
                     <l>In an inamo'ring checke; yet makes ſo deepe,</l>
                     <l>So deadly and immedicable wounds.</l>
                     <l>Ay me my brest is all one bleeding wound;</l>
                     <l>A thouſand armed darts alas are lodg'd</l>
                     <l>By that fell tyrant Loue in Siluia's eyes;</l>
                     <l>Cruell Loue, cruell Siluia, ſauadger</l>
                     <l>Then the wilde deſarts; O how well thy name</l>
                     <l>Sutes with thy nature (Siluan as thou art)</l>
                     <l>The woods vnder their greene roofes hide the Snake,</l>
                     <l>The Beare, the Lyon; and thou in thy breſt</l>
                     <l>Hydest diſdaine, hate, and impietie,</l>
                     <l>More balefull then the Lion, Beare, or Snake;</l>
                     <l>For they will ſomeway be reclaim'de; thou neither</l>
                     <l>With prayers or gifts; Alas when I preſent thee</l>
                     <l>Freſh floures, thou frowardly refuſest them;</l>
                     <pb facs="tcp:177232:16"/>
                     <l>Perhaps becauſe th'haſt in thy louely face,</l>
                     <l>Fairer then thoſe; Alas when I preſent thee</l>
                     <l>Faire Apples, thou do'ſt ſcornfully reiect them;</l>
                     <l>Perhaps becauſe thy boſome beares a paire</l>
                     <l>Fairer then thoſe; Ay mee when I preſent thee</l>
                     <l>Sweet honey, thou diſdainfully deny'ſt it,</l>
                     <l>Perhaps becauſe thy lips breathe ſweeter honey</l>
                     <l>Then the Bee makes; but if my pouerty</l>
                     <l>Can giue thee nought that thou haſt not more faire,</l>
                     <l>And louely in thy ſelfe, my ſelfe I giue thee;</l>
                     <l>But thou vniuſt ſcorn'ſt, and abhorr'ſt the gift.</l>
                     <l>Yet I'me not ſo fowle, to be ſo diſpiz'de,</l>
                     <l>If well I mark'd my ſelfe, when th'other day</l>
                     <l>I view'd my ſhadowe in the watry mayne,</l>
                     <l>When the winde blew not, and the ſea lay ſtill.</l>
                     <l>The manly tincture of my ſanguine brow,</l>
                     <l>Theſe muſcled armes, and ſhoulders large enough;</l>
                     <l>This hairy breſt of mine, and hory thyes</l>
                     <l>Proclaime my able force, and manly hood;</l>
                     <l>Make triall of mee if thou doubt'ſt of it.</l>
                     <l>What wilt thou do with theſe ſame tenderlings,</l>
                     <l>On whoſe bare cheeke the young downe ſcarſely ſprings?</l>
                     <l>With what an art they place their haire in order?</l>
                     <l>Women in ſhew, and women in their ſtrength.</l>
                     <l>Tell mee, who wilt thou haue to follow thee</l>
                     <l>O're the bald hills, and through the leauy woods,</l>
                     <l>And fight for thee with Beare, and armed Bore?</l>
                     <l>No no, my ſhape's not it thou hat'ſt mee for,</l>
                     <pb facs="tcp:177232:16"/>
                     <l>But 'tis my pouerty thou doſt abhorre.</l>
                     <l>Ah that poore Cottages will follow ſtill</l>
                     <l>Great Townes example in what ere is ill;</l>
                     <l>This may be truely call'd the Golden age,</l>
                     <l>For gould alone preuailes, gould only raynes.</l>
                     <l>O thou (who ere thou wert) that firſt didſt teach</l>
                     <l>To ſell loue thus, accurſed be thy duſt.</l>
                     <l>And thy colde buried bones; nor euer may</l>
                     <l>Shepherd or Nimphe ſay to them, reſt in peace;</l>
                     <l>But be they waſht with raines, and toſt with windes,</l>
                     <l>And may the paſſers by, and all the rout</l>
                     <l>Of beaſts with fowle feete ſpurne them all about.</l>
                     <l>Baſe mercinary loue, thou haſt deflour'd</l>
                     <l>Loues nobleneſſe; and turn'd his happy ioyes</l>
                     <l>Into ſuch bitterneſſe, and ſharpe annoyes.</l>
                     <l>Loue to be ſlaue to golde? O miracle</l>
                     <l>More odious, and abominable farre</l>
                     <l>Then the large earth produces, or the Mayne.</l>
                     <l>But why alas, why do I vexe my ſelfe</l>
                     <l>Thus all in vaine? no, let each creature vſe</l>
                     <l>Thoſe armes that Nature for his ayde hath giu'n him,</l>
                     <l>The Hart his ſpeede, the Lyon his ſtrong pawe,</l>
                     <l>The foaming Bore his tuske; the womans armes</l>
                     <l>And powre lye in her beauty', and gracefull ſhape;</l>
                     <l>I, ſince my ſtrength is the beſt helpe I haue,</l>
                     <l>And am by nature fit for deedes of force,</l>
                     <l>Will for reward of all my loue miſpent,</l>
                     <l>Force this proud cruell to my owne content.</l>
                     <pb facs="tcp:177232:17"/>
                     <l>And by ſo much as I can vnderſtand,</l>
                     <l>(As yon Goteherd that hath obſeru'd her wayes</l>
                     <l>Hath lately tolde me) ſhe doth oft repaire</l>
                     <l>To'a water-fount to waſh her ſelfe; the place</l>
                     <l>He made me knowe, and there I meane to lye</l>
                     <l>Cloſe in a thickett neere, t'attend her comming,</l>
                     <l>And as occaſion fits, I'le make her myne,</l>
                     <l>What can ſhe do then, what auayle alas</l>
                     <l>Can her hands giue her, or her leggs to flye</l>
                     <l>(Poore wretch) from me ſo forcible, and ſwift?</l>
                     <l>Let her a good yeere weepe, and ſigh, and rayle,</l>
                     <l>And put on all the powre her beauty hath;</l>
                     <l>If once I catch her by the ſnary curles,</l>
                     <l>We will not part in haſt, till I haue bath'd</l>
                     <l>(For my reuenge) my armes in her warme bloud.</l>
                  </sp>
               </div>
               <div n="2" type="scene">
                  <head>Actus Secundus. Scen: Secunda.</head>
                  <stage>Daphne. Thirſis.</stage>
                  <sp>
                     <l>THirſis (as I haue tolde thee) well I knowe</l>
                     <l>How well, Aminta Siluia loues; heau'n knowes</l>
                     <l>How many friendly offices I haue,</l>
                     <l>And will do for him; and ſo much the rather</l>
                     <l>For that thou do'ſt intreate in his behalfe;</l>
                     <l>But I would ſooner take in hand to tame</l>
                     <l>A Beare, or Tygar then a fond young wench;</l>
                     <l>The ſilly thing (ſimple as faire) ſees not</l>
                     <pb facs="tcp:177232:17"/>
                     <l>How ſharpe and burning be her beauties rayes,</l>
                     <l>But ſmiles or cries; yet wounds where ere ſhee goe,</l>
                     <l>And fondly knowes not if ſhee hurt or no.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Thi:</speaker>
                     <l>Tuſh there's no wench ſo ſimple but ſhee knowes</l>
                     <l>Soone as ſhee leaues the cradle, how to ſeeme</l>
                     <l>Spruce, and delightfull; and what armes to vſe</l>
                     <l>To hurte, or kill outright, and what to heale</l>
                     <l>A wounded heart, and giue it life withall.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Da:</speaker>
                     <l>What Master is't that ſhewes 'hem all theſe arts?</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Thi:</speaker>
                     <l>He that inſtructs the birds to ſing and flye;</l>
                     <l>The Fiſh to ſwimme, the Ramme to butt, the Bull</l>
                     <l>To vſe his horne, the Peacocke to diſplay</l>
                     <l>His many-ey'ed-plumes beautie to the day.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Da:</speaker>
                     <l>How name you this ſame teacher?</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Thi:</speaker>
                     <l>H'has a name.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Da:</speaker>
                     <l>Go trifler.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Thi:</speaker>
                     <l>Why I pre'thee art not thou</l>
                     <l>Fitt enough to teach twenty girles their leſſons?</l>
                     <l>I'le warrant thee, I; and yet to ſpeake the troth</l>
                     <l>They neede no teacher; Nature teacheth them</l>
                     <l>Although the nurſe and mother haue a part.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Da:</speaker>
                     <l>Come y'ar vnhappy; but in earnest now</l>
                     <l>I'me not reſolu'd Siluia ſo ſimple is</l>
                     <l>As by her words ſhee ſeemes; for th'other day</l>
                     <l>One deede of hers put me in doubt of her:</l>
                     <l>I found her in thoſe broad fields neere the towne,</l>
                     <l>Where amongst drown'de grounds, lies a little Iſle,</l>
                     <l>And round about, a water cleare, and calme;</l>
                     <l>There o're ſhee hung her head; and ſeem'd (me thought)</l>
                     <l>Full proud to ſee her ſelfe, and tooke aduice</l>
                     <pb facs="tcp:177232:18"/>
                     <l>O'th'water, in what order beſt to lay</l>
                     <l>Her locks, and them about her brow diſplay,</l>
                     <l>And ouer them her vaile, and ouer that</l>
                     <l>The flowres ſhee carried in her lapp; now heere</l>
                     <l>Shee hung a Lilly, there ſhee ſtuck a Roſe;</l>
                     <l>Then layd them to her neck, and to her cheeke,</l>
                     <l>As to try whethers hew the other paſt;</l>
                     <l>At laſt, (as ioyfull of the victory)</l>
                     <l>Shee ſmiling ſeem'd to ſay, the day is mine;</l>
                     <l>Nor do I weare you for my ornament,</l>
                     <l>But for your owne diſgrace (counterfait floures)</l>
                     <l>To ſhew how much my beauty paſſeth yours.</l>
                     <l>But while ſhee thus ſtood decking of her ſelfe,</l>
                     <l>Shee turn'd her eye by chance, and ſoone had found</l>
                     <l>That I had noted her, and bluſht a mayne,</l>
                     <l>Downe fell her flowres; I laught to ſee her bluſh;</l>
                     <l>And ſhe bluſht more, perceiuing that I laught;</l>
                     <l>But, (for of one ſide of her face, the haire</l>
                     <l>Was hung abroad, and th'other not,) ſhee turnes</l>
                     <l>To th'water once on twice, to mend the fault,</l>
                     <l>And gaz'd as 'twere by ſtealth, (fearfull belike</l>
                     <l>That I too neerly ey'd her,) where ſhe ſawe</l>
                     <l>Her haire (though orderleſſe, yet) hanging ſo,</l>
                     <l>As grac'd her well; I ſaw, and ſaw her not.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Thi:</speaker>
                     <l>All this I will beleeue: gueſt I not well?</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Da:</speaker>
                     <l>Thou didſt: but yet I will be bolde to ſay</l>
                     <l>That I haue ſeldome ſeene a Shepherdeſſe</l>
                     <l>Or Nimph what euer of her yeares diſcreeter;</l>
                     <pb facs="tcp:177232:18"/>
                     <l>Nor was I ſuch when I was of her yeares:</l>
                     <l>The world growes olde, and of a troth I thinke</l>
                     <l>It growes as ill as olde.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Thi:</speaker>
                     <l>True; heretofore</l>
                     <l>Thoſe of the Cittie were not wont ſo much</l>
                     <l>To haunt theſe woods as now adayes they do,</l>
                     <l>Nor meaner people in the village bredd,</l>
                     <l>To come ſo much among the cittizens;</l>
                     <l>Their blouds are now more mingled, and their cu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtomes.</l>
                     <l>But leaue we this diſcourſe; and tell me now</l>
                     <l>Could'st thou not finde a time Aminta might</l>
                     <l>Either alone, or in thy preſence come</l>
                     <l>To ſpeake to Siluia?</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Da:</speaker>
                     <l>I cannot tell;</l>
                     <l>Siluia is nyce and ſtrange beyond all meaſure.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Thi:</speaker>
                     <l>And he nicely respest full beyond meaſure.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Da:</speaker>
                     <l>He's i'the wrong then, fye on ſuch a louer;</l>
                     <l>Nice (quoth you?) counſel him to leaue that vice,</l>
                     <l>If he will learne to loue; he muſt be bould,</l>
                     <l>And vrge with speeding importunitie;</l>
                     <l>Let him a little filtch; if that be vaine,</l>
                     <l>Then rauiſh: tush know'ſt thou what women ar?</l>
                     <l>They flye; but eu'ry ſtep wish to be tane;</l>
                     <l>What they denie, they wish were ſnatcht fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> them;</l>
                     <l>They fight, but ſtill wiſh to be ouercome.</l>
                     <l>I tell thee this Thirſis, but in thine eare:</l>
                     <l>Blabb not what I' ſay to thee', I cannot ſpeake</l>
                     <l>Inrime (thou know'ſt) but if I could, I'de ſay</l>
                     <l>Somewhat more worth then rime to beare away.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Thi:</speaker>
                     <l>Feare not, I will not ſpeake</l>
                     <pb facs="tcp:177232:19"/>
                     <l>Ought from thy lips what ere they ope to me.</l>
                     <l>But gentle Daphne, for the deare dayes ſake</l>
                     <l>Of thy paſt youth, helpe me to helpe Aminte</l>
                     <l>Poore wretch that dyes.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Dap:</speaker>
                     <l>Ah what a propper ſtile</l>
                     <l>Of coniuration (foole) haſt thou deuiz'd</l>
                     <l>To mooue me with; bringing my youth to minde,</l>
                     <l>The pleaſure I haue loſt, and paine I finde.</l>
                     <l>But what would'ſt haue me doe?</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Thi:</speaker>
                     <l>Th'art not to ſeeke of wit, nor yet of powre,</l>
                     <l>Do but diſpoſe thy will, I'le aske no more.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Da:</speaker>
                     <l>Well then, I'le tell thee: wee ar going now</l>
                     <l>Siluia and I together all alone</l>
                     <l>Vnto Diana's fount, to waſh our ſelues;</l>
                     <l>There where the planetree with his ſafer ſhade</l>
                     <l>Ore-ſpreds the coole ſtreame, and is wont t'inuite</l>
                     <l>The weary huntreſſes to reſt, and coole them:</l>
                     <l>There ſhee'll vncaſe her ſo-beloued limbs.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Thi:</speaker>
                     <l>And what of that?</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Da:</speaker>
                     <l>What of that? ſilly th'art</l>
                     <l>Or elſe thou would'ſt not aske me what of that.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Thi:</speaker>
                     <l>Suppoſe I hit thy meaning, who knowes yet</l>
                     <l>If he will dare to meete her there or no?</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Da:</speaker>
                     <l>No? Why then truely let him ſtay till ſhee</l>
                     <l>Come to woee him; and when will that be trow yee?</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Thi:</speaker>
                     <l>Do ſhee or not, he does deſerue ſhee did.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Da:</speaker>
                     <l>But now let's leaue this theame; and talk a word</l>
                     <l>Or two of thee; ſay Thirſis, wilt not thou</l>
                     <l>Reſolue at laſt to be a louer too?</l>
                     <l>Th'art not yet olde; fewe more then thirty yeeres</l>
                     <pb facs="tcp:177232:19"/>
                     <l>Haue ouer-ſlipt thee, and I well remember</l>
                     <l>Thy infancie; wilt thou liue ioyleſſe ſtill?</l>
                     <l>For only 'a louers is the happy life.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Thi:</speaker>
                     <l>The ioyes of Venus he inioyes as well,</l>
                     <l>That ſhunning louers painfull miſeries,</l>
                     <l>Taſtes of the ſweet, and lets the ſowre alone.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Da:</speaker>
                     <l>O but that ſweet growes dull, and gluts betime,</l>
                     <l>That is not ſeas'ned with a little ſowre.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Thi:</speaker>
                     <l>Better 'tis to be glutted (of the two)</l>
                     <l>Then pine before one feedes, and after two.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Da:</speaker>
                     <l>But if the foode be pleaſing, and poſſeſt,</l>
                     <l>'Tis good before; and in the taſting beſt.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Thi:</speaker>
                     <l>No man can ſo poſſeſſe what he deſires,</l>
                     <l>As iuſt t'inioy it then when's hunger craues it.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Da:</speaker>
                     <l>Who hopes to finde, that neuer meanes to ſeeke?</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Thi:</speaker>
                     <l>'Tis dangerous to ſeeke that which once found,</l>
                     <l>Pleaſes a little, but not found, torments</l>
                     <l>Much more; no, no, I'le go no more a wooing;</l>
                     <l>Cupid ſhall triumph ouer me no more;</l>
                     <l>I know a little what thoſe ſuffrings be,</l>
                     <l>Let others prooue them if they liſt for me.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Da:</speaker>
                     <l>Belike th'haſt not inioy'd loues pleaſure yet:</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Thi:</speaker>
                     <l>Nor do I wiſh to buy the plague ſo deare.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Da:</speaker>
                     <l>You may perhaps be forc'd againſt your will;</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Thi:</speaker>
                     <l>Who keepes himſelfe farr off, cannot be forc'd.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Da:</speaker>
                     <l>Who can be far fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> loue?</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Thi:</speaker>
                     <l>Who feares &amp; flies.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Da:</speaker>
                     <l>But what auayles to flye from him hath wings?</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Thi:</speaker>
                     <l>Loue but new borne, hath wings but ſhort &amp; ſmall,</l>
                     <pb facs="tcp:177232:20"/>
                     <l>And hardly ſtrong enough to flye with all.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Da:</speaker>
                     <l>Be'ing young, we know him not; but after, long;</l>
                     <l>And when we feele him once, he's growne too ſtrong.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Thi:</speaker>
                     <l>Not if we neuer felt him grow before.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Da:</speaker>
                     <l>Well; yee ſhall hau't; wee'll ſee how well you will</l>
                     <l>Bridle your eye and heart; but I protest</l>
                     <l>Since thou canſt play both Hound and Hare ſo well,</l>
                     <l>If ere I heare thee call and cry for helpe,</l>
                     <l>I will not mooue a foote, nor yet a finger,</l>
                     <l>Nor ſtirr an eye, nor ſpeake a word for thee.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Thi:</speaker>
                     <l>Would'st haue the heart (cruell) to ſee me dye?</l>
                     <l>If thou wouldſt haue me loue, why loue thou mee,</l>
                     <l>And lett's now make a louing bargaine on't.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Da:</speaker>
                     <l>Away you mock me now; well well, perhaps</l>
                     <l>You do not merit ſuch a loue as mine.</l>
                     <l>I'ue ſeene many a ladd as fine as you</l>
                     <l>Deceiu'd with a faire ſeeming painted face.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Thi:</speaker>
                     <l>I doe not jest nor mock thee; this is but</l>
                     <l>A couler now to barr me louing thee,</l>
                     <l>As 'tis the cuſtome of you all to do:</l>
                     <l>But if you will not loue me, I'm content,</l>
                     <l>To liue ſtill as I do.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Da:</speaker>
                     <l>I, liue ſo ſtill,</l>
                     <l>Happyer then twenty others; liue in eaſe;</l>
                     <l>Perhaps vnwares eaſe may ingender loue.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Thi:</speaker>
                     <l>O Daphne, a God this eaſe hath bred mee; he</l>
                     <l>That hath appear'd a ſecond god to mee</l>
                     <l>By whom ſo many heards and flocks ar fedd</l>
                     <pb facs="tcp:177232:20"/>
                     <l>From th'one to th'other Sea, vpon the faire</l>
                     <l>And fruitfull Plaines, and on the craggy backs</l>
                     <l>Of the ſteepe <hi>Apenines:</hi> he ſaid to mee,</l>
                     <l>When as he made me his; Thirſis (quoth he)</l>
                     <l>Let others chaſe the Wolfe, and Thiefe, and keepe</l>
                     <l>A watchfull eye ouer my walled ſheepe;</l>
                     <l>Let others care be to reward, or puniſh</l>
                     <l>My Ministers; let others feede and tende</l>
                     <l>My flocks, and keep the accoumpt of milke &amp; wooll;</l>
                     <l>And take, and pay: take thou thine eaſe, and ſing,</l>
                     <l>Wherefore 'tis reaſon good, I let goe by</l>
                     <l>All looſer ſtraines, and vainer carrolings;</l>
                     <l>And ſing his Aunceſters, and their high praiſe,</l>
                     <l>Who is to me <hi>Ioue,</hi> and <hi>Apollo</hi> both;</l>
                     <l>Since in his lookes and deeds he both reſembles</l>
                     <l>Iſſue of <hi>Saturne</hi> and of Heau'ne. Poore Muſe</l>
                     <l>To meane for ſuch a taske; and yet how e're</l>
                     <l>Horce voic'd, or clere ſhe ſings, he not contemns her.</l>
                     <l>I ſing not him, too high for my lowe rimes,</l>
                     <l>Whom ſilent adoration onely can</l>
                     <l>Worthily honour; but ſtill ſhall his altars</l>
                     <l>Be ſprinckled with my floures, and ne're without</l>
                     <l>My humble Incenſe fuming all about.</l>
                     <l>Which ſimple (yet deuoute) religion in me</l>
                     <l>When it ſhall leaue my heart, the Harts ſhal feede</l>
                     <l>
                        <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>n th'ayre on ayre; and ſo the flouds ſhall change</l>
                     <l>
                        <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>heir bedd, and courſe; that <hi>Sone</hi> ſhall <hi>Perſia</hi> greete,</l>
                     <l>
                        <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>nd the large <hi>Tigris</hi> beat the French-<hi>Alpes</hi> feete.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <pb facs="tcp:177232:21"/>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Da:</speaker>
                     <l>O thou fly'ſt high; pre'thee deſcend a little,</l>
                     <l>And to our purpoſe.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Thi:</speaker>
                     <l>Then heere lyes the poynt;</l>
                     <l>That as thou go'st with her vnto the fount,</l>
                     <l>Thou vſe thy beſt cunning to make her comming,</l>
                     <l>And heare Aminta ſpeake; meane time my care</l>
                     <l>Shall be to make Aminta meete you there.</l>
                     <l>I feare my taske will be the hard'ſt of both.</l>
                     <l>Onn then o' Gods name.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Da:</speaker>
                     <l>Yes, I goe; but Thirſis,</l>
                     <l>Wee were diſcourſing of an other matter.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Thi:</speaker>
                     <l>If mine eye faile me not, yon ſame ſhould be</l>
                     <l>Aminta, that comes hitherward; 'tis he.</l>
                  </sp>
               </div>
               <div n="3" type="scene">
                  <head>Actus Secundus. Scena Tertia.</head>
                  <stage>Aminta. Thirſis.</stage>
                  <sp>
                     <l>NOw ſhall I ſee what Thirſi' has done for me;</l>
                     <l>And if he haue done nothing, ere my woes</l>
                     <l>Melt me'into nothing, I'le go kill my ſelfe</l>
                     <l>Before the proud face of that cruell mayde,</l>
                     <l>That ſo delights to ſee my hearts deepe wound</l>
                     <l>Made by her murth'ring eyes, as ſure it can</l>
                     <l>Pleaſe her no leſſe, to ſee her ſad command</l>
                     <l>Fulfill'd on my owne breſt with my owne hand.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Thi:</speaker>
                     <l>Newes, newes Aminta, happy newes I bring thee;</l>
                     <l>Cleare then thy browe, and caſt thy griefes away.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <pb facs="tcp:177232:21"/>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Am:</speaker>
                     <l>What is't thou ſayſt Thirſis, what bringſt thou me,</l>
                     <l>Life, or death? new ioy, or new miſerie?</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Thi:</speaker>
                     <l>I bring thee life and ioy, if thou but dare</l>
                     <l>To goe and meet them; but I tell thee true</l>
                     <l>Thou muſt not faint but play the man Aminta.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Am:</speaker>
                     <l>Why againſt whom ſhould I aduance my force?</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Thi:</speaker>
                     <l>Suppoſe the Nymphe thou lou'ſt were in a wood</l>
                     <l>That (wal'de about with mountaines of ſharpe briars)</l>
                     <l>Were full of Tygars, and of greedy Lyons,</l>
                     <l>Wouldſt thou go thither?</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Am:</speaker>
                     <l>Yes, more cheerefully,</l>
                     <l>Then village-laſſe to the daunce o'holly dayes.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Thi:</speaker>
                     <l>Were ſhe ingag'd 'mongſt troopes of armed theeues,</l>
                     <l>VVould'ſt thou goe thither?</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Am:</speaker>
                     <l>Yes more greedily,</l>
                     <l>Then runnes the thirſtie Hart to the coole ſtreeme.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Thi:</speaker>
                     <l>O but a harder taske askes greater labour.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Am:</speaker>
                     <l>Why I would paſſe through the deuouring torre<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ts,</l>
                     <l>VVhen the diſſolu'de ſnowes downe the mountaines raine:</l>
                     <l>And headlong runne t'ingulph them in the mayne:</l>
                     <l>Or through the fire; or indeed downe to hell;</l>
                     <l>If any place a hell may termed bee,</l>
                     <l>That ſhall containe ſo heau'nly a thing as ſhee.</l>
                     <l>But pre'thee tell me all.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Thi:</speaker>
                     <l>Here then.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Am:</speaker>
                     <l>Say on.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Thi:</speaker>
                     <l>Siluia' at a Fount, ſtarnak'd, and all alone</l>
                     <l>Attends thy comming; dare'ſt thou now goe thither?</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Am:</speaker>
                     <l>Siluia? and all alone? and ſtaies for me?</l>
                  </sp>
                  <pb facs="tcp:177232:22"/>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Thi:</speaker>
                     <l>Yes all alone, vnleſſe haply there bee</l>
                     <l>Daphne', who thou know'ſt is all in all for thee. (ah do not</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Am:</speaker>
                     <l>Naked?</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Thir:</speaker>
                     <l>I, naked, but.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Am:</speaker>
                     <l>But what?</l>
                     <l>Mangle me thus.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Thir:</speaker>
                     <l>Why but ſhe does not knowe</l>
                     <l>That you ſhould meete her there; though (as I ſay)</l>
                     <l>Shee'll there attend you, do but haſt away.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Am:</speaker>
                     <l>Bitter concluſion; that infects, and poyſons</l>
                     <l>What euer ſweet thy former ſpeeches promis'd,</l>
                     <l>Why with ſuch art</l>
                     <l>Do'ſt thou delude me, cruell as thou art?</l>
                     <l>Is't not enough</l>
                     <l>Think'ſt thou for me thus full of griefe to be,</l>
                     <l>But thou muſt come to mock my miſery?</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Thi:</speaker>
                     <l>Be rul'd by me Aminta, and be happy;</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Am:</speaker>
                     <l>What ſhould I doe?</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Thi:</speaker>
                     <l>Why not let ſlip that good</l>
                     <l>That fortune (much thy friend) preſents thee with.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Am:</speaker>
                     <l>The beau'ns forbid that euer I ſhould do</l>
                     <l>Ought to diſpleaſe her; nor yet euer did I</l>
                     <l>The thing that iuſtly merited her frowne;</l>
                     <l>Vuleſſe it were my louing her ſo much;</l>
                     <l>Which yet if'twere a fault, was none of mine;</l>
                     <l>It was her beauties; and by beau'n I vowe</l>
                     <l>I meane not to begin to'offend her now.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Thi:</speaker>
                     <l>Why but yet tell me, if'twere in thy powre</l>
                     <l>To leaue to loue her, wouldſt thou do't to pleaſe her?</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Am:</speaker>
                     <l>No ſure; loue will not let me ſay, or thinke</l>
                     <l>That ere I ſhould deſist from louing her,</l>
                     <pb facs="tcp:177232:22"/>
                     <l>Though'twere in my owne powre.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Thi:</speaker>
                     <l>Why an't be ſo,</l>
                     <l>In her diſpight whether ſhe will or no,</l>
                     <l>Youl'd loue her,</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Am:</speaker>
                     <l>No, no, not in ſpight of her,</l>
                     <l>But I would loue her.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Thi:</speaker>
                     <l>Yet againſt her will?</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Am:</speaker>
                     <l>Why yes, againſt her will.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Thi:</speaker>
                     <l>And wherefore then</l>
                     <l>Dare you not take of her againſt her will,</l>
                     <l>That which (although't erkes thee at firſt to doo)</l>
                     <l>In th'end will quite thy paines and pleaſe her too.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Am:</speaker>
                     <l>Thirſis, let loue that ſpeakes within my breſt</l>
                     <l>Make anſwer for me; thou, (through thy long vſe</l>
                     <l>Of reas'ning much of loue) too ſuttle art</l>
                     <l>For me; loue tyes my tongue, who tyed my heart.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Thi:</speaker>
                     <l>Why then thou wilt not goe?</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Am:</speaker>
                     <l>Yes, yes, I'le goe;</l>
                     <l>But not where you would haue me:</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Thi:</speaker>
                     <l>Whether then?</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Am?</speaker>
                     <l>To death; if this be all y'haue done for me.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Thi:</speaker>
                     <l>Is this that I haue done then nothing worth?</l>
                     <l>And do'ſt thou thinke Daphne would counſaile thee</l>
                     <l>To goe, vnleſſe ſhee ſaw a little more</l>
                     <l>Into thy Siluias heart, then thou and I?</l>
                     <l>Suppoſe ſhee has reueal'd her minde to her;</l>
                     <l>Thinke you ſhee would abide that any elſe</l>
                     <l>Should know't? or know ſhe knew it ere the more?</l>
                     <l>So that to couet an expreſſe conſent</l>
                     <l>On her part, thinke you not it were to ſeeke</l>
                     <l>What in all reaſon muſt offend her most?</l>
                     <pb facs="tcp:177232:23"/>
                     <l>VVhere's this your care then, and deſire to pleaſe her?</l>
                     <l>Perhaps ſhee would that your delight ſhould bee</l>
                     <l>Your owne theft, not her gift; what skil't I pray.</l>
                     <l>VVhether you haue it this, or th'other way?</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Am:</speaker>
                     <l>VVhat certainty' haue I that her minde is ſuch?</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Thi:</speaker>
                     <l>See ſtill how ſillily you ſeeke to haue</l>
                     <l>That certainty which muſt of force diſpleaſe her;</l>
                     <l>And which 'boue all things elſe you ſhould not craue:</l>
                     <l>But who aſſures you to the contrary</l>
                     <l>But that ſhe may meane ſo as well as not?</l>
                     <l>Now if ſhee did, and that you would not goe;</l>
                     <l>(Since both the doubts and dangers equall be)</l>
                     <l>Is not a valiant then a baſe death better?</l>
                     <l>Th'art mute; th'art ouerthrowne;</l>
                     <l>Confeſſe it then;</l>
                     <l>Nor doubt but this thy ouerehrow will bee</l>
                     <l>Th'occaſion of a greater victorie.</l>
                     <l>Go'we.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Am:</speaker>
                     <l>Stay.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Thi:</speaker>
                     <l>VVhy ſtay?</l>
                     <l>Know'ſt not how ſwiftly the time runnes away?</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Am:</speaker>
                     <l>Pre'thee lett's thinke firſt what, and how to doe.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Thi:</speaker>
                     <l>Wee'll thinke of all things as we goe; but he</l>
                     <l>That thinkes too much, does little, commonly.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Chorus.</speaker>
                     <l>
                        <hi>O Loue,</hi> of whom, and where is taught</l>
                     <l>This thy ſo doubtfull Arte, and long</l>
                     <l>Of louing, that inſtructs the tounge</l>
                     <pb facs="tcp:177232:23"/>
                     <l>At eaſe to vtter eu'ry thought.</l>
                     <l>That the wilde fant' ſie doth deuize?</l>
                     <l>Whilſt with thy wings aboue the heau'n it flyes.</l>
                     <l>The learned <hi>Athens</hi> taught it not;</l>
                     <l>Nor was it to <hi>Liceus</hi> knowne;</l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Apollo,</hi> god of <hi>Helicon</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>For all his knowledge knew it not.</l>
                     <l>Faint and colde is what he ſpeakes,</l>
                     <l>Nor from his voice ſuch a fire breakes</l>
                     <l>As doth thy greatneſſe (Loue) befitt:</l>
                     <l>Nor can his witt,</l>
                     <l>Or thoughts vnto the height ariſe</l>
                     <l>Of thy profounder miſteries:</l>
                     <l>Thou readſt thine owne leſson beſt</l>
                     <l>(Great <hi>Loue</hi>) and onely'art by thy ſelfe exprest.</l>
                     <l>Thou of thy grace and bounty dayneſt</l>
                     <l>T'instruct th' vnlearnedest, and plaineſt</l>
                     <l>Men of thouſands, how to ſee</l>
                     <l>And reade thoſe wondrous things that be</l>
                     <l>Writ with thine owne hand in an others eyes.</l>
                     <l>Thou teacheſt thoſe thou loueſt beſt,</l>
                     <l>A purer language then the reſt,</l>
                     <l>And with ſmoth eaſe to breath their fantaſies.</l>
                     <l>Nay often times, ſuch is thy rare</l>
                     <l>And moſt miſterious eloquence,</l>
                     <l>That in a confuſd'e broken ſence</l>
                     <l>And halfe words that imperfect are,</l>
                     <l>The heart is beſt reueal'd and ſeene;</l>
                     <pb facs="tcp:177232:24"/>
                     <l>And ſuch perhaps mooue more by farr</l>
                     <l>Then many words that better polliſht beene.</l>
                     <l>Yea eu'ne Loues ſilence oft doth more expreſſe</l>
                     <l>Then words could doe, the mindes vnhappineſse.</l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>(Loue)</hi> let others if they pleaſe</l>
                     <l>Turne ore the workes of <hi>Socrates,</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>And thoſe great volumes of the wiſe;</l>
                     <l>While I but reade what's writ in two faire eyes.</l>
                     <l>Perhaps the penn that higher climes,</l>
                     <l>Will but halt after the rimes,</l>
                     <l>That in the rough and vncooth tree</l>
                     <l>With my rude artleſſe hand ingrauen bee.</l>
                  </sp>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div n="3" type="act">
               <head>Actus Tertius.</head>
               <div n="1" type="scene">
                  <head>Scena Prima.</head>
                  <stage>Thirſis. Chorus.</stage>
                  <sp>
                     <l>O Sauadge cruelty'; O th'ungratefull minde</l>
                     <l>Of a moſt moſt vngratefull Mayde; O Sexe</l>
                     <l>Full of ingratitude: and thou lewd Nature,</l>
                     <l>Nigligent miſtreſſe, and maker of things,</l>
                     <l>Wherefore, ah wherefore mad'st thou womankinde</l>
                     <l>So faire, and ſweet, and milde ouely without;</l>
                     <l>And didſt forget to make their inſides good?</l>
                     <l>Poore youth, I feare 'has made away himſelfe</l>
                     <l>Ere this; alas I cannot finde him out:</l>
                     <l>Three houres from place to place, &amp; wher I left him</l>
                     <l>Haue I bin ſeeking him; but cannot finde</l>
                     <pb facs="tcp:177232:24"/>
                     <l>Or him, or any print of his ſtrai'd foot:</l>
                     <l>Sure ſure hee's dead.</l>
                     <l>I will goe aske yon Swaines I ſee, if they</l>
                     <l>Can tell me any tydings of him. Friends</l>
                     <l>Did you not ſee Aminta, or happly heare</l>
                     <l>Newes of him lately?</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Cho:</speaker>
                     <l>Thou doſt ſeeme to me</l>
                     <l>Full of diſtraction, what is't troubles thee?</l>
                     <l>How cam'ſt thou ſo'out of breath, and to ſweat ſo?</l>
                     <l>What ayl'ſt thou? ſay what is't thou fear'ſt or wantest;</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Thi:</speaker>
                     <l>I feare Amintas harmes; tell me I pray'</l>
                     <l>Saw yee him not?</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Cho:</speaker>
                     <l>Not ſince he went with you</l>
                     <l>A while agon, but what d'yee feare in him.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Thi:</speaker>
                     <l>Alas I feare</l>
                     <l>Leſt he haue ſlaine himſelfe with his owne hand.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Cho:</speaker>
                     <l>Slaine with his owne hand? how ſo? what might cauſe</l>
                     <l>Such vengeance on himſelfe?</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Thi:</speaker>
                     <l>VVhy loue, and hate.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Chor:</speaker>
                     <l>Two powerfull enemies:</l>
                     <l>VVhat cannot they doe, when they meet together?</l>
                     <l>But ſpeake yet clearer.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Thir:</speaker>
                     <l>His too much loue, and her too much diſdaine</l>
                     <l>VVhom he lou'd ſo.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Cho:</speaker>
                     <l>Ah tell thy ſtory out;</l>
                     <l>This is a way of paſſage, and ere long</l>
                     <l>Perhaps ſome one will bring vs newes of him,</l>
                     <l>Or himſelfe come.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Thi:</speaker>
                     <l>I'le tell it willingly;</l>
                     <l>For 'tis not iuſt that ſuch ingratitude</l>
                     <l>Should reſt without the due deſerued blame.</l>
                     <l>Aminta heard (and I had told it him,</l>
                     <l>And was his conduct too, the gods forgiue mee)</l>
                     <pb facs="tcp:177232:25"/>
                     <l>That Siluia was with Daphne gone to'a Founte</l>
                     <l>To waſh themſelues; thither then (not without</l>
                     <l>A thouſand doubts and feares in him) we went;</l>
                     <l>And twenty times we turn'd againe, (his heart</l>
                     <l>Being all againſt it,) but that I was faine</l>
                     <l>Almoſt againſt his will to force him onn;</l>
                     <l>But drawing neere vnto the Fount, we heard</l>
                     <l>A ſadd lamenting voice; and all at once</l>
                     <l>Daphne wee ſpy'de wringing her hands, and ſtraite</l>
                     <l>Seeing vs comming, ah runne, runne (ſhee cryes)</l>
                     <l>Siluia's deflowr'd. Th'inamoured Aminta</l>
                     <l>No ſooner heard it, but ſwift as a Pard</l>
                     <l>He flung away; and I made after him:</l>
                     <l>Nor farre we went, when loe before our eyes</l>
                     <l>We ſaw the young mayde nak'd as at her birth,</l>
                     <l>Faſt fettr'd by the faire haire to a tree;</l>
                     <l>About whoſe branches in a thouſand knotts</l>
                     <l>The curles were link'd, and entertwin'de, the girdle</l>
                     <l>That wont to decke, and guard her mayden loynes,</l>
                     <l>Seru'd as an actor in her rauiſhment;</l>
                     <l>Binding her armes about the trees hard trunke,</l>
                     <l>The tree it ſelfe became a helper too,</l>
                     <l>For by her feete a branch or two grew out,</l>
                     <l>Which (eaſie bending) both her tender leggs</l>
                     <l>Had faſtned to the tree; and face to face</l>
                     <l>A beaſtly Satyr ſtood; who but eu'ne then</l>
                     <l>Had newly made an ende of binding her,</l>
                     <l>All the defence ſhee could (poore ſoule) ſhee made;</l>
                     <pb facs="tcp:177232:25"/>
                     <l>But ſure'twould haue but little ſteeded her,</l>
                     <l>Had not we come. Aminta with his dart</l>
                     <l>Flue like a Lyon</l>
                     <l>Vpon the Satyr; and I gathered ſtones;</l>
                     <l>VVhereat he fledd; and gaue Aminta leaſure</l>
                     <l>To feaſt his greedy eyes with her faire limbes,</l>
                     <l>VVhich trembling ſeem'd as tender, white, &amp; ſoft,</l>
                     <l>As vnpreſt curds new from the whay diuided.</l>
                     <l>Full was her face of anger, griefe, and ſpight;</l>
                     <l>He gently accoſting her with modeſt lookes,</l>
                     <l>Spake thus; O louely Siluia pardon me;</l>
                     <l>Fardon my hands for daring to approache</l>
                     <l>So neere theſe beauteous limbes of thine; alas</l>
                     <l>It is neceſsity inforceth them,</l>
                     <l>Neceſsitie t'unlooſe theſe bands of thine;</l>
                     <l>And let it (I beſeech thee) not displeaſe thee,</l>
                     <l>That Fate has rais'd them to this happineſſe.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Cho:</speaker>
                     <l>VVords that would mollifie a heart of flint;</l>
                     <l>But what reply made ſhee?</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Thir:</speaker>
                     <l>VVhy none at all.</l>
                     <l>But with a looke full of diſdaine, hung downe</l>
                     <l>The head, and hidd her faire lapp all ſhee could;</l>
                     <l>He ſtood vnbrayding her intangled' treſſes,</l>
                     <l>And ſighing ſaid (the whiles,) O how vnworthy</l>
                     <l>Is this rude trunke of ſo faire knots as theſe?</l>
                     <l>See what aduantage haue Loues votaries,</l>
                     <l>That (like this tree) haue with ſo pretious bands</l>
                     <l>Their hearts entwin'd: Cruell plant, couldſt thouſe</l>
                     <pb facs="tcp:177232:26"/>
                     <l>This haire thus iniur'd, that thus honours thee?</l>
                     <l>Then with his hands her hands he faire vnlooz'd,</l>
                     <l>In ſuch a ſort, as that he ſeem'd affraide</l>
                     <l>To touch them, yet deſir'd to touch them ſtill:</l>
                     <l>Then ſtoop'd he downe t'untye her feet; when ſhee</l>
                     <l>Finding her late bound hands at libertie,</l>
                     <l>Said with a ſcornefull, and diſdayning looke;</l>
                     <l>Shepherd, I am <hi>Diana's;</hi> touch me not;</l>
                     <l>Leaue me, I ſhall vnbinde my feete my ſelfe.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Cho:</speaker>
                     <l>Ah that the ſoft beſt of a mayde ſhould harbor</l>
                     <l>Such pride; O Curteſie full ill repayde.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Thir:</speaker>
                     <l>Straite he with reuerence withdrew himſelfe,</l>
                     <l>Not lifting once his eyes to looke on her;</l>
                     <l>Barring himſelfe of his delight; that ſhee</l>
                     <l>Might lay no blame on his immodeſtie.</l>
                     <l>I that was hid neere hand, and ſaw all this,</l>
                     <l>And heard it all, was eu'ne exclaiming on her,</l>
                     <l>But that I curb'd my ſelfe; ſee the ſtrange creature;</l>
                     <l>After ſhe was with much adoe got looſe,</l>
                     <l>Away ſhee hurryed ſtrait, ſwift as a Doe,</l>
                     <l>Without ſo much as 'Thanke yee, or farewell;</l>
                     <l>And yet knew well, ſhee had no cauſe to feare;</l>
                     <l>So modeſt and reſpectfull was Aminta.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Cho:</speaker>
                     <l>Why fled ſhe then?</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Th:</speaker>
                     <l>Perhaps ſhe thought it ſhew'd</l>
                     <l>Better; and argued more her modeſtie.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Cho:</speaker>
                     <l>Her foule ingratitude: but what did then,</l>
                     <l>VVhat ſaid the poore Aminta?</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Thir:</speaker>
                     <l>I cannot tell.</l>
                     <pb facs="tcp:177232:26"/>
                     <l>For (angry) after her I ranne amaine</l>
                     <l>To haue oretane, and ſtaid her; but in vaine;</l>
                     <l>For ſoone I loſt her; and againe returning</l>
                     <l>Vnto the Fountaine where I left Aminta,</l>
                     <l>I found him not; and my heart much miſgiues me</l>
                     <l>Of ſome ſelfe ill befalne him; for I knowe</l>
                     <l>He was reſolu'd (before this hapned him)</l>
                     <l>To ende his life and miſeries together.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Cho:</speaker>
                     <l>It is the common vſe and art of Louers</l>
                     <l>To threaten their owne deaths; but rarely ſhall</l>
                     <l>Wee ſee th'effect in any of them all.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Thi:</speaker>
                     <l>Pray heau'ne he be not of thoſe rare ones then.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Cho:</speaker>
                     <l>Tuſh feare him not.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Thi:</speaker>
                     <l>Well I'le downe to the Caue</l>
                     <l>Of the ſage Elpine; thither he perhaps</l>
                     <l>Will be retyr'de, if he be yet aliue;</l>
                     <l>For there he went full oft to'allay and eaſe</l>
                     <l>The rage of his bitter calamities,</l>
                     <l>With the ſweet ſound of Elpines Reeds; that winn</l>
                     <l>And draw with their alluring voice, to heare them,</l>
                     <l>The hard ſtones from the craggy mountaine topps;</l>
                     <l>Make flouds and waterfounts runne with pure milke;</l>
                     <l>And oft the rough bark'd trees againſt their kindes</l>
                     <l>Diſtill ſweet honny from their bitter rindes.</l>
                  </sp>
               </div>
               <div n="2" type="scene">
                  <pb facs="tcp:177232:27"/>
                  <head>Actus Tertius. Scen: Secunda.</head>
                  <stage>Aminta, Daphne, Nerina.</stage>
                  <sp>
                     <l>PIttileſſe (Daphne) was that Pitty of thine,</l>
                     <l>When thou held'st backe the dart; becauſe my death</l>
                     <l>Will but more painefull be, the more delay'de:</l>
                     <l>And now, why doeſt thou ſtay me trifling thus,</l>
                     <l>And hold me' in vaine with theſe thy long diſcourſes?</l>
                     <l>If thou beeſt fearefull of my death, thou fear'ſt</l>
                     <l>My happineſſe.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Daph.</speaker>
                     <l>Leaue leaue Aminta</l>
                     <l>This thy vniuſt deſpaire: I know her well;</l>
                     <l>And 'twas her baſhfulneſſe, not cruelty,</l>
                     <l>That made her runne away ſo faſt from thee.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Am:</speaker>
                     <l>Ah that my onely friend muſt be Diſpaire,</l>
                     <l>Seeing that onely Hope hath bredd my ruyne:</l>
                     <l>And yet it would be breeding in my breſt</l>
                     <l>Againe, and bid me liue; when, what can bee</l>
                     <l>A greater ill to ſo great miſery,</l>
                     <l>Then ſtill to liue, but to be ſtill vnhappy?</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Da:</speaker>
                     <l>Why liue yet, liue with thy vnhappines;</l>
                     <l>And beare it for thy greater happines</l>
                     <l>When the time comes; think what thou lately ſaw'ſt</l>
                     <l>In the faire naked one, and let that ſerue thee</l>
                     <l>For a reward ſufficient for thy hope,</l>
                     <l>And make thee in loue with life.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Am:</speaker>
                     <l>'Twas not enough</l>
                     <l>For loue, and fortune, that I was before,</l>
                     <pb facs="tcp:177232:27"/>
                     <l>So wretched, as I ſcarſly could be more;</l>
                     <l>But that I muſt be ſhew'd (t'augment my ill)</l>
                     <l>Part of my bliſſe, yet go without it ſtill.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Ner:</speaker>
                     <l>Muſt I be then the Rauen, and ſiniſter</l>
                     <l>Relater of ſo bitter newes? O wretched,</l>
                     <l>Wretched Montano; ah what wilt thou do,</l>
                     <l>When thou ſhalt heare the ſad, and killing ſtory</l>
                     <l>Of thy owne only Siluia? poore olde man,</l>
                     <l>Moſt hapleſſe father of a hapleſs childe;</l>
                     <l>Ah now no father.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Da:</speaker>
                     <l>I doe heare a ſad</l>
                     <l>Lamenting voyce.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Am:</speaker>
                     <l>I heare the name of Siluia,</l>
                     <l>That ſtrikes mine eare, and my heart through at once;</l>
                     <l>But who is't names her?</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Da:</speaker>
                     <l>'Tis I thinke the Nimphe</l>
                     <l>Nerina, ſhee whom Dian loues ſo well,</l>
                     <l>That has ſo liuely eyes, and louely hands,</l>
                     <l>And ſo becomming a behauiour.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Ner:</speaker>
                     <l>Yet he ſhall know it; and go gather vp</l>
                     <l>Th'vnhappy reliques, (if yet any be;)</l>
                     <l>Ah Siluia Siluia, O accurſed fate.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Am:</speaker>
                     <l>Ay mee, what meanes this Nimph? what ſay's ſhee?</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Ner:</speaker>
                     <l>Daphne?</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Da:</speaker>
                     <l>Nerina? what's the matter that thou nam'ſt</l>
                     <l>Siluia ſo oft, and ſigh'ſt at eu'ry word?</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Ner:</speaker>
                     <l>There's cauſe enough Daphne; ah too too much.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Am:</speaker>
                     <l>Ay mee I feele, I feele my breſt ſo full</l>
                     <l>Of yce, my breath halfe ſtopt; liues ſhee, or no?</l>
                  </sp>
                  <pb facs="tcp:177232:28"/>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Da:</speaker>
                     <l>Tell vs all, tell the worſt Nerina.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Ner:</speaker>
                     <l>O heau'n,</l>
                     <l>Muſt I be then th'vnhappy' hiſtorian?</l>
                     <l>And yet it's fit I tell my ſad tale out.</l>
                     <l>Silu'ia ſtarnak'd (whereof yee know perhaps</l>
                     <l>The cauſe) came to our houſe, where being clad,</l>
                     <l>Shee afterward deſir'd me I would goe</l>
                     <l>A hunting with her, as it was before</l>
                     <l>Appointed, to the Groue of Okes, (for ſo</l>
                     <l>The place yee know is call'd;) I did agree;</l>
                     <l>And onn we went, and found there many Nimphes</l>
                     <l>Gath'red together; not farr off, behold</l>
                     <l>Ruſheth a huge Wolfe foorth, whoſe yawning iawes</l>
                     <l>Foam'd with a bloudy froth; Siluia then neare him</l>
                     <l>Let flie a ſhaft at him; and in his head</l>
                     <l>The arrow light; he tooke the wood againe,</l>
                     <l>And ſhee at heeles perſu'd him with a Dart</l>
                     <l>Into the wood.—</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Am:</speaker>
                     <l>Ah ſorrowfull beginning,</l>
                     <l>I feare, I feare a ſad concluſion.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Ner:</speaker>
                     <l>I with an other Dart follow'd their footing;</l>
                     <l>But ſetting out too late, was caſt farr off;</l>
                     <l>And hauing gain'd the wood, I loſt the ſight</l>
                     <l>Of them; yet kept their track, and ranne ſo farr,</l>
                     <l>Till I was got into the deſerteſt</l>
                     <l>And thickeſt of the wood; at length I found</l>
                     <l>(And tooke vp) Siluias Dart vpon the ground;</l>
                     <l>And not farr off a white vaile, which (ere while)</l>
                     <l>I did my ſelfe binde vp her haire withall;</l>
                     <pb facs="tcp:177232:28"/>
                     <l>And whilſt I look'd about me', Iſpi'de ſeu'n Wolues</l>
                     <l>Licking bloud off the ground, that ſcatt'red lay</l>
                     <l>About a few bare bones; and 'twas my hap</l>
                     <l>To ſcape vnſeene, while they ſo earneſtly</l>
                     <l>Minded their pray.</l>
                     <l>I full of feare turn'd back, and came my way.</l>
                     <l>And this is all that I can ſay of Siluia;</l>
                     <l>And heere's the vaile.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Am:</speaker>
                     <l>Th'haſt ſayd, th'haſt ſayd enough;</l>
                     <l>O bloud, O vayle, O Siluia, 'dead dead —</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Dap:</speaker>
                     <l>Poore youth he dyes; he's dead; ay me he's dead</l>
                     <l>With griefe.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Ner:</speaker>
                     <l>He breath's yet, he's but in a traunce;</l>
                     <l>Tarry he comes againe t'himſelfe.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Am:</speaker>
                     <l>O griefe,</l>
                     <l>Why do'ſt, why do'ſt thou thus torment me?</l>
                     <l>And wilt not end me? th'art vniuſt. Perhaps</l>
                     <l>Thou leau'ſt the worke to my owne hand: I am,</l>
                     <l>I am content it ſhall be my owne care;</l>
                     <l>Since thou wilt not, or canſt not doe't; Ay mee,</l>
                     <l>Ay mee if nothing want to make this cleere,</l>
                     <l>And nothing want to make my miſeries</l>
                     <l>Now brimfull; why do' I linger? why do I ſtay?</l>
                     <l>O Daphne Daphne, was it to this end,</l>
                     <l>This bitter, bitter end thou didſt reſerue me?</l>
                     <l>My death had then bin ſweet, and pleaſing to me,</l>
                     <l>When thou and heau'n held back my Dart, and ſau'd me;</l>
                     <l>Heau'n that was lothe (belike) I ſhould preuent</l>
                     <l>With death, the woes it has prepar'd for me;</l>
                     <l>But now't has done the very worſt it can,</l>
                     <pb facs="tcp:177232:29"/>
                     <l>I hope both heau'n, and you may ſuffer me</l>
                     <l>To dye in peace.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Da:</speaker>
                     <l>Stay yet, ſtay wretch, and learne</l>
                     <l>The trueth yet better.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Am:</speaker>
                     <l>Ah the trueth is ſuch,</l>
                     <l>'Iue ſtay'd too long, alas I'ue heard too much.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Ner:</speaker>
                     <l>Ay mee, wretch that I am, why did I ſpeake?</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Am:</speaker>
                     <l>Gentle Nimphe, let me craue that vayle of thee,</l>
                     <l>The poore remaynder of her; they it may</l>
                     <l>Accompanie me for theſe fewe ſad houres</l>
                     <l>Of way, and life yet left me; and increaſe</l>
                     <l>That martirdom, that were no martirdom</l>
                     <l>Were it not much more then enough to kill me.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Ner:</speaker>
                     <l>Shall I denie't, or ſhall I giue it him?</l>
                     <l>The cauſe he askes it for, bids me retaine it.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Am:</speaker>
                     <l>Cruell Nimphe, to deny me' a grace ſo ſmall</l>
                     <l>In my extremity; and eu'n I ſee</l>
                     <l>How in each trifle fortune croſſeth mee.</l>
                     <l>I yeeld, I yeeld; long may it bide with thee:</l>
                     <l>Long liue yee; my way to my death muſt bee.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Da:</speaker>
                     <l>Aminta ſtay, Aminta', a word Aminta,</l>
                     <l>Harke, ſtay; alas how ſwift he flyes away.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Ner:</speaker>
                     <l>He runnes ſo faſt, t'will be in vaine for vs</l>
                     <l>To follow him; 'twere beſt I onward went</l>
                     <l>Vpon my way; and yet perhaps 'twere better</l>
                     <l>I ſtay'd, and held my peace, then my ſelfe be</l>
                     <l>Author of poore Montano's miſery.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <pb facs="tcp:177232:29"/>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Chorus.</speaker>
                     <l>DEath, there is no neede of thee:</l>
                     <l>Loue alone, and Conſtancie</l>
                     <l>Ar enough (without thy Dart)</l>
                     <l>To tyre vpon an honeſt heart.</l>
                     <l>Yet ſo hard is not the way</l>
                     <l>To Loues fame, as many ſay;</l>
                     <l>For Lone no price but loue regards;</l>
                     <l>And with it ſelfe, it ſelfe rewards.</l>
                     <l>And oft in ſeeking it, is found</l>
                     <l>Glory that liues, when we are vnder ground.</l>
                  </sp>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div n="4" type="act">
               <head>Actus Quartus. </head>
               <div n="1" type="scene">
                  <head>Scena Prima.</head>
                  <stage>Daphne. Siluia. Chorus.</stage>
                  <sp>
                     <l>NOw may the winde vpon his wings beare hence</l>
                     <l>All ill may happen thee; together with</l>
                     <l>Th'accurſed newes ſo lately ſpread of thee.</l>
                     <l>Thou art aliue (the gods be thanked fort't)</l>
                     <l>And eu'n but now I did beleeue thee dead;</l>
                     <l>So had Nerina painted to the life</l>
                     <l>Thy late hap; but I would ſhee had bin dumbe,</l>
                     <l>Or ſome that heard her deafe.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Sil:</speaker>
                     <l>Indeede I ſcap'd</l>
                     <l>So narrowly, as I beleeue ſhee might</l>
                     <l>Full well ſuppoſe me dead.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Da:</speaker>
                     <l>Suppoſe ſhe might</l>
                     <pb facs="tcp:177232:30"/>
                     <l>Yet not haue tolde it with ſuch certainty.</l>
                     <l>But tell me pre'thee how thou didſt eſcape</l>
                     <l>The danger ſo.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Sil:</speaker>
                     <l>Why I in following</l>
                     <l>A Wolfe into the wood, had thickt with him</l>
                     <l>So farr, till I at length had loſt his track;</l>
                     <l>And as I ſtood thinking to turne againe</l>
                     <l>Back as I went, I ſpide him, and I knew him</l>
                     <l>By' a ſhaft that ſtuck in's head neere to his eare,</l>
                     <l>Which I not long before had ſhot at him:</l>
                     <l>He was accompany'd with many more,</l>
                     <l>About the body of ſome beaſt new ſlaine;</l>
                     <l>But what beaſt 'twas I knew not; the ſame Wolfe</l>
                     <l>I thinke knew me ſo well, that on he made</l>
                     <l>Towards me with his head beſmear'd with bloud.</l>
                     <l>I bouldly ſtood, and bent a Dart at him,</l>
                     <l>And when I thought his diſtance fit for me,</l>
                     <l>I threw, but (whether it was fortunes fault</l>
                     <l>Or mine) I miſt him, as thou know'ſt I vſe</l>
                     <l>Not oft to do; he fiercer then before</l>
                     <l>Ruſheth vpon me; and was come ſo neere,</l>
                     <l>That I, (my ſhafts now ſpent) found it too late</l>
                     <l>To truſt my bowe, and tooke me to my heeles:</l>
                     <l>Away Tranne; he follow'd me as faſt.</l>
                     <l>See now my hap; a vaile that I had ty'de</l>
                     <l>My haire withall, was halfe vndone, and flew</l>
                     <l>At the windes pleaſure looſely, that at length</l>
                     <l>'Thad wound it ſelfe about a bough; I felt</l>
                     <l>That ſomewhat ſtay'd me; but the feare I had,</l>
                     <pb facs="tcp:177232:30"/>
                     <l>Redoubled ſo my ſtrength, that though the bough</l>
                     <l>Did all it could to hold me, I broke looſe;</l>
                     <l>And as I left my vaile behinde, I left</l>
                     <l>Part of my haire withall; and ſo had feare</l>
                     <l>Lent my feete wings, that I out-went the Wolfe,</l>
                     <l>And came ſafe from the wood; when turning home</l>
                     <l>I met thee thus amaz'd, and am no leſſe</l>
                     <l>Amaz'd my ſelfe to ſee thee ſo.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Da:</speaker>
                     <l>Ay mee</l>
                     <l>Thou liu'ſt, 'tis well, would all were well beſides.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Sil:</speaker>
                     <l>What ayl'ſt thou? pre'thee art thou ſory then</l>
                     <l>That I'm aliue?</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Da:</speaker>
                     <l>No; that thou liu'ſt I'm glad;</l>
                     <l>But for an others death I muſt be ſad.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Sil:</speaker>
                     <l>How's this? for whoſe death?</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Da:</speaker>
                     <l>Why Aminta's death.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Sil:</speaker>
                     <l>Aminta dead? alas how may that be?</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Da:</speaker>
                     <l>Nay how I cannot tell; nor yet am ſure</l>
                     <l>Of the deede done; but I beleeue it firmly.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Sil:</speaker>
                     <l>What's this thou tell'ſt me? alas what might be</l>
                     <l>Th'occaſion of Aminta's death?</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Da:</speaker>
                     <l>Thy death.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Sil:</speaker>
                     <l>Make mee conceiue thee.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Da:</speaker>
                     <l>Eu'n the heauy newes</l>
                     <l>Of thy death, which he heard, and credited,</l>
                     <l>Hath brought him to his end, ſome-way or other.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Sil:</speaker>
                     <l>Fye, th'art deceiu'd; and this thy thought will be</l>
                     <l>As vaine as was the newes thou heardſt of me;</l>
                     <l>For ſurely no man will dye willingly.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Da:</speaker>
                     <l>O Silu'ia Siluia, thou doſt not feele</l>
                     <l>Nor know what 'loues flame can do, in a breſt</l>
                     <l>That is a breſt of fleſh, and not of flint</l>
                     <l>As thine is; for didſt thou but know't, I know</l>
                     <pb facs="tcp:177232:31"/>
                     <l>Thou wouldſt haue loued him that lou'd thee more</l>
                     <l>Then both his eyes; more then his breath and life;</l>
                     <l>I do beleeue it, nay I'ue ſeene, and know it.</l>
                     <l>I ſaw, I ſaw him when thou fledst from him</l>
                     <l>(Vnkinde and cruell as thou wert) when he,</l>
                     <l>Eu'n then when thou ſhouldſt rather haue imbrac'd</l>
                     <l>Then ſcorn'd him ſo, againſt his breſt had bent</l>
                     <l>His Dart, with full intent to kill himſelfe:</l>
                     <l>Nor any whit repented of the deede,</l>
                     <l>When (ſtay'd by me from farther wounding him)</l>
                     <l>The ſharpe ſteele had his garment and his skinne</l>
                     <l>Dyed in his bloud, and had pierc'd through that heart</l>
                     <l>That loyall heart of his, that thou before</l>
                     <l>Hadſt wounded worſe, had not I held his hand,</l>
                     <l>And ſau'd him all I could: but O alas</l>
                     <l>That ſlight wound ſeru'd but as a triall only</l>
                     <l>And ſmall proofe of his deſp'rate conſtancie;</l>
                     <l>And but to teach the fatall ſteele, to do</l>
                     <l>The black deede it was preappointed to.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Sil:</speaker>
                     <l>Ay mee what's this thou tell'ſt me?</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Da:</speaker>
                     <l>But at laſt</l>
                     <l>When the newes came that thou wert dead, I ſaw him</l>
                     <l>Sound at the hearing on't, and dye away;</l>
                     <l>And came no ſooner to himſelfe againe,</l>
                     <l>But furiouſly he flings away amayne;</l>
                     <l>And ſure I feare, alas, too ſure 'twill prooue</l>
                     <l>Has kill'd himſelfe;</l>
                     <l>Such was his too much griefe, and too much loue.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Sil:</speaker>
                     <l>But hold'ſt thou this for certaine?</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Da:</speaker>
                     <l>Tis too true.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <pb facs="tcp:177232:31"/>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Sil:</speaker>
                     <l>Ay me why didſt thou not ſtraite follow him?</l>
                     <l>And ſtay him? ah let's ſeeke, let's finde him out;</l>
                     <l>Since from my death, his deaths deſire is bredd,</l>
                     <l>He muſt liue ſtill becauſe I am not dead.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Da:</speaker>
                     <l>Alas I follow'd him, but he had ſoone</l>
                     <l>So farre outrunne me, as I now despaire</l>
                     <l>That we ſhall finde him hauing loſt his footing.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Sil:</speaker>
                     <l>We muſt alas we muſt inquire him out</l>
                     <l>Some way or other speedily, leaſt he</l>
                     <l>Thorough our ſlowneſſe his owne murdrer be.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Da:</speaker>
                     <l>Belike then (Cruell) th'art but grieu'd he ſhould</l>
                     <l>Take from thee th'honour of this goodly deede?</l>
                     <l>And would'ſt thy ſelfe be the braue murdreſſe?</l>
                     <l>Muſt no hand elſe but thine, an Actor be</l>
                     <l>In th' execution of this Tragedy?</l>
                     <l>Well, ſet thy heart at reſt; for howſo're</l>
                     <l>He dyes, thou art his onely murderer.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Sil:</speaker>
                     <l>Ah thou doſt wound me; and thy eu'ry word</l>
                     <l>Addes to the agony'e of my bleeding breſt,</l>
                     <l>Strooke through with feare of him; and with the bitter</l>
                     <l>Remembrance of the ſauadge cruelty</l>
                     <l>In me, which I call'd honeſty', and ſo 'twas,</l>
                     <l>But too ſeuereit was, and rigorous;</l>
                     <l>I finde it now, alas I now repent it.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Da:</speaker>
                     <l>VVhat's this? what do I heare?</l>
                     <l>Why thou art pittifull then, and thy heart</l>
                     <l>Seemes to haue feeling of anothers harmes;</l>
                     <l>VVhat doe I ſee?</l>
                     <pb facs="tcp:177232:32"/>
                     <l>Why thou do'ſt weepe too; I'm amaz'd at this?</l>
                     <l>Whence ar theſe teares? Is't loue that cauſes them?</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Sil:</speaker>
                     <l>'Tis pitty, 'tis compaſsion cauſes them.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Da:</speaker>
                     <l>Compaſsion is the meſſenger of loue,</l>
                     <l>As is the lightning of the thunder clap.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Cho:</speaker>
                     <l>'Tis often times the property of loue</l>
                     <l>When he would creepe vnſeene into young hearts</l>
                     <l>Which auſtere Chaſtity hath long time ſhut</l>
                     <l>And barr'd againſt him, to aſſume the habit</l>
                     <l>And ſemblance of his handmayd Pitty', and ſo</l>
                     <l>Deceiues them ere they be aware, and gets</l>
                     <l>Into their breſts vnknowne and vndiſcry'de.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Da:</speaker>
                     <l>Theſe ar loue-teares (Siluia) they flow ſo faſt;</l>
                     <l>Do'ſt thou not loue indeede? ha? not a word?</l>
                     <l>Yes, 'tis too true, but alas 'tis too late.</l>
                     <l>Behold the ſtrange wayes of Loues chaſtiſement;</l>
                     <l>Wretched Aminta, thou that (like the Bee,</l>
                     <l>Which hurting dyes, and in an others wound</l>
                     <l>Leaues his owne life,) haſt with thy death, at laſt</l>
                     <l>Pierc'd that hard heart, which liuing felt thee not.</l>
                     <l>But if, O erring Spirit, (as I feare</l>
                     <l>Thou art, and ſeuer'd from thy empty corſe)</l>
                     <l>Thou wandreſt here abouts; behold her playnts;</l>
                     <l>Liuing thou lou'dſt her, ſee ſhee loues thee dead.</l>
                     <l>And if thy cruell fate would haue it ſo,</l>
                     <l>That thy loue could not be repay'd till now,</l>
                     <l>And that her loue was onely to be purchas'd</l>
                     <l>By thee at this deare price; let it ſuffice thee</l>
                     <pb facs="tcp:177232:32"/>
                     <l>(Where more thou canſt not haue) that thou haſt bought it</l>
                     <l>As dearely now, as ſhee could rate it thee;</l>
                     <l>Euen with thy death.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Cho:</speaker>
                     <l>Deare bargaine for the buyer;</l>
                     <l>And all vnprofitable, and infamous</l>
                     <l>Vnto the cruell ſeller.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Sil:</speaker>
                     <l>O that I</l>
                     <l>Could with my loue redeeme his life againe,</l>
                     <l>Or with my life his life, if he liue not.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Da:</speaker>
                     <l>O pitty, O diſcretion, too late bredd;</l>
                     <l>Little auaile they to reuiue the dead.</l>
                  </sp>
               </div>
               <div n="2" type="scene">
                  <head>Actus Quartus. Scen: Secunda.</head>
                  <stage>Nuntius, Chorus, Siluia. Daphne.</stage>
                  <sp>
                     <l>
                        <hi>I</hi> Am ſo full of woe, ſo full of borror</l>
                     <l>As all I heare and whatſoere I looke on</l>
                     <l>Me thinks afflicts, diſquiets, and affrights me.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Cho:</speaker>
                     <l>What ſtrange newes brings this man, that ſeemes to me</l>
                     <l>So troubled in his lookes, and in his ſpeech?</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Nun:</speaker>
                     <l>I bring the ſad newes of Aminta's death.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Sil:</speaker>
                     <l>Ay me what ſayes he?</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Nun:</speaker>
                     <l>Aminta nobleſt Shepherd of theſe woods;</l>
                     <l>That was ſo comely and ſo gratious;</l>
                     <l>So deare vnto the Nymphes, and to the Muſes;</l>
                     <l>And dead but eu'ne a ladd.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Cho:</speaker>
                     <l>Ah of what death?</l>
                     <l>Tell vs, ah tell all; that we may in one</l>
                     <l>Lament with thee his miſchiefe, and our owne.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <pb facs="tcp:177232:33"/>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Sil:</speaker>
                     <l>Ay me my heart failes me'; I dare not approach</l>
                     <l>Th'unwelcome newes which I of force muſt heare.</l>
                     <l>Vilde breaſt of mine, ohdurate heart of mine,</l>
                     <l>What fear'fl thou now? go hard'ly, preſſe vpon</l>
                     <l>The murth'ring kniues that are in yon mans tongue;</l>
                     <l>And there diſplay thy fiercenes? freind, I come</l>
                     <l>To beare my part of all the woe thou bringest;</l>
                     <l>Perhaps it does concerne me more by much</l>
                     <l>Then th'art aware of; It belongs to me;</l>
                     <l>Grutch me not on't then.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Nun:</speaker>
                     <l>Nimphe I doe beleeue thee;</l>
                     <l>For eu'ne vpon his death, I heard the wretch</l>
                     <l>Call ſtill vpon thy name to his laſt breath.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Da:</speaker>
                     <l>Now, now beginnes, the heauy hiſtory.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Nun:</speaker>
                     <l>I was vpon the middes of yon high hill,</l>
                     <l>Where I had ſpred abroad ſome netts of mine</l>
                     <l>To drie them, when not far off from me, came</l>
                     <l>Aminta by, with a ſad clowdy looke,</l>
                     <l>And altred much from what he wont to bee</l>
                     <l>Both in his face and faſhion; which I spying</l>
                     <l>Ranne after him; and ſtaying him, quoth hee</l>
                     <l>Ergaſtus thou muſt doe a curteſie</l>
                     <l>For me of much importance and auaile;</l>
                     <l>'Tis to goe with me but a little hence,</l>
                     <l>For witneſſe of a deede I haue to doo;</l>
                     <l>But firſt I'le haue thee binde thy faith to me</l>
                     <l>By a ſtrict oath to ſtand aloofe from mee</l>
                     <l>And not approach to lett or hinder that</l>
                     <pb facs="tcp:177232:33"/>
                     <l>That I ſhall do: I (that could nere haue dream't</l>
                     <l>Of ſuch a furious madneſſe in him) yeelded</l>
                     <l>To's will; and made deſperate inuocations</l>
                     <l>Calling to witneſs <hi>Pan,</hi> and <hi>Priapus:</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Pales, Pomona',</hi> and nightly <hi>Hecate,</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>Which done, he led me higher vp the hill:</l>
                     <l>Where, clambring through wilde rocky paſſages,</l>
                     <l>(By wayes nere found, and neuer trode before)</l>
                     <l>VVee gayn'd the top, that ouer-hung a valley,</l>
                     <l>'Twixt which and vs was a ſteepe precipice,</l>
                     <l>And there we ſtay'd; I caſting downe mine eye,</l>
                     <l>Began for feare to tremble, and ſhrunke back.</l>
                     <l>After a little pauſe, he ſmil'de me thought,</l>
                     <l>And ſeem'd more cheerefull then he was before;</l>
                     <l>And that made me miſdoubt him leſſe then euer:</l>
                     <l>After that; (quoth he to me) ſee thou tell</l>
                     <l>The Nimphes and Shepherds what thou ſhalt behold;</l>
                     <l>Then looking downe, Ah that I had (ſayd he)</l>
                     <l>So ready at my will, the throat and teeth</l>
                     <l>Of thoſe ſame greedy VVolues, as theſe rocks be;</l>
                     <l>I would not dye of other death, then ſhe</l>
                     <l>VVho was my life; nor haue my carkaſs torne</l>
                     <l>But by thoſe teeth that tore thoſe delicate</l>
                     <l>And beautious limbs of hers; but ſince that heau'n</l>
                     <l>Denies ſo great a bleſsing to me, I</l>
                     <l>Muſt be content ſome other way to dye;</l>
                     <l>And though a worſe way, yet a ſpeedier.</l>
                     <l>Siluia I follow thee, Siluia I come</l>
                     <pb facs="tcp:177232:34"/>
                     <l>To beare thee comapny,</l>
                     <l>If thou diſdaine me not; O I ſhould dye</l>
                     <l>Much more contentedly; were I but ſure</l>
                     <l>My follow'ing thee would not diſquiet thee,</l>
                     <l>And that thy hate had ending with thy life:</l>
                     <l>Siluia I follow thee, I come. Which ſayd,</l>
                     <l>Downe from the place he headlong threw himſelfe,</l>
                     <l>And I turn'd yee to ſee't.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Da:</speaker>
                     <l>VVretched Aminta.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Sil:</speaker>
                     <l>Ay mee, ay mee.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Cho:</speaker>
                     <l>Why didſt not hinder him?</l>
                     <l>Perhaps the oath thou took'ſt barr'd thee to doo't?</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Nun:</speaker>
                     <l>Not ſo; for ſetting all ſuch oathes at nought,</l>
                     <l>(Vaine doubtleſſe in ſuch caſes) when I ſaw</l>
                     <l>VVhither his fond and headdy madneſſe tended,</l>
                     <l>I reacht at him; and (as ill hap would haue it)</l>
                     <l>Layd hold but of this thinne ſcarfe, wherewithall</l>
                     <l>He girt himſelfe; which (all too weake to beare</l>
                     <l>His bodies weight, that reſted all vpon't)</l>
                     <l>Remayn'd broke in my hand.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Cho:</speaker>
                     <l>And what became</l>
                     <l>Of the vnhappy carkaſs?</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Nun:</speaker>
                     <l>I know not;</l>
                     <l>For I was ſo dead ſtrucken at the ſight,</l>
                     <l>As my heart would not ſuffer me, to looke</l>
                     <l>And ſee him daſht to peeces.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Cho:</speaker>
                     <l>O ſtrange fate.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Sil:</speaker>
                     <l>Ay mee, were I not made of ſtone indeede,</l>
                     <l>This newes would kill me. Ah if the falſe death</l>
                     <l>Of me that car'd no more for him, was cauſe</l>
                     <l>Enough to end his life;</l>
                     <l>Much more cauſe is there that the certaine death</l>
                     <l>Of him that lou'd me ſo, ſhould be enough</l>
                     <pb facs="tcp:177232:34"/>
                     <l>To end my life; and it ſhall end my life;</l>
                     <l>And if griefe cannot do't, the ſharpe ſteele ſhall;</l>
                     <l>Or elſe this girdle heere, which iuſtly ſtayes</l>
                     <l>As loath to follow his ſweet Maſters ruines,</l>
                     <l>Till it haue done on me the due reuenge</l>
                     <l>Of his ſad death, and my ingratitude.</l>
                     <l>Vnhappy girdle (relique of a more</l>
                     <l>Vnhappy Maſter) ah do not diſdaine</l>
                     <l>T'abide a while with one ſo odious;</l>
                     <l>For thou ſhalt ſtay but to be th'inſtrument</l>
                     <l>Of his reuenge, and of my puniſhment.</l>
                     <l>I might haue bin, alas I ſhould haue bin</l>
                     <l>Yoke-fellow with Aminta heere on earth;</l>
                     <l>But ſince that cannot be, by thy helpe now</l>
                     <l>I'le finde him out among th'infernall ſhades,</l>
                     <l>And there goe beare him better company.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Cho:</speaker>
                     <l>Content thee (thou ſad ſoule) 'tis Fortunes fault,</l>
                     <l>And not by thy meane, that this ill is wrought.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Sil:</speaker>
                     <l>Shepherds why plaine yee? if yee moane my woes,</l>
                     <l>I do deſerue no pitty; that haue bin</l>
                     <l>My ſelfe ſo pittileſſe; if yee wayle the death</l>
                     <l>Of the poore Innocent, ab tis too ſmall;</l>
                     <l>Griefe is too poore to pay his deede withall.</l>
                     <l>And Daphne thou I prethee dry thy teares;</l>
                     <l>If for my ſake thou weep'ſt; for my ſake ceaſe.</l>
                     <l>And for his ſake that was a thouſand times</l>
                     <l>More worth then I; and go along and helpe me</l>
                     <l>To finde th'vnhappy bones; and bury them;</l>
                     <pb facs="tcp:177232:35"/>
                     <l>'Tis that alone that keepes me ſtill aliue,</l>
                     <l>And that I do not eu'n now kill my ſelfe.</l>
                     <l>It is the leaſt and laſt duty is left</l>
                     <l>For me to do him, for the loue he bore me;</l>
                     <l>And though this vile hand of mine, might perhaps</l>
                     <l>Blemiſh the pi'ety of ſo iuſt a deede;</l>
                     <l>Yet he I know will like the deede the better,</l>
                     <l>For being done by it; for I am ſure</l>
                     <l>He loues me ſtill; his death aſsures it me.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Da:</speaker>
                     <l>I am content to'aſsiſt thee'in ſeeking him,</l>
                     <l>But talke (for heau'ns ſake) of this death no more.</l>
                     <l>Alas wee'ue had too much of that before.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Sil:</speaker>
                     <l>Till now I'ue liu'd only vnto my ſelfe,</l>
                     <l>And my owne wayward humor: for the reſt,</l>
                     <l>I vowe it all to'Aminta; and if to him</l>
                     <l>I may not, I'le liue yet to his colde carkaſs,</l>
                     <l>Till I haue done it the laſt obſequies:</l>
                     <l>So long I may; longer I will not liue.</l>
                     <l>But Shepherd ſet me in the way (I pray')</l>
                     <l>Vnto the valley at the high hills foote.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Nun:</speaker>
                     <l>There O'that hand 'tis, and not far from hence.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Da:</speaker>
                     <l>I'le goe along and guide thee, for I well Remember't.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Sil:</speaker>
                     <l>Farwell Shepherds, Nimphes farwell;</l>
                     <l>Farwell woods, fields, and flocks; farwell, farwell.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Nun:</speaker>
                     <l>This mayden ſpeakes me thinkes in ſuch a ſtraine,</l>
                     <l>As if ſhee went nere to returne againe.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <pb facs="tcp:177232:35"/>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Chorus.</speaker>
                     <l>
                        <hi>LOue;</hi> thou reioyn'ſt what Death vnbinds?</l>
                     <l>(Thou freind of Peace but ſhee of Bloud;)</l>
                     <l>Yet thou her Triumphes ouer raigneſt;</l>
                     <l>And in vniting gentle mindes,</l>
                     <l>Mak'ſt Earth ſo heau'nly an abode,</l>
                     <l>As thou to dwell among vs dayneſt:</l>
                     <l>Thou ſmooth'ſt the rugged hearts of men;</l>
                     <l>And inward rancors driu'ſt away</l>
                     <l>(Great prince of happy peace;) and when</l>
                     <l>Milde breaſts are troubled, do'ſt allay</l>
                     <l>Their woes; and by thy working ſtrange,</l>
                     <l>Framſt of things mortall, an eternall change.</l>
                  </sp>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div n="5" type="act">
               <head>Actus Quintus.</head>
               <div n="1" type="scene">
                  <head>Scena Prima.</head>
                  <stage>Elpine, Chorus.</stage>
                  <sp>
                     <l>DOubtleſſe the lawes where with <hi>Loue</hi> gouerneth</l>
                     <l>His Empire euermore, are neither hard</l>
                     <l>To follow, nor vniuſt; and thoſe his workes</l>
                     <l>Which many men do condemne wrongfully,</l>
                     <l>Are full of prouidence, and miſtery,</l>
                     <l>Lo with what art,</l>
                     <l>And by how many vnknowne waies, he leades</l>
                     <l>His votaries vnto their happineſſe;</l>
                     <l>And placeth them among the higheſt ioyes</l>
                     <pb facs="tcp:177232:36"/>
                     <l>And pleaſures of his amorous Paradiſe,</l>
                     <l>When oftentimes they feele themſelues ſunk downe</l>
                     <l>Eu'ne to the very bottome of all ills.</l>
                     <l>Behold Aminta with his headlong fall,</l>
                     <l>Aſpires vnto the top of all delight;</l>
                     <l>O happy' Aminta; and ſo much the more</l>
                     <l>Happy now, as vnfortunate before.</l>
                     <l>This thy example makes me hope no leſſe,</l>
                     <l>That once at laſt my loueleſſe faire (that couers</l>
                     <l>Vnder thoſe freindly ſmiles, ſuch cruelty)</l>
                     <l>Will with true pitty heale the wounds, that ſhee</l>
                     <l>Hath with her fained pittie made in me.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Cho:</speaker>
                     <l>Yon is the reu'rend Elpine; and me thinkes</l>
                     <l>Speakes of Aminta' as if he were aliue,</l>
                     <l>Calling him happy, bleſt, and fortunate,</l>
                     <l>Ah hard condition of vnhappy louers;</l>
                     <l>He belike counts him fortunate, that dyes</l>
                     <l>For loue, and is belou'd (when he is dead)</l>
                     <l>Of her he lou'de ſo well; and this he calls</l>
                     <l>The paradiſe of loue; O with how light</l>
                     <l>And poore rewards the wing'd Loue-god contents</l>
                     <l>His ſeruants. Art thou (Elpine) then indeed</l>
                     <l>In ſuch a pittifull eſtate, as that</l>
                     <l>Thou canſt terme fortunate, the miſerable</l>
                     <l>Death of the poore Aminta? and wouldſt thou</l>
                     <l>So farr thy life to loues ſubiection bowe,</l>
                     <l>And vndergoe the like fate?</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Elp:</speaker>
                     <l>Freinds be merry</l>
                     <l>What of his death perhaps ye haue heard, is falſe.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <pb facs="tcp:177232:36"/>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Cho:</speaker>
                     <l>That were a welcome newes.</l>
                     <l>Did he not throw himſelfe downe headlong then</l>
                     <l>From yon high Mountaines topp?</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Elp:</speaker>
                     <l>Tis true he did.</l>
                     <l>But 'twas a fortunate and happy fall;</l>
                     <l>That look'd ſo like death, and is proou'd to him</l>
                     <l>Not life alone, but a moſt ioyfull life;</l>
                     <l>For now he lyes lull'd in the tenter lapp.</l>
                     <l>Of his beloued one that ſeemes much more</l>
                     <l>Fonde of him now, then ſhe was coy before;</l>
                     <l>Drying each teare he lets fall, with a ſighe,</l>
                     <l>Or with the like, freindly requiting it.</l>
                     <l>But I am going to finde out Montane</l>
                     <l>Her Father, and conduct him where they bee;</l>
                     <l>For there wants nothing elſe but his conſent,</l>
                     <l>To both their boundleſſe ioyes accompliſhment.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Cho:</speaker>
                     <l>Their age, their bloud and birth, their mutuall loues,</l>
                     <l>And all agree; and the good oulde Montano</l>
                     <l>Will he glad doubtleſſe of poſteritie,</l>
                     <l>And to' arme his gray haires with ſo ſweet a guard,</l>
                     <l>So that his will no doubt ſhall ſecond theirs.</l>
                     <l>But thou (good Elpine) tell what god, what fate</l>
                     <l>In that ſo dangerous, and deadly fall</l>
                     <l>Preſcru'd Aminta.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Elp:</speaker>
                     <l>I am well content;</l>
                     <l>Heare then, heare that which with theſe eyes I ſaw;</l>
                     <l>I was before my Caues mouth, which ye knowe</l>
                     <l>Lyes at the hills foote, on the valleyes brimme;</l>
                     <l>There Thirſi' and I were reaſoning together</l>
                     <pb facs="tcp:177232:37"/>
                     <l>Of the faire ſhee that in the ſelfe ſame nett</l>
                     <l>Had firſt inſnar'd him, and me afterward;</l>
                     <l>When I preferring my lou'de ſeruitude</l>
                     <l>Before his free ſtate; all at once we heard</l>
                     <l>A ſhreeke; and ſaw a man fall frbm aboue,</l>
                     <l>Vpon a buſhy knowle; for on the ſide</l>
                     <l>Of the ſteepe hill, there growes (all of a heape,</l>
                     <l>And as 'twere woue tog ther,) a round maſſe</l>
                     <l>Of brambles, thornes, and certaine weedes among;</l>
                     <l>There firſt he light before he lower fell;</l>
                     <l>And though hee made way through them with his weight,</l>
                     <l>And fell downe to the ground before our feete;</l>
                     <l>Yet ſo that ſtop abated the falls force,</l>
                     <l>As 'twas not mortall; though ſo dangerous</l>
                     <l>As that he lay a while deuoyd of ſenſe,</l>
                     <l>And as a dead man without ſhow of motion.</l>
                     <l>We with amazement, and compaſsion were</l>
                     <l>Dumbe-ſtrucken at the ſudden ſpectacle:</l>
                     <l>And knowing him, and knowing ſoone (with all)</l>
                     <l>He was not dead, nor perhas like to die,</l>
                     <l>Appeaz'd his woe, and eas'd him all we could;</l>
                     <l>Then Thirſis made me throughly' acquainted with</l>
                     <l>Th'whole paſſage of his loues. but while we ſought</l>
                     <l>To bring him to himſelfe againe, and ſent</l>
                     <l>To fetch <hi>Alpheſibeo</hi> (t'whom <hi>Appollo</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>Tanght th'art of Phiſicke, when he gaue his Harp</l>
                     <l>And Lute to me) came Daphne, and Siluia,</l>
                     <l>Who (as I heard) had bin to ſeeke him out</l>
                     <pb facs="tcp:177232:37"/>
                     <l>Whom they ſuppos'd dead. But when Siluia</l>
                     <l>Had found and knew him, and beheld his cheekes</l>
                     <l>And lips ſo bloudleſſe, and diſcoloured,</l>
                     <l>As the wanne Violet's hue their paleneſſ paſt;</l>
                     <l>And ſaw him languiſh, as if then he had</l>
                     <l>Bin drawing his laſt breath; ſhee gaue her ſorrowes</l>
                     <l>A liberall paſsage through her earneſt cryes;</l>
                     <l>And beating her faire breſt, falls downe vpon him,</l>
                     <l>Laying her face on his, and on his lipps</l>
                     <l>Her lipps.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Cho:</speaker>
                     <l>And did not baſhfull ſhame reſtraine</l>
                     <l>Her more, who is ſo ſtrict and ſo ſeuere?</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Elp:</speaker>
                     <l>Baſhfulnes oft barrs weak loues of their longings,</l>
                     <l>But is too weake a curbe for a ſtrong loue.</l>
                     <l>But then, as if her eyes had bin two fountaines,</l>
                     <l>She drown'd his colde face with her powring teares;</l>
                     <l>Whoſe water was of ſo great force, and vertue,</l>
                     <l>That he reuiu'd; and op'ning his dimme eyes,</l>
                     <l>He ſighes foorth a hollow' Ay mee, from the bottome</l>
                     <l>Of his ſad breſt; ſhee caught the heauy ſound</l>
                     <l>Of that ſame bitter breath; and mingled it</l>
                     <l>With her ſweet breath; and ſo reſtor'd, and heal'd him.</l>
                     <l>Then; who can ſay? who can imagine what</l>
                     <l>Both of them thought, and at that inſtant felt?</l>
                     <l>Each now aſsur'd of others life? and he</l>
                     <l>Aſsur'd of her loue, and to finde himſelfe</l>
                     <l>Intangled in ſo lou'd, and louing armes?</l>
                     <l>He that loues firmly may imagine it,</l>
                     <l>Yet hardly too; but no tongue ſure can tell it.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <pb facs="tcp:177232:38"/>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Cho:</speaker>
                     <l>Is then Aminta ſafe belike, and well,</l>
                     <l>And ſo cleare from all danger of his death?</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Elp:</speaker>
                     <l>He's ſafe, and well; ſaue that he has a little</l>
                     <l>Battred his fleſh, and ſomwhat ſcratcht his face;</l>
                     <l>But 'twill be nothing; and he wayes it not.</l>
                     <l>Thriſe happy he, t'haue giu'n ſo great and high</l>
                     <l>A ſigne, and earneſt of his Conſtancie;</l>
                     <l>And now inioyes the fruit of his firme loue;</l>
                     <l>To which his ſad indurings, and paines paſt,</l>
                     <l>Prooue pleaſing and ſweet ſawces at the laſt.</l>
                     <l>But peace be wi'yee'; I muſt goe ſeeke about</l>
                     <l>Till I haue found the good Montano out.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Chorus.</speaker>
                     <l>
                        <hi>I</hi> Know not whether the much ſowre</l>
                     <l>This (now bleſt) Louer (ſeruing, burning,</l>
                     <l>Now dispairing, and ſtill mourning)</l>
                     <l>Hath felt; may in one happy' houre</l>
                     <l>Be thoroughly repay'd againe</l>
                     <l>With pleaſure equall to his paine.</l>
                     <l>But if the good more pleaſing be,</l>
                     <l>And come more welcome, after wee</l>
                     <l>Haue felt the ill; I doe not craue</l>
                     <l>(O <hi>Loue</hi>) this happineſs to haue.</l>
                     <l>Let others be ſo bleſt by thee,</l>
                     <l>And graunt the Nimph I loue, may bee</l>
                     <l>Wonne with a little leſſe adooe;</l>
                     <l>Leſs pray'rs, leſs ſeruice when I wooe;</l>
                     <pb facs="tcp:177232:38"/>
                     <l>And let the ſawce to our loues, be</l>
                     <l>Not ſo much paine, and miſery:</l>
                     <l>But ſweet diſdaines, repulſes ſweet;</l>
                     <l>Fall off a little, and ſtraite meete.</l>
                     <l>That after a ſhort frowne or twayne,</l>
                     <l>New peace, or truce may knit our hearts againe.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <p>Th'end of Taſſo's Aminta.</p>
               </div>
            </div>
         </div>
         <div type="poem">
            <head>VENVSSES <hi>Search for</hi> CVPID.</head>
            <lg>
               <l>DOwne from the third heau'n, I (that am</l>
               <l>His queene, goddeſſe, &amp; mother) come</l>
               <l>To ſeeke my ſonne, (the run-away</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Cupid.</hi>) I loſt him yeſterday.</l>
               <l>As he lay playing in my lapp</l>
               <l>(Whether of purpoſe, or by happ</l>
               <l>I cannot ſay,) but his golde ſhaft</l>
               <l>Fell with the point on my left ſide,</l>
               <l>And prickt me'; and when my hurt he ſpide,</l>
               <l>(As erſt h'has ſeru'd me') he flew away, and laught.</l>
               <l>But though ſomtime I angry ſeem,</l>
               <l>A tender care I haue of him;</l>
               <l>And now (my anger layd aſide)</l>
               <l>Haue bin to ſeeke him farr and wide;</l>
               <pb facs="tcp:177232:39"/>
               <l>As well my heau'ns each part about</l>
               <l>As <hi>Mars</hi> his orbe, and thoroughout</l>
               <l>All th'other wheeles that mooue, and ſtand;</l>
               <l>The ſhining heau'n has not a Sphere,</l>
               <l>But I haue bin to ſeeke him there,</l>
               <l>Yet cannot finde this little vagabond.</l>
               <l>Wherefore now amongſt you (meeke</l>
               <l>Mortalls) I am come to ſeeke</l>
               <l>My childe, who of entim s I knowe,</l>
               <l>Takes delight to liue with you;</l>
               <l>But I more then halfe diſpaire</l>
               <l>To finde him 'mongſt you (Ladyes faire)</l>
               <l>For though oftentimes he flyes</l>
               <l>About your face, and by your eyes,</l>
               <l>And would faine enter your breſt,</l>
               <l>And in your boſomes make his neſt;</l>
               <l>Yet they'r ſo bard againſt him with diſdaine,</l>
               <l>That there I feare he does but knock in vain.</l>
               <l>But amongſt you Men more kinde</l>
               <l>I may hope my ſonne to finde;</l>
               <l>Your milder breſts will not diſdaine</l>
               <l>This fugitiue to entertaine;</l>
               <l>Therefore to you my ſute muſt be;</l>
               <l>Tell mee' (I pray') then, where is he?</l>
               <l>He that can but giue me tyding</l>
               <l>Where the Wag has his abiding;</l>
               <l>Shall for his rewarding, ſipp</l>
               <l>A paire of kiſſes from my lipp,</l>
               <pb facs="tcp:177232:39"/>
               <l>Soone as he will wiſh to take them,</l>
               <l>Full as ſweet as I can make them:</l>
               <l>But he that ſhall the kindneſſe do mee</l>
               <l>To bring my little wandrer to mee,</l>
               <l>Shall expect a greater meede</l>
               <l>Wherwith to recompence his friendly deed;</l>
               <l>And ſuch as all the wealth I haue</l>
               <l>Cannot exceede; no though I gaue</l>
               <l>All <hi>Loues</hi> Kingdome; and I take</l>
               <l>To witneſſe the blacke <hi>Stigian</hi> lake,</l>
               <l>That I will truely pay my vowe.</l>
               <l>Tell mee therefore, tell mee now</l>
               <l>Where's my Sonne? who graunts my ſuite?</l>
               <l>But no man anſweres; all are mute.</l>
               <l>Perhaps yee haue not ſeene the Elfe,</l>
               <l>Or he hath ſo diſguiz'de himſelfe</l>
               <l>Yee know him not; perhaps h'has left</l>
               <l>His brand, and from his ſhoulders reft</l>
               <l>His painted wings; and throwne them by,</l>
               <l>With th'reſt of his Artillerie.</l>
               <l>But I'le giue y'other markes of him, wherby</l>
               <l>Yee ſhall diſerne, and finde him eaſily.</l>
               <l>This <hi>Loue</hi> (thus masked) although he be</l>
               <l>Olde both in yeares, and ſubtiltie;</l>
               <l>Seemes but a boye in ſhape, and face,</l>
               <l>And (like a boye in gate, and pace)</l>
               <l>Is neuer conſtant to one place.</l>
               <l>Such ſports and paſtimes vſeth hee,</l>
               <pb facs="tcp:177232:40"/>
               <l>As common vnto children be;</l>
               <l>But all his ſports he tempers ſo,</l>
               <l>Th'ar dangerous, and full of woe</l>
               <l>To thoſe he playes withall; diſpleaſ'd</l>
               <l>He will be ſoone, and ſoone appeaz'd;</l>
               <l>And in his face at once appeares</l>
               <l>An enterchange of ſmiles and teares.</l>
               <l>His haire is gould, &amp; curl'd, &amp; growes</l>
               <l>(As Fortune often painted ſhowes)</l>
               <l>Hanging long before; but ſhort</l>
               <l>And thinne on his heads hinderpart.</l>
               <l>His face cleare-colour'd, &amp; delightful,</l>
               <l>Like to fire is quicke and ſprightfull;</l>
               <l>And doth eaſily expreſſe</l>
               <l>His mindes audacious wantonneſſe.</l>
               <l>His inflam'd eyes are full of guile,</l>
               <l>Which ſtill he ſugars with a ſmile.</l>
               <l>Vnder the brow vnhappily</l>
               <l>He vſes oft to throw his eye,</l>
               <l>That rowles vnſteedy heere and there,</l>
               <l>And ne're is firmely fixed any where.</l>
               <l>His toung is ſweet; and when he ſpeakes</l>
               <l>A pleaſing ayre from his lipps breakes,</l>
               <l>In many' a peec'd imperfect word,</l>
               <l>Which yet a winning ſound affoord.</l>
               <l>His voice is ſhrill, and cleare, and ſmall,</l>
               <l>Which vttering, ſtill he ſmiles withall;</l>
               <l>And thoſe his fleering ſmiles doth baiyt</l>
               <pb facs="tcp:177232:40"/>
               <l>With hidden treaſon, and deceipt,</l>
               <l>Which (like the Snake) ſurke in the bed</l>
               <l>Of thoſe flowres vndiſcouered.</l>
               <l>And firſt with theſe he doth beginne</l>
               <l>To'vnlocke your breaſts, and enter in.</l>
               <l>When hauing ſeem'd all courteſie,</l>
               <l>All meekeneſſe, and humilitie,</l>
               <l>And that (as a poore pligrim) yee</l>
               <l>Haue harber'd him in charitie,</l>
               <l>Then 'ginnes he by degrees, t'expreſſe</l>
               <l>Himſelfe, and wrong your eaſineſſe,</l>
               <l>Growes proud and wondrous inſolent.</l>
               <l>And neuer reſts, is nere content</l>
               <l>Vntill he be (Ingratefull Elfe).</l>
               <l>Poſſeſt of your heats keyes himſelfe;</l>
               <l>And ſtraite turnes all thoſe out of dore</l>
               <l>That there inhabited before;</l>
               <l>And placeth others in their roome,</l>
               <l>A troope of newer gueſts; to whom</l>
               <l>He makes your reaſon thrall; and findes</l>
               <l>New Lawes wherwith to rule your minds;</l>
               <l>And thus becomes of a milde gueſt,</l>
               <l>A cruell Tyrant ore the breſt;</l>
               <l>And ſo his new plac'd Powres aſsiſt him</l>
               <l>He kills or conquers all that ere reſiſt him,</l>
               <l>Now by theſe markes (both of his face,</l>
               <l>His hauiour, quallities, and grace)</l>
               <l>Which I haue giu'n yee', I hope yee may</l>
               <pb facs="tcp:177232:41"/>
               <l>Know this diſguized run-away.</l>
               <l>Tell me' I pray' then, where is he?</l>
               <l>But not a man will anſwer mee.</l>
               <l>Yee'll conceale him from me then?</l>
               <l>Ah fooliſh vnaduiſed men,</l>
               <l>Yee cannot <hi>Loue</hi> ſo cloſely hyde,</l>
               <l>But that at length he will be ſpy'de;</l>
               <l>And in your words &amp; looks appeare,</l>
               <l>By tokens euident and cleare;</l>
               <l>And then ſuch happ will you betide,</l>
               <l>As vnto him that ſeekes to hide</l>
               <l>A Snake in's boſome, till his cryes</l>
               <l>And bloud diſcouer where he lyes.</l>
               <l>But ſince I cannot find him heere,</l>
               <l>(Ere I returne vp to my Sphere,)</l>
               <l>I'le ſeek for him on Earth ſome other wher.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <head>Madrigall.</head>
               <l>VEnus, <hi>I heare thou roam'ſt about</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>To finde thy wandring</hi> Cupid <hi>out,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Who (hauing play'd the wag laſt day)</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>For feare of britching flue away;</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>And promiſeſt to giue a kiſse</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>To him can tell thee where he is;</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Come then, and thriue in thy request;</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Kiſse me, and take him in my breſt.</hi>
               </l>
            </lg>
         </div>
         <div type="poem">
            <pb facs="tcp:177232:41"/>
            <head>
               <hi>ARIADNES</hi> COMPLAINT In Imitation of ANGVILLARA.</head>
            <lg>
               <l>NOw were the leſſer tapers of the Night</l>
               <l>Burnt out; the Moone to' her blazing Brothers ray</l>
               <l>Yeelding the faint ſtreames of her frailer light;</l>
               <l>And now the roſie Meſſenger of Day</l>
               <l>Her purple doores vnbarring, reſtores ſight</l>
               <l>To the blinde world; fannes the ſoft miſtes away</l>
               <l>From ſleeping eyes; and to the dayes beheſt</l>
               <l>Rowſes vp eu'ry bird, and eu'ry beaſt.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>When hapleſſe <hi>Ariadne,</hi> with the day</l>
               <l>Opes her (yet drowzie) eyes; and firſt her head</l>
               <l>Turnes on that ſide, where ſhee ſuppoſed lay</l>
               <l>The treche'rous man that from her ſide is fled.</l>
               <l>Her louing hand firſt this, then th'other way</l>
               <l>She vaine extendes; in vaine about the bed</l>
               <l>Her legg, and arme mooues; whence a colde feare takes her,</l>
               <l>That ſtartles eu'ry limbe, and broad awakes her.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Shee riſen vp; about her ſhoulders throwes</l>
               <l>Her garment, and her widdowed bed forſakes;</l>
               <l>With haire vnbound, and robe that looſely flowes,</l>
               <l>(Led by the rage wherewith her ſwolne breſt akes)</l>
               <l>Shrieking as one diſtraught, ſhee frantick throwes</l>
               <l>Her wilde eyes heere and there; then (ſpeedy) makes</l>
               <l>Tow'rd the ſtill ſhore; and that ſhee findes bereft</l>
               <l>Of the falſe barke ſhee late at anchor left.</l>
            </lg>
            <pb facs="tcp:177232:42"/>
            <lg>
               <l>Now on the wharfe ſhee pores, now on the Mayne;</l>
               <l>But more then ſhore, and waters cannot ſee.</l>
               <l>A thouſand times and more ſhee calls in vaiue,</l>
               <l>And the lou'd name repeates inceſſantly.</l>
               <l>Her voyce the rocks receiue, and back againe</l>
               <l>The ſound returne, calling as well as ſhee.</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Theſeus</hi> ſhe calls; the rocks do <hi>Theſeus</hi> cry;</l>
               <l>Yet neither voyce can purchaſe a reply.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Along the ſandy beache a ſteepe cliffe ſtands,</l>
               <l>Whoſe vaſter limbes th'aſpiring for head ſtraine</l>
               <l>To height ſo aerye', as it the ſight expands</l>
               <l>Farr ore the broad blue boſome of the Mayne.</l>
               <l>To this ſhe runnes; clambers with legs and hands,</l>
               <l>Nor weary reſts till ſhe the top attaine.</l>
               <l>Hard is th'aſcent of the rough craggy ſtone,</l>
               <l>Yet her will makes the difficulty none.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Thence ſhe diſcouers (for by this the day</l>
               <l>His broader light had opte) the ſwoln ſailes ſpred,</l>
               <l>And by the wilde winde now browne farre away.</l>
               <l>From her diſcolour'd cheekes the warme bloud fled,</l>
               <l>Within her vaynes freezes; in her diſmay</l>
               <l>Shee faints; and falls to th'carth colder then lead;</l>
               <l>Yet the ſame griefe that doth of ſence depriue her,</l>
               <l>Wakes her againe, and doth anew reuiue her.</l>
            </lg>
            <pb facs="tcp:177232:42"/>
            <lg>
               <l>'Twixt griefe, diſdaine, and rage deuided, thus</l>
               <l>She lowde exclaimes; whither (falſe man) O whither</l>
               <l>Fly'ſt thou diſloyall? looke, looke <hi>Theſeus,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>Looke if that barke that brought vs both together,</l>
               <l>(And ſhould hold both, and holdes but one of vs)</l>
               <l>Carry the full freight hence it came with hither.</l>
               <l>Cruell! if th'haſt with thee my ſoule, and minde,</l>
               <l>Why leau'ſt thou th'other halfe of me behinde?</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Ah canſt tho' abide my loyall Spirit to range</l>
               <l>So farr (to follow and attend on thee)</l>
               <l>From her owne home; and this knowne breſt exchange,</l>
               <l>For one ſo willing to be rid of mee?</l>
               <l>Thus ſhee complaines; ſhreekes, weepes; to'her paſsions ſtrange</l>
               <l>Strange geſtures ſuting of calamity.</l>
               <l>But th'heedleſſe winde, what ere ſhee ſighing ſay,</l>
               <l>Blowes the vaine breath, and the wing'd barke away.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Feeling her voyce with ſhriekes growne faint, and hoarce,</l>
               <l>Shee waues her ceaſeleſſe armes about her head,</l>
               <l>And oft her garment; th'imbark'd eyes to force</l>
               <l>Back to the ſhore; but all was vaine ſhe did.</l>
               <l>The farr-ſayl'd pine beares on his ſteady courſe</l>
               <l>So faſt, as wholly' almoſt to blue ayre ſled.</l>
               <l>Shee waues, and beckons ſtill, till from her ſight</l>
               <l>Shee findes th'vngratefull ſayle is vaniſht quite.</l>
            </lg>
            <pb facs="tcp:177232:43"/>
            <lg>
               <l>Yet ſtill ſhee gazes; and at length anue</l>
               <l>Mournes, and ſuch clowdes of woe her Powres benight,</l>
               <l>As, though her eyes redouble could their viewe,</l>
               <l>Her ſwelling teares would ſcarſe alowe them ſight.</l>
               <l>More weake, her ſence the more impatient grue;</l>
               <l>Whence with new thought ſhee leaues the craggy height,</l>
               <l>And to the Tent breathleſſe her ſelfe withdrue.</l>
               <l>Shee ſayes, perhaps yet I may finde him there;</l>
               <l>So ſtriues to cozen, and delay her feare.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>But there her buſieſt ſearch can nothing finde,</l>
               <l>But death-like ſilence, and an empty bed;</l>
               <l>Whereat (freſh paſsion tyring on her minde)</l>
               <l>With cheekes paler then roſes pluckt, and dead,</l>
               <l>Downe on that ſide the Cabane where th'vnkinde</l>
               <l>And falſe <hi>Athenian</hi> late layd his head,</l>
               <l>Her head ſhee layes; and with eyes ſhowring ſtill,</l>
               <l>Croſs'd armes, and ſad groanes, thus repeates her ill.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>O faithleſs man, what haue I done alas,</l>
               <l>Or wherein euer ill deſeru'd of thee,</l>
               <l>That in this vncouth ſolitary place</l>
               <l>Thou thus inhumanly abandon'ſt mee?</l>
               <l>Ah whither in this miſerable caſe</l>
               <l>Shall I repaire? what can my refuge bee</l>
               <l>But death (for end of a ſtate ſo diſtreſt)</l>
               <l>By famine, or by ſome deuowring beaſt.</l>
            </lg>
            <pb facs="tcp:177232:43"/>
            <lg>
               <l>In this inhoſpitable Iſle, vntrode</l>
               <l>By humane foote, accompany'de with none</l>
               <l>But ſuch as farr from man haue their abode,</l>
               <l>(Wilde beaſts, and wandring fowles,) thus all a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lone,</l>
               <l>Thus to be left? and vnder ſuch a loade</l>
               <l>Of woe, and none to pitty', or heare my moane?</l>
               <l>O falſeſt man, must I that from the graue</l>
               <l>Sau'de thee, for meede this ſad requit all haue?</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>When through thoſe errors of the maze I led thee,</l>
               <l>T' auoid th'undoubted forfeit of thy life;</l>
               <l>And with ſo timely' aduice, and ayde beſtedd thee,</l>
               <l>As ridde thy land of tribute, thee of ſtrife,</l>
               <l>Exchang'd my natiue ſhores for thoſe that bredd thee,</l>
               <l>Kingdome, and freinds, and all to dye thy wife;</l>
               <l>Haue I for this, for this (falſe <hi>Theſeus</hi>)</l>
               <l>Haue I deſeru'd to be requited thus?</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>If through the doubtfull Laborinth I gaue</l>
               <l>Thee th'eaſie meane t'eſcape, and ſet thee free,</l>
               <l>(Whom from the Minotaure no arte could ſaue</l>
               <l>But mine that purchaſt thy deliuery,)</l>
               <l>Why doſt thou not (an eaſier boone I craue)</l>
               <l>Why dost thou not from hence deliuer me?</l>
               <l>If from that rauenous beaſt I ſaude thee, why</l>
               <l>Leau'st thou me heere by rauenous beasts to dye?</l>
            </lg>
            <pb facs="tcp:177232:44"/>
            <lg>
               <l>Or ſhall I tell my ſelfe, this Iſle may bee</l>
               <l>By men (though barb'rous ſure) inhabited,</l>
               <l>That may perhaps releeue, and ſuccour mee;</l>
               <l>Ere with beaſts iawes, or hunger I be dead?</l>
               <l>Oh ſillyeſt hope! when all this miſerie</l>
               <l>By truſting Man is falne vpon my head,</l>
               <l>Is't poſsible I can ere be ſo vaine,</l>
               <l>Ere be ſo madd to truſt to Man againe?</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Ah falſe ſmoth lookes, fain'd vizar of deceipt;</l>
               <l>Lewde breſt, fowle harbour of impiety;</l>
               <l>Bitter-ſweete, tounge, balefull alluring bayte</l>
               <l>Of my ore-credulous ſimplicity.</l>
               <l>Ah <hi>Theſeus</hi> lay'dſt thou all theſe foes in waite</l>
               <l>To circumuent ſo much Integrity?</l>
               <l>A great exploit no doubt th'haue done: betray'de</l>
               <l>The loyall boſome of a ſilly mayde.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Trecherous ſleep; why charmd'ſt thou ſo mine eyes,</l>
               <l>And in thy ſoft chaine held'ſt them fetter'd ſtill,</l>
               <l>While the falſe fugitiue did from me riſe?</l>
               <l>Yee windes too, acceſſaries to my yll,</l>
               <l>Oh how officious (like corrupted ſpies</l>
               <l>Sett to betray me) did y'obey his will?</l>
               <l>Firſt th'one ſurpriz'd, and bound me where I lay;</l>
               <l>Th'other then ſtole, and bore my wealth away.</l>
            </lg>
            <pb facs="tcp:177232:44"/>
            <lg>
               <l>And thou deceitfull Tent, and faithleſſe bedd;</l>
               <l>O how vngratfull, how vniuſt yee bee?</l>
               <l>When my Soules treaſure I depoſited,</l>
               <l>And ſafe intruſted to your cuſtodie,</l>
               <l>Was't not your dues t'haue redeliu'red</l>
               <l>Into my hands what I deliuered yee?</l>
               <l>But <hi>Theſeus,</hi> why do' I blame, bed, ſleepe, or wind,</l>
               <l>Poore vnder-agents of thy treas'nous minde?</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Thou, onely thou'tis reau'st me of my life;</l>
               <l>Thou that ſo late coupled'st my hand with thine,</l>
               <l>In ſigne thou took'st me for thy wedded wife;</l>
               <l>And to the Rite ſummond'ſt the Powers diuine</l>
               <l>For records; vowing till Deaths fatall Knife</l>
               <l>Thy breath diuided, to be euer myne.</l>
               <l>Then pluckd'ſt my Virgin flowre; Thou, onely thou</l>
               <l>Falſe Man, haſt thus abus'de, and left me now.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Thou (my hearts firſt, next honours, now liues theef)</l>
               <l>Thou thou haſt thus amidd theſe frights, and feares</l>
               <l>Left me'on this deſolate ſhore, voyde of reliefe.</l>
               <l>A pray for howling Wolues, and greedy Beares.</l>
               <l>Farre from the care of a Paternall griefe;</l>
               <l>Farr from the comfort of a Mothers teares;</l>
               <l>Whom I muſt neuer more behold; but dye</l>
               <l>Without a freind neere me to cloſe my eye.</l>
            </lg>
            <pb facs="tcp:177232:45"/>
            <lg>
               <l>Ah <hi>Theſeus,</hi> thou now to thy natiue ſhore</l>
               <l>Return'ſt with honour, and immortall praiſe;</l>
               <l>Where (as a god) each one will thee adore,</l>
               <l>And circle thy victorious head with Bayſe;</l>
               <l>When thou ſhalt tell how to the fatall dore,</l>
               <l>(Through th' intricacy of ſo many wayes)</l>
               <l>Thou gott'ſt; and then hauing the Monſter ſlaine,</l>
               <l>So eaſy' a meane, found'ſt to get out againe.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>The father to his childe will pointing crye,</l>
               <l>Loe yon is <hi>Theſeus</hi> that aduentured</l>
               <l>His life, to gaine his Countries libertie;</l>
               <l>And hath the Land from thrall deliuered.</l>
               <l>When I that help't thee to the victory,</l>
               <l>Shall here lye dead; perhaps vnburied.</l>
               <l>Annexe this ſtratageme to th'other paſt,</l>
               <l>How thou here left'ſt thy loyall wife at laſt.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>So foule a deede will all the reſt deface,</l>
               <l>T'haue paid ſuch faith with ſuch impiety.</l>
               <l>Ah neuermore (for ſhame) ſteale for thy grace</l>
               <l>From auncient Kings thy fained Pedegree;</l>
               <l>Thy mother neuer was of <hi>Pitheus</hi> race;</l>
               <l>Nor could <hi>Egeus</hi> ere thy father bee.</l>
               <l>Rather the breſts of ſome wilde Panthar fed thee,</l>
               <l>Or ſauadge Tigar in the deſert bred thee.</l>
            </lg>
            <pb facs="tcp:177232:45"/>
            <lg>
               <l>This ſigh'd; ſhe leaues the Tent; and the ſteep cliffe</l>
               <l>Againe aſcendes: diuerſifies her woes</l>
               <l>With freſh plaints; now weepes, now ſhrieks out her griefe.</l>
               <l>Ecco (that from the depths at her cry roſe)</l>
               <l>Lends (in compaſsion) all the poore reliefe</l>
               <l>She can; meeting her plaints at eu'ry cloſe.</l>
               <l>And when her tender hand each th'other beates,</l>
               <l>She imitates, and the ſad noiſe repeates.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Ah (ſayes ſhe) could I'in ſpace of a ſhort groane</l>
               <l>From hence to thy Ships prowe trenſported bee,</l>
               <l>That from the hatches thou wight'ſt heare my moane,</l>
               <l>And theſe ſad pangs of my affliction ſee;</l>
               <l>Were not thy heart harder then is the ſtone</l>
               <l>I tread vpon, ſure thou wouldſt pitty me.</l>
               <l>But though groſſe ayre doth from thine eyes withhold me,</l>
               <l>With ſome remorſe yet in thy thought behould mee.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Behould yet in thy thought my bitter plaint:</l>
               <l>Behould theſe teares, that with a frequent raine</l>
               <l>Drench my torne haire: o' could thy fant'ſie paint</l>
               <l>To life but the leaſt part of my vaſt paine,</l>
               <l>Knew'ſt thou how oft this voice (now hoarce and faint)</l>
               <l>Hath call'de thee' already, and ſtill calls in vaine;</l>
               <l>Thou'ldſt restore all, to me of all bereft;</l>
               <l>T'whom ſcarſe ſo much as eu'ne to hope is left.</l>
            </lg>
            <pb facs="tcp:177232:46"/>
            <lg>
               <l>Ah <hi>Theſeus,</hi> yet returne: do not forget</l>
               <l>Thy ſelfe ſo much, to be ſo mercileſs;</l>
               <l>For my deſert of thee, relieue me yet,</l>
               <l>Before I fall into ſo great diſtreſs.</l>
               <l>Ah no! for my deſert I'll not intreate;</l>
               <l>Since thou neglect'ſt it, and my faithfulneſs.</l>
               <l>Yet be 'it thy owne ſword ſau'd thy life, not I;</l>
               <l>It followes not that I ſhould therefore dye.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>O if ere humane pitty one ſoft beame ſhed</l>
               <l>Into thy boſome, let me not in vaine</l>
               <l>Thus ſtill implore thee; but (though far hence fled)</l>
               <l>Steare hither that ſo long'd-for Barke againe.</l>
               <l>And if at thy returne thou finde me dead,</l>
               <l>Let yet thy hapleſſe wiues colde bones obtaine</l>
               <l>This mercy; to be gath'red vp by thee,</l>
               <l>And in thy natiue <hi>Athens</hi> buried be.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>While thus th'afflicted one (her ſhining haire</l>
               <l>And faire fleſh tearing) desperately mournes;</l>
               <l>And in her reſtleſs fit of rage, and feare</l>
               <l>(Mixt Feauer-like) freezes at once, and burnes;</l>
               <l>Th'euer-young god, that late was conquerer</l>
               <l>Of <hi>Inde,</hi> and now thence vnder ſayle returnes,</l>
               <l>In happy houre eſpyes her; and his ſayles</l>
               <l>Directs toward the rock whereon ſhe wayles.</l>
            </lg>
            <pb facs="tcp:177232:46"/>
            <lg>
               <l>Soone as the <hi>Ioue</hi>-borne <hi>Bacchus</hi> his gaze bent</l>
               <l>On her ſheene forhead, and aluring eyes;</l>
               <l>And (with the ſhrill ſighes that her boſome rent)</l>
               <l>Obſeru'd the ſweet ſad tenor of her cryes;</l>
               <l>And vnderſtood her linage and deſcent</l>
               <l>Deriu'd from two ſo ſupreame dietyes</l>
               <l>As <hi>Ioue</hi> himſelfe by <hi>Sires;</hi> by mothers ſide</l>
               <l>From the bright God that doth the wing'd Day guide;</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>He burnes in amorous fire; prayes, perſwades, tryes</l>
               <l>From their ſad moode her ſorrowing thoughts to wooe</l>
               <l>With all the ſofteſt words he can deuiſe:</l>
               <l>But findes all vaine that he can ſay, or doo.</l>
               <l>She heedes him not; but ſtill on <hi>Theſeus</hi> cryes.</l>
               <l>Yet he, reſolu'd to winne, and wed her too,</l>
               <l>Summons the <hi>Paphian</hi> queene; and to her care</l>
               <l>Commits the menage of his loues affaire.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>
                  <hi>Venus,</hi> that euer was god <hi>Bacchus</hi> friend,</l>
               <l>(And whom his abſence faint, &amp; mirthleſs makes<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>)</l>
               <l>Doth at his call, her beſt aſsiſtance lend;</l>
               <l>And to accompliſh what ſhe vndertakes,</l>
               <l>With carefull hand doth to the cure attend</l>
               <l>Of th'olde wound (firſt,) whereof her boſome akes.</l>
               <l>Which heald; ſhe' inſpires <hi>Liaeus</hi> eyes, that dart</l>
               <l>New fires, which through her eyes inflame her heart.</l>
            </lg>
            <pb facs="tcp:177232:47"/>
            <lg>
               <l>And for his ſake, to do her grace, whom he</l>
               <l>Hath choſen for companion of his bed;</l>
               <l>Though from <hi>Apollo</hi> ſhe deſcended be,</l>
               <l>(Whom ſince her ſtolne loues he diſcouered,</l>
               <l>She hates;) yet as from her ſires forfait free,</l>
               <l>She'imbraces her; and from her owne faire head</l>
               <l>A bright crowne takes, (for mortall browes vnfit,</l>
               <l>So rich it was;) and crownes her browes with it.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>This Crowne had <hi>Vulcan</hi> forg'd: Earth's richeſt myne</l>
               <l>The matter gaue; which to imbelliſh more,</l>
               <l>He taught the curious hoope all o're to ſhine</l>
               <l>With brighteſt gemmes the wealthy <hi>Orient</hi> bore.</l>
               <l>So rich a diadem ſcarſe Powre diuine,</l>
               <l>Much leſſe inferiour Mortall euer wore.</l>
               <l>No maruaile; ſince the great Artificer</l>
               <l>Made it of purpoſe for his wife to weare.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>The <hi>Cyprian</hi> goddeſſe with her faire hand dries</l>
               <l>The wayling mayds drown'd cheekes <hi>Liaeus</hi> wooes;</l>
               <l>She ſhuns; but faintly. Faintly' a while denies.</l>
               <l>At laſt yeelds For alas how can ſhe chooſe,</l>
               <l>Aſſayl'd by two ſo powrefull dyeties?</l>
               <l>Her minde doth now all thought of <hi>Theſeus</hi> looſe.</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Bacchus</hi> ſhe loues. He marries her. And (night</l>
               <l>Once come) both taſte the nuptiall beds delight.</l>
            </lg>
            <pb facs="tcp:177232:47"/>
            <lg>
               <l>And that her fame (although ſhe mortall were)</l>
               <l>Might to enſuing times be euer new;</l>
               <l>The pleas'd god takes the crowne from her faire haire;</l>
               <l>Which as to th'<hi>Artick</hi> ycie <hi>Pole</hi> he threw,</l>
               <l>The diadem through thinne and yeelding ayre</l>
               <l>In an vninterrupted circle flew</l>
               <l>Vp tow'rds <hi>Bootes,</hi> and the ſlowe Teeme; where</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Arcturus</hi> guards the great, and leſſer Beare.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>As it aſcends, each pretious gemme thereon</l>
               <l>Redoubled luſter by the motion gaines.</l>
               <l>A ſeu'erall Starre is now each ſeu'erall ſtone.</l>
               <l>Yet ſo the former ſhape entyre remaynes,</l>
               <l>As ſtill in eu'ry eye that lookes thereon,</l>
               <l>The Conſtellation a crownes forme retaynes.</l>
               <l>And when the ſullen night on th'earth doth frowne,</l>
               <l>Who ſee's it, calls it <hi>Ariadnes Crowne.</hi>
               </l>
            </lg>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
