<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Andria the first comoedie of Terence, in English. A furtherance for the attainment vnto the right knowledge, &amp; true proprietie, of the Latin tong. And also a commodious meane of help, to such as haue forgotten Latin, for their speedy recouering of habilitie, to vnderstand, write, and speake the same. Carefully translated out of Latin, by Maurice Kyffin.</title>
            <title>Andria. English</title>
            <author>Terence.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1588</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 176 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 45 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-04">2011-04 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A13611</idno>
            <idno type="STC">STC 23895</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC S111416</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99846768</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99846768</idno>
            <idno type="VID">11757</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A13611)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 11757)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 399:14)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>Andria the first comoedie of Terence, in English. A furtherance for the attainment vnto the right knowledge, &amp; true proprietie, of the Latin tong. And also a commodious meane of help, to such as haue forgotten Latin, for their speedy recouering of habilitie, to vnderstand, write, and speake the same. Carefully translated out of Latin, by Maurice Kyffin.</title>
                  <title>Andria. English</title>
                  <author>Terence.</author>
                  <author>Kyffin, Maurice, d. 1599.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[88] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>By T[homas] E[ast] for Thomas VVoodcocke, at the signe of the black Beare in Paules Church-yard,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>Printed at London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1588.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>At foot of title: Plura posthac.</note>
                  <note>Printer's name from STC.</note>
                  <note>Signatures: [fleuron]⁴ A-K⁴.</note>
                  <note>[Fleuron]3 is signed [par.]3.</note>
                  <note>Running title reads: The first comoedie of Terence.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the Henry E. Huntington Library and Art Gallery.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2009-07</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-08</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-12</date>
            <label>Simon Charles</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-12</date>
            <label>Simon Charles</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-04</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:11757:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:11757:1"/>
            <p>ANDRIA The firſt Comoedie of Terence, in Engliſh.</p>
            <p>A furtherance for the attain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment vnto the right knowledge, &amp;
true proprietie, of the Latin Tong. And alſo a commodious meane of help, to
ſuch as <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1+ letters">
                  <desc>•…</desc>
               </gap>ue forgotten Latin, for
their ſpeedy recouering of habilitie, to vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtand, write, and ſpeake
the ſame.</p>
            <p>Carefully tranſlated out of Latin, by Maurice Kyffin.</p>
            <q>Haud fruſtrà Spero.</q>
            <q> 
               <p>Comoedia, Imitatio Vitae: Speculum Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſuetudinis: Imago
Veritatis.</p> 
               <bibl>Cic.</bibl>
            </q>
            <p>Printed at London by T.E. for <hi>Thomas Woodcocke,</hi> at the
Signe of the black Beare in Paules Church<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>yard. 1588.</p>
            <q>Plura Poſthac.</q>
            <figure>
               <figDesc>author's device</figDesc>
               <q>HAVD FRVSTRA SPERO.</q>
               <p>M Kyffin</p>
               <q>INVITA INVIDIA</q>
            </figure>
         </div>
         <div type="encomia">
            <pb facs="tcp:11757:2"/>
            <div type="poem">
               <head>In M. Kyffini Andriam.</head>
               <l>CAutè ſectatus quondam, ſapienſque
<hi>Menandrum,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>Aeternum nomen <hi>Publius</hi> eſt meritus.</l>
               <l>Conſimiles laudes puto te <hi>Kyffine</hi> mereri,</l>
               <l>Afri quod Vatis ſtrictè imitere pedem.</l>
               <l>Namque aliena ſequi, quam ſit veſtigia magnum</l>
               <l>Noui. Qui neſcit, carpere ſolus auet.</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Andria</hi> multarum fuit illi prima ſororum:</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Andria</hi> ſit caueas vltima ſcena tibi.</l>
               <closer>
                  <signed>W. Morgan.</signed>
               </closer>
            </div>
            <div type="poem">
               <head>In Andriam a M. Kyffino Angl. donatam.</head>
               <l>ARte laborata prodit vetus <hi>Andria,</hi> veſte</l>
               <l>Cultior: &amp; noſtris nunc magis apta ſcholis.</l>
               <l>Reſtat, vt <hi>Eunuchum,</hi> reliquoſque annectere
libros</l>
               <l>Pergas: nam facilis iam labor omnis erit.</l>
               <closer>
                  <signed>Th. Lloid.</signed>
               </closer>
            </div>
            <div type="poem">
               <head>Eiuſdem in Zoylum.</head>
               <l>INuide quid turges? quid non laudabile cernis?</l>
               <l>Dic, ſi diſpliceat, quis meliora dedit?</l>
            </div>
            <div type="poem">
               <head>In Andriam Anglicè a M. Kyffino con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerſam. G.
Camdeni Tetraſtichon.</head>
               <l>DVm laudes cumulare tuas <hi>Kyffine</hi> parabam,</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Andria</hi> quòd ſtudiis facta ſit Angla
tuis:</l>
               <l>Adſtitit en ſtatim, ridenſque <hi>Terentius</hi>
inquit,</l>
               <l>Quid vis? quid laudas? carpere nemo poteſt.</l>
            </div>
            <div type="poem">
               <pb facs="tcp:11757:3"/>
               <head>In amiciſs, ſui, M. Kyffini Andriam, Petri Bizari
Carmen.</head>
               <lg>
                  <l>VT nemo ex Comicis, Latina lingua</l>
                  <l>Quos effert, potuit Terentianum</l>
                  <l>Stylum vincere, candidum, &amp; nitentem,</l>
                  <l>Purumque, ac ſine fuco, &amp; arte mira</l>
                  <l>Constructum, ac ſalibus facetijsque</l>
                  <l>Conditum vndi<expan>
                        <am>
                           <g ref="char:abque"/>
                        </am>
                        <ex>que</ex>
                     </expan>, et omnibus placentem:</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>Sic nemo tua ſcripta, quae Terentii</l>
                  <l>Senſus, verbáque in Anglicum relata</l>
                  <l>Sermonem, enucleant, venuſta &amp; apta,</l>
                  <l>Verborum ſerie, optimîſque verbis</l>
                  <l>Vincet. Perge itaque, vt facis, iuuare</l>
                  <l>Et dulcem patriam, &amp; ſimul perennem</l>
                  <l>Aeternamque tibi parare laudem.</l>
               </lg>
               <closer>
                  <signed>Petrus Bizarus.</signed>
               </closer>
            </div>
            <div type="poem">
               <head>R. Cooke to the Readers of Mr. Kyffins Tranſlation.</head>
               <l>THE perfect pattern of pure Latin ſpeche,</l>
               <l>In Engliſh phraſe moſt fitly here expreſt,</l>
               <l>Yelds Pleaſure, Profit, Eaſe, and Aide, to eche,</l>
               <l>That would of Latin language be poſſeſt.</l>
               <l>Thank <hi>Kyffin</hi> then, whoſe pen hath purchaſt
praiſe:</l>
               <l>His pain (your gaine) deſerues the ſame alwaies.</l>
            </div>
         </div>
         <div type="dedication">
            <pb facs="tcp:11757:3"/>
            <head>TO THE RIGHT WOORSHIPFVLL, AND woorthy gentleman, Maiſter
<hi>VVilliam Sackeuille,</hi> ſonne to the Right honorable (my verie good L.
and Maiſter) The Lord Buckhurſt, one of her Maieſties moſt honorable
priuie Councell.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">S</seg>IR, by intermiſsion of your noble exerciſes in feats of
Armes, and your ſtudious endeuor emploied in forrein tongs: I muſt needes
craue at your hands, to vouchſafe ſome ſpare tyme (for your recreation)
in the intertein<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of your old acquaintance <hi>Pub. Tere<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tius:</hi> whom I
here preſent vnto you, in ſuch and ſo much, Engliſh attire, as my poore
iudgement found fitteſt for him to be clad withall.</p>
            <p>Whyle he liued at <hi>Rome,</hi> his moſt com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pany, and
conuerſation, was among the Nobilitie, and moſt of al other, with thoſe
twoo noble and learned gentlemen, <hi>Laeli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>us,</hi> and <hi>Scipio
Africane:</hi> In like ſort, after his death, his woorks were right currantly
accounted of, and highly commended, by the two Princes of eloquence, euen
<hi>Caeſar,</hi> 
               <pb facs="tcp:11757:4"/> and <hi>Cicero:</hi> as their own vvritings do
wit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes the ſame vnto vs. Therefore, ſith <hi>Te<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rence,</hi> neither aliue,
nor dead, did euer vvant a noble Moecenas to protect him: I hope that novv,
being partly put into en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gliſh, &amp; hauing cheefly choſen you for his
Patrone in Engla<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d: you likevviſe, in regard of your noble birth, &amp;
vertues, wil graunt him like curteous &amp; frendly fauour, as by theſe noble
men in <hi>Rome,</hi> vvas heretofore affoorded vnto him. I truſt alſo he
ſhal be neuer the vvoorſe vvelcome vnto you, in that he is diligently
attended on, vvith my poore name: &amp; like as my firſt attempt to
tranſlate him, proceeded cheefly fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> you, ſo look I that my labour ſpe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t
on him, ſhal be fauorablie protected by your vvhich to me vvill bee a thing
much comfortable, &amp; to you nothing cu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>berſome. And ſo, fully
re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſting, &amp; relying my ſelfe on your vvonted curteſies, I here make
an end: &amp; beſech the almighty, ſtil to increaſe &amp; acco<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>pliſh,
thoſe his good gifts &amp; graces, vvhich he hath pla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ced in you moſt
ſhining &amp; apparant.</p>
            <closer>
               <dateline>At London. 
<date>Decemb. 3. 1587.</date>
               </dateline> 
               <signed>By your wor, alwaies to be commaunded <hi>Maurice
Kyffin.</hi>
               </signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="dedication">
            <pb facs="tcp:11757:4"/>
            <head>TO THE RIGHT WOORSHIPFVL GENTLE<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men, maiſter <hi>Henry,</hi>
and maiſter <hi>Thomas Sackeuille,</hi> ſonnes to the Right Honorable the
Lord Buckhurſt (one of her Maieſties moſt honorable Priuie Councell,)
<hi>Maurice Kyffin</hi> wiſheth all health, and happines.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg>T is now full. 7. yeeres (as you can well reme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ber) ſince I
firſt attempted the tranſlation of <hi>Andria</hi> into Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſh verſe,
being thereto partely inci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted by your meanes: But afterward perceiuing what
difficultie it was, to enforce the pithie and prouerbiall ſayings of
<hi>Terence</hi> into Rime, and withall what inconuenience grew, by reaſon of
diuers ſeuerall Speakers, ſometime ſeuerally happening, within the length
of one line or leſſe: I playnely ſaw, that ſuch manner of forced
tranſlation, muſt needs be both harſh and vnpleaſa<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t to the Reader, and
alſo not halfe ſeemly beſitting the ſweete ſtyle and eloquence of the
Author. So as hauing thus tranſla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted the whole Comoedie in verſe (ſauing
the two laſt leaues) my paines beſtowed therein did ſomuch miſlike me,
as that euer ſithens yt lay by me, vtterly neglect<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted, and neuer fully
finiſhed: Tyll that now of late, being by ſome, much requeſted to make
common the ſame, for the benefit of ſuch as ſtudie the latin: I haue
therevpon ſomwhat altered my cours, and indeuored to turne it into proſe,
as a thing of leſſe labour in ſhow, <pb facs="tcp:11757:5"/> and more libertie in
ſubſtance, ſeeming withall, moſt accordant, with this Comicall kinde of
writing. And bicauſe I am not ignorant, with what ardent loue, and liking,
you haue alwaies, moſt ſtudiouſlie embraced all good Authors: (being of
your ſelues, euen naturally in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clined, to all learning and knowledge:) I
cannot ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore, but recome<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d to your fauour, this peece of <hi>Terence,</hi>
bearing the frame of my poore workemanſhip: which I deſire you, at idle,
and vacant times, to vouchſafe to peruſe, both for <hi>Terence</hi> ſake,
whom I am ſure you loue: And alſo at my requeſt, whom I know you do not
hate. And ſo I commit you to the moſt gracious Protection of the
Higheſt.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="preface">
            <pb facs="tcp:11757:5"/>
            <head>A Preface to the cur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teous Reader.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">A</seg>MONG all the Romane writers, there is none (by the iudgement of
the learned) ſo much auailable to bée read and ſtudied, for the true
knowledge and puritie of the Latin tong, as <hi>Pub. Terentius:</hi> for,
ſith the chée<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſt matter in ſpeech, is to ſpeak properly and
aptly, and that we haue not a more cun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning Craftſ-maſter of apt and proper
ſpéech than <hi>Te<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rence,</hi> well woorthy is he then, euen with all
care and dilligence, to be both taught and learned before any o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther. And
ſurely, great is the pity, that <hi>Terence</hi> were not more vſed of
maiſters in teaching, and made more familiar to ſchollers in learning, than
commonly it is: being (as I haue knowen my ſelfe) by dyuers men, in diuers
ſentences, diuerſly miſvnderſtood: for, the Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thor in many places,
vſing abbreuiations, and figura<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiue ſpéeches, aſwell in regard of
his verſe, as alſo that ſuch maner of writing, was very eloquent and
famili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ar in his tyme: doth thereby cauſe the ſence ſéeme very
doubtful, to ſuch Readers as are not fully acquainted with him: which comes
to paſſe, by meanes that this booke, is not ſo frequented in ſchooles,
nor laboured in ſtudie, according to the woorthines of it: but other baſe
and inferior bookes, commonly preferd before it, to the vtter marring, and
maiming of Schollers both in ſtile and iudgement.</p>
            <p>Though this Comoedie, now engliſhed, perhaps ſéeme not
altogether ſo pleaſant, as could be wiſhed, neither in matter, nor manner
of handling: Yet is it to be con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſidered <pb facs="tcp:11757:6"/> (beſides that it
léeſeth his natural grace, being turnd into another language) that the
tyme when, and the place where, it was firſt publiſhed in Latin, affoor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded
no other ſort of Comoedies than this is. And there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore, it was no part of my
meaning, to tra<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſlate the ſame, as a thing either pleaſant to be played,
or very delight<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful to bée read: (Notwithſtanding that this Author was
moſt excellent, and moſt learned, of any that wrote in this kinde:) but
eſpecially, for that the Latin is pure &amp; eloquent, much commended by
<hi>Tullie</hi> himſelfe, &amp; right requiſite to be ſtudied, &amp;
vnderſtood of all ſuch, as would attaine to the knowledge of right
ſpeaking, and readi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes of wel writing, in the Latin tong: for whoſe only
ſakes (and alſo at the earneſt requeſt of ſome, whom I was deſirous
to ſatiſfy) I haue aduentured the engli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhing hereof: wiſhing, that as
I haue thus boldly begoon with the firſt, ſo ſome other hauing more
leiſure, and learning, would go thorough with the reſt of the Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>medies. I
haue vſed (as neere as I could) the moſt knowen, vſuall, and familiar
phraſes in common ſpéech, to expreſſe the authors meaning, as
(to my thinking) beſt agréeing therewithall. Neuertheles, I make
ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>count my doing herein, ſhall be carpt and caueld at by ſome, from
whoſe malicious cenſure, euen the beſt writers can not ſcape vntouched,
and therefore no mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ueile if they ſpurne at me. Of which kinde of men, I
haue knowen by experience, &amp; noted for memory, twoo ſorts: One ſort
pretending a ſhew of learning, &amp; being indéed but very dunſes,
loue to be ſpeaking they wot not what, to diſgrace they care not whom, and
yet not rendring any reaſon why, but onely to feed their owne bad humours: In
whom, true iudgement, being alto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether ſuppreſt, what with affection, or
ignorance, or both: as either mooued by fond lyking, to commend that is bad: or
ſtird with fowle hatred to diſpraiſe that is good: are thus commonly
carried along, with the vaine tyde and winde of their willes, without any
re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gard <pb facs="tcp:11757:6"/> of right, or due reſpect of wrong. An other ſort
(whereof I knew ſome good ſchollers, the more the pi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty) blinded with
ouerweening of themſelues, and miſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lyking al other mens dooings (how wel
ſoeuer they de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerue:) like onely of their owne, be they neuer ſo mean:
neuer geuing any man his due, fearing, by like, what<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoeuer commendation is
attributed to others, that the ſame muſt néeds be a derogation fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
themſelues: wher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in they are far vnlike <hi>Tullie,</hi> the welſpring of
wit and learning: who alwaies praiſed, all men of deſert, euen in thoſe
things, wherein he both deſired, and deſerued, moſt praiſe himſelfe:
This is read of <hi>Tullie,</hi> to his great praiſe, and remembred of others
to their iuſt reproch. And here, leaſt perchance I be miſtaken more than
I would, &amp; miſconſtrued otherwiſe than I meane, though my woords
before doo ſufficiently declare my meaning: yet (to auoyd all dowt) it
ſhall not be amiſſe, if I ad a few more in this place. To diſalow the
iudgement of ſuch, as by learning can, and by reaſon know, where, when, and
how, to finde fault, as iuſt cauſe and matter ſhall lead them: were to be
wilfully blinde, and obſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nately fooliſh: God forbid I ſhould be ſo
vnreaſonable, or that men ſhould iudge of mée ſo vnrightly.</p>
            <p>Of the curious <hi>Carper</hi> I looke not to be fauoured, and yet
if my labour may be equally compared with my Authors words and meaning, I doubt
not but it will appeare vnto him, an eaſier matter to finde fault with part,
than to amend the whole.</p>
            <p>Onely, I ſubmit this poore tranſlation vnto the vew &amp;
iudgement of the learned: who lyking the Truth, and louing to ſpeake Truth,
will both allow what is well don, and amend that is amiſſe: As for others,
I ſee not but that they ought firſt to learne, before they take vppon them
to Controll:</p>
            <closer>
               <salute>Farewel.</salute>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="to_the_reader">
            <pb facs="tcp:11757:7"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:11757:7"/>
            <head>To all young Students OF THE LATIN TONG (for whoſe onely help
and benifit this Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moedie is publiſhed) Maurice Kyffin, wiſheth encreaſe
of knowledge, &amp; finall perfection.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">H</seg>Ow neceſſarie, the vſe and familiaritie of
<hi>Terence,</hi> is for all ſuch, as would attaine, vnto ripenes in
vnderſtanding, readynes in ſpeaking, and right iudge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment in writing Latin:
is a thing, ſo commonly knowen and confeſſed of all men, as I ſhall not
néede any reaſons to prooue the ſame. Therefore, for the better
furthering of thoſe, that as yet are vnacquainted with him, I was the ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther
perſwaded, to publiſh this my Tranſlation of <hi>Andria:</hi> wherein,
whither my labour meriteth, ought, or nought, <hi>Aliorum ſit
Iudicium.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>My chéefeſt care hath bin, to lay open the meaning of the
Author, eſpecially, in all hard and difficult places of this Comoedie, and to
vtter the ſame, in ſuch apt, plaine, and familiar words, as are moſt
méete, for this low ſtile and Argument: for, to handle a meane matter,
with high and lofty phraſe, were as great ouerſight, &amp; lack of
iudgement as could be.</p>
            <p>Touching the interpretation of ſome places in <hi>An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dria.</hi>
I was forced to diſſent, from ſome of no ſmall Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thoritie, and
ſpecially from one very learned man, who occaſioned (in a work that he
wrote) to engliſh certaine diſperſed phraſes of <hi>Terence,</hi> hath
(without offence be it ſpoken) ſo engliſhed ſome, and namely in
<hi>Andria,</hi> as I am faine to forſake the ſame, and giue other quite
con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trary engliſhe vnto them.</p>
            <p>One of thoſe places in <hi>Andria,</hi> hath theſe words:
<hi>Ali<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quid monſtri alunt.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Act. 1. Scen. 5.</note> By
him thus engliſhed: <hi>They bring <pb facs="tcp:11757:8"/> ſome monſtrous
creature:</hi> And by mée in this ſort: <hi>They cloake ſome
ſecret fault in her:</hi> which may bee ſéene, interpreted to that
effect, by <hi>Eraſ. Roterod.</hi> han<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dling that place in his
<hi>Chiliads.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>An other place, is this, (conteining the anſwere of
<hi>Pamphilus</hi> vnto <hi>Carinus:</hi>) <hi>Neque pol conſilij locum
habeo, neque auxilij copiam:</hi>
               <note place="margin">Act. 2. Scen. 1.</note>
which he hath thus en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gliſhed: <hi>I neither haue place to take counſaill,
nor helpe of any man:</hi> and by me contrariwiſe, as thus: <hi>In good
faith, I am neither a meete man to geue counſail, nor yet haue wherewith to
helpe another.</hi> Now to prooue that I haue geuen it a right Engliſh: read
that page in <hi>Terence,</hi> and you ſhall ſoone fynde, that of
neceſſitie the ſence muſt ſo be ment and taken. Some other like
places I could recite, but theſe ſhall ſuffice for a Say: whereof I
thought good to aduertiſe you, to thend you may ſée, that my
diſſenting (in theſe points) from a man of ſo great learning and
authority, hath not bin without vrgent occaſion.</p>
            <p>One thing more I muſt note vnto you, that com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monly in all
bookes of <hi>Terence,</hi> this place of <hi>Andria, [Num quod tuiſperas
propulſabo facile]</hi>
               <note place="margin">Act. 2. Scene. 3.</note> is noted
thus in the margine: <hi>Speras .j. times:</hi> which, put the caſe,
<hi>Speras</hi> were here ſo to bée vnderſtood (as I ſée no
rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon why it ſhould) yet neuertheles, the ſence remaines ſtill very
lame and vnperfect: vnderſtand you there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore, that as <hi>Dauus</hi> in that
Scene, counſelleth <hi>Pamphi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lus</hi> to make anſweare to his father that
he will marry: ſo <hi>Pamphilus</hi> on the other ſide, (fearing that would
bée a meane to induce marriage betwixt him and <hi>Philume<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>na</hi>) will
not in a good while geue conſent thereunto: thinking (as it ſéemes)
that by not aſſenting to his fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers will therein, he ſhall be quite
freed from marry<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing either her, or any other: for hée hoped that no man
would geue him his doughter in marryage, ſith his ſtate and condition was
ſo to be reiected: wherefore <pb facs="tcp:11757:8"/> 
               <hi>Dauus</hi> perceiuing whereupon
he moſt inſiſted: ſéekes to diſſwade him from the ſame,
and among other rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons vſeth this: 
<q> 
                  <l>Nam quod tu ſperas, propulſabo facile,</l> 
                  <l>Vxorem his moribus</l> 
                  <l>Dabit nemo: Iuueniet inopem potius quam te corrum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pi
ſinat.</l>
               </q> Which (for your better vnderſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding) I haue thus
tranſlated by way of Paraphraſe:</p>
            <p>
               <hi>For as for that vaine hope of yours (imagining thus with your
ſelfe, tuſh it is no danger for mee to with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtand my father: No man will
marry his doughter vnto a man of my manners) I ſhall eaſily put you out of
that hope: hee wil finde out a poore and mean marriage for you, rather than hee
will ſuffer you to bee ſp<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>t by
Harlots.</hi>
               <note place="margin">In the inter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pretation of this place. I haue
wholly re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lyed vpon the iudgement of that learned man Muretus, who expoun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deth
the ſame to this effect.</note> By this you may ſee, that it much better
beſitteth the woord <hi>Speras,</hi> here in this place, to haue his owne
naturall ſignification of <hi>Hope,</hi> than that wreſted ſignification
of <hi>Feare.</hi> I know by expe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rience, that ſome Scholemaſters are to
ſeeke in theſe matters themſelues, and therefore no maruayll though their
Schollers be ignorant. And here I remember one Scholemaiſter aboue the
reſt: who (notwithſtanding hée were maiſter of Art,) was yet ſo
blunt and vnſkilfull in <hi>Terence,</hi> as (a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mong other errors) he taught
his Schollers to vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtand this place of <hi>Andria [Non tu ibi
gnatum]</hi> in this ſort. <hi>Non tu ibi gnatum <hi>ſupple</hi>
Negaſti:</hi>
               <note place="margin">Act 1. Scen. 1.</note> whereas it
manifeſtly appeareth by the next lyne following, that the woord
<hi>Obiurgaſti</hi> is there to be vnderſtood, and not <hi>Negaſti.</hi>
Moreouer, for that the not well vnderſtanding of the Argument of this
co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moedie, hath in diuers, bred errors and miſtakings: I haue therefore bin
carefull herein to explane the Argument at large vnto you: and withall, to
ſet downe each particular Argument before euery Scene. Lykewyſe, by my
notes in the margine, <pb facs="tcp:11757:9"/> you ſhall be inſtructed (as occaſion
is offered) touching any dowtfull ſpéeches of the ſpeakers: as
whether they ſpeake vnto him that ſpake laſt before, or elſe to the
audience, or to themſelues.</p>
            <p>Thus, haue I for your ſakes, bin carefull to diſſolue all
dowts, and difficulties, in this part of <hi>Terence:</hi> which, if I may
perceiue, that you doo as curteouſly ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cept from me, as it is frendly ment
for you: I ſhal bée more willing (if God ſpare me life and health)
to plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure you hereafter in a greater matter: In the meane tyme, I commit
you to God, and my ſelfe into your good loue and frendſhip.</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>Your faithfull wellwiller M. K.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="argument">
            <pb facs="tcp:11757:9"/>
            <head>The Argument of the COMOEDIE.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">C</seg>Hremes &amp; Phania (two brethren) were citizens of Athens:
which Chremes, ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king his iourney into Aſia, left Paſsi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bula (as then his
onely daughter) to the charge and ſafe keeping of his brother Phania: but not
long after his depar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, there enſued in Greece ſo great ſturre and
tumult of warre, as that Phania determining to folow his bro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther into Aſia,
did therefore embarke himſelfe (and his little Neece Paſsibula) for that
voyage: But, a ſore tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peſt ariſing, he ſuſteined ſhipwrack in
ſuch ſort, as both he and his forenamed Neece, were caſt on ſhore at
the Ile of Andros, where he chaunced into the houſe of a certain dweller in
that countrie, by whome he was gent<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly receiued and relieued, &amp; in whoſe
houſe ſhortly after he died. After whoſe death, the good man of the
houſe changed the name of the young childe, calling her by the name of
Glycerie: and when he had by the ſpace of cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teine yeeres, brought her vp
with like care, and in like knowledge, as he did bring vp his owne daughter
Chry<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſis, he likewiſe ended his lyfe. Chryſis (perceiuing her ſelfe
bereft of Father and friends, &amp; being alſo pinched with pouertie) toke
Glycerie with her, and ſayled to A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thens. In which Citie, during a ſmall
ſeaſon, ſhe earned her liuing by Wooll and making Cloth: but afterward,
being haunted by certain youths, who fed her with guifts and faire promiſes,
ſhe (ouercome by thoſe men, and by theſe meanes) yelded the vſe of her
bodie for gaine. A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mong other younkers, Pamphilus the ſonne of Simo, a well
minded young man, dyd oftentimes reſort to the houſe, not for her ſake,
but onely for the great loue and <pb facs="tcp:11757:10"/> liking he bare vnto Glycerie: by
whome Glycerie, (with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in a while,) proouing to be with childe, he made
faithfull promis vnto her, that he would make her his wife. By this time,
Chremes (hauing long ſince returned home to Athens,) had an other daughter
become marriageable, named Philumena, whome he much deſired to match in
marriage with Pamphilus, in reſpect of the good re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>port that generally went
of him: Wherevpon, by his owne ſeeking vnto Simo for the ſame, the match
with conſent of both parents, is made vp, &amp; vtterly vnawares vnto
Pamphilus, a day is appointed for the marriage.</p>
            <p>In the meane ſeaſon Chryſis dyeth, by which meanes Simo came
firſt to knowledge that his ſonne is in loue. For at the buriall of
Chryſis, Glycerie for pure griefe and ſorrow being about to haue throwen
her ſelfe into the fire with the coars, was ſo ſpeedely ſtayed, and
ſo louingly recomforted by Pamphilus, as thereby their wonted loue and
familiaritie was manifeſtly bewrayed. Herevpon Chremes reuoked his former
offer, declaring how he had certaine intelligence that Pamphilus vſed this
ſtrange minion for his wife: little thinking that ſhe whome he termed by
ſo vile a name, was his owne daughter.</p>
            <p>Pamphilus (at length) perceiuing that Chremes brake of the
marriage, was very ioyfull: Simo on the other ſide was exceeding ſorry. The
day once appointed for the wedding, is come. Simo therfore of meere craft and
pollicie (determining to feele the mynde of his ſonne Pamphilus) pretendeth
notwithſtanding all this, that the marriage ſhall bee made out of hand:
with intent that if his ſonne ſhould refuſe to marrye, that thereby hee
might haue good occaſion to reprehend him, which till then hee could not well
doo. But contrarywiſe, yf his ſonne ſhould conſent to marry, than hee
hoped to obteyne his deſire at Chremes hands, and ſo to make vp 
<pb facs="tcp:11757:10"/> the marriage preſently. Therefore meeting with his ſonne,
(who little minded any ſuch matter) he ſpake thus vnto him: Pamphilus, go
home and make thee ready, thou muſt be married to day.</p>
            <p>Pamphilus ſoddeinly amaſed with theſe woords, knew neither
what to ſay, nor what to doo: But Da<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uus (a craftie knauiſh ſeruant)
ſmelling out the drift and deuiſe of the olde man, comes to Pamphilus and
ſhew<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth by circumſtance of tyme, place, and perſons, the great
vnlikelyhood of the marriage.</p>
            <p>In this very time Carinus (a young man of Athens) exceedingly
enamoured on Philumena, and heareing ſhe ſhould be furthwith married vnto
Pamphilus, dyd therefore come to him and prayed him for Gods ſake, as he
tendred his lyfe, that either he would not marry her at all, or at leaſt
wiſe, that he would put of the mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riage for a few dayes longer.</p>
            <p>Pamphilus on the other ſide being wonderfully in loue with
Glycerie, deſires nothing more than that he might haue quite and cleane
ryddance of this ſame mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riage pretended for him, and ſo made aunſwere
vnto Carinus accordingly. To this ende therefore, Dauus aduiſeth Pamphilus to
ſaye vnto his father, that he is willing to marry (though he ment nothing
leſſe) ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ping thereby both to ſatiſfie the minde of Simo, and withall
to continue ſtill loue and familiaritie with Gly<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerie, hauing no
miſtruſt in the world that Chremes would euer be induced to match his
daughter Philume<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>na vnto Pamphilus, whome he had once before reiected for his
ſonne in lawe. But Pamphilus folowing this deuiſe of Dauus, is notably
ouertaken, when and where he leaſt thought of: for Simo ſo much preuailed
with Chremes by earneſt intreatie, as that contrarie to all expectation, the
marriage matter is brought to that paſſe, euen to haue bene made out of
hand: <pb facs="tcp:11757:11"/> ſo as Dauus, hauing no other meane to ſhift of this
mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riage, cauſeth the childe, whereof Glycerie the ſame day was deliuered,
to be layed before Simoes dore: which, when Chremes ſaw, and vnderſtoode to
be the childe of Pamphilus, he ſtraight way falls of againe from perfor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mance
of the marriage. Heerevpon enſueth great ſturre and hurleburly, till that
by the comming of Crito from Andros to Athens, (by meere chaunce) euen the
whole difficulty of the Comoedie is diſſolued: for thorough him, Chremes
comes to certaine knowledge that Glycerie is his owne daughter, ſometime
called by the name of Paſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſibula: And ſo with great ioy and contentation
of all parts, he giues Glycerie in marriage vnto Pamphilus, and Philumena to
Carinus.</p>
            <p>
               <note n="*" place="margin">Some wil haue it conſiſt of 4. &amp;
the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>logue is y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> firſt.</note>¶The Comoedie conſiſts of
three parts: to witte: 
<q>
                  <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>,
<gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>,
<gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>
               </q> Which in Latin are
ſignified by theſe three woords: 
<q>
                  <hi>Propositio, Intentio, Conuersio.</hi>
               </q>
            </p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">
                  <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>.
<hi>Propositio.</hi>
               </note>The firſt, is <hi>Proposition,</hi> conteining the
firſt Act and the beginning of variety of Speakers, ſome entring, ſome
remaining on the Stage, and ſome departing away.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">
                  <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>.
<hi>Intentio.</hi>
               </note>The ſecond is <hi>Intention</hi> or <hi>Full
Sway,</hi> conteyning the growing on &amp; continuance of all the hot ſturre,
trouble and difficult ſtate of the Comoedie.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">
                  <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>.
<hi>Conuersio.</hi>
               </note>The third and laſt part, is <hi>Conuersion,</hi> in
the which all is turned to a ioyfull ende, and the whole matter made
knowen.</p>
            <p>By heedfull reading, and diligent marking, the due
<hi>Decorum</hi> obſerued by Terence in his Comoedies, the <pb facs="tcp:11757:11"/>
ſcholer ſhall gather verie much pleaſure and profit, as for example, in
this Comoedie of Andria, he oppoſeth ſeuerall ſpeakers, of ſeuerall
natures, and contrary con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dicions, one to another: as, Simo beeing hot and
teſty, is oppoſed vnto Chremes, a milde and moderate man. Pamphilus, a
ſtayed and ſhamefaſt young man, is oppo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed vnto Carinus, a harebraind
fellow voyde of diſcreti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on. Dauus, a ſlye and ſuttle ſeruant, is
oppoſed vnto Byr<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ria, a ſlouthfull and rechles fellow. Myſis, a ſober
maide, is oppoſed vnto Leſbia, a drunken Goſsip. Crito, honeſt and
poore, is oppoſed vnto Chryſis, diſhoneſt and rich.</p>
            <p>Theſe perſo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s, are of ſet purpoſe thus placed by Terence,
to the end that the vndue demeanor in the one, may the ſooner be ſeen by
the contrarie in the other.</p>
            <p>Very ſinguler alſo is the eloquence of the Author, in
ſetting downe the moane and complaint of Pamphilus, The Narration,
Conſultation, and Reprehenſion of Simo: From which places, are to be
learned choice woords, apt figures, and right order of ſpeaking Latin.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="dramatis_personae">
            <pb facs="tcp:11757:12"/>
            <head>¶The ſpeakers in this Comoedie.</head>
            <list>
               <label>Simo,</label>
               <item>the olde man.</item>
               <label>Soſia,</label>
               <item>the late Bondman.</item>
               <label>Dauus,</label>
               <item>the ſeruant.</item>
               <label>Myſis,</label>
               <item>the maide.</item>
               <label>Pamphilus,</label>
               <item>a young man.</item>
               <label>Byrria,</label>
               <item>the ſeruant.</item>
               <label>Lesbia,</label>
               <item>the Midwife.</item>
               <label>Glycerie,</label>
               <item>Louer vnto <hi>Pamphilus.</hi>
               </item>
               <label>Chremes,</label>
               <item>the olde man.</item>
               <label>Crito,</label>
               <item>the ſtranger.</item>
               <label>Dromo,</label>
               <item>the whipping Bedle.</item>
            </list>
         </div>
         <div n="1" type="act">
            <pb facs="tcp:11757:12"/>
            <div n="1" type="scene">
               <head>¶Act. 1. Scen. 1.</head>
               <argument>
                  <head>The Argument.</head>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Simo</hi> diſcourſeth vnto his late Bondman, firſt
of the honeſt life of his ſonne: And afterward of his falling in loue:
Laſtlie he diſcloſeth for what cauſe he faineth a mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riage for
him.</p>
               </argument>
               <stage> 
                  <list>
                     <item>
                        <hi>Simo,</hi> the olde man.</item>
                     <item> 
                        <hi>Soſia,</hi> the ſeruant.</item>
                  </list>
               </stage>
               <sp>
                  <p>
                     <seg rend="decorInit">S</seg>Irs, haue in theſe things: diſpatch. <hi>So<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſia</hi>
ſtay thou héere. I wil ſpeake a word or two with thée.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Soſia.</speaker>
                  <p>I know your minde alredie, you would haue theſe things wel
hand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Simo.</speaker>
                  <p>Nay, it is an other manner of matter.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>So.</speaker>
                  <p>What is it ſir? that my ſcience can ſtande you in more
ſteade than this comes to?</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Si.</speaker>
                  <p>There is no néede of that ſcience, for this matter
which I am now about: But faithfulneſſe and ſecrecie, which I alwaies
noted to bée in thée, are the ſciences I haue néede of
now.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>So.</speaker>
                  <p>I long to know what is your will with mée.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Si.</speaker>
                  <p>Thou wotſt how reaſonable and eaſie a bondage thou
hadſt with me, euer ſince the time I bought thée of a little one:
and by cauſe thou didſt thy ſeruice honeſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lie, and with good will, lo,
of a Bondſlaue I made thee my frée man, ſo as I rewarded thée
with the very beſt thing I had.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>So.</speaker>
                  <p>I remember it well.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Si.</speaker>
                  <p>I repent me not of that I did.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>So.</speaker>
                  <p>Maſter, I am glad if I haue done, or doe, any ſeruice that
may pleaſe you, and I thanke you with <pb facs="tcp:11757:13"/> all my heart that you
take it in good woorth: But yet this ſpéech of yours troubles
mée: for this manner of ripping vp things paſt, is as it were an
vpbrayding to one vnmindefull of a good turne done him: but ſpeake at a word
what is your will with mée.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Si.</speaker>
                  <p>So will I doe, onelie this I tell thée firſt and
formoſt: This marriage which thou wéeneſt to be certaine, is but a
fained marriage.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>So.</speaker>
                  <p>For what cauſe doo you pretend it than?</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Si.</speaker>
                  <p>Thou ſhalt heare all the matter from the begin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning, ſo
ſhalt thou vnderſtand both my ſonnes lyfe, and my purpoſe, and alſo
what I would haue thée do in this behalfe. When my ſonne grew to
mannes eſtate, it lay in his power to liue more at randon, for till than, how
could a man know his nature, or diſcerne his diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſition, while as
tender yéeres, fearefullneſſe, and his Maſter, kept him vnder.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>So.</speaker>
                  <p>It is true Sir.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Si.</speaker>
                  <p>That which all young men for the moſt parts do applying
their minds to ſome kinde of ſtudie or other, as either to horſes, and
horſmanſhip: or to kéepe hounds for hunting, or to ſtudie
Philoſophie: he gaue him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe ſpeciallie, to none of theſe things more
than other, and yet was reaſonablie well ſéene in them all: I was
glad of it.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>So.</speaker>
                  <p>And good cauſe why, for I holde it a verie com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>modious
matter in a mans lyfe, <hi>Not to go too far in any thing.</hi>
                  </p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Si.</speaker>
                  <p>In this ſorte was the manner of his lyfe, euen gently to
beare, and take all in good worth, at all mens hands that he kept companie
with: betaking himſelfe to doo as they did, and to follow their ſtudies and
exerciſes: Not thwarting any man, nor at any time putting furth himſelfe
before his companions, ſo as a man might full eaſily purchas prayſe, and
not be enuied, and alſo furniſh himſelfe with fréends.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <pb facs="tcp:11757:13"/>
                  <speaker>So.</speaker>
                  <p>He tooke him to a wiſe courſe of liuing, for now a dayes,
<hi>Flatry gaynes Freends, and Truthe gets Foes.</hi>
                  </p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Si.</speaker>
                  <p>In the meane time, a certaine woman of excel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lent beautie, and
in the flowre of age, came from <hi>An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dros,</hi> (now thrée
yéeres ſince) to dwell héere, in our neigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>borhod,
béeing thereto dryuen thorough very pouertie, and the ſmall reckning
that was made of her among her owne kindred.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>So.</speaker>
                  <p>Alas I feare mée, that this woman of <hi>Andros,</hi>
might be cauſe of ſome euell.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Si.</speaker>
                  <p>At the firſt, ſhe liued chaſtlie, ſparingly, and
hardly, earning her liuing by wooll and web. But af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terwards reſorted, now
one louer, and then an other, promiſing reward vnto her, and as all are
naturally geuen full ſoone to leaue of labour and follow luſt, euen ſo
this woman accepted the offers, and then ſhe began the gaine.</p>
                  <p>They which then loued her (as it fell out) carried my ſonne
thether, in company with them. I ſtraight way imagined with my ſelfe:
without doubt he is caught for a bird: he hath his errand: I watched their
Pages betimes in the morning, as they were wont to come thence, or goe thither:
I oftimes aſked, ho Sir boy, tell mée if thou be a good fellow, who
yeſterday had his pleaſure of <hi>Chryſis,</hi> (for ſo was the name of
her of <hi>An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dros.</hi>)</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>So.</speaker>
                  <p>I perceiue you.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Si.</speaker>
                  <p>They would ſay, either <hi>Phedria,</hi> or <hi>Clinia,</hi>
or <hi>Ni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceratus:</hi> for theſe thrée than loued her all at once.
But what did <hi>Pamphilus,</hi> hah? (What, ſayd they) Mary he ſupt and
payed his ſhare. I was well apaid of this. In like ſorte, I made enquirie
at an other time, and could not finde, that <hi>Pamphilus</hi> was any way
toucht with diſhoneſty. Therefore I thought I had ſuffici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ent tryall of
him, and that he was a notable Pattern of Chaſtitie: for he that hath to doe
with men of ſuch <pb facs="tcp:11757:14"/> condicions, and yet is not moued in mynde that
way, one wold thinke hee might ful well haue the rule and
<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1+ letters">
                        <desc>•…</desc>
                     </gap>uyding of his owne life. Now ouer
and beſides that this lyked my ſelfe well, lo all other men alſo, euen
with one cenſent, gaue al the commendations that might be, and praiſed my
happy ſtate, in that I <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap> a
ſonne, en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dued with ſo good witte and gouernment. What néede I make
many woordes? <hi>Chremes</hi> ſtird vp by this good report, came of him
ſelfe vnto me, to the end to match his onely daughter in marryage to my
ſonne, and that with a <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1+ letters">
                        <desc>•…</desc>
                     </gap>ry large
dowry: I was well pleaſ'd withall: promyſd him my ſonne: and this very
day was appoin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted for the marryage.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>So.</speaker>
                  <p>Why than what letteth, that it is not made ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cordingly?</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Si.</speaker>
                  <p>That ſhall thou heare: ſhortly after within few dayes that
theis thinges were a dooing, this <hi>Chryſis</hi> our neighbour dyed.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>So.</speaker>
                  <p>O happy chaunce, you haue now made mée glad, for
ſtill I doubted the woorſt of that <hi>Chryſis.</hi>
                  </p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Si.</speaker>
                  <p>Than ſpecially my ſon vſed thither, euer and anon in
company with thoſe which loued <hi>Chryſis:</hi> he was as buſie as the
beſt, in ſetting furth the buryal: beyng all this while very ſad: and now
and than, would euen ſhead teares with them for company: well, this alſo
lyked mée welinough: for thus thought I: hée that vppon ſmall
acquaintance and familiarity, takes this womans death ſo greeuouſly at the
hart? what if hee had loued her himſelfe? or how would he take on for me his
father? ſo as I tooke all this to haue proceeded of a good nature, and gentle
hart. To bée bréfe, I my ſelfe lykewiſe for his ſake go
furth to the buriall, miſtruſting no ill in the world.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>So.</speaker>
                  <p>O what followed?</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Si.</speaker>
                  <p>Thou ſhalt knowe by and by. The Coars is brought furth: we
paſſe along with it: Anon I chuance <pb facs="tcp:11757:14"/> to caſt myne eye (among
the women there) vpon an od young damoſell, of ſuch fauour.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>So.</speaker>
                  <p>What, ſo good?</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Si.</speaker>
                  <p>Yea <hi>Soſia,</hi> of ſuch modeſt and ſober
countenance and ſo paſſing beautifull to looke too, as there could not
poſſibly bée more in a woman: who than to my ſéeming, made
greater ſorrow than any of the reſt: And for that ſhe excelled all the
other women, bearing a face worthy an honeſt woman and well borne, I get me
to the wayting maides and aſke what ſhée might bee: They tell
mée that ſhée is ſiſter vnto <hi>Chryſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1+ letters">
                           <desc>•…</desc>
                        </gap>
                     </hi> That went by and by, to the very
hart of mee. Out alas, this is it I wiſt not of: hence grew thoſe tears of
his: here is ſhée whom hée pittied ſo.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>So.</speaker>
                  <p>O how greatly I feare whereto your tale tends.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Si.</speaker>
                  <p>Well, on goeth the coars ſtill: wée follow after: we
are come to the place of buriall: it is put into the fire: They wéepe.
In the meane ſpace, this ſiſter whom I told you of, ruſht headlong to
the flame with no ſmall ieopardy: wherat my ſonne <hi>Pamphilus</hi> being
ſore frigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted, did than lo, bewray his loue which hée had cun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ningly
cloked and kept ſecrete all this while: hee runnes vnto her, and takes her
about the middle: My ſwéete hart <hi>Glycerie</hi> (quoth hee) what do
you? why goe you about to caſt away your ſelfe? with that, ſhée
caſte her ſelfe weeping, and leaning vpon him ſo familiarly, as a man
might eaſily perceiue their old accuſtomed loue.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>So.</speaker>
                  <p>What, ſay you ſo?</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Si.</speaker>
                  <p>I returne thence angry and diſquieted in minde, &amp; yet
had I not cauſe ſufficie<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t to chide him: for he mought haue ſayd: father
what haue I done? What puniſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment haue I deſerued? or wherein haue I
offended? The mayd which wilfully would haue throwen her ſelfe into the fire,
I ſtaied and ſaued her lyfe: This were an honeſt excuſe.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <pb facs="tcp:11757:15"/>
                  <speaker>So.</speaker>
                  <p>It is well conſidered of you: for if you would chide him
which helped to ſaue ones life, what would you doo to him that wrought ones
harme or miſchiefe?</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Si.</speaker>
                  <p>The next day following, <hi>Chremes</hi> came to me exclaming
what a ſhamefull Act it was, that <hi>Pam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>philus</hi> (as he had found out
for certenty) vſed this ſtra<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ge noughtie pack euen as his wife: I
ſtraight way de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nyed that there was any ſuch matter, he earneſtly
af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firmes that it was ſo: well, in the end I parted from him, as one then
vtterly refuſing to match his Daugh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter to my ſonne.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>So.</speaker>
                  <p>Did you not then rebuke your Sonne for it?</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Si.</speaker>
                  <p>No, nor this was not cauſe great inough to rebuke him.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>So.</speaker>
                  <p>How ſo I pray you?</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Si.</speaker>
                  <p>Hée inought haue aunſwered thus: Father you your
ſelfe haue ſet a time when theſe things ſhall ceaſe: ywis it is not
long hence that I muſt liue after an others pleaſure: ſuffer me than, now
in the meane while to liue as I lyſt my ſelfe.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>So.</speaker>
                  <p>What occaſion then is left to rebuke him?</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Si.</speaker>
                  <p>Mary, if for cauſe of this loue hée ſhall refuſe
to take a wife, Than lo, for that offence will I firſt cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rect him to begin
with all. And now my indeuour is this, that by meanes of this fained marriage,
I may haue vnfayned cauſe to rebuke him, if he doo not agrée to it:
And with all that the naughtie knaue <hi>Dauus,</hi> if he haue any ſuttle
deuice, may ſpende it now, while his craft can doo no harme: whom I verely
beleeue wil labour with tooth and nayl, to the vttermoſt that in him lyeth,
and ſo much the rather that he may worke mee a diſpleaſure, than for any
care hee hath to followe my ſonnes fancy.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>So.</speaker>
                  <p>Why ſo?</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Si.</speaker>
                  <p>Aſke you why ſo? <hi>An ill minde, an ill meaning:</hi>
whom if I ſhall perciue, But what néede I vſe many <pb facs="tcp:11757:15"/>
words, and if ſo be it, all doe fall out as I would, that ther be no let or
delay in my ſonne <hi>Pamphilus:</hi> Than reſteth that I entreate
<hi>Chremes</hi> for his Daughter, and that I hope to bring to paſſe well
inough. Now is it thy parte to ſet on a good face in faining this ſame
mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riage: to make <hi>Dauus</hi> thorowly afrayed, and to be a watch ouer my
ſonne, eſpying what he doth, and where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of <hi>Dauus</hi> and he do
conſult together.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>So.</speaker>
                  <p>You haue ſaid inough. I will ſée to it: wée
may now goe in.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Si.</speaker>
                  <p>Goe thou firſt, I will come anon.</p>
               </sp>
            </div>
            <div n="2" type="scene">
               <head>¶Act. 1. Scen. 2.</head>
               <argument>
                  <head>The Argument.</head>
                  <p>The father hauing found out that his Sonne is in loue,
pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tendeth a marriage for him, he threatneth Dauus with puniſhment if he
ſhall go about any deceyt to hinder the marriage.</p>
               </argument>
               <stage> 
                  <list>
                     <item>
                        <hi>Simo,</hi> the olde man.</item>
                     <item> 
                        <hi>Dauus,</hi> the ſeruant.</item>
                  </list>
               </stage>
               <sp>
                  <p>
                     <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>Here is no doubt of this, but that my Sonne will refuſe to
haue a wife: I no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted ſuch feare er while in <hi>Dauus,</hi> as ſoone as he
hard that there was a mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riage towards: but lo where he comes forth
himſelfe.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Dauus.</speaker>
                  <p>I meruailed if this matter ſhould paſſe away ſo, and
ſtill I feared whereto my Maſters long gen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tlenes <pb facs="tcp:11757:16"/> would grow
at length: who after he heard that ſhée whom hee thought of, ſhould
not bée geuen in marriage to his ſon, did, (notwithſtanding) neuer
ſpeake woorde to an<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> of vs, nor
yet was any thing mooued at it.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Si.</speaker>
                  <p>
                     <note place="margin"> 
                        <stage>Simo ſpeaketh this out of the hearing of
Dauus.</stage>
                     </note>But now hee will, and that, as I wéene to thy
coſt.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Da.</speaker>
                  <p>His purpoſe was to haue vs brought vnder hande into fooles
paradiſe, to the end that now hoping the beſt, and hauing caſt of all
feare, wée ſhould ſuddeinly bee taken napping, in ſuch ſorte, as
wée might not haue time to bethinke vs how to preuent the marryage. A
ſuttle foxe I warrant him.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Si.</speaker>
                  <p>What prates this Gallowelapper?</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Da.</speaker>
                  <p>Good Lord my maiſter is here, and I ſaw him not till
now.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Si.</speaker>
                  <p>Dauus?</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Da.</speaker>
                  <p>Now, what is the matter?</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Si</speaker>
                  <p>Come your way hether to mée.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Da.</speaker>
                  <p>What a Deuill will hée haue?</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Si.</speaker>
                  <p>What is that thou talkeſt of?</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Da.</speaker>
                  <p>Whereof ſhould I talke?</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Si.</speaker>
                  <p>Aſkeſt thow whereof? Sirra, the report is that my ſonne
is in loue.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Da.</speaker>
                  <p>Yea no doubt the world cares much for that.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Si.</speaker>
                  <p>Nay, but doſt thou minde what I ſpeake to thee or not?</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Da.</speaker>
                  <p>Yes truly I mynde it well inough.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Si.</speaker>
                  <p>Wel, for mée now to go ſerch and fift out that
mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, were but the part of a harde father: for what he did heretofore,
pertaynes nothing at all to mee: ſo long as he tooke time conuenient for it,
I ſuffered him to fulfill his deſire. Now it is high time for him to leade
an other life, and chaunge his manners. And therefore I require, or if it be
reaſon I deſyre thée <hi>Dauos,</hi> that now at length he do
returne into the right way.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <pb facs="tcp:11757:16"/>
                  <speaker>Da.</speaker>
                  <p>What meane you by this?</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Si.</speaker>
                  <p>All men that bée in loue, can ill away to haue wiues
appoynted them by others.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Da.</speaker>
                  <p>So they ſay.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Si.</speaker>
                  <p>Then if one take a knaue for his ſcholmaiſter in that
behalfe, The loue ſicke mynde of the ſcholler is by him commonly applied to
all naughtines.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Da.</speaker>
                  <p>Truely I vnderſtand you not.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Si.</speaker>
                  <p>No, doſt thou not?</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Da.</speaker>
                  <p>No, I am plaine <hi>Dauus,</hi> and not <hi>Oedipus</hi> [the
rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der of Riddels.]</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Si.</speaker>
                  <p>Wilt thou then that I ſpeake the reſt of my minde
plainly.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Da.</speaker>
                  <p>Yea a Gods name.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Si.</speaker>
                  <p>If I ſhall perceiue that thou go about to worke a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny deceyte
this day, to the ende to breake of this mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riage, or that thou wilt therein
ſhew how ſlie and craf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty a companion thou art: I will kudgill thee well
and thriftely, and then caſt thee into the grinding houſe to grinde till
thou die: with this couenant and condicion, that if I take thée out
thence, then I my ſelfe to grinde in thy place. What, haſt thou
vnderſtoode me now? or doſt thou not yet vnderſtande this neither?</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Da.</speaker>
                  <p>Yes full well, you went now very plainly to the matter, and
nothing about the buſh.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Si.</speaker>
                  <p>I could rather beare any abuſe at thy hands, than bée
deluded in this matter.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Da.</speaker>
                  <p>Yet good woordes I pray you ſir.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Si.</speaker>
                  <p>What, doſt thou laugh mee to ſcorne? I ſée I am
not a whit deceiued in thée: But I tell thée this, that thou be
not ouer raſh, and that thou maiſt not hereafter ſay but thou hadſt a
faire warning.</p>
               </sp>
            </div>
            <div n="3" type="scene">
               <pb facs="tcp:11757:17"/>
               <head>¶Act. 1. Scen. 3.</head>
               <argument>
                  <head>The Argument.</head>
                  <p>In this ſcene Dauus deliberateth whether it be beſt for
him to ayde Pamphilus, or to obey the olde man.</p>
               </argument>
               <stage> 
                  <list>
                     <item>
                        <hi>Dauus</hi> alone.</item>
                  </list>
               </stage>
               <sp>
                  <p>
                     <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg>N good earneſt <hi>Dauus</hi> it is no time now to be flow
and fluggiſh, ſo far as I per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiued of late by the old mans ſpeech
tou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ching the marriage: which if it bee not cunningly prouided for and
preuented, will caſt either me or my maiſter cleane vnder foote: And yet I
wot not in the world what to doo: whether I ſhall helpe <hi>Pamphilus,</hi>
or els liſten af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter the old man. Yf I leaue him helples, I feare me yt will
coſt him his life: Contrariwiſe, if I ayd and fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther him, than ſtand I
in feare of the old mans threat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning, whom yt is a hard matter to beguyle: for
firſt and formoſt, he knoweth certeynlie of this ſame loue, and beyng at
deadly fewd with me, he watcheth leaſt I go about ſome guile to hinder the
marriage: yf hée ſhall ſée any ſuch matter by mée, I
am vtterly vndon: or if the Toy take him in the head, hée will finde
ſome cauſe or other, and ſo bée it right or wrong, he will tum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble
me headlong into the grinding hous: Now ouer and beſides theſe
miſcheeues, this comes alſo in the very
<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>icke: This ſame woman an of
<hi>Andros</hi> whether ſhe be wife to <hi>Pamphilus,</hi> or but his loue, I
knowe not, but great with childe ſhe is by him: And it is a world to heare
their preſumption: They fare as they were lunaticke, and not loue ſicke,
for be it boy or gyrle that ſhe ſhal be deliuered of, they are determined
to bring it <pb facs="tcp:11757:17"/> 
                     <note n="*" place="margin">It was not Lawful in A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thens to bring
vp the children begotten out of wedlocke vpon ſtrange wome<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, but rather to
doo them a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>way.</note>vp. And now they faine betwixt themſelues an od
péece of craft, that this <hi>Glycerie</hi> is a free borne woman of
A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thens: Ther was a good while ſince (ſay they) a certaine old Marchant
which ſuffred ſhipwracke at the Ile of <hi>Andros,</hi> who afterward died
there: and that ſhée being then a ſmall ſuccourles childe caſt
on the ſhore, ſhould (forſooth) bée foſtred by
<hi>Chryſis</hi> father: A trim fable. In good faith me thinks it ſoundes
nothing like troth, and yet this fayned deuiſe pleaſeth them well. But lo
where <hi>Myſis</hi> comes furth from her. Now wil I go get me hence to the
market place to méete with <hi>Pamphilus,</hi> leaſt his father come
vpon him vnawares with this ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riage matter.</p>
               </sp>
            </div>
            <div n="4" type="scene">
               <head>¶Act. 1. Scen. 4.</head>
               <argument>
                  <head>The Argument.</head>
                  <p>MYSIS declareth the cauſe of her comming furth from
Glyce<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie: And here Terence g<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ues a
leſſon, That ſuch eſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cially as haue charge of waighty buſines,
ought to eſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chew immoderate drinking of wine, concluding that a drunkard can
do nothing rightly.</p>
               </argument>
               <stage> 
                  <list>
                     <item>
                        <hi>Myſys,</hi> the mayde.</item>
                  </list>
               </stage>
               <sp>
                  <p>
                     <hi>
                        <seg rend="decorInit">A</seg>Rchillis,</hi> I heard you a prety while ſince, bid
that <hi>Lesbia</hi> ſhould be brought hither: In very truth ſhe is a
drunken harebraynd woman, and far vnfit to take charge of a woman in trauaile
of her firſt child: yet neuertheleſſe I will bring her: See how erneſt
the olde Trot is, to haue her here, and all becauſe ſhe is a drinking
Goſſip of hers. God graunt my Miſtres ſafe and ſpéedy
deliuerance, and that any other miſcarry vnder the handes of the Tip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſie 
<pb facs="tcp:11757:18"/> Midwiefe, rather than ſhée: But what is the matter that
I ſée <hi>Pamphilus</hi> ſo much out of quiet, I feare me all is not
well: I will ſtay, and know whither this his trooble of minde, bring not
ſome hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uy newes.</p>
               </sp>
            </div>
            <div n="5" type="scene">
               <head>¶Act. 1. Scen. 5.</head>
               <argument>
                  <head>The Argument.</head>
                  <p>This ſcene conteynes the griefe of Pamphilus as touching the
marriages where likewiſe he promiſeth to keepe faith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful touch with
Glycerie, yea, whether his father will or no, if cauſe ſo require.</p>
               </argument>
               <stage> 
                  <list>
                     <item>
                        <hi>Pamphilus,</hi> the young man.</item>
                     <item> 
                        <hi>Myſis</hi> the, Mayde.</item>
                  </list>
               </stage>
               <sp>
                  <p>
                     <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg>S this a point of good nature, or a kinde<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ly déede?
Is this the part of a Father?</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>My.</speaker>
                  <p>
                     <note n="*" place="margin"> 
                        <stage>Myſis ſpeakes this to her ſelf, out of the
hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring of Pam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>philus.</stage>
                     </note>What might that be?</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Pamph.</speaker>
                  <p>O the faith of God and man, what can be greater ſpite than
this? he had purpoſed with himſelfe to marry me to a wife to day: ought not
I haue knowen ſo much before hand? had it not bin méete to haue made
me pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uie to it long ere this?</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>My.</speaker>
                  <p>
                     <note n="*" place="margin"> 
                        <stage>This alſo is ſpoken by Myſis, out of the
hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring of Pam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>philus.</stage>
                     </note>Wo is me (ſilly wench that I am,) what
newes doo I heare?</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Pamph.</speaker>
                  <p>What meanes <hi>Chremes,</hi> who hauing once denyed to giue
me his daughter to wife, doth he now change his minde in that, becauſe he
ſéeth me ſtill one manner of man? Dooth he deale ſo ouerthwartly,
to thend to part me from <hi>Glycerie,</hi> forlorne man that I am? which, if
it come to paſſe, I am cleane caſt away. Alas, alas, is there any man
lyuing ſo reſt of all grace <pb facs="tcp:11757:18"/> and good fortune as my ſelfe? O
Lord God, ſhall I by no meanes be able to auoyd the Aliance of
<hi>Chremes?</hi> How many waies am I deſpiſed and ſet at naught? All
things were done and paſt, and ſo, I that was re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fuſed am ſought for
againe, and wherefore, without it be as I ſuſpect, they cloake ſome
ſecret fault in her, and becauſe ſhe cannot be ſhifted to any other,
they would thruſt her on me.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>My.</speaker>
                  <p>
                     <note place="margin"> 
                        <stage>This likewiſe ſhe ſpeakes to her
ſelfe.</stage>
                     </note>Theſe wordes do aſtony me for feare, (ſillie wench
that I am)</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Pamph.</speaker>
                  <p>But what ſhould I now ſay of my father? is it fit he go
ſo careleſlie to woork about ſo great a matter? who paſſing by me
crewhile at the market place, ſpake to me in this ſorte:
<hi>Pamphilus;</hi> thou muſt be married to day: Get the home and make
thée ready. It ſéemed to me he ſaid, Get thee away quicklie
and hang thy ſelfe. I was vtterlie amazed: Think ye that I could bring furth
one woord, or make any excuſe for my ſelfe, were it wrong, fals, or neuer
ſo fooliſh? I became quite dumbe. But had I wiſt ſo much before, if one
ſhould now aſke me, what would I then haue don, ſurely ſom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>what I would
haue don, rather than doo as I dyd. But now whereto ſhall I firſt betake
me? I am cumbred with ſo many cares, which diuerſlie hale my minde to &amp;
fro, what with loue &amp; pitie toward this woman, The griefe I conceiue of
this marriage, and the ſhame I incurre with my father, who hitherto ſo
gently ſuffred me to do what I would, (and ſhall I now gaineſay him?)
That wo is me, I wot not what to do.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>My.</speaker>
                  <p>
                     <note place="margin"> 
                        <stage>This ſpeech of Myſis is ouer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>heard by
Pam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>philus.</stage>
                     </note>I feare me wretch whereto this doubtfull pang will
breake in the end, ſo as now it is very needfull that either he come and
ſpeake with my Miſtres himſelfe, or els that I ſay ſomewhat to him as
touching her. For while his minde hangs thus in doubt, it is carryed
héere, and there, with the leaſt thing in the world.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Pamph.</speaker>
                  <p>Who talkes héere? O <hi>Myſis,</hi> welcome.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <pb facs="tcp:11757:19"/>
                  <speaker>My.</speaker>
                  <p>God ſaue you maiſter <hi>Pamphilus.</hi>
                  </p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Pamph.</speaker>
                  <p>How dooth thy miſtres?</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>My.</speaker>
                  <p>Doo you not know? ſhe is in labour with childe: And for this
the ſilly woman takes care and thought, bycauſe heretofore your mariage was
appointed to bée made as this day: Moreouer ſhe is in great feare
leaſt you will forſake her.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Pamph.</speaker>
                  <p>O Lord, ſhould I finde in my hart to do ſo? Alas poore
ſowle, ſhould I ſuffer her to bée deceiued thorough me, which
committed her whole truſt vnto me, and euen put her life in my hands? Shall I
deale ſo by her (whom I haue intirely loued as my wife) that through
néed and neceſſity her chaſt behauiour and wel ordered life
ſhould be corrupted and changed? No, I wil neuer doo it.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>My.</speaker>
                  <p>I would not feare at all, if it lay onely in you, but I feare
how you will be able to hide the brunt of your father.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Pamph.</speaker>
                  <p>What, doſt thou thinke me ſo faint harted, or moreouer,
ſo vnkinde, or vncurteous, or ſo cruell, as that neither our daily
familiarity, nor loue, nor yet ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry ſhame, can mooue me nor put mée
in minde to kéepe promiſe with her?</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>My.</speaker>
                  <p>This one thing I wot well: ſhée hath deſerued that
you ſhould be mindefull of her.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Pamph.</speaker>
                  <p>That I ſhould be mindfull of her? O <hi>Myſis
Myſis,</hi> thoſe woordes of <hi>Chryſis</hi> remaine yet printed in my
minde, which ſhe ſpake vnto mée, as touching <hi>Gly<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerie:</hi>
Being néere the point of Death, ſhee calles mée to her: I came,
and after you were gone aſide and no body left but wée twoo: thus
ſhée began: Frend <hi>Pam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>philus,</hi> you ſée of what beauty
and yéeres this ſame mayden is: neither are you to bée tolde,
what incon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uenience theſe twoo thinges are vnto her, both for ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing her
honeſty and her ſtocke: And therefore I pray you by this right hand of
yours, and your honeſty: <pb facs="tcp:11757:19"/> I beſéech you alſo on your
faith and troth, and in reſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pect of the ſolitary ſtate of this maiden,
that you will neither part her from you, nor forſake her: euen as I haue
loued you as myne owne brother, and as ſhée al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>waies eſtéemed
you alone aboue all men liuing, and was in all things ready at your
commaundement. I bequeath you to her, as huſband, frend, tutor, and fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther.
Theſe our goods I commit vnto you, and charge you with them of truſt.
Herevpon ſhée deliuered <hi>Glyce<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie</hi> vnto mee in way of
marriage, and by and by gaue vp the Ghoſt: I receiued <hi>Glycerie</hi> of
her, and hauing once receiued her, I will kepe her ſtill.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>My.</speaker>
                  <p>Truly I hope no leſſe.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Pamph.</speaker>
                  <p>But why art thou come from her?</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>My.</speaker>
                  <p>I go for the midwife.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Pamph.</speaker>
                  <p>Hye thée apace: and hearſt thou mée? beware
thou ſpeake not one woorde of the marriage, leaſt that alſo increaſe
her griefe.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>My.</speaker>
                  <p>O, I vnderſtand you.</p>
               </sp>
            </div>
         </div>
         <div n="2" type="act">
            <div n="1" type="scene">
               <head>¶Act 2. Scen. 1.</head>
               <argument>
                  <head>The Argument.</head>
                  <p>CARINVS vnderſtanding that Philumena ſhall be maried to
Pamphilus: entreateth Pamphilus that he doo not marry her. Here Carinus and
Byrria are purpoſely brought in, leaſt that Philumena ſhould not bee
e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſteemed of at all.</p>
               </argument>
               <stage>
                  <pb facs="tcp:11757:20"/> 
                  <list>
                     <item>
                        <hi>Carinus,</hi> a yong man.</item>
                     <item>
                        <hi>Byrria,</hi> the ſeruant.</item>
                     <item>
                        <hi>Pamphilus.</hi>
                     </item>
                  </list>
               </stage>
               <sp>
                  <p>
                     <hi>
                        <seg rend="decorInit">B</seg>Yrria,</hi> what ſayeſt thou? ſhall ſhée
bée married this day to <hi>Pamphilus?</hi>
                  </p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Byr.</speaker>
                  <p>Yea, euen ſo.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Ca.</speaker>
                  <p>How knoweſt thou?</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Byr.</speaker>
                  <p>I heard it of <hi>Dauus</hi> but a little while ſince, at
the market place.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Car.</speaker>
                  <p>Wo is mée vnhappy man, for as my minde was held
betwéene hope and feare euer till now: ſo now that all hope is paſt,
euen worne and wearied with care, it is vtterly diſmayed.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Byr.</speaker>
                  <p>I pray you Sir for Gods ſake, ſith you cannot haue what
you would, that you will haue what you may.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Car.</speaker>
                  <p>There is nothing that I will haue but <hi>Philu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mena.</hi>
                  </p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Byr.</speaker>
                  <p>Alas how much better were it for you, to ſéeke to
weare this loue out of your mynde, than to vtter furth ſuch
ſpéeches, whereby your deſire is kindled more and more in vayne.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Car.</speaker>
                  <p>Wée can all lightly when wee are in health, geue good
counſayle to ſuch as are ſicke: But if thou wert in my caſe, thou
wouldſt ſing mée a new ſong.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Byr.</speaker>
                  <p>Wel, go too then, doo as you liſt.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Car.</speaker>
                  <p>But to where I ſée <hi>Pamphilus,</hi> I am
de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>termined to prooue all manner of wayes before I dye.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Byr.</speaker>
                  <p>What will he now doo?</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Car.</speaker>
                  <p>This ſame man will I intreate, him wil I ear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſtly
beſéech, to him will I diſcouer my loue: I be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>léeue 
<pb facs="tcp:11757:20"/> I ſhall get him to put of the marriage, at leaſt, for a few
dayes longer: and in the meane ſpace I hope ſomewhat may be done.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Byr.</speaker>
                  <p>That ſomewhat, will prooue iuſt nothing.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Car.</speaker>
                  <p>But how thinkeſt thou <hi>Byrria,</hi> were I beſt go to
him or not?</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Byr.</speaker>
                  <p>Yes, what els? though you obteyne nothing at his handes, that
yet hée may thinke you ready to make him cuckold, if hée do marry
her.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Car.</speaker>
                  <p>Go get thée hence knaue, with a miſchiefe to
thée for thy peeuiſh ſuſpicion.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Pamph.</speaker>
                  <p>I ſee <hi>Carinus:</hi> God ſpéede ſir.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Car,</speaker>
                  <p>O <hi>Pamphilus,</hi> God ſaue you: I come to you
re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>queſting at your handes, hope, health, helpe, and coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſaile.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Pamph.</speaker>
                  <p>In good faith I am neither a méete man to geue
counſaile, nor yet haue wherewith to helpe an o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther: but what is your
matter?</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Car.</speaker>
                  <p>Do you marry to day?</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Pamph.</speaker>
                  <p>So the talke goeth.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Car.</speaker>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Pamphilus</hi> if you do ſo, then ſhall you neuer
ſée mée aliue after this day.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Pamph.</speaker>
                  <p>Why, how ſo?</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Car.</speaker>
                  <p>Alas I feare to vtter it: I pray thée <hi>Byrria</hi>
doe thou tell it him.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Byr.</speaker>
                  <p>I will.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Pamph.</speaker>
                  <p>What is it?</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Byr.</speaker>
                  <p>He is in loue with your Bride.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Pamph.</speaker>
                  <p>Now in good fayth hée is not of my minde: but come
néere and tel mee <hi>Carinus,</hi> hath there bene any further matter
betwéene you and her?</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Car.</speaker>
                  <p>O, Alas <hi>Pamphilus,</hi> no.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Pamph.</speaker>
                  <p>Mary ſir I would there had.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Car.</speaker>
                  <p>Now I hartely beſéech you, euen for the loue and
frendſhip betwixt you and mée: firſt and formoſt, that you do not
marry her at all.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <pb facs="tcp:11757:21"/>
                  <speaker>Pamph.</speaker>
                  <p>Truely I will do my beſt indeuor.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Car.</speaker>
                  <p>But if you may not otherwiſe chooſe, or that this marriage
be according to your owne hart:</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Pamph.</speaker>
                  <p>According to my hart?</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Car</speaker>
                  <p>Yet at leaſt wiſe, prolong it for a day or twoo, while I
get mée away ſomewhither, that I may not behold it.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Pamph.</speaker>
                  <p>Nay but liſten to mée now <hi>Carinus,</hi> I hold it
in no wiſe the part of an honeſt man, to pike a thanke where none is due
vnto him: God wot I am more deſirous to be rid of this mariage, than you are
to obtayne it.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Car.</speaker>
                  <p>You haue reuiued my ſpirites.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Pamph.</speaker>
                  <p>Now if either your ſelfe, or <hi>Byrria</hi> here, can do
ought in the matter, be doing, faine, finde out and pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cure the meanes that
you may haue her: I for my part will ſo handle the matter, as ſhée
may not bée marri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed to mée.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Car.</speaker>
                  <p>I haue my deſire.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Pamph.</speaker>
                  <p>Oh, in very good tyme do I ſée <hi>Dauus,</hi>
whoſe aduiſe I vſe altogether.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Car.</speaker>
                  <p>
                     <note place="margin"> 
                        <stage>He ſpeaketh to his ſeruant
Byrria.</stage>
                     </note>But in good ſooth thou wilt tell mée nothing,
ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cept ſuch things as are not woorth the knowing: doſt thou not get
thée hence.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Byr.</speaker>
                  <p>Yes truely, and that with a very good wil.</p>
               </sp>
            </div>
            <div n="2" type="scene">
               <head>¶Act. 2. Scen. 2.</head>
               <argument>
                  <head>The Argument.</head>
                  <p>DAVVS hauing gathered by ſundry ſignes and coniectures the
vnlikelihood of the mariage, ſeeketh all the towne ouer for Pamphilus, &amp;
reioiceth out of meaſure.</p>
               </argument>
               <stage>
                  <pb facs="tcp:11757:21"/> 
                  <list>
                     <item>
                        <hi>Dauus.</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>
                        <hi>Charinus.</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>
                        <hi>Pamphilus.</hi>
                     </item>
                  </list>
               </stage>
               <sp>
                  <p>
                     <seg rend="decorInit">O</seg> Good God, what good newes doo I bring with me, But where
ſhall I now finde <hi>Pamphilus,</hi> that I may releaſe him from that
feare he is in, and fill his hart with ioy.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Car.</speaker>
                  <p>
                     <note n="*" place="margin"> 
                        <stage>This talke of Carinus and Pamphilus muſt bee
ſuppo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed to be be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>twixt them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelues, Dauus neither hearing nor ſeeing
the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, and therefore he goeth on ſtil with his ſpeche</stage>
                     </note>He is
very méery, what the mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter is I know not.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Pamph.</speaker>
                  <p>It is nothing to any purpos, he hath not yet vnderſtood of
this miſchiefe.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Da:</speaker>
                  <p>Whome I verily beléeue, if he haue yet hard of the
marriage prepared for him.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Car.</speaker>
                  <p>
                     <note n="*" place="margin"> 
                        <stage>He ſpeaketh ſtill to Pam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>philus.</stage>
                     </note>Doo
you not heare what he ſaith?</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Da:</speaker>
                  <p>That he is beſide himſelfe, ſéeking for me all
the Towne ouer. But where ſhall I ſeke for him, or whi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther ſhall I now
firſt go?</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Car.</speaker>
                  <p>
                     <note n="*" place="margin"> 
                        <stage>And this alſo he ſpeaketh to
Pamphilus.</stage>
                     </note>What, doo you linger to ſpeake to him?</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Da:</speaker>
                  <p>Well, I go my waies.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Pamph.</speaker>
                  <p>Dauus, come hither, ſtay.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Da.</speaker>
                  <p>Who calles me? O my Maſter <hi>Pamphilus,</hi> you are the
man I looke for. Well met <hi>Carinus:</hi> I finde you both in good time, euen
you two I would ſpeaks with all.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Pamph.</speaker>
                  <p>Dauus, I am a forlorn man.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Da:</speaker>
                  <p>But yet liſten to me a little.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Pamph.</speaker>
                  <p>I am caſt away.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Da:</speaker>
                  <p>I wot what you feare.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Car.</speaker>
                  <p>Truely and my liefe is in hazard in very déede.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Da:</speaker>
                  <p>I wot alſo what you feare.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Pamph.</speaker>
                  <p>I muſt be married.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Da:</speaker>
                  <p>And that I know too.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Pamph.</speaker>
                  <p>Yea but too day.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <pb facs="tcp:11757:22"/>
                  <speaker>Da.</speaker>
                  <p>You dull me with too many wordes, and yet I know the matter
already. You feare leaſt you muſt marry <hi>Philumena:</hi> And you
<hi>(Carinus)</hi> take care how you may marry her.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Car.</speaker>
                  <p>Thou haſt hit the nayle on the head.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Pamph.</speaker>
                  <p>That ſame is it.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Da.</speaker>
                  <p>And in that, is there no daunger at all: I war<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rant you.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Pamph.</speaker>
                  <p>I pray thée for Gods ſake, ryd me preſently out of
this feare, poore wretch that I am.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Da:</speaker>
                  <p>Lo, I put you out of feare, <hi>Chremes</hi> will not at this
time giue you his daughter to wife.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Pamph.</speaker>
                  <p>How knoweſt thou ſomuch?</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Da:</speaker>
                  <p>I know it full well: your father met me ere<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>while and told me
that he would marry you this day to a wiefe, beſides many things elſe,
which now is no time to rehers. By and by I haſted me and ran eue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry foote to
the market place, to tel you of this: and when I could not finde you there, I
got me vp, on a high ſtanding, and looked round about me, you were no where
to be ſéene. By chaunce I ſpied <hi>Byrria</hi> this mans ſeruant,
I aſke him for you, he ſayd he ſawe you not. This troubled me: Then I
bethink me what to doo: and as I was returning thence, I fell to miſtruſt
whether there were any marriage towards or no, I remembred there was verie
ſmall prouiſion of meate: he himſelfe was very ſad: The marriage was to
be made on the ſoddeyn, This did not hang well to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Pamph.</speaker>
                  <p>What of all this?</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Da:</speaker>
                  <p>I preſently got me to <hi>Chremes</hi> houſe, and be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing
come thither, there was no body ſturring about the doore, I was glad of
that.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Car.</speaker>
                  <p>You ſay well.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Pamph.</speaker>
                  <p>Tell on.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Da:</speaker>
                  <p>I ſtay there a while, and could ſée no body either 
<pb facs="tcp:11757:22"/> going in, or comming out, I went my waies in, and looked
narrowly, there was neuer an elderly woman, no tryming vp of the houſe, no
ſtur or preparacion.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Pamph.</speaker>
                  <p>I graunt you, it is great likelihood.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Da:</speaker>
                  <p>Nay but doo theſe thinges ſéeme to agrée
with a marriage matter?</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Pamph.</speaker>
                  <p>No <hi>Dauus,</hi> as I gheſſe.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Da:</speaker>
                  <p>Gheſſe ſay you? you take your marke amis: The matter is
out of al doubt: Moreouer, as I was comming thence, I met with <hi>Chremes</hi>
boy, carrying potherbs and a halpwoorth of ſmall fiſh for the old mans
ſupper.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Car.</speaker>
                  <p>Dauus, I am ryd out of danger this day by thy meanes.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Da:</speaker>
                  <p>Truely but you are neuer the néerer.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Car:</speaker>
                  <p>How can that be? for ſurely <hi>Chremes</hi> will not giue
his daughter in marriage to him.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Da:</speaker>
                  <p>O wiſe woodcok, as though it muſt néedes folow, if
he giue not his Daughter to him, that therefore you ſhall marry her: vnles
you ſée better vnto it, and vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſſe you make ſute to the olde
mans fréends, you do but throw your cap in the winde.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Car.</speaker>
                  <p>You aduiſe me well, I will go thither, al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>though in good
faith, this hope hath deceyued me alre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy more than once or twiſe.
Farewell.</p>
               </sp>
            </div>
            <div n="3" type="scene">
               <pb facs="tcp:11757:23"/>
               <head>¶Act. 2. Scen. 3.</head>
               <argument>
                  <head>The Argument.</head>
                  <p>DAVVS earneſtly prayeth and perſwadeth Phamphilus, to
ſay vnto his father that he will marry.</p>
               </argument>
               <stage> 
                  <list>
                     <item>
                        <hi>Phamphilus.</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item> 
                        <hi>Dauus.</hi>
                     </item>
                  </list>
               </stage>
               <sp>
                  <p>
                     <seg rend="decorInit">W</seg>Hat meanes my father then? why doth he diſſemble with
vs?</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Da:</speaker>
                  <p>Mary I ſhal tel you, if ſo be it he be now in a chafe
bycauſe <hi>Chremes</hi> will not marry his daughter vnto you: Then lo, may
he thinke with himſelfe that he doth you wrong: But yet he will thinke it no
wrong at all, before ſuch time as he ſhall perceyue how your minde is
ſetled towards marriage. But if you ſhall refuſe to marry, then will he
lay all the fault vpon you, and then will be old ſturre and hurleburly.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Pamph.</speaker>
                  <p>What wouldſt thou haue me to doo? that I ſhould
yéeld to marry?</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Da:</speaker>
                  <p>O maſter conſider, he is your father, it is hard to
withſtand him: Moreouer this <hi>Glycerie</hi> is a loue woman, he will
quickly picke a quarell againſt her, and ſo turn her packing out of
town:</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Pamph.</speaker>
                  <p>May he turn her away?</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Da.</speaker>
                  <p>Yes, out of hand.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Pamph.</speaker>
                  <p>Then I pray thée <hi>Dauus</hi> what ſhall I doo?</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Da.</speaker>
                  <p>Say to your father that you will marry.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Pamph.</speaker>
                  <p>Alas.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Da.</speaker>
                  <p>Why, what is the matter?</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Pamph.</speaker>
                  <p>Should I ſay ſo?</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Da.</speaker>
                  <p>Why not?</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <pb facs="tcp:11757:23"/>
                  <speaker>Pamph.</speaker>
                  <p>I will neuer doe it.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Da:</speaker>
                  <p>Neuer deny it.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Pamph.</speaker>
                  <p>Neuer doo thou perſwade me to it.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Da:</speaker>
                  <p>Do but conſider what will follow of this.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Pamph.</speaker>
                  <p>This will follow, that I ſhall be ſhut from Glycerie, and
tyed vp to this woman.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Da:</speaker>
                  <p>Not ſo: Mary I wene your father will ſay thus much to you:
I will haue you to marry a wyfe to day. You ſhall ſay, I will: And then I
pray you what cauſe ſhall he haue to chide you? By this meanes you ſhall
make all his deuiſes which now are of force, to be then altogether friuolous:
and that without any danger to your ſelfe: for this is without all
queſtion, that <hi>Chre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mes</hi> will not marry his daughter vnto you: And
for more ſurety, you ſhall not ceaſe to vſe <hi>Glyceries</hi> compa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny
ſtill as you haue done, leaſt haply he ſhould alter his minde. Tell your
father that you are willing to marry, ſo as when he would be angrie with you,
he may haue no cauſe: for as for that vaine hope of yours (imagining thus
with your ſelfe: Tuſh, it is no da<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ger for me to withſtand my father, No
man will marry his daughter vnto a man of my manners) I ſhall eaſilie put
you out of that hope: he will finde out a poore and meane marriage for you,
rather than he will ſuffer you to be ſpilt by harlots. But if he ſhall
perceiue that you are well content with this marriage, you ſhall make him
reckles of the matter, he will ſeeke an other wife for you at leyſure, and
in the meane ſpace ſome good fortune will fall.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Pamph.</speaker>
                  <p>Doſt thou think ſo?</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Da:</speaker>
                  <p>Nay ſurely there is no doubt of that.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Pamph.</speaker>
                  <p>Yea, but take héede whereto thou perſwadeſt me.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Da:</speaker>
                  <p>What, are you not yet reſolued?</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Pamph.</speaker>
                  <p>Well, I will ſay ſo to my father: but we muſt take
héede, that he vnderſtand not of the childe I haue <pb facs="tcp:11757:24"/> by
<hi>Glycerie,</hi> for I haue promiſed to bring it vp.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Da.</speaker>
                  <p>O notable hold déede.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Pamph.</speaker>
                  <p>Shée earneſtly beſought mée to geue her my
fayth and troth on this, that ſo ſhée might bée ſure I
would not forſake her.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Da.</speaker>
                  <p>Well, it ſhall bée cared for. But your father is here
hard by, beware that hée do not finde you ſad.</p>
               </sp>
            </div>
            <div n="4" type="scene">
               <head>¶Act 2. Scen 4.</head>
               <argument>
                  <head>The Argument.</head>
                  <p>In this ſcene bee deuiſes practiſed of both ſides:
Dauus putteth Pamphilus in mynde that hee doe not feare or faint, but that he
be prouided what to ſay to his father.</p>
               </argument>
               <stage> 
                  <list>
                     <item>
                        <hi>Simo.</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>
                        <hi>Dauus.</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>
                        <hi>Pamphilus.</hi>
                     </item>
                  </list>
               </stage>
               <sp>
                  <p>
                     <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg> Come againe to ſée what they are a dooing or
conſulting.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Da.</speaker>
                  <p>
                     <note n="*" place="margin"> 
                        <stage>This he ſaith ſoftly to Pam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>philus: Simo neither
hear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing nor ſeeing them.</stage>
                     </note>Hée makes ſure account that
you will refuſe to marry: he hath ſtudied by himſelfe, and is now come
out of ſome ſolitary corner, hoping he hath de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uiſed talke wherewith
hée may bring you beſide your ſelfe: Therefore ſée that
your wits bée your owne.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Pamph.</speaker>
                  <p>I will doo as well as I may.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Da.</speaker>
                  <p>Maiſter, credite mée in this: I ſay vnto you that
your father will not geue you one euill woord to day, if you doo but ſay that
you will marry.</p>
               </sp>
            </div>
            <div n="5" type="scene">
               <pb facs="tcp:11757:24"/>
               <head>¶Act. 2. Scen. 5.</head>
               <argument>
                  <head>The Argument.</head>
                  <p>BYRRIA watcheth Pamphilus: Pamphilus anſweareth his father
that hee is ready in all things at his commaun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dement. Byrria makes report
thereof to Carmus.</p>
               </argument>
               <stage> 
                  <list>
                     <item>
                        <hi>Byrria.</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>
                        <hi>Simo.</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>
                        <hi>Dauus.</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>
                        <hi>Pamphilus.</hi>
                     </item>
                  </list>
               </stage>
               <sp>
                  <p>
                     <seg rend="decorInit">M</seg>Y maiſter gaue mée commaundement, that ſetting
all buſines aſide, I ſhould watch <hi>Pamphilus</hi> this day, to thend I
might learne what hée did as touching the marriage: and that is the
matter I am now come after him hither: but lo where he is with <hi>Dauus,</hi>
here hard at hand. I will do that, that I come for.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Si.</speaker>
                  <p>
                     <note n="*" place="margin"> 
                        <stage>Simo ſaith this to himſelf, hauing Dauus and
Pamphilus in ſight.</stage>
                     </note>I ſée them both preſent before
my face.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Da.</speaker>
                  <p>
                     <note n="˘" place="margin"> 
                        <stage>Dauus ſpeak<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth this to Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>philus, becauſe Simo
draweth nigh.</stage>
                     </note>Hem, looke to your ſelfe.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Si.</speaker>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Pamphilus.</hi>
                  </p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Da.</speaker>
                  <p>
                     <note n="ʒ" place="margin"> 
                        <stage>All the ſpech of Dauus in this Scene, is onely vnto
Pa<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                           <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>philus, and out of the hearing of Simo.</stage>
                     </note>Turne ſuddenly
toward him as though you were not aware of his comming.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Pamph.</speaker>
                  <p>Oh father.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Da.</speaker>
                  <p>Well handled of you.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Si.</speaker>
                  <p>I will haue thée to bée married to daye, as I
told thée before.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Byr.</speaker>
                  <p>
                     <note n="*" place="margin"> 
                        <stage>Byrria ſaith this to himſelfe out of their
hearing.</stage>
                     </note>Now feare I of our ſide, how this man will
anſweare.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Pamph.</speaker>
                  <p>Neither in this thing, nor in any thing els, ſhall you finde
any let or delay, in me.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Byr.</speaker>
                  <p>
                     <note n="℈" place="margin"> 
                        <stage>All the ſpeech of Byrria in this Scene, is either to
him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe, or to the Audiens: and not to any of the
ſpeakers.</stage>
                     </note>Out alas.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Da.</speaker>
                  <p>He hath neuer a word more to ſay.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Byr.</speaker>
                  <p>What did he anſweare?</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Si.</speaker>
                  <p>Thou doſt as becommeth thée, in that I obteine with
thy good wil, y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> thing which I require at thy hands.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <pb facs="tcp:11757:25"/>
                  <speaker>Da:</speaker>
                  <p>did not I ſay true?</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Byr.</speaker>
                  <p>As far as I héere, my maſter is like to leape
be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſide his wife.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Si.</speaker>
                  <p>Now go thy waies in, that there be no tarrying for thée
when néede is.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Pamph.</speaker>
                  <p>I go.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Byr.</speaker>
                  <p>Is there no truſt to be put in any man, for any thing in the
world? 
<note place="margin">Euery man for himſelfe and God for vs
all.</note>That ſame is a true ſaying which is commonly vſed: <hi>Euery
man wiſheth more good to himſelfe than to an other.</hi> I my ſelfe haue
ſéene that ſame mayden, and I remember ſhe was of a good loue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly
fauour: Therefore I blame not <hi>Pamphilus</hi> ſo much though he had
leauer, lye colling of her himſelfe a nights, than that my Maiſter
ſhould: well, I will go ſhew all to my Maiſter, that for theſe ill
newes he may giue me ill language.</p>
               </sp>
            </div>
            <div n="6" type="scene">
               <head>¶Act. 2. Scen. 6.</head>
               <argument>
                  <head>The Argument.</head>
                  <p>IN this ſcene Dauus and Simo deceyue one an other: which is
woorth the noting.</p>
               </argument>
               <stage> 
                  <list>
                     <item>
                        <hi>Dauus.</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>
                        <hi>Simo.</hi>
                     </item>
                  </list>
               </stage>
               <sp>
                  <p>
                     <note place="margin"> 
                        <stage>This he ſpeak<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth to the
au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diens.</stage>
                     </note>
                     <seg rend="decorInit">N</seg>Ow thinks the old man verilie, that I bring ſome
flye ſhift to beguyle him, and that I ſtaied here therefore of purpos.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Si.</speaker>
                  <p>What ſaith <hi>Dauus?</hi>
                  </p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Da:</speaker>
                  <p>Truly euen as much now as be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Si.</speaker>
                  <p>What, is it nothing thou ſaieſt?</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Da:</speaker>
                  <p>Nothing at all.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <pb facs="tcp:11757:25"/>
                  <speaker>Si.</speaker>
                  <p>But I had hoped to heare ſomewhat.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Da.</speaker>
                  <p>
                     <note place="margin"> 
                        <stage>Dauus ſpea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>keth this to the Audience, out of the
hearing of Simo.</stage>
                     </note>I perceiue the matter fell out otherwiſe than
he thought for, and that troubles the man.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Si.</speaker>
                  <p>Canſt thou tell mée truth?</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Da.</speaker>
                  <p>Why, nothing readier.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Si.</speaker>
                  <p>Is my ſonne any thing gréeued at this marriage, in
reſpect of the loue and familiarity betwixt him and this ſtrange
harlatry?</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Da.</speaker>
                  <p>No certeinly, or if he be, his gréefe is but for two or
three dayes (perceiue you mée?) and than it is don: for hée will
take a right courſe with himſelfe, as tou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ching that matter.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Si.</speaker>
                  <p>I commend him for it.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Da.</speaker>
                  <p>While he might, &amp; while it ſtood with his youth<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full
yéeres, he gaue himſelfe to loue: nor then neither, but ſecretly:
for he tooke héede that it ſhould not at any tyme bring him to ill
name, euen as became a manly man to do. Now it is méete for him to haue
a wife, hée hath ſetled his minde on marriage.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Si.</speaker>
                  <p>Mée thought that he was ſomewhat ſad.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Da.</speaker>
                  <p>Not a whit for this matter, but there is ſome cauſe why he
is not wel pleaſed with you.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Si.</speaker>
                  <p>What is that?</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Da.</speaker>
                  <p>A trifling matter.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Si.</speaker>
                  <p>What is it, I ſay?</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Da.</speaker>
                  <p>Nothing in effect.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Si.</speaker>
                  <p>But yet tell me what it is?</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Da.</speaker>
                  <p>He ſaith that there is too much niggardnes vſed in this
matter.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Si.</speaker>
                  <p>What, by mée?</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Da.</speaker>
                  <p>Yea by you. Hée ſcarcely (quoth hée)
beſtowed for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty pence in cates, and doth hée ſéeme to marry
his ſonne to a wife: what man of calling (of my fréendes and
e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>qualles) ſhall I bid to my wedding feaſt, as the caſe now ſtands? And
you likewiſe, here be it ſpoken, are too much ſparing indéede,
which I do not commend in you.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <pb facs="tcp:11757:26"/>
                  <speaker>Si.</speaker>
                  <p>Sirra hold you your peace.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Da.</speaker>
                  <p>I haue mooued his patience.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Si.</speaker>
                  <p>I will ſée thoſe things cared for well inough: but
what is the meaning of this? what is it that this de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceitfull knaue goeth
aboute? ſurely if any thing happen otherwiſe than well, euen that ſame
varlet is the chéefe woorker of it.</p>
               </sp>
            </div>
         </div>
         <div n="3" type="act">
            <div n="1" type="scene">
               <head>¶Act. 3. Scen. 1.</head>
               <argument>
                  <head>The Argument.</head>
                  <p>SIMO, thorough his ouermuch wilines, is notably deceiued,
thin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king the birth of the childe to bee a fained matter: which indeede was
nothing leſſe.</p>
               </argument>
               <stage> 
                  <list>
                     <item>
                        <hi>Myſis.</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>
                        <hi>Simo.</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>
                        <hi>Dauus.</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item> 
                        <hi>Lesbia,</hi> the Midwife.</item>
                     <item> 
                        <hi>Glycerie,</hi> lying in childbed.</item>
                  </list>
               </stage>
               <sp>
                  <p>
                     <note place="margin"> 
                        <stage>This talke be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tweene Myſis and the mid<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wife is
ouer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>heard by Simo, whom they ſee not.</stage>
                     </note>
                     <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg>N good ſooth
<hi>Lesbia,</hi> it is very true as you ſay: one ſhall hardly finde a man
that is faithfull and true of his woord to a woman.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Si.</speaker>
                  <p>This mayde belongs to her of <hi>Andros,</hi> how ſaieſt
thou?</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Da.</speaker>
                  <p>Shée doth ſo.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>My.</speaker>
                  <p>And yet this yong man <hi>Pamphilus.</hi>
                  </p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Si.</speaker>
                  <p>
                     <note n="*" place="margin"> 
                        <stage>He ſpeaketh ſtill to Dauus, &amp; Myſis goeth on
with her ſpeche, not hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring him.</stage>
                     </note>What ſaieth
ſhée?</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>My.</speaker>
                  <p>Was as good as his woord.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Si.</speaker>
                  <p>What?</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Da.</speaker>
                  <p>
                     <note n="ʒ" place="margin"> 
                        <stage>Dauus ſpeakes to the audience out of Simoes
hearing.</stage>
                     </note>I would to God that either the olde man were deafe, or
that pratling wench dumbe.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>My.</speaker>
                  <p>For were it man childe or woman childe that my miſtres were
deliuered of, hée tooke order for the nur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing of it.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <pb facs="tcp:11757:26"/>
                  <speaker>Si.</speaker>
                  <p>O the king of heauen, what is this I heare? Why, all is paſt
helpe, at leaſt if it bee true that this mayde tells.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Lesb.</speaker>
                  <p>
                     <note place="margin"> 
                        <stage>Lesbia &amp; My<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſis go on ſtill with their talk
and theſe in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terſpeeches of Simo and Da<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uus, muſt be ſuppoſed to be
vttered by the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                           <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelues, out of the womens ſight and
hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring.</stage>
                     </note>He is a good natured yong man, by your ſaying.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>My.</speaker>
                  <p>Yea of an excellent good nature: But doo you fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low me in
preſently, that ſhe néede not to ſtay for you.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Lesb.</speaker>
                  <p>I come after you.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Da.</speaker>
                  <p>
                     <note n="℈" place="margin"> 
                        <stage>Dauus ſpeakes this to the au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dience, out of Simoes
hearing</stage>
                     </note>What remedy now may I find for this
miſchéefe?</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Si.</speaker>
                  <p>What meanes this? doth he dote ſo much on this ſtrange
harlat indéede? Now I perceiue how this geare cottens: I ſcarſe
found it out now at laſt, fooliſh man that I am.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Da.</speaker>
                  <p>
                     <note n="˘" place="margin"> 
                        <stage>He ſpeaks (as it were) to the
audience.</stage>
                     </note>What doth he ſay that he hath found out?</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Si.</speaker>
                  <p>That knaue ſéekes to abuſe me with this falſhood
firſt and formoſt. They faine that this quean is brought a bed, to thend
that ſo they may driue <hi>Chremes</hi> from geuing his daughter.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Glycer.</speaker>
                  <p>
                     <note n="*" place="margin"> 
                        <stage>This is vtte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red within by Glycerie, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing in
trauaile with childe.</stage>
                     </note>Oh lady <hi>Iuno Lucina,</hi> helpe and
ſaue mée I beſéech thée.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Si.</speaker>
                  <p>Whup hoyda: what in all the haſt? ſée a fooliſh
deuiſe: as ſoone as ſhe heard me at the dore, ſhée ſtraight
falles in labour: <hi>Dauus,</hi> this was not halfe cunningly contriued of
thée, ech thing in his due time.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Da.</speaker>
                  <p>What, by mée?</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Si.</speaker>
                  <p>Why make you it ſo ſtrange, haue you forgot your
ſcholler?</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Da.</speaker>
                  <p>I wot not what you ſay.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Si.</speaker>
                  <p>If this knaue had ſet his craft a broche againſt me
vnawares, and in a marriage ment in good earneſt: what prancks would
hée than haue played mée, trow you? But now, be it vpon his
perill: as for me I am ſafe.</p>
               </sp>
            </div>
            <div n="2" type="scene">
               <pb facs="tcp:11757:27"/>
               <head>¶Act. 3. Scen. 2.</head>
               <argument>
                  <head>The Argument.</head>
                  <p>LESBIA comming furth, ſheweth the ſtate of Glycery lying
in childbed: and withall appointes a drinke to be ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen her, thereby imitating
the Phiſitians, which are wont to preſcribe vnto the ſicke, what they
ſhall eate and drinke. Laſtly, Simo and Dauus are at variance about the
birth of the child.</p>
               </argument>
               <stage> 
                  <list>
                     <item>
                        <hi>Lesbia,</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>
                        <hi>Simo,</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>
                        <hi>Dauus.</hi>
                     </item>
                  </list>
               </stage>
               <sp>
                  <p>
                     <seg rend="decorInit">H</seg>Itherto <hi>Archillis</hi> I ſée all good ſignes
of health in her, that are vſuall &amp; ought to bée in a woman in her
caſe: Now firſt and formoſt, cauſe you thoſe things to be waſhed,
and then geue her that drink, and the ſame quantity that I ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>appointed for
her. I will come backe againe hither by and by. Before god there is a iolly
bouncing boy borne vnto <hi>Pamphilus:</hi> Now I pray God ſend him long to
liue, bycauſe he hath ſo honeſt a man to his father, who had care &amp;
conſcience not to deale amis with this kinde harted young woman.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Si.</speaker>
                  <p>And who that knew thée, would not iudge this al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo to
be a craft of thy budget.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Da.</speaker>
                  <p>And what is that, I pray you?</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Si.</speaker>
                  <p>
                     <note place="margin"> 
                        <stage>So as Simo thinks that Glycerie is not brought a bed,
but that al this is fained to bleare his eyes with
all.</stage>
                     </note>Shée did not will them while ſhe was in the
houſe, to doo what was néedefull for the woman that lyes in, but after
ſhee was come furth, ſhe kept a pratling out of the ſtréet, vnto
them which were within doores. Why <hi>Dauus,</hi> am I ſo little ſet by of
thée? Or I pray thée, doo I ſéeme ſo fit a man, for
thée to ſéeke to beguile, with ſuch manifeſt fraud and
falſhood? At leaſt wiſe thou doſt <pb facs="tcp:11757:27"/> thy diligence, ſo as
I may wel ſéeme to bée put in feare by thée: Surely if I
had knowen it before.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Da.</speaker>
                  <p>
                     <note n="*" place="margin"> 
                        <stage>Dauus ſaith this to the Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dience.</stage>
                     </note>Now
in good faith this man beguiles himſelfe, I doo not.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Si.</speaker>
                  <p>Why, did I not geue thée ſtraight charge to the
contrary? did I not threaten thée with puniſhment, that thou
ſhouldſt not doo it? did it feare thée a whit? what hath it booted?
Shall I now geue thée credite in this: that ſhée there, is
brought a bed of childe by <hi>Pam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>philus?</hi>
                  </p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Da.</speaker>
                  <p>
                     <note n="*" place="margin"> 
                        <stage>This he ſpeaks to himſelfe.</stage>
                     </note>O, ho, I
ſée now wherein he is deceiued: I wot well what I wil doo.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Si</speaker>
                  <p>Doſt thou not anſweare mée?</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Da.</speaker>
                  <p>What ſhould you geue mée credite? as though it was
not told you before, that theſe things would come ſo to paſſe.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Si.</speaker>
                  <p>Did any body tell mée ſo?</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Da.</speaker>
                  <p>Why than, did you of your ſelfe, finde that this is a fained
matter?</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Si.</speaker>
                  <p>Hée laughes mée to ſcorn.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Da.</speaker>
                  <p>No doubt it was told you before, for how els ſhould it come
vpon you to ſuſpect it?</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Si.</speaker>
                  <p>How? marry bycauſe I knew thée.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Da.</speaker>
                  <p>As who ſhould ſay, it was done by my deuiſe.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Si.</speaker>
                  <p>Yea I am well aſſured of that.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Da.</speaker>
                  <p>Well ſir, you doo not yet throughly know what manner of man
I am.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Si.</speaker>
                  <p>Doo not I know thée knaue?</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Da.</speaker>
                  <p>But when I begin to tell you any thing, you ſtraight way
thinke that I go about to beguyle you.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Si.</speaker>
                  <p>That is a lye.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Da.</speaker>
                  <p>So as in good faith, now a daies, I dare not ſcarce open my
lips to you.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Si.</speaker>
                  <p>This one thing I am ſure of, that here is no wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man
deliuered of childe.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Da.</speaker>
                  <p>Haue you vnderſtoode ſo? But neuertheleſſe ere it 
<pb facs="tcp:11757:28"/> be long, the childe ſhall be brought here and laid before the
doore: Maiſter, I tel you of it now before hand, that you may certainly know
what will follow: leaſt here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>after you ſhould ſay, that this was don by
the counſaile or craft of <hi>Dauus:</hi> And I would in any wiſe, that
this euil opinion which you haue of mée, were cleane out of your
minde.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Si.</speaker>
                  <p>How cameſt thou to know this?</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Da.</speaker>
                  <p>I heard it, and I beléeue it be true.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Si.</speaker>
                  <p>There be many things mo than one, which cauſe me to
coniecture as I doo: Euen now, is the firſt tyme that this queane declared
her ſelfe to be with childe by <hi>Pam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>philus,</hi> which is but a falſe
deuiſe. Moreouer, now that ſhe ſées preparation at home for the
wedding, the maid forſooth, in all haſt is ſent for the midwife to come
to her, and withall to bring alſo a childe with her.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Da.</speaker>
                  <p>Well, without that it come ſo to paſſe that you do
ſée the childe with your owne eies, nothing will hinder the courſe
of this marriage.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Si.</speaker>
                  <p>What ſayeſt thou? when thou once vnderſtoodeſt that
they purpoſed ſuch a matter, why didſt thou not than preſently tell it
vnto <hi>Pamphilus?</hi>
                  </p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Da.</speaker>
                  <p>Why than, who els hath withdrawen him from theſe harlots but
my ſelfe? for certeynly we all know how excéedingly he loued this
woman. Now he is deſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rous to haue a wife, and as for that matter, let
mée a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lone withall: yet neuertheleſſe go you on forward ſtill with
this marriage as you doo: and I hope God will proſper it.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Si.</speaker>
                  <p>Very well, go thy waies in, ſtay there till I come: and
prouide what is néedfull. 
<note place="margin"> 
                        <stage>Dauus being gon in, Simo turne his tale to the
audiens.</stage>
                     </note>He could not driue it in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to my head, to make me
beléeue all this, neither am I certaine whether all that hée told
me be true or no: But I paſſe not greatly for that. Marry the matter I
ſtand moſt vpon, is the promiſe which my ſonne himſelfe made vnto me:
Now will I go méete with <hi>Chremes:</hi> 
                     <pb facs="tcp:11757:28"/> I will intreate
him for his daughter to my ſonne in marryage, and if I doo obteine her, why
ſhould I make any more daying for the matter, but marry them out of the way?
for as touching my ſonnes promiſe, I haue no doubt at all, if hée
ſhall refuſe to performe it, but I may full rightly compel him to it. But
lo yonder where <hi>Chremes</hi> himſelfe comes towards mée, euen in
as good time as may be.</p>
               </sp>
            </div>
            <div n="3" type="scene">
               <head>¶Act. 3. Scen. 3.</head>
               <argument>
                  <head>The Argument.</head>
                  <p>In this ſcene, by meanes of Chremes and Simo meeting
together, the fained marriage is become a marriage in good earneſt.</p>
               </argument>
               <stage> 
                  <list>
                     <item>
                        <hi>Simo,</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>and <hi>Chremes,</hi>
                     </item>
                  </list>the old men.</stage>
               <sp>
                  <p>
                     <seg rend="decorInit">G</seg>OD ſaue you neighbour <hi>Chremes.</hi>
                  </p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Chr.</speaker>
                  <p>O ſir, you are the onely man I ſought.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Si.</speaker>
                  <p>And I you.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Ch.</speaker>
                  <p>You com as wel as I could wiſh: There haue ſome bin with
me, which told me they heard you ſay that my daughter ſhould this day be
marryed to your ſonne: Now the matter I come for, is to ſée, whether
you, or they, do dote.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Si.</speaker>
                  <p>Heare me a word, or twoo, and you ſhall ſoone know both
what I deſire of you, and alſo what you require of me.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Ch.</speaker>
                  <p>I heare you, go too, ſpeake your minde.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Si.</speaker>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Chremes</hi> I beſéech you for Gods ſake, and
for our frendſhips ſake begun betwixt vs from our childehood, and growen
together with our years: I beſeech you as you loue your onely daughter, &amp;
as you tender my ſon, <pb facs="tcp:11757:29"/> whome it lieth in you chéefely to
ſaue or to ſpill, y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> you will help me now in this matter, and like as the
mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riage ſhould haue bin, that ſo now, it may be made vp betwixt them.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Chre.</speaker>
                  <p>Tuſh, neuer pray mée ſo much, as though you could
not obteine this at my hands but by much pray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing: Doo you think mée now
an other manner of man, than I was then, when I promiſed my daughter vnto
you? If it be a matter profitable for both parts, that this marriage be made,
then cauſe hir furthwith to be ſent for. But if there grow of this, more
harme than good, as well to the one as to the other: Then my deſire is, that
you will conſider of the matter indifferently for both parts, euen no
otherwiſe than if ſhe were your daughter, and that I were father vnto
<hi>Pamphilus.</hi>
                  </p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Si.</speaker>
                  <p>Yea <hi>Chremes,</hi> euen ſo is my meaning, and ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore
doo I requeſt that it may be effected. Neither would I requeſt it at your
hands, if the matter if ſelfe dyd not geue me good occaſion.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Chr.</speaker>
                  <p>What may that be?</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Si.</speaker>
                  <p>Mary ſir, my ſonne and <hi>Glycerie</hi> are fallen
out.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Chr.</speaker>
                  <p>I heare you.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Si.</speaker>
                  <p>Nay, but ſo far fallen out, as I hope they may be quite
ſet a ſunder.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Chr.</speaker>
                  <p>Tuſh, it is but a Tale.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Si.</speaker>
                  <p>Nay, without dowt it is as I ſay.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Chr.</speaker>
                  <p>Yea forſooth, thus, as I ſhall tell you, <hi>The falling
out of Louers, is a Renewing of Loue.</hi>
                  </p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Si.</speaker>
                  <p>Alas, I pray you then, let vs now preuent that, while time is,
and while his hot loue is alaid with bit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter words: Let vs couple him to a
wife, before that this naughtie parks ſhrewd crafts, and fained teares, doo
woork againe his loueſick minde, vnto pitie and com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paſſion: I hope
<hi>(Chremes)</hi> that being once reclaimed, by meanes of good company and
honeſt wedlock, he will afterward, w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> cas, winde himſelf out of theſe
miſchéefs.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <pb facs="tcp:11757:29"/>
                  <speaker>Chr.</speaker>
                  <p>It ſéemes ſo to you, but I think it neither
poſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble for him to continue with this wife, nor yet for me to be able to
endure it.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Si.</speaker>
                  <p>How can you know that, vntill you haue made tryall of it?</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Chr.</speaker>
                  <p>Yea mary, but it is a ſhrewd matter to make that Tryall vpon
my daughter.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Si.</speaker>
                  <p>Well yet, the very worſt and vttermoſt of all, can be but
a diuorſe or ſeperation, if any ſuch matter ſhould happen, as God
forbyd it ſhould: But contrari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe, if by this meanes he doo amend and
become a new man, ſée than how many commodities enſue: Firſt and
formoſt, you ſhall reſtore to your fréend his ſonne: next, you
ſhall finde a ſure ſonne in law to your ſelfe, and laſtly, a ſtayed
huſband to your daughter.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Chr.</speaker>
                  <p>What? ſay you ſo? If you be perſwaded that this is
expedient, I for my part, will not haue you hin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dred of any good turne that I
may affoord you.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Si.</speaker>
                  <p>Chremes, not without good cauſe haue I alwaies ſet moſt
ſtore by you of any man.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Chr.</speaker>
                  <p>But what ſayd you erewhile?</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Si.</speaker>
                  <p>What?</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Chr.</speaker>
                  <p>How came you to know, that they be at iarre betwéene
themſelues?</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Si.</speaker>
                  <p>Euen <hi>Dauus</hi> himſelfe, the chéefe of their
priuie Councell, dyd tell it me. And he likewiſe perſwades me to haſten
this marriage, as much as I may: Think you he would haue done this, vnleſſe
he were ſure that my ſonne deſires the ſame? You ſhall heare him your
ſelfe, by and by. Holo ſirs, call me out <hi>Dauus</hi> hither. But
ſée yonder where he comes furth of him ſelfe.</p>
               </sp>
            </div>
            <div n="4" type="scene">
               <pb facs="tcp:11757:30"/>
               <head>¶Act. 3. Scen. 4.</head>
               <argument>
                  <head>The Argument.</head>
                  <p>Dauus fawning vppon the olde man, dooth perſwade him to make
vp the marriage, little thinking that it ſhould come to paſſe in deede:
But whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> he perceiueth that Si<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mo deales in good earneſt with Chremes as
touching his daughter: he is then much perplexed, and cleane beſide
himſelfe.</p>
               </argument>
               <stage> 
                  <list>
                     <item>
                        <hi>Dauus.</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>
                        <hi>Simo.</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>
                        <hi>Chremes.</hi>
                     </item>
                  </list>
               </stage>
               <sp>
                  <p>
                     <hi>
                        <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg>
                     </hi> was comming to you.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Si.</speaker>
                  <p>well, what is the matter?</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Da.</speaker>
                  <p>Why is not the bryde ſent for? it waxeth now very late.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Si.</speaker>
                  <p>
                     <note n="*" place="margin"> 
                        <stage>Simo ſaith this ſoftly to
Chre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mes.</stage>
                     </note>Doo you not héere him. Well Dauus, I ſtood
ſomewhat in feare of thée erewhile, leaſt thou (as the common ſort
of ſeruants are wont) ſhouldſt by craft and knauery haue deceyued me, in
reſpect that my ſonne is in loue.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Da.</speaker>
                  <p>Alas ſir, ſhould I haue don ſuch a déede?</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Si.</speaker>
                  <p>I was of that beléefe, and therefore fearing ſuch a
matter, I kept ſecret from my ſonne and thée, that which now I will
tell thée.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Da.</speaker>
                  <p>What is it?</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Si.</speaker>
                  <p>Thou ſhalt know, for now in a manner, I begin to haue ſome
truſt in thée.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Da.</speaker>
                  <p>At laſt then, you know what manner of man I am.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Si.</speaker>
                  <p>This marriage, was not meant to haue bin made
indéede.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Da.</speaker>
                  <p>What, was it not?</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Si.</speaker>
                  <p>No, but I fayned it of purpoſe, that I might thoroughlie
trye you.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Da.</speaker>
                  <p>What, is it true ſir?</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Si.</speaker>
                  <p>It is euen ſo as I tell thée.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <pb facs="tcp:11757:30"/>
                  <speaker>Da.</speaker>
                  <p>Sée, I could neuer perceyue ſo muche. O notable
pollicie.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Si.</speaker>
                  <p>Nay but liſten to me, as ſoone as I bade thée go
hence in, this man met me in excellent good time.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Da.</speaker>
                  <p>
                     <note n="*" place="margin"> 
                        <stage>Dauus ſaith this ſoftly to
himſelfe.</stage>
                     </note>Out alas, are we not cleane caſt a way?</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Si.</speaker>
                  <p>I ſhew him all that thou toldſt me erewhile.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Da.</speaker>
                  <p>
                     <note n="*" place="margin"> 
                        <stage>And this like wiſe to
him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe.</stage>
                     </note>What is this I héere?</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Si.</speaker>
                  <p>I entreat him for his daughter, and with much a doo I obtaine
her.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Da.</speaker>
                  <p>I am vtterly vndon.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Si.</speaker>
                  <p>Hah, what ſayeſt thou?</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Da.</speaker>
                  <p>I ſay it is excellently well don.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Si.</speaker>
                  <p>Now is there no let or delay on this mans behalfe.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Chr.</speaker>
                  <p>I will ſtraight goe hence to byd euery thing be made redy,
and ſo bring woord hither againe.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Si.</speaker>
                  <p>Now <hi>Dauus</hi> I pray thée, ſith thou alone
haſt brought this marriage for mée to paſſe:</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>(<hi>Da.</hi>
                  </speaker>
                  <p>Yea truly, I, and none elſe.)</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Si.</speaker>
                  <p>That thou wilt yet moreouer labour my ſonnes amendment.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Da.</speaker>
                  <p>In déede I will doo what I can.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Si.</speaker>
                  <p>Thou maiſt now well do it, eſpecially while he is netteled
at the heart.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Da.</speaker>
                  <p>Well, ſet your minde at reſt.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Si.</speaker>
                  <p>Go to then, But where is he now?</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Da.</speaker>
                  <p>It is maruaile if he be not at home.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Si.</speaker>
                  <p>
                     <note n="*" place="margin"> 
                        <stage>Simo depar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teth and Dauus ſtayeth
ſtill.</stage>
                     </note>I will go to him, and tell him my minde in the ſame
ſort, as I told it thée.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Da.</speaker>
                  <p>I am a forlorne creature, what ſhall kéepe me but
that I muſt go hence ſtreight into the grinding houſe to priſon? No
prayer or intreaty wil ſerue, I haue now brought all out of frame: I haue
deceyued my maſter: I haue forced a marriage on my Maſters ſonne: I was
the cauſe y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> the marriage ſhal be made to day, euen quite vnhoped for of
y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> old man, &amp; cleane contrary to the minde of <hi>Pamphilus.</hi>
Sée theſe goodly crafts of mine: had I not <pb facs="tcp:11757:31"/> buſied my
ſelfe, there had hapned no harme at all: 
<note place="margin"> 
                        <stage>Dauus eſpieth Pamphilus comming.</stage>
                     </note>But
lo yonder I ſée him himſelfe, I am but a dead ma<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1+ letters">
                        <desc>•…</desc>
                     </gap>: I would to God héere were
ſome place, where I <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1+ letters">
                        <desc>•…</desc>
                     </gap>ight throwe
my ſelfe downe headlong.</p>
               </sp>
            </div>
            <div n="5" type="scene">
               <head>¶Act. 3. Scen. 5.</head>
               <argument>
                  <head>The Argument.</head>
                  <p>PAMPHILVS takes on very much, that by following the
de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceitfull deuiſe of Dauus, he made aunſwere to his fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther that he would
marry.</p>
               </argument>
               <stage> 
                  <list>
                     <item>
                        <hi>Pamphilus,</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>
                        <hi>Dauus.</hi>
                     </item>
                  </list>
               </stage>
               <sp>
                  <p>
                     <seg rend="decorInit">W</seg>Here is that ſame miſchéeuous varlet, which hath
cleane vndon mée?</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Da.</speaker>
                  <p>Now Lord haue mercy vpon mée.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Pamph.</speaker>
                  <p>And yet I confeſſe, this that hath hapned, is euen good
enough for mée, when I would bée ſo ſottiſh, and ſo ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry
a dolt, as to commit my whole eſtate and welfare vnto a prating villaine.
Therefore I reape a iuſt reward for my folly. But he ſhal neuer ſcape
ſcotfrée with it.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Da.</speaker>
                  <p>
                     <note place="margin"> 
                        <stage>This he ſaith out of Pam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>philus
hearing.</stage>
                     </note>I am ſure to bée ſafe enough for euer
hereafter, if I may but now auoide this miſchéefe.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Pamph.</speaker>
                  <p>But what may I now ſay to my father? ſhal I now refuſe
marriage, and yet promiſed erewhile that I would marry? with what face dare I
doo that? I wot not what to doo with my ſelfe.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Da.</speaker>
                  <p>
                     <note n="*" place="margin"> 
                        <stage>Dauus ſpeak<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth all this out of Pamphilus
hearing.</stage>
                     </note>Truely nor I neither, what to doo with my ſelf: yet
this is it I am fully reſolued vpon, I will tell him that I ſhall
preſently finde out ſome remedy, and ſo put of my puniſhment yet a
little while.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Pamph.</speaker>
                  <p>Oh.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Da.</speaker>
                  <p>Now hée ſées mée.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <pb facs="tcp:11757:31"/>
                  <speaker>Pamph.</speaker>
                  <p>Come hither you honeſt man: how ſay you ſirra,
ſée you not how I (poore ſoule) am beſtad by meanes of your
deuiſes?</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Da.</speaker>
                  <p>But I will remedy it by and by.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Pamph.</speaker>
                  <p>Wilt thou remedy it?</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Da.</speaker>
                  <p>Yes certainly maiſter <hi>Pamphilus.</hi>
                  </p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Pamph.</speaker>
                  <p>Yes, euen as thou didſt of late.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Da.</speaker>
                  <p>Nay rather better, I hope.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Pamph.</speaker>
                  <p>O, ſhould I credit thée vile hangman? canſt thou
recouer a matter full of trouble, and paſt all hope of helpe? Out alas, what
a ſure ſtay had I of thée, who this day, out of my greateſt
quietnes, haſt forced mée into a marriage ſpite of my téeth?
did I not tell thee it would come thus to paſſe?</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Da.</speaker>
                  <p>You did ſo.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Pamph.</speaker>
                  <p>What then art thou woorthy of?</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Da.</speaker>
                  <p>Hanging. But yet ſuffer mée a litle to come to my
ſelfe, I will ſtraight way ſéeke out ſome helpe.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Pamph.</speaker>
                  <p>Alas that I haue not leyſure to puniſh thée as I
would: it is now time for mée to ſée to my ſelfe, and not to
be auenged of thée.</p>
               </sp>
            </div>
         </div>
         <div n="4" type="act">
            <div n="1" type="scene">
               <head>¶Act 4. Scen. 1.</head>
               <argument>
                  <head>The Argument.</head>
                  <p>This ſcene doth cheefly containe the angry ſpeeches of
Carinus a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt Pamphilus.</p>
               </argument>
               <stage>
                  <pb facs="tcp:11757:32"/> 
                  <list>
                     <item>
                        <hi>Carinus.</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>
                        <hi>Pamphilus.</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>
                        <hi>Dauus.</hi>
                     </item>
                  </list>
               </stage>
               <sp>
                  <p>
                     <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg>S this a thing credible, or wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thy to be ſpoken of, that
there ſhold be ſomuch peruerſneſſe in any man, as to delight in
euill, and to ſéeke his owne commoditie, euen by the diſcommodity of
an other? Is this kinde of people to be truſted? Nay certainely, thoſe are
the very worſt kinde of people, who are ſomewhat ſhamefaſt in denying a
Requeſt, but af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terward, when time requires performance of their pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſes,
Then of neceſſitie, they bewray themſelues and faulter, and yet the
matter it ſelfe driues them then to a flat denyall: Then is their
ſpéech void of all ſhame and honeſty, as thus: who are you ſir?
What friend of mine are you? why ſhould you deſire my ſwéete hart?
O ſir, heare you me, I loue you well, but my ſelfe bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter.
Neuertheleſſe, if you aſke where is truth and truſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes of promis,
they are neuer a whit aſhamed. Now they are not a frayd to deny, when as they
ought to performe: And yet are they then afrayd, when they ſhold not. But
what ſhall I doo? Is it beſt that I goe to him, to taunt and take him vp
for this iniurie? I ſhall giue him ſhrewd woords his fill: But one may
ſay to me, thou ſhalt be neuer the néere: yes very much: without
doubt I ſhall anger euerie vayne in his hart, and withall ſhall eaſe mine
owne minde.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Pamph.</speaker>
                  <p>Carinus, I haue vnawares (without God help vs) euen cleane
caſt away both you and my ſelfe.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Car.</speaker>
                  <p>Yea, vnawares: is it ſo indéede? Now at laſt you
haue got an excuſe: Tuſh, thou haſt broken thy faith and promis.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Pamph.</speaker>
                  <p>Why, what excuſe now at laſt?</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <pb facs="tcp:11757:32"/>
                  <speaker>Car.</speaker>
                  <p>What, woldſt thou yet againe deceiue me now, with thoſe
ſuttle ſpéeches of thine?</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Pamph.</speaker>
                  <p>Why, what is the matter with you now?</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Car.</speaker>
                  <p>Mary after I had told you that I was in loue with
<hi>Philumena,</hi> forſooth it pleaſed you to like her well for your
ſelfe: Wo is me wofull wretch, who eſtéemed the honeſty of thy
minde by mine owne.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Pamph.</speaker>
                  <p>You miſtake the matter.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Car.</speaker>
                  <p>Why, and doſt thou not think this yet a ioy perfect enough
for thée, vnles thou maiſt make a tame foole of me that am in loue,
and feede me with vaine hope? well, take her to thée.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Pamph.</speaker>
                  <p>Shold I take her? Alack, ful little do you know, in how great
troobles I am wrapt, vnhappie man that I am: and what care and anguiſh, this
my Tormen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tor hath put me to, with his deuiſes.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Car.</speaker>
                  <p>Why, is that ſuch a marueill? he takes en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſample by
you.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Pamph.</speaker>
                  <p>Well, you would not ſay this, if you knew either me, or my
loue.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Car.</speaker>
                  <p>I know you were at words with your father of late, and that is
the matter he is now diſpleaſed with you, but yet he could not co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>pel you
to marry her to day.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Pamph.</speaker>
                  <p>Yea and by how much the more you are ig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>norant of my heauines:
This ſame marriage was not meant or intended for me, neither did any man
mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, now at this time, to procure a wife for me.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Car.</speaker>
                  <p>I wot well, you are compeld to it euen of your owne
frée will.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Pamph.</speaker>
                  <p>Abide, you wot not yet how the caſe ſtands.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Car.</speaker>
                  <p>Yes certainely, I wot full well that you will marry her.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Pamph.</speaker>
                  <p>Why do you thus kil my hart? heare me what I ſhall ſay to
you: he neuer ceaſſed, preaſſing, perſwa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding, and praying me ſo
long, till at laſt he inforced me to ſay vnto my father, that I would marry
her.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <pb facs="tcp:11757:33"/>
                  <speaker>Car.</speaker>
                  <p>What man did this?</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Pamph.</speaker>
                  <p>Dauus.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Car.</speaker>
                  <p>What, <hi>Dauus?</hi>
                  </p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Pamph.</speaker>
                  <p>Yea, hée brought all out of ſquare.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Car.</speaker>
                  <p>Wherefore did hée ſo?</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Pamph.</speaker>
                  <p>I wot not in the world, without that God were highly offended
with mée, in that I followed his counſaile.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Car.</speaker>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Dauus,</hi> Didſt thou doo this?</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Da.</speaker>
                  <p>Yes.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Car.</speaker>
                  <p>Hah, what ſayeſt thou villayne? Now I pray God geue thee a
miſchéeuous end as thou haſt deſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued. Why I pray thee tell me,
if all the enemies hée hath in the world would haue wiſhed to force a
mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ryage vpon him, what other counſaile could they haue geuen him than
this?</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Da.</speaker>
                  <p>Well, I am deceiued, but not diſcouraged.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Car.</speaker>
                  <p>
                     <note n="*" place="margin"> 
                        <stage>Ironice.</stage>
                     </note>I know it well.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Da.</speaker>
                  <p>The matter came not well to paſſe this way, now wee will
take an other courſe, vnleſſe you be of opini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, that bycauſe it had
ill ſucceſſe at the firſt: that ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore this euill may not now be
remedied at the laſt.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Pamph.</speaker>
                  <p>Yes mary may it, for I verily beleeue if thou doo bend thy
whole indeuor vnto it, thou wilt make for me two marriages of one.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Da.</speaker>
                  <p>Maiſter <hi>Pamphilus,</hi> this I owe vnto you of duty, as
being your ſeruaunt: euen day and night to labours to my vttermoſt with
might and maine, and to hazard my life to doo you good withall: it is your
part, if ought hath hapned otherwiſe than was looked for, to pardon
mée. Be it that my doings proſper not: Why yet I doo my true intent:
Or finde you ſome better reme<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy your ſelfe, and let not mée either
make or meddle withall.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Pamph.</speaker>
                  <p>That is it I deſire: ſet mée againe in the ſame
ſtate thou foundeſt me.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <pb facs="tcp:11757:33"/>
                  <speaker>Da.</speaker>
                  <p>I will.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Pamph.</speaker>
                  <p>But it muſt be don by and by.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Da.</speaker>
                  <p>Alas, but yet ſtay a little, <hi>Glyceries</hi> doore
creaks.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Pamph.</speaker>
                  <p>That is nothing to thée.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Da.</speaker>
                  <p>Yet I would know.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Pamph.</speaker>
                  <p>What, ſtill more ſtaying?</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Da.</speaker>
                  <p>Well, I will preſently finde you out a deuiſe for
this.</p>
               </sp>
            </div>
            <div n="2" type="scene">
               <head>¶Act. 4. Scen. 2.</head>
               <argument>
                  <head>The Argument.</head>
                  <p>HEERE Pamphilus makes promis vnto Myſis that he will ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer
forſake Glycerie: yea though he ſhall procure all men to be his enimies for
it.</p>
               </argument>
               <stage> 
                  <list>
                     <item>
                        <hi>Myſis.</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>
                        <hi>Pamph.</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>
                        <hi>Carinus.</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>
                        <hi>Dauus.</hi>
                     </item>
                  </list>
               </stage>
               <sp>
                  <p>WHereſoeuer your friend <hi>Pamphilus</hi> be, I wil
furthwith ſéeke him out, and bring him with me: In the meane time
(dere hart) doo not you vexe your ſelfe with thought.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Pamph.</speaker>
                  <p>Myſis?</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>My.</speaker>
                  <p>Who is there? O maſter <hi>Pamphilus,</hi> you méete
me in very good time.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Pamph.</speaker>
                  <p>What is the matter with thée?</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>My.</speaker>
                  <p>My miſtres bad me pray you for Gods ſake, if you loue her,
that you will come to her, now out of hand. She ſaith that ſhe longs much
to ſée you.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Pamph.</speaker>
                  <p>Out alas, I am a forlorne man? This miſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chéefe
beginnes now againe a freſh: Is it méete that both I and ſhe
(ſilly ſoules) ſhould be thus vexed and diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quieted <pb facs="tcp:11757:34"/>
thorough thy meanes? for dowtles that is the cauſe ſhe now ſends for
mée, hauing vnderſtood of the marriage I am towards.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Car.</speaker>
                  <p>Concerning which matter truly, full eaſily mought we haue
bin at quiet, if this knaue had not bu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſted himſelfe.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Da.</speaker>
                  <p>Go too, if he be not mad enough of himſelfe, doo thou pricke
him forward.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>My.</speaker>
                  <p>Truly forſooth, and euen that is the cauſe that the
woefull woman is in ſorrow for.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Pamph.</speaker>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Myſis</hi> I ſweare to thée by all the Gods,
that I will neuer forſake her, no not if I wiſt, I ſhould haue all men
liuing myne enemies for it. I haue deſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red this woman in my hart:
Shée is fallen to my lot: wée are alike in manners and condition:
farewel they, that would ſet vs two a ſunder. There ſhall none part her
from me, but onely death.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Car.</speaker>
                  <p>I am now come to my ſelfe.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Pam.</speaker>
                  <p>No not the anſweare of God <hi>Apollo</hi> can be tru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er
than this. Mary I would faine (if it may bée) that my father ſhall not
thinke, that I withſtood the going forward of this marriage: But if it may
not bée, then will I go the plaine way to woork, that he may thinke that
I did withſtand it. What manner of man do I ſeeme?</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Car.</speaker>
                  <p>Euen as forlorn a creature as my ſelfe.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Pamph.</speaker>
                  <p>I ſéeke for counſaile.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Car.</speaker>
                  <p>Thou art a valiant man.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Pamph.</speaker>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Dauus</hi> I know whereabout thou goeſt.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Da.</speaker>
                  <p>Wel, certeinly I will bring this to paſſe for you.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Pamph.</speaker>
                  <p>It is more than time it were don.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Da.</speaker>
                  <p>I haue it but euen now to doo.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Car.</speaker>
                  <p>What is it?</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Da.</speaker>
                  <p>That thou deceiue not thy ſelfe, I haue it for this mans
behoofe, and not for thyne.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Car.</speaker>
                  <p>That is ſufficient for me.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <pb facs="tcp:11757:34"/>
                  <speaker>Pam.</speaker>
                  <p>Tell mée I pray thée, what is that thou wilt
doo?</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Da.</speaker>
                  <p>I feare me, this day will ſkant ſerue me to doo my
buſines: Thinke not than, that I am now at lei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure to diſcourſe:
Therefore get yée both away hence, for yée doo but trouble
mée.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Pamph.</speaker>
                  <p>I will go ſée <hi>Glycerie.</hi>
                  </p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Da.</speaker>
                  <p>And what will you? whither away hence?</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Car.</speaker>
                  <p>Wilt thou haue me ſay the truth?</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Da.</speaker>
                  <p>Nay, now he begins to tell me ſome long tale.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Car.</speaker>
                  <p>But what ſhall become of mée?</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Da.</speaker>
                  <p>Why thou ſhameles man, is it not well for thée, that
I gayne thée one litle dayes reſpite, in that I doo prolong his
marriage?</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Car.</speaker>
                  <p>O <hi>Dauus,</hi> yet notwithſtanding.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Da.</speaker>
                  <p>What then?</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Car.</speaker>
                  <p>That I may attaine to marry her.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Da.</speaker>
                  <p>Sée a foole.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Car.</speaker>
                  <p>Well, looke thou come hither to me, if ſo hée thou
mayſt doo any good in the matter.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Da.</speaker>
                  <p>To what end ſhall I come? I can do nothing.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Car.</speaker>
                  <p>But yet if thou may doo ought.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Da.</speaker>
                  <p>Well, go too, I will come.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Car.</speaker>
                  <p>Yf thou maiſt doo any thing, thou ſhalt finde me at
home.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Da.</speaker>
                  <p>
                     <note n="*" place="margin"> 
                        <stage>Now he ſpea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>keth to
Myſis.</stage>
                     </note>
                     <hi>Myſis</hi> doo thou ſtay here a little for
mée, till I come furth againe.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>My.</speaker>
                  <p>Wherefore?</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Da.</speaker>
                  <p>For a thing that muſt néedes be don.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>My.</speaker>
                  <p>Hye thee apace.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Da.</speaker>
                  <p>I tell thée, I will bée here againe by and
by.</p>
               </sp>
            </div>
            <div n="3" type="scene">
               <pb facs="tcp:11757:35"/>
               <head>Act. 4 Scen. 3.</head>
               <argument>
                  <head>The Argument.</head>
                  <p>DAVVS brings the childe before Simoes doore, to thend to driue
Chremes backe from accompliſhing the marriage. And this ſcene conſiſts
more in geſture, then in vtterance.</p>
               </argument>
               <stage> 
                  <list>
                     <item>
                        <hi>Myſis.</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>
                        <hi>Dauus.</hi>
                     </item>
                  </list>
               </stage>
               <sp>
                  <p>
                     <seg rend="decorInit">W</seg>Hat, can one be ſure of nothing in this world? O Lord God,
I ſtill thought, that this <hi>Pamphilus</hi> was my miſtres
chéefeſt ioy, as being her frend, her lo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer, her huſband, and one
ready to ſerue her turne in all aſſayes. But now (a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lack forlorne woman,)
what gréefe takes ſhe for his ſake? without doubt there is more
harme in this, than there was good in the other. But lo, <hi>Dauus</hi> comes
furth. Abide fellow, what is that, I pray thée? whither away carrieſt
thou the childe?</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Da.</speaker>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Myſis,</hi> now muſt I néeds haue thée
ſhew thy rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy wit and cunning in this matter.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>My.</speaker>
                  <p>Where about goeſt thou?</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Da.</speaker>
                  <p>Take this ſame childe of me quickly, and lay it downe before
our doore.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>My.</speaker>
                  <p>What I pray thée, on the bare ground?</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Da.</speaker>
                  <p>Take thée ſome herbes of this alter, and ſtraw
vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der it.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>My.</speaker>
                  <p>And why doeſt not thou doo it thy ſelfe?</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Da.</speaker>
                  <p>Bycauſe if perhaps I ſhall be driuen to ſweare to my
maiſter, that I layd it not there: That then I <pb facs="tcp:11757:35"/> may ſweare
with a ſafe conſcience.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>My.</speaker>
                  <p>I perceiue you. But yet tell me, I pray thée, how is it
come vpon thee to be ſo holy now of late?</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Da.</speaker>
                  <p>Go too, beſtir thée, that thou mayeſt know further
of my minde, what I will doo. O good Lord.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>My.</speaker>
                  <p>Why, what now?</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Da.</speaker>
                  <p>The Brides father is come, and hath preuen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted me. Now I leaue
of my purpoſe which I firſt entended.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>My.</speaker>
                  <p>I wot not what thou ſayeſt.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Da.</speaker>
                  <p>I will now make as though I came this other way on the right
hand: Sée that thou bée ready to an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſweare and vphold my talke,
in euery point as ſhall bée néedfull.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>My.</speaker>
                  <p>I perceiue not at all, what thou intendeſt to doo. But if
there bée any thing that my helpe may ſtand you in ſteade, or that
thou ſée further into the matter than I doo: I will ſtay here,
leaſt you ſhould be hinde<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red of any benefite by my default.</p>
               </sp>
            </div>
            <div n="4" type="scene">
               <head>Act. 4. Scen. 4.</head>
               <argument>
                  <head>The Argument.</head>
                  <p>CHREMES heareth that Glycerie hath a childe by Pam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>philus, and
withall that ſhee is a free borne woman of Athens: by which meanes, he is
quite with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>drawen from the marriage.</p>
               </argument>
               <stage> 
                  <list>
                     <item>
                        <hi>Chremes.</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item> 
                        <hi>Myſis.</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item> 
                        <hi>Dauus.</hi>
                     </item>
                  </list>
               </stage>
               <sp>
                  <pb facs="tcp:11757:36"/>
                  <p>
                     <seg rend="decorInit">N</seg>Ow that I haue made all things in a readines for my
daughters marriage, I am come againe that I may cauſe her to be ſent for.
But what haue we here? In good faith it is a childe: woman didſt thou lay
this ſame childe here?</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>My.</speaker>
                  <p>
                     <note n="*" place="margin"> 
                        <stage>She lookes af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter Dauus.</stage>
                     </note>Whether is this
fellow gon?</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Chr.</speaker>
                  <p>What, wilt thou not aunſwere me?</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>My.</speaker>
                  <p>Alack he is no where in ſight, wo is me (poore wench) the
fellow is gon his waies, and left me here.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Da.</speaker>
                  <p>
                     <note n="*" place="margin"> 
                        <stage>Now Dauus comes a long.</stage>
                     </note>Good Lord of
heauen, what hurleburley is yonder at the market? how much people is there at
ſtrife? without it be that corne be at a high price, I wot not in the world
what to make of it.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>My.</speaker>
                  <p>I pray you ſirra, why did you leaue me here all alone?</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Da.</speaker>
                  <p>How now, what tale is this of a roſted horſe? Nay but
heareſt thou me <hi>Myſis,</hi> whoſe childe is this? or who brought it
hether?</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>My.</speaker>
                  <p>Art thou well in thy wits, that aſkeſt me this
queſtion?</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Da.</speaker>
                  <p>Whom then ſhould I aſke, ſéeing here is no body
els?</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Chr.</speaker>
                  <p>
                     <note n="*" place="margin"> 
                        <stage>This he ſaith to himſelfe. Chremes muſt be
ſuppoſed to ſtand a loof liſtening vnto all the talke betweene Dauus
and Myſis, and yet not ſhewing himſelfe vnto them, but vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pon occaſion
of their talke he oftimes vtte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reth ſpeaches as to
himſelfe.</stage>
                     </note>I marueil whence it ſhould be?</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Da.</speaker>
                  <p>Wilt thou not tell me what I aſke?</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>My.</speaker>
                  <p>Ahlas.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Da.</speaker>
                  <p>Come thy way hither on my right hand.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>My.</speaker>
                  <p>Thou raueſt, dydſt not thou thy ſelfe?—</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Da.</speaker>
                  <p>Huſht, be not ſo hard for thy eares as to ſpeake one
word more than I ſhall aſke thée.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>My.</speaker>
                  <p>Thou rayleſt.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Da.</speaker>
                  <p>Whence is this childe? ſpeake out aloud.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>My.</speaker>
                  <p>From among you.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <pb facs="tcp:11757:36"/>
                  <speaker>Da.</speaker>
                  <p>Ha ha ha, it is a wonder no doubt, if a hoore play a
ſhameles parte.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Chr.</speaker>
                  <p>
                     <note n="*" place="margin"> 
                        <stage>He ſpeakes this to himſelfe</stage>
                     </note>This
maid belongs to her of <hi>Andros</hi> for ought I can perceiue.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Da.</speaker>
                  <p>Doo we ſéeme ſuch fit copesmates for you to mock
and dally withall?</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Chr.</speaker>
                  <p>
                     <note n="˘" place="margin"> 
                        <stage>To himſelfe.</stage>
                     </note>I came in time.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Da.</speaker>
                  <p>Beſtur thée quickly, and take a way the childe hence
from the doore. 
<note n="℈" place="margin"> 
                        <stage>This, Dauus ſpeakes in a lo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wer voice, that Chremes
may not here him.</stage>
                     </note>Abide ſtill, ſée thou ſtur not a
foote out of the place thou ſtandſt in.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>My.</speaker>
                  <p>I pray God a very vengeance light on thée, that ſo
doſt terrifie me, poore wretch that I am.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Da.</speaker>
                  <p>Doo I ſpeake to thée or not?</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>My.</speaker>
                  <p>What wouldſt thou?</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Da.</speaker>
                  <p>And doſt thou yet aſke me what? I pray the whoſe childe
haſt thou laid here? Tel me.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>My.</speaker>
                  <p>Doſt not thou know?</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Da.</speaker>
                  <p>
                     <note n="£" place="margin"> 
                        <stage>This he ſpeaketh ſoft<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly vnto
her.</stage>
                     </note>Let paſſe what I know, and tell me what I aſke.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>My.</speaker>
                  <p>It is yours among you.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Da.</speaker>
                  <p>Which of vs oweth it?</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>My.</speaker>
                  <p>Pamphilus.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Da.</speaker>
                  <p>
                     <note n="℥" place="margin"> 
                        <stage>This hee re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peats alowd bycauſe Chre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mes may heare
him.</stage>
                     </note>Hah, what ſaydſt thou? Is it <hi>Pamphilus</hi>
childe?</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>My.</speaker>
                  <p>Why I pray thée and is it not?</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Chr.</speaker>
                  <p>
                     <note n="℞" place="margin"> 
                        <stage>To him ſelf.</stage>
                     </note>I ſée I did wel
alwaies to ſhun this ſame mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riage.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Da.</speaker>
                  <p>O notable prank worthie of puniſhment.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>My.</speaker>
                  <p>What exclaming makeſt thou?</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Da.</speaker>
                  <p>Why, did not I ſée this ſame child brought vnto you
yeſterday in the euening?</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>My.</speaker>
                  <p>O thou braſen faaſt fellow.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Da.</speaker>
                  <p>
                     <note n="*" place="margin"> 
                        <stage>Dauus vrg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth Myſis to proue plainely that the child
is borne of Gly<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerie, leaſt otherwiſe Chre<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>mes ſhould imagin it to be a
fayned mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, as Simo doth. Act. 3. Scen. 1.</stage>
                     </note>At leaſt I ſaw
Gammar <hi>Canthara</hi> with her clothes tuckt about her, carrying ſomewhat
in her lap.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>My.</speaker>
                  <p>In good faith yet I thank GOD with all my hart, <pb facs="tcp:11757:37"/>
that there were ſome frée women of the citie, at my miſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tres
deliuerance.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Da.</speaker>
                  <p>Without doubt ſhe knewe not him, for whoſe cauſe ſhe
takes this matter in hand. If <hi>Chremes</hi> ſhall ſée this ſame
childe, layd héere before the doore, then will he not giue his daughter
in marriage: Ah, in good ſooth he will giue her ſomuch the ſooner.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Chr.</speaker>
                  <p>
                     <note place="margin"> 
                        <stage>Meaning by him ſelfe.</stage>
                     </note>But in good
ſooth he will not.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Da.</speaker>
                  <p>Now be thou well aſſured of this, that if thou do not take
awaie the childe, I will by and by ſpurn it into the midſt of the ſtrete,
where I will trample thée alſo in the durt.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>My.</speaker>
                  <p>In good ſadneſſe fellow, thou art not well in thy
wits.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Da.</speaker>
                  <p>One deceitfull deuiſe bringes an other to light: I heare now
ſuch whiſpering among them, that this ſame <hi>Glycerie</hi> is
frée borne of <hi>Athens.</hi>
                  </p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Chr.</speaker>
                  <p>
                     <note n="*" place="margin"> 
                        <stage>Chremes ſpeakes ſtill to
himſelfe.</stage>
                     </note>What is this?</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Da.</speaker>
                  <p>So as he ſhall be driuen by law to marry her.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>My.</speaker>
                  <p>Why I pray thée, and is ſhe not frée of this
Citie indéede?</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Chr.</speaker>
                  <p>I ſée I was well nigh fallen into a ſhrewd
ſpor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting game vnawares.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Da.</speaker>
                  <p>Who talketh here? O <hi>Chremes,</hi> you come, in as good
time as may be: heare me what I ſhall ſay.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Chr.</speaker>
                  <p>I haue heard euery word alredy.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Da.</speaker>
                  <p>What, haue you hard all this talke?</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Chr.</speaker>
                  <p>I tell thee I hard all from the beginning.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Da.</speaker>
                  <p>I pray you and haue you hard it in déede? fye, out
vppon theſe lewd pranks: Now ſhould this ſame queane be had hence into
Bridewell. This ſame is the man thou doſt mock: think not then, that thou
mock<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eſt <hi>Dauus.</hi>
                  </p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>My.</speaker>
                  <p>Alas for me vnhappy wench that I am: In good ſooth, olde
father, I haue tolde nothing but truth.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <pb facs="tcp:11757:37"/>
                  <speaker>Chr.</speaker>
                  <p>I know the whole matter already: but is <hi>Simo</hi>
within.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Da.</speaker>
                  <p>Yes.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>My.</speaker>
                  <p>
                     <note n="*" place="margin"> 
                        <stage>It ſeems that Dauus offe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reth to d<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap>ly and play with Myſis, ſeeking
thereby to pleaſe her: and ſhee wil not a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bide him.</stage>
                     </note>Touch me
not thou varlet. By God if I tell not all this vnto <hi>Glicerie,</hi> [neuer
credit me.]</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Da.</speaker>
                  <p>Why thou fooliſh wench, thou perceiueſt not what is
don.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>My.</speaker>
                  <p>What ſhould I perceiue?</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Da.</speaker>
                  <p>This man is the brides father: it might not other<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe be
compaſſed, to make him vnderſta<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d theſe things that we would haue
him.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>My.</speaker>
                  <p>Why then, thou ſhouldſt haue told me ſo before.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Da.</speaker>
                  <p>I pray thée now, and doſt thou thinke but ſmall
difference betwéene that, that one doth in good earneſt, and that
which is done for the nones.</p>
               </sp>
            </div>
            <div n="5" type="scene">
               <head>¶Act. 4. Scen. 5.</head>
               <argument>
                  <head>The Argument.</head>
                  <p>CRITO comming from Andres to Athens, enquireth whether
Glycerie haue found out who be her parents or no: and vnderſtanding that
ſhe hath not yet found them, hee is therewith much greeued, bycauſe that
matter doth hinder his enioying of the goods fallen vnto him by Gly<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceries
death.</p>
               </argument>
               <stage> 
                  <list>
                     <item>
                        <hi>Crito,</hi> the ſtranger.</item>
                     <item>
                        <hi>Myſis.</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>
                        <hi>Dauus.</hi>
                     </item>
                  </list>
               </stage>
               <sp>
                  <p>
                     <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg>T was tolde me, that héere in this ſtréete,
dwelt <hi>Chryſis,</hi> who choſe ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther in this town to gather goods with
diſhoneſty, than to lead an honeſt poore life, in her owne countrey. By
whoſe death, thoſe ſame goods, by right of law, are come to me. But I
ſée now of whom I may <pb facs="tcp:11757:38"/> enquire. God ſpéede
you.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>My.</speaker>
                  <p>I pray you whom doo I ſée? Is not this
<hi>Crito,</hi> coſin germain to <hi>Chryſis?</hi> it is euen he.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Cr.</speaker>
                  <p>O <hi>Myſis,</hi> God ſaue you.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>My.</speaker>
                  <p>And you too good <hi>Crito.</hi>
                  </p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Cr.</speaker>
                  <p>Alack for pity, and is <hi>Chryſis</hi> dead
indéede?</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>My.</speaker>
                  <p>Yea truly forſooth, we poore ſoules are vndon by hir
death.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Cr.</speaker>
                  <p>Why, what do you? how goeth the world with you here, all
well?</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>My.</speaker>
                  <p>What we? Truly (as the prouerb goeth) <hi>Wee doo as wee may,
ſith wee may not as wee would.</hi>
                  </p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Cr.</speaker>
                  <p>How fares <hi>Glycerie,</hi> hath ſhe found out yet who be
her parents here?</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>My.</speaker>
                  <p>Would God ſhe had.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Cr.</speaker>
                  <p>Why than, &amp; hath ſhe not yet? Than in an il howre am I
come hether. For in good faith if I had knowen this, I would neuer haue ſet
foot forward in this iour<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ney. For ſhe hath euer bin held and reputed for
<hi>Chryſis</hi> own ſiſter. She is in preſent poſſeſſion of al
that y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> other had. And now, for me a ſtranger to go follow ſutes and
brables in law, how eaſy and profitable a matter were that for me here to
doo, euen the examples of others doo foreſhew me. Beſides that, I cannot
but thinke, that ſhe hath now ſome frend and defender, for ſhe was of
méetely good age and ſtature, when ſhe went from vs. I ſhould be
exclaimed vpon to bée a beggerly fogger, gréedily hunting after
heritage. And moreouer, it were no reaſon to ſpoyle her of that ſhe
hath.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>My.</speaker>
                  <p>O Gaffar <hi>Crito,</hi> in good ſooth full well doſt thou
kéepe thy old wont ſtill.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Cr.</speaker>
                  <p>Well, ſith I am come hether, bring me to her, that I may yet
ſée her.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>My.</speaker>
                  <p>With a very-good will.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Da.</speaker>
                  <p>I will follow theſe, but I would not for any thing, that the
old man ſhould now ſée me.</p>
               </sp>
            </div>
         </div>
         <div n="5" type="act">
            <div n="1" type="scene">
               <pb facs="tcp:11757:38"/>
               <head>¶Act. 5. Scen. 1.</head>
               <argument>
                  <head>The Argument.</head>
                  <p>SIMO earneſtly deſireth to effect the marriage: Chremes on
the other ſide vtterly renounceth Pamphilus for his ſonne in law, bycauſe
hee hath a childe by Glycerie.</p>
               </argument>
               <stage> 
                  <list>
                     <item>
                        <hi>Chremes.</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>
                        <hi>Simo.</hi>
                     </item>
                  </list>
               </stage>
               <sp>
                  <p>
                     <seg rend="decorInit">W</seg>EL neighbour <hi>Simo,</hi> you haue now had tryall enough
and enough againe, of my loue and frendſhip towards you. I began to enter
into daunger far e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nough for you. Now at length ceaſe your entreating: for
whyle I bent my ſelfe to follow your fancie, I had well nigh caſt away my
doughter.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Si.</speaker>
                  <p>Nay rather (neighbour <hi>Chremes</hi>) I moſt inſtant<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly
requeſt and beſeech you, that you will now per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forme in déede, the
good turne that ere whyle you promi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed me on your woord.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Chr.</speaker>
                  <p>See how vnreaſonable you are, reſpecting your owne
deſire: ſo you may bring to paſſe what you would haue, you neither
regard a meane in courteſie, nor yet conſider what you requeſt at my
hands: for if you did, you would (now at laſt) geue ouer to ſurcharge mee
with your vnreaſonablenes.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Si.</speaker>
                  <p>With what vnreaſonablenes?</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Chr.</speaker>
                  <p>Why, &amp; do you aſke me with what? mary ſir, you
enforced me thus far, that to a looſe young man entang<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led <pb facs="tcp:11757:39"/> in
loue with a ſtrange harlot, and vtterly miſliking marriage, I ſhould giue
my daughter to wife, to be in daily diſcord, and vncertaine ſtate of
wedlock, to thend that with her trauail, and trooble, I might heale your
ſonnes diſeas. You obteyned this at my hands, and I went about it while
there was any boote: now it boots not, you muſt therefore beare with me. They
ſay, that ſame woman is frée born of this Cittie. She is deliue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red
of a childe. Séeke to vs no further.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Si.</speaker>
                  <p>I beſech you for Gods ſake, not to giue your minde to
credit thoſe, whoſe greateſt profit groweth by my ſonnes lewdeſt
liuing: All this, is but forged and framed for the nones, by reaſon of this
marriage: when the cauſe why they do this, is once taken away, Then they will
ceaſe.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Chr.</speaker>
                  <p>You are diceyued, for I my ſelfe ſaw her maide chiding and
brawling with <hi>Dauus.</hi>
                  </p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Si.</speaker>
                  <p>I graunt you.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Chr.</speaker>
                  <p>Nay but in right good earneſt, when as neither of them both
was aware of my being there.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Si.</speaker>
                  <p>I beléeue it well, and that they would do ſo,
<hi>Dauus</hi> fortolde me a prety while ſince, but I wot not how,
otherwiſe than I ment, I forgot to tell you ſomuch.</p>
               </sp>
            </div>
            <div n="2" type="scene">
               <head>¶Act. 5. Scen. 2.</head>
               <argument>
                  <head>The Argument.</head>
                  <p>SIMo hearing by Dauus, that there was one come, which
affir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med Glycerie to be free borne of Athens: in a great rage, cauſeth Dauus
to be had into priſon faſt bound. And here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in, Terence doth liuely
expreſſe the vſuall manner both of an angry father, and alſo of an
angrie maſter.</p>
               </argument>
               <stage>
                  <pb facs="tcp:11757:39"/> 
                  <list>
                     <item>
                        <hi>Dauus.</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>
                        <hi>Chremes.</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>
                        <hi>Simo.</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>
                        <hi>Dromo,</hi> the whipping Bedle.</item>
                  </list>
               </stage>
               <sp>
                  <p>
                     <seg rend="decorInit">A</seg>T my word, now (at length) ſet your hart at reſt:</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Chr.</speaker>
                  <p>
                     <note n="*" place="margin"> 
                        <stage>Thus Simo and Chremes do talk betwixt themſelues,
&amp; Dauus goeth on ſtill in his ſpeach.</stage>
                     </note>Sée where
<hi>Dauus</hi> is.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Si.</speaker>
                  <p>
                     <note n="*" place="margin"> 
                        <stage>Thus Simo and Chremes do talk betwixt themſelues,
&amp; Dauus goeth on ſtill in his ſpeach.</stage>
                     </note>Whence comes
he?</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Da.</speaker>
                  <p>What thorough my helpe, and yonder ſtranger.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Si.</speaker>
                  <p>
                     <note n="℈" place="margin"> 
                        <stage>He ſpeaketh out of Dauus hearing.</stage>
                     </note>What
knauery is that?</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Da.</speaker>
                  <p>I haue not ſéene a méeter man, a more
ſeaſona<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble comming, nor a fitter time.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Si.</speaker>
                  <p>
                     <note n="˘" place="margin"> 
                        <stage>And ſo heere likewiſe.</stage>
                     </note>Whome doth
this varlet prays thus?</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Da.</speaker>
                  <p>Now all is out of danger.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Si.</speaker>
                  <p>Why doo I linger to ſpeake to him?</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Da.</speaker>
                  <p>
                     <note n="℥" place="margin"> 
                        <stage>Now at laſt he eſpyeth Simo.</stage>
                     </note>My
maſter is here, what ſhall I do.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Si.</speaker>
                  <p>O, all haill to you honeſt man.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Da.</speaker>
                  <p>Now maſter, and maſter <hi>Chremes,</hi> all things be in
a redines within.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Si.</speaker>
                  <p>O it is trimly don of you.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Da.</speaker>
                  <p>Now ſend for him when you will.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Si.</speaker>
                  <p>Very well ſurely: that is the cauſe forſooth he is now
abſent: Nay but aunſwere me to this, what buſines haſt thou there?<note n="*" place="margin"> 
                        <stage>That is in Glyceries houſe</stage>
                     </note>
                  </p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Da.</speaker>
                  <p>Who, I?</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Si.</speaker>
                  <p>Yea.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Da.</speaker>
                  <p>What, I?</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Si.</speaker>
                  <p>Yea, you ſirra.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Da.</speaker>
                  <p>I went in but euen now.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Si.</speaker>
                  <p>As though I aſked how long ago it was.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Da.</speaker>
                  <p>Your ſonne and I went in together.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Si.</speaker>
                  <p>Why than, and is <hi>Pamphilus</hi> within? I am ſtill vext
vnhappy man that I am. Why thou hang<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man thou, didſt not thou tell me that
they are fallen at debate.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <pb facs="tcp:11757:40"/>
                  <speaker>Da.</speaker>
                  <p>So they are.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Si.</speaker>
                  <p>What makes he there than?</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Chr.</speaker>
                  <p>
                     <note n="*" place="margin"> 
                        <stage>This is ſpok<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>en in deriſion.</stage>
                     </note>What
think you that he is a dooing? he is ſure chiding with her.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Da.</speaker>
                  <p>Nay but maſter <hi>Chremes,</hi> you ſhall here me tel you
of a notable ſtrange matter: I wot not what olde man is come yonder euen now,
but to looke to, he is a ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtantiall and warie man: if you ſawe his
face, you would take him for a right honeſt man. In his counte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nance is ſad
grauitie, and his wordes do ſound of truth.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Si.</speaker>
                  <p>What tydings bringſt thou?</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Da.</speaker>
                  <p>Nothing forſooth but what I hard him ſay.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Si.</speaker>
                  <p>And what ſaith he, I pray you?</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Da.</speaker>
                  <p>Mary that he knoweth <hi>Glycerie</hi> to be a frée
born woman of <hi>Athens.</hi>
                  </p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Si.</speaker>
                  <p>
                     <note n="*" place="margin"> 
                        <stage>Simo calles for him that whips the
ſlaues.</stage>
                     </note>Hola howh, <hi>Dromo, Dromo.</hi>
                  </p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Dro.</speaker>
                  <p>What is the matter?</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Si.</speaker>
                  <p>Dromo.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Da.</speaker>
                  <p>Why, here me ſir.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Si.</speaker>
                  <p>If thou ſpeake one word more—<hi>Dromo.</hi>
                  </p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Da.</speaker>
                  <p>I beſech you here me.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Dro.</speaker>
                  <p>What would you haue ſir?</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Si.</speaker>
                  <p>Hoyſe vp this knaue on thy back, and cary him in as faſt
as thou canſt.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Dr.</speaker>
                  <p>Whom?</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Si.</speaker>
                  <p>Dauus.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Da.</speaker>
                  <p>Wherefore?</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Si.</speaker>
                  <p>Bycauſe I will haue it ſo, take him away I ſay.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Da.</speaker>
                  <p>What haue I don ſir?</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Si.</speaker>
                  <p>Away with him.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Da.</speaker>
                  <p>If you do finde that I told you any lye, kill me furth
right.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Si.</speaker>
                  <p>I will not here one word: I ſhall ſet thée in a
beate by and by, I warrant thée.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Da.</speaker>
                  <p>What, notwithſtanding I ſay nothing but Troth?</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <pb facs="tcp:11757:40"/>
                  <speaker>Si.</speaker>
                  <p>
                     <note n="˘" place="margin"> 
                        <stage>He ſpeakes to Dromo.</stage>
                     </note>Yea
neuertheleſſe, ſirra ſée thou that he be kept faſt fetterd:
and heareſt thou me? binde his hands and féete together, 
<note n="*" place="margin"> 
                        <stage>He turnes his ſpeach to Dauus and
Pamphilus.</stage>
                     </note>Now ſir go to: By God if I liue this day to an end,
I will teach thée and him both, what danger it is for the one of you to
beguile his maſter, and for the other to deceiue his father.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Chr.</speaker>
                  <p>Tuſh man, be not in ſo great a rage.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Si.</speaker>
                  <p>O <hi>Chremes,</hi> do you not pitie me, to ſée what
re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerend regard my ſonne hath towards me? and that I ſhould take ſomuch
trauaill for ſuch a ſonne? Well go to <hi>Pamphilus:</hi> Come out here
<hi>Pamphilus,</hi> Is there no ſhame in thée?</p>
               </sp>
            </div>
            <div n="3" type="scene">
               <head>Act. 5. Scen. 3.</head>
               <argument>
                  <head>The Argument.</head>
                  <p>SIMO ſharply rebuketh his ſonne: who confeſſing his
fault, ſubmit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teth himſelfe wholy vnto his fathers pleaſure, Chremes
en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deuoreth to appeaſe thextreame Rage of Simo.</p>
               </argument>
               <stage> 
                  <list>
                     <item>
                        <hi>Pamphilus.</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>
                        <hi>Simo.</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>
                        <hi>Chremes.</hi>
                     </item>
                  </list>
               </stage>
               <sp>
                  <p>
                     <seg rend="decorInit">W</seg>Ho calles me? O I am vndone, it is my father.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Si.</speaker>
                  <p>What ſaieſt thou? thou arrand—</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Chr.</speaker>
                  <p>Fie, go to the matter, and ceaſe your euill language.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Si.</speaker>
                  <p>Yea as though there could be any name to ill for this fellow.
Now ſirra, doo you ſay the ſame too? Is <hi>Glycerie</hi> frée
bone of this Citie?</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Pamph.</speaker>
                  <p>So it is reported.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <pb facs="tcp:11757:41"/>
                  <speaker>Si.</speaker>
                  <p>So it is reported? O wonderfull impudency, dooth he conſider
what he ſayth, thinke you? is he any thing ſorry for his miſdéede?
Nay but ſée, dooth his colour a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny whit change, or ſhew any ſigne
of ſhamefaſtnes? is it meete he ſhould be ſo vnruly, as that contrary
to the cuſtome of his cuntrimen, contrary to law, and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trary to the minde
of his father, hée doo labour to haue that ſame naughty packe, euen to
his vtter infamie and reproche?</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Pam.</speaker>
                  <p>Wo is me, forlorne man that I am.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Si.</speaker>
                  <p>O <hi>Pamphilus, Pamphilus,</hi> doſt thou now per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiue
that, and neuer before? Long ſince ywis, long ſince, when thou gaueſt thy
mynde ſo lewdly, as that by one meane or other thou muſt fulfill thy
luſt: lo, euen that very firſt day, had this bin truely ſayd of
thée. But what meane I? why do I vexe and diſquiet my ſelfe? why doo
I conſume my ſelfe with care? why doo I weare my old age, with ſorrowing
for his madnes? is it, that I ſhould ſuffer puniſhment for his faults?
Nay rather, let him haue her: and farewell hée: let him liue with her
and ſpare not.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Pam.</speaker>
                  <p>My good father.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Si.</speaker>
                  <p>What my good father? as who ſhould ſay, you haue any
néede of this father: why, you haue got you houſe, and wife, and
children, and all maugre your fathers hart. There be alſo thoſe brought,
which af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firme that ſame quean to be frée borne of this city: wel, you
ſhall haue the victory.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Pam.</speaker>
                  <p>Father, may I ſpeake a word or twoo?</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Si.</speaker>
                  <p>What wilt thou ſay to me?</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Chr.</speaker>
                  <p>O <hi>Simo,</hi> yet heare him.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Si.</speaker>
                  <p>I heare him <hi>Chremes?</hi> what ſhould I heare him?</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Chr.</speaker>
                  <p>Why man, yet geue him leaue to ſpeake.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Si.</speaker>
                  <p>Well go too, he may ſpeake, I let hm not.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Pamph.</speaker>
                  <p>Father, I confeſſe I loue that ſame woman: and if that
be an offence, I confeſſe that alſo. I ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mit <pb facs="tcp:11757:41"/> my ſelfe
into your hands father, lay vppon mee what charge you will: commaund me. Is it
your plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure I ſhould marry a wife? will you haue mée forgo this
woman? well, I will beare all as I may. Onely this I beſéech you, not
to beléeue that this old man is come hether by my appointment. Geue mee
leaue to cléere my ſelfe, and that I may bring the man here before
your face.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Si.</speaker>
                  <p>That thou maiſt bring him here?</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Pam.</speaker>
                  <p>Yea Father, ſuffer. mée.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Chr.</speaker>
                  <p>He craues but reaſon, geue him leaue.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Pam.</speaker>
                  <p>Let me obteine this much at your hands.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Si.</speaker>
                  <p>I am content. <hi>Chremes,</hi> I yéeld to any thing,
ſo that I finde not my ſelfe to be deceiued by this fel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Chr.</speaker>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Small puniſhment contents a father, for a great offence
in his ſonne.</hi>
                  </p>
               </sp>
            </div>
            <div n="4" type="scene">
               <head>¶Act. 5. Scen. 4.</head>
               <argument>
                  <head>The Argument.</head>
                  <p>In this ſcene Crito of Athens meeteth both with Simo and
Chre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mes, wherby the whole error of the comoedy is laid ope<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>: for here,
Glycerie is manifeſted to be the doughter of Chremes.</p>
               </argument>
               <stage> 
                  <list>
                     <item>
                        <hi>Crito,</hi> the ſtranger.</item>
                     <item>
                        <hi>Chremes.</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>
                        <hi>Simo.</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>
                        <hi>Pamphilus.</hi>
                     </item>
                  </list>
               </stage>
               <sp>
                  <p>
                     <seg rend="decorInit">C</seg>Eas to pray me, any one of theſe re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpects, ſhall
cauſe mée to doo it: as ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther for your owne ſake, or for that the
matter is truth, or in reſpect that I wiſh well to <hi>Glycerie.</hi>
                  </p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Chr.</speaker>
                  <p>What, is it <hi>Crito</hi> of <hi>Andros</hi> that I doo
ſée? Truly it is hée indéede. Welcome <hi>Cri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to:</hi> 
                     <pb facs="tcp:11757:42"/> what make you at Athens, being here ſuch a ſtran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger?</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Cr.</speaker>
                  <p>It is ſo fallen out. But is this <hi>Simo?</hi>
                  </p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Chr.</speaker>
                  <p>This ſame is hée.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Si.</speaker>
                  <p>What, is it for mée thou aſkeſt? why ſirra,
doſt thou ſay that <hi>Glycerie</hi> is frée borne of this
Citie?</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Cr.</speaker>
                  <p>Dooſt thou deny it?</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Si.</speaker>
                  <p>What, and art thou come ſo well prouided
in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>déede.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Cr.</speaker>
                  <p>Why ſo?</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Si.</speaker>
                  <p>Aſkeſt thou why? ſhalt thou doo this, and ſcape
vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>puniſhed? doſt thou toll here into thy ſnare, yong men voyd of
experience, and honeſtly brought vp? Art thou hée that
féedeſt furth their mindes with intyſing &amp; faire
promiſing?</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Cr.</speaker>
                  <p>Abyde, art thou well in thy wits?</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Si.</speaker>
                  <p>And doſt thou make marriages betwixt them and the harlots
that they are in loue withall?</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Pamph.</speaker>
                  <p>
                     <note place="margin"> 
                        <stage>This to him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe.</stage>
                     </note>Alas I am vndon, I
feare me the ſtranger will haue neuer a word to ſay.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Chr.</speaker>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Simo,</hi> if you knew this man thorowly, you would not
think ſo of him: this is an honeſt man.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Si.</speaker>
                  <p>May this fellow be an honeſt man? comes he this day ſo
iump in the very time of this marriage: and could he come neuer before now? why
<hi>Chremes,</hi> is this a man to bée beléeued?</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Pam.</speaker>
                  <p>Were I not afeard of my father, I could tell him that which
would ſatiſfie him in this point well y<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nough.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Si.</speaker>
                  <p>Hah fogging knaue.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Cr.</speaker>
                  <p>What?</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Chr.</speaker>
                  <p>O <hi>Crito</hi> beare with him, this is his faſhon.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Cr.</speaker>
                  <p>Nay let him conſider what he is: As for me, if hée
procéede to call mée at his pleaſure, hée ſhall heare
that, that ſhall bée litle to his lyking. Doo I let that ſame
marriage? or doo I ought at all paſſe <pb facs="tcp:11757:42"/> for it? 
<note n="*" place="margin"> 
                        <stage>He turnes his ſpeech to Simo.</stage>
                     </note>Thou
doſt not beare thy gréefe patiently: for as touching what I ſpake,
whether it bée true or falſe that you heard, may ſoone be
knowen.</p>
                  <p>
                     <note place="margin"> 
                        <stage>Here is recited the argument of the
Comoe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>die.</stage>
                     </note>A certaine man of Athens, a good while ſince,
ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fring Shipwracke, was caſt on ſhore at <hi>Andros,</hi> to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether
with that ſame <hi>Glycerie,</hi> as than a little childe. This man being
than in néede &amp; neceſſitie: by chaunce firſt arriued at the
houſe of <hi>Chryſis</hi> father.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Si.</speaker>
                  <p>Now he beginnes a fable.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Chr.</speaker>
                  <p>Suffer him to go on.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Cr.</speaker>
                  <p>What, euen ſo indéede? hée interrupts me.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Chr.</speaker>
                  <p>Go on with your tale.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Cr.</speaker>
                  <p>Moreouer, hée which receiued him into his houſe, was
my Coſin: there did I heare the man himſelfe ſay, that hée was of
Athens: and in that houſe he died.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Chr.</speaker>
                  <p>What was his name?</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Cr.</speaker>
                  <p>would you know his name ſo quickly? Pha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nia.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Chr.</speaker>
                  <p>Out alas to day.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Cr.</speaker>
                  <p>In good ſooth, I take it, his name was <hi>Phania.</hi> This
I am well aſſured of, that he ſaid he was a 
<note n="*" place="margin">Rhamnus was a famous village by
A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thens. And Rhamnuſius, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 word">
                           <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                        </gap> is a
ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of that village.</note>
                     <hi>Rhamnuſian.</hi>
                  </p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Chr.</speaker>
                  <p>O the King of heauen.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Cr.</speaker>
                  <p>Yea <hi>Chremes,</hi> there were than many other in
<hi>An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dros,</hi> which hard him ſay the ſame.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Chr.</speaker>
                  <p>Would to God it were no otherwiſe than I hope for. But tell
me this <hi>Crito,</hi> what ſaid he than as touching the girle? dyd
hée ſay that ſhée was his doughter?</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Cr.</speaker>
                  <p>No.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Chr.</speaker>
                  <p>Whoſe than?</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Cr.</speaker>
                  <p>His brothers doughter.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Chr.</speaker>
                  <p>Without dowt ſhe is myne.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Cr.</speaker>
                  <p>What ſay you?</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Si.</speaker>
                  <p>Nay what ſaieſt thou?</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <pb facs="tcp:11757:43"/>
                  <speaker>Pamph.</speaker>
                  <p>Liſten to this geare <hi>Pamphilus.</hi>
                  </p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Si.</speaker>
                  <p>What think you of this?</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Chr.</speaker>
                  <p>That ſame <hi>Phania</hi> was my brother.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Si.</speaker>
                  <p>I knew the man, and I wot wel he was your bro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Chr.</speaker>
                  <p>He flying hence, for feare of the warre, takes his way after
me into <hi>Aſia,</hi> and than he was afraid to leaue her here behind him.
Since which time, I neuer hard what became of him till now.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Pam.</speaker>
                  <p>I am well nigh beſide my ſelfe, my minde is ſo whelmed,
with feare, hope, Ioy, and with wond<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring at ſo great, and ſo ſodeyn good
hap.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Si.</speaker>
                  <p>Now in good faith, I am glad that by many proofs ſhe is
found to be your daughter.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Pamph.</speaker>
                  <p>Father I beléeue it well.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Chr.</speaker>
                  <p>But there remaines yet one doubt, which ſore troubles
me.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Pamph.</speaker>
                  <p>You are well worthie to be hated for your péeuiſh
preciſenes: you make a doubt where all is as plaine as a pack ſtaf.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Cr.</speaker>
                  <p>What is that you doubt of?</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Chr.</speaker>
                  <p>Her name falles not out right.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Cr.</speaker>
                  <p>Truly ſhe had an other name, when ſhe was a childe.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Chr.</speaker>
                  <p>What name? Cannot you remember it <hi>Crito?</hi>
                  </p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Cr.</speaker>
                  <p>I am calling it to minde.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Pamph.</speaker>
                  <p>Shall I ſuffer this mans memory to be a hinderance vnto my
wiſhed ioy, when as I may helpe my ſelfe in this point? no, I will not
ſuffer it. Lo you heare <hi>Cremes,</hi> the name you ſéeke for, is
<hi>Paſsibula.</hi>
                  </p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Cr.</speaker>
                  <p>That ſame is ſhe.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Chr.</speaker>
                  <p>Is it euen ſhe.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Pamp.</speaker>
                  <p>ſhe hath told it me her own ſelf a thouſa<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d times.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Si.</speaker>
                  <p>Chremes, I wene you beleue that we all reioyce at this.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Chr.</speaker>
                  <p>Yea ſo God me help, doo I beleue it.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <pb facs="tcp:11757:43"/>
                  <speaker>Pamph.</speaker>
                  <p>Father, what remaines now to be don?</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Si.</speaker>
                  <p>The matter it ſelfe hath reconciled me a good while
ſince.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Pamph.</speaker>
                  <p>O an excellent father. <hi>Chremes</hi> altereth no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing as
touching my wife, but that I may ſtill enioy her, as I haue don.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Chr.</speaker>
                  <p>Mary and good cauſe why. Vnleſſe your father ſay
otherwiſe.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Pamph.</speaker>
                  <p>Onely, as touching the dowry.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Si.</speaker>
                  <p>Yea marry, that.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Chr.</speaker>
                  <p>Pamphilus her dowry is fiue hundered pound.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Pamph.</speaker>
                  <p>I accept it.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Chr.</speaker>
                  <p>I will now hye me to my daughter, and you Crito, go with me:
for I beleue ſhe neuer knew me.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Si.</speaker>
                  <p>And why doo you not rather cauſe her to be brought hether to
you?</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Pamph.</speaker>
                  <p>You put vs well in minde, I will preſent<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly cauſe
<hi>Dauus</hi> to go about that matter.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Si.</speaker>
                  <p>He cannot.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Pamph.</speaker>
                  <p>How ſo?</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Si.</speaker>
                  <p>Mary bycauſe he hath a great matter of his own, which
toucheth him néerer.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Pamph.</speaker>
                  <p>What is that?</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Si.</speaker>
                  <p>He lieth bound in priſon.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Pamph.</speaker>
                  <p>Father, then is he wrongfully bound.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Si.</speaker>
                  <p>Not ſo, I commaunded it.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Pamph.</speaker>
                  <p>I beſeche you, command that he be let looſe.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Si.</speaker>
                  <p>Go to, be it ſo.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Pamph.</speaker>
                  <p>But make haſt than.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Si.</speaker>
                  <p>I go in ſtraight way.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Pamph.</speaker>
                  <p>O Bliſfull and happy day that this is.</p>
               </sp>
            </div>
            <div n="5" type="scene">
               <pb facs="tcp:11757:44"/>
               <head>¶Act. 5. Scen. 5.</head>
               <argument>
                  <head>The Argument.</head>
                  <p>PAMPHILVS declareth vnto Dauus, how that Glycerie is found to
be free borne of Athens, &amp; that he ſhall marry her Likewiſe Carinus
ſheweth vnto Pamphilus, that by his meanes, he alſo may obtaine Philumena
at Chremes hands. This Scene brings an other ſonne in law to Chremes: leaſt
that either Carinus ſhould depart away ſorowfull, or that Philumena
ſhould be left vnprouided for.</p>
               </argument>
               <stage> 
                  <list>
                     <item>
                        <hi>Carinus.</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>
                        <hi>Pamphilus.</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>
                        <hi>Dauus.</hi>
                     </item>
                  </list>
               </stage>
               <sp>
                  <p>
                     <hi>
                        <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg>
                     </hi> I am come furth, to ſée what
<hi>Pamphilus</hi> is a doing: but lo where he is.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Pamph.</speaker>
                  <p>Perhaps ſome body would think that I ſkant beleue this to
be true, but I will haue it to be true, as it is in déede. I ſuppoſe
that therefore the lyfe of the Gods is euerlaſting, bycauſe pleaſures do
proper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly belong vnto them: for mine own part, I am in heauen al redy, if ſo
be it, no griefe of minde doo intermingle with this ioy. But now what man
ſhould I moſt ſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cially deſire to méete withall, to whome I
might ſhew all that hath happened.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Car.</speaker>
                  <p>
                     <note place="margin"> 
                        <stage>This to him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe.</stage>
                     </note>What great ioy is
that?</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Pamph.</speaker>
                  <p>Lo, I ſee <hi>Dauus:</hi> There is no man liuing that I
would fayner haue: for I am ſure that he, of all other, will vnfainedly
reioyce at my ioy and gladneſſe.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Da.</speaker>
                  <p>whereabout here, is <hi>Pamphilus?</hi>
                  </p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Pamph.</speaker>
                  <p>Dauus.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Da.</speaker>
                  <p>What man is that?</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <pb facs="tcp:11757:44"/>
                  <speaker>Pamph.</speaker>
                  <p>It is I.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Da.</speaker>
                  <p>O my maſter <hi>Pamphilus.</hi>
                  </p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Pamph.</speaker>
                  <p>Thou wotſt not what hath hapned to me.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Da.</speaker>
                  <p>Very true, but I wot well what hath hapned to my ſelfe.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Pamph.</speaker>
                  <p>And ſo doo I too.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Da.</speaker>
                  <p>Yea it came to pas after the common courſe of the world,
that you knew of the euil that hapned to me, ſooner than I knew of the good
that hapned to you.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Pamph.</speaker>
                  <p>My ſwéete loue <hi>Glycerie,</hi> hath found out who
be her parents.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Da.</speaker>
                  <p>O happy chaunce.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Car.</speaker>
                  <p>
                     <note n="*" place="margin"> 
                        <stage>This he ſaith to himſelfe.</stage>
                     </note>What is
that?</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Pamph.</speaker>
                  <p>Her father is a very ſpeciall frend of ours.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Da.</speaker>
                  <p>Who is that?</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Pamph.</speaker>
                  <p>Chremes.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Da.</speaker>
                  <p>You ſay well.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Pamph.</speaker>
                  <p>Neither is there any let or tariance, but that I may marry her
out of hand.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Car.</speaker>
                  <p>
                     <note place="margin"> 
                        <stage>This is ſpoken out of the hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring of
Pam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>philus.</stage>
                     </note>What, doth he not dreame trow you, that which his
minde ran vpon being awake?</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Pamph.</speaker>
                  <p>Now moreouer <hi>Dauus,</hi> as touching the childe.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Da.</speaker>
                  <p>Tuſh let it alone, God doth ſpecially prouide for it aboue
all other children.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Car.</speaker>
                  <p>
                     <note place="margin"> 
                        <stage>Carinus is ouer heard by Pam<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>philus.</stage>
                     </note>I
am a made man, if this be true: I will ſure ſpeake with him.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Pamph.</speaker>
                  <p>What man is there? O <hi>Carinus,</hi> you come to me, euen as
well as heart can wiſh.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Car.</speaker>
                  <p>It is well.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Pamph.</speaker>
                  <p>What, haue you heard the matter?</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Car.</speaker>
                  <p>Yes euery whit: Go to, haue ſome reſpect of me, now in the
time of your proſperitie: I know that <hi>Chremes</hi> is now yours
altogether, and will doo all that you will haue him doo.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Pamph.</speaker>
                  <p>I wot it full well: but it would be too long for vs, to tarry
and looke for his comming furth:</p>
                  <p>
                     <pb facs="tcp:11757:45"/>Therefore follow me along this way: he is now
with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in with <hi>Glicerie. Dauus</hi> go thou thy way home: hye thée, go
for company to bring her away hence. Why doſt thou ſtand ſtill? why
goeſt thou not?</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Da.</speaker>
                  <p>I am going.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <p>
                     <note place="margin"> 
                        <stage>This ſeems not to he ſpoken by any of the
in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terloquutors, but by ſome o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther comming laſt on the
ſtage.</stage>
                     </note>Do not ſtay looking for their comming out: for
ſhée ſhall be betrothed within: and if any thing more remaine to be
don, it ſhall bée diſpatcht within alſo.</p>
                  <p>Now clap hands, and reioyce.</p>
               </sp>
            </div>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
            <argument>
               <p>Here is to be vnderſtood that as Pamphilus hath Glycerie to
wife: Euen ſo Carinus likewiſe hath Philumena, the other Dough<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter of
Chremes.</p>
            </argument>
            <pb facs="tcp:11757:45"/>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
