<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>The valiant Scot. By I.W. Gent</title>
            <author>I. W., gent.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1637</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 164 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 40 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-04">2011-04 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A14599</idno>
            <idno type="STC">STC 24910</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC S119334</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99854541</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99854541</idno>
            <idno type="VID">19967</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A14599)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 19967)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 1014:4)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>The valiant Scot. By I.W. Gent</title>
                  <author>I. W., gent.</author>
                  <author>Henry, the Minstrel, fl. 1470-1492. Wallace.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[80] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed by Thomas Harper for Iohn Waterson, and are to be sold at his shop in Pauls Church-yard, at the signe of the Crown,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1637.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>A tragedy based upon: Henry the Minstrel.  Actis and deidis of Schir William Wallace.</note>
                  <note>Partly in verse.</note>
                  <note>Signatures: A-K⁴.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the Henry E. Huntington Library and Art Gallery.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Wallace, William, --  Sir, d. 1305 --  Drama --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2009-03</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-04</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-06</date>
            <label>Scott Lepisto</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-06</date>
            <label>Scott Lepisto</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-09</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:19967:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:19967:1"/>
            <p>THE VALIANT SCOT.</p>
            <p>By <hi>J. W.</hi> Gent.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON,</hi> Printed by <hi>Thomas Harper</hi> for <hi>Iohn Waterſon,</hi> and are to be ſold at his ſhop in <hi>Pauls</hi> Church-yard, at the ſigne of the Crown. 1637.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="dedication">
            <pb facs="tcp:19967:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:19967:2"/>
            <head>To the right Honorable <hi>James,</hi> Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>queſſe <hi>Hamilton,</hi> Earle of <hi>Cambridge</hi> and <hi>Arran,</hi> Lord of <hi>Even, Enner<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dale</hi> and <hi>Arbroth,</hi> Maſter of the Horſe to his Majeſty, Steward of the Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour of <hi>Hampton</hi> Court, Gentleman of the Kings Bed-chamber, and Knight of the moſt noble Order of the Garter, <hi>and one of his Majeſties Privie</hi> Councell in both King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>domes.</head>
            <opener>
               <salute>Right Honorable,</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">M</seg>Ens actions have not their difference alwayes from the relation of their perſons, for hee that preſented his King with a diſh of water, having nothing elſe, made the gift ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceptable. I would uſe the application to my ſelfe,
<pb facs="tcp:19967:3"/>
having been one amongst your meaneſt followers in your Lordſhips practicall life of a Souldier: what I haue I beſtow upon you, and doe hope though it be clothed in the light dreſsing of a Play, it will not be denied your Lordſhips accep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tance ſince it contains the Character which Hi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtory hath left to Posterity of your own truly va<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liant Countriman: I moſt humbly beg pardon for my boldneſſe, and that I may continue knowne to your Lordſhip, at the becomming diſtance of your Honours truly honourer, and humblest ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vant.</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>
                  <hi>Your Lordſhips moſt humble ſervant and Souldier,</hi> William Bowyer.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div n="1" type="act">
            <pb facs="tcp:19967:3"/>
            <head>Actus I.</head>
            <stage>
               <hi>Enter</hi> Halſerigge, Thorne, Selby, <hi>and Sir</hi> Ieoffrey VViſeacres.</stage>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Tho.</speaker>
               <l>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">F</seg>Ellow colleagues, ſince it hath pleas'd our King,</l>
               <l>Renowned <hi>Edward,</hi> of his ſpeciall favour</l>
               <l>To ſpheare us in this height of eminence,</l>
               <l>And maks vs rulers over <hi>Scotland,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>Lets ſhew our ſelves worthy the dignities</l>
               <l>Conferred upon us.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Sel.</speaker>
               <l>That's not by lenity,</l>
               <l>For howſoere the armed hand of war</l>
               <l>Ha's made them ours, they are a Nation</l>
               <l>Haughty and full of ſpleen, and muſt be manag'd</l>
               <l>With ſtraighter reins and rougher bitts.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Tho.</speaker>
               <l>Ahlas,</l>
               <l>I finde them eaſie, tractable and mild,</l>
               <l>Autority may with a ſlender twine</l>
               <l>Hold in the ſtrongeſt head, then what needs tyranny,</l>
               <l>Vſe rein or bitt, by this all doubts are cleer'd,</l>
               <l>'Tis alwayes better to be lov'd then fear'd?</l>
               <l>And by your leave, Sir <hi>Thomas,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>We have good reaſon to defend our own.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Sel.</speaker>
               <l>You are as cleer of danger, and as free from foes.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Haſ.</speaker>
               <l>As he that holds a hungry wolfe by th' eares,</l>
               <l>
                  <pb facs="tcp:19967:4"/>The principles are true, truſt not thy wife</l>
               <l>With ſecrets, nor thy vaſſall with thy life,</l>
               <l>Sound example proves it.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Ieof.</speaker>
               <p>And private policy confirms it, I could urge rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon why, ſhew cauſe, wherefore, and ſpeake to purpoſe wherby, but my betters are in place, I know them to be pregnant, and a ready wit's worth all.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Sel.</speaker>
               <l>For our owne ſafeties then, and <hi>Englands</hi> honour,</l>
               <l>Let not us loſe what our King hardly wonne.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Haſ.</speaker>
               <l>To that effect called we this ſolemne meeting,</l>
               <l>To which we have ſummon'd divers: chiefly <hi>Wallace,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>Late Sheriffe of <hi>Ayre,</hi> which office tho the King</l>
               <l>Conferred on me, the haughty <hi>Scot</hi> thinks much</l>
               <l>To tender up, obſerve his inſolence.</l>
            </sp>
            <stage>
               <hi>Enter</hi> Wallace, <hi>and takes his place.</hi>
            </stage>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Sel.</speaker>
               <l>Preſumptuous Groom, this is a ſeat for Eagles,</l>
               <l>And not for Haggards.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>O. Wal.</speaker>
               <l>
                  <hi>Selbie</hi> 'tis a ſeat,</l>
               <l>I, and my Grandſires Grandſire have enjoyed</l>
               <l>And held with worſhip, and till <hi>Edwards</hi> hand</l>
               <l>Remove me from't, <hi>Wallace</hi> will ſtill poſſes't.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Sel.</speaker>
               <l>Proud <hi>Wallace</hi> dares not.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>O. Wal.</speaker>
               <l>
                  <hi>Selbie,</hi> both dares and doe,</l>
               <l>And muſt, and will, tho ſubject unto <hi>Edward,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>I'me <hi>Selbies</hi> equall both in birth and place:</l>
               <l>Tho in mine Office, <hi>Edward</hi> joyn'd you with me,</l>
               <l>He never made you ruler over me.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Haſ.</speaker>
               <l>You'le finde he did, reade that Commiſſion,</l>
               <l>And tell me then, if <hi>Selby</hi> or your ſelf,</l>
               <l>Be Sheriffe of <hi>Ayre.</hi>
               </l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>O. Wal.</speaker>
               <l>To what my King commands</l>
               <l>I humbly bend, reſigning on my knee</l>
               <l>Both Staffe and Office.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Sel.</speaker>
               <l>Which thus <hi>Selby</hi> breaks</l>
               <l>
                  <pb facs="tcp:19967:4"/>Over thy head, and now proud Sir acknowledge</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Selby</hi> your Ruler, and with your place reſigne</l>
               <l>Your Caſtle and your Lands.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>O. Wal.</speaker>
               <l>That's not inſerted in your Commiſſion.</l>
               <l>What the King has given I ſurrender,</l>
               <l>For my Lands they'r ſtill mine own,</l>
               <l>Were purchas'd with the ſweat of my deer Anceſtors,</l>
               <l>And ere I loſe a pole, a foot, I or the ſmalleſt turfe a ſilly</l>
               <l>Larke may build on, Ile loſe life.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Sel.</speaker>
               <l>At your own choice, either your lands or life,</l>
               <l>Or both.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>O. Wal.</speaker>
               <l>Or neither, royall <hi>Edwards</hi> mercy</l>
               <l>Sits above <hi>Selbies</hi> malice.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Sel.</speaker>
               <l>Surly Groom,</l>
               <l>Mercie's for ſubjects, by what Evidence,</l>
               <l>Charter or Service do you hold your Land?</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>O. Wal.</speaker>
               <l>
                  <hi>Selby</hi> by none, that title which I had</l>
               <l>I have given my ſonne, a boy of that proud temper,</l>
               <l>As ſhould he heare thy inſolent demand,</l>
               <l>Would pluck thee from thy ſeat, and lay thy head</l>
               <l>A ſatisfaction at his fathers feet,</l>
               <l>But heavens forbid it, <hi>Selby</hi> thus it ſtands,</l>
               <l>Thou haſt my Office, and my ſonne my Lands.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Sel.</speaker>
               <l>He muſt ſhew how he holds 'em.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>O. Wal.</speaker>
               <l>So he can,</l>
               <l>And <hi>Selby</hi> will ſhew evidence ſufficient,</l>
               <l>Mine, my deere Fathers, and my Grandſires ſword.</l>
               <l>He weares good evidence about him <hi>Selby,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>And will upon the leaſt occaſion</l>
               <l>Both ſhew and prove it lawfull.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Haſ.</speaker>
               <l>If the ſword be your beſt plea, y'ave but a naked title,</l>
               <l>And by our autority we here command</l>
               <l>You and your ſonne at our next generall meeting,</l>
               <l>To bring in your Surrender, or undergo</l>
               <l>The penalty of traytors.
<stage>Enter Sir John Graham.</stage>
               </l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <pb facs="tcp:19967:5"/>
               <speaker>Gra.</speaker>
               <l>Oh you the patrons of poore injur'd ſubjects,</l>
               <l>Do <hi>Graham</hi> juſtice, <hi>Selbies</hi> riotous ſonne</l>
               <l>Aſſiſted by a crew of diſſolutes!</l>
               <l>Has ſtole my onely daughter, and intends</l>
               <l>A violent Rape, or which more cuts my ſoule</l>
               <l>A forced marriage.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Sel.</speaker>
               <l>Inconſiderate foole,</l>
               <l>The boy affects her, and with my conſent</l>
               <l>Intends a lawfull marriage, 'tis a favour</l>
               <l>Her betters ſue for.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Gra.</speaker>
               <l>Oh let u'm hate, my bloud</l>
               <l>Shall never enter league nor hold alliance</l>
               <l>With him that hates my Country.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Sel.</speaker>
               <l>Reſt your thoughts,</l>
               <l>He has her, if he likes her he ſhall wed her,</l>
               <l>And <hi>Graham</hi> as a dowry ſhall enjoy</l>
               <l>Thy preſent ſtate, revenues, goods and lands,</l>
               <l>Fret out thy ſoule, he ſhall.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Gra.</speaker>
               <l>Shall?</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Sel.</speaker>
               <l>I, Sir ſhall,</l>
               <l>It's the higheſt favour conqueſt can afford,</l>
               <l>For a ſlave to joyn alliance with his Lord,</l>
               <l>And <hi>Wallace</hi> ſee preſent ſurrender made</l>
               <l>Or look for ſtorms.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Jeof.</speaker>
               <p>So ſay I too, and 'tis not the leaſt part of policy, neither.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>O. Wal.</speaker>
               <l>Will have my Lands.
<stage>Exeunt.</stage>
               </l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Gra.</speaker>
               <l>Inforce me give a dower.</l>
               <l>Miſery decre'd above compariſon.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>O. Wal.</speaker>
               <l>Complain unto the King.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Gra.</speaker>
               <l>The King alas.</l>
               <l>I have heard a ſtory how the ſubtle Fox</l>
               <l>Having ſtole a Lambe, the family of ſheep</l>
               <l>Drew a petition, and with full conſent</l>
               <l>Prefrr'd it to the Lion, he imploy'd</l>
               <l>
                  <pb facs="tcp:19967:5"/>'Bout earneſt and more ſerious buſineſſe,</l>
               <l>Appoints the Beare Commiſſioner, to take up</l>
               <l>This bloudy difference; the Beare impannels</l>
               <l>A partiall jury all of Wolves, they chooſe</l>
               <l>The Fox their Fore-man, they conſult and finde</l>
               <l>The ſheepiſh Nation guilty, and with generall breath,</l>
               <l>Caſt, judged, condemned, and ſentenc'd all to death.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>O. Wal.</speaker>
               <l>Men ſhould have ſouls.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Gra.</speaker>
               <l>But tyrants being no men,</l>
               <l>Have conſequently none; complaints in ſlaves,</l>
               <l>Are like to prayers made over dead mens graves,</l>
               <l>Nor heard, nor pitied, heaven ha's impos'd a curſe,</l>
               <l>Which ſuffrance in time may cure, co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>plaints make worſe.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>O. Wal.</speaker>
               <l>Then as it is lets bear't, win heaven to friend</l>
               <l>He that begins knows when and how to end.
<stage>Exeunt.</stage>
               </l>
            </sp>
            <stage>
               <hi>Enter yong</hi> Selby, <hi>and other gallants guarding</hi> Peggie.</stage>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Y. Sel.</speaker>
               <l>Maske her, come <hi>Peg</hi> hide your Scottiſh face.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Peg.</speaker>
               <p>Why ſhild I hayd my Scottis face, my Scottis face is as gude as yare Engliſh feace, 'tis a true Scotties feace.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Y. Sel.</speaker>
               <p>I know 'tis ſweet <hi>Peggy,</hi> and becauſe 'tis not a picture for every Painter to draw forth, let this curtaine be pind before it.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Peg.</speaker>
               <p>Hange yare flee-flaps, na Scottis woeman is a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſheamed a that luke, that the maſter painter abuife guifes her, whare mun I gang and now, fay, fay, fay, what loſſell am I that am hurrand thus till and fra with ſweards and wapins, whay mun backerd men gang fencing and flori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhing about me, am I yare may-game?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Y. Sel.</speaker>
               <l>No <hi>Peggy,</hi> th'art my priſoner, but here's thy jaile.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Peg.</speaker>
               <p>Are yee my jalor? what kin bin you to the hang<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man? ſenu you? whare's hee? wha is that foule loone a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mang you, that mun be my hangman?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Y. Sel.</speaker>
               <l>Here's no man here your hangman, or your jailor.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <pb facs="tcp:19967:6"/>
               <speaker>Peg.</speaker>
               <l>Wha then be you?</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Y. Sel.</speaker>
               <l>Your friends that hold you only in bonds of love.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Peg.</speaker>
               <p>I reckand mickle your luife, fay upon ſike luife, the awd fellon theef, luifand the true mans ſiller as you luifand me, I'de rather be a Scutchmans whore, then an Engliſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mans waife, and be dreave toth' Kirke with helters.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Y. Sel.</speaker>
               <p>Tell mee what proud Scot loves thee, what Scot dare touch thee now th'art <hi>Selbies?</hi>
               </p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Peg.</speaker>
               <l>Hang thee, hang thee foule meazel'd lowne,</l>
               <l>What Scuttiſhman darres guiff my luif underſtood</l>
               <l>My caſe, on Gads deare earth yow ſud no farder gange</l>
               <l>As butchers kie toth the grund he ſud yow bange.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>2 <hi>Gall.</hi>
               </speaker>
               <l>All mildneſſe is in vain, take ſome rough courſe.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Y. Sel.</speaker>
               <l>Toth' Church, away, Ile marry her there by force.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>1 <hi>Gall.</hi>
               </speaker>
               <l>Away with her.</l>
            </sp>
            <stage>
               <hi>Enter</hi> Wallace, Comming, <hi>and</hi> Mentith, Peggy <hi>runs to</hi> Wallace.</stage>
            <sp>
               <speaker>2 <hi>Gall.</hi>
               </speaker>
               <l>Yonders <hi>Wallace,</hi> and's true.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Y. Sel.</speaker>
               <l>The Devill and's dambe bee't, budge not.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Peg.</speaker>
               <p>O my luife theſe Sotherne Carles mickle wrang 'gainſt mee warcke, and now wad force mee gang untill the Kirke, and marry <hi>Selby, Wallace</hi> my <hi>Io</hi> not I.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Y. Sel.</speaker>
               <l>Vnhand that beauteous prize, proud ſlave, 'tis mine.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Wall.</speaker>
               <l>Slave! th'art a villain <hi>Selby.</hi>
               </l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Y. Sel.</speaker>
               <l>Are ye ſo brave.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Wall.</speaker>
               <l>Look to my wench.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Com. Ment.</speaker>
               <l>Kill 'em.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Wall.</speaker>
               <l>We are no Stares to die by dozens.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Y. Sel.</speaker>
               <p>Back, the quarrels mine, and if one ſingle Scot proud'ſt of your ſwarme dares anſwer me, ſtep forth.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Wall.</speaker>
               <l>Your firſt man I Sir.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Y. Sel.</speaker>
               <l>Harke Gentlemen, let not ſo ſleight a ſhowre,</l>
               <l>Which yet lies hid and wrapt in one poore cloud,</l>
               <l>
                  <pb facs="tcp:19967:6"/>Be by rough winds (raiz'd up by you) diſperſ'd</l>
               <l>Into a generall ſtorme, to many eyes</l>
               <l>Of <hi>Scots</hi> and <hi>Engliſh</hi> ſhoots, quick lightning forth</l>
               <l>Already, but your abſence will allay</l>
               <l>Thoſe fires which elſe muſt kindle, get then away,</l>
               <l>Take ſhelter in yon taverne.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Omnes.</speaker>
               <l>Agreed.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Wall.</speaker>
               <l>Look to my <hi>Peggie.</hi>
                  <stage>Exeunt.</stage>
               </l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Y. Sel.</speaker>
               <p>Guard my love, hee and I will onely exchange cold words.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Wall.</speaker>
               <l>Now Sir, your cold words.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Y. Sel.</speaker>
               <l>This Scotch Laſle I love.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Wall.</speaker>
               <l>Is that all?</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Y. Sel.</speaker>
               <l>Yes.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Wall.</speaker>
               <l>I love her too, can any words more cold,</l>
               <l>Strike to your heart?</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Y. Sel.</speaker>
               <l>Is ſhe your wife?</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Wall.</speaker>
               <l>No.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Y. Sel.</speaker>
               <l>She's your whore.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Wall.</speaker>
               <l>Vmh, neither.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Y. Sel.</speaker>
               <l>She gangs with me then.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Wall.</speaker>
               <l>But the dew lekens not whither,</l>
               <l>If you can win her, weare her, ſhe's wholly mine.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Y. Sel.</speaker>
               <l>She is?</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Wall.</speaker>
               <l>She is, our Laſſe are not Engliſh common,</l>
               <l>I'me right Scotch bred, till death ſtick to a woman.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Y. Sel.</speaker>
               <l>And to the death thou ſhalt, no more but this,</l>
               <l>Thou ſhalt beare from me <hi>Scot.</hi>
               </l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Wall.</speaker>
               <l>When?</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Y. Sel.</speaker>
               <l>Inſtantly.</l>
               <l>Make time Sir, of your weapon, time, and place.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Wall.</speaker>
               <l>This Whinyard.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Y. Sel.</speaker>
               <l>This.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Wall.</speaker>
               <l>Our ſwords do now agree, and of one length and ſcantling.</l>
               <l>
                  <pb facs="tcp:19967:7"/>Why ſhould not we, if we muſt Surgeons</l>
               <l>Have to morrow or anon</l>
               <l>If not as good now, 'tis the Engliſh faſhion</l>
               <l>To ſwagger it out, and then drink and then fight</l>
               <l>And kill in cold bloud having ſlept ſound all night,</l>
               <l>And oftentimes all gaſh'd, the ſeconds fall,</l>
               <l>When home in whole skins come the principall.</l>
               <l>So about words, the Lawyer wrangling ſtands,</l>
               <l>And loſes in mean time his clients lands.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Y. Sel.</speaker>
               <l>Do'ſt teach me fencing too in thy own ſchool?</l>
               <l>I'le beat thee or be beaten, one draws ſhort breath.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Wall.</speaker>
               <l>I feele no ſickneſſe.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Y. Sel.</speaker>
               <l>Yet th'art neere thy death.
<stage>Fight.</stage>
               </l>
            </sp>
            <stage>
               <hi>Enter</hi> 2 Gallants, Coming, Mentith. Wallace <hi>loſes his weapon.</hi>
            </stage>
            <sp>
               <speaker>1 <hi>Gal.</hi>
               </speaker>
               <l>At it ſo hotly.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>2 <hi>Gal.</hi>
               </speaker>
               <l>Kill him, 'tis faire.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Y. Sel.</speaker>
               <l>Inglorious conqueſt, for King <hi>Edwards</hi> crown,</l>
               <l>I'de trample on no enemy were hee down.</l>
               <l>There—if th'art well, part.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Wal.</speaker>
               <l>I'le die, or in thy heart bloud waſh this infamy.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Y. Sel.</speaker>
               <l>Mercy on my ſoule. <stage>Dies.</stage>
               </l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Com.</speaker>
               <l>He's ſlain.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Men.</speaker>
               <l>Away.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Wal.</speaker>
               <l>Shift for your ſelves, 'twill prove a ſtormy day.</l>
            </sp>
            <stage>Exeunt.</stage>
            <stage>A cry within murder, murder.</stage>
            <stage>
               <hi>Enter old</hi> Selby, Thorn, Haſlerig, Peggy, <hi>and the two Gallants.</hi>
            </stage>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Omn.</speaker>
               <l>Search, call for Surgeons, follow the murderer.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Peg.</speaker>
               <l>Wa is me, ligs my luife on the cawd ground,</l>
               <l>Let me come kiſſe his froſty mouth.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <pb facs="tcp:19967:7"/>
               <speaker>O. Sel.</speaker>
               <l>What <hi>Scot</hi> iſt?</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Omn.</speaker>
               <l>Oh, 'tis yong <hi>Selby!</hi>
               </l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>O. Sel.</speaker>
               <l>Ha'my ſonne, who ſlue him?</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>1 <hi>Gal.</hi>
               </speaker>
               <l>That fatall hand of <hi>Wallace.</hi>
               </l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>O. Sel.</speaker>
               <l>Follow the villain.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Peg.</speaker>
               <l>Ize jocund and weel now.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Has.</speaker>
               <l>Lay upon her faſt hold.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Peg.</speaker>
               <l>Hang me I reck not.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Tho.</speaker>
               <l>Away with her to priſon.
<stage>Exeunt.</stage>
               </l>
            </sp>
            <stage>
               <hi>Enter King</hi> Edward, Elinor, Percy, Beaumont, Grimsby, Prince, Sebaſtian, Bruce.</stage>
            <sp>
               <speaker>King.</speaker>
               <l>Not all the bloud and treaſure we have ſpent</l>
               <l>Like zealous prodigals in <hi>Paleſtine,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>Goes half ſo neer our heart, as that proud <hi>France,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>Knowing our merit ſhould bar us of our due.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Per.</speaker>
               <l>
                  <hi>France</hi> dares not.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>K.</speaker>
               <l>Yet he does.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Per.</speaker>
               <l>'Twas not demanded.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Gri.</speaker>
               <l>How, not demanded? thinks the bold Lord <hi>Percy,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>That <hi>Grimſby</hi> dares not (lawfully employ'd) demand.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Per.</speaker>
               <l>But not command.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Grim.</speaker>
               <l>Yes command, <hi>Percy.</hi>
               </l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Per.</speaker>
               <l>
                  <hi>Grimſby,</hi> thou canſt do well in Gariſon.</l>
               <l>Weare ſhamoys for a grace, project for bloud,</l>
               <l>Make eight dayes to one week, turn executioner,</l>
               <l>And hangman like ſend fifty in one morning,</l>
               <l>To feed the Crows, and live upon dead pay.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Grim.</speaker>
               <l>He's a man worſe then dead that—</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Per.</speaker>
               <l>Stop thy throat or—</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Grim.</speaker>
               <l>VVhat?</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Per.</speaker>
               <l>Ile cut it.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Grim.</speaker>
               <l>Cut throat.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Per.</speaker>
               <l>'Tis a trade,</l>
               <l>
                  <pb facs="tcp:19967:8"/>By which few proſper, and yet thou art made.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Grim.</speaker>
               <l>A man as good as—</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Per.</speaker>
               <l>A hangman.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Grim.</speaker>
               <l>A foule blot</l>
               <l>Lies in your throat.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Per.</speaker>
               <l>Thy foul-mouth, waſh it <hi>Scot.</hi>
               </l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Grim.</speaker>
               <l>In <hi>Percies</hi> bloud Il'e waſh't.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>K.</speaker>
               <l>
                  <hi>Grimſby</hi> you leane</l>
               <l>To hard upon our ſufferance, and noble <hi>Percy.</hi>
               </l>
               <l>Our honor'd ſecond in all inward combats,</l>
               <l>Thou haſt too many worthy parts of man,</l>
               <l>To throw thy ſelf on this unequall ha<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>zard,</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Grimſby</hi> thou ſtandſt ſo much degreed below him,</l>
               <l>Both in deſcent and eminent qualitie,</l>
               <l>The many favours we have grac'd thee with,</l>
               <l>Bluſh to have been conferr'd upon a man</l>
               <l>No better temper'd.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Bruce.</speaker>
               <l>May it pleaſe my Soveraigne</l>
               <l>Confirme his grant touching—</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>K.</speaker>
               <l>The Crown of <hi>Scotland,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>Save other time, <hi>Grimſby</hi> th'aſt raiſed</l>
               <l>A ſtorm which ſhowers of bloud can hardly lay.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Grim.</speaker>
               <l>Dread Liege,</l>
               <l>If all the youthfull bloud that I have ſpent,</l>
               <l>And wealthy honors that my ſword hath wonne</l>
               <l>Waving the Chriſtian Standard in the face</l>
               <l>Of the proud Pagan, in the holy Land,</l>
               <l>Merit the name of hangman, <hi>Grimsby</hi> caſts</l>
               <l>Them and himſelfe at royall <hi>Edwards</hi> feet,</l>
               <l>And like an out worn ſouldier, humbly begs,</l>
               <l>No penſion (but look <hi>Percy</hi>) nor yet office</l>
               <l>But leave to leave the Court, and rich in ſtars</l>
               <l>To loſe more bloud, or win more worth in wars.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>K.</speaker>
               <l>VVe will not loſe thee <hi>Grimſby,</hi> valiant <hi>Percy,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>If love in us, or loyaltie in you,</l>
               <l>Have any power.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <pb facs="tcp:19967:8"/>
               <speaker>Per.</speaker>
               <l>My Soveraignes pleaſure ſits above my private paſſions.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>K.</speaker>
               <l>Then joyn hands,</l>
               <l>Our ſubjects both the native of two Lands.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Per.</speaker>
               <l>Friends <hi>Grimſby.</hi>
               </l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Grim.</speaker>
               <l>Friends in ſhew,</l>
               <l>But in my breſt bloudy revenge lies ambuſh't.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Bruce.</speaker>
               <l>Gracious Liege.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>K.</speaker>
               <l>Th'art no Muſician, <hi>Bruce,</hi> thou keep'ſt falſe time,</l>
               <l>We ſtrike a bloudy <hi>lachrymae</hi> to <hi>France,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>And thou keep'ſt time to a Scotch ligge to armes.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Elenor.</speaker>
               <l>
                  <hi>Edward</hi> will be more kind to Chriſtians.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>K.</speaker>
               <l>Let Chriſtians be more honeſt then to <hi>Edward,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>In expedition of this holy warre,</l>
               <l>When <hi>France</hi> in perſon was enjoyn'd to march,</l>
               <l>To work his ſafetie we engag'd our own,</l>
               <l>Caſheer'd his fainting ſouldiers, and on promiſe,</l>
               <l>Of ſo much gold at our return, ſuppli'd</l>
               <l>The French deſignes our ſelfe, and is our love,</l>
               <l>And loſſe of bloud, halfe which at leaſt had drop'd</l>
               <l>Out of <hi>French</hi> boſomes, quittant with owe none,</l>
               <l>Pillage and play the free-butter for more,</l>
               <l>The news.</l>
            </sp>
            <stage>Enter Haſlerig.</stage>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Has.</speaker>
               <l>Dread Soveraigne, <hi>Scotland</hi> is infected</l>
               <l>With a moſt dangerous ſurfet, it breaks out</l>
               <l>In ſtrong rebellion.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Edw.</speaker>
               <l>This is your Kingdome <hi>Bruce.</hi>
               </l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Bru.</speaker>
               <l>I have no hand in't tho.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>K.</speaker>
               <l>Shouldſt have no head, did we but think it,</l>
               <l>VVhoſe the chief?</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Has.</speaker>
               <l>One <hi>Wallace,</hi> a fellow meanly bred,</l>
               <l>But ſpirited above beleefe.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>K.</speaker>
               <l>Some needy borderer.</l>
               <l>How is our boſome parted, is their power</l>
               <l>
                  <pb facs="tcp:19967:9"/>Of any ſtrength? <hi>Bruce,</hi> leavy powers for <hi>France;</hi>
               </l>
               <l>If we but thought thee touch'd in't, warlike <hi>Percy,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Beaumont</hi> and <hi>Sebaſtian</hi> fetch him in</l>
               <l>Or with a ſecond and more fatall conqueſt</l>
               <l>Ruine that ſtubborne Nation.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Ellin.</speaker>
               <l>Gracious <hi>Edward,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>Tho war ha's made them ſubjects, heaven defend</l>
               <l>Subjects ſhould make 'em vaſſals.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>K.</speaker>
               <l>We conceit you,</l>
               <l>If any officer of ours tranſgreſſe</l>
               <l>Our will, or go beyond his bounds prefix't</l>
               <l>VVee'l have his head, he our high worth depraves,</l>
               <l>That our free ſubjects ſeek to make his ſlaves.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Has.</speaker>
               <l>We do not.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>K.</speaker>
               <l>See we finde it not.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Ell.</speaker>
               <l>Let <hi>Ellianor</hi> win ſo much favour as to march along</l>
               <l>Tho conquer'd, 'las we are neighbours of one clime,</l>
               <l>And live like them ſubject to change and time.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Grim.</speaker>
               <l>Royall <hi>Edward,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>Though <hi>Wallace</hi> and ſome ſpleenfull diſſolutes</l>
               <l>Wrong'd with the yoke of bondage caſt it off.</l>
               <l>Let not the whole Land ſuffer.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>K.</speaker>
               <l>Nor do we wiſh it <hi>Grimsby,</hi> ſhould the fates</l>
               <l>But turn the wheele we might with them change ſtates,</l>
               <l>Be <hi>Scotlands</hi> ſubjects, let but Rebellion kneele,</l>
               <l>Wee'l weare ſoft mercy, and caſt off rough ſteele.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Grim.</speaker>
               <p>I'le undertake it.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>K.</speaker>
               <l>Let meſſengers be ſent,</l>
               <l>To queſtion the proud Rebell, and if <hi>Grimsby</hi>
               </l>
               <l>Faile in his plot, <hi>Northumberland</hi> and <hi>Clifford</hi>
               </l>
               <l>Shall ſecond him in armes, ſo ſlight a fo</l>
               <l>Muſt not detain us from our <hi>French</hi> deſignes,</l>
               <l>Our Queen ha's all our breſt, and tho we might</l>
               <l>Iuſtly perhaps confine your liberty,</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Bruce,</hi> we inlarge it, giving you command</l>
               <l>
                  <pb facs="tcp:19967:9"/>In our <hi>French</hi> wars, obſerve him neerly Lords,</l>
               <l>I have read this maxime in ſtate policie.</l>
               <l>Be ſure to weare thy danger in thy eye,</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>France</hi> lights a Comet, <hi>Scotland</hi> a blazing Star,</l>
               <l>Both ſeeke for bloud, wee'le quench um both with war.</l>
            </sp>
            <stage>Exeunt.</stage>
            <stage>
               <hi>Enter yong</hi> Wallace, Coming, Mentith.</stage>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Com.</speaker>
               <l>Prethee good <hi>Wallace.</hi>
               </l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Y. Wal.</speaker>
               <l>Ill betides his ſoule,</l>
               <l>That ſpeaks of goodneſſe, thinks or meditates</l>
               <l>Of any goodneſſe more then how to free</l>
               <l>Impriſon'd <hi>Peg.</hi>
               </l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Men.</speaker>
               <l>But heare me.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Wal. Laverek</speaker>
               <l>Caſtle weares but a ſlender bolt of brick.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Com.</speaker>
               <l>Turn'd mad!</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Wal.</speaker>
               <l>And ſay the moat be fifty fathomes deep,</l>
               <l>Fiftie times fiftie, ſay it reach through to hell,</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Wallace</hi> will ſwim't.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Com.</speaker>
               <l>Swim't, yes ſo wilt thruſt an oxe into an Eg-ſhell,</l>
               <l>And roſt it by Moon-ſhine, but why ſhould <hi>Wallace?</hi>
               </l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Wal.</speaker>
               <l>Why ſhould proud <hi>Selby,</hi> though his forward ſon</l>
               <l>Were juſtly ſlain, impriſon <hi>Peg?</hi>
               </l>
               <l>Poor Lambe ſhe is no murtherer.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Com.</speaker>
               <l>In my conſcience ſhe ne're drew weapon</l>
               <l>In anger in her life.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Men.</speaker>
               <l>Not at ſharp I think, but by your leave 'tis thought,</l>
               <l>She ha's practis'd in private; put <hi>Wallace</hi> to foil, and made</l>
               <l>Him lie at his hanging ward many a time and oft.</l>
            </sp>
            <stage>
               <hi>Enter Old</hi> Wallace, <hi>and</hi> Graham.</stage>
            <sp>
               <speaker>O. Wal.</speaker>
               <l>Wher's my ſonne?</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Wal.</speaker>
               <l>With <hi>Peggie,</hi> father, manacles of griefe,</l>
               <l>Hang heavy on my ſences.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <pb facs="tcp:19967:10"/>
               <speaker>O. Wal.</speaker>
               <l>Shake 'em off.</l>
               <l>Shew thy ſelf worthy him that thou call'ſt father,</l>
               <l>Or <hi>Peggie</hi> dies.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Wal.</speaker>
               <l>What thunderclap was that?</l>
               <l>Able to waken death or ſhake the ſhrowd</l>
               <l>From off a dead mans ſhoulders, <hi>Peggie</hi> dies,</l>
               <l>Should thunder ſpeak it, <hi>Wallace</hi> would ſweare it lies,</l>
               <l>Who ſpake that, fatall <hi>Nuntio?</hi>
               </l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>O. Wal.</speaker>
               <l>His breath.</l>
               <l>That gave thee being, <hi>Haſlerigs</hi> return'd.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Wal.</speaker>
               <l>Whence, from the Devill?</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>O. W.</speaker>
               <l>From <hi>England,</hi> and this inſtant</l>
               <l>But thou com'ſt in, and yeeld thy ſelf, her life</l>
               <l>Diſſolves to aire.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Wal.</speaker>
               <l>The charitable Angels waft her to heaven.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Gra.</speaker>
               <l>Reſolve you then to loſe her?</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Wal.</speaker>
               <l>How ſhall we ſave her, ſingly as I am</l>
               <l>I will oppoſe me 'gainſt the town of <hi>Lavercke,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>Swim the vaſt moat, and with my truſtie ſword</l>
               <l>Hew down the Caſtle-gates, diſhinge the doores,</l>
               <l>File off her irons, and through a wall of ſteele</l>
               <l>Attempt her reſcue.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>O. W.</speaker>
               <l>'Tis impoſſible.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Wal.</speaker>
               <l>Impoſſible, what's the news from <hi>Englands?</hi>
               </l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>O. W.</speaker>
               <l>
                  <hi>Grimsby</hi> the fire-brand of his Country</l>
               <l>Comes to inſnare you, on the heele of him</l>
               <l>Treads a huge army led on by the Queen,</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Percy</hi> and <hi>Clifford.</hi>
               </l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Om.</speaker>
               <l>Torture and death itſelf cannot divide us.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Wal.</speaker>
               <l>Sir <hi>John Graham,</hi> you ſhall be the engine</l>
               <l>Our policie muſt work with, ſtreight give out</l>
               <l>That hearing of the Engliſh expedition,</l>
               <l>Our faction is diſſolv'd.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Gra.</speaker>
               <l>Whats's this to <hi>Peggies</hi> reſcue?</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Wal.</speaker>
               <l>Much, this rumour</l>
               <l>
                  <pb facs="tcp:19967:10"/>Blown through the Land will ſtay the Engliſh forces,</l>
               <l>And give us time and means to ſtrengthen ours,</l>
               <l>That once in act, repair to <hi>Haſterig,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Selby</hi> and <hi>Thorn,</hi> urge <hi>Peggies</hi> innocence,</l>
               <l>And for her freedom and your own make faith,</l>
               <l>To yeeld me priſoner, 'twill be no doubt excepted,</l>
               <l>Your ſelf once pardon'd, and your daughter free.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Gra.</speaker>
               <l>What reſts for <hi>Wallace?</hi>
               </l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Wal.</speaker>
               <l>Proſper'd deſtinie,</l>
               <l>If the great cauſe we undertake be good,</l>
               <l>'Twill thrive, if not, be't waſht in <hi>VVallace</hi> bloud.</l>
            </sp>
            <stage>Exeunt.</stage>
            <stage>
               <hi>Enter</hi> Haſlerig, Thorne, Selby, <hi>Sir</hi> Ieffrey.</stage>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Has.</speaker>
               <l>Is it by generall Proclamation voic'd</l>
               <l>That but proud <hi>VVallace</hi> yeild, <hi>Peg Graham</hi> dies,</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Sir Ief.</speaker>
               <l>The Cryers are all hoarſe with balling of it.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Has.</speaker>
               <l>T'is time for providence to ſtirre the King,</l>
               <l>(I know not upon what complaints) pretends</l>
               <l>This rank Rebellion rather, took his root</l>
               <l>From wrongs in us, then treacheries in <hi>VVallace.</hi>
               </l>
               <l>And ſends his forces rather to examine</l>
               <l>And queſtion our demeanours, then their treaſons.</l>
               <l>We muſt prevent it, how think you, Sir <hi>Jeffery?</hi>
               </l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Sir Jef.</speaker>
               <l>Troth even as you think, policie muſt prevent it.</l>
            </sp>
            <stage>Enter Meſſenger.</stage>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Meſ.</speaker>
               <l>Sir <hi>John Graham</hi> craves conference with the Co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>miſſioners.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Has.</speaker>
               <l>Admit him.</l>
               <stage>
                  <hi>Enter Sir</hi> Iohn Graham.</stage>
               <l>A man, me thinks, of your experience,</l>
               <l>
                  <pb facs="tcp:19967:11"/>Reſpect and education ſhould not linke</l>
               <l>Your ſelf in ſuch a chain of counterfeits.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Io. Gra.</speaker>
               <l>Nor have I Lords, but for your beſt advantage,</l>
               <l>And <hi>Englands</hi> good, traitors and dottrels,</l>
               <l>Are ſold for all alike, he that will take them</l>
               <l>Muſt ſeem to do as they do, imitate</l>
               <l>Their vicious actions, ſtrive to take upon him</l>
               <l>Their idle follies, joyn companies, and drive</l>
               <l>Them into a net ſuſpectleſſe.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Haſ.</speaker>
               <l>So did not <hi>Graham.</hi>
               </l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Io. Gra.</speaker>
               <l>Speak not before your knowledge, you detain</l>
               <l>My onely daughter priſoner, will <hi>Selby</hi>
               </l>
               <l>And his colleagues free her and pardon me,</l>
               <l>If I diſſolve the brood of traitors</l>
               <l>And give up <hi>Wallace</hi> in bands?</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Sel.</speaker>
               <l>Let's daughter be produc'd.</l>
               <stage>
                  <hi>Enter</hi> Peggie.</stage>
               <l>And th' execution for awhile deferr'd,</l>
               <l>Though in her cauſe <hi>Selby</hi> ha's loſt a ſonne</l>
               <l>And with him all content, ſo deer I tender</l>
               <l>The peace of <hi>Scotland</hi> and my Soveraignes good,</l>
               <l>As give the traitour to the hand of Law</l>
               <l>And with her life take thine.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Ieff.</speaker>
               <l>Good policie.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Peg.</speaker>
               <l>Aye trowe, ye mean not <hi>Wallas</hi> his devoire,</l>
               <l>And dowty valour merits mare repute nor</l>
               <l>Sike fawe language.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Gra.</speaker>
               <l>A fowle traitour,</l>
               <l>I have converſt with <hi>Wallace,</hi> thrown my ſelfe</l>
               <l>Into his boſome, mingled thoughts with him,</l>
               <l>And find him neither worthy of thy love,</l>
               <l>Nor my alliance.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Peg.</speaker>
               <l>Fay, ſa, not ſea, my bunny <hi>Wllace</hi> luifes me.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <pb facs="tcp:19967:11"/>
               <speaker>Gra.</speaker>
               <l>Yes as a Politician does a knave</l>
               <l>For his own ends, hearing thy death proclaim'd,</l>
               <l>But he come in, I told him on't, he ſmiled.</l>
               <l>I urg'd thy love and conſtancy, ſtill he ſmil'd,</l>
               <l>And to confirm't he baſely ha's cut off</l>
               <l>All his aſſociates, and given up himſelfe</l>
               <l>Wholly to me.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Peg.</speaker>
               <l>Hawd rherefor cherritie, and wad yee give</l>
               <l>Him to his faes, that gave</l>
               <l>His blood to your protect?</l>
            </sp>
            <stage>
               <hi>Enter</hi> Wallace, <hi>with a guard bound.</hi>
            </stage>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Gra.</speaker>
               <l>I will and have,</l>
               <l>For thine enlargement and my own I have,</l>
               <l>No more, here comes the Rebell.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Wal.</speaker>
               <l>Traiterous man,</l>
               <l>Is this thy love? theſe thy deep promiſes?</l>
               <l>Art thou their <hi>Aspies?</hi> See <hi>Selby</hi> here's the hand</l>
               <l>Cleft thy ſonnes heart.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Sel.</speaker>
               <l>For which baſe villain I'le ſee thee hang'd.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Wal.</speaker>
               <l>Thou knoweſt not thy own eyes,</l>
               <l>May feed the Crows aſſoon as mine, Toads and Snakes</l>
               <l>May dig their lodgings in thy breſt,</l>
               <l>And Devils make faggots of thy bones firſt,</l>
               <l>But my ſentence.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Sel.</speaker>
               <l>Here, <hi>Graham,</hi> for thy ſervice,</l>
               <l>We enlarge thy beauteous daughter.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Wall.</speaker>
               <l>A milde exchange,</l>
               <l>Angels approve it.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Haſ.</speaker>
               <l>Next, thee to thy Lands and Offices we reſtore.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Peg.</speaker>
               <l>And what for <hi>Wallace?</hi>
               </l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Sel.</speaker>
               <l>Race him from your thoughts.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Peg.</speaker>
               <l>Rac'd byn his name furth the</l>
               <l>Whayte buke of life that ſpeaks it.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <pb facs="tcp:19967:12"/>
               <speaker>Sir Jeff.</speaker>
               <l>Hence.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Peg.</speaker>
               <l>Dear <hi>Wallace,</hi> thoe ane ſhrude</l>
               <l>Hawd not our bands, wees meet in yander cloud,</l>
               <l>Whare na fell Southern nowther can extrude,</l>
               <l>Nor bar na fra celeſtiall pulchritude,</l>
               <l>Aid gange thy gate, till heaven, and as we flay,</l>
               <l>Like turtle Dowes weeſe bill &amp; find gude play.
<stage>Exit Peg.</stage>
               </l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Wall.</speaker>
               <l>Rare reſolution, what weak heart would faint,</l>
               <l>Having ſo conſtant a companion?</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Selby</hi> my ſoul's bound on a glorious voyage,</l>
               <l>And would be free'd out of this jayle of fleſh,</l>
               <l>Then hinder not my voyage.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Jef.</speaker>
               <l>'Tis not policie, wee'l rather ſet it forwards.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Haſ.</speaker>
               <l>Raiſe a Gallowes fifty foot high,</l>
               <l>ye ſhall not go by water, wee'l ſend you up a neerer way.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Wall.</speaker>
               <l>All's one,</l>
               <l>Axe, halter, famine, martyrdome, or fire,</l>
               <l>All are but ſeverall paſſages to heaven,</l>
               <l>Let my ſoule go the furtheſt way about,</l>
               <l>Come tir'd with tortures, ſhooting out my heart,</l>
               <l>The deepeſt wounds, like ſtrong Certificates</l>
               <l>Find kindeſt welcome.</l>
            </sp>
            <stage>
               <hi>Enter</hi> Grimſby.</stage>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Gri.</speaker>
               <l>Stay th'execution, and having read this Warrant, know</l>
               <l>'Tis the Queens pleaſure, you ſend in this traitour</l>
               <l>Vnder my conduct to the Engliſh Campe:</l>
               <l>Rebellion of this nature muſt be ſearch'd,</l>
               <l>With ſharper torture.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Wall.</speaker>
               <l>I outdare the worſt,</l>
               <l>He is no man that is afraid of death,</l>
               <l>And <hi>Wallace</hi> his reſolve ſhall out-live breath.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Gri.</speaker>
               <l>'Tis but ſhort-liv'd elſe, firſt ſee him bound and hud-winckt,</l>
               <l>Then leave him to my care.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <pb facs="tcp:19967:12"/>
               <speaker>Sel.</speaker>
               <l>Bear with this Rebell, my love.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Haſ.</speaker>
               <l>My ſervice.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Jef.</speaker>
               <l>And my policie to the good Queen and Ladies.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Grim.</speaker>
               <l>Come <hi>Wallace,</hi> now your pride draws neer the fall.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Wal.</speaker>
               <l>Why <hi>Grimsby,</hi> if I fall,</l>
               <l>'Tis but to gather ſtronger force to riſe,</l>
               <l>For as a ball's thrown down to raiſe it higher,</l>
               <l>So death's rebound ſhall make my ſoule aſpire</l>
               <l>The glorious clouds, ſo long I die ſecure.</l>
               <l>Death cannot threat more then I dare endure.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Gri.</speaker>
               <l>No not a man more then my private followers,</l>
               <l>The Queen enjoyns it.
<stage>
                     <hi>Exeunt</hi> Wa. <hi>and</hi> Gri.</stage>
               </l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Haſ.</speaker>
               <l>Farwell, valiant <hi>Grimsby,</hi> and farwell danger.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Ief.</speaker>
               <l>Policie and all.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Sel.</speaker>
               <l>The traitors fled, and <hi>Wallace</hi> thus ſuppreſt,</l>
               <l>My ſons blouds paid, and his wrong'd ghoſt at reſt.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Haſ.</speaker>
               <l>And the whole land at quiet, wher's Sir <hi>Iohn Graham?</hi>
               </l>
               <l>Wee'l joyn him partner in Commiſſion,</l>
               <l>'Twill be a means to make our party ſtrong,</l>
               <l>And keep down mutinies, ſearch out old <hi>Wallace,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>And hang the Carle at his own door, Sir <hi>Ieffrey,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>Place tables in the ſtreets, bonefires, and bels,</l>
               <l>Since without cauſe they murmur, let u'm know</l>
               <l>That with their knees wee'l make their proud harts bow.</l>
               <l>Sir <hi>Jeffrey,</hi> be you Maſter of the Feaſt,</l>
               <l>You keep the purſe, if money fall out ſhort,</l>
               <l>Send out for more, you have commiſſion for't.</l>
            </sp>
            <stage>Exeunt.</stage>
         </div>
         <div n="2" type="act">
            <pb facs="tcp:19967:13"/>
            <head>Act. II.</head>
            <stage>
               <hi>Enter</hi> Grimsbie, <hi>two or three followers,</hi> VVal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lace <hi>bound and hoodwinkt.</hi>
            </stage>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Gr.</speaker>
               <l>VVHat talk'ſt of Conſcience? th'art an appa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rant rebell.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Wall.</speaker>
               <l>How can he be a rebell was nere ſubject?</l>
               <l>What right has <hi>Edward</hi> to the Crowne of Scotland</l>
               <l>(The ſword except) more than my ſelfe, or <hi>Grymsbie?</hi>
               </l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Gri.</speaker>
               <l>What greater right then conqueſt?</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Wall.</speaker>
               <l>Then what cauſe,</l>
               <l>Iuſter thou mine? reſpected Country man,</l>
               <l>Thou haſt beene nobly valued, and held ranke</l>
               <l>With beſt deſervers, look upon the wounds</l>
               <l>And mortall ſtabs of that diſtreſſed breaſt</l>
               <l>That gave thee ſuck; ſee thy poore brethren ſlaves,</l>
               <l>Thy ſiſters raviſht, and all out-rages</l>
               <l>That bloudy Conqueſt can give lycence to,</l>
               <l>See this, and then aske Conſcience if the man</l>
               <l>That with his bloud ſeeks generall reformation</l>
               <l>Deſerves the name of Traitour,</l>
               <l>Whither do'ſt leade me?</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Gri.</speaker>
               <l>To Northumberland</l>
               <l>And Beaumont.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Wa.</speaker>
               <l>Butchers do your worſt,</l>
               <l>Torture, I ſpit defiance in thy face,</l>
               <l>And death, embrace thee with as kinde a narme</l>
               <l>As if thou wert.</l>
            </sp>
            <stage>
               <pb facs="tcp:19967:13"/>
               <hi>Enter old</hi> Wallace, Peggie, Graham, Frier, Coming, <hi>and</hi> Mentith.</stage>
            <sp>
               <speaker>O. Wa.</speaker>
               <l>Thy Father.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Peg.</speaker>
               <l>And thy waife.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Wall.</speaker>
               <l>In heaven or in a ſlumber, who reſolves me?</l>
               <l>Speake, am I dead, or living? or aſleep?</l>
               <l>Or all, or both, or neither? tell me fate.</l>
               <l>Me thinks I ſee my Father, warlike <hi>Graham,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>The Fryer, what <hi>Peggie</hi> too? I prethee joye</l>
               <l>Do not ore-flow my ſences, deereſt friends</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Pegg, Father, Coming, Mentith, Graham,</hi> ſee</l>
               <l>I am new moulded, and here ſtands the creature</l>
               <l>That by a warrant granted from the Queene</l>
               <l>Form'd me from out a ſecond Chaos breath'd</l>
               <l>New life, new motions, new dimenſions,</l>
               <l>To tell the ſtory were to ſhame the world,</l>
               <l>And make all mankinde bluſh.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Peg.</speaker>
               <l>May luive.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Gra. Fri.</speaker>
               <l>Our prayers.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Cow.</speaker>
               <l>And all our friendſhip like a coat of ſteele</l>
               <l>Stand betwixt him, and danger.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Wa.</speaker>
               <l>All joyne hands,</l>
               <l>Thus like a mountaine Cedar <hi>Wallace</hi> ſtands</l>
               <l>Amongſt a grove of friends, not to remove</l>
               <l>For <hi>Edwards</hi> thunder, nor the frowne of <hi>Jove,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>I'le hew the yoke from off my countries necke,</l>
               <l>Or never houſe, this religious Fryer</l>
               <l>Is a full witneſſe to the ſacred bond</l>
               <l>Twixt heaven and me, which on my part I'le keep,</l>
               <l>Or pay the forfeit with my bloud.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Fri.</speaker>
               <l>Heaven ſhield</l>
               <l>Many a tall wood oake beene fell'd</l>
               <l>Ere <hi>Wallace</hi> ſtoope, heed <hi>Gentrid</hi> ſawe</l>
               <l>
                  <pb facs="tcp:19967:14"/>Theke ſword ſhall keep in mickle aw,</l>
               <l>Fell Sotherne folk, many a crie,</l>
               <l>Fray cradled barns, e're he ſhall flie,</l>
               <l>Nurſes ſighes, and mothers tears</l>
               <l>Shall ſwell the clouds, till thy awne bloud,</l>
               <l>Prove falſe thilk Crag ſall nere lig dead.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Wal.</speaker>
               <l>Shall <hi>Wallace</hi> live till his owne bloud prove falſe,</l>
               <l>Why, that can never be till palſey age</l>
               <l>Hath thruſt his icy fingers through my veins,</l>
               <l>And frozen up the paſſages of bloud.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Com.</speaker>
               <l>The town of <hi>Lavercke,</hi> peopled only with Engliſh pride</l>
               <l>And overjoyed with thy ſurprizall are made drunk with mirch,</l>
               <l>Bonefires, bels, banquets, and the devill and all</l>
               <l>Invite our ſwords to their ſad funerall.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Wal.</speaker>
               <l>Cloſe with advantage, put your ſelves in Armes,</l>
               <l>And ceaſe their forfeit lives, this holy Frien</l>
               <l>Shall firſt beſtow a matrimoniall band</l>
               <l>Of our united love, and then my ſword</l>
               <l>Like winged lightning ſhall prepare a way,</l>
               <l>To <hi>Lavercks</hi> doom.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Fri.</speaker>
               <l>Nea marry, ſtay a wheane,</l>
               <l>Dip not thy winyard in the weambe</l>
               <l>Of <hi>Lavercks</hi> town, for giffe thou gange,</l>
               <l>Thouſe weark thy lives friend mickle wrang,</l>
               <l>Thouſe come back ſeafe, but barne I feare,</l>
               <l>Iſe never blinck upon thee meare,</l>
               <l>Kneel till thy Sier his benuſon crave,</l>
               <l>Next duty bin till dig her grave,</l>
               <l>Kiſſe, kiſſe thy <hi>Peg,</hi> for well a neer,</l>
               <l>Thaſe amerous twins ſall nere kiſſe mare,</l>
               <l>Till in deaths armes they kiſſe, thilke ſtate</l>
               <l>Stands writ in heaven and ſeal'd by fate.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Wal.</speaker>
               <l>Then fate diſſembles with mee, this the ſecond time</l>
               <l>She has by viſion ſummon'd me to armes,</l>
            </sp>
            <stage>Exeunt.</stage>
            <stage>
               <pb facs="tcp:19967:14"/>
               <hi>Alarum. Enter</hi> Haſlerig <hi>one way,</hi> Selby, and <hi>Sir</hi> Ieffrey <hi>with Frier, Old</hi> Wallace <hi>and</hi> Peggie.</stage>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Haſ.</speaker>
               <l>Whom have you there?</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Sel.</speaker>
               <l>Seeking the cave for ſhelter,</l>
               <l>See whom kind fare hath given us.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Haſ.</speaker>
               <l>Trecherous <hi>Wallace,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>The doting wizzard, and diſſembling woman</l>
               <l>Chief cauſe of this Rebellion, now revenge,</l>
               <l>Clothe thee in crimſon, and prepare to feaſt,</l>
               <l>Wee'l tune ſuch diſmall muſick, as ſhall dint,</l>
               <l>Smiles in thy ſhallow cheeks.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Peg.</speaker>
               <l>Alas, for wae,</l>
               <l>What gars this Iewde? what ill intend ye man?</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Haſ.</speaker>
               <l>To make rebellion fatherleſſe,</l>
               <l>And murder a madding widdower.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>O. Wal.</speaker>
               <l>Oh, ſpare mine age.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Peg.</speaker>
               <l>Pitie my beauty.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Fri.</speaker>
               <l>My religion.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Sel.</speaker>
               <l>Like pity, as thy barbarous ſonne beſtow'd</l>
               <l>On my boyes life, ile print upon thy boſome.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Haſ.</speaker>
               <l>Like pitie as thy husband pitileſſe,</l>
               <l>Took on the widdows tears, and Orphans cryes</l>
               <l>That kiſt his, and hung about his knees</l>
               <l>At <hi>Lavercks</hi> maſſacre, Ile ſhew on thee.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Sel.</speaker>
               <l>Thus fell my ſonne,</l>
               <l>And thus the father of his murtherer fals.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Haſ.</speaker>
               <l>Thus wither'd the pride of <hi>Laverck,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>And thus fades the flower that caus'd their ruine.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Jef.</speaker>
               <l>Thus religious cries
<stage>Exit Haſlerig.</stage>
               </l>
               <l>Were ſtopt with ſteele, and thus religion dies.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>O. Wal.</speaker>
               <l>
                  <hi>Wallace,</hi> revenge me as thou art my ſonne.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Peg.</speaker>
               <l>Revenge thy wait,</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Fri.</speaker>
               <l>Revenge Religion.</l>
            </sp>
            <stage>
               <pb facs="tcp:19967:15"/>
               <hi>A Crie within,</hi> Wallace <hi>and</hi> Conqueſt. <hi>Enter</hi> Haſlerigg.</stage>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Haſ.</speaker>
               <l>Thunderbolts and fire rampier your throats,</l>
               <l>The ſlaves growne infinite,</l>
               <l>And moves in every place at once,</l>
               <l>Shift for your ſelves:</l>
               <l>Proud <hi>Wallace</hi> recking in the bloud of Lavercke,</l>
               <l>Like a fierce tiger nurſt in humane ſpoyle,</l>
               <l>Purſues the ſlaughter, the barren hills lye ſtrewed</l>
               <l>With mangled limbes, ſuch as the gentle night</l>
               <l>Reſcue from death, fall in the morning flight,</l>
               <l>Then flye or fall for company,</l>
               <l>Flie from a rebell, but fate keep true courſe,</l>
               <l>Weele ebbe like flouds, to flow with ſtronger force.</l>
            </sp>
            <stage>Exeunt.</stage>
            <stage>
               <hi>Enter</hi> Wallace <hi>all bloudy.</hi>
            </stage>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Wal.</speaker>
               <l>Purſue the ſlaughter, whilſt I, ſalvation ſhield me.</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Fryer Gertrid</hi> anſwer me, what barbarous hand</l>
               <l>Has caſt my friend into this cold dead ſweat,</l>
               <l>Reſolve me gentle Father, fellon death,</l>
               <l>Tha'ſt acted ſacrilegious burglary, and told my father.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>O. W.</speaker>
               <l>Wallace.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Wal.</speaker>
               <l>No excuſe.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Peg.</speaker>
               <l>Ay ſea husband.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Wall.</speaker>
               <l>Intreat not, ye are guilty both.</l>
               <l>And parties in the deereſt robbery,</l>
               <l>Then though my wife and father (mercy fate,)</l>
               <l>Play not the tyrant with me, do not try</l>
               <l>My ſences bore their weake abilitie,</l>
               <l>Ceaſe to afflict me, or I ſhall turne Rebell,</l>
               <l>And breathe invectives gainſt thy power.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Peg.</speaker>
               <l>O my deare <hi>Wallas</hi> for the luive waife,</l>
               <l>For ſiuve of awe ſawles, and thy daying waife,</l>
               <l>
                  <pb facs="tcp:19967:15"/>Lift to my latter accens, and attend</l>
               <l>Of all thy joyes the derne and diſmawe end.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Wall.</speaker>
               <l>Torture above indurance,</l>
               <l>King of dreames diſſolve my viſion.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Peg.</speaker>
               <l>
                  <hi>Wallace</hi> is awake.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Wall.</speaker>
               <l>O if I be, let my ſoule never ſleepe,</l>
               <l>In the bleſt boſome of my Anceſtors,</l>
               <l>Till I have drawne a ſea of purple teares</l>
               <l>From forth the boſomes of the murderers,</l>
               <l>Deere <hi>Peggie,</hi> father, <hi>Gertrid,</hi> which way, where</l>
               <l>How, when, what meanes, what cauſe ſhall I deviſe</l>
               <l>To finde it out, and venge your tragedies?</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Peg.</speaker>
               <l>I'le teach ye how,</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Selby</hi> and <hi>Haſlerigg</hi> byn the fell blood-hounds</l>
               <l>Whae have hunted laife untill thicke toyles of death,</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Wa.</speaker>
               <l>Are they turn'd hangmen?</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Peg.</speaker>
               <l>Religious cryes, beauteous entreats, and reverend well-awayes</l>
               <l>Could not winne grace or favour,</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Wallas</hi> revenge my death,</l>
               <l>And for a favour keep my hindmoſt breath.
<stage>Dies.</stage>
               </l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Wall.</speaker>
               <l>And houſe it here.</l>
            </sp>
            <stage>
               <hi>Enter</hi> Grimsby, Coming, Mentith, <hi>and</hi> Graham.</stage>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Gri.</speaker>
               <l>Where's <hi>VVallas?</hi> never eye</l>
               <l>Saw ſuch a ruthleſſe maſſacre.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>VVal.</speaker>
               <l>Yes <hi>Grimsby,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>VVallace</hi> can ſhewe a maſſacre will proove</l>
               <l>Thine but a may-game.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Gri.</speaker>
               <l>Terrible and ſtrange!</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>VVall.</speaker>
               <l>Doſt ſtart at this? then ſee a ſpectacle</l>
               <l>Of force to ſtay the motion of the ſpheares,</l>
               <l>Or ſtrike the Sun dead in the browe of heaven,</l>
               <l>Looke, and like men ſhort from the browe of thunder,</l>
               <l>
                  <pb facs="tcp:19967:16"/>Fall ſeneeles, death wounds not ſo deepe as wonder.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Gra.</speaker>
               <l>Whoſe bloody act was this?</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>VVal.</speaker>
               <l>The bloody acts</l>
               <l>Contriv'd and plotted by experienc'd villaines.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Gri.</speaker>
               <l>Who were the authors?</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>VVal.</speaker>
               <l>Iudge, they all ſpake Engliſh,</l>
               <l>Death beſt becomes that Dialect,</l>
               <l>The firſt was bloody <hi>Haſleriggs,</hi> the ſecond</l>
               <l>More villaine-like was <hi>Selbyes,</hi> but the third</l>
               <l>All had a hand in.</l>
            </sp>
            <stage>
               <hi>Trumpet. Enter</hi> Meſſenger.</stage>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Meſſ.</speaker>
               <l>Engliſh Embaſſadours.
<stage>Exit Meſſ.</stage>
               </l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Wa.</speaker>
               <l>They are welcome, let not one ſullen browe</l>
               <l>Be ſeene in all this fiery firmament.</l>
            </sp>
            <stage>
               <hi>Enter</hi> Mountford, Glaſcot, <hi>and</hi> Sebaſtian.</stage>
            <sp>
               <speaker>VVal.</speaker>
               <l>Welcome, your buſineſſe?</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Seb.</speaker>
               <l>Farre more like a Prince,</l>
               <l>Then a baſe rebell looks the Northerne traytor.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Mount.</speaker>
               <l>Thus to a rebell from a royall King,</l>
               <l>If <hi>VVallace</hi> will confeſſe himſelfe a traytor,</l>
               <l>And for his bloody outrages and thefts,</l>
               <l>Crave mercy, and ſubmit himſelfe to <hi>Edward,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>There's hope of life.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>VVal.</speaker>
               <l>Still charitable Engliſh.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Seb.</speaker>
               <l>Tis not he ſure,</l>
               <l>This looks not like a man ſhold ſhake a kingdome.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Mount.</speaker>
               <l>This it he ſhall denie,</l>
               <l>Rape, murther, ruine, all the ſonnes of warre</l>
               <l>Stands ſtriving for the prey, and once let looſe,</l>
               <l>Shall not be checkt, nor taken up, till rage</l>
               <l>Be tyr'd with murther, and thy ſelfe in chaynes</l>
               <l>
                  <pb facs="tcp:19967:16"/>Hang'd like a villaine.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Wal.</speaker>
               <l>This is all perfit Engliſh, have ye yet ſpoke?</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Moun.</speaker>
               <l>We have.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Wa.</speaker>
               <l>Then we begin,</l>
               <l>And to a tyrant thus ſayes a loyall ſubject,</l>
               <l>If <hi>Edward</hi> will confeſſe himſelfe a tyrant,</l>
               <l>And kingly fellon, and make good ſuch theft</l>
               <l>As he and his have practis'd, ſue his peace</l>
               <l>By yeelding up his and himſelfe to <hi>VVallace,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>There's hope of life, this if he ſhall deny</l>
               <l>Rape, murther, ruine, all the brood of warre</l>
               <l>Shalbe let flie, and never be lur'd of</l>
               <l>Till they be gorg'd, and bated with the heart</l>
               <l>Of the proud King himſelfe.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Seb.</speaker>
               <l>Now ſpeakes a man</l>
               <l>Would thruſt <hi>Iove</hi> from <hi>Olympus.</hi>
               </l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Glaſ.</speaker>
               <l>Calme your ſpleene,</l>
               <l>For now ſpeaks mercy, if your Countryes wrongs</l>
               <l>Grow from abuſe in <hi>Edwards</hi> ſubſtitutes,</l>
               <l>You ſhall have equall hearing, and the wrongs</l>
               <l>Puniſh't in the deſervers.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>VVa.</speaker>
               <l>This ſhould not be Engliſh,</l>
               <l>Or if it be King <hi>Edward</hi> is no tyrant.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Glaſ.</speaker>
               <l>What anſwers <hi>VValace?</hi>
               </l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>VVa.</speaker>
               <l>Firſt pray pardon me,</l>
               <l>If like the working of a troubled ſea</l>
               <l>My boſome roſe in billows, for though the windes</l>
               <l>That rais'd the ſtorme be downe, yet the deare ruines</l>
               <l>Lye ſtill in view, a father, and a wife,</l>
               <l>Age, beauty, and religion, for thee</l>
               <l>Thouſands ſhall weep, as many wives</l>
               <l>Shed purple teares for thee, as many Church-men</l>
               <l>Offer their reeking ſoules in ſacrifice,</l>
               <l>Court, City, Church, the Chamber of your King,</l>
               <l>The Chaire of State ſhall be no priviledge.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <pb facs="tcp:19967:17"/>
               <speaker>Seb.</speaker>
               <l>This was not <hi>Edwards</hi> act.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>VVa.</speaker>
               <l>Yet ſuch as <hi>Edward</hi>
               </l>
               <l>Plac'd in commiſſion, oh t'was a churliſh ſtorme,</l>
               <l>And wretched I like a forlorne ſurviver</l>
               <l>Left to interre their deare remembrances.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Seb.</speaker>
               <l>Good gentleman.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>VVa.</speaker>
               <l>But bid relentleſſe <hi>Edward</hi>
               </l>
               <l>Send in the pyrats <hi>Haſlerigg</hi> and <hi>Selbye,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>And in their hands letters of Murt ſubſcribed,</l>
               <l>To make me Maſter of my owne revenge,</l>
               <l>Or like a Ball wrapt in a cloud of fire,</l>
               <l>Ruine ſhall fall upon his palace top,</l>
               <l>Pierce through the roofe, and in his chayre of State</l>
               <l>Sollicit Iuſtice.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Mo.</speaker>
               <l>Into his Princely eares I'le give your wrongs.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Gri.</speaker>
               <l>Will <hi>VValace</hi> here adviſe?</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>VVa.</speaker>
               <l>Yes.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Gri.</speaker>
               <l>Then be rul'd by <hi>Grymsby.</hi>
                  <stage>VVhiſpers.</stage>
               </l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>VVal.</speaker>
               <l>Thanks for thy kindneſſe. Lords Embaſſadors,</l>
               <l>Such we eſteeme you, may we crave peruſall</l>
               <l>Of your commiſſion?</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Moun.</speaker>
               <l>
                  <hi>VVallace</hi> ſhall command it.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Wa.</speaker>
               <l>
                  <hi>Mountfort</hi> and <hi>Glaſcott,</hi> what third fellow's that?</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Mou.</speaker>
               <l>One of our followers.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>VVal.</speaker>
               <l>Good, his name is not inſerted,</l>
               <l>One call out a headſman.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Seb.</speaker>
               <l>Ambitious rebell, know I am a Prince,</l>
               <l>And nephew to the Queene.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>VVal.</speaker>
               <l>Wer't thou the King,</l>
               <l>Having no portion in the Embaſſie,</l>
               <l>I'de ha' thy head, goe on, and ſtrike it of,</l>
               <l>A ſecond cut his tongue out, and a third</l>
               <l>Thruſt out their eyes, and put their followers to the ſword.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Omu.</speaker>
               <l>
                  <hi>VVallace</hi> wilbe more milde.
<stage>Exeunt.</stage>
               </l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>VVa.</speaker>
               <l>
                  <hi>VVallace</hi> wilbe more juſt</l>
               <l>
                  <pb facs="tcp:19967:17"/>Then ſee the Law of Armes diſgrac'd</l>
               <l>Sound Drums and drown their cries.</l>
               <l>Revenge beats at heavens gates for tyrannies.</l>
               <stage>
                  <hi>Enter</hi> Agen.</stage>
               <l>So now our tragick Muſe jets on the ſtage,</l>
               <l>You that for ſeeing baſeneſſe want your ſight,</l>
               <l>Beare with this preſent our indeer'd, commends</l>
               <l>Back to the Queen, and ſay ſo much we tender</l>
               <l>Her ſacred honour, weed not ſee it wrong'd</l>
               <l>Even in her Nephew, you that for ſparing ſpeech</l>
               <l>In honours cauſe are juſtly mute, conduct</l>
               <l>This eyeleſſe meſſenger, abuſe not our intent</l>
               <l>In the delivery, make ſpeedy haſte,</l>
               <l>Leſt we be there before you, ſhare in like wrong,</l>
               <l>Lend him your eyes, and borrow you his tongue,</l>
               <l>If any queſtion you about your harms,</l>
               <l>Say <hi>Wallace</hi> did it in the right of Armes.
<stage>Exeunt Engliſh.</stage>
               </l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Gri.</speaker>
               <l>This will affright the Engliſh.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Wall.</speaker>
               <l>Honor'd <hi>Grimsby,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>This and ten thouſand, thouſand more extremes</l>
               <l>Cannot appeaſe my anger, you that love me</l>
               <l>See thoſe I lov'd inhum'd, my ſelfe diſguiſ'd,</l>
               <l>Will be their Convoy to the Engliſh Campe,</l>
               <l>And ſee their uſage.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Gri.</speaker>
               <l>'Twill be an act of danger.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Wal.</speaker>
               <l>The fitter him that undertakes it, <hi>Wallace</hi>
               </l>
               <l>Would hold himſelf not worthy of his fate</l>
               <l>Should he bawke danger, diſſwade not, I will on</l>
               <l>Were certain death againſt my boſome bent,</l>
               <l>There's gain in bloud it's honorably ſpent.
<stage>Exit.</stage>
               </l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Gri.</speaker>
               <l>And ſuch I feare will thine be, honour'd friends</l>
               <l>See thoſe remayns of honorable love</l>
               <l>Cradled in earth, that once perform'd take Armes</l>
               <l>
                  <pb facs="tcp:19967:18"/>To venge their deaths, <hi>Mentith,</hi> I attend</l>
               <l>The comming of ſome ſpeciall friends by oath,</l>
               <l>Bound to aſſiſt us, hark how their friendly drums</l>
               <l>Chide them for loytring.</l>
               <stage>
                  <hi>Enter</hi> Douglas, Mackbeth, <hi>and</hi> VVinterſdale.</stage>
               <l>Honor'd <hi>Douglas,</hi> welcome,</l>
               <l>Welcome <hi>Mackbeth,</hi> and doughty <hi>Winterſdale,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>Not, unto men more, driven in needfull want,</l>
               <l>Could you have brought ſupply.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Doug.</speaker>
               <l>The better welcome,</l>
               <l>Gold to rich men, and treaſure to the wealthy,</l>
               <l>Are known companions, wher's our Generall,</l>
               <l>The hopefull <hi>VVallace?</hi>
               </l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Gri.</speaker>
               <l>Gone in queſt of death,</l>
               <l>Firme as his fate, cauſe he ſees danger ſhuns him,</l>
               <l>He's gone to ſeek it in the Engliſh tents.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Mack.</speaker>
               <l>So <hi>Hercules</hi> ſought honour out in Hell.</l>
               <l>He not deſerves, the name of Generall,</l>
               <l>Dares not face danger, and out-do the Devill.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Gri.</speaker>
               <l>And ſuch a man is <hi>VVallace,</hi> yet leaſt worth</l>
               <l>Bears him beyond his ſtrength, bring up your powers</l>
               <l>For preſent charge, his thoughts are tragicall,</l>
               <l>And full of bloud, active, and violent all.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Doug</speaker>
               <l>You that beſt know 'em, feed 'em, all that's ours,</l>
               <l>For <hi>Scotlands</hi> good call <hi>VVallaces</hi> and yours.</l>
            </sp>
            <stage>Exeunt.</stage>
            <stage>
               <hi>Enter</hi> Wallace, <hi>like a halting Souldier on wooden ſtumps, with</hi> Mountford <hi>dumbe, and</hi> Glaſcot <hi>blinde.</hi>
            </stage>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Wal.</speaker>
               <p>Whare man? till the Engliſh Campe ſenu you,
<pb facs="tcp:19967:18"/>
gad ſides you gang as I ha' ſeene mony a your Contry<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men like ranck riders amble up weſtward, you gang the wrang wey man, you ſall luſe and ye play at ſhoola<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>groate, ha' ye na linckers?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Glaſ.</speaker>
               <l>Ahlas I want my eyes, but have a tongue,</l>
               <l>He ſees, but cannot ſpeake.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Wa.</speaker>
               <p>Blyncke at ſmaw faults then, make me the thrid<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man, and here's a bunny noyſe of Fidlers to gang fra winehouſe to winehouſe, a blind harper, a mute Cornet, and an old Scotch bagpipe worne toth' ſtumps.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Glaſ.</speaker>
               <l>Are you a Scotch man Sir?</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Wa.</speaker>
               <p>Ye marry am I, boddy and ſawle a true Scotch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man borne, but a true liegeman, hang him that does not luife your King, and your Countryman, what gude vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctales is that which thilke bonny man that haz glazen windows to his lindging has tyed up in his wallet there?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Glaſ.</speaker>
               <l>Tis the head of a young murderd gentleman.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>VVa.</speaker>
               <p>What ſenn you man! a mans ſcalpe, I doubt ye be three fawſe knaves liggand yare heads together about na gudenes, a traytors head iſt not?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Gla.</speaker>
               <l>No, but we ha' met with villaynes worſe then traytors.</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>VValace</hi> your countryman, that bloody hangman</l>
               <l>Mangled us all three thus.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>VVa.</speaker>
               <l>
                  <hi>VValas</hi> my Countryman, ay ſay upon him,</l>
               <l>Fawe lymmerlike wad I had his head here too,</l>
               <l>Ized beare it by my ſawle toth' <hi>Engliſh</hi> Campe</l>
               <l>Or neere gang farder.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Gla.</speaker>
               <l>Twold be a glorious fight there.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>VVa.</speaker>
               <l>And you could ſee it ye ſulled ſea ſo man, <hi>VVallace</hi>
               </l>
               <l>Cut of my ſhancks too, cauſe I ran away from him</l>
               <l>To ſerve your gude Prince, harke man, I weare</l>
               <l>Na ſhooen but wodden clampers.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Gla.</speaker>
               <l>Of charity leade us to th' <hi>Engliſh</hi> Campe,</l>
               <l>
                  <pb facs="tcp:19967:19"/>Ye ſhall beſides thanks be moſt royally payd.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Wal.</speaker>
               <l>Gan<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap>alang man tis hard by now, a mans head</l>
               <l>I deempt the pure man had gaugand lang to lawe</l>
               <l>And ſae was thruſt out of dores by head and ſhoulders.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Glaſ.</speaker>
               <l>No lawe was ere ſo cruell as <hi>Wallas</hi> is.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Wa.</speaker>
               <p>Ne marry? na law ſa cruell, fay man fay, I luick'd upon a man a lawe not lang ſince that ſent an awde man and his wife, and many barnes a begging, he had better a ſlizand theire weazond pipes, and cut theire heads off, but whay was a ſa bludy mynded thinke ye?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Gla.</speaker>
               <l>I cannot judge.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Wa.</speaker>
               <p>Marry man, to get poſſeſſion of the pure mans houſe, but there was a cat ganged beyond the man a lawe.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Gla.</speaker>
               <l>A cat goe beyond a lawyer? how?</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Wa.</speaker>
               <p>I'le tell you how, the man a lawe being got in, the Cat outreach'd him, and leaped to th' top oth lindg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, and ſtandand on the tyles, the man a lawe ſcoarning any ane to be abuife him, offer to fling and dingand downe the poore puſcatt, but ſhe meawed at him, and cryed hawd thou foule lowne hawd, as thou thruſts out this poore man and his barnes, ſa there is ane abuife ſall thruſt out thee, ſtay blind man, here comes ſouldiers.</p>
            </sp>
            <stage>
               <hi>Enter</hi> Bolt <hi>with three or foure tattar'd Souldiers.</hi>
            </stage>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Omn.</speaker>
               <l>Stand <hi>que voula,</hi> ſpyes about our trenches?</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Bolt.</speaker>
               <l>And ſee they have knock'd ſome man downe ſirra,</l>
               <l>You that carry two faces under a hood,</l>
               <l>What are you?</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>1 <hi>So.</hi>
               </speaker>
               <l>He muſt be preſt, he will not ſpeake.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Bol.</speaker>
               <l>What art thou I charge thee? haſt thou neere a tongue</l>
               <l>In thy head? give the word.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <pb facs="tcp:19967:19"/>
               <speaker>Gla,</speaker>
               <l>He has no tounge indeed ſir.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Bol.</speaker>
               <l>Two heads and neere a tongue, what are you?</l>
               <l>That like a blind <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ſſe ſtand ſtill, and cannot tell us ſo.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Gla.</speaker>
               <l>I'me blind indeed,</l>
               <l>Conduct us to the Lords i'th' <hi>Engliſh</hi> Campe.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>2 <hi>So.</hi>
               </speaker>
               <l>How Lords, are you Ladyes that you long for Lords?</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Bol.</speaker>
               <p>Do you take us for gulls to goe tell the Lords here's a dumbe man would ſpeake with'em, what are you ſirra? come halt not, lets not find you in two tales y'are beſt.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Wa.</speaker>
               <p>Ize a <hi>Scotch</hi> man ſir, ye ſhall neere find me in twa tales.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Bo.</speaker>
               <l>A <hi>Scotch</hi> man ſir, do you know where you are ſir?</l>
               <l>Your blew bonnet on before an <hi>Engliſh</hi> ſcull,</l>
               <l>Where's your leg ſir, when an Officer ſpeaks to you?</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Wa.</speaker>
               <p>My leg ſir is not in my galligaskin and flop as yours is, I'ze a pure <hi>Scotch</hi> ſouldier out at heeles, and am glad to beſtirr my ſtumps, guide theſe gude men y'are wranged Countrymen, wha that fawſe traytor <hi>Wallace</hi> has miſuſand in ſike wiſe.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Om.</speaker>
               <l>
                  <hi>Wallas,</hi> oh ſlave!</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Bolt.</speaker>
               <l>I ſhall live (fellows in armes out at Elbows)</l>
               <l>To give fire to my peece with a burnt ynch of match</l>
               <l>Made of that raſcals fat of mawegut.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Wa.</speaker>
               <l>By my ſawle ſir wad I might come</l>
               <l>To'th making of ſike a match.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Bol.</speaker>
               <l>Here's my hand, becauſe thou ſayeſt ſo,</l>
               <l>Thou ſhalt be by when I make him give fire to my touch-hole.</l>
            </sp>
            <stage>
               <hi>Enter Queene</hi> Elenor, Clifford, Percy, Beau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mont, <hi>and others.</hi>
            </stage>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Omn.</speaker>
               <l>The Lords are going to view the trenches.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Bol.</speaker>
               <l>Every man to his parrapet,</l>
               <l>
                  <pb facs="tcp:19967:20"/>To your trenches you tatterd roagues!</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Cli.</speaker>
               <l>Its well done fellowes.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Bol.</speaker>
               <l>Cry your Lordſhip mercy,</l>
               <l>This blind buzzard here cannot ſee,</l>
               <l>Whither will you march headlong my friend?</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Per.</speaker>
               <l>What men are theſe?</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Bol.</speaker>
               <l>I leave them to your Honors ſifting,</l>
               <l>I have fortifications to look too.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Cliff.</speaker>
               <l>There's drinking money, hence to your works.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Bol.</speaker>
               <l>Bleſſe your honours.
<stage>
                     <hi>Exeunt Bolt.</hi> and <hi>Sould.</hi>
                  </stage>
               </l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Percy.</speaker>
               <l>What men are theſe, I aske, will no man ſpeak?</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Gla.</speaker>
               <l>Heare and in hearing wiſh the ſound unheard,</l>
               <l>Youthfull <hi>Sebaſtian</hi> nephew to the Queene</l>
               <l>Longing to ſee the man fam'd for th' exceſſe</l>
               <l>Or goodnes and of badnes, ſeeing unjoyned</l>
               <l>In honored Embaſſie diſguis'd attempted</l>
               <l>The rebell <hi>Wallaces</hi> preſence.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Omn.</speaker>
               <l>
                  <hi>Glaſcot</hi> and <hi>Mountford.</hi>
               </l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Clif.</speaker>
               <l>Who did this damned villany?</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Gla.</speaker>
               <l>Our meſſage told,</l>
               <l>The traytor newly ſet on fire with madnes,</l>
               <l>Showing the mangled bodies of a Fryer,</l>
               <l>His wife and father, burſt out into flames</l>
               <l>Hye hot and violent, In which fierce rage</l>
               <l>Revolted <hi>Grimsby</hi> knew <hi>Sebaſtian</hi>
               </l>
               <l>(Tho Herald like he went diſguiſ'd) and ſeazed</l>
               <l>Him and us for three intelligencing ſpies,</l>
               <l>Cut off his head, his tongue, and <hi>Glaſcots</hi> eyes.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Per.</speaker>
               <l>Hang up this, provide for theſe, trufle him up.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Wa.</speaker>
               <l>What ſen ye man?
<stage>
                     <hi>Exeunt Moun.</hi> and <hi>Glaſ.</hi>
                  </stage>
               </l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Per.</speaker>
               <l>What ſlave, what Turke that murders his owne brethren</l>
               <l>Durſt play the tyrant thus? hang all the Nation</l>
               <l>Whom we have tane to mercy, I'le not ſpare</l>
               <l>Fathers, nor mothers, nor their bawling barnes,</l>
               <l>
                  <pb facs="tcp:19967:20"/>fire their houſes, hang up this tike firſt.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Wal.</speaker>
               <p>Ah bonny men, I met um playe and at bo-peep, &amp; gangand out a their way, and ſall I be hanged for my good deeds of charrity, I'ze a poor Scutch ſouldier, and am ron away from that Rebell <hi>Wallas,</hi> to feight and for your gude Prince, ah he's a gude King, and y'are all bonny men, I'ze follow ye all to the death, and to the Devill, and ony man dare gang ſo far for all my clutches, giffe I clutch <hi>Wallace,</hi> he's neer carry it till hell nor heaven.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Per.</speaker>
               <l>If he do, may <hi>Percies</hi> name be croſt</l>
               <l>Out of the roll of men.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Clif.</speaker>
               <l>So much ſwears <hi>Clifford.</hi>
               </l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Per.</speaker>
               <l>Sneak not away ſirra, y'are not gone yet.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>VVal.</speaker>
               <l>I ken it vary weel.</l>
               <l>I'ze not gangan to hanging yet.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Clif.</speaker>
               <l>Yet though a traitour, thus much let me ſpeak</l>
               <l>For abſent <hi>VVallace,</hi> were the caſe your own,</l>
               <l>Or one that's baſer having any ſpirit,</l>
               <l>A murder'd father and a bleeding wife,</l>
               <l>Mangled before him, would ſtrike fire in ſnow,</l>
               <l>Make loyalty turn traitor, and obedience</l>
               <l>Forget all duty.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>El.</speaker>
               <l>But our Nephews death</l>
               <l>And the diſgrace done our Embaſſadours.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Clif.</speaker>
               <l>They then put off their title, and put on</l>
               <l>The name of ſpies, when in their companies,</l>
               <l>They take diſguiſ'd obſervers.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>VVal.</speaker>
               <l>By my ſawle the <hi>Engliſh</hi> are gallant men.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Per.</speaker>
               <l>No ſnare to intrap this Wolfe?</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Clif.</speaker>
               <l>How <hi>Northumberland,</hi> intrap a fo?</l>
               <l>Sure 'tis no <hi>Engliſh</hi> word,</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Clifford</hi> at leaſt was ne're acquainted with't.</l>
               <l>Give him fair ſummons, dare him to the field,</l>
               <l>And trap him then.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>VVal.</speaker>
               <l>Ah bony man!</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <pb facs="tcp:19967:21"/>
               <speaker>Per.</speaker>
               <l>His being a traitour warrants it, diſpatch</l>
               <l>A ſecond meſſage with acknowledgment</l>
               <l>Of former wrongs to our Embaſſadours,</l>
               <l>With promiſe of a friendly enterview</l>
               <l>Early to morrow, impartially to heare</l>
               <l>Their wrongs, and mildely miniſter redreſſe.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Clif.</speaker>
               <l>Inſnare him ſo and ſpare not, for you'le finde I feare,</l>
               <l>That <hi>Selby, Haſlerig,</hi> and the reſt</l>
               <l>Lay yokes too heavy on the Nations neck.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>El.</speaker>
               <l>If they do puniſh 'em.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Clif.</speaker>
               <l>Puniſh 'em, ſdeath hang 'em.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Per.</speaker>
               <l>Shall we agree to have ſuch meſſage ſent</l>
               <l>To allure this bloudy Tygre into th' net</l>
               <l>And waking then or ſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>eping kill him.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Clif.</speaker>
               <l>No.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Per.</speaker>
               <l>All ſtratagems are lawfull 'gainſt a fo.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Clif.</speaker>
               <l>Do what you will, but my conſent is no.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Beau.</speaker>
               <l>I'le venture to the Rebell.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Per.</speaker>
               <p>Do good <hi>Beaumont, Scotchman</hi> dar'ſt thou con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duct him as his guide?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Clif.</speaker>
               <l>But return ſirra, or the next time we take yee</l>
               <l>Y'are Crag ſhall pay for't.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Wal.</speaker>
               <p>I'ze not run away fra yee, giffe I do hang mee and drae mee, cum bully <hi>Joe,</hi> I dare not gang to the Scottis Campe, th'yle ſa ſlay upon me, Iſe near cum back agen, but lze bring you where yee ſhall ſee that Lowne <hi>VVal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lace.</hi>
               </p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Beau.</speaker>
               <l>That's all I wiſh; lead on.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Wal.</speaker>
               <l>Marry ſall I, luke to your ſelfe,</l>
               <l>Iſe thruſt you into the Dewles chops.</l>
            </sp>
            <stage>Exeunt Beaum. and VVal.</stage>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Beau.</speaker>
               <l>For getting out let me ſcuffle.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>El.</speaker>
               <l>Conſult for preſent execution.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Cliff.</speaker>
               <l>What is, what ſhould, what can this <hi>Wallace</hi> be?</l>
               <l>
                  <pb facs="tcp:19967:21"/>Whom fame limbs out for ſuch a gallant peece,</l>
               <l>And is ſo curious in her workmanſhip,</l>
               <l>No part deforms him,</l>
               <l>Yet <hi>Wallace</hi> is a Rebell, his chief ſcandall</l>
               <l>Is poverty of Gentry, by my ſword</l>
               <l>Wert no impeach to my deare Anceſtors,</l>
               <l>I well could ſpare him ſome of my unus'd titles,</l>
               <l>Or would at martiall gaming ſo I might loſe</l>
               <l>And <hi>Wallace</hi> winne ſo much of <hi>Cliffords</hi> honour,</l>
               <l>Our ſtocks might be alike, but I exceed,</l>
               <l>This night he is betray'd, he ſhall not,</l>
               <l>I'le turn traitor firſt he ſhall not,</l>
               <l>Call <hi>Beaumont</hi> back, or elſe by <hi>Cliffords</hi> honor,</l>
               <l>An oath which I eſteem above my life,</l>
               <l>I will turn traitor, and reveale your plots,</l>
               <l>Call him back.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Per.</speaker>
               <l>Is <hi>Clifford</hi> mad?</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Clif.</speaker>
               <l>No <hi>Percie's</hi> lunatick, ſuppoſe he be a traitor</l>
               <l>And diſcipline of the field allow the act,</l>
               <l>What honour is it for a herd of yours</l>
               <l>To worry a ſleeping Beare? goe call him back.</l>
            </sp>
            <stage>
               <hi>Enter</hi> Beaumont <hi>with a wooden ſtump.</hi>
            </stage>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Per.</speaker>
               <l>See he comes uncall'd.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Clif.</speaker>
               <l>The news.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Bea.</speaker>
               <l>News call you it, let no <hi>Scot</hi> come neer your tents,</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Wallace</hi> ſends you this token.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Clif.</speaker>
               <l>Ha, how, <hi>Wallace.</hi>
               </l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Per.</speaker>
               <l>Was that the traitor?</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Clif.</speaker>
               <l>By <hi>Mars</hi> his helme, a compleat Warrior,</l>
               <l>I ſo love his worth, I'le court it with my ſword.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Bea.</speaker>
               <l>Had you but ſtood in diſtance of his thunder,</l>
               <l>For, we parted juſt where our trenches ended,</l>
               <l>You'de ha' ſworn the God of VVar had ſpoke,</l>
               <l>
                  <pb facs="tcp:19967:22"/>Quoth he, tell <hi>Percy,</hi> he ſhall not need.</l>
               <l>To hunt me in my tent, I'le rouze him in's own,</l>
               <l>And bids me give you this wooden ſtumpe,</l>
               <l>And ſweares to make you weare it,</l>
               <l>If you dare ſtand him in the field.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Per.</speaker>
               <l>Baſe Rebell, why durſt he not ſtand here?</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Clif.</speaker>
               <l>None pray'd him ſtay,</l>
               <l>Twas manners being not welcom'd to get away.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Beau.</speaker>
               <l>He ſends, commends to <hi>Clifford,</hi> with this wiſh,</l>
               <l>That if at this great match of life, and death,</l>
               <l>He chance to loſe the ſmalleſt part of honour</l>
               <l>His ſword may joyn't, he knows beſt how to uſe it.</l>
               <l>At my return from <hi>France,</hi> quoth he, this vow</l>
               <l>Which I have promis'd ſhall be ſurely payed,</l>
               <l>Our Country overtopt with tyranny,</l>
               <l>Makes us flie thither for ſuccour, <hi>Aeolus,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>Let favourable winds and tydes aſſiſt me,</l>
               <l>That ſpoak, revolted <hi>Grimsby</hi> and his powers</l>
               <l>Met him in Armes, what further he intends,</l>
               <l>Harke their Drum tels, here my Commiſſion ends.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Clif.</speaker>
               <l>Lets ſend him commendations too, beat ours.</l>
            </sp>
            <stage>Exeunt.</stage>
         </div>
         <div n="3" type="act">
            <head>Act. III.</head>
            <stage>
               <hi>Enter Sir</hi> Ieffrey <hi>and</hi> Bolt <hi>with a Trunke.</hi>
            </stage>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Ief.</speaker>
               <l>Set downe <hi>Bolt,</hi> I can beare with thee no longer.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Bolt.</speaker>
               <p>No more can I beare any longer with you, Sir <hi>Ieffry,</hi> but what a reeling drunken ſot is this ſea, that caſts up ſuch gobbets as this, is this a windfall or no now ſir <hi>Ieffery?</hi> your Worſhip knows both the tags and points of the law.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <pb facs="tcp:19967:22"/>
               <speaker>Ief.</speaker>
               <p>Yes ſure it is a windfall, for as we walk'd upon the ſhore, we ſaw the ſhip ſplit, this fell out, the winds were the cauſe, therefore it muſt needs be a windfall.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Bol.</speaker>
               <p>Well ſome body ha's had but a bad fiſh-dinner to day.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Jef.</speaker>
               <p>The Seas have croſt them that ſought to croſſe the Seas, and therefore for my part I'le never meddle with theſe water-works.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Bolt.</speaker>
               <p>Nor I, lets be more wiſe then a number of gal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lants, and keep the land that's left us, did you ever ſee ſuch gambols as the waves made ſir <hi>Ieffery?</hi>
               </p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Ieff.</speaker>
               <p>Never ſince I wore the nightcap of Iuſtice, and that this her dudgeon dagger was a my ſide.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Bol.</speaker>
               <p>Did you note what puffing the winds made till they got great bellies, and then how ſorely the ſhip fell in labour.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Ieff.</speaker>
               <l>Didſt heare what a dolefull cry they made,</l>
               <l>When their maine yard was ſplit?</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Bolt.</speaker>
               <p>Alas ſir, would it not make any man roare that had but an inch of feeling or compaſſion in his belly to have his mayne yard ſplit, and how the marriners hung by the ropes like Saint <hi>Thomas</hi> Onyons.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Ieff.</speaker>
               <l>I ſaw it <hi>Bolt</hi> with ſalt eyes.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Bolt.</speaker>
               <p>So that you may ſee at ſea however the winde blowes, if a man be well hung, hees cocke ſure.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Ieff.</speaker>
               <l>But <hi>Bolt</hi> what doſt thou thinke this to be?</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Bol.</speaker>
               <l>A matter of ſome weight as I take it.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Ieff.</speaker>
               <p>I hope 'tis gold 'tis ſo heavy, and 'twas going out of the Land.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Bol.</speaker>
               <p>Like enough, for gold goes now very heavily from us, and ſilver too, both red chincks, and white chincks flie away, but ſir <hi>Ieffery,</hi> if this be gold, how rich is the ſea, thinke ye, that has innumerable ſuch ſands?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Ief.</speaker>
               <l>More rich then the land, and more fat.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Bo.</speaker>
               <p>So it had need, for the land looks with a leane
<pb facs="tcp:19967:23"/>
payre of cheeks, yet it has an excellent ſtomach, it digeſts any thing.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Ieff.</speaker>
               <p>Then tis like the ſea, for all's fiſh that comes to net there.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Bol.</speaker>
               <p>I'le tell you the myſtery of that, looke what mouthes gape at land, the ſelfe ſame gape at ſea, all the land is one kingdome, and all the ſea another.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Ief.</speaker>
               <l>And people in't.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Bo.</speaker>
               <p>And people in't (right worſhipful) but they all go Weſthod, as there are good and bad here, ſo there are good and bad there, gulls here, gulls there, as great men here eate up the little men: ſo Whales feed upon the leſſer fiſhes.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Ie.</speaker>
               <p>Belike then the watry common wealth are ill govern'd.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Bo.</speaker>
               <p>No bravely, for heroicall <hi>Hector Herring</hi> is King of fiſhes.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Ie.</speaker>
               <l>So.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Bo.</speaker>
               <p>Rich cobs his good ſubjects, who at Yarmouth lay downe their lives in his quarrell, ſword-fiſh and Pike are his guard.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Ie.</speaker>
               <l>On.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Bo.</speaker>
               <p>Freſh Cods the gallants, and ſweet ſlipper the Knights, whiting-mopps the Ladies, and Lillie-white-muſſels the wayting-gentlewomen.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Ie.</speaker>
               <l>Dangerous meat to take too much of.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Bol.</speaker>
               <l>But who the pages?</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Ie.</speaker>
               <l>Shrimps.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Bo.</speaker>
               <p>No, no ſir, perriwinckles are the pages, perriwinc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kles.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Ie.</speaker>
               <l>No Iuſtices among them?</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Bo.</speaker>
               <p>Yes ſir <hi>Ieffery,</hi> Thornebacks are the Iuſtices, Crabs the Conſtables, whom if you butter with good words, 'tis paſſing meat at midnight.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Ie.</speaker>
               <l>Ah, ha.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <pb facs="tcp:19967:23"/>
               <speaker>Bo.</speaker>
               <l>Dogfiſh are Iaylors,</l>
               <l>And Stockfiſh the poore common people.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Je.</speaker>
               <l>Indeed they live hardly.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Bo.</speaker>
               <p>But ſir they are beaten too't, then have you wet Eeles for whores, and great Oyſters for Bawds.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Ie.</speaker>
               <l>Why great Oyſters Bawd?</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Bo.</speaker>
               <l>Becauſe for the moſt part they are ſtewed.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Ie.</speaker>
               <l>Very good.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Bo.</speaker>
               <p>Laſtly, becauſe no Kingdome can ſtand without laws, and where law ha's her eyne, there Lawyers &amp; Pet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tifoggers ſwarme, therfore the Lawyers here are ſharks, and gudgeons the poore Clyents.</p>
            </sp>
            <stage>Wallace <hi>within.</hi>
            </stage>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Wa.</speaker>
               <l>Wa ho ro ſol fa, ſol fa.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Bo.</speaker>
               <l>Harke.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Ie.</speaker>
               <l>Peace <hi>Bolt.</hi>
               </l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Bol.</speaker>
               <l>Nay peace you good ſir <hi>Ieffery,</hi> peace, peace.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Wa.</speaker>
               <l>Sol la, ſol la ſol la ſol la.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Bo.</speaker>
               <p>Some Faulconers teaching his Hawke prickſong, Shall I mocke him in's owne key.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Ie.</speaker>
               <l>Do.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Bo.</speaker>
               <l>Sol fa ſol fa, here boy.</l>
            </sp>
            <stage>
               <hi>Enter</hi> Wallace.</stage>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Wa.</speaker>
               <l>Here boy, wa ha ho ho,</l>
               <l>All haile to you two.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Bo.</speaker>
               <l>And all ſnow to you ſir.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Ie.</speaker>
               <p>Sirra what art thou that wiſheſt all the haile to light upon us two?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Bo.</speaker>
               <l>Anſwer wiſely to my maſter,</l>
               <l>For hee's a Iuſtice of peace, and you'l be ſmelt out.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Wal.</speaker>
               <l>I am a drown'd rat.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <pb facs="tcp:19967:24"/>
               <speaker>Ie.</speaker>
               <l>A Rat?</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Bo.</speaker>
               <l>Do you take ſir <hi>Ieffrey</hi> for a Rat-catcher,</l>
               <l>Youle tell a ſweet tale for your ſelfe anon.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Wal.</speaker>
               <l>Pox rot you, I am ſhipwrack't,</l>
               <l>Give me ſome meate.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Bo.</speaker>
               <l>Shall I make his <hi>Mittimus?</hi> he begs ſir.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Wa.</speaker>
               <l>I'ha met more then my match, <hi>Neptune</hi> and I,</l>
               <l>Wraſtling for fals, he got the maſterie,</l>
               <l>I'me with his beating bruis'd, weary, cold, weak,</l>
               <l>Liquor'd ſoundly.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Bo.</speaker>
               <l>He's drunk.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>VVal.</speaker>
               <l>Yet ſo thirſtie ſcarce can ſpeak,</l>
               <l>If ye be men, help me to food and fire.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Ie.</speaker>
               <l>What Countryman art thou ſirra?</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>VVal.</speaker>
               <l>A <hi>Scot,</hi> give me ſome victuals pray.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Bo.</speaker>
               <l>No minde but of thy belly.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Ie.</speaker>
               <l>Sirra, ſirra, you are a <hi>Scot,</hi> and I a true <hi>Engliſh</hi> Juſtice.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Bo.</speaker>
               <l>Not a word of Latine, neither Juſtice, nor Clarke.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Ie.</speaker>
               <p>Peace Bolt in the Kings name, I charge thee, if you will eat bread earn bread, take up this luggage, ſirra, fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low me home to my houſe, thou ſhalt have good bread, good drink, and good fire, up I command thee.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Wal.</speaker>
               <l>I am neceſſities ſlave, and now muſt beare.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Bo.</speaker>
               <p>Muſt! nay, ſhall: are not the <hi>Engliſh</hi> your good Lords and Maſters?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Wal.</speaker>
               <l>Well they are.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Bo.</speaker>
               <l>Do you grumble ſir, on ſir <hi>Jeffrey.</hi>
               </l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Ie.</speaker>
               <l>Have an eye to him <hi>Bolt,</hi> leſt he give us the ſlip,</l>
               <l>And were you in this terrible ſtorm at Sea ſay you?</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>VVal.</speaker>
               <l>Over head and eares, ſir.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Bo.</speaker>
               <p>If th'execution had been upon the land Sir <hi>Ieffrey,</hi> as 'twas upon the Sea, your worſhip had been in a worſe pickle then he.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Ie.</speaker>
               <l>Why Knave? why?</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Bo.</speaker>
               <l>Becauſe he that ha's a bad name is half-hang'd,</l>
               <l>
                  <pb facs="tcp:19967:24"/>And your worſhip knowes, ye have but an ill name.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Ie.</speaker>
               <l>Thou Varlet is not wiſe good?</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Bo.</speaker>
               <l>Yes, come along porter, wiſe is good.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Ie.</speaker>
               <l>And is not acre good?</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Bo.</speaker>
               <l>Yes paſſing good.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Ie.</speaker>
               <p>Why ſhould <hi>Wiſeacre</hi> being put together be nought then?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Bo.</speaker>
               <l>Is not Plumb-porridge good, Sir <hi>Ieffrey?</hi>
               </l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Ie.</speaker>
               <l>Yes.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Wa.</speaker>
               <l>Would I had this trunk full of 'em.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Bo.</speaker>
               <p>Peace Greedi-gut, Plum-porridge is good, and Bag-pudding is good, but put them together, and they are filthy meat.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Ie.</speaker>
               <l>Well, that's true.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Wal.</speaker>
               <l>Right ſir.
<stage>Sets down the Trunk.</stage>
               </l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Ie.</speaker>
               <l>How now?</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Wal.</speaker>
               <p>Hunger is good, and two Woodcocks are good, But the feathers of thoſe two Woodcocks muſt be pluck'd firſt.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Ie.</speaker>
               <l>Hold I charge thee.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Wal.</speaker>
               <p>Y are a ſcurvy Iuſtice, yare man's an Aſſe, and you another with a velvet foot-cloth on your back, I ken ye vary weel, and Iſe knock ye vary weele, if any thing be worth victales, it goes down here.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Bo.</speaker>
               <p>The Devill choake you, if you be a man of your word.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Wal.</speaker>
               <p>
                  <hi>Wiſeacres,</hi> if you would fain know who ha's got this traſh from yee, 'tis I, <hi>Wallace</hi> the <hi>Scot.</hi>
               </p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Both:</speaker>
               <l>
                  <hi>Wallace.</hi>
               </l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Bo.</speaker>
               <l>Flie ſir <hi>Ieffrey,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>He calls us Woodcocks, let's flie and raiſe the Country.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Wal.</speaker>
               <l>D'e ye grumble? raiſe the Devill and ſpare not.</l>
               <stage>Exeunt.</stage>
               <l>Wert thou a cheſt of gold, I'de give thee all for victuals,</l>
               <l>Hunger, they ſay, will break ſtone wals,</l>
               <l>
                  <pb facs="tcp:19967:25"/>Your chops are not ſo hard,</l>
               <l>Ye ſhall burſt tho with iron ribs ye were bar'd,</l>
               <p>—victuals—wine too,—few juſtices doe feed the hungry thus, o theſe <hi>VViſeacres</hi> are the braveſt fel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowes, ſpecially <hi>Engliſh VViſeacres.</hi>
               </p>
            </sp>
            <stage>
               <hi>Enter</hi> Selby <hi>miſerably poore.</hi>
            </stage>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Sel.</speaker>
               <l>I'le now be my own carver, miſery and age</l>
               <l>Want and deſpaire have brought me to deaths doore,</l>
               <l>And ſhall I not enter? yes I will, this key</l>
               <l>Shall doo't, is death ſo ſurly, may a poore man</l>
               <l>Speake ſooner with a King then ſpeake with him</l>
               <l>When he has moſt need of him, ugly leane ſlave,</l>
               <l>So I may ſee him, no matter for a grave.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Wall.</speaker>
               <l>How now, what do'ſt looke for?</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Sel.</speaker>
               <l>For that which a quarter of the world</l>
               <l>Wants, a tree to be hang'd upon.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Wall.</speaker>
               <l>Art weary of thy life?</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Selby.</speaker>
               <p>Yes all men are of their old wives, my life ha's gone up and downe with me this threeſcore and odde yeares, 'tis time to be weary on't I thinke now.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Wal.</speaker>
               <p>And when tha'ſt hang'd thy ſelfe, whither do'ſt thinke to go then?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Sel.</speaker>
               <l>To the Linnen-draper.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>VVa.</speaker>
               <l>What Linnen-draper?</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Sel.</speaker>
               <p>The richeſt in the world, my old Grandmother the Earth, how many paire of ſheets has ſhe had, thinke ye, ſince <hi>Adam</hi> and <hi>Eve</hi> lay together, It's the beſt Inne to lye at, a man ſhall be ſure of good linnen.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Wal.</speaker>
               <l>Who dwels hereabouts?</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Sel.</speaker>
               <p>One upon whom all the poore in the Countrey cryes out.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>VVa.</speaker>
               <l>Whoſe that?</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Sel.</speaker>
               <p>Scarcity, dearth, penurie, famine, hunger, I have
<pb facs="tcp:19967:25"/>
not knowne that man lives by food theſe foure dayes, and therefore I'le deſcend to th' Antipodes, becauſe I'le kicke at this world.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Wall.</speaker>
               <l>Stay, famine ſhall not kill thee, ſit and eate</l>
               <l>Thy belly full, thy cares in good wine drowne,</l>
               <l>By my owne fall I pitty others downe,</l>
               <l>Is't not good cheere?</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Sel.</speaker>
               <p>Brave, I thanke you for it, how many beggers does a rich man eate at his table at one meale, when thoſe few crummes are able to ſave a mans life, how came you ſir into this fearefull neſt of Screech-owles and Ravens?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Wa.</speaker>
               <p>Caſt up by the Sea, I was ſhipwrack'd and loſt all my company.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Sel.</speaker>
               <p>Would I had beene one of 'em, I have loſt more then you have done, I ha' loſt all that I had but my ſinnes, and they hang ſo heavy on my eye-lids, I can ſcarce look ſo high as the brimmes of my hatt to heaven, I have ſuch a minde downwards, I have almoſt forgot who dwels over my head.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Wa.</speaker>
               <l>Looke up, be not afraid, there raignes no tyrant,</l>
               <l>Wud thou hadſt beene with me at ſea.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Sel.</speaker>
               <l>So wud I.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Wa.</speaker>
               <l>Hadſt thou an <hi>Atheiſt</hi> been, and God not known,</l>
               <l>Th'adſt found him in the deepe, there hee's beſt ſhowne,</l>
               <l>He that at Sea is ſhipwrackt, and denyes</l>
               <l>A Deity (being there ſav'd) damn'd lives and dyes,</l>
               <l>Man no where in the twinckling of an eye</l>
               <l>Is throwne ſo neare to hell, or rais'd ſo high</l>
               <l>Towards heaven, then when hee's toſſ'd upon the waves</l>
               <l>It muſt be a hand omnipotent there that ſaves,</l>
               <l>But how came you ſir hither?</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Sel.</speaker>
               <l>I was baniſh'd from <hi>England</hi> (but that grieves me not)</l>
               <l>But I kill'd an old man, he was call'd <hi>Wallace.</hi>
               </l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <pb facs="tcp:19967:26"/>
               <speaker>Wa.</speaker>
               <l>Ha?</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Sel.</speaker>
               <l>
                  <hi>Wallace,</hi> and me thinks hee's ſtill at mine elbow.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Wa.</speaker>
               <l>Elbowe? idle: <hi>Selby</hi> my fathers murderer?</l>
               <l>Thinke not upon it, ſit eat heartily</l>
               <l>Thy laſt, ſit downe, I ſay, never to riſe,</l>
               <l>Drinke wine, drinke deepe, let thy ſoule reele to hell.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Sel.</speaker>
               <l>I am almoſt dead with cold.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Wa.</speaker>
               <l>I'le fetch dry ſticks,</l>
               <l>And with two flints kindle fire, beat out his braines:</l>
               <l>O that phyſicke had the power to make thee yong,</l>
               <l>I'de fetch thee drugs from th'utmoſt of the world,</l>
               <l>And then would arme thee, or, into thy veines</l>
               <l>Halfe my owne bloud I'de power, to lend thee ſtrength,</l>
               <l>That I might kill thee nobly.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Sel.</speaker>
               <l>Be quiet, I'le pay thee.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Wa.</speaker>
               <l>How now?</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Sel.</speaker>
               <l>A ſlumber took me, and me thought old <hi>Wallace</hi>
               </l>
               <l>Clapt me upon the ſhoulder with one hand,</l>
               <l>And with the other pointed to his wounds,</l>
               <l>At which I ſtarted, ſpake, but know not what,</l>
               <l>I'me cold at heart.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Wa.</speaker>
               <l>I'le ſeeke for fire.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Sel.</speaker>
               <l>I thanke ye, if what I utter ye tell to any, I am a dead man,</l>
               <l>You have me at your mercy, and may betray me.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Wa.</speaker>
               <l>Not I, eate and get ſtrength, I'le ſeek for fire,</l>
               <l>Vnleſſe I be a devill (tho I have cauſe</l>
               <l>To kill thee) yet my quicke hand ſhall eſchew it,</l>
               <l>Thy careleſſe confidence does bind me to it,</l>
               <l>This mercy which I ſhow now is for Gods ſake,</l>
               <l>In part of payment of his ſhowne to me,</l>
               <l>If I ſhould kill thee now, thou oweſt me nothing,</l>
               <l>Live, and be ſtill my debter, I ſhall do thee</l>
               <l>More harme to give thee life, then take it from thee,</l>
               <l>Heaven in my fathers bloud who is chiefe ſharer,</l>
               <l>Shall ſtrike for me a revenge more juſt and fairer.</l>
            </sp>
            <stage>Exit.</stage>
            <stage>
               <pb facs="tcp:19967:26"/>
               <hi>Enter</hi> Haſlerig, <hi>poore as th'other with Apples.</hi>
            </stage>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Haſ.</speaker>
               <l>
                  <hi>Selby, Selby,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>How like a Churle thou feed'ſt alone,</l>
               <l>And greedy art to fatten miſery—<hi>Selby?</hi>
               </l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Sel.</speaker>
               <l>Here.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Haſ.</speaker>
               <l>Look I ha' found a jenniting tree.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Sel.</speaker>
               <l>Where ſtands it?</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Haſ.</speaker>
               <l>I'le not tell thee; ſee brave food.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Sel.</speaker>
               <l>Lets taſte it.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Haſ.</speaker>
               <l>Not a paring, what haſt there?</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Sel.</speaker>
               <l>The dole of plenty.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Haſ.</speaker>
               <l>Good old Rogue I thank thee,</l>
               <l>I have a ſtomack like a Lawyer,</l>
               <l>Lets eat fruit when we have fill'd our bellies.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Sel.</speaker>
               <l>Not a bitt.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Haſ.</speaker>
               <l>Ha?</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Sel.</speaker>
               <l>Not a paring of cheeſe.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Haſ.</speaker>
               <l>I muſt.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Sel.</speaker>
               <l>Thou ſhalt not, I pay thee in thy own coyne.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Haſ.</speaker>
               <l>Thy doting age is almoſt at her journies end,</l>
               <l>My youth having far to go needs more proviſion,</l>
               <l>And ile have this—</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Sel.</speaker>
               <l>Hands off
<stage>Kils him.</stage>
               </l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Haſ.</speaker>
               <l>You Dog, you old Devill.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Sel.</speaker>
               <l>I thank thee, thou haſt cut the threed in two,</l>
               <l>Of all my woes, heaven pardon us both, adue.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Haſ.</speaker>
               <l>
                  <hi>Selby,</hi> no water from the hallowed Fount,</l>
               <l>Toucht thee, thou art ſo fatall, <hi>Selby,</hi> dead!</l>
               <l>Gods building which ha's ſtood this threeſcore yeeres,</l>
               <l>This ha's defac'd, would it were up agen</l>
               <l>With ruine of mine own, I never knew</l>
               <l>Partners but one ſtill th'other overthrew,</l>
               <l>
                  <pb facs="tcp:19967:27"/>Thou and I did ſet up with one ſtock of care</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>I</hi> have undone thee, and now all's my ſhare,</l>
               <l>'Tis not ſo ſinfull nor ſo baſe a ſtroke</l>
               <l>To ſpoile a Willow as an old reverend Oke,</l>
               <l>From me th'art gone, but i'le from hence nere fly,</l>
               <l>But ſit by thee, and ſigh, and weep, and die.</l>
            </sp>
            <stage>
               <hi>Enter Sir</hi> Jeffrey, Bolt, <hi>Souldiers.</hi>
            </stage>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Bo.</speaker>
               <p>Stand, that's he who turns his taile to us, which is as much as to ſay, A fart for your Worſhip.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Om.</speaker>
               <l>Down with him.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Sir Jef.</speaker>
               <p>Peace, it's a wilde Bull wee come to ſet upon, and therfore let thoſe Dogs that can faſten bite ſoundly.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Bo.</speaker>
               <p>My harts, we come not to bait an Aſſe in a Beares skin, but a Lion in his own skin, he's a traitour.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Om.</speaker>
               <l>How know we that?</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Bo.</speaker>
               <p>Thus, he hides his face, and wee are not to back a traitor, Sir <hi>Jeffrey,</hi> you'le get between mee and the Gal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lows, if <hi>I</hi> ſtrike him down.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Jeff.</speaker>
               <p>I'le enter into a Recognizance to hang before thou ſhalt hang.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Bo.</speaker>
               <p>If you ſee my heart begin to faint, knock you mee down to put life into me.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Ief.</speaker>
               <l>Feare nothing.
<stage>Bolt ſtrikes him down.</stage>
               </l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Haſ.</speaker>
               <l>Be damn'd both gods and men the act deteſt,</l>
               <l>Oh heaven; wipe this ſinne out for all the reſt.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Bo.</speaker>
               <p>Your ſins are wip'd out ſir, your <hi>Scottiſh</hi> ſcore is paid ſir.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Ief.</speaker>
               <l>Is he down?</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Bo.</speaker>
               <l>He ſprawles, ſtay there's one aſleep by him,</l>
               <l>Shall <hi>I</hi> kill the lice in his head too?</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Ief.</speaker>
               <p>No, wake not a ſleeping Maſtive, the Kings in the field, Lets poſt to him, <hi>Bolt,</hi> thou ſhalt be a Knight as deep as my ſelfe, for this manly deed, as ye go through the
<pb facs="tcp:19967:27"/>
Country, cry aloud, the traitor's dead.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Bo.</speaker>
               <l>Cry it out at the Croſſe, and at the old Palace,</l>
               <l>That <hi>Bolt</hi> was the man that brain'd luſty <hi>Wallace.</hi>
               </l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Om.</speaker>
               <l>The traitor's dead, the traitor's dead, &amp;c.</l>
            </sp>
            <stage>
               <hi>Enter</hi> Wallace, <hi>with dry ſticks and ſtraw, beating two flints.</hi>
            </stage>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Wal.</speaker>
               <l>Thou ſhalt have fire anon old man, ba', murdred?</l>
               <l>What ſhouldſt thou be? the face of <hi>Haſlerig,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>'Tis he, juſt heavens ye have beſtow'd my office</l>
               <l>Vpon ſome other, I thank ye that my bloud</l>
               <l>Stains not my hand, however both did die</l>
               <l>(In love or hate) both ſhall together lie,</l>
               <l>The Coffin you muſt ſleep in is this Cave,</l>
               <l>Whole heaven your winding ſheet, all earth your grave,</l>
               <l>The early Lark ſhall ſadly ring your Knell,</l>
               <l>Your Dirge be ſung by mournfull <hi>Philomell,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>Inſtead of flowres and ſtrewing herbs take theſe,</l>
               <l>And what my charity now fails to do,</l>
               <l>Poor Robin-redbreſt ſhall, my laſt adue,</l>
               <l>I have other ſtreames to ſwim through, or calme</l>
               <l>Venture, 'tis brave when danger's crown'd with palme.</l>
            </sp>
            <stage>Exit.</stage>
            <stage>
               <hi>Enter with Drum and Colours, the Generall of Scot<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land, with</hi> Grimsby, Mentith, Coming, <hi>and Souldiers with blew Caps.</hi>
            </stage>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Gen.</speaker>
               <l>Vpon this field-bed will we lodge this night,</l>
               <l>The earth's a ſouldiers pillow, here pitch our tents.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Men. Om.</speaker>
               <l>Vp with our tents.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Gen.</speaker>
               <l>To councell, beat a Drum.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Gri.</speaker>
               <l>Beat it for action then, and not for words,</l>
               <l>Vpon our Speare points our beſt counſell fits,</l>
               <l>
                  <pb facs="tcp:19967:28"/>Follow that (noble Generall) up with no tents</l>
               <l>If you dare hold me worthy to adviſe,</l>
               <l>But with an eaſie march move gently on.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Gen.</speaker>
               <l>You ſpeak againſt the Scholerſhip of war.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Gri.</speaker>
               <l>Now their Beef-pots, and their Cans,</l>
               <l>Are toſſ'd in ſtead of Pikes, their Armes are thrown</l>
               <l>About their Wenches middles, there's their cloſe feight,</l>
               <l>Let us not loſe the forelock in our hands,</l>
               <l>Of us they dream not, yet we are as free-born</l>
               <l>As th' <hi>Engliſh</hi> King himſelf, be not their ſlaves,</l>
               <l>Free <hi>Scotland,</hi> or in <hi>England</hi> dig our graves.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Within.</speaker>
               <l>A <hi>Wallace,</hi> A <hi>Wallace,</hi> A <hi>Wallace!</hi>
               </l>
            </sp>
            <stage>Enter Rugeroſſe a Scottiſh Herald.</stage>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Gen.</speaker>
               <l>
                  <hi>Rugeroſſe,</hi> what cry is this?</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Ruge.</speaker>
               <l>Of the whole Army,</l>
               <l>Grown wild twixt joy and admiration,</l>
               <l>At the ſight of <hi>Wallace.</hi>
               </l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Om.</speaker>
               <l>Ha.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Ru.</speaker>
               <l>That dreadleſſe Souldier,</l>
               <l>For whom all <hi>Scotland</hi> ſhed a ſea of teares</l>
               <l>As deep as that in which men thought him dead,</l>
               <l>Sets with his preſence all their hearts on fire,</l>
               <l>That have but ſight of him.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Within.</speaker>
               <l>A <hi>Wallace,</hi> A <hi>Wallace.</hi>
               </l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Gri.</speaker>
               <l>Intreat him hither.</l>
            </sp>
         </div>
         <div n="4" type="act">
            <head>Act. IIII.</head>
            <stage>
               <hi>Enter</hi> Wallace <hi>with Drum, Colours and Souldiers, they all imbrace him.</hi>
            </stage>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Com.</speaker>
               <l>D'ee heare th' <hi>Engliſh</hi> march? they are at hand.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <pb facs="tcp:19967:28"/>
               <speaker>Gen.</speaker>
               <l>Now <hi>Grimsby,</hi> they for Pikes are toſſing Cans.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Gri.</speaker>
               <l>
                  <hi>I</hi> am glad our thunder wakes 'em.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Men.</speaker>
               <l>Shall we on?</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Gen.</speaker>
               <l>Whether iſt beſt to ſtop 'em in their march,</l>
               <l>Or here to make a ſtand and front 'em.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Om.</speaker>
               <l>Stand.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Gen.</speaker>
               <l>Or elſe retire back to the ſpacious Plaine</l>
               <l>For battaile far more advantagious.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Wal.</speaker>
               <l>And ſo retiring be held runawayes.</l>
               <l>Here ſtands my body, and ere this <hi>Engliſh</hi> Wolves</l>
               <l>Stretch their jaws ne're ſo wide, from hence ſhall drive</l>
               <l>I'le rather lie here fifty fathome deep,</l>
               <l>Now at this minute, then by giving back</l>
               <l>One foot, prolong my life a thouſand yeers.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Gen.</speaker>
               <l>Then let us die or live here.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Om.</speaker>
               <l>Arme, arme.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Wal.</speaker>
               <l>Fall back? not I, death of my ſelfe is part,</l>
               <l>I'le never flie my ſelf, heres no falſe heart:</l>
               <l>Lets in our riſing be, or in our falls</l>
               <l>Like bels which ring alike at Funerals,</l>
               <l>As at Coronations, each man meet his wound,</l>
               <l>With ſelf-ſame joy as Kings go to be crown'd,</l>
               <l>Where charge you?</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Gen.</speaker>
               <l>In the battaile, valiant <hi>Grimsby</hi>
               </l>
               <l>Is Generall of our Horſe, the infantry</l>
               <l>By comming is commanded, <hi>Mentith</hi> and you</l>
               <l>Shall come up in the Reare.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>VVal.</speaker>
               <l>The Reare.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Gen.</speaker>
               <l>Yes.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Wal.</speaker>
               <l>No, ſir.</l>
               <l>Let <hi>Mentith, Wallace</hi> ſhall not.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Gen.</speaker>
               <l>He may chooſe.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Wal.</speaker>
               <l>Were I to hunt within a Wilderneſſe</l>
               <l>A herd of Tigres, I would ſcorn to cheat</l>
               <l>My glories from the ſweat of others brows,</l>
               <l>
                  <pb facs="tcp:19967:29"/>By encountring the fierce beaſts at ſecond hand,</l>
               <l>When others ſtrength had tam'd him, let me meet</l>
               <l>The Lion being new rowz'd, and when his eyes</l>
               <l>Sparkle with flames of indignation,</l>
               <l>I ha' not in the Academe of War</l>
               <l>So oft read Lectures, chief now to come lag,</l>
               <l>Ile ha' the leading of the Van or none.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Gen.</speaker>
               <l>Then none, you wrong us all,</l>
               <l>Men now are plac'd, and muſt not be diſhonour'd.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Wal.</speaker>
               <l>So, diſhonour'd.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Gen.</speaker>
               <l>Charge in the Reare for Gods ſake, now to ſtand</l>
               <l>On terms of worth hazards the fate of all.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Wal.</speaker>
               <l>Well be't ſo then, the Reare, ſee you yon hill,</l>
               <l>Yonder i'le ſtand, and tho I ſhould ſee Butchers,</l>
               <l>Cut all your throats like ſheep, I will not ſtirre</l>
               <l>Till I ſee time my ſelfe.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Gen.</speaker>
               <l>Your pleaſure, on,</l>
               <l>Each Leader ſpend his beſt direction.
<stage>Exeunt.</stage>
               </l>
            </sp>
            <stage>
               <hi>Enter King,</hi> Percy, <hi>and</hi> Bruce, Hertford, <hi>Sir</hi> Ieffrey, <hi>and</hi> Bolt, <hi>with Drums and Colours.</hi>
            </stage>
            <sp>
               <speaker>King.</speaker>
               <l>Which is the fellow?</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Bo.</speaker>
               <l>I am the party ſir.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Per.</speaker>
               <l>Stand forth before the King,</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Jef.</speaker>
               <l>Nay, he's no ſheep-biter.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>King.</speaker>
               <l>Didſt thou kill <hi>Wallace?</hi>
               </l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Bo.</speaker>
               <p>Yes marry did I ſir, if I ſhould be hang'd here before yee, I would not deny it.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>King.</speaker>
               <l>How didſt thou kill him? hand to hand?</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Bo.</speaker>
               <p>Hand to hand, as Dog-killers kill dogs, ſo I beat out his brains I'me ſure.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>K.</speaker>
               <l>Me thinks, thou ſhouldſt not look him in the face.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Bo.</speaker>
               <l>No more I did, <hi>I</hi> came behind his back &amp; felld him.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>King.</speaker>
               <l>Art thou a Gentleman?</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <pb facs="tcp:19967:29"/>
               <speaker>Bolt.</speaker>
               <p>I am no gentleman borne, my Father was a poore Fletcher in Grubſtreet, but <hi>I</hi> am a gentleman by my place.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Kin.</speaker>
               <l>What place?</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Bo.</speaker>
               <l>A Juſtices Clarke, ſir <hi>Jeffery Wiſeacres.</hi>
               </l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Je.</speaker>
               <p>My man, if it pleaſe your Majeſty, an honeſt true Knave.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Kin.</speaker>
               <l>Give to ſir <hi>Wiſeacres</hi> Clark an hundred pounds.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Jef.</speaker>
               <l>I thank your grace.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Bolt.</speaker>
               <l>God confound all your foes at the ſame rate.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>K.</speaker>
               <l>But if this <hi>Wallace,</hi> ſirra, be alive now,</l>
               <l>You and your hundred pounds ſhall both be hang'd.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Bolt.</speaker>
               <l>Nay I will be hang'd ere I part from my money,</l>
               <l>Who payes, who payes?</l>
            </sp>
            <stage>
               <hi>Enter</hi> Clifford.</stage>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Clif.</speaker>
               <l>Charge, charge.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>K.</speaker>
               <l>The news brave <hi>Clifford.</hi>
               </l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Cli.</speaker>
               <p>The daring <hi>Scot</hi> fuller of inſolence then ſtrength Stand forth to bid us battell.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>K.</speaker>
               <l>Throw defiance back downe their throats, and of our Heralds</l>
               <l>Northumberland the honor ſhall be thine, tell'um</l>
               <l>We come to ſcourge their pride with whips of ſteele,</l>
               <l>Their City hath from Iuſtice ſnatch'd her ſword</l>
               <l>To ſtrike their Soveraigne, who ha's turn'd the point</l>
               <l>Vpon their own breaſts, tell 'em this.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Per.</speaker>
               <l>I ſhall.
<stage>Exit.</stage>
               </l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Cliff.</speaker>
               <l>Where's noble <hi>Bruce?</hi>
               </l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Bru.</speaker>
               <l>Here.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Cliff.</speaker>
               <l>I have a meſſage, but tis more honorable, ſent to you too,</l>
               <l>The Herald ſaies that <hi>Wallace</hi> dares ye, his</l>
               <l>Spite is all at you, and if your ſpirit be great</l>
               <l>
                  <pb facs="tcp:19967:30"/>As his, you finde him in the reare.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>K.</speaker>
               <l>Hang up that wiſeacres, and the fool his man.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Bolt.</speaker>
               <l>My maſter, not me ſir, I have a Recognizance of him</l>
               <l>To ſtand betwixt me and the gallows.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>K.</speaker>
               <l>A Kings word muſt be kept, hang 'em both.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Bolt.</speaker>
               <p>One word more good Sir, before I go to this geere,</p>
               <p>If a Kings word muſt be kept, why was it not kept, when he gave me the 100. li. wipe out one, I'le wipe out the other.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Kin.</speaker>
               <p>That jeſt hath ſav'd your lives, let me ſee you fight to day.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Jeff.</speaker>
               <l>Bravely like Cocks.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Bolt.</speaker>
               <l>Now <hi>Wallace</hi> look to your coxcombe.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Omn.</speaker>
               <l>Move on.</l>
            </sp>
            <stage>
               <hi>Enter to them the</hi> Scottiſh <hi>Army, and are beaten off.</hi>
            </stage>
            <sp>
               <speaker>King.</speaker>
               <l>We have fleſh'd them ſoundly.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Cliff.</speaker>
               <l>I would not wiſh to meet with braver ſpirits.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>K.</speaker>
               <l>Stay, <hi>Bruce,</hi> what's yonder on the hill?</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Bru.</speaker>
               <l>They are Collors.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Kin.</speaker>
               <l>Why do they mangle thus their Armies limbes?</l>
               <l>Whats that ſo farre off?</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Br.</speaker>
               <l>Sure 'tis the Reare, where burns the black brand,</l>
               <l>Kindles all this fire, I meane the Traytor <hi>Wallace?</hi>
               </l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>King.</speaker>
               <l>What turn'd Coward?</l>
               <l>A dogge of ſo good mouth, and ſtand at bay?</l>
               <l>If in this heat of fight we breake their ranks,</l>
               <l>Preſſe through, and charge that devill, <hi>Bruce</hi> thy ſelfe.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Bru.</speaker>
               <l>To hell if I can chaſe him.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Kin.</speaker>
               <l>Charge up ſtrong, harke, brave,</l>
               <l>Let now our hands be warriors, not our tongues.</l>
            </sp>
            <stage>Exeunt.</stage>
            <stage>
               <pb facs="tcp:19967:30"/>
               <hi>Enter the</hi> Scottiſh <hi>Army, Generall</hi> Grimsby, Coming, Mentith.</stage>
            <sp>
               <speaker>A cry within.</speaker>
               <l>They flye, they flie.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Generall.</speaker>
               <l>The <hi>Engliſh</hi> ſhrink, knit all our nerves</l>
               <l>And faſten Fortunes offer.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Gri.</speaker>
               <l>Keep ſteedy footing, the daye is loſt if you ſtir,</l>
               <l>Stirre not, but ſtand the tempeſt.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Coming.</speaker>
               <l>I cry on.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Gen.</speaker>
               <l>And I.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Grim.</speaker>
               <p>So do not I, this ſtarting backe is but an <hi>Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſh</hi> earth-quake, which to duſt, ſhakes rotten towers, but builds the ſound more ſtrong.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Gen.</speaker>
               <l>Lets on, and dare death in the thickeſt throng.</l>
            </sp>
            <stage>
               <hi>Enter the</hi> Engliſh <hi>Army, and encompaſſe them.</hi>
            </stage>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Grim.</speaker>
               <l>Did I not give you warning of this whirpoole</l>
               <l>For going too farre?</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Ment.</speaker>
               <l>We are all dead men, yet fight</l>
               <l>So long as legges and Armes laſt.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>King.</speaker>
               <l>In how quicke time</l>
               <l>Have we about you built a wall of braſſe?</l>
               <l>Had he whom here you call your Generall</l>
               <l>A Souldier beene remarkable of great breeding,</l>
               <l>And now to be caught with lyme-twigs?</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Generall.</speaker>
               <l>Keepe our ground.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Grim.</speaker>
               <l>If we muſt fall, fall bravely.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Ment.</speaker>
               <l>Wound for wound.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Alarum.</speaker>
               <l>
                  <hi>Exeunt King and</hi> Bruce <hi>purſuing the</hi> Scots.</l>
            </sp>
            <stage>Clifford, Percy, Grimsby, <hi>and</hi> Generall <hi>ſtay.</hi>
            </stage>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Cliff.</speaker>
               <p>Take breath, I would not have the world rob'd
<pb facs="tcp:19967:31"/>
of two ſuch ſpirits, poaſt to the King, and tell him that the nobleſt Harts of the whole heard are hunted to the toyle,</p>
               <p>Aske whether they ſhall fall, or live for gaine.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Meſſenger.</speaker>
               <l>I ſhall.</l>
               <stage>Exit.</stage>
               <l>Charge.</l>
            </sp>
            <stage>
               <hi>Enter</hi> Mentith <hi>at another doore.</hi>
            </stage>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Ment.</speaker>
               <p>For honours ſake come downe, and ſave thy Countrey.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Wal.</speaker>
               <l>Whoſe is the day?</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Ment.</speaker>
               <l>Tis <hi>Edwards,</hi> come reſcue</l>
               <l>Our Generall, and the noble <hi>Grimsby.</hi>
               </l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Wal.</speaker>
               <l>Who?</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Ment.</speaker>
               <l>Our Generall and ſtout <hi>Grimsby</hi> are encloſd</l>
               <l>With quick-ſets made of ſteele, come fetch them off,</l>
               <l>Or all is loſt.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Wal.</speaker>
               <l>Is the day loſt?</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Ment.</speaker>
               <l>Loſt, loſt.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Wal.</speaker>
               <l>Vnleſſe the day be quite loſt, I'le not ſtirre.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Ment.</speaker>
               <l>Tis quite loſt.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Wal.</speaker>
               <l>Why then deſcend amaine, art ſure tis loſt?</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Ment.</speaker>
               <l>Yes.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Wal.</speaker>
               <l>Then wee'le winne it againe.</l>
            </sp>
            <stage>Enter Meſſenger.</stage>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Clif.</speaker>
               <l>How now?</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Meſ.</speaker>
               <l>The King proclaimes that man a traytor</l>
               <l>That ſaves when he may kill.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Cliff.</speaker>
               <l>Charge them blacke day,</l>
               <l>The Lyon hunts a Lyon for his prey.</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>A fight.</hi>
               </l>
            </sp>
            <stage>
               <pb facs="tcp:19967:31"/>
               <hi>Enter</hi> Wallace <hi>and Souldiers, beat off the</hi> Engliſh, <hi>the Generall, and</hi> Grimsby <hi>ſlaine.</hi>
            </stage>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Generall.</speaker>
               <l>Too late.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Wall.</speaker>
               <l>Why then farewell,</l>
               <l>I'le make what haſte I can to follow thee,</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Bruce, Bruce,</hi> I am here, 'tis <hi>Wallace</hi> calls thee,</l>
               <l>Dares thee.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Bru.</speaker>
               <l>Tho I nere ſtoopt unto a traitors lure,</l>
               <l>I ſcorne thine, why do'ſt thou ſingle me,</l>
               <l>Yet turnſt thy weapon downward to the earth?</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Wal.</speaker>
               <l>Lets breathe and talke.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Bru.</speaker>
               <l>I'le parly with no traytor but with blows.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>VVal.</speaker>
               <l>Ye ſhall have blows your guts full,</l>
               <l>I am no traytor.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Bru.</speaker>
               <p>Why 'gainſt thy Soveraigne lifts thou then thy ſword?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Wal.</speaker>
               <l>You ſee I lift it not.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Bru.</speaker>
               <l>Tell <hi>Edward</hi> ſo thy King.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Wal.</speaker>
               <l>Longſhancks was never Soveraigne of mine,</l>
               <l>Nor ſhall whilſt <hi>Bruce</hi> lives, <hi>Bruce</hi> is my Soveraigne,</l>
               <l>Thou art but baſtard <hi>Engliſh, Scotch</hi> true borne,</l>
               <l>Th'art made a maſtive 'mongſt a heard of wolves,</l>
               <l>To weary thoſe thou ſhouldſt be ſhepheard of.</l>
               <l>The fury of the battell now declines,</l>
               <l>And take my counſell, though I ſeeme thy foe,</l>
               <l>Waſh both thy hands in bloud, and when anon</l>
               <l>The <hi>Engliſh</hi> in their Tents their deeds do boaſt,</l>
               <l>Lift thou thy bloudy hands up, and boaſt thine,</l>
               <l>And with a ſharpe eye note, but with what ſcorne,</l>
               <l>The <hi>Engliſh</hi> pay thy merit.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Bru.</speaker>
               <l>This I'le try.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Wal.</speaker>
               <l>Dar'ſt thou alone meet me in <hi>Glaſco</hi>-moore,</l>
               <l>And there I'le tell thee more?</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Bru.</speaker>
               <l>Thou haſt no treaſon towards me?</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <pb facs="tcp:19967:32"/>
               <speaker>VVa.</speaker>
               <l>Here's my hand,</l>
               <l>I am cleare as innocence, had I meant treaſon</l>
               <l>Here could I worke it on thee, I have none.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Bru.</speaker>
               <l>In <hi>Glaſco-moore</hi> I'le meet thee, fare thee well.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>VVa.</speaker>
               <l>The time.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Bru.</speaker>
               <l>Some two houres hence.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>VVa.</speaker>
               <l>There I will untie</l>
               <l>A knot, at which hangs death or Soveraigntie.</l>
            </sp>
            <stage>Exeunt.</stage>
            <stage>
               <hi>Enter the</hi> Engliſh <hi>Army.</hi>
            </stage>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Kin.</speaker>
               <l>We have ſwet hard to day.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Cli.</speaker>
               <l>Twas a brave hunting.
<stage>Bolt <hi>offers to lay his Coat under the king.</hi>
                  </stage>
               </l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Kin.</speaker>
               <l>Sit, ſome wine</l>
               <l>Away in the field all fellows, whoſe is this?</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Bolt.</speaker>
               <p>It was my Coat at Armes, but now tis yours at legges.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>King.</speaker>
               <l>Away, why giveſt thou me a cuſhion?</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Bolt.</speaker>
               <p>Becauſe of the two, <hi>I</hi> take you to be the better man.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>King.</speaker>
               <l>A ſouldiers coat ſhall never be ſo baſe</l>
               <l>To lye beneath my heele, th'art in this place</l>
               <l>My fellow, and companion, a health to all in <hi>England.</hi>
               </l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Omn.</speaker>
               <l>Let it come.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Cliff.</speaker>
               <l>Is not this he that kill'd <hi>VVallace?</hi>
               </l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Bolt.</speaker>
               <l>No ſir, <hi>I</hi> am onely he that ſaid ſo,</l>
               <l>As you ſit, ſo did <hi>I</hi> lye.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>King.</speaker>
               <l>Sirra, where's your maſter?</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Bol.</speaker>
               <l>My maſter is ſhot.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>King.</speaker>
               <l>How ſhot, where?</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Bol.</speaker>
               <l>I'th backe.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Clif.</speaker>
               <l>Oh he ranne away.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Bol.</speaker>
               <p>No, my Lord, but his harneſſe Cap was blowne off, and he running after it to catch it, was ſhot betweene necke and ſhoulders, and when he ſtood upright he had two heads.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>King.</speaker>
               <l>Two heads how?</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <pb facs="tcp:19967:32"/>
               <speaker>Bolt.</speaker>
               <p>Yes truly, his own head and the arrow head, it was twenty to one that <hi>I</hi> had not beene ſhot before him.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>King.</speaker>
               <l>Why prethee?</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Bolt.</speaker>
               <p>Becauſe my Knights name being <hi>Wiſeacres,</hi> and mine <hi>Bolt,</hi> and you know a fooles bolt is ſoon ſhot.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Clif.</speaker>
               <p>He ha's pind the foole upon his maſters ſhoulder very handſomly.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>King.</speaker>
               <p>Sirra, go ſeek your maſter, and bid him take or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der for burying of the dead.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Bolt.</speaker>
               <p>
                  <hi>I</hi> ſhall Sir, and whilſt he takes order for the bu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rials of the dead, i'le take order for the ſtomacks of the living.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>King.</speaker>
               <l>How fought to day our <hi>Engliſh?</hi>
               </l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Per.</speaker>
               <l>Bravely.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>King.</speaker>
               <l>How the <hi>Scots?</hi>
               </l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Cliff.</speaker>
               <l>The pangs of war are like to child-bed throwes</l>
               <l>Bitter in ſuffering, but the ſtorme being paſt,</l>
               <l>The talk, as of ſcap't ſhipwrack ſweet, doth taſte,</l>
               <l>The death of the <hi>Scotch</hi> Generall went to my heart,</l>
               <l>He had in him of man aſmuch as any,</l>
               <l>And for ought I think, his bloud was poorly ſold</l>
               <l>By his own Countrymen, rather then ſought by us.</l>
               <l>Had not the Reare where <hi>Wallace</hi> did command,</l>
               <l>Stood and given ayme, it had bin a day</l>
               <l>Bloudy and diſmall, and whoſe hard to ſay,</l>
               <l>Sir, you ſhall give me leave to drink a health</l>
               <l>To all the valiant <hi>Scots.</hi>
               </l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>King.</speaker>
               <l>
                  <hi>Clifford,</hi> I'le pledge thee, give me my bowle.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Clif.</speaker>
               <l>Sir, <hi>I</hi> remembred <hi>Wallace</hi> in my draught.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>King.</speaker>
               <l>
                  <hi>I</hi> did not, ſo this cup were <hi>Wallace</hi> Skull,</l>
               <l>I'de drinke it full with bloud, for it would ſave</l>
               <l>The lives of thouſands.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Clif</speaker>
               <l>
                  <hi>I</hi> for your Kingdoms would not pledge it ſo.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Per.</speaker>
               <l>
                  <hi>I</hi> would, no matter how a traitor falls.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <pb facs="tcp:19967:33"/>
               <speaker>King.</speaker>
               <l>
                  <hi>Percy,</hi> ten thouſand Crowns ſhould buy</l>
               <l>That traitors head, if <hi>I</hi> could hav't for money.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Clif.</speaker>
               <l>
                  <hi>I</hi> would give</l>
               <l>Twice twenty thouſand Crowns to have his head</l>
               <l>On my ſwords point cut from him with this arme,</l>
               <l>But how i'th field, nobly, hand to hand, not this ſtraw</l>
               <l>To a hangman that ſhould bring it me.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>King.</speaker>
               <l>Let that paſſe,</l>
               <l>Wher's <hi>Bruce,</hi> our noble Earle of <hi>Carrick?</hi>
               </l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Per.</speaker>
               <l>I ſaw him not to day,</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Clif.</speaker>
               <l>I did, and ſaw his ſword</l>
               <l>Like to a Reapers Sithe, mow down the <hi>Scots.</hi>
               </l>
               <stage>
                  <hi>Enter</hi> Bruce.</stage>
               <l>Here he comes.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>King.</speaker>
               <l>Brave Armory, a rampant Lion within a field all Gules,</l>
               <l>Where haſt been <hi>Bruce?</hi>
               </l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Bruce.</speaker>
               <l>Following the execution which we held</l>
               <l>Three <hi>Engliſh</hi> miles in length.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>King.</speaker>
               <l>Give him ſome wine, art not thirſty?</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Bruce.</speaker>
               <l>Yes for <hi>Scottiſh</hi> bloud, I never ſhall have</l>
               <l>Enough on't, the Kings health.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Omnes.</speaker>
               <l>Let come.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Per.</speaker>
               <l>How greedily you <hi>Scot</hi> drinks his own bloud!</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Omnes.</speaker>
               <l>Ha, ha, ha.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>K.</speaker>
               <l>If he ſhould taſte your bitterneſſe, 'twere not well.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Bruce.</speaker>
               <l>What's that ye all laugh'd at?</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Clif.</speaker>
               <l>Nothing but a jeſt.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Bruce.</speaker>
               <l>Nay, good Sir tell me.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>King.</speaker>
               <l>An idle jeſt, more wine for <hi>Bruce.</hi>
               </l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Bruce.</speaker>
               <l>No more, I have drunk too much,</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Wallace</hi> and I did parlee.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <pb facs="tcp:19967:33"/>
               <speaker>Per.</speaker>
               <l>How in words?</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Bruce.</speaker>
               <l>No <hi>Percy,</hi> I'me no prater, 'twas with ſwords,</l>
               <l>Your laughing jeſt was not at me?</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Omnes.</speaker>
               <l>Sir, no.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>King.</speaker>
               <l>
                  <hi>Bruce</hi> would fain quarrell,</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Bruce.</speaker>
               <l>I ha done ſir.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>King.</speaker>
               <l>Peace, what Trumpet's that?</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Clif.</speaker>
               <l>From the enemy ſure.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>King.</speaker>
               <l>Go learn.</l>
            </sp>
            <stage>
               <hi>Enter</hi> Rugecroſſe <hi>a Scottiſh Herald.</hi>
            </stage>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Ruge.</speaker>
               <l>I come from <hi>Wallace.</hi>
               </l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>King.</speaker>
               <l>So Sir, what of him?</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Ruge.</speaker>
               <l>Thus he ſpeaks.</l>
               <l>He bids me dare you to a freſh battaile, by to morrowes ſunne,</l>
               <l>Army to Army, troup to troup, he challenges,</l>
               <l>Or to ſave bloud, fifty to fifty, ſhall the ſtrife decide,</l>
               <l>Or one to one.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>King.</speaker>
               <l>A Herald to the traitor.</l>
               <l>Go and thus ſpeak, we bring whips of ſteele,</l>
               <l>To ſcourge Rebellion, not to ſtand the braves</l>
               <l>Of a baſe daring vaſſall, bid him ere that Sun</l>
               <l>Which he calls up be riſen, pay it and ſave</l>
               <l>His Country and himſelfe from ruine, charge him on his head,</l>
               <l>To make his quick ſubmiſſion; if he ſlow the minutes,</l>
               <l>Wee'le proclaime in thunder his and his Countries ruine,</l>
               <l>Go be gon, Arme.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Omnes.</speaker>
               <l>Arme, Arme.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>King.</speaker>
               <l>A Land that's ſick at heart muſt take ſharp pils,</l>
               <l>For dangerous phyſick beſt cures dangerous ils.</l>
            </sp>
            <stage>Exeunt.</stage>
         </div>
         <div n="5" type="act">
            <pb facs="tcp:19967:34"/>
            <head>Actus V.</head>
            <stage>
               <hi>Enter</hi> Bruce <hi>and</hi> Clifford.</stage>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Bruce.</speaker>
               <l>As you are a ſouldier, as y' are noble</l>
               <l>I charge you and conjure you to unclaſpe</l>
               <l>A book in which I am graveld.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Cliff.</speaker>
               <l>Perhaps I cannot.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Bruce.</speaker>
               <l>Yes, if you dare you can.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Clif.</speaker>
               <l>Dare? <hi>Clifford</hi> dares</l>
               <l>Do any thing but wrong and what's not juſt.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Bruce.</speaker>
               <l>Then tell me ſir, what was that bitter ſcorn,</l>
               <l>Which I like poyſon taſted in my wine?</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Clif.</speaker>
               <l>I care not if I doe, becauſe I love vertue even in</l>
               <l>My enemy, the bowle of wine kiſſing your lip.</l>
               <l>Behold, quoth one how eagerly you <hi>Scot,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>Drinks his own bloud.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Bruce.</speaker>
               <l>You <hi>Scot</hi> drinks his own bloud, which <hi>Scot?</hi>
               </l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Clif.</speaker>
               <l>Beſt wake ſome Oracle.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Bruce.</speaker>
               <l>Who brake the jeſt upon me?</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Clif.</speaker>
               <l>Pray pardon me.
<stage>Exit Cli</stage>
               </l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Bruce.</speaker>
               <l>The Oracle I'le wake is here, oh <hi>Wallace,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>I ne're had eyes till now, they were clos'd up</l>
               <l>By braving <hi>Engliſh,</hi> witchcraft drinks his own bloud,</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>England</hi> my ſtepdame take my bitter curſe,</l>
               <l>Thy own nails teare thy own bowels, oh my parent</l>
               <l>Dear <hi>Scotland,</hi> I no more will be a goad,</l>
               <l>Pricking thy ſides, but if ere I draw a ſword,</l>
               <l>It ſhall be double-edg'd with bloud and fire,</l>
               <l>To burn and drown this Kingdome and this King.</l>
            </sp>
            <stage>
               <pb facs="tcp:19967:34"/>
               <hi>Enter a Gentleman.</hi>
            </stage>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Gent.</speaker>
               <l>My Generall</l>
               <l>Charg'd me in privacie to give you theſe.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Bruce.</speaker>
               <l>Thanks noble <hi>Clifford,</hi> what did he bid thee ſay?</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Gent.</speaker>
               <l>Nothing but ſo.
<stage>Exit.</stage>
               </l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Bruce.</speaker>
               <l>A pair of Spurs, <hi>Bruce</hi> nere was runaway,</l>
               <l>Twelve ſilver pence, oh bitter ſcorn, with <hi>Judas,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>I</hi> have betray'd my Maſter, my dear Country,</l>
               <l>And here's the embleme of my treachery,</l>
               <l>To haſten to ſome tree, and deſperate die,</l>
               <l>Twelve ſterling ſilver pence, ſterling, ha ſterling,</l>
               <l>'Tis a limbe of <hi>Scotland,</hi> ſpurs for flight,</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Clifford,</hi> i'le thither, comment I wrong or right.</l>
            </sp>
            <stage>Exit.</stage>
            <stage>
               <hi>Enter</hi> Grimsby, Mentith, Coming, <hi>Engliſh Herald, and Rouge-croſſe.</hi>
            </stage>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Ment.</speaker>
               <l>Stay noble <hi>Grimsby,</hi> ere he further paſſe</l>
               <l>One of us certifie our Generall,</l>
               <l>Perhaps hee'l not admit him to his preſence.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Grim.</speaker>
               <l>'Tis like ſo, ſtay him here, that pains be mine.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Com.</speaker>
               <l>Let <hi>Ruge-croſſe</hi> bring his pleaſure.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Grim.</speaker>
               <l>Come agreed.</l>
            </sp>
            <stage>
               <hi>Exeunt</hi> Grimsby, <hi>and</hi> Ruge-croſſe.</stage>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Men.</speaker>
               <p>You bring from <hi>Longſhanks</hi> ſome ſtrange meſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſage now.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Com.</speaker>
               <l>At leaſt he ſends his Gauntlet.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Men.</speaker>
               <l>Gauntlet, no the <hi>Engliſh</hi>
               </l>
               <l>Fight not two dayes together, but like ſwaggerers,</l>
               <l>A fray being made up with a wound or ſo,</l>
               <l>The man whoſe throat before ſhould have been cut,</l>
               <l>
                  <pb facs="tcp:19967:35"/>Is a ſworn brother, now we have mall'd your Nation,</l>
               <l>Thei'le fawn on us like Spaniels, will they not?</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Com.</speaker>
               <l>And that's thy errand, iſt not?</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Ment.</speaker>
               <p>Commonly, when <hi>Engliſh</hi> ſee at cuffs they are too weak, they fall to fiſhing, and then bait the hook with mercie, and the Kings pardon, at which who bites ha's his ſwallowing ſpoiled for ever, there's no <hi>Scot</hi> but ſcorns to hang his hope on your Kings promiſes, be it nere ſo ſmoothly gilded.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Herald.</speaker>
               <l>He gilds none ſir.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Ment.</speaker>
               <p>
                  <hi>I</hi> warrant he would pawn half his Dominions to ſhake hands with <hi>Wallace,</hi> and be friends.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Com.</speaker>
               <l>Had he but him in's Court, he would out-ſhine</l>
               <l>His capring gallants, be would dote on him,</l>
               <l>As <hi>Jupiter</hi> did on <hi>Ganymede,</hi> and make him</l>
               <l>His chief Minion.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Herald.</speaker>
               <p>Hee does already ſo really dote upon him, 'tis not yet the age of one houre ſince my Maſter ſware to give ten thouſand Crowns to <hi>Scot</hi> or <hi>Engliſh,</hi> that were ſo bold to bring him <hi>Wallace's</hi> head.</p>
            </sp>
            <stage>Enter Ruge-croſſe.</stage>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Ruge.</speaker>
               <l>The <hi>Engliſh</hi> Herald.</l>
            </sp>
            <stage>
               <hi>Exeunt</hi> Ruge <hi>and</hi> Herald.</stage>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Ment.</speaker>
               <l>Ten thouſand Crowns.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Com.</speaker>
               <l>Would make a faire ſhew in our purſes <hi>Jack.</hi>
               </l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Ment.</speaker>
               <l>
                  <hi>I</hi> could pick out five thouſand heads,</l>
               <l>That <hi>I</hi> durſt boldly ſell him at that rate.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Com.</speaker>
               <l>Ten thouſand Crowns.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Ment.</speaker>
               <l>
                  <hi>I</hi> and Court wind-falls too,</l>
               <l>Some <hi>Engliſh</hi> Earldome or ſo, here is none but friends,</l>
               <l>Should you betray the conference, I care not,</l>
               <l>I would deny it, and I would oreſway</l>
               <l>Your proofs tho neere ſo maſſie.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <pb facs="tcp:19967:35"/>
               <speaker>Com.</speaker>
               <l>It ſhall not need, beleeve me worthy <hi>Mentith.</hi>
               </l>
               <l>What here you looke is ſafe.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Ment.</speaker>
               <p>Shall we earne this <hi>Engliſh</hi> gold, ten thouſand crownes?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Com.</speaker>
               <l>My hand.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Ment.</speaker>
               <l>They are ours, hee's dead.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Com.</speaker>
               <l>No more, he comes.</l>
            </sp>
            <stage>
               <hi>Enter</hi> Wallace, Grimsbie, <hi>Herald.</hi>
            </stage>
            <sp>
               <speaker>VVal.</speaker>
               <l>I am to him no vaſſal, hee's a tyrant,</l>
               <l>So tell him, ere his frowne ſhall bend my knee,</l>
               <l>This ſhall be hang'd upon the gallow tree,</l>
               <l>For my appearance tell him this, I'le dyne</l>
               <l>On Chriſtmas day next in his <hi>Engliſh</hi> Court,</l>
               <l>And in his great Hall at Weſtminſter, at's owne boord,</l>
               <l>Wee'le drink <hi>Scotch</hi> healths in his ſtanding cups of gold:</l>
               <l>His blacke Iackes hand in hand about his Court</l>
               <l>Shall march with our blew bonnets, we'le eate nothing</l>
               <l>But what our ſwords ſhall carve, ſo tell his Souldiers,</l>
               <l>Wee'le ſit like Lords there whilſt they rayle like ſlaves,</l>
               <l>Go with <hi>Scotch</hi> threats, pay backe your <hi>Engliſh</hi> braves.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Grim.</speaker>
               <l>Youle make the <hi>Engliſh</hi> mad.
<stage>Exit Herald.</stage>
               </l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Omn.</speaker>
               <l>A brave defiance.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>VVal.</speaker>
               <l>Defiance,</l>
               <l>Lets mad them more, they ſhall not ſleep to night,</l>
               <l>Good <hi>Grimsbie</hi> beat a drum, let bon-fires ſhine</l>
               <l>Through all our army, as if our Tents were burnt,</l>
               <l>And we diſlodg'd, but recollect our troops</l>
               <l>Into an ordered body, ſome thing wee'le do</l>
               <l>To make our Chronicles ſwell with <hi>Engliſh</hi> rue.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Grim.</speaker>
               <l>A Drum, call a Drum.
<stage>Exit Grimsbie.</stage>
               </l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>VVa.</speaker>
               <l>Oh ſir <hi>John Mentith</hi> I have crackt the Ice,</l>
               <l>To a deſigne, which if it will ſucceed,</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>England</hi> no more ſhall ſtrike, nor <hi>Scotland</hi> bleed.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <pb facs="tcp:19967:36"/>
               <speaker>Ment.</speaker>
               <l>
                  <hi>Com.</hi> Lets be partakers, deare ſir.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>VVal.</speaker>
               <p>What will you ſay, if I winne <hi>Bruce</hi> from the <hi>Engliſh?</hi>
               </p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Ment.</speaker>
               <l>The happieſt day that ever ſhone on <hi>Scotland.</hi>
               </l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Com.</speaker>
               <l>And crowne him King?</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>VVal.</speaker>
               <l>That's the up-ſhot muſt crowne all, I'm to meet him</l>
               <l>Before one houre grow old in <hi>Glaſco</hi>-moore.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Ment.</speaker>
               <l>How meet him?</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Wa.</speaker>
               <l>As I am, both come alone, no words to any.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Ment.</speaker>
               <l>Our lips are ſeal'd.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Com.</speaker>
               <l>Will you ride, or go on foot?</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Wal.</speaker>
               <l>No more, I'le ride.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Ment.</speaker>
               <l>Wee'le paſſe the wood on foot.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Wal.</speaker>
               <l>
                  <hi>Jack Mentith,</hi> I do laugh to think what face,</l>
               <l>Longſhancks wil make, when he ſhall heare what gueſts</l>
               <l>Will dine with him in's Court on Chriſtmas day.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Ment.</speaker>
               <l>What face? he'le kill the Herald ſure.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Wal.</speaker>
               <p>Oh! ſome charme for me to be inviſible there, and ſee him.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Ment.</speaker>
               <l>For my part, of ten thouſand crownes by this hand,</l>
               <l>I do wiſh you there.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Com.</speaker>
               <l>For as many of mine, I ſweare.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Ment.</speaker>
               <l>Time may come,</l>
               <l>In his Exchequer we may ſhare twice that ſumme.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Wall.</speaker>
               <l>Hence, hye you before, keep cloſe in the wood,</l>
               <l>Breake forth if you ſpie treaſon, if not, not.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Both.</speaker>
               <l>Good.
<stage>Exeunt.</stage>
               </l>
            </sp>
            <stage>Enter the Fryers Ghoſt.</stage>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Wa.</speaker>
               <l>Ha, if what thou ſeem'ſt thou art, ſtep forward, ſpeake,</l>
               <l>I have fac'd more horrid terror.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <pb facs="tcp:19967:36"/>
               <speaker>Fryer.</speaker>
               <l>Whare do'ſt gang?</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Wall.</speaker>
               <l>What's that to thee?</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Fryer.</speaker>
               <l>Thouſe not leſt and lang,</l>
               <l>Twa wolves will ſuike thy bluide, by the third night,</l>
               <l>I charge thy ſawle meete mine, thy death is dight.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Wal.</speaker>
               <l>Thou art a lying ſpirit.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Fryer.</speaker>
               <l>
                  <hi>Bruce</hi> byn thy bane,</l>
               <l>Gif on thou gang luke not turne backe againe,</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Wallace</hi> beweere, me thinks it thee ſhould irke,</l>
               <l>Mare need haſt thou to ſerve God in the Kirke.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>VVa.</speaker>
               <l>Stay, if thou haſt a voyce th'art bloud and bone,</l>
               <l>As I am, let me feele thee, elſe I'le thinke thee</l>
               <l>A ſorcerous imaginarie ſound:</l>
               <l>Stand me, th'art ſome <hi>Engliſh</hi> damned witch,</l>
               <l>That from a reverend Fryer has ſtoln his ſhape</l>
               <l>To abuſe me—ſtay—art gone? no Hagge I will not.</l>
               <l>It ſpake ſure, told me <hi>Bruce</hi> ſhould
<stage>Exit Ghoſt beckon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing him to follow.</stage>
               </l>
               <l>be my bane,—cannot—ſhall not,</l>
               <l>heaven knows ſuch things onely.</l>
               <stage>
                  <hi>Enter old</hi> Wallace <hi>his Ghoſt.</hi>
               </stage>
               <l>That eye hath ſhot me throw, wounds me to death,</l>
               <l>I know that face too well, but 'tis ſo gaſtly,</l>
               <l>I'le rather with my nayles here dig my grave,</l>
               <l>Then once more behold thee.
<stage>Exit Ghoſt.</stage>
               </l>
               <l>Part from me vext ſpirit, my bloud turnes to water,</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>I</hi> beſeech thee affright me not—it's gone.</l>
            </sp>
            <stage>
               <hi>Enter</hi> Peggies <hi>Ghoſt.</hi>
            </stage>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Peg.</speaker>
               <l>Alace <hi>Scotland</hi> to wham ſalt thou compleyne,</l>
               <l>Alace, fra mourning wha ſall the refayne?</l>
               <l>I thee beſeekand for him dy'd on tree,</l>
               <l>Come not nere <hi>Bruyce,</hi> yet <hi>Bruyce</hi> ſall not hurt thee,</l>
               <l>
                  <pb facs="tcp:19967:37"/>Alace, alace, no man can ſtand 'gainſt fate.</l>
               <l>The dampe dew fra the heaven does gyn to faw,</l>
               <l>I to my reſt mim gange ere the Cock crawe.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Wall.</speaker>
               <l>It was my wife, what horror meete I here?</l>
               <l>No Armour in the world can hold out feare.</l>
            </sp>
            <stage>
               <hi>Enter</hi> Grimsbie.</stage>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Grim.</speaker>
               <l>We ſtay for your direction.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Wal.</speaker>
               <l>Whom did you meete?</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Grim.</speaker>
               <l>No body.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Wa.</speaker>
               <l>Saw ye nothing?</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Grim.</speaker>
               <l>Not any thing.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Wa.</speaker>
               <l>Twas my braines weakneſſe then,</l>
               <l>I have ſeene ſtrange ſights, that anon I'le tell;</l>
               <l>If <hi>Grimsbie</hi> we meete never more, farewell.
<stage>Exit.</stage>
               </l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Grim.</speaker>
               <l>Ha, I am ſtrucke dumbe, oh mans ſlippery fate!</l>
               <l>Miſchiefes that follow us at our backs we ſhunne,</l>
               <l>And are ſtrucke downe with thoſe we dreame not on.</l>
            </sp>
            <stage>Exit.</stage>
            <stage>
               <hi>Enter</hi> Mentith, <hi>and</hi> Comyne.</stage>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Ment.</speaker>
               <l>I have beſide with <hi>Wallace</hi> ſherife of life,</l>
               <l>Held private conference, who in Longſhancks name,</l>
               <l>Who ſweares to me we ſhall have good preferment,</l>
               <l>Beſide the promiſt gold.
<stage>
                     <hi>Enter</hi> Wallace.</stage>
               </l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Com.</speaker>
               <l>Peace, <hi>Wallace</hi> comes.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Ment.</speaker>
               <l>Is the <hi>Bruyce</hi> come?</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Wal.</speaker>
               <l>It is not yet his houre.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Ment.</speaker>
               <l>Who came along with you?</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Wa.</speaker>
               <l>My foot-boy onely, who is tying up my horſe.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Ment.</speaker>
               <l>Him muſt I kill.</l>
               <l>I'le looke if <hi>Bruce</hi> be in ſight yet— <stage>Exit.</stage>
               </l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Wal.</speaker>
               <l>Do.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Com.</speaker>
               <l>Y'are ſad.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <pb facs="tcp:19967:37"/>
               <speaker>VVa.</speaker>
               <l>My minde is ſhaken but the ſtorme is o're,</l>
               <stage>A cry, helpe, murder within.</stage>
               <l>What cry is that?</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Ment.</speaker>
               <l>Be arm'd, <hi>Bruce</hi> with a force comes to betray thee,</l>
               <l>From ſome villaines hand thy foot-boy is murdered.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>VVal.</speaker>
               <l>Murdred? <hi>Bruce</hi> ſhall repent this deed.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Both.</speaker>
               <l>So ſhalt thou, away with him.</l>
            </sp>
            <stage>Enter Souldiers, knocke him downe, hurry him away in a ſound. Exeunt.</stage>
            <stage>
               <hi>Enter</hi> Bruce <hi>muffled with a Souldier.</hi>
            </stage>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Bru.</speaker>
               <l>Helpe to diſguiſe me Souldier, in exchange</l>
               <l>Take theſe for thine, and here's ſome gold to boot.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Soul.</speaker>
               <l>If I be not hang'd, my Lord, in all my bravery,</l>
               <l>I care not.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Bru.</speaker>
               <l>Phew, I warrant thee,</l>
               <l>Seale up thy lips and eyes, thou neither ſeeſt</l>
               <l>Nor canſt tell where I am.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Soul.</speaker>
               <l>Not I my Lord.</l>
               <l>Oh my poore wrong'd countrey, pardon me heaven,</l>
               <l>And with a feather pluck'd from mercies wing,</l>
               <l>Bruſh off the purple ſpots, that elſe would grow,</l>
               <l>Like freckles on my ſoule.</l>
            </sp>
            <stage>
               <hi>Enter</hi> North <hi>and</hi> Clifford.</stage>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Soul.</speaker>
               <l>My Lord, here comes company.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Bru.</speaker>
               <l>Here quicke mine own agen, and get thee gone.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Per.</speaker>
               <l>Sirra Souldier, ſaw'ſt thou the Earle of Huntington?</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Soul.</speaker>
               <l>Huntington?</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Cliff.</speaker>
               <l>The Lord <hi>Bruce,</hi> I meane.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Bru.</speaker>
               <l>Who cals for <hi>Bruce?</hi>
               </l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <pb facs="tcp:19967:38"/>
               <speaker>Per.</speaker>
               <l>Muffled up, and alone, I'le to the King.
<stage>Exit.</stage>
               </l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Cliff.</speaker>
               <l>Do, ſirra be gone.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Bru.</speaker>
               <l>Whither's <hi>Percy</hi> gone? he ask'd for <hi>Bruce.</hi>
               </l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Cliff.</speaker>
               <l>There's great enquirie for you.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Bru.</speaker>
               <l>By whom?</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Cliff.</speaker>
               <l>The King has a freſh command for <hi>Bruce.</hi>
               </l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Bru.</speaker>
               <l>For me? he may command his Subjects.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Cliff.</speaker>
               <l>True, and Huntington is one.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Bru.</speaker>
               <l>Is none.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Cliff.</speaker>
               <l>No Subject?</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Bruce.</speaker>
               <l>None that dare oppoſe your King, Oh my impoſtum'd ſpleene,</l>
               <l>Will flie into their faces, what command</l>
               <l>Has <hi>England</hi> now?</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Clif.</speaker>
               <l>Freſh powers are to be levied,</l>
               <l>Which <hi>Bruce</hi> of Huntington muſt leade.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Bruce.</speaker>
               <l>'Gainſt whom?</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Clif.</speaker>
               <l>Gainſt proud <hi>Wallace,</hi> 'gainſt the <hi>Scots.</hi>
               </l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Bruce.</speaker>
               <l>I will not, I'm not his Butcher,</l>
               <l>Gainſt the <hi>Scots</hi> I will not fight.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Clif.</speaker>
               <l>How, will not?</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Bruce.</speaker>
               <l>No, will not <hi>Clifford.</hi>
               </l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Cliff.</speaker>
               <l>Peace.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Bruce.</speaker>
               <l>My Lord, I dare not,</l>
               <l>In this laſt battell I receiv'd ſome wounds</l>
               <l>That yet bleed inward, <hi>I</hi> will no more banquet ſtrangers</l>
               <l>With my native bloud.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Cliff.</speaker>
               <l>
                  <hi>Bruce</hi> ſpeaks not like a ſubject.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Bruce.</speaker>
               <l>
                  <hi>Engliſh Edward</hi> commands not like a King,</l>
               <l>Thrice honour'd <hi>Clifford,</hi> I'le truſt you with my boſome.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Clif.</speaker>
               <l>No, you ſhall not.</l>
               <l>My virgin honour is ſo chaſt, it ſhall not</l>
               <l>Keepe companie with a diſquiet boſome,</l>
               <l>Nor talke with diſcontents.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <pb facs="tcp:19967:38"/>
               <speaker>Bru.</speaker>
               <l>It ſhall not, <hi>I</hi> will but,</l>
               <l>Spare me, the ayre hath eares no more,</l>
               <l>You ſent to me, <hi>I</hi> will but tell bold <hi>Clifford</hi>
               </l>
               <l>Not a word,</l>
               <l>My thoughts owe as much honour as their Lord.</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Within traytor, traytor.</hi>
                  <stage>
                     <hi>Enter</hi> Mentith.</stage>
               </l>
            </sp>
            <stage>
               <hi>Enter King,</hi> North, Herefor, <hi>and followers.</hi>
            </stage>
            <sp>
               <speaker>King.</speaker>
               <l>A mutinie, what noyſe is't?</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Per.</speaker>
               <l>
                  <hi>Mentith,</hi> a Knight of <hi>Scotland.</hi>
               </l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Cliff.</speaker>
               <l>Keepe him off.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>King.</speaker>
               <l>What com'ſt thou for?</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Ment.</speaker>
               <l>
                  <hi>Comyn</hi> my countryman and I have brought</l>
               <l>A jewell to your Highneſſe, which if 'twere right</l>
               <l>As 'tis known counterfeit, 'twere worth a kingdome,</l>
               <l>Wearied with warre, and pittying the deep wounds</l>
               <l>Which fainting <hi>Scotland</hi> beares upon her breaſt,</l>
               <l>And knowing that the onely ſword which gaſhes</l>
               <l>Her tender ſides, is grip'd in <hi>Wallace</hi> hands,</l>
               <l>I in my love to peace, and to the ſafetie</l>
               <l>Of two great Nations, am the man that layed</l>
               <l>Snares to entrap this monſter, that devoures</l>
               <l>So many thouſand lives, the Rebell's tane.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>King.</speaker>
               <l>Where is he?</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Ment.</speaker>
               <l>
                  <hi>I</hi> have brought him to your <hi>Engliſh</hi> Camp,</l>
               <l>Force would not doo't, but policie, we ſtruck the Stagge</l>
               <l>To the ground, and thought him dead, but heaven put backe</l>
               <l>The blow of purpoſe, hee's now come to life,</l>
               <l>From an aſtoniſhment when we thought him dead,</l>
               <l>To th'end the world may ſee the publique ſhame</l>
               <l>Of an Arch-traytor.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>King.</speaker>
               <l>
                  <hi>Mentith</hi> hath wonne fame,</l>
               <l>And honour by this act, fetch in this devill.
<stage>Exit Ment.</stage>
               </l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <pb facs="tcp:19967:39"/>
               <speaker>Clif.</speaker>
               <l>Thou wilt have <hi>Englands</hi> thanks, but <hi>Scotlands</hi> curſe,</l>
               <l>Thou never haſt done better, never worſe,</l>
               <l>Damn'd <hi>Iudas</hi> to thy Country-man and friend.</l>
            </sp>
            <stage>
               <hi>Enter</hi> Wallace, Mentith, Comyn.</stage>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Wal.</speaker>
               <l>Where am <hi>I?</hi>
               </l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Bru.</speaker>
               <l>Here with <hi>Bruce.</hi>
               </l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Wal.</speaker>
               <l>
                  <hi>Bruce</hi> my Soveraigne?</l>
               <l>My bloud is ſold, this is not <hi>Glaſco</hi>-moore,</l>
               <l>Some villaine hath betray'd me.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Cli.</speaker>
               <l>Speak to your country-men, <hi>Comyn</hi> and <hi>Mentith.</hi>
               </l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Wal.</speaker>
               <l>
                  <hi>Comyn</hi> and <hi>Mentith?</hi>
               </l>
               <l>Something it was that made the modeſt night</l>
               <l>Looke angry on the world, I this was it,</l>
               <l>And this was it that cleft my fathers grave,</l>
               <l>And rais'd him from his monumentall bed of earth</l>
               <l>To give me gentle warning, this was it,</l>
               <l>That made my ſtarre, when all the reſt look'd pale,</l>
               <l>Bluſh like a fiery Meteor, can Heaven winke at this?</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Ment.</speaker>
               <l>It can, it doth, and at farre greater miſchiefs.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Wal.</speaker>
               <l>Not of thy acting?</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Ment.</speaker>
               <l>Yes of mine.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Wal.</speaker>
               <l>Not here.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Ment.</speaker>
               <l>Here or in Hell.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Wal.</speaker>
               <l>Why then goe act them there,</l>
               <l>Boaſt of them there, in that black Kingdome tell</l>
               <l>That by a true ſubject a baſe Rebell fell.</l>
            </sp>
            <stage>Kils him with his fiſt.</stage>
            <sp>
               <speaker>King.</speaker>
               <l>Whats that?</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Clif.</speaker>
               <l>Your <hi>Scotch</hi> jeweller is ſlain,</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>King.</speaker>
               <l>By whom?</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Clif.</speaker>
               <l>By <hi>Wallace.</hi>
               </l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <pb facs="tcp:19967:39"/>
               <speaker>Wal.</speaker>
               <l>Heare me ſpeak King <hi>Edward.</hi>
               </l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Clif.</speaker>
               <l>Good my Liege heare him,</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>King.</speaker>
               <l>
                  <hi>Clif.</hi> I have vow'd,</l>
               <l>Neither to heare nor ſee him, drag him hence,</l>
               <l>Mine eye ſhall nor be ſo compaſſionate</l>
               <l>To view him, leaſt I pitie him: hang, draw, and quarter him.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Wal.</speaker>
               <l>Firſt heare me ſpeak,</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>King.</speaker>
               <l>Drag him hence, and let that heart, thoſe limbes,</l>
               <l>Which were the motives to rebellious warre</l>
               <l>Be torn aſunder, caſt upon that ground,</l>
               <l>Which he with unkinde ſteele ſo oft did wound,</l>
               <l>Away with him.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Wal.</speaker>
               <l>Farewell, to all the World,</l>
               <l>I ha met death too often to feare him now,</l>
               <l>Only it grieves me that I have not freed</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Scotland</hi> my native ſoile from tyranny,</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Bruce,</hi> thou haſt a Kingdome, loſe it not.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>King.</speaker>
               <l>Stop his throat.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Wal.</speaker>
               <l>I go to one too,</l>
               <l>And on my grave, when death hath there down laid me,</l>
               <l>Be this my Epitaph, mine own betrayes me— <stage>Exit.</stage>
               </l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Bruce.</speaker>
               <l>Let him have noble triall.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>King.</speaker>
               <l>He ſhall have the triall of an Arch-traitour,</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Percy</hi> and <hi>Clifford</hi> take hence <hi>Bruce.</hi>
               </l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Bruce.</speaker>
               <l>Me hence?</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>King.</speaker>
               <l>You hence ſir, from this houre I ſweare,</l>
               <l>Never to ſee thee Earle of <hi>Huntingdon,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>Harke <hi>Clifford,</hi> and <hi>Northumberland,</hi> awa</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Bruce.</speaker>
               <l>What is King <hi>Edwards</hi> meaning?</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>King.</speaker>
               <l>Your head ſhal feel our meaning, ſee it diſpatch'd.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Bruce.</speaker>
               <l>You may.
<stage>
                     <hi>Exeunt</hi> Bruce, North <hi>and</hi> Clifford.</stage>
               </l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Com.</speaker>
               <l>My honor'd Lord, although untimely death,</l>
               <l>Hath taken hence one engine of that work,</l>
               <l>
                  <pb facs="tcp:19967:40"/>That brought that Rebell <hi>Wallace</hi> to his end.</l>
               <l>Seeing our Countries peace, and <hi>Englands</hi> good,</l>
               <l>Is by his death made perfect and compleat,</l>
               <l>I doubt not but the promiſed reward</l>
               <l>Of full ten thouſand Crowns ſhall now remayn,</l>
               <l>To the Survivor.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>King.</speaker>
               <l>
                  <hi>Comin,</hi> I perceive</l>
               <l>It was reward, not love that acted it,</l>
               <l>But you ſhall have your due, of that anon.
<stage>A flouriſh.</stage>
               </l>
               <stage>Enter all in ſtate.</stage>
               <l>I told thee <hi>Bruce,</hi> that thou upon thy head,</l>
               <l>Shouldſt feele our meaning, and that all the world,</l>
               <l>May know we value honour above conqueſt,</l>
               <l>Having a power able to turn all <hi>Scotland</hi>
               </l>
               <l>Into a Chaos, here twixt both our Armies,</l>
               <l>Give us thy oath of fealty, and weare</l>
               <l>Both Crown and title of thine Anceſtors.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Bruce.</speaker>
               <l>
                  <hi>England</hi> is full of honour, <hi>Bruce</hi> doth bend</l>
               <l>To thy command.
<stage>They crown him.</stage>
               </l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>King.</speaker>
               <l>Give him his oath of fealty,</l>
               <l>With him thoſe Lords which are his Countrymen.</l>
            </sp>
            <stage>
               <hi>They ſweare,</hi> Bruce <hi>ſtabs</hi> Comin.</stage>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Bruce.</speaker>
               <l>Stand back, a Serpent ſhall not with his breath</l>
               <l>Infect our Kingly eares, die ſlave, for he</l>
               <l>That would betray his friend ſhall nere ſerve me.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>King.</speaker>
               <l>What hath <hi>Bruce</hi> done?</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Bruce.</speaker>
               <l>A ſacrifice of honour and revenge, no traitors hand</l>
               <l>Shall help to lift a Crown up to my head,</l>
               <l>Thou didſt betray, then die unpitied.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <pb facs="tcp:19967:40"/>
               <speaker>Clif.</speaker>
               <l>Brave <hi>Bruce,</hi> I'le love thee for this honor'd act,</l>
               <l>Thou haſt perform'd a noble piece of juſtice:</l>
               <l>Now ſhall the Ghoſt of <hi>Wallace</hi> ſleepe in peace,</l>
               <l>And perfect love ſhall twixt theſe Lands increaſe.</l>
               <l>He hath his full reward for his foule treaſon,</l>
               <l>Drag hence the ſlave, and make him food for Crows.</l>
               <l>The Lamp that gave Rebellion light, hath ſpent</l>
               <l>The oile that fed it, all our ſpears are turn'd</l>
               <l>To Palmes and Olive branches, all our ſtars</l>
               <l>Are now made whole, peace is the balme of wars.</l>
            </sp>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
