<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>The costlie vvhore A comicall historie, acted by the companie of the Revels.</title>
            <title>Costly whore.</title>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1633</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 141 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 32 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2013-12">2013-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A15291</idno>
            <idno type="STC">STC 25582A</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC S119903</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99855109</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99855109</idno>
            <idno type="VID">20581</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A15291)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 20581)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 1400:4)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>The costlie vvhore A comicall historie, acted by the companie of the Revels.</title>
                  <title>Costly whore.</title>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[64] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed by Augustine Mathewes, for William Sheares, and are to be sold at his shoppe in Brittaines Burse,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1633.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>In verse.</note>
                  <note>Signatures: A-H⁴.</note>
                  <note>The first leaf is blank.</note>
                  <note>Running title reads: The costly whore.</note>
                  <note>A variant of the edition with imprint giving Hugh Perrie as the second publisher.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the Henry E. Huntington Library and Art Gallery.</note>
                  <note>Some print faded and show-through; some pages stained.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2012-07</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-07</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-09</date>
            <label>Colm MacCrossan</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-09</date>
            <label>Colm MacCrossan</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-02</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:20581:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:20581:1"/>
            <p>THE COSTLIE WHORE. A COMICALL HISTORIE, Acted by the companie of <hi>the Revels.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>LONDON Printed by <hi>Auguſtine Mathewes,</hi> for WILLIAM SHEARES, and are to be ſold at his ſhoppe in <hi>Brittaines Burſe.</hi> 1633.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="dramatis_personae">
            <pb facs="tcp:20581:2"/>
            <head>The Actors names.</head>
            <list>
               <item>Duke of Saxonie.</item>
               <item>Fredericke <hi>his ſonne.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Hatto. <hi>Brothers to the Duke.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Alrid. <hi>Brothers to the Duke.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Montano: <hi>kinſman to the Duke</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Euphrata, <hi>daughter to the Duke.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Conſtantine, <hi>a lover of</hi> Euphrata.</item>
               <item>Otho, <hi>a friend to</hi> Conſtantine.</item>
               <item>Alberto. <hi>two Lords.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Reynaldo <hi>two Lords.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>andermas, <hi>a Pander.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>alentia, <hi>the Coſtly</hi> Whore.</item>
               <item>Iulia, <hi>a Gentlewoman to</hi> Eu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phrata.</item>
               <item>Two Maides.</item>
               <item>Petitioners.</item>
               <item>Beggers.</item>
               <item>Seruants.</item>
            </list>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="play">
            <pb facs="tcp:20581:2"/>
            <head>THE COSTLY <hi>WHORE.</hi>
            </head>
            <div type="act">
               <stage>Enter Conſtantine and Otho.</stage>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Conſtantine.</speaker>
                  <p>
                     <seg rend="decorInit">H</seg>Ow do'ſt thou like the lovely <hi>Euphrata?</hi>
                  </p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Otho.</speaker>
                  <p>I did not marke her.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Conſt.</speaker>
                  <l>Then thou didſt not marke</l>
                  <l>The faireſt <hi>Saxon</hi> Lady in mine eye,</l>
                  <l>That ever breath'd a maid.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Otho.</speaker>
                  <l>Your minde now knowne,</l>
                  <l>Ile ſay ſhee is the faireſt in the world,</l>
                  <l>Were ſhe the fouleſt.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Con.</speaker>
                  <l>Then thos canſt diſſemble.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Otho.</speaker>
                  <l>You know I cannot, but deare <hi>Conſtantine,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>I prethee tell me firſt, what is that Ladie?</l>
                  <l>That wonder of her ſexe, cal'd <hi>Euphrata,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>Whoſe daughter is ſhe?</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Conſt.</speaker>
                  <l>I cannot blame thee <hi>Otho.</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>Though thou be ignorant of her high worth,</l>
                  <l>Since here in <hi>Saxon</hi> we are ſtrangers both,</l>
                  <l>But if thou cal'ſt to minde, why we left <hi>Meath,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>Reade the trice reaſon in that Ladies eye,</l>
                  <l>Daughter unto the Duke of <hi>Saxonie,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>Shee unto whom ſo many worthy Lords,</l>
                  <l>Vail'd Bonnet, when ſhe paſt the Triangle,</l>
                  <l>Making the pavement Ivory where ſhe trode.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Otho.</speaker>
                  <l>She that ſo lightly toucht the marble path,</l>
                  <pb facs="tcp:20581:3"/>
                  <l>That leadeth from the Temple to the preſence.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Conſt.</speaker>
                  <l>The ſame.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Otho.</speaker>
                  <l>Why that was white before,</l>
                  <l>White Marble <hi>Conſtantine,</hi> whiter by odds</l>
                  <l>Then that which lovers terme the Ivory hand,</l>
                  <l>Nay then the Lillie, whiteneſſe of her face.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Con.</speaker>
                  <l>Come, thou art a cavilling companion,</l>
                  <l>Becauſe thou ſeeſt my heart is drown'd in loue,</l>
                  <l>Thou wilt drowne me too, I ſay the Ladie's faire,</l>
                  <l>I ſay I love her, and in that more faire,</l>
                  <l>I ſay ſhe loves me, and in that moſt faire,</l>
                  <l>Love doth attribute in Hyperbolies,</l>
                  <l>Vnto his Miſtris the creation of every excellence,</l>
                  <l>Becauſe in her his eies do dreame of perfect excellence,</l>
                  <l>And here ſhe comes.</l>
                  <stage>Enter Euphrata.</stage>
                  <l>Obſerve her, gentle friend.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Euph.</speaker>
                  <l>Welcome ſweete <hi>Conſtantine.</hi>
                  </l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Con.</speaker>
                  <l>My <hi>Euphrata.</hi>
                  </l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Euph.</speaker>
                  <l>Thy <hi>Euphrata,</hi> be thou my <hi>Conſtantine,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>But what is he a ſtranger, or thy friend?</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Con.</speaker>
                  <l>My ſecond ſelfe, my ſecond <hi>Euphrata,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>If thou beeſt mine, ſalute her gentle <hi>Otho.</hi>
                  </l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Otho.</speaker>
                  <l>An humble and a true devoted heart,</l>
                  <l>I tender to you in a mindes chaſt kiſſe.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Euph.</speaker>
                  <l>Welcome to me, ſince welcome to my friend.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Otho.</speaker>
                  <l>A beautifull, an admirable Ladie,</l>
                  <l>I thinke 'tis fatall unto every friend,</l>
                  <l>Never to love, untill his friend firſt love,</l>
                  <l>And then his choice; but ſooner will I teare</l>
                  <l>Out of this breſt, mine affection with my heart.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Eu.</speaker>
                  <l>Hearing ſweet <hi>Conſtantine</hi> thou wert ſo nere me,</l>
                  <l>I came as I were wing'd to gaze on thee.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Con.</speaker>
                  <l>And would to heaven there were no barin time</l>
                  <l>To hinder me from thy deſired ſight,</l>
                  <l>But thouſand ſutors eyes do watch my ſteps,</l>
                  <l>And harke I heare ſome trampling, how now <hi>Iulia?</hi>
                  </l>
               </sp>
               <stage>Enter Julia.</stage>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Iuli.</speaker>
                  <l>Madam, the Lord <hi>Montano</hi> ſpying you,</l>
                  <pb facs="tcp:20581:3"/>
                  <l>To leave the preſence, and to enter here,</l>
                  <l>Hath ever ſince waited your comming foorth,</l>
                  <l>And will not be denied untill he ſee you.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Euph.</speaker>
                  <l>Of all my ſutors, moſt importunate.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Con.</speaker>
                  <l>What is he love?</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Euph.</speaker>
                  <l>Of very noble birth.</l>
                  <l>But my affection is not tyed to birth,</l>
                  <l>I muſt diſpenſe with this kind conference,</l>
                  <l>For ſome ſmall time, untill I rid him hence,</l>
                  <l>Therefore within my cloſet hide thy ſelfe,</l>
                  <l>Your friend ſhall <hi>Iulia</hi> guide into the garden,</l>
                  <l>Where through a private doore, but ſeldome vs'd,</l>
                  <l>He may at pleaſure leave us and returne,</l>
                  <l>Deny me not, I prethee <hi>Conſtantine,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>Thou haſt my heart, and would thy birth were ſuch,</l>
                  <l>I need not feare t'avouch thee for my Love.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Otho.</speaker>
                  <l>Madam, I take my leave.</l>
               </sp>
               <stage>Exit Otho.</stage>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Con.</speaker>
                  <l>Farewell deare friend,</l>
                  <l>Returne as ſoone as may be, farewell Love.</l>
               </sp>
               <stage>Exit.</stage>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Eup.</speaker>
                  <l>Now guide <hi>Montano</hi> hither.</l>
               </sp>
               <stage>Enter Montano.</stage>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Mon.</speaker>
                  <l>Gracious Madam, I have ſeene the noble Palſgrave,</l>
                  <l>The Prince of <hi>Milleine,</hi> and the Palatine of the Rheine,</l>
                  <l>With divers other honorable ſutors,</l>
                  <l>Mounted to ride unto their ſeverall places.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Euph.</speaker>
                  <l>Of me they tooke their farewell yeſternight.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Mon.</speaker>
                  <l>What meanes your grace to be ſo unkind to all?</l>
                  <l>You drive away good fortune by diſdaine.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Euph.</speaker>
                  <l>Why are you grieving too?</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Mon.</speaker>
                  <l>I am your ſubiect;</l>
                  <l>The meaneſt that did humbly ſeeke your love,</l>
                  <l>Yet not the meaneſt in affection,</l>
                  <l>And <hi>I</hi> am come to take my farewell too.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Eup.</speaker>
                  <l>Why then farewell.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Mon.</speaker>
                  <l>So ſhort with them that love you.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Eup.</speaker>
                  <l>Your journey may be great for ought <hi>I</hi> know,</l>
                  <l>And 'tis an argument of little love,</l>
                  <pb facs="tcp:20581:4"/>
                  <l>To be the hinderer of a traveller.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Mon.</speaker>
                  <l>My journey Madame is unto my houſe,</l>
                  <l>Scarce halfe a league hence, there to pine and die,</l>
                  <l>Becauſe I love ſuch beauteous crueltie.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Euph.</speaker>
                  <l>God ſpeede you ſir.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Mon.</speaker>
                  <l>Nay then I will not leave you:</l>
                  <l>Madam, 'tis thought, and that upon good ground</l>
                  <l>You have ſhrin'd your affection in the heart</l>
                  <l>Of ſome (what ere he be) noble, or baſe,</l>
                  <l>And thats the cauſe you lightlie cenſure all.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Euphr.</speaker>
                  <l>Who thinkes it?</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Mon.</speaker>
                  <l>I doe Madame, and your father.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Eu.</speaker>
                  <l>It is upon my vowed chaſtitie.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Mon.</speaker>
                  <l>What devill made you ſweare to chaſtitie,</l>
                  <l>Or have you tane that oath onely for a terme.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Euphr.</speaker>
                  <l>A terme, what terme?</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Mon.</speaker>
                  <l>A terme of ſome ſeven yeeres,</l>
                  <l>Or peradventure halfe the number more.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Euphr.</speaker>
                  <l>For terme of life.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Mon.</speaker>
                  <l>You have ſworne to be forſworne,</l>
                  <l>He was no well diſpoſed friend of yours,</l>
                  <l>That gave you conſaile to forſweare ſuch beautie,</l>
                  <l>Why tis as if ſome traveiler had found</l>
                  <l>A mine of gold, and made no vſe of it.</l>
                  <l>For terme of life; why then die preſently,</l>
                  <l>So ſhall your debt to nature be farre leſſe;</l>
                  <l>Your tyranny over mans yeelding heart</l>
                  <l>Be leſſe condemned: oh you were made for man,</l>
                  <l>And living without man, to murder men:</l>
                  <l>If any creature be ſo fortunate</l>
                  <l>That lives in grace of your all gracious ſelfe,</l>
                  <l>Though I am well perſwaded 'tis not I</l>
                  <l>I vow by all the rites of vertuous love,</l>
                  <l>Be he ignoble, of the baſeſt ſort,</l>
                  <l>To pleaſe you Madame, Ile renounce my ſuite,</l>
                  <l>And be a ſpeciall meane unto your father,</l>
                  <l>To grant your hearts affection, though I die.</l>
               </sp>
               <pb facs="tcp:20581:4"/>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Euph.</speaker>
                  <l>Now Lord <hi>Montano</hi> you come neere my heart,</l>
                  <l>And were I ſure that you would keepe your word,</l>
                  <l>As I am ſure you love me by your deedes,</l>
                  <l>I might perchance deliver you my thoughts.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Mon.</speaker>
                  <l>By heaven, and by your beauteous ſelfe I will.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Euph.</speaker>
                  <l>Then <hi>Conſtantine</hi> come forth, behold thy friend.</l>
               </sp>
               <stage>Enter Conſtantine.</stage>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Con.</speaker>
                  <l>Madame what meane you, to reveale our love?</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Mon.</speaker>
                  <l>This is a very ſtubborne Gentleman,</l>
                  <l>A Gentleman, a peſant, <hi>Saxonie</hi> affords not one more baſe.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Con.</speaker>
                  <l>He does me wrong, that termes me meaner then a gentle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Mon.</speaker>
                  <l>I tearme thee ſo.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Euph.</speaker>
                  <l>Why how now Lord <hi>Montano,</hi> you do forget your oath.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Mont.</speaker>
                  <l>And you your ſelfe,</l>
                  <l>Your Princely father, and the Dukedomes honour.</l>
                  <l>To chaine your liking to a groome ſo baſe.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Con.</speaker>
                  <l>He lies that calles me groome.</l>
               </sp>
               <stage>Enter Iulia.</stage>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Iu.</speaker>
                  <l>O God, forbeare,</l>
                  <l>His Excellence, your father's comming hither.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Mon.</speaker>
                  <l>He comes in happie time, to know the cauſe,</l>
                  <l>Why ſuch great Princes have bin made your ſcorne.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Euph.</speaker>
                  <l>What will you tell him?</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Mon.</speaker>
                  <l>Will I? let me die</l>
                  <l>Contemn'd of heaven, in publique obloquie,</l>
                  <l>If I reveale not this laſcivious courſe.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Iu.</speaker>
                  <l>We are undone.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Con.</speaker>
                  <l>Hence with this prating Maide,</l>
                  <l>If thou haſt any anger in thy breſt,</l>
                  <l>Towards this Lady, turne it all on me,</l>
                  <l>She is a woman, timerous by her kinde,</l>
                  <l>I man-like borne, and beare a man-like minde.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Mon.</speaker>
                  <l>Ile trie your courage — draw.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Eup.</speaker>
                  <l>As thou fear'ſt my frowne,</l>
                  <l>As thou haſt hope to thrive in thy new choice,</l>
                  <l>As thou reſpect'ſt the favour of the gods,</l>
                  <l>Welfare in any action thou intends,</l>
                  <l>Doe not reveale unto my fretfull father</l>
                  <pb facs="tcp:20581:5"/>
                  <l>This humble choice that my high birth hath made.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Mon.</speaker>
                  <l>Why then forſweare him.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Euph.</speaker>
                  <l>Sooner ſet thy feet</l>
                  <l>Vpon my breaſt, and tread me to the ground.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Iu.</speaker>
                  <l>As thou art any thing more then a beaſt.</l>
                  <l>Doe not procure my Ladie ſuch diſgrace.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Mon.</speaker>
                  <l>Peace bawde, Ile have no conference with you.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Euph.</speaker>
                  <l>He cannot hurt me, 'tis my Love I feare,</l>
                  <l>Although my father be as ſterne as warre,</l>
                  <l>Inexorable like conſuming fire,</l>
                  <l>As iealous of his honour, as his crowne,</l>
                  <l>To me his anger is like <hi>Zephires</hi> breath,</l>
                  <l>Caſt on a banke of ſommer violets:</l>
                  <stage>floriſh,</stage>
                  <l>But to my Love, like whirlewinde to a boate,</l>
                  <l>Taken in midſt of a tumultuous ſea.</l>
                  <stage>Enter Duke of Saxonie, and Fredericke.</stage>
                  <l>Alas he comes, <hi>Montane,</hi> prethee peace,</l>
                  <l>Courage ſweete Love.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Con.</speaker>
                  <l>I ſee our love muſt ceaſe.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Euph.</speaker>
                  <l>Not if my wit can helpe,</l>
                  <l>It ſhall goe hard but Ile prevent the traitor.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Mon.</speaker>
                  <l>Heare me my Lord.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Eup.</speaker>
                  <l>Heare me my gracious father.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Mon.</speaker>
                  <l>Heare me my liege, ther's treaſon in your Court,</l>
                  <l>I have found a peaſant in the Princeſſe cloſet,</l>
                  <l>And this is he that ſteales away her honour.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Euph.</speaker>
                  <l>This villaine gracious father 'tis that ſeekes</l>
                  <l>To rob me of mine honor, you your daughter.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Mon.</speaker>
                  <l>Now as you are a right heroike Prince,</l>
                  <l>Be deafe unto your daughters faire words.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Euph.</speaker>
                  <l>Be deafe to him, as you regard your ſelfe.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Duke.</speaker>
                  <l>What ſtrange confuſion's this, that cloyes our hearing?</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Fred.</speaker>
                  <l>Speake beauteous ſiſter, who hath done thee wrong?</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Mon.</speaker>
                  <l>Her ſelfe.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Euph.</speaker>
                  <l>This traitor.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Fre.</speaker>
                  <l>Lord <hi>Montano.</hi>
                  </l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Euphr.</speaker>
                  <l>Hee.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Fred.</speaker>
                  <l>Villaine thou dyeſt.</l>
               </sp>
               <pb facs="tcp:20581:5"/>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Mon.</speaker>
                  <l>Stay, ſhe meanes <hi>Conſtantine,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>Hee that I found infolded in her cloſet,</l>
                  <l>Reaping the honour, which a thouſand Lords</l>
                  <l>Have fail'd in ſeeking, in a lawfull courſe.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Con.</speaker>
                  <l>He does me wrong my gracious ſoveraigne.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Iu.</speaker>
                  <l>He wrongs my Ladie, an't pleaſe your grace.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Mon.</speaker>
                  <l>Ile tell the trueth.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Euph.</speaker>
                  <l>Or rather let me tell it.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Mon.</speaker>
                  <l>Laſcivious love is ever full of ſleights.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Euph.</speaker>
                  <l>Villaines that ſeeke by treaſon their deſires,</l>
                  <l>Want no ſuggeſtion to beguile a trueth.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Mon.</speaker>
                  <l>Iſay, I found this peaſant in her cloſet,</l>
                  <l>Kiſſing, imbracing, and diſhonouring her.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Euph.</speaker>
                  <l>I ſay, an'c pleaſe your gracious Excellence.</l>
                  <l>I found this Gentleman within my cloſet,</l>
                  <l>There ſet by ſubornation of this Lord,</l>
                  <l>And here appointed to diſhonor me,</l>
                  <l>Speake, is't not true?</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Con.</speaker>
                  <l>True, if it pleaſe your grace.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Duke.</speaker>
                  <l>What ſay you ſtrumpet?</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Iul.</speaker>
                  <l>Since my Ladie ſaies ſo,</l>
                  <l>I ſay and't pleaſe your Excellence.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Duke.</speaker>
                  <l>Speake woman.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Iu.</speaker>
                  <l>'Tis very true.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Mon.</speaker>
                  <l>O monſtrous forgerie.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Fre.</speaker>
                  <l>O more then falſhood to become ſo ſmooth,</l>
                  <l>In ſuch a dangerous action.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Duke.</speaker>
                  <l>This is ſtrange,</l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Montano</hi> ſeeke the ruine of my daughter.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Eup.</speaker>
                  <l>Becauſe I would not yeeld unto his ſuite,</l>
                  <l>Which hee in rapefull manner oft hath ſought,</l>
                  <l>Hee ſet this Gentleman to doe me ſhame,</l>
                  <l>Intending by exclaimes to raiſe the Court,</l>
                  <l>But that repentance in my waiting Maide,</l>
                  <l>And of his ſorrowfull ſelfe, reveal'd the plot.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Mon.</speaker>
                  <l>O ye gods, how am I over-reacht!</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Duke.</speaker>
                  <l>I know the yong man to be well diſcended,</l>
                  <l>Of civill carriage, and approved faith,</l>
                  <pb facs="tcp:20581:6"/>
                  <l>How ere ſeduced to this enterpriſe.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Con.</speaker>
                  <l>My conſcience would not propagate that plot.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Ju.</speaker>
                  <l>Nor mine my Lord, though gold corrupted me.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Mon.</speaker>
                  <l>Cleane from the byas wit, by heaven rare wit,</l>
                  <l>Ile tell another tale, if they have done.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Duke.</speaker>
                  <l>What canſt thou ſpeake vild traitor,</l>
                  <l>Thou ſeeſt thou art prevented in thy plot,</l>
                  <l>And therefore deſperately coin'ſt any thing,</l>
                  <l>But I am deafe to all ſuch ſtratagems.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Mon.</speaker>
                  <l>Will you not heare me?</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Duke.</speaker>
                  <l>Forgeries and lies,</l>
                  <l>My daughters honour is of that high prize,</l>
                  <l>That I preferre it 'fore a traitors braine,</l>
                  <l>Let it ſuffice, we know ſhe hath deni'd thee,</l>
                  <l>And ſome denied (like devills) turne their love,</l>
                  <l>Into excrutiation of themſelves,</l>
                  <l>And of the parties whom they have belou'd;</l>
                  <l>Revenge begins where flatteries doe end,</l>
                  <l>Being not her husband, thou wilt be no friend.</l>
                  <l>Thus is thy policy by heaven prevented,</l>
                  <l>Therefore henceforth, we baniſh thee our Court,</l>
                  <l>Our Court? our territorie, every place,</l>
                  <l>Wherein we beare the ſtate of Royaltie:</l>
                  <l>Vrge no replie, the fact is plainely prou'd,</l>
                  <l>And thou art hatefull where thou wert belou'd.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Mon.</speaker>
                  <l>My gracious Lord.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Duke.</speaker>
                  <l>We can afford no grace,</l>
                  <l>Stay there, and reade thy ruine in my face.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Mon.</speaker>
                  <l>I goe, contented with this heavy doome</l>
                  <l>'Twas mine owne ſeeking, faire, and wiſe adiew,</l>
                  <l>Deceit hath kil'd conceit, you know tis true.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Fre.</speaker>
                  <l>An vpright ſentence of an act ſo vilde.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Duk.</speaker>
                  <l>Remove this waiting virgin from your cham<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber,</l>
                  <l>But let this gentleman attend on me,</l>
                  <l>The beſt may be deceiu'd by trecherie.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Euph.</speaker>
                  <l>Then ſo my gracious father may this maid.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Duke.</speaker>
                  <l>Then let her keep her place, beware of gold,</l>
                  <pb facs="tcp:20581:6"/>
                  <l>Honour's too precious to be baſelie ſold.</l>
                  <l>Now to our dying friend, his grace of <hi>Meath,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>Daughter prepare you, you ſhall ride along,</l>
                  <l>For to that end we came, come ſonne to horſe,</l>
                  <l>Ere we come there, our friend may prove a coarſe.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Euph.</speaker>
                  <l>Twas well done both, this action rarely fell,</l>
                  <l>Where women trie their wits, bad plots prove well.</l>
                  <stage>Exeuxt omnes.</stage>
                  <stage>Enter three Beggers.</stage>
                  <l>1. Come away fellow louſe, thou art ever eating,</l>
                  <l>2. Have I not neede, that muſt feede ſo many</l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Cannibals,</hi> as will waite on me whether I will or no?</l>
                  <l>3. Heres one in my necke, I would'twere on thy ſhoulder.</l>
                  <l>1. Keepe it your ſelfe, I have retainers enow of mine owne.</l>
                  <l>2. But, whether are you going now?</l>
                  <l>1. Why, are you our King, and doe not know that?</l>
                  <l>2. Your King? I am a very rogniſh King, and I hav</l>
                  <l>A companie of lowſie ſubiects.</l>
                  <stage>Enter Hatto, and Alfrid conferring.</stage>
                  <l>2. But looke about my ragged ſubiects here comes ſome body,</l>
                  <l>1. O the devills, ſhall we aske them an almes?</l>
                  <l>2. Why not, now the rats haue eaten up their brother Biſhop, they will be more charitable, your vecation you ſlaves.</l>
                  <l>3. For the Lord ſake be pittifull to a companie of poore men.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Hatto.</speaker>
                  <l>What cry is this? beggars ſo neere the doore</l>
                  <l>Of our deceaſed brother; whip them hence,</l>
                  <l>Or bring the Maſtiffe foorth, worry them,</l>
                  <l>They are lazie drones, 'tis pittie ſuch ſhould live.</l>
                  <l>1. I told you my Lord how we ſhould find them: whip us,</l>
                  <l>Leade the way ſoveraigne, weele none of your whipping.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Hat.</speaker>
                  <l>Hence with theſe dogs, what make they neere this houſe?</l>
                  <l>2. He will be eaten with rats too, he looks like a piece of cheeſe alreadie.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Hat.</speaker>
                  <l>You Rogues.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Alf.</speaker>
                  <l>Good brother ſtay your ſelfe from wrath,</l>
                  <l>Thinke on the Biſhop and his odious death.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Hat.</speaker>
                  <l>What odious death I pray?</l>
               </sp>
               <pb facs="tcp:20581:7"/>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Al.</speaker>
                  <l>Eaten with Rats,</l>
                  <l>Whileſt he was liuing, for the wrong he did</l>
                  <l>Vnto the poore, the branches of our God.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Hat.</speaker>
                  <l>Tis true, and therefore call the poore againe,</l>
                  <l>Come hither friends, I did forget my ſelfe.</l>
                  <l>Pray for me, ther's ſome ſilver for thy wants.</l>
                  <l>2. Now the Lord bleſſe you, and keep your good fate.</l>
                  <l>From being Mouſe-eaten, wee came thinking</l>
                  <l>Wee ſhould have ſome dole at the Biſhops funerall,</l>
                  <l>But now this ſhall ſerve our turne, wee will</l>
                  <l>Pray for you night and day.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Hat.</speaker>
                  <l>Goe to the backe gate, and you ſhall have dole.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Om.</speaker>
                  <l>O the Lord ſave thee.</l>
               </sp>
               <stage>Exeunt Beggers.</stage>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Hat.</speaker>
                  <l>Theſe Beggers pray and curſe, both in a breath,</l>
                  <l>Oh wherefore ſhould we fawne upon ſuch curres,</l>
                  <l>The mice of mankind, and the ſcorne of earth?</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Alf.</speaker>
                  <l>So ſaid our brother.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Hat.</speaker>
                  <l>And he was a Biſhop,</l>
                  <l>Had read the Scripture, and knew what he ſaid.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Alf.</speaker>
                  <l>But he hath brought that ſaying with his death,</l>
                  <l>With ſuch a loathſome and notorious death,</l>
                  <l>As while the World's a World, 'twill ſpeake of <hi>Meath.</hi>
                  </l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Hat.</speaker>
                  <l>The Lord Archbiſhop of <hi>Meath,</hi> and die by Rats.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Alf.</speaker>
                  <l>He did proclaime reliefe unto the poore,</l>
                  <l>Aſſembled them unto a private Barne,</l>
                  <l>And having lockt the doore, ſet it on fire,</l>
                  <l>Saying, hee'de rid the countrie of ſuch Mice,</l>
                  <l>And Mice and Rats have rid him from the World:</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Hat.</speaker>
                  <l>Well, Ile not hurt the poore ſo publikely,</l>
                  <l>But privately I'le grinde their very hearts,</l>
                  <l>Torture them living, and yet have their prayers,</l>
                  <l>And by ſuch meanes, that few or none ſhall know it.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Al.</speaker>
                  <l>In ſuch a courſe <hi>Alfred</hi> would wind with you,</l>
                  <l>For though I counſail'd you to be more calme,</l>
                  <l>Twas not in pittie of their povertie,</l>
                  <l>But to auoide their clamour, to give nothing,</l>
                  <pb facs="tcp:20581:7"/>
                  <l>Will make them curſe you: but to threaten them,</l>
                  <l>Flie in your face, and ſpit upon your beard,</l>
                  <l>No devill ſo fierce, as a bread-wanting heart,</l>
                  <l>Eſpecially being baited with ill tearmes,</l>
                  <l>But what courſe can you take to plague theſe dogges?</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Hat.</speaker>
                  <l>Why, buy up all the corne, and make a dearth,</l>
                  <l>So thouſands of them will die under ſtalles.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Alf.</speaker>
                  <l>And ſend it unto forraine nations,</l>
                  <l>To bring in toies, to make the wealthy poore.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Hat.</speaker>
                  <l>Or make our land beare wood inſtead of wheate.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Al.</speaker>
                  <l>Incloſe the commons, and make white meates deare.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Hat.</speaker>
                  <l>Turne paſture into Parke grounds, and ſtarve cattle,</l>
                  <l>Or twentie other honeſt thriving courſes;</l>
                  <l>The meaneſt of theſe, will beggar halfe a Kingdome.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Al.</speaker>
                  <l>I have a commiſsion drawne for making glaſſe,</l>
                  <l>Now if the Duke come, as I thinke he will;</l>
                  <l>Twill be an excellent meanes to laviſh wood,</l>
                  <l>And then the cold will kill them, had they bread.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Hat.</speaker>
                  <l>The yron Mills are excellent for that,</l>
                  <l>I have a pattent drawne to that effect,</l>
                  <l>If they goe up, downe goes the goodly trees,</l>
                  <l>Ile make them ſearch the earth to find new fire.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Alf.</speaker>
                  <l>We two are brothers, and the Duke's our brother,</l>
                  <l>Shall we be brothers in Commiſsion?</l>
                  <l>And Ile perſwade him to authorize thee</l>
                  <l>His ſubſtitute in <hi>Meath,</hi> when he enioyes it.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Hat.</speaker>
                  <l>Death Ile get thee Regent under him</l>
                  <l>In <hi>Saxonie,</hi> to oppreſſe as well as <hi>I,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>And we will ſhare the profits, live like Kings,</l>
                  <l>And yet ſeeme liberall in common things.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Al.</speaker>
                  <l>Content, what though the Rats devour'd our brother?</l>
                  <l>Was not a Prophet murdered by a Lyon?</l>
                  <l>King <hi>Herod</hi> died of Lice, wormes doe eate us all,</l>
                  <l>The Rats are wormes, then let the Rats eate me,</l>
                  <l>Is the dead courſe prepar'd?</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Hat.</speaker>
                  <l>Embalm'd and coffin'd,</l>
                  <l>The Citie keyes delivered to my hands,</l>
                  <pb facs="tcp:20581:8"/>
                  <l>We ſtay but onely for his Excellence.</l>
               </sp>
               <stage>Enter Conſtantine.</stage>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Con.</speaker>
                  <l>The Duke is comming if it pleaſe your honors.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Al.</speaker>
                  <l>And he is welcome, let the trumpets found.</l>
               </sp>
               <stage>ſecond FLoriſh.</stage>
               <stage>Enter Duke of Saxon, Euphrata, and Iulia.</stage>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Hat.</speaker>
                  <l>Welcome, thrice welcome our renowned brother,</l>
                  <l>Loe at thy feete, the Citizens of <hi>Meath,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>By us their Agents, do lay downe the keyes,</l>
                  <l>And by this crownet, and ſword reſign'd,</l>
                  <l>The ſtate Maieſtique to your Princely hands,</l>
                  <l>Diſcended to you, by our brothers death.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Duke</speaker>
                  <l>Then with your loves, and perſons we receive it,</l>
                  <l>Is then our brother the Archbiſhop dead?</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Hat.</speaker>
                  <l>Too true my Lord.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Euph.</speaker>
                  <l>I am ſorry for my Vncle.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Hat.</speaker>
                  <l>And of a death ſo publike by reporte.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Al.</speaker>
                  <l>Devour'd by Rats, in ſtrange and wonderous ſort.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Duke.</speaker>
                  <l>Could not this palace ſeated in the Rheine,</l>
                  <l>In midſt of the great River, (to the which</l>
                  <l>No bridge, nor convay, other then by boats,</l>
                  <l>Was to be had) ree him from vermine Rats?</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Alf.</speaker>
                  <l>Againſt their kind, the land Rats took the water</l>
                  <l>And ſwomme in little armies to the houſe,</l>
                  <l>And though we drownd, and kild innumerable,</l>
                  <l>Their numbers were like <hi>Hydra's</hi> heads increaſing,</l>
                  <l>Ruine bred more untill our brother died.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Duke.</speaker>
                  <l>The houſe is execrable, Ile not enter.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Hat.</speaker>
                  <l>You need not feare my Lord, the houſe is free,</l>
                  <l>From all reſort of Rats, for at his death,</l>
                  <l>As if a trumpet founded a retreat,</l>
                  <l>They made a kind of murmure, and departed.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Du.</speaker>
                  <l>Sure 'twas the hand of heaven, for his contempt</l>
                  <l>Of his poore creatures: but what writs are thoſe?</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Hat.</speaker>
                  <l>Commiſſions (if it pleaſe your grace) for glaſſe</l>
                  <l>For yron Mines, and other needfull things.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Duke.</speaker>
                  <l>Our ſelfe inveſted in the government</l>
                  <pb facs="tcp:20581:8"/>
                  <l>The Cities care, ſhall lie upon your care.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Hat.</speaker>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Alfred</hi> our brother may awaite your grace ſeven,</l>
                  <l>in <hi>Saxony,</hi> ſo pleaſe you to command.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Duke.</speaker>
                  <l>We are now but three, that lately have bin</l>
                  <l>We have cauſe to love each other, for my part,</l>
                  <l>Betweene you both, we give a brothers heart,</l>
                  <l>Here, or at <hi>Saxonis,</hi> command at pleaſure,</l>
                  <l>I weare the corronet, be yours the treaſure.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Al.</speaker>
                  <l>We thanke our brother.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Duke.</speaker>
                  <l>Where's my ſonne <hi>Fredericks?</hi>
                  </l>
               </sp>
               <stage>Enter Fredericke with a gloue.</stage>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Fre.</speaker>
                  <l>Father, the ſtate of <hi>Meath</hi> deſire your grace.</l>
                  <l>To take the paines to paſſe unto the Senate.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Duke.</speaker>
                  <l>What glove is that ſon <hi>Fred.</hi> in your hand!</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Fre.</speaker>
                  <l>I found it if it pleaſe your Excellence,</l>
                  <l>Neere to the ſtate-houſe, the imbroiderie</l>
                  <l>Is very excellent, and the faſhion rare.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Duke.</speaker>
                  <l>I have not ſeene a prettier forme of hand?</l>
                  <l>Daughter let's ſee, is't not too bigge for you?</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Eup.</speaker>
                  <l>Sure 'tis ſome admirable worke of nature,</l>
                  <l>If it fit any hand that owes this glove,</l>
                  <l>If all the reſt doe parallel the hand.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Duke.</speaker>
                  <l>Will it not on?</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Euph.</speaker>
                  <l>Not for a diadem,</l>
                  <l>Ile trie no longer, leſt I ſhame my ſelfe.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Duke.</speaker>
                  <l>Try <hi>Iulia.</hi>
                  </l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Iu.</speaker>
                  <l>My hand's bigger then my Ladies.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Duke.</speaker>
                  <l>I cannot tell, but in my minde I feele</l>
                  <l>A wondrous paſſion of I know not what.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Fre.</speaker>
                  <l>The imbroidered glove may be ſome childs no womans</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Duke,</speaker>
                  <l>I ſhould miſtruſt as much, but that this place</l>
                  <l>Beares greater compaſſe then a childiſh hand,</l>
                  <l>I muſt command it.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Fre.</speaker>
                  <l>Willingly my Lord.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Du.</speaker>
                  <l>Then to the ſtate-houſe brothers lead the way.</l>
                  <pb facs="tcp:20581:9"/>
                  <l>Firſt our inſtalement, then a funerall day.</l>
               </sp>
               <stage>Exeunt Duke and brothers, and Fred.</stage>
               <stage>Enter Otho.</stage>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Otho.</speaker>
                  <l>Yonder ſhe goes, the mirrour of her ſexe,</l>
                  <l>Stay beauteous <hi>Euphrata.</hi>
                  </l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Euph.</speaker>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Otho,</hi> what <hi>Iulia?</hi>
                  </l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Ju.</speaker>
                  <l>Here Madam, what's your will.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Euph.</speaker>
                  <l>Call <hi>Conſtantine,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>Tell him, his deare friend <hi>Otho</hi> is return'd.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Iu.</speaker>
                  <l>I will.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Otho.</speaker>
                  <l>Stay <hi>Iulia.</hi>
                  </l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Euph.</speaker>
                  <l>Doe as I bid you, goe.</l>
               </sp>
               <stage>Exit Iulia.</stage>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Otho.</speaker>
                  <l>I had rather have a word or twaine with you.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Euph.</speaker>
                  <l>I have heard him oft enquire for thee his friend,</l>
                  <l>I have heard him ſigh, I have ſeene him weepe for thee,</l>
                  <l>Imagining ſome miſchiefe, or diſtreſſe</l>
                  <l>Had falne thee ſince the cloſets ſeparation.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Otho.</speaker>
                  <l>And what a ſlave am I to wrong this friend.</l>
               </sp>
               <stage>Enter Conſtantine with Iulia.</stage>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Con.</speaker>
                  <l>Where is he?</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Iu.</speaker>
                  <l>Here.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Con.</speaker>
                  <l>The welcom'ſt man alive,</l>
                  <l>Vnkind, how couldſt thou ſtay from me ſo long?</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Otho.</speaker>
                  <l>I have bin ill at eaſe, pray pardon me,</l>
                  <l>But I reioyce to ſee my friend ſo well.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Euph.</speaker>
                  <l>Some Ladies love hath made him melancholy.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Otho.</speaker>
                  <l>Shee hath read the letter that I lately ſent her,</l>
                  <l>In a pomegranat, by thoſe words I hope.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Con.</speaker>
                  <l>Why ſpeak you not, is't love, or melancholy?</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Otho.</speaker>
                  <l>If upon love my griefe is melancholy.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Con.</speaker>
                  <l>Ile haue the beſt Phiſitians here in <hi>Meath.</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>Aſſay by art to cure that malladie.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Eup.</speaker>
                  <l>Gainſt mellancholy minds your onely Phiſick</l>
                  <l>Our <hi>Saxon</hi> doctors hold that principle,</l>
                  <l>Now I remember you did lately ſend me</l>
                  <l>A choice pomegranate, fetch it <hi>Iulia,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>Some of thoſe graines well ſtir'd in Gaſcoine wine,</l>
                  <pb facs="tcp:20581:9"/>
                  <l>Is preſent remedie.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Otho.</speaker>
                  <l>Madam, Ile none</l>
                  <l>Of all fruits, that <hi>I</hi> hate.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Eu.</speaker>
                  <l>And commended it ſo highly by the meſſenger that brought it.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Con.</speaker>
                  <l>Twas well remembred, you ſhall take a graine.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Otho.</speaker>
                  <l>You will but vexe me.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Con.</speaker>
                  <l>So his melancholly</l>
                  <l>Doth make him froward with his deareſt friend,</l>
                  <stage>Enter Iulia with the pomegranate.</stage>
                  <l>Tis well done <hi>Iulia,</hi> quickely cut it up,</l>
                  <l>And bring a cup of wine, or let me doo't.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Otho.</speaker>
                  <l>I ſee <hi>I</hi> ſhall be plagu'd with mine owne wit:</l>
                  <l>Being aſham'd to ſpeake, I writ my minde,</l>
                  <l>Were you my friends, you would not martyr me</l>
                  <l>With needleſſe phiſicke, fie upon this traſn,</l>
                  <l>The very ſight is loathſome.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Con.</speaker>
                  <l>Take it up.</l>
                  <l>But let me ſee, what letter's that that dropt,</l>
                  <l>Came it from you, or from the Spaniſh fruit.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Iu.</speaker>
                  <l>Tis all the graines that the pomegranate had.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Con.</speaker>
                  <l>Then ther's ſome trechery within theſe grains,</l>
                  <l>Ile breake it up,</l>
                  <l>And 'tis directed to my <hi>Euphrata.</hi>
                  </l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Eup.</speaker>
                  <l>What may the tenure be, <hi>I</hi> pray thee reade it.</l>
               </sp>
               <stage>He opens the letter &amp; reads.</stage>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Otho.</speaker>
                  <l>O fall upon me ſome wind-ſhaken turrer,</l>
                  <l>To hide me from the anger of my friend,</l>
                  <l>O from his frowne, becauſe he is my friend,</l>
                  <l>Were he an enemie, <hi>I</hi> would be bold.</l>
                  <l>But kindnes makes this wound; ô this horror,</l>
                  <l>The words of friends are ſtronger then their power.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Con.</speaker>
                  <l>Withdraw good <hi>Iulia.</hi>
                  </l>
               </sp>
               <stage>Exit Iulia.</stage>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Eup.</speaker>
                  <l>'Pray what is it love?</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Con.</speaker>
                  <l>Tis love indeed to thee, but to my heart</l>
                  <l>Every looſe ſentence is a killing dart.</l>
                  <l>I brought this Gorges to my hearts delight.</l>
                  <l>And he hath drown'd his ſenſes with the ſight,</l>
                  <pb facs="tcp:20581:10"/>
                  <l>Except thy ſelfe, all things to him were free,</l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Otho,</hi> thou haſt done me more then iniurie,</l>
                  <l>Well maiſt thou fixe thy eye vpon the earth,</l>
                  <l>This action fith breedes a prodigious birth,</l>
                  <l>It is ſo monſtrous and againſt all kinde,</l>
                  <l>That the lights ſplendor would confound thy minde.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Otho.</speaker>
                  <l>I have offended, prethee pardon me.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Con.</speaker>
                  <l>What cauſe did move thee?</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Otho.</speaker>
                  <l>Her all-conquering ſight.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Con.</speaker>
                  <l>Couldſt thou uſurpe upon my well known right?</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Otho.</speaker>
                  <l>Thinke I am fleſh and blood, and ſhe is faire.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Con.</speaker>
                  <l>Thinke how I love thee.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Otho.</speaker>
                  <l>There proceeds my care.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Con.</speaker>
                  <l>Our amitie hath bin of ancient dayes,</l>
                  <l>During which time, wrong'd I thee any wayes?</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Otho.</speaker>
                  <l>Never.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Con.</speaker>
                  <l>But rather I have done thee good.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Otho.</speaker>
                  <l>I grant you have, ô rather ſhed my blood,</l>
                  <l>Then number the kind deedes betweene us paſt,</l>
                  <l>For this unkindneſſe here I love my laſt.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Euph.</speaker>
                  <l>He doth repent, and will renounce his ſuite,</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Otho.</speaker>
                  <l>I doe renounce it.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Con.</speaker>
                  <l>O thou canſt not do't.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Otho.</speaker>
                  <l>Suffer me ſtay a while in her faire ſight,</l>
                  <l>'T will heale my wound and all love baniſh quite.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Con.</speaker>
                  <l>The ſight of the belov'd, makes the deſire</l>
                  <l>That burnt but ſlowly, flame like ſparkling fire.</l>
                  <l>As thou doſt love me, take thee to ſome place,</l>
                  <l>Where thou maiſt nere ſee her, nor I thy face.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Otho.</speaker>
                  <l>By what is deere betwixt us, by our ſelves,</l>
                  <l>I vow hencefoorth ten thouſand deaths to prove,</l>
                  <l>Then be a hinderance to ſuch vertuous love.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Con.</speaker>
                  <l>Breake heart, tis for thy ſake.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Otho.</speaker>
                  <l>When I am dead,</l>
                  <l>O then forget that I haue iniured.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Con.</speaker>
                  <l>O hell of love.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Otho.</speaker>
                  <l>Or rather hell of friends.</l>
               </sp>
               <pb facs="tcp:20581:10"/>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Con.</speaker>
                  <l>Firmely till they love.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Otho.</speaker>
                  <l>Then thus all friendſhip ends.</l>
               </sp>
               <stage>Exeunt.</stage>
            </div>
            <div type="act">
               <head>Actus Secundus.</head>
               <stage>Enter Duke, Fredericke, Hatto and Alfred.</stage>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Hat.</speaker>
                  <l>Good brother heare ſome Muſicke, twill delight you.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Al.</speaker>
                  <l>Ile call the Actors, will you ſee a play?</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Fre.</speaker>
                  <l>Or gracious father, ſee me runne the race,</l>
                  <l>On a light footed horſe, ſwifter then winde.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Duke.</speaker>
                  <l>I pray forbeare.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Al.</speaker>
                  <l>This moode will make you mad,</l>
                  <l>For melancholy Vſhers franticke thoughts.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Hat.</speaker>
                  <l>It makes hot wreaking blood turne cold and drie,</l>
                  <l>And drithe and coldneſſe are the ſignes of death.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Duke.</speaker>
                  <l>You doe torment me.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Fred.</speaker>
                  <l>Is it any thing</l>
                  <l>That I have done, offends your grace?</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Hat.</speaker>
                  <l>Or comes this hidden anger from my fault?</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Alf.</speaker>
                  <l>Heres none but gladly would reſigne his life,</l>
                  <l>To doe you pleaſure, ſo pleaſe you to command.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Duke.</speaker>
                  <l>Ifaith you are too blame to vexe me thus.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Hat.</speaker>
                  <l>Then grounds this ſorrow on your brothers death?</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Fred.</speaker>
                  <l>Or rather on the glove I lately found.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Duke.</speaker>
                  <l>A plague vpon the glove, whats that to me,</l>
                  <l>Your prating makes me almoſt lunatike.</l>
                  <l>As you reſpect my welfare, leave me, leave me,</l>
                  <l>The ſooner you depart, the ſooner <hi>I</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>Shall finde ſome meanes to cure my maladie.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Fred.</speaker>
                  <l>Our beſt courſe is to be obedient.</l>
               </sp>
               <stage>Exeunt all but the Duke.</stage>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Duke.</speaker>
                  <l>Farewell,</l>
                  <l>Was ever ſlave beſotted like to me,</l>
                  <l>That Kings have lou'd, thoſe that they never ſaw,</l>
                  <l>Is nothing ſtrange, ſince they have heard their praiſe,</l>
                  <l>Birds that by painted grapes have bin deceiu'd,</l>
                  <pb facs="tcp:20581:11"/>
                  <l>Had yet ſome ſhadow to excuſe their error,</l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Pigmalion</hi> that did love an Ivory Nimph,</l>
                  <l>Had an <hi>Idea</hi> to delight his ſence,</l>
                  <l>The youth that doted on <hi>Minerva's</hi> picture,</l>
                  <l>Had ſome contentment for his eye</l>
                  <stage>ſoft Muſique.</stage>
                  <l>But love, or rather an infernall hagge,</l>
                  <l>Envying <hi>Saxons</hi> greatnes and his ioyes,</l>
                  <l>Hath given me nothing but a trifling glove,</l>
                  <l>As if by the proportion of the caſe,</l>
                  <l>Art had the power to know the jewels nature,</l>
                  <l>Or Nimph, or goddeſſe, woman, or faire devill</l>
                  <l>If any thing thou art within my braine,</l>
                  <l>Draw thine owne picture, let me ſee thy face,</l>
                  <l>To doate thus groſſely, is a groſſe diſgrace.</l>
                  <stage>Muſique within.</stage>
                  <l>I heare ſome Muſique, ô ye Deities.</l>
                  <l>Send you this heavenly conſort from the ſpheares?</l>
                  <l>To recreate a love-perplexed heart.</l>
                  <l>The more it founds, the more it refreſheth,</l>
                  <l>I ſee no inſtruments, nor hands that play,</l>
                  <l>And my deare brothers durſt not be ſo bold,</l>
                  <l>'Tis ſome celeſtiall rapture of the minde,</l>
                  <l>No earthlie harmonie is of this kinde,</l>
                  <l>Now it doth ceaſe, ſpeake who comes there?</l>
               </sp>
               <stage>Enter Fredericke, Alfred, and Hatto.</stage>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Fred.</speaker>
                  <l>Father.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Duke.</speaker>
                  <l>From whence proceeds the Muſicke that I heard?</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Fred.</speaker>
                  <l>The beauteous and the famous Curtezan,</l>
                  <l>Allyed unto the baniſhed <hi>Montano,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>Admir'd <hi>
                        <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>alontia,</hi> with a troope of youths,</l>
                  <l>This day doth keepe her yeerely feſtiuall,</l>
                  <l>To all her ſutors, and this way ſhe paſt</l>
                  <l>Vnto her Arbor, when the Muſique plaide.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Duke.</speaker>
                  <l>Admir'd <hi>
                        <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>alentia,</hi> Curtezans are ſtrange</l>
                  <l>With us in <hi>Germanie,</hi> except her ſelfe,</l>
                  <l>Being a <hi>Venetian</hi> borne, and priviledg'd,</l>
                  <pb facs="tcp:20581:11"/>
                  <l>The ſtate allowes none here.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Fred.</speaker>
                  <l>Twere good for <hi>Meath</hi> ſhe were unpriuiledgd</l>
                  <l>And ſent to <hi>
                        <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>enice.</hi>
                  </l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Al.</speaker>
                  <l>Of all the faces that mine eye beheld,</l>
                  <l>Hers is the brighteſt.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Duke.</speaker>
                  <l>Is ſhe then ſo faire?</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Hat.</speaker>
                  <l>O beyond all compariſon of beautie.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Fred.</speaker>
                  <l>Vpon her hand,</l>
                  <l>Father I ſaw the fellow to your glove.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Duke.</speaker>
                  <l>What the imbroidred glove you lately found?</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Fred.</speaker>
                  <l>Fellow to that.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Duke.</speaker>
                  <l>Then let it be reſtor'd,</l>
                  <l>What ſhould a Prince retaine a ſtrumpets glove?</l>
                  <l>O ye eternall powers, am I inſnar'd</l>
                  <l>With the affection of a common trull,</l>
                  <l>Wheres your commiſſions that you would have ſign'd,</l>
                  <l>'Tis time I had a preſident in <hi>Saxonie,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>Receive our ſignet, and impreſſe them ſtraight,</l>
                  <l>Ile remaine here in <hi>Meath,</hi> ſome little time,</l>
                  <l>Brother have care my Dukedome be well rul'd,</l>
                  <l>Here I put over my affaires to you,</l>
                  <l>My ſonne I leave unto the ioyes of youth,</l>
                  <l>Tis pittie that his mind ſhould be oppreſt</l>
                  <l>So ſoone with care of governments,</l>
                  <l>Goe to your pleaſures, ſeeke your ſiſter foorth,</l>
                  <l>Send <hi>Conſtantine</hi> to us, ſo leaue me all,</l>
                  <l>I am beſt accompanied with none at all.</l>
                  <stage>Exeunt.</stage>
                  <stage>Manet Duke.</stage>
                  <l>Either the Plannets that did meete together,</l>
                  <l>In the grand conſultation of my birth,</l>
                  <l>Were oppoſite to every good infuſion,</l>
                  <l>Or onely <hi>Venus</hi> ſtood as retrograde,</l>
                  <l>For but in love of this none loving trull,</l>
                  <l>I have beene fortunate even ſince my birth,</l>
                  <l>I feele within my breaſt a ſearching fire,</l>
                  <l>Which doth aſcend the engine of my braine,</l>
                  <l>And when I ſeeke by reaſon to ſuppreſſe</l>
                  <pb facs="tcp:20581:12"/>
                  <l>The heate it gives, the greaters the exceſſe:</l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>I</hi> loath to looke upon a common lip.</l>
                  <l>Were it as corrall as <hi>Aurora's</hi> cheeke,</l>
                  <l>Died with the faire virmillion ſunne:</l>
                  <l>O but <hi>I</hi> loue her, and they ſay ſhe is faire,</l>
                  <l>Now <hi>Conſtantine.</hi>
                  </l>
               </sp>
               <stage>Enter Conſtantine.</stage>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Con:</speaker>
                  <l>Your grace did ſend for me.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Duke.</speaker>
                  <l>Lend me your habit in exchange of mine,</l>
                  <l>For <hi>I</hi> muſt walke the Citie for a purpoſe.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Con.</speaker>
                  <l>Withall my heart, my habit and my ſelfe.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Duke.</speaker>
                  <l>In any caſe, watch at the privie chamber.</l>
                  <l>If any aske for me, ſay <hi>I</hi> am not well,</l>
                  <l>And tho it be my ſonne, let him not enter.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Con</speaker>
                  <l>I will.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Duke.</speaker>
                  <l>Be carefull gentle <hi>Conſtantine,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>Now faire <hi>Valentia, Saxon</hi> to thy bower,</l>
                  <l>Comes like a <hi>Iove</hi> to raine a golden ſhower.</l>
               </sp>
               <stage>Exit.</stage>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Con.</speaker>
                  <l>Proſper kind Lord, what ere the action be,</l>
                  <l>Counſailes of Princes ſhould be ever free.</l>
               </sp>
               <stage>Exit.</stage>
               <stage>Enter Valentia, and Montano.</stage>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>a.</speaker>
                  <l>Torches and Muſique there, the room's too darke.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Mon.</speaker>
                  <l>Prethee Neece</l>
                  <l>Abandon this laſcivious unchaſte life,</l>
                  <l>It is the onely blemiſh of our houſe,</l>
                  <l>Scandall unto our name, a Curtezan,</l>
                  <l>O what's more odious in the eares of men!</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Val.</speaker>
                  <l>Then why doe men reſort to Curtezans,</l>
                  <l>And the beſt ſort; <hi>I</hi> ſcorne inferiour groomes.</l>
                  <l>Nor will <hi>I</hi> denie to draw aſide my maske,</l>
                  <l>To any meaner then a Noble man.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Val.</speaker>
                  <l>Come, can you dance: a caper and a kiſſe,</l>
                  <l>For every turne, Ile fold thee in my armes,</l>
                  <l>And if thou fal'ſt although no a kin we be,</l>
                  <l>That thou maiſt light fall ſoft, Ile fall under thee,</l>
                  <l>Oh for the lightneſſe of all light heel'd girles.</l>
                  <l>And <hi>I</hi> would touch the Ceeling with my lips,</l>
                  <l>Why art thou ſad <hi>Montano?</hi>
                  </l>
               </sp>
               <pb facs="tcp:20581:12"/>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Mon.</speaker>
                  <l>On iuſt cauſe,</l>
                  <l>You know I am baniſh't from my natiue countrey.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Val.</speaker>
                  <l>This citie is <hi>Meath,</hi> thou art of <hi>Saxonie.</hi>
                  </l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Mon.</speaker>
                  <l>But this belongs unto the <hi>Saxons</hi> Duke:</l>
                  <l>By the deceaſe of the departed Biſhop.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>al.</speaker>
                  <l>Feare not, thou art as ſafe within my houſe,</l>
                  <l>As if perculliz'd in a wall of braſſe.</l>
                  <l>Wheres <hi>
                        <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>andermas?</hi>
                  </l>
               </sp>
               <stage>Enter <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>andermas.</stage>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Van.</speaker>
                  <l>Madam did you call?</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Mon.</speaker>
                  <l>What noble man is that, a ſutor to you?</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Val.</speaker>
                  <l>An excellent Pander, a rare doore-keeper.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Mon.</speaker>
                  <l>
                     <hi>I</hi> had thought he had bin a gentleman at leaſt.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Val.</speaker>
                  <l>Becauſe of his attire?</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Mon.</speaker>
                  <l>True.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Val.</speaker>
                  <l>O the attire, in theſe corrupted daies, is no true ſigne</l>
                  <l>To ſhew the gentleman; peaſants now weare robes</l>
                  <l>In the habiliments of noblemen.</l>
                  <l>The world's grovvn naught, ſuch iudgement then is baſe,</l>
                  <l>For Hares and Aſſes we are the Lions caſe.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Mon.</speaker>
                  <l>'Tis very coſtly and exceeding rich.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Val.</speaker>
                  <l>Riches to me, are like traſh to the poore,</l>
                  <l>I haue them in abundance, gold's my ſlave,</l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>I</hi> keepe him priſoner in a three-fold cheſt,</l>
                  <l>And yet his kindred daily viſit me.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Mon.</speaker>
                  <l>Lord how diligent</l>
                  <l>Is this rich clothed fellow!</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Val.</speaker>
                  <l>Were he proud,</l>
                  <l>And ſhould but dare to ſtand ſtill when <hi>I</hi> call,</l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>I</hi>'de runne him through with a killing frowne.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Mon.</speaker>
                  <l>Why then belike his ſervice is for love.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Val:</speaker>
                  <l>Why ſo are all the ſervants that attend mee,</l>
                  <l>They keepe themſelves in ſattin, velvets, gold,</l>
                  <l>At their owne charge, and are diligent,</l>
                  <l>Daies, moneths, and yeeres, to gaine an amorous ſmile.</l>
                  <l>Looke on my face with an indifferent eye.</l>
                  <l>And thou ſhalt finde more muſicke in my lookes,</l>
                  <l>Then in <hi>Amphions</hi> Lute, or <hi>Orpheus</hi> Harpe,</l>
                  <pb facs="tcp:20581:13"/>
                  <l>Mine eye conſiſts of numbers like the ſoule,</l>
                  <l>And if there be a ſoule, tis in mine ey,</l>
                  <l>For of the harmonie theſe bright ſtarres make,</l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>I</hi> comprehend the formes of all the world,</l>
                  <l>The ſtory of the <hi>Syrens</hi> in my voyce,</l>
                  <l>Is onely verified, for Millions ſtand</l>
                  <l>In chanted, when <hi>I</hi> ſpeake, and catch my words,</l>
                  <l>As they were orient pearle to adorne their eares,</l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Circe</hi> is but a fable, <hi>I</hi> transforme</l>
                  <l>The vertuous, valiant, and the moſt preciſe,</l>
                  <l>Into what forme of minde my fancie pleaſe,</l>
                  <l>Thou might'ſt bee proud great Lord of my abundance,</l>
                  <l>For in this beautie <hi>I</hi> ſhall more renowne</l>
                  <l>Our noble progenie, then all the pennes</l>
                  <l>Of the beſt Poets that ere writ of men.</l>
                  <l>Vnto your health, a health, let Muſique ſound,</l>
                  <stage>Muſick.</stage>
                  <l>That what <hi>I</hi> taſte, in Muſique may be drown'd.</l>
                  <l>So, fill more wine, we vſe to drinke up all,</l>
                  <l>Wine makes good blood, and cheeres the heart withal.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Van.</speaker>
                  <l>Madam, at ſuch time as <hi>I</hi> heard you call,</l>
                  <l>A gentleman it ſeemes of good diſcent,</l>
                  <l>Humblie did craue acceſſe unto your honor,</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>alen.</speaker>
                  <l>What did he give?</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Van.</speaker>
                  <l>A brace of bags of gold.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Valen.</speaker>
                  <l>He ſhall have libertie to enter ſtraight.</l>
                  <l>But firſt inrich the chamber with perfumes.</l>
                  <l>Burne choice <hi>Arabian</hi> Drugs more deare then</l>
                  <l>Waters diſtil'd out of the ſpirit of Flowers,</l>
                  <l>And ſpread our coſtly Arras to the eye.</l>
                  <l>My ſelfe ſufficiently doe ſhine in jems,</l>
                  <l>Where ſuch faire coated Heraulds doe proceed,</l>
                  <l>It ſeemes he is honorable and of noble ſame.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Mon.</speaker>
                  <l>Shall <hi>I</hi> behold this ſutor?</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Valen.</speaker>
                  <l>At the full,</l>
                  <l>At pleaſure paſſe through every ſpacious Roome,</l>
                  <l>Be he a Prince, <hi>Ile</hi> know his high diſcent.</l>
                  <pb facs="tcp:20581:13"/>
                  <l>Or proudly ſcorne to give him his content,</l>
                  <l>What drum is that?</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Van.</speaker>
                  <l>A Maske ſent by a friend.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Valen.</speaker>
                  <l>Belike our ſelfe muſt know the myſterie,</l>
                  <l>Tell them we are prepar'd to ſee the Maske,</l>
                  <l>And bid the other noblemen come neere,</l>
                  <l>Thus am <hi>I</hi> hourely viſited by friends,</l>
                  <l>Beautie's a counſellor that wants no fee,</l>
                  <l>They talke of circles and of powerfull ſpells,</l>
                  <l>Heres heavenly art, that all blacke art excells,</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Mon.</speaker>
                  <l>Ile walke into the farther gallery.</l>
               </sp>
               <stage>Enter Duke.</stage>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Valen.</speaker>
                  <l>Sir you are welcome what ſo ere you be,</l>
                  <l>I gueſſe your birth great by your bounteous fee.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Duke.</speaker>
                  <l>Your humble ſervant bound by a ſweet kiſſe.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Valen.</speaker>
                  <l>I give you freedome gentle Sir by this.</l>
               </sp>
               <stage>He whiſpers her.</stage>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>al.</speaker>
                  <l>I know your mind, firſt cenſure of the ſport,</l>
                  <l>Then you and I will enter <hi>Venus</hi> Court.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Du.</speaker>
                  <l>More then immortall, ô more then divine,</l>
                  <l>That ſuch perfection ſhould turne Concubine.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Mon.</speaker>
                  <l>That voice is like unto the <hi>Saxon Dukes,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>I feare he hath heard I liu'd here in this place,</l>
                  <l>And he is come to doe me more diſgrace,</l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Montano</hi> hide thy ſelfe till he be gone,</l>
                  <l>His daughter thirſts for my deſtruction.</l>
               </sp>
               <stage>Exit Mont</stage>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Val.</speaker>
                  <l>Come ſit by me, the Maskers are at hand,</l>
                  <stage>Enter Maske.</stage>
                  <l>Where are my Maides, to helpe to make the dance?</l>
               </sp>
               <stage>
                  <hi>Enter</hi> 2. <hi>Maids.</hi>
               </stage>
               <stage>They dance, Valentia with them, they whiſper to to have her play at dice, and ſtake on the drum.</stage>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Valen.</speaker>
                  <l>VVhat ſhall we have a Mumming? heres my jewell.</l>
               </sp>
               <stage>Play on the drum head.</stage>
               <pb facs="tcp:20581:14"/>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Duke.</speaker>
                  <l>Thou art a iewell moſt incomparable,</l>
                  <l>Malicious heaven, why from ſo ſweete a face</l>
                  <l>Have you exempt the mind adorning grace?</l>
               </sp>
               <stage>they ſtake and play.</stage>
               <stage>She wins, the drum ſtrikes up.</stage>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Val.</speaker>
                  <l>More gold, for this is mine, I thanke yee dice</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Duke.</speaker>
                  <l>And ſo are all that doe behold thy beautie,</l>
                  <l>Were ſhe as chaſte as ſhe is outward bright,</l>
                  <l>Earth would be heaven, and heaven eternall night,</l>
                  <l>The more I drinke of her delicious eye,</l>
                  <l>The more I plunge into captivitie.</l>
               </sp>
               <stage>She wins, ſtrike up.</stage>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Valen.</speaker>
                  <l>Have I wonne all? then take that back agen,</l>
                  <l>What ſcorne my gift, I ſee you are gentlemen,</l>
                  <l>No, is't not poſſible that I may know,</l>
                  <l>Vnto whoſe kindneſſe this great debt I owe?</l>
                  <l>Well, Ile not be importunate, farewell,</l>
                  <l>Some of your gold let the torch-bearers tell.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Duk.</speaker>
                  <l>Beauteous <hi>Madona,</hi> do you know theſe galants?</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Valen.</speaker>
                  <l>I gueſſe them of the Duke of <hi>Saxons</hi> Court.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Duke.</speaker>
                  <l>My ſubiects, and ſo many my corrivalls,</l>
                  <l>O every ſlave is grac't before his Prince.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Valen.</speaker>
                  <l>Are you not well ſir, that your colour fades.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Duke.</speaker>
                  <l>If I be ſicke, 'tis onely in the minde,</l>
                  <l>To ſee ſo faire, ſo common to all kinde.</l>
                  <l>I am growne iealous now of all the world,</l>
                  <l>Lady how ere you prize me, without pleaſure,</l>
                  <l>More then a kiſſe, I tender you this treaſure.</l>
                  <l>O what's a mint ſpent in ſuch deſire,</l>
                  <l>But like a ſparke that makes a greater fire?</l>
                  <l>She muſt be made my Dutches, there it goes,</l>
                  <l>And marrying her, I marry thouſand woes.</l>
                  <l>Adiew kind Miſtreſſe, the next nevves you heare,</l>
                  <pb facs="tcp:20581:14"/>
                  <l>Is to ſit crown'd in an Imperiall crowne.</l>
               </sp>
               <stage>Exit.</stage>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Valen.</speaker>
                  <l>Either the man diſlikes me, or his braine,</l>
                  <l>Is not his owne to give, ſuch gifts in vaine.</l>
                  <l>But 'tis the cuſtome in this age to caſt</l>
                  <l>Gold upon gold, to encourage men to waſte,</l>
                  <l>Lightly it comes, and it ſhall lightly flie.</l>
                  <l>Whilſt colours hold, ſuch preſents cannot die.</l>
               </sp>
               <stage>Exit.</stage>
               <stage>Enter Reinaldo, Alfred and Albert.</stage>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Alb.</speaker>
                  <l>But this is ſtrange, that I ſhould have her honour?</l>
                  <l>So farre from Court, pray whither were you riding?</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Alf.</speaker>
                  <l>Vnto your mannor, heard you not the newes.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Alb.</speaker>
                  <l>What newes?</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Alf.</speaker>
                  <l>This morning by the breake of day,</l>
                  <l>His excellence ſent to me by a poſt,</l>
                  <l>Letters, by which the pillars of the ſtate</l>
                  <l>Should be aſſembled to a Parliament,</l>
                  <l>Which he intends my Lords, to hold in <hi>Meath.</hi>
                  </l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Alb.</speaker>
                  <l>When if it pleaſe your honor?</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Alf.</speaker>
                  <l>Inſtantly, withall the haſt that winged time can make.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Albert.</speaker>
                  <l>Sooner the better,</l>
                  <l>Tis like the realmes affaires are of ſome weight.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Alb.</speaker>
                  <l>
                     <hi>I</hi> will bee there to night,</l>
                  <l>And ſo I take my leave.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Reinal.</speaker>
                  <l>We take our leaves.</l>
               </sp>
               <stage>Exit Albert, and Reinaldo.</stage>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Alf.</speaker>
                  <l>Farewell my honor'd friend,</l>
                  <l>There is within my braine a thouſand wiles,</l>
                  <l>How I may heape up riches, ô the ſight</l>
                  <l>Of a gold ſhining Mountaine doth exceede,</l>
                  <l>Silver is good, but in reſpect of gold,</l>
                  <l>Thus I eſteeme it.</l>
               </sp>
               <stage>Exit.</stage>
               <stage>Enter Hatto with three petitioners.</stage>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Hat.</speaker>
                  <l>How now my friends, what are you?</l>
                  <l>1. Poore petitioners.</l>
               </sp>
               <pb facs="tcp:20581:15"/>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Hat.</speaker>
                  <l>Stand farther then, the poore is as unpleaſing Vnto me as the plague.</l>
                  <p n="2">2. An't pleaſe your good Lordſhip, I am a Merchant and gladly would convay a thouſand quarters of wheate and other graine over the ſea, and heres a hundred pounds for a commiſſion.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Hat.</speaker>
                  <l>Thou art no beggar, thou ſhalt ha't my friend, Give me thy money.</l>
                  <p n="3">3. I an't pleaſe your honour have a commoditie of good broad cloth, not paſt two hundred, may I ſhippe them over, and theres a hundred poundes.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Hat.</speaker>
                  <l>Thou ſhalt have leave.</l>
                  <l>1. Although I ſeeme a poore petitioner,</l>
                  <l>My Lord I crave a warrant to tranſport</l>
                  <l>A hundred Cannons, fiftie Culverings,</l>
                  <l>VVith ſome ſlight armours, halberts, and halfe pikes,</l>
                  <l>And theres as much as any of the reſt.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Hat.</speaker>
                  <l>Away <hi>Cannibal,</hi> wouldſt thou ſhip ordnance?</l>
                  <l>What though we ſend unto the foes our corne,</l>
                  <l>To fatten them, and cloth to keepe them warme,</l>
                  <l>Lets not be ſo forgetfull of our ſelves</l>
                  <l>As to provide them knives to cut our throates,</l>
                  <l>So I ſhould arme a thiefe to take my purſe,</l>
                  <l>Haſt thou no other courſe of Merchandize?</l>
                  <l>Thou ſhouldſt get gold, twill yeeld thee ten in the hun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dred</l>
                  <l>On bare exchange, and raiſe the price with vs,</l>
                  <l>Make us for want, coyn, braſſe, and paſſe it currant,</l>
                  <l>Vntill we find profit to call it in,</l>
                  <l>There are a thouſand waies to make thee thrive,</l>
                  <l>And Ile allow of all bee it nere ſo bad,</l>
                  <l>Excepting guns to batter downe our houſes.</l>
                  <l>1. Letters of Mart <hi>I</hi> humblie then intreate,</l>
                  <l>To ceaſe on Rovers that doe ſcoure the ſeas.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Hat.</speaker>
                  <l>And on our friends too, if thou canſt do't clean<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lie,</l>
                  <l>Spare none, but paſſe it very cloſely,</l>
                  <l>VVe will be loath to ſift thy Piracie.</l>
                  <l>But open care to heare what they complaine,</l>
                  <pb facs="tcp:20581:15"/>
                  <l>Haſt thou a Letter?</l>
                  <l>1. Ready drawne my Lord,</l>
                  <l>And heres a brace of hundred pounds for you.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Hat.</speaker>
                  <l>'Tis very well, I thinke I ſhall be rich,</l>
                  <l>If dayly tenants pay me rent thus faſt,</l>
                  <l>Giue me your licenſes, they ſhall bee ſeal'd,</l>
                  <l>About an houre hence, here attend our pleaſure.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Omnes.</speaker>
                  <l>VVe thanke your Lordſhip.</l>
               </sp>
               <stage>Exeunt petiti.</stage>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Hat.</speaker>
                  <l>O vild catterpillers,</l>
                  <l>And yet how neceſſarie for my turne,</l>
                  <l>I have the Dukes ſeale for the Citie <hi>Meath,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>VVith which Ile ſigne their warrants,</l>
                  <l>This corne and twentie times as much</l>
                  <l>Alreadie covertly convai'd to <hi>France,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>And other bordering Kingdomes neere the ſea,</l>
                  <l>Cannot but make a famine in this land,</l>
                  <l>And then the poore like dogs will die apace,</l>
                  <l>Ile ſeeme to pittie them, and give them almes,</l>
                  <l>To blind the world, 'tis excellent policie,</l>
                  <l>To rid the land of ſuch, by ſuch denice,</l>
                  <l>A famine to the poore, is like a froſt</l>
                  <l>Vnto the earth, which kills the paltry wormes,</l>
                  <l>That would deſtroy the harveſt of the ſpring,</l>
                  <l>As for the which, I count them painefull men</l>
                  <l>VVorthy to enioy what they can get,</l>
                  <l>Beggars are traſh, and I eſteeme them ſo,</l>
                  <l>Starve, hang, or drowne themſelves, I am alive,</l>
                  <l>Looſe all the world, ſo <hi>I</hi> have wit to thrive,</l>
                  <l>But I muſt to the Parliament, and then</l>
                  <l>Ile have a clauſe to beggar ſome rich meu.</l>
               </sp>
               <stage>Exit.</stage>
            </div>
            <div type="act">
               <head>Actus Tertius.</head>
               <stage>Enter Duke, Fredericke, Conſtantine, Reinaldo, Alberto, Alfrid, and a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mongſt them Hatto ſhuffles in.</stage>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Alberto.</speaker>
                  <l>Princes and pillars of the <hi>Saxon</hi> State.</l>
               </sp>
               <pb facs="tcp:20581:16"/>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Duke.</speaker>
                  <l>You are the elected, ſpeake for the Court,</l>
                  <l>Stay Lord <hi>Alberto,</hi> we uſurpe your office,</l>
                  <l>Who had the charge to fetch <hi>Valentia.</hi>
                  </l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Con.</speaker>
                  <l>I gracious Lord, and when I gave the charge,</l>
                  <l>A ſudden ſcare by paleneſſe was diſplar'd</l>
                  <l>Vpon her roſie cheeke, the crimſon blood,</l>
                  <l>That like a robe of ſtate did beautifie</l>
                  <l>The goodly buildings with a two fold grace,</l>
                  <l>From either ſide ſhrunke downewards to her heart,</l>
                  <l>As if thoſe ſummons were an adverſarie,</l>
                  <l>And had ſome mighty crime to charge her with,</l>
                  <l>Millions of thoughts were crowded in her braines,</l>
                  <l>Her troubled minde, her abrupt words deſcrib'd,</l>
                  <l>She did accuſe her ſelfe without accuſers,</l>
                  <l>And in the terrour of a ſoule perplext,</l>
                  <l>Cry'd out, the Duke intends to ceaſe my goods,</l>
                  <l>Cauſe I am noted for a Concubine,</l>
                  <l>I did replie ſuch comfort as beſeemes,</l>
                  <l>But comfortleſſe <hi>I</hi> brought her to the Court.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Duke.</speaker>
                  <l>Then ſhe attends our pleaſure?</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Con.</speaker>
                  <l>Mightie Lord in the next Roome.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Duke.</speaker>
                  <l>You are carefull <hi>Conſtantiue,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>Conduct her in, and Lords give mee your thoughts,</l>
                  <l>What thinke ye wee intend to <hi>
                        <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>alentia?</hi>
                  </l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Alf.</speaker>
                  <l>Her ſelfe hath read my ſentence in the ſpeech,</l>
                  <l>That <hi>Conſtantine</hi> delivered to your grace.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Fred.</speaker>
                  <l>What ſhould my noble father thinke,</l>
                  <l>But that ſhee is a ſtrumpet, and in that,</l>
                  <l>A blemiſh to the ſtate wherein ſhe lives.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Hat.</speaker>
                  <l>She is rich in iewells, and hath ſtore of treaſure,</l>
                  <l>Got by the ſlavery of that choice beautie,</l>
                  <l>Which otherwiſe admires her to the world.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Alb.</speaker>
                  <l>Confiſcate all her goods unto the Crown,</l>
                  <l>Thereby diſburdening many heavie taxes.</l>
                  <l>Impos'd upon the commons of the land.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Hat.</speaker>
                  <l>Publique example make her to all ſuch</l>
                  <pb facs="tcp:20581:16"/>
                  <l>Offences in that kind are growne too common,</l>
                  <l>Leſſe ſhameleſſe now were the beautious dames</l>
                  <l>Of <hi>Meath</hi> and <hi>Saxony,</hi> when the ſufferance</l>
                  <l>Hath at this inſtant made them good my Lord,</l>
                  <l>Enact ſome mighty penaltie for luſt.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Duke.</speaker>
                  <l>How wide theſe Archers ſhoote from the faire aime</l>
                  <l>Of my affection: bring <hi>Valentia</hi> in.</l>
               </sp>
               <stage>Enter Valentia, uſher'd by Conſtantine.</stage>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Valen.</speaker>
                  <l>The duetie that in generall <hi>I</hi> doe owe</l>
                  <l>Vnto your excellence and to this Court,</l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>I</hi> pay at once upon my bended knee.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Duke.</speaker>
                  <l>Behold her Princes with impartiall eyes,</l>
                  <l>And tell me, looks ſhe not exceeding faire?</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Hat.</speaker>
                  <l>If that her mind coher'd with her faire face,</l>
                  <l>Shee were the worthy wonder of this age.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Alfred.</speaker>
                  <l>I never ſaw a beautie more divine,</l>
                  <l>Groſſely deform'd by her notorious luſt.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Fred.</speaker>
                  <l>Faireneſſe and wantonneſſe haue made a match</l>
                  <l>To dwell together, and the worſt ſpoyles both.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Albert.</speaker>
                  <l>Shee is doubly excellent in ſin and beauty.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Duke.</speaker>
                  <l>That they ſpeake truth my conſcience ſpeaks,</l>
                  <l>But that I loue her that <hi>I</hi> ſpeake my ſelfe:</l>
                  <l>Stand up divine deformitie of nature,</l>
                  <l>Beautious corruption, heavenly ſeeing evill,</l>
                  <l>What's excellent in good and bad ſtand up,</l>
                  <l>And in this Chaire prepared for a Duke,</l>
                  <l>Sit my bright Dutcheſſe, I command thee ſit:</l>
                  <l>You looke I am ſure for ſome apologie,</l>
                  <l>In this raſh action; all that I can ſay</l>
                  <l>Is that <hi>I</hi> loue her, and wil marry her.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Fred.</speaker>
                  <l>How, loue a Lais, a baſe Rodophe,</l>
                  <l>Whoſe body is as common as the Sea</l>
                  <l>In the receipt of every luſtfull ſpring?</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Albert.</speaker>
                  <l>The elements of which theſe orbes conſiſts</l>
                  <pb facs="tcp:20581:17"/>
                  <l>Fire, ayre, and water, with the good we tread</l>
                  <l>Are not more vulgar, common, popular</l>
                  <l>Then her imbracements.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Alberto.</speaker>
                  <l>To inch<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>yne the thoughts</l>
                  <l>Vnto this diſſemblance of laſcivious loue</l>
                  <l>Were to be maried to the broad rode way,</l>
                  <l>Which doth receiue the impreſſion of every kind.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Fred.</speaker>
                  <l>Speech doth want modeſty to ſet her forth</l>
                  <l>In her true forme, baſe and contemptible,</l>
                  <l>The very hindes and peaſants of the land</l>
                  <l>Will bee Corrivals with your excellence,</l>
                  <l>If you eſpouſe ſuch a notorious Trull.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Albert.</speaker>
                  <l>We ſhall haue luſt a vertue in the Court:</l>
                  <l>The wayes of ſinne be furthered by reward:</l>
                  <l>Panders and Paraſites ſit in the places</l>
                  <l>Of the wiſe Counſellors and hurry all.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Fred.</speaker>
                  <l>Father as you are princely in your birth,</l>
                  <l>Famous in your eſtate, belou'd of all</l>
                  <l>And (which ads greateſt glory to your greatneſſe)</l>
                  <l>Eſteem'd wiſe: Shew not ſuch open folly,</l>
                  <l>Such palpable, ſuch groſſe, ſuch mountaine folly,</l>
                  <l>Be not the By-word of your neighbour Kings,</l>
                  <l>The ſcandall of your Subiects, and the triumph</l>
                  <l>Of Lenos mathrens and the hatefull ſtewes:</l>
                  <l>Why ſpeake you not that are his brother friends,</l>
                  <l>You that doe weare the Liveries of time,</l>
                  <l>The ſilver cognizance of gravitie?</l>
                  <l>Shall none but young me ſchoole? the reverent old</l>
                  <l>Birds teach the Dam, ſtars fill the glorious ſpheares</l>
                  <l>Of the all lightning Sunne, ſpeake whilſt you may,</l>
                  <l>Or this raſh deede will make a fatall day.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Duke.</speaker>
                  <l>You haue ſaid too much, encourage none to ſpeake</l>
                  <l>More then haue ſpoke; by my royall blood,</l>
                  <l>My mind's eſtabliſht not to be withſtood,</l>
                  <l>Thoſe that applaude my choyſe giue us your hands,</l>
                  <l>And helpe to tye theſe ſacred nuptiall bands.</l>
               </sp>
               <pb facs="tcp:20581:17"/>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Hat.</speaker>
                  <l>What likes your excellence, likes me well.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Alfred.</speaker>
                  <l>And I agree to what my Soveraigne pleaſe.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Fred.</speaker>
                  <l>Theſe are no brothers, they are flatterers,</l>
                  <l>Contrary to themſelues in their owne ſpeech,</l>
                  <l>You that doe loue the honour of your Prince</l>
                  <l>The care and long life of my father,</l>
                  <l>The hereditary right deriv'd to me,</l>
                  <l>Your countries Welfare and your owne renowne,</l>
                  <l>Lend me your hands to plucke her from the throne.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Valen.</speaker>
                  <l>Princes forbeare, I doe not ſeeke the match,</l>
                  <l>It is his highneſſe pleaſure I fit here,</l>
                  <l>And if he loue me tis no fault of mine,</l>
                  <l>Behoues me to be thankefull to his Grace,</l>
                  <l>And ſtriue in vertue to deſerue this place.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Duke.</speaker>
                  <l>Thou ſpeak'ſt too mildly to theſe hare braind youthes:</l>
                  <l>He that preſumes to plucke her from the chaire</l>
                  <l>Dyes in the attempt, this ſword ſhall end all care.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Fred.</speaker>
                  <l>Why, ſhee's notorious.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Duke.</speaker>
                  <l>But ſhe will amend.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Fred.</speaker>
                  <l>'Tis too farre growne to haue a happy end.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Duke.</speaker>
                  <l>The dangerous the diſeaſe greater's the cure.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Fred.</speaker>
                  <l>Princes may ſeeke renowne by wayes more ſure,</l>
                  <l>Shee is diſhoneſt.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Duke.</speaker>
                  <l>Honeſtie's vnſeene,</l>
                  <l>Shee's faire, and therefore fit to be a Queene.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Fred.</speaker>
                  <l>But vertue is to be preferd ere luſt.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Duke.</speaker>
                  <l>Thoſe that are once falſe ſhal we ne're truſt?</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Fred.</speaker>
                  <l>Wiſe men approue their actions by the tryall.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Duke.</speaker>
                  <l>I ſay ſhe is mine in ſpight of all deniall.</l>
                  <l>Bring me the Crowne.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Fred.</speaker>
                  <l>To ſet upon her head?</l>
                  <l>Friends draw your ſwords firſt ſtrike the ſtrumpet dead.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Duke.</speaker>
                  <l>My guard, my guard.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Alfred.</speaker>
                  <l>For ſhame put up your ſwords.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Fred.</speaker>
                  <l>For ſhame great Rulers leaue your flattering words.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Albert.</speaker>
                  <l>'Tis madneſſe in the King, and worſe in you.</l>
               </sp>
               <pb facs="tcp:20581:18"/>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Hat.</speaker>
                  <l>Though you proue traytors we'le not proue untrue.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Fred.</speaker>
                  <l>Will you diſmiſſe this Strumpet to the ſtewes,</l>
                  <l>Or our allegance in this act refuſe.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Duke.</speaker>
                  <l>Doe what you dare, the election ſtill ſhall ſtand.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Fred.</speaker>
                  <l>Woe and deſtruction then muſt rule the land.</l>
                  <l>Come Lord <hi>Rinaldo,</hi> valiant <hi>Alberto</hi> come,</l>
                  <l>We haue friends enough to grace a warlike Drum.</l>
                  <stage>A ſhout within.</stage>
                  <l>Hearke how the Commons doe applaud our cauſe,</l>
                  <l>Laſcivious Duke, farewell father, oh vilde,</l>
                  <l>Where Queanes are mothers, <hi>Fredericke</hi> is no child.</l>
               </sp>
               <stage>Exeunt.</stage>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Duke.</speaker>
                  <l>My guard purſue them, and aliue or dead,</l>
                  <l>Cut off the cauſe by which theſe cries are bred,</l>
                  <l>Come my faire Dutcheſſe firſt unto the Church,</l>
                  <l>There ſollemnize our nuptials, then unto our armes,</l>
                  <l>A little rough breath over beares theſe ſtormes.</l>
               </sp>
               <stage>Exeunt. Manet Alfred &amp; Hatto.</stage>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Alfred.</speaker>
                  <l>The Duke's beſotted now we are ſecure,</l>
                  <l>This match makes well for us, we may command,</l>
                  <l>And on them lay the abuſes of the land.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Hat.</speaker>
                  <l>Excellent good, we are like to haue warres indeed,</l>
                  <l>But in the meane the poore will ſtarue for bread,</l>
                  <l>Wee muſt ſhare proffits howſoere things goe</l>
                  <l>Winner, or looſer, neither is our foe,</l>
                  <l>For mutually we'le beare our ſelues in all,</l>
                  <l>Or taking part leane to the ſtrongeſt wall.</l>
               </sp>
               <stage>Exeunt.</stage>
               <stage>Enter Conſtantine and Euphrata.</stage>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Eup.</speaker>
                  <l>My father married to a Concubine,</l>
                  <l>Then hee will pardon though <hi>I</hi> marry thee,</l>
                  <l>And howſoe'r, about it preſently,</l>
                  <l>The rather for <hi>Montano</hi> is repealde</l>
                  <l>Becauſe of his alliance to <hi>
                        <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>alentia.</hi>
                  </l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Con.</speaker>
                  <l>
                     <hi>I</hi> am ready gentle loue and glad in mind</l>
                  <l>That my faire <hi>Euphrata</hi> will proue ſo kind.</l>
               </sp>
               <pb facs="tcp:20581:18"/>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Euph.</speaker>
                  <l>Come my deare <hi>Conſtantine</hi> performe this right,</l>
                  <l>And arme in arme thus will we ſleepe to night.</l>
               </sp>
               <stage>Exeunt.</stage>
               <stage>Enter Fredericke, Rinaldo, and Alberto with Drum, Colours, and Souldiers.</stage>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Fred.</speaker>
                  <l>You that are carefull of your countries weale,</l>
                  <l>Fellow compere, Supporter of the State,</l>
                  <l>Let us imbrace in ſteele, our cauſe is good,</l>
                  <l>What mind ſo baſe that would not ſhed his blood</l>
                  <l>To free his countrey from ſo great an ill,</l>
                  <l>As now raignes in it by laſcivious will,</l>
                  <l>Our friends to warre, and for my part,</l>
                  <l>Ere luſt beare ſway Ile gladly yeeld my heart.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Alberto.</speaker>
                  <l>I heare the Duke is ſtrong.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Fred.</speaker>
                  <l>Suppoſe him ſo,</l>
                  <l>And be advis'd ſtrongly to meete the foe:</l>
                  <l>I had rather you ſhould think him ten thouſand ſtrong,</l>
                  <l>Then find it ſo to our deſtruction,</l>
                  <l>An enemy thought many and found few,</l>
                  <l>When our firſt courage failes giues us a new.</l>
               </sp>
               <stage>Alarum.</stage>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Albert.</speaker>
                  <l>That's the Dukes Drum.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Fred.</speaker>
                  <l>They are welcome to their death,</l>
                  <l>The ground they tread on covers them with earth.</l>
               </sp>
               <stage>Exeunt.</stage>
               <stage>Enter Fredericke and Duke ſeverall.</stage>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Fred.</speaker>
                  <l>The enemy ſends forth a Champion,</l>
                  <l>To encounter me, I heard him uſe my name,</l>
                  <l>The honour of the combate ſhall be mine.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Duke.</speaker>
                  <l>Come boy retreate not, only I intend,</l>
                  <l>With thy lifes loſſe this bloody warre to end.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Fred.</speaker>
                  <l>My naturall father in my blood I feele,</l>
                  <l>Paſſion more powerfull then that conquering ſteele.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Duke.</speaker>
                  <l>Why doſt thou pauſe baſe boy thy Soveraigne's come,</l>
                  <l>To inter the life <hi>I</hi> gaue thee, in this tombe.</l>
               </sp>
               <pb facs="tcp:20581:19"/>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Fred.</speaker>
                  <l>My father, oh my father: nature be ſtill,</l>
                  <l>That I may haue my fame, or he his will.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Duk.</speaker>
                  <l>What doſt thou feare thy cauſe, is't now ſo evill?</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Fred.</speaker>
                  <l>I am poſſeſt with a relenting devill;</l>
                  <l>Legions of kinde thoughts haue ſurpriz'd my ſenſe,</l>
                  <l>And I am too weake to be mine owne defence.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Duke.</speaker>
                  <l>Thou art a coward.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Fred.</speaker>
                  <l>And you make me ſo:</l>
                  <l>For you come charm'd like a diſhonour'd foe,</l>
                  <l>You haue conferr'd with ſpirits, and tane their aydes</l>
                  <l>To make me weake, by them I am betraid,</l>
                  <l>My ſtrength drawne from me by a ſlight,</l>
                  <l>What other meanes could hold me from the fight?</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Duke.</speaker>
                  <l>I haue no ſpells about me.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Fred.</speaker>
                  <l>Tis vntrue,</l>
                  <l>For naturall Magique you haue brought with you,</l>
                  <l>And ſuch an exorciſme in your name,</l>
                  <l>That I forbeare the combate to my ſhame:</l>
                  <l>But that I am no coward, from your hoſt</l>
                  <l>Elect two of the valiantſt that dare moſt,</l>
                  <l>Double that number, treble it, or more,</l>
                  <l>I haue heart at will t'encounter with a ſcore.</l>
                  <l>Or had your ſelfe come in a ſtrange attire,</l>
                  <l>One of us twaine had loſt his living fire.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Duke.</speaker>
                  <l>Ile trie your valour: ſee audacious boy,</l>
                  <l>Thou art incompaſt with a world of foes,</l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Montano, Alfred Vandermas</hi> and all,</l>
                  <l>My Dutcheſſe comes too to, behold thy fall.</l>
                  <l>If thou haſt ſpirit enough, now craue her ayd,</l>
                  <l>Never was poore ventrous ſouldier worſe apayd.</l>
               </sp>
               <stage>Exit Duke.</stage>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Fred.</speaker>
                  <l>My deſire now from the skie of ſtarres,</l>
                  <l>Dart all your Deitie, ſince I am beſet,</l>
                  <l>In honourable wiſe payes all Natures debt.</l>
               </sp>
               <stage>They fight, Fredericke beats them off, and courſes the Dutcheſſe over the ſtage.</stage>
            </div>
            <div type="act">
               <pb facs="tcp:20581:19"/>
               <head>Actus quartus.</head>
               <stage>Enter Duke, Montano, Valentia, Hatto and Alfred, Drumme, Colours and Souldiers.</stage>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Duke.</speaker>
                  <l>Our anger long agoe, renowned Lords,</l>
                  <l>Is ſatisfied in faire <hi>Valentias</hi> loue.</l>
                  <l>Behold our proud ſonne and theſe traiterous crew,</l>
                  <l>That dares confront us in the field of <hi>Mars.</hi>
                  </l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Valen.</speaker>
                  <l>You haue been too patient, my beloved Lord,</l>
                  <l>In calming theſe tumultuous jarring ſpirits:</l>
                  <l>Scourge them with ſteele, and make the proudeſt know,</l>
                  <l>Tis more then death to haue their Prince their foe.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Mon.</speaker>
                  <l>Bloody conſtraints beſeemes where dutie failes,</l>
                  <l>And Oratory ceaſing, force prevailes.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Hat.</speaker>
                  <l>Peace would doe better, ſo it pleas'd your ſonne.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Fred.</speaker>
                  <l>In her allurements firſt begun,</l>
                  <l>Baniſh her from the land, and Ile reſigne.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Duk.</speaker>
                  <l>Learne thine owne dutie traitor, I know mine.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Albert.</speaker>
                  <l>Then there's no baniſhment.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Duk.</speaker>
                  <l>None but by death.</l>
                  <l>Thy head is forfeit for that daring breath.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Alfred.</speaker>
                  <l>Submit degenerate and preſumptuous Lord.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Albert.</speaker>
                  <l>When we are ignorant to weild a ſword.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Fred.</speaker>
                  <l>Never ſhall noble knee bend to this ground,</l>
                  <l>As long as that vile ſtrumpet liveth crownd.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Duk.</speaker>
                  <l>I cannot ſtay to heare my loue deprau'd,</l>
                  <l>In few words is it peace, or ſhall we fight,</l>
                  <l>Till our deepe wounds ſhall dampe the heavenly light,</l>
                  <l>Make the ayre purple with the reaking gore.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Fre.</speaker>
                  <l>Fight whilſt life ſerues you, we will nere giue ore,</l>
                  <l>The graſſe greene pauement ſhall be drownd in blood,</l>
                  <l>And yet Ile wade to kill her in the flood.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Duke.</speaker>
                  <l>Alarum Drum, madneſſe is on their ſide,</l>
                  <l>All vertuous counſell is by them defied.</l>
                  <pb facs="tcp:20581:20"/>
                  <l>Vpon our part ſtrike Drums, Trumpets proclaime,</l>
                  <l>Death moſt aſſur'd to thoſe that haue their ſhame.</l>
               </sp>
               <stage>Alarum, fight luſtily and driue away the Duke, Fredericke purſues Valentia, over the ſtage, and takes her, a Retreate ſounded.</stage>
               <stage>Enter at one doore the Duke, Mon, Hatto, and Alfred with Drum and Colours. Enter at the other doore Fredericke leading Valentia priſoner, Rinaldo and Alberto with Drum and Colours.</stage>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Duke.</speaker>
                  <l>Why doe traitors ſound retreat ſo ſoone?</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Fred.</speaker>
                  <l>Behold the cauſe.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Duke.</speaker>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Valentia</hi> priſoner?</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Fred.</speaker>
                  <l>The firebrand of this tumultuous warre,</l>
                  <l>The originall from whence your ſubjects bloud</l>
                  <l>Flowes in abundance of this ſpatious play.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Valen.</speaker>
                  <l>And what of all this?</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Fred.</speaker>
                  <l>That thy lifes too meane</l>
                  <l>To ſatisfie the unworthieſt of the Campe,</l>
                  <l>For the effuſion of a loyall drop.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Duk.</speaker>
                  <l>Meanes <hi>Fredericke</hi> then to kill his fathers heart,</l>
                  <l>In faire <hi>Valentia's</hi> death?</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Fred.</speaker>
                  <l>Not touch your hand, other</l>
                  <l>Then humble as becomes a ſonne:</l>
                  <l>But ſhee ſhall ſuffer for enchanting you.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Valen.</speaker>
                  <l>I am a Dutcheſſe, ſet my ranſome downe.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Fred.</speaker>
                  <l>A dutcheſſe! whence proceeds that borowed name?</l>
                  <l>Of what continuance? ſcarcely hath the Sunne</l>
                  <l>Beheld thy pride a day, but doth decline,</l>
                  <l>Shaming to view a crowned Concubine.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Duke.</speaker>
                  <l>In mine owne honour <hi>Fredericke,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>I command thou ſet a ranſome on <hi>Valentia.</hi>
                  </l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Fred.</speaker>
                  <l>What honor's that? your Dukedomes intereſt?</l>
                  <l>Your princely birth? your honourable fame?</l>
                  <l>All theſe are blemiſht with a ſtrumpets name.</l>
               </sp>
               <pb facs="tcp:20581:20"/>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Mon.</speaker>
                  <l>Be not ſo cruell to bereaue her life,</l>
                  <l>'Twill draw upon thee a perpetuall ſcar:</l>
                  <l>Thy fathers curſe, and a continuall warre.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Duke.</speaker>
                  <l>Oh doe not threaten, <hi>Fredericke</hi> is ſo mild,</l>
                  <l>He will not proue ſuch a degenerate child:</l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>I</hi> cannot blame him tho' hee riſe in armes,</l>
                  <l>'Twas not in hate to me, but in disdaine,</l>
                  <l>That <hi>I</hi> ſhould ſell my royaltie ſo vaine,</l>
                  <l>But did he know the value of the iem,</l>
                  <l>Hee would not craſe it for a Dyadem:</l>
                  <l>That ſhee was common her owne words approue,</l>
                  <l>But many faults are cover'd where men loue,</l>
                  <l>As thou reſpects my bleſsing and good dayes,</l>
                  <l>Reſtore her <hi>Fredericke</hi> and augment her prayſe.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Fred.</speaker>
                  <l>Reſtore her?</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Albert.</speaker>
                  <l>Never.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Duke.</speaker>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Albert</hi> Thou wert kind and I ne're wrong'd thee,</l>
                  <l>Doe not change thy minde.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Hat.</speaker>
                  <l>You doe abaſe your honour to intreate.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Duke.</speaker>
                  <l>How can I chooſe my affection is ſo great.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Alfred.</speaker>
                  <l>Your power is ſtrong, the enemy is but weake.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Duke.</speaker>
                  <l>In her deſtruction all my powers will breake,</l>
                  <l>As thou doſt hope of kindneſſe in thy choyſe,</l>
                  <l>If ere thou loue, giue eare unto my voice,</l>
                  <l>Turne not aſide thy eye, the feares I feele,</l>
                  <l>Makes me to bow where tis thy part to kneele:</l>
                  <l>Loe vaſſailelike, laying aſide command,</l>
                  <l>I humbly craue this favour at thy hand,</l>
                  <l>Let me haue my beloved, and take my ſtate,</l>
                  <l>My life I undervalue to that rate:</l>
                  <l>Craue any thing that in my power doth lye,</l>
                  <l>Tis thine, ſo faire <hi>Valentia</hi> may not dye.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Fred.</speaker>
                  <l>My ſoule is griev'd, and it appals my blood,</l>
                  <l>To ſee my father puſſeld in ſuch mood:</l>
                  <l>Yet ſhall ſhee dye, Ile doe as I haue ſaid</l>
                  <l>With mine hand, Ile chop off the Stumpets head.</l>
               </sp>
               <pb facs="tcp:20581:21"/>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Alberto.</speaker>
                  <l>Kill her my Lord, or let me haue the honour.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Duke.</speaker>
                  <l>Tigers would ſaue her, if they lookt upon her,</l>
                  <l>Shee is ſo beautifull, ſo heavenly bright,</l>
                  <l>That ſhee would make them loue her for the ſight,</l>
                  <l>Thou art more rude then ſuch if thou proceede,</l>
                  <l>In the execution of ſo vilde a deede:</l>
                  <l>Remember one thing, I did never loue,</l>
                  <l>Till thou my <hi>Frederick</hi> broughtſt that fatall Gloue:</l>
                  <l>That and the Owners name thou didſt deſcry,</l>
                  <l>Onely for that cauſe let not my loue dye.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Fred.</speaker>
                  <l>O gods!</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Duke.</speaker>
                  <l>Cannot my kneeling ſerue, my teares prevaile.</l>
                  <l>When all helpes faile mee, yet this will not faile:</l>
                  <l>Proffer thy weapon to her beauteous ſide,</l>
                  <l>And with her heart, my heart I will divide:</l>
                  <l>Intreaty Ile urge none more then are paſt:</l>
                  <l>And either now relent or heres my laſt.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Fred.</speaker>
                  <l>Stay, if <hi>I</hi> ſhould relent; will you agree,</l>
                  <l>To ſigne our generall pardon preſently?</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Duke.</speaker>
                  <l>By heaven <hi>I</hi> doe, I freely pardon all,</l>
                  <l>And a reward <hi>I</hi> giue in generall.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Fred.</speaker>
                  <l>Then take her, you deſerue her were ſhee better,</l>
                  <l>Making your Crowne and life to be her Debter.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Duke.</speaker>
                  <l>Welcome a thouſand times, welcome ſweete wife:</l>
                  <l>Never more deare then now, <hi>I</hi> haue ſould thy life.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Valen.</speaker>
                  <l>This more then kindneſſe <hi>I</hi> turne backe to you,</l>
                  <l>Doubling my chaſt vow to bee ever true.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Fred.</speaker>
                  <l>Then here the warres end, are our fightings mande:</l>
                  <l>Yet by your leaue Ile ſtand upon my Guard.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Duke.</speaker>
                  <l>Take any courſe you pleaſe, Citie, or Towne,</l>
                  <l>My royall word Ile keepe by this my Crowne.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Fred.</speaker>
                  <l>Then thus Ile take my leaue.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Duke.</speaker>
                  <l>Since we muſt part,</l>
                  <l>Farewell my Sonne, all farewell with my heart.</l>
               </sp>
               <stage>Exount Fred. and his.</stage>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Mon.</speaker>
                  <l>Twas well my Lord, 'twas a good policie,</l>
                  <pb facs="tcp:20581:21"/>
                  <l>To gaine your bride, I hope your grace did not meane,</l>
                  <l>To be thus overrulde by a proud Sonne.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Duke.</speaker>
                  <l>Why thinke you he intends ſome treachery?</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Mon.</speaker>
                  <l>Why not, and did releaſe <hi>Valentia.</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>To blind your eyes; hee that could be ſo proud,</l>
                  <l>To riſe in armes againſt his naturall Father,</l>
                  <l>Hath courage to doe more when he ſees time.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Duke.</speaker>
                  <l>But <hi>I</hi> haue pardon'd that offence by oath.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Mon.</speaker>
                  <l>It were no periury to make him know,</l>
                  <l>Hee is your Sonne, and ſonnes a dutie owe:</l>
                  <l>This ſequeſtration will in time aſpire,</l>
                  <l>Vnto a flame ſhall ſet your Realme on fire:</l>
                  <l>Warre when a Subiect hath the meanes of will,</l>
                  <l>'Tis not enough to ſay he has no will.</l>
                  <l>For will is alter'd by the place and time,</l>
                  <l>And hee that's once up, knowes the way to clime:</l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>I</hi> ſpeake perchance like a prophetique foole,</l>
                  <l>But theſe are wiſe can counſaile, with your bride</l>
                  <l>Wiſedome adviſeth timely to provide.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Duke.</speaker>
                  <l>What thinkes my loue of <hi>Frederickes</hi> reconcilement?</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Valen.</speaker>
                  <l>That he has ſpirit enough to be a traytor:</l>
                  <l>But I am be holding to him for a life,</l>
                  <l>And he may brag he gaue your grace a wife:</l>
                  <l>A good old man, he could not chooſe but feele,</l>
                  <l>For ſhame ſome ſmall remorſe, to ſee you kneele,</l>
                  <l>Pray God he gaue me not into your hand.</l>
                  <l>That he might be the ruine of your land.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Duke.</speaker>
                  <l>Thinkes my loue ſo? but brothers what's your cenſure?</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Hat.</speaker>
                  <l>I am no Polititian.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Alfred.</speaker>
                  <l>Neither I.</l>
                  <l>Wee are both content to liue quietly.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Duke.</speaker>
                  <l>Hee may be a villaine tho' he be my Sonne.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Mon.</speaker>
                  <l>Why not, and worke your ruine like a foe;</l>
                  <l>Had he meant well, why did he leaue you ſo?</l>
                  <l>Your noble heart was free from all deceipt,</l>
                  <l>But hee's retirde to doe ſome dangerous feate,</l>
                  <pb facs="tcp:20581:22"/>
                  <l>When Subiects ſtand upon their guard looke to't,</l>
                  <l>They haue ſome plot in hand and they will do't.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Duke.</speaker>
                  <l>What courſe is readieſt to prevent ſuch miſchiefe?</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Mon.</speaker>
                  <l>Plucke up the fulſome thiſtle in the prime;</l>
                  <l>Young trees bend lightly but grow ſtrong in time:</l>
                  <l>Were I the worthieſt to adviſe your honour,</l>
                  <l>You ſhould purſue him with your ſpredding bands,</l>
                  <l>Swifter in march then is the lightning flame,</l>
                  <l>And take him tardy whilſt his plots are tame;</l>
                  <l>Now to charge on his army queſtionleſſe,</l>
                  <l>Would driue them all into a great diſtreſſe,</l>
                  <l>If not confound them, having tane your Sonne,</l>
                  <l>You may be as kind, and doe as hee hath done:</l>
                  <l>So ſhall he know himſelfe, and be leſſe proud.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Valen.</speaker>
                  <l>The counſailes good.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Duke.</speaker>
                  <l>And it ſhall be allowed.</l>
                  <l>You that doe loue me, ſee the hoſt prepar'd,</l>
                  <l>To ſcare thoſe traytors that our liues haue ſcarde:</l>
                  <l>Our armie's many, but their power is free;</l>
                  <l>Beſides they are traytors, all with us are true:</l>
                  <l>Sound Drums and trumpets, make the world rebound,</l>
                  <l>Hearten our friends, and all our foes confound.</l>
               </sp>
               <stage>Alarum.</stage>
               <stage>Exeunt.</stage>
               <stage>Enter Montano with two or three Souldiers. Vandarman leading Fredericke bound.</stage>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Fred.</speaker>
                  <l>Baſe cowards, traytors, how am I ſurprizde</l>
                  <l>With theſe bonds? I am a Prince by birth,</l>
                  <l>And princely ſpirits disdaine ſuch clogs of earth;</l>
                  <l>Let goe you ſlaues.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Mon.</speaker>
                  <l>Firſt know your fathers pleaſure.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Fred.</speaker>
                  <l>You are too bold.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Mon.</speaker>
                  <l>But you ſhall keepe a meaſure.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Fred.</speaker>
                  <l>Thou blood of common Concubines muſt I,</l>
                  <l>Be bound by thee, and heire of <hi>Saxony?</hi>
                  </l>
               </sp>
               <pb facs="tcp:20581:22"/>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Duke.</speaker>
                  <l>It is our pleaſure.</l>
               </sp>
               <stage>Enter Duke and Valen.</stage>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Valen.</speaker>
                  <l>Haue you caught him ſo?</l>
                  <l>Now ſhall you waite the mercy we will ſhew:</l>
                  <l>I was too baſe to be your fathers wife.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Duke.</speaker>
                  <l>But he ſhall ſue to thee to ſaue his life.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Fred.</speaker>
                  <l>Periurde, ungratefull, unnaturall,</l>
                  <l>Is this the Pardon given in generall.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Duke.</speaker>
                  <l>Wee'l talke of that hereafter, make him faſt.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Valen.</speaker>
                  <l>Helpe <hi>
                        <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>andermas,</hi> our ſelfe will ayding be,</l>
                  <l>To keepe in awe ſuch ſenſeleſſe trechery.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Duke.</speaker>
                  <l>My helpe and all to priſon there till death,</l>
                  <l>Remaine in dureſſe.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Fred.</speaker>
                  <l>Rather ſtop my breath,</l>
                  <l>Strangle me with theſe cords, priſon to me</l>
                  <l>Is twenty deaths, I will haue liberty:</l>
                  <l>Now as you are a father be more kind,</l>
                  <l>You did not find me in ſo ſterne a mind:</l>
                  <l>And you forgetfull of the life I ſav'd:</l>
                  <l>Shall a Dukes Sonne by treaſon thus be ſlau'd?</l>
                  <l>If you ſuſpect my loue, grant me the fight,</l>
                  <l>I dare in ſingle combate any knight,</l>
                  <l>Any adventurer, any pandorus hinde,</l>
                  <l>To proue my faith of an unfained mind.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Duke.</speaker>
                  <l>Away with him.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Fred.</speaker>
                  <l>I ſee my death's ſet downe,</l>
                  <l>And ſome adulterous heire muſt weare that Crowne:</l>
                  <l>To intreate a Rodophe, I had rather dye,</l>
                  <l>Then haue my life lodg'd in ſuch infamy:</l>
                  <l>If all my fortunes on her words depend,</l>
                  <l>Let her ſay kill me, and ſo make an end.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Duke.</speaker>
                  <l>Why ſtay you?</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Vander.</speaker>
                  <l>Good my Lord.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Fred.</speaker>
                  <l>Peace untaught Groome:</l>
                  <l>My heart's ſo great that Ide forerun my doome:</l>
                  <l>There's no releaſe meant, you haue vowed I ſee,</l>
                  <l>To dam your ſoules by wilfull periury.</l>
                  <pb facs="tcp:20581:23"/>
                  <l>Yet that I am my ſelfe let theſe words ſhew,</l>
                  <l>To die is naturall, 'tis a death I owe,</l>
                  <l>And I will pay it with a minde as free,</l>
                  <l>As I enioyed in my beſt libertie.</l>
                  <l>But this aſſure your ſelfe, when all is done,</l>
                  <l>They'l kill the father, that will kill the ſonne.</l>
               </sp>
               <stage>Exit.</stage>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Duke.</speaker>
                  <l>What's to be done now?</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Mon.</speaker>
                  <l>Seale unto his death;</l>
                  <l>Your warrant nere the ſooner takes effect:</l>
                  <l>'Twill be a meanes to make him penitent,</l>
                  <l>And pardon's meet for ſuch as doe repent.</l>
                  <l>Seeing his fault, hee'l taſte your mercie beſt,</l>
                  <l>When now he proudly thinkes he is oppreſt.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Duke.</speaker>
                  <l>A Warrant ſhall be ſign'd, and unto thee</l>
                  <l>I doe commend it: deale not partially,</l>
                  <l>If he be ſorry, and in true remorſe</l>
                  <l>Cancell the Writ, elſe let it haue full force.</l>
                  <l>Had I ten ſonnes, as I haue onely this,</l>
                  <l>They ſhould all die ere thou depriv'd of bliſſe:</l>
                  <l>So great is my affection, my faire wife,</l>
                  <l>That to ſaue thine Ide frankly giue my life.</l>
                  <l>Come, weele about it ſtrait, all time ſeemes long,</l>
                  <l>Where thou haſt found flight cauſe to feare my wrong.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Valen.</speaker>
                  <l>That writ Ile take, and a concluſion trie,</l>
                  <l>If he can loue he liues, if hate me, die.</l>
                  <l>For howſoere I ſeeme to ſcorne the man,</l>
                  <l>Hee's ſomewhat deare in my affection.</l>
                  <l>Here comes your brothers.</l>
               </sp>
               <stage>Enter Alfred and Hatto.</stage>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Alfred.</speaker>
                  <l>May it pleaſe your grace,</l>
                  <l>By chance entring into Saint <hi>Maries</hi> Church</l>
                  <l>This morne by breake of day, I eſpied</l>
                  <l>That that I know will vexe your Excellence:</l>
                  <l>Your daughter <hi>Euphrata</hi> is married</l>
                  <l>To the ambitious beggar <hi>Conſtantine.</hi>
                  </l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Duk.</speaker>
                  <l>My daughter married my Chamber-ſquire!</l>
               </sp>
               <pb facs="tcp:20581:23"/>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Mon.</speaker>
                  <l>Your Excellence did baniſh me the land,</l>
                  <l>Becauſe I did ſuſpect her with that fellow.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Duke.</speaker>
                  <l>He ſhall be tortur'd with th'extreameſt plague</l>
                  <l>For his preſumption — Haue you brought them,</l>
                  <l>That I may kill them with a killing looke.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Hat.</speaker>
                  <l>Without direction we haue ventured to lay upon them</l>
                  <l>Your ſtrict command, and they attend.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Duke.</speaker>
                  <l>Bring the preſumptuous.</l>
               </sp>
               <stage>Enter Constantine and Euphrata, Otho following in diſguiſe.</stage>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Euphr.</speaker>
                  <l>Forward <hi>Conſtantine,</hi> our Rites are done,</l>
                  <l>Thou art my husband: doe not feare his eye,</l>
                  <l>The worſt it can import is but to die.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Duke.</speaker>
                  <l>Baſe and degenerate.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Euphr.</speaker>
                  <l>He is a Gentleman,</l>
                  <l>'Twas baſe in you to wed a Curtizan.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Mon.</speaker>
                  <l>Her brothers ſpirit right, bold and audacious.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Euph.</speaker>
                  <l>Then I am no baſtard, wherefore ſhould I feare,</l>
                  <l>The knot is ſacred, and I hold it deare.</l>
                  <l>I am wedded unto vertue, not to will,</l>
                  <l>Such bleſſed unions never bring forth ill.</l>
                  <l>If I offend in diſobedience,</l>
                  <l>Iudge of the power of loue by your offence.</l>
                  <l>Father, you haue no reaſon for this ire,</l>
                  <l>Frowne whilſt you kill us, deſire is deſire.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Duke.</speaker>
                  <l>A Curtezan? hath that ambitious boy</l>
                  <l>Taught you ſuch Rethoricke? you ſhall taſte like joy.</l>
                  <l>I will not reaſon with you, words are vaine,</l>
                  <l>The fault is beſt diſcerned in the paine.</l>
                  <l>Your haſtie marriage hath writ downe his death,</l>
                  <l>And thy proud words ſhall ſeale it with thy breath.</l>
                  <l>By what is deareſt to mee, here I ſweare,</l>
                  <l>Both of your heads ſhall grace a fatall beere:</l>
                  <l>Take them to priſon, Ile not heare a word,</l>
                  <l>This is the mercie that we will afford,</l>
                  <l>Since they are growne ſo proud, next morne begun,</l>
                  <pb facs="tcp:20581:24"/>
                  <l>Let them be both beheaded with my ſonne.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Con.</speaker>
                  <l>Short and ſweet, <hi>Euphrata,</hi> the doome is faire,</l>
                  <l>We ſhall be ſoone in heaven, there ends my care.</l>
                  <l>I ſcorne entreatie, and my deare I know,</l>
                  <l>All ſuch ſlavery thou hateſt ſo.</l>
                  <l>'Twill be a famous deed for this good man</l>
                  <l>To kill all's children for a Curtezan.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Euph.</speaker>
                  <l>Wilt thou die with me?</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Conſt.</speaker>
                  <l>Would I liue in heaven?</l>
                  <l>Thou art now too high for me, death makes us even.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Eup.</speaker>
                  <l>Looke to your dukedome, thoſe that haſt our fall,</l>
                  <l>Haue by their avarice almoſt hurried all.</l>
                  <l>There's a whole Regiſter of the poores crie,</l>
                  <l>Whilſt they are reading them, imbrace and die.</l>
               </sp>
               <stage>Flings downe her lap full of Petitions. Exeunt Euph. and Conſtant.</stage>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Duke.</speaker>
                  <l>Beare them away.</l>
                  <l>And now let's reade theſe Writes.</l>
                  <l>What's here? complaints againſt my worthy brothers,</l>
                  <l>For corne tranſported, Copper money ſtampt,</l>
                  <l>Our ſubjects goods ceaz'd, and I know not what.</l>
                  <l>A plague upon this buſie-headed rabble,</l>
                  <l>We will haue tortures made to awe the ſlaues,</l>
                  <l>Peace makes them ever proud, and malapert.</l>
                  <l>They'l be an Overſeer of the State.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Valen.</speaker>
                  <l>And plead reformation to depoſe you.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Duk.</speaker>
                  <l>True my faire Dutcheſſe, but Ile cut them ſhort.</l>
                  <l>Rule ſtill deare brothers: take theſe to the fire,</l>
                  <l>Let me reade ſomewhat that augments deſire,</l>
                  <l>Authors and golden Poems full of loue,</l>
                  <l>Such the Petitions are that I approue:</l>
                  <l>So I may liue in quiet with my wife,</l>
                  <l>Let fathers, mothers, children, all loſe life.</l>
                  <l>If thou haue iſſue, in deſpight of fate,</l>
                  <l>They ſhall ſucceed in our Imperiall ſtate.</l>
                  <l>Come ſweet to dauncing, then to ſport and play,</l>
                  <l>Till we haue ruled all our life away.</l>
               </sp>
               <stage>Exeunt.</stage>
               <stage>Manet Otho.</stage>
               <pb facs="tcp:20581:24"/>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Otho.</speaker>
                  <l>O pittifull condition of a Realme,</l>
                  <l>Where the chiefe ruler is ore-rul'd by pleaſure,</l>
                  <l>Seeing my friend ſurpriz'd in this diſguiſe,</l>
                  <l>I followed him to meete the conſequence:</l>
                  <l>And to my griefe I ſee his marriage rites</l>
                  <l>Will cut him ſhort of all this earths delights.</l>
                  <l>What's that to mee, when <hi>Conſtantine</hi> is dead,</l>
                  <l>I have ſome hope to attaine her Nuptiall bed.</l>
                  <l>But ſhee is doom'd as well as hee to die,</l>
                  <l>Can the Duke act his daughters Tragedie.</l>
                  <l>It is impoſſible, he will relent,</l>
                  <l>And Ile perſwade her freely to repent.</l>
                  <l>Yet 'tis moſt likelie that he will agree</l>
                  <l>He is ſo farre ſpent in vild tyrannie.</l>
                  <l>The commons hate him for the wrong he hath done,</l>
                  <l>(By his brothers meanes) the Nobles for his ſonne.</l>
                  <l>Famine ſpreads through the land, the people die,</l>
                  <l>Yet he lives ſenſeleſſe of their miſerie.</l>
                  <l>Never were ſubiects more miſlead by any,</l>
                  <l>Nor ever Soveraigne hated by ſo many.</l>
                  <l>But <hi>Conſtantine,</hi> to thee I caſt an eye,</l>
                  <l>Shall all our friendſhip end in enmitie?</l>
                  <l>Shall I that ever held thee as my life,</l>
                  <l>Haſten thy death, that I may get thy wife,</l>
                  <l>Or love or friendſhip, whether ſhall exceed,</l>
                  <l>Ile explaine your vertue in this following deed.</l>
               </sp>
               <stage>Exit.</stage>
               <stage>Enter <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>alentia, Montano and <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>andermas.</stage>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Va.</speaker>
                  <l>Have you the inſtruments I gave in charge?</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>and,</speaker>
                  <l>Wee have.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Val.</speaker>
                  <l>And reſolution fitting for the purpoſe?</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Mon.</speaker>
                  <l>All things are ready with our faithfull hearts.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Val.</speaker>
                  <l>And ſhe that undertakes ſo great an act,</l>
                  <l>As I intend, had need of faithfull hearts,</l>
                  <l>This is the priſon, and the jaylor comes</l>
                  <pb facs="tcp:20581:25"/>
                  <l>In happy time, where's trayterous <hi>Frederick?</hi>
                  </l>
               </sp>
               <stage>Enter Iaylor.</stage>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Jaylor.</speaker>
                  <l>What is your highneſſe pleaſure with the Prince?</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Val.</speaker>
                  <l>Looke there if you can reade?</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Iai</speaker>
                  <l>O heavenly God, what doe I read, a warrant for his death?</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Valen.</speaker>
                  <l>Reſigne your keyes, goe weepe a di<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ge or twaine,</l>
                  <l>But make no clamour with your lamentation.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Iay.</speaker>
                  <l>I dare not propheſie what my ſouſe feares.</l>
                  <l>Yet Ile lament his tragedie in teares.</l>
               </sp>
               <stage>Exit.</stage>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>alen.</speaker>
                  <l>Oft have I ſeene a Nobleman arraign'd,</l>
                  <l>By mighty Lords the pillars of the land,</l>
                  <l>Some of which number his inclined friends,</l>
                  <l>Have wept, yet paſt the verdict of his death,</l>
                  <l>So fares it with the Prince, were I his jaylor,</l>
                  <l>And ſo affected unto <hi>Fredericks</hi> life,</l>
                  <l>The fearefull'ſt tyrant, nor the cruelſt plagues,</l>
                  <l>That ever lighted on tormented ſoules,</l>
                  <l>Should make me yeeld my priſoner to their hands.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Mon.</speaker>
                  <l>Madam, he knowes his dutie and performes it,</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>alen.</speaker>
                  <l>Setting aſide all dutie, I would die,</l>
                  <l>Ere like a woman weepe a tragedie.</l>
                  <l>Tis baſeneſſe, cowardize, dutie? ô ſlave,</l>
                  <l>Had I a friend, <hi>I</hi>'de dye in my friends grave.</l>
                  <l>But it ſorts well for us, Hindes will be Hindes,</l>
                  <l>And the Ambitious tread upon ſuch mindes,</l>
                  <l>Waite whileſt <hi>I</hi> call you in the jaylors houſe.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Mon.</speaker>
                  <l>We will.</l>
               </sp>
               <stage>Exeunt <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>an. and Mon.</stage>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Valen.</speaker>
                  <l>My Lord, Prince <hi>Fredericke.</hi>
                  </l>
               </sp>
               <stage>Enter Fred.</stage>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Fred.</speaker>
                  <l>Wofull <hi>Fredericke,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>Were a beſeeming Epitaph for me,</l>
                  <l>The other taſtes of too much ſoveraigntie.</l>
                  <l>What, is it you? the glory of the ſtewes.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Valen.</speaker>
                  <l>Thy mother <hi>Fredericke.</hi>
                  </l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Fred.</speaker>
                  <l>I deteſt that name,</l>
                  <l>My mother was a Dutches of true fame,</l>
                  <l>And now I think upon her when ſhe died,</l>
                  <l>I was ordain'd to be indignified,</l>
                  <pb facs="tcp:20581:25"/>
                  <l>She never did incenſe my Princely Father</l>
                  <l>To the deſtruction of his loving ſonne,</l>
                  <l>Oh ſhe was vertuous, trulie naturall,</l>
                  <l>But this ſtep-divell doth promiſe our fall.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Val.</speaker>
                  <l>Why doeſt thou raile on me? I am come</l>
                  <l>To ſet thee free from all impriſonment.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Fred.</speaker>
                  <l>By what true ſuperſedeas, but by death,</l>
                  <l>If it be ſo, come ſtrike me to the earth,</l>
                  <l>Thou needeſt no other weapon but thine eye,</l>
                  <l>Tis full of poyſon, fixe it and Ile die.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Val.</speaker>
                  <l>Vncharitable youth, I am no ſerpent venom'd,</l>
                  <l>No baſiliske to kill thee with my ſight,</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Fre.</speaker>
                  <l>Then thou ſpeakſt death, I am ſorry I miſtooke,</l>
                  <l>They both are fatall, there's but little choice,</l>
                  <l>The firſt inthral'd my father, the laſt me,</l>
                  <l>No deadlier ſwords ever vs'd enemie,</l>
                  <l>My lot's the beſt, that I dye with the ſound,</l>
                  <l>But he lives dying in a death profound.</l>
                  <l>I grow too bitter being ſo neere my end,</l>
                  <l>Speake quickly, boldly, what your thoughts intend.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>alen.</speaker>
                  <l>Behold this warrant, you can reade it well.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Fred.</speaker>
                  <l>But you the interpretation beſt can tell:</l>
                  <l>Speake beauteous ruine, twere great iniurie,</l>
                  <l>That he ſhould read the ſentence that muſt dye.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Val.</speaker>
                  <l>Then know in briefe, 'tis your fathers pleaſure—</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Fred.</speaker>
                  <l>His pleaſure, what?</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Val.</speaker>
                  <l>That you muſt looſe your life.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Fred.</speaker>
                  <l>Fatall is his pleaſure, 'tis to pleaſe his wife,</l>
                  <l>I prethee tell me, didſt thou ever know,</l>
                  <l>A Father pleas'd, his ſonne to murder ſo?</l>
                  <l>For what is't elſe, but murder at the beſt,</l>
                  <l>The guilt whereof will gnawe him in his breſt,</l>
                  <l>Torment him living, and when I am dead,</l>
                  <l>Curſe thee, by whoſe plot I was murdered?</l>
                  <l>I have ſeene the like example, but ô baſe,</l>
                  <l>Why doe I talke with one of thy diſgrace:</l>
                  <l>Where are the officers? I have liv'd too long,</l>
                  <pb facs="tcp:20581:26"/>
                  <l>When he that gave me life, does me this wrong.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Val.</speaker>
                  <l>That is thy fathers hand, thou doſt not doubt?</l>
                  <l>And if thou ſhouldſt I have witneſſe to approve it,</l>
                  <l>Yet tho it be his hand, grant to my requeſt,</l>
                  <l>Love me, and live.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Fred.</speaker>
                  <l>To live ſo I deteſt, love thee?</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Valen.</speaker>
                  <l>I, love me, gentle <hi>Fredericke,</hi> love me.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Fred.</speaker>
                  <l>Inceſtuous ſtrumpet ceaſe.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>al.</speaker>
                  <l>Oh thou dealeſt ill.</l>
                  <l>To render ſo much ſpleene for my good will.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Fred.</speaker>
                  <l>Torment farre worſe then death.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>alen.</speaker>
                  <l>Ile follow thee,</l>
                  <l>Deare <hi>Fredericke</hi> like thy face be thy words faire.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Fre.</speaker>
                  <l>This monſtrous dealing doubles my deaths care</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Valen.</speaker>
                  <l>What ſhall I call thee to allay this ire?</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Fred.</speaker>
                  <l>Why call me ſon, and bluſh at thy deſire.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Valen.</speaker>
                  <l>I never brought thee foorth.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Fred.</speaker>
                  <l>Art thou not wife unto my father?</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Val.</speaker>
                  <l>Thinke upon thy life,</l>
                  <l>It lyes like mine, onely in gentle breath,</l>
                  <l>Or that thy father's dead, and after death,</l>
                  <l>'Tis in my choice to marry whom I will.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Fred.</speaker>
                  <l>Any but me.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>alen.</speaker>
                  <l>O doe not thinke ſo ill,</l>
                  <l>Rather thinke thou art a ſtranger not his ſonne,</l>
                  <l>Then 'tis no inceſt tho the Act be done,</l>
                  <l>Nature unto her ſelfe is too unkind,</l>
                  <l>To buzze ſuch ſcruples into <hi>Fredericks</hi> minde,</l>
                  <l>Twas a device of man to avoid ſelfe love,</l>
                  <l>Elſe every pleaſure in one ſtocke ſhould move,</l>
                  <l>Beautie in grace part never from the kinne.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Fred.</speaker>
                  <l>If thou perſever as thou haſt begun,</l>
                  <l>I ſhall forget I am my fathers ſonne,</l>
                  <l>I ſhall forget thou art my fathers wife,</l>
                  <l>And where 'tis I muſt die, abridge thy life.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Valen.</speaker>
                  <l>Why did'ſt not kill me being thy priſoner then,</l>
                  <l>But friendly didſt deliver me a jemme?</l>
                  <pb facs="tcp:20581:26"/>
                  <l>Vnto thy father, wert not thou didſt love me.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Fred.</speaker>
                  <l>Be yond all ſufferance, monſter thou doſt move me,</l>
                  <l>'Twas for my fathers ſake, not for thine owne,</l>
                  <l>That to thy lifes loſſe, thou hadſt throughly knowne,</l>
                  <l>But that relenting nature playde her part,</l>
                  <l>To ſave thy blood, whoſe loſſe had ſlaine his heart,</l>
                  <l>And it repents me not hee doth ſurvine.</l>
                  <l>But that his fortune was ſo ill to wive,</l>
                  <l>Come kill, for, for that you came; ſhun delayes,</l>
                  <l>Leſt living, Ile tell this to thy diſpraiſe,</l>
                  <l>Make him to hate thee, as he hath iuſt cauſe,</l>
                  <l>And like a ſtrumpet turne thee to the lawes.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Valen.</speaker>
                  <l>Good <hi>Fredericke.</hi>
                  </l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Fred.</speaker>
                  <l>Tis reſolu'd on, <hi>I</hi> have ſaid.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Valen.</speaker>
                  <l>Then fatall Miniſters I crave your ayde.</l>
                  <stage>Enter <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>an. and Mont.</stage>
                  <l>Come <hi>Vandermas, Montano,</hi> wheres your corde?</l>
                  <l>Quicklie diſpatch, ſtrangle this hatefull Lord,</l>
                  <l>Or ſtay, becauſe <hi>I</hi> loue him, he ſhall chuſe,</l>
                  <l>The eaſieſt of three deaths that we may vſe,</l>
                  <l>The halter, poyſon or bloodſhedding blade.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Fred.</speaker>
                  <l>Any of them.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>alen.</speaker>
                  <l>This Aconite's well made, a cup of poyſon,</l>
                  <l>Stuft with diſpatching ſimples, give him this,</l>
                  <l>And he ſhall quickly leave all earthly bliſſe.</l>
                  <l>There, take it <hi>Fredericke,</hi> our laſt gift of grace,</l>
                  <l>Since thou muſt die, Ile have thee die apace.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Fred.</speaker>
                  <l>O happie meanes given by a trecherous hand</l>
                  <l>To be my true guide to the heavenly land.</l>
                  <l>Death ſteales upon me like a ſilken ſleepe,</l>
                  <l>Through every vaine doe leaden rivers flowe,</l>
                  <l>The gentleſt poyſon that <hi>I</hi> ever knewe,</l>
                  <l>To worke ſo coldly, yet to be ſo true,</l>
                  <l>Like to an infant patiently I goe,</l>
                  <l>Out of this vaine world, from all worldly woe,</l>
                  <l>Thankes to the meanes, tho they deſerve no thankes,</l>
                  <l>My ſoule beginnes t'ore-flow theſe fleſhly bankes,</l>
                  <l>My death I pardon unto her and you,</l>
                  <pb facs="tcp:20581:27"/>
                  <l>My ſinnes God pardon, ſo vaine world adiew.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Valen,</speaker>
                  <l>Ha, ha, ha.</l>
               </sp>
               <stage>he falls aſleepe.</stage>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Mon.</speaker>
                  <l>Hee's dead, why does your highneſſe laugh?</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Valen.</speaker>
                  <l>Why Lord <hi>Montane,</hi> that I love to ſee,</l>
                  <l>He that hath ſav'd my life, to die for me.</l>
                  <l>But there's a riddle in this Princes death,</l>
                  <l>And Ile explaine it on this floore of earth.</l>
                  <l>Come, to his ſiſters execution goe,</l>
                  <l>We have varietie of ioyes in woe,</l>
                  <l>I am ſure you have heard his Excellence did ſweare,</l>
                  <l>Both of their heads ſhould grace a Kingly beare,</l>
                  <l>Vpon a mourning hearſe let him be layd,</l>
                  <l>He ſhalbe intombed with a wived maid.</l>
               </sp>
               <stage>Exeunt.</stage>
            </div>
            <div type="act">
               <head>Actus Quintus.</head>
               <stage>Enter Duke, Hatto, and Alfred.</stage>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Duke.</speaker>
                  <l>Bring forth the priſoners, wher's my beauteous Dutches,</l>
                  <l>That ſhe may ſee the ruine of her foes,</l>
                  <l>She that upbraided her with ſlanderous wordes,</l>
                  <l>She that in ſcorne of due obedience,</l>
                  <l>Hath matcht the honour of the <hi>Saxons</hi> blood,</l>
                  <l>Vnto a beggar, let them be brought foorth,</l>
                  <l>I will not riſe from this cribunall ſeate,</l>
                  <l>Till I have ſeene their bodies from their heads.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Alfred.</speaker>
                  <l>Here comes the Dutches with proud <hi>Fredericks</hi> hearſe</l>
               </sp>
               <stage>Enter Valentia, Montano, Vandermas with others, bearing the hearſe with Fredericke on, couered with a blacke robe.</stage>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Duke.</speaker>
                  <l>So ſet it downe, why have you honored it</l>
                  <l>With ſuch a ſable coverture? a traytor</l>
                  <l>Deſerves no cloth of ſorrow, ſet it downe,</l>
                  <l>And let our other off-ſpring be brought foorth,</l>
                  <l>My beauteous lovely and admired love,</l>
                  <l>Come ſit by us in an imperiall chayre.</l>
                  <pb facs="tcp:20581:27"/>
                  <l>And grace this ſtate throne with a ſtate more fayre.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Valen.</speaker>
                  <l>My gracious Lord, <hi>I</hi> hope your excellence</l>
                  <l>Will not be ſo forgetfull of your honour,</l>
                  <l>Prove ſo unnaturall to your loving daughter,</l>
                  <l>As to bereave her of her life,</l>
                  <l>Becauſe ſhe hath wedded baſely gainſt your will,</l>
                  <l>Though <hi>Fredericke</hi> dyed deſervedly, yet ſhe</l>
                  <l>May by her loves death cleare her indignitie.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Duke.</speaker>
                  <l>She and her love we have ſentenced to die,</l>
                  <l>Not for her marriage onely, tho that deede</l>
                  <l>Crownes the contempt with a deſerved death,</l>
                  <l>But chiefly for ſhe raild againſt thy worth,</l>
                  <l>Vpbraided thee with tearmes ſo monſtrous baſe,</l>
                  <l>That nought but death can cleare the great diſgrace,</l>
                  <l>How often ſhall <hi>I</hi> charge they be brought foorth?</l>
                  <l>Were my heart guiltie of a crime ſo vilde,</l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>I</hi>'de rend it forth, then much more kill my childe.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>al.</speaker>
                  <l>O that this love may laſt, 'tis ſprung ſo hie,</l>
                  <l>Like flowers at full growth, that grow to die.</l>
               </sp>
               <stage>Enter Iulia with a vaile over her head, Otho with another, with Officers.</stage>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Duk.</speaker>
                  <l>What means theſe ſable vailes upon their faces,</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Val.</speaker>
                  <l>In ſigne they ſorrow for your high diſpleaſure,</l>
                  <l>For ſince the houre they were impriſoned,</l>
                  <l>They have liv'd like ſtrangers, hood-winkt, together,</l>
                  <l>You may atchieve great fame victorious Lord,</l>
                  <l>To ſave the liues of two ſuch innocents.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Duke.</speaker>
                  <l>Tis pretty in thee my ſoule lov'd Dutcheſſe,</l>
                  <l>To make this Princely motion for thy foes,</l>
                  <l>Let it ſuffice, the'are traitors to the ſtate,</l>
                  <l>Confederators with thoſe that ſought my life,</l>
                  <l>A kinne to <hi>Fredericke</hi> that preſumptuous boy,</l>
                  <l>That durſt beare armes againſt his naturall father.</l>
                  <l>Are they more deare then he? off with their vailes.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Mon.</speaker>
                  <l>O yet be mercifull unto your daughter.</l>
               </sp>
               <pb facs="tcp:20581:28"/>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Duke.</speaker>
                  <l>You make me mad, headſman diſpatch I ſay.</l>
                  <l>They are doom'd to die, and this the lateſt day.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Otho.</speaker>
                  <l>Then let him ſtrike, who ever traitors be,</l>
                  <stage>Otho pult of his vaile.</stage>
                  <l>I am ſure no treaſon lives in her or me.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Duke.</speaker>
                  <l>How now, whats here? <hi>Otho</hi> and <hi>Iulia.</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>Am I deluded, where is <hi>Euphrata,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>And that audacious traitor <hi>Conſtantine?</hi>
                  </l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Otho.</speaker>
                  <l>Why fled.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Duke.</speaker>
                  <l>To whom?</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Otho.</speaker>
                  <l>To ſafetie, here was none,</l>
                  <l>I can reſolve you of the circumſtance.</l>
                  <l>Betwixt the noble <hi>Conſtantine</hi> and I,</l>
                  <l>Noble I call him, for his vertuous minde,</l>
                  <l>There was a league of love ſo ſtrongly made</l>
                  <l>That time wants houres, and occaſion cauſe,</l>
                  <l>To violate the contract of our hearts,</l>
                  <l>Yet on my part the breach did firſt appeare,</l>
                  <l>He brought me to behold his beauteous love,</l>
                  <l>The faire <hi>Euphrata,</hi> her Angel ſight,</l>
                  <l>Begate in me the fire of private love,</l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>I</hi> that before did like her for my friend,</l>
                  <l>Now to deceive him, ſought her for my ſelfe,</l>
                  <l>But my deuice was knowne unto my friend,</l>
                  <l>And worthilie he baniſht me his ſight.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Duke.</speaker>
                  <l>Whats this to their deſtruction, ſeeke them forth.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Otho.</speaker>
                  <l>They are far enough for ſuffering ſuch a death,</l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>I</hi> well conſidering my unfriendly part,</l>
                  <l>Bethought me how to reconcile my ſelfe,</l>
                  <l>Vnto my hearts endeared <hi>Conſtantine,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>And ſeeing him carried to the priſon, we</l>
                  <l>Followed, and found meanes for their libertie.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Duk.</speaker>
                  <l>Are they eſcapt then?</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Otho.</speaker>
                  <l>Both in our diſguiſe,</l>
                  <l>And we ſtand here to act their tragedies,</l>
                  <l>It they have done amiſſe, on us</l>
                  <l>Impoſe the Law.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Iulia.</speaker>
                  <l>O let our ſuites prevaile,</l>
                  <pb facs="tcp:20581:28"/>
                  <l>I aske to dye for my deare Ladies ſake.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Otho.</speaker>
                  <l>I for my friend.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Duke.</speaker>
                  <l>This friendly part doth make</l>
                  <l>My heart to bleede within me, and my mind</l>
                  <l>Much perplext, that I haue beene ſo unkind,</l>
                  <l>What ſecond funerall march is that I heare?</l>
               </sp>
               <stage>Enter Rainaldo, and Alberto like ſchollers, grieving before the Beare, others following them with the bodies of Euphrata, and Conſtantine covered with blacke.</stage>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Alberto.</speaker>
                  <l>Health to this preſence, though the newes,</l>
                  <l>Impairing health <hi>I</hi> bring unto this preſence,</l>
                  <l>The bodies of the drowned <hi>Conſtantine,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>And the faire <hi>Euphrata,</hi> behold them both.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Duke.</speaker>
                  <l>Of drowned <hi>Conſtantine</hi> and <hi>Euphrata,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>Declare the manner, and with killing words;</l>
                  <l>Temper thy words, that it may wound my life.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Albert.</speaker>
                  <l>Paſsing the Rhine bordering upon the tower,</l>
                  <l>From whence it ſeemes they lately had eſcapt,</l>
                  <l>By an unskilfull Guide their gundelet</l>
                  <l>Encountred with an other, and the ſhocke</l>
                  <l>Drown'd both the veſſayles, and their hapleſſeliues:</l>
                  <l>Their bodies hardly were recover'd,</l>
                  <l>But knowne we brought them to your excellence,</l>
                  <l>As to a father that ſhould mourne for them.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Duke.</speaker>
                  <l>Vnto a tyrant, doe not call me father,</l>
                  <l>For <hi>I</hi> haue beene no father to their liues:</l>
                  <l>The barbarous Canniball that never knew</l>
                  <l>The naturall touch of humane beauty</l>
                  <l>Would haue beene farre more mercifull then <hi>I:</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>Oh tyrannie the overthrow of Crownes,</l>
                  <l>Kingdomes, ſubverſion, and the deaths of Kings.</l>
                  <l>Loe here a piteous object ſo compleate,</l>
                  <l>With thy inteſtine and deſtroying fruite,</l>
                  <l>That it will ſtrike thee dead, oh <hi>Euphrata.</hi>
                  </l>
                  <pb facs="tcp:20581:29"/>
                  <l>Oh princely <hi>Fredericke,</hi> never deare to me</l>
                  <l>Till now, in you I ſee my miſery</l>
                  <l>My ſonne, my daughter, vertuous <hi>Conſtantine.</hi>
                  </l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Hat.</speaker>
                  <l>What meanes this griefe my Lord, theſe are the traytors,</l>
                  <l>That you in iuſtice ſentenced to dye.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Alfred.</speaker>
                  <l>A trecherous ſonne, and a rebellious daughter.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Valen.</speaker>
                  <l>Thoſe that did ſeeke to take away your life.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Mon.</speaker>
                  <l>Bereaue you of your Crownes prerogatiue.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Duke.</speaker>
                  <l>Hence from my ſight, blood thirſty Counſellors.</l>
                  <l>They never ſought my life, but you haue ſought it,</l>
                  <l>Vertuous <hi>Alberto,</hi> and <hi>Rinaldo:</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>Had I given eare to them and to my ſonne,</l>
                  <l>My ioyes had flouriſhed that now are done.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Valen.</speaker>
                  <l>Yet for my ſake, allay this diſcontent.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Duke.</speaker>
                  <l>Tis for thy ſake, thou vilde notorious woman,</l>
                  <l>That I haue paſt the limits of a man,</l>
                  <l>The bonds of nature.</l>
                  <l>'Twas thy bewitching eye, thy Syrens voice,</l>
                  <l>That throwes me upon millions of diſgrace,</l>
                  <l>Ile haue thee tortur'd on the Racke;</l>
                  <l>Plucke out thoſe baſiliske enchaunting eyes,</l>
                  <l>Teare thee to death, with Pincers burning hot,</l>
                  <l>Except thou giue me the departed liues</l>
                  <l>Of my deare children.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Valen.</speaker>
                  <l>What am I a Goddeſſe,</l>
                  <l>That I ſhould fetch their flying ſoules from heaven,</l>
                  <l>And breath them once more in their clay cold bodies?</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Duke.</speaker>
                  <l>Thou art a witch, a damn'd forcereſſe;</l>
                  <l>No goddeſſe but the goddeſſe of blacke hell,</l>
                  <l>And all thoſe devils thy followers:</l>
                  <l>What makes thou on the earth to murder men?</l>
                  <l>Will not my ſonnes and daughters timeleſſe liues,</l>
                  <l>Taken away in prime of their freſh youth</l>
                  <l>Serue to ſuffice thee?</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Valen.</speaker>
                  <l>O you are mad my Lord:</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Duke.</speaker>
                  <l>How can I chooſe,</l>
                  <l>And ſuch a foule <hi>Erynnis</hi> gaſe on me,</l>
                  <pb facs="tcp:20581:29"/>
                  <l>Such furious legions circle mee about,</l>
                  <l>And my ſlaine Sonne and Daughters fire brands,</l>
                  <l>Lying ſo neere me, to torment my ſoule,</l>
                  <l>Extremitie of all extremities.</l>
                  <l>Take pitty on the wandring ſenſe of mine,</l>
                  <l>Or it will breake the priſon of my ſoule:</l>
                  <l>And like to wild fire, fly about the world,</l>
                  <l>Till they haue no abioing in the world:</l>
                  <l>I faint, <hi>I</hi> dye, my ſorrowes are ſo great,</l>
                  <l>Oh mortalitie renounce thy ſeate.</l>
               </sp>
               <stage>He fals down</stage>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Valen.</speaker>
                  <l>The Duke <hi>I</hi> feare is ſlaine with extreame griefe:</l>
                  <l>I that had power to kill him, will aſſay hence forth,</l>
                  <l>My utmoſt induſtry to ſaue his life.</l>
                  <l>Looke up my Lord, 'tis not <hi>Valentias</hi> voice,</l>
                  <l>That Courtezan, that hath betray'd thy honour:</l>
                  <l>Murder'd thy children, and almoſt ſlaine thee:</l>
                  <l>I am thy ſonne, I am Prince <hi>Fredericke;</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>If thou haſt any liking of that name,</l>
                  <l>Looke on my face, I come to comfort thee.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Duke.</speaker>
                  <l>The name of <hi>Fredericke</hi> is like <hi>Hermes</hi> wande,</l>
                  <l>Able to charme and uncharme ſorrowfull men,</l>
                  <l>Who nam'd <hi>Fredericke?</hi>
                  </l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Valen.</speaker>
                  <l>I pronounc't his name,</l>
                  <l>That haue the power to giue thee thy loſt Sonne:</l>
                  <l>Had I like vertue to reſtore the other:</l>
                  <l>Behold my Lord, behold thy headleſſe Sonne</l>
                  <l>Bleſt with a head, the late deceaſed living,</l>
                  <l>As yet not fully waken'd from the ſleepe:</l>
                  <l>My drowfie potion kindled in his braine,</l>
                  <l>But much about this houre the power ſhould ceaſe,</l>
                  <l>And ſee he wakes.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Duke.</speaker>
                  <l>O happineſſe 'tis hee.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Valen.</speaker>
                  <l>Imbrace him then, but ne're more imbrace me.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Fred.</speaker>
                  <l>Where am <hi>I,</hi> in what dungeon, where's my graue?</l>
                  <l>Was <hi>I</hi> not dead, or dreamt <hi>I, I</hi> was dead,</l>
                  <l>This am I ſure that <hi>I</hi> was priſoned.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Duke.</speaker>
                  <l>Thou art deceiv'd my Sonne, but this deceit</l>
                  <pb facs="tcp:20581:30"/>
                  <l>Is worth commendations, thanke my Dutcheſſe,</l>
                  <l>Her diſcretion reedified thy life,</l>
                  <l>But ſhe hath pron'd her ſelfe a gracious wife.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Fred.</speaker>
                  <l>She tempt me to luſt, wait in my grave?</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>alen.</speaker>
                  <l>'Twas but to try thy faith unto thy father,</l>
                  <l>Let it ſuffice, his hand was at thy death,</l>
                  <l>But twas my mercie that proclaim'd thy breath.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Fred.</speaker>
                  <l>To heaven and you I render worthy thankes.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Duke.</speaker>
                  <l>O liv'd my <hi>Euphrata</hi> and <hi>Conſtantine,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>How gladly would I all my griefe reſigne.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Albert.</speaker>
                  <l>On that condition: and with this beſides,</l>
                  <l>That you are pleaſ'd to pardon us and them,</l>
                  <l>We doe referre our perſons to your mercie.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Duke.</speaker>
                  <l>My daughter, my deare ſonne in law,</l>
                  <l>Vertuous <hi>Alberto,</hi> then my friend,</l>
                  <l>My ioyes are at the higheſt, make this plaine,</l>
                  <l>How theſe ſav'd drownd, as <hi>Fredericke</hi> has bin ſlaine.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Albert.</speaker>
                  <l>Preſuming on the example of theſe friends,</l>
                  <l>And know we are all actors in this plot,</l>
                  <l>Boldly preſented your preſence with this minde,</l>
                  <l>If pardoning them, your grace would pardon us,</l>
                  <l>If otherwiſe, this was the ioy of either,</l>
                  <l>That death's leſſe painefull, when friends die together.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Duke.</speaker>
                  <l>We doe receive you all into our fauour,</l>
                  <l>And my faire Dutcheſſe my unkind divorce,</l>
                  <l>Shall be confounded with a ſecond marriage,</l>
                  <l>I here receive thee once more as my wife.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Val.</speaker>
                  <l>You have your children, I have paid that debt,</l>
                  <l>You have divore'd me, therefore I am free,</l>
                  <l>And henceforth I will be at libertie.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Duke.</speaker>
                  <l>There's no divorce can part thee from thy Lord.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Valen.</speaker>
                  <l>Like to unkindneſſe ther is no divorce.</l>
                  <l>I will no more be won unto your bed,</l>
                  <l>But take ſome courſe to lament my life miſlead.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Duk.</speaker>
                  <l>Canſt thou live better then in ſacred wedlock?</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Valen.</speaker>
                  <l>Wedlocke to me is unpleaſing, ſince my Lord</l>
                  <l>Hath broke the band of marriage with unkindneſſe.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Duke.</speaker>
                  <l>Intreate her children, <hi>Fredericke, Euphrata,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <pb facs="tcp:20581:30"/>
                  <l>Let me not looſe the eſſence of my ſoule,</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Fred.</speaker>
                  <l>Divine <hi>Valentia,</hi> mirrour of thy ſexe,</l>
                  <l>The pride of true reclaim'd incontinence,</l>
                  <l>Honour of the diſhonoring, yeeld I pray,</l>
                  <l>And be mercifull, pitty my fathers ſmart,</l>
                  <l>Since thy laſt thraldome hath neare cleft his heart.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Eup.</speaker>
                  <l>'Twas for his children that his ſpleene did riſe,</l>
                  <l>Anger, a torture haunting the moſt wiſe,</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Valen.</speaker>
                  <l>O no I am a murdereſſe, an <hi>Erinnis,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>A fury ſent from <hi>Limbo,</hi> to affright</l>
                  <l>Legions of people with my horrid ſight.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Hat.</speaker>
                  <l>What doe you meane, be won by their intrea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Alfred.</speaker>
                  <l>'Tis madneſſe in you to be thus perverſe.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>al.</speaker>
                  <l>Who ever ſpeaks, baſe wretches be you dumb,</l>
                  <l>You are the catter pillers of the ſtate,</l>
                  <l>By your bad dealings he is unfortunate,</l>
                  <l>Thou honourable true beloved Lord,</l>
                  <l>Hearken to me, and by thy antient love,</l>
                  <l>I charge thee baniſh theſe realme-ſucking ſlaues,</l>
                  <l>That build their pallace upon poore mens graves,</l>
                  <l>O thoſe are they, that have wrong'd both you and me,</l>
                  <l>Made this bleſt land, a land of miſerie.</l>
                  <l>And ſince by too much loving your grace, hath falne</l>
                  <l>Into a generall hatred of your ſubiects,</l>
                  <l>Redeeme your loſt eſtate with better dayes,</l>
                  <l>So ſhall you merit never dying praiſe,</l>
                  <l>So ſhall you gaine lives quietneſſe on earth,</l>
                  <l>And after death a new celeſtiall birth.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Duke.</speaker>
                  <l>Vnto thy wiſedome I referre their doomes,</l>
                  <l>My ſelfe my Dukedome, and my crowne,</l>
                  <l>Oh were there any thing of higher rate,</l>
                  <l>That, unto hee I'de wholly conſecrate.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Val.</speaker>
                  <l>This kind ſurrender ſhewes you are a Prince,</l>
                  <l>Worthy to be an Angell in the world</l>
                  <l>Of immortalitie:</l>
                  <l>Which theſe curſed creatures never can attaine,</l>
                  <l>But that this world may know how much I hate,</l>
                  <l>This cruell baſe oppreſſion of the poore:</l>
                  <pb facs="tcp:20581:31"/>
                  <l>Firſt I enioyne you for the wrongs you haue done,</l>
                  <l>Make reſtitution, and becauſe your goods,</l>
                  <l>Are not ſufficient ſo to ſatisfie;</l>
                  <l>I doe condemne your bodies to the Mynes,</l>
                  <l>Where liue like golden drudges all your liues:</l>
                  <l>In digging of the mettall you beſt loue:</l>
                  <l>Death is your due, but for your noble race,</l>
                  <l>This gentle ſentence I impoſe on you,</l>
                  <l>The Duke ſucceeding ſhall behold it done.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Duke.</speaker>
                  <l>Who's that my loue?</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Valen.</speaker>
                  <l>Kind <hi>Freaericke</hi> your ſonne,</l>
                  <l>The intereſt that your grace hath given to me,</l>
                  <l>I freely doe impart.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Duke.</speaker>
                  <l>We doe agree to what my Dutcheſſe pleaſe:</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Valen.</speaker>
                  <l>The ſtate is thine:</l>
                  <l>Thy Vncles ſentence <hi>Fredericke</hi> ſhall be mine.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Fred.</speaker>
                  <l>Beare them away, what you haue ſaid ſhall ſtand,</l>
                  <l>Whilſt <hi>I</hi> haue intereſt in this new given land.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Hat.</speaker>
                  <l>We doe receiue our iudgements with a curſe.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>alen.</speaker>
                  <l>Learne to pray better, or it ſhall be worſe:</l>
                  <l>Lords ſee theſe wormes of kingdomes be deſtroyed:</l>
                  <l>And now to giue a period to my ſpeech:</l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>I</hi> doe intreate your grace, if that your loue</l>
                  <l>Be not growne cold; but that your heart deſires</l>
                  <l>The true ſocietie of a chaſte wife:</l>
                  <l>Be pleas'd to undergoe a further doome,</l>
                  <l>Wee haue liv'd too lightly, we haue ſpent our dayes,</l>
                  <l>Which ſhould be dedicated to our God,</l>
                  <l>In ſoule deſtroying pleaſure, and our ſloth</l>
                  <l>Hath drawne upon the Realme a world of playes:</l>
                  <l>Therefore hereafter let us liue together,</l>
                  <l>In ſome removed cell or hermitage,</l>
                  <l>Vnto the which, poore travellers miſlead,</l>
                  <l>May haue direction and reliefe of wants.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Duke.</speaker>
                  <l>A hermetary life is better then a kingdome,</l>
                  <l>So my <hi>
                        <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>alentia</hi> beare me company.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Valen.</speaker>
                  <l>If my dread Lord will for my ſake endure,</l>
                  <pb facs="tcp:20581:31"/>
                  <l>So ſtrickt a calling, my bewitching haires,</l>
                  <l>Shall be made napkins to dry up the teares,</l>
                  <l>That true repentance wringeth from our hearts,</l>
                  <l>Our ſinnes we'l number with a thouſand ſighes:</l>
                  <l>Faſting ſhall be the Steward of our Feaſt:</l>
                  <l>Continuall prayer in ſtead of coſtly cates,</l>
                  <l>And the Remainder of our life a ſchoole,</l>
                  <l>To learne new leſſons for the land of heaven:</l>
                  <l>The will where power is wanting is good payment:</l>
                  <l>Grace doth reiect no thoughr, tho' nere ſo ſmall,</l>
                  <l>So it be good, our God is kind to all:</l>
                  <l>Come my deare Lord, this is a courſe more kind:</l>
                  <l>No life like us that haue a heavenly mind.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Mon.</speaker>
                  <l>O let me be a ſervant in that life.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Valen.</speaker>
                  <l>With all my heart, a Partner let him be,</l>
                  <l>There's ſmall ambition in humility.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Duke.</speaker>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Fredericke</hi> farewell, deare <hi>Euphrata</hi> adue,</l>
                  <l>Remember us in prayer, as we will you.</l>
               </sp>
               <stage>Exeunt D. &amp; D.</stage>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Fred.</speaker>
                  <l>A happy change, would all that ſtep awry,</l>
                  <l>Would take like courſe in ſeeking pietie.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Otho.</speaker>
                  <l>Two humble ſuites <hi>I</hi> craue of my beſt friend:</l>
                  <l>Firſt pardon for my raſhneſſe in your loue,</l>
                  <l>Next this moſt loyall Virgin for my wife.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Con.</speaker>
                  <l>With all my heart if <hi>Iulia</hi> be pleas'd.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Iulia.</speaker>
                  <l>I haue no power to diſobey your grant.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Con.</speaker>
                  <l>Then ſhe is yours.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Fred.</speaker>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Alberto.</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>The offices belonging to our Vncles,</l>
                  <l>We doe deriue to you for your good ſervice,</l>
                  <l>In our late warres, and in our ſiſters loue.</l>
                  <l>And now ſet forwards, Lords let us be gone,</l>
                  <l>To ſolemnize two mariages in one.</l>
               </sp>
            </div>
            <div type="epilogue">
               <pb facs="tcp:20581:32"/>
               <head>The Epilogue.</head>
               <l>ENcouragement unto the valiant,</l>
               <l>Is like a golden ſpurre upon the heele</l>
               <l>Of a young Knight, like to a wreath of Bay</l>
               <l>To a good Poet: like a ſparkeling Crowne,</l>
               <l>Vnto a Kings Son. Honour and renowne</l>
               <l>Is the efficient and perſevering cauſe</l>
               <l>Of every well deſerved action.</l>
               <l>Take away ſome recorde, encouragement,</l>
               <l>And the World's like a <hi>Chaos,</hi> all delight</l>
               <l>Buried, unborne in everlaſting night.</l>
               <l>Even ſo it fares with us and with the reſt,</l>
               <l>Of the ſame facultie, all meerely nothing,</l>
               <l>Without your favour, every labour dyes,</l>
               <l>Saue ſuch whoſe ſecond ſprings comes from your eyes:</l>
               <l>Extend your beames of loue to us at full;</l>
               <l>As the Sunne does unto the Eaſterne clime:</l>
               <l>And England may bring forth like India,</l>
               <l>As coſtly ſpice, as orientall Iems:</l>
               <l>The earth's all one, the heare refines the moulde:</l>
               <l>And favour makes the pooreſt ground yielde gold.</l>
            </div>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
