<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Euerie vvoman in her humor</title>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1609</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 147 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 40 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2013-12">2013-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A15676</idno>
            <idno type="STC">STC 25948</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC S120276</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99855475</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99855475</idno>
            <idno type="VID">20970</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A15676)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 20970)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 1017:7)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>Euerie vvoman in her humor</title>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[64] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed by E[dward] A[llde] for Thomas Archer, and are to be solde at his shop in the Popes-head-Pallace, neere the Royall Exchange,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1609.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Partly in verse.</note>
                  <note>Printer's name from STC.</note>
                  <note>Signatures: A-H⁴.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the University of Illinois (Urbana-Champaign Campus). Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2012-08</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-08</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-10</date>
            <label>Olivia Bottum</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-10</date>
            <label>Olivia Bottum</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-02</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:20970:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:20970:1"/>
            <p>EVERIE Woman in her Humor.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON</hi> Printed by <hi>E. A.</hi> for <hi>Thomas Archer,</hi> and are to be ſolde at his ſhop in the <hi>Popes-head-Pallace,</hi> neere the Royall Exchange. 1609.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="play">
            <pb facs="tcp:20970:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:20970:2"/>
            <head>Euerie Woman in her <hi>Humor.</hi>
            </head>
            <stage>Enter Flauia as a Prologue.</stage>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">G</seg>Entles of both ſexes, and all ſortes, I am ſent to bid yee welcome, I am but inſteade of a Prologue: for a ſhe pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>logue is as rare as an Vſurers Almes: <hi>non reperitur in vſu,</hi> and the rather I come woman, becauſe men are apt to take kindelye any kinde thing at a womans hand; and wee poore ſoules are but too kinde, if we be kindely intreated, marry otherwiſe, there I make my <hi>Apoſiopeſis:</hi> the Author hath indeede made me an honeſt merrye wench, one of his humoriſts, yet I am ſo much be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>holding to him, I cannot get mee a husband in his play that's worthe the hauing, vnleſſe I be better halfe of the ſutor my ſelfe: and hauing impoſed this audacity on me, he ſends me hither firſt for exerciſe I come among ye all: theſe are the Contentes, that you would heare with patience, iudge with lenity, and correct with ſmiles, for the which our endea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uours ſhall ſhew it ſelfe like a tall fellow in action: if vve ſhall ioyne hands, a bargaine.</p>
            <p>As a lowely earneſt, I giue this curteſie before, And in conceite I giue ye twenty more.</p>
            <stage>
               <pb facs="tcp:20970:3"/>
               <hi>Enter Accutus and Graccus.</hi>
            </stage>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Gra.</speaker>
               <p>Nay, but <hi>Accutus,</hi> prethee what miſ-ſhapen vizard of Melancholly haſt thou mask't thy ſelfe in? thou lookſt as thou wer't changing thy religion: what? is there a breach in thy Faith? come, declare, and let me ſet thy wits on worke, to amend it.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Acut.</speaker>
               <p>Ha ha ha!</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Grac.</speaker>
               <p>Prettie: a man's well aduiſd to offer good coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſell, and be laught at for his labour: we ſhall ſhortly haue no Counſellors but Phyſitians, I ſpend my breath to thee, and thou anſwereſt me ſome halfe an houre after in a ſem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>breue, or like to a Sexton with a Sobeitor Amen.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Acu.</speaker>
               <p>Condemne my Stars then.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Grac.</speaker>
               <p>I ſhould wrong am then, as thou doſt with a falſe inditement, I know it tooke not, beeing at thy birth, thou haſt bene merrie, thou haſt ſounded hoopes, ſwallowed whiffes, walkt late, worne fauours, ſeene whore ſons: thou canſt feele and vnderſtand, come, thou haſt bene a ſinner: vnloade, diſcharge, vntune, confeſſe, is venus dominatrix? art not in loue?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Acut.</speaker>
               <p>Yes, I loue God and my neighbors.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Grac.</speaker>
               <p>Then either for Gods ſake or thy Neighbors, or both, be ſmothe, and participate, iſt not ſome vnderlayer, ſome ſhe Cammell that will beare as much of her belly, as three beaſtes on their backes? ſome Lanthorne-maker, Ile holde thy head: come, vp with't.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Acut.</speaker>
               <p>Prethee I hate none, but heauen hate me if I be in loue with any.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Grac.</speaker>
               <p>Off with theſe clogs, then break priſon, and get out of this melancholly Gaole, harke how the generall noiſe doth welcome from the Parthian wars, each ſpirit's iocund, fraught with glee, then wrong not thine with this dull meditation.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <pb facs="tcp:20970:3"/>
               <speaker>Acut.</speaker>
               <p>Oh! how doe they then wrong my meditati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on? my thoughts are with themſelues at a counſell, til with noiſe and thou with continuall talke, haſt driuen them to a <hi>nonplus.</hi>
               </p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Gra.</speaker>
               <p>Then make me of thy counſell, and take my ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uice, for ile take no denyall, Ile not leaue thee til the next new Almanackes be out of date: let him threaten the ſhar<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>peſt weather he can, in Saint <hi>Swithin</hi> week, or it ſnow on our Ladies face, ile not budge, ile be thy mid-wife til thou beeſt deliuered of this paſſion.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Acut.</speaker>
               <p>Partake then, and giue me the beleefe: thinkſt thou or knowſt thou any of this opinion, that, that moouing ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſh element, that ſwels and ſwages as it pleaſe the moone, to be in bignes equall to that ſolide lump that brings vs vp?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Gra.</speaker>
               <p>I was ſure thou wert beyond the <hi>Antipodes:</hi> faith I am of that faith I was brought vp in, I haue heard my Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther ſay, and i'me ſure his Recordes came from his Father, that the Land and Sea are in nature thus much alike; the owne growes by the Sunne, the other by the Moone, both by Gods bleſſing; and the Sea rather the greater, and ſo thinke I.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Acut.</speaker>
               <p>Good: there we haue a farther ſcope, and holde the ſea, can (as a looking glaſſe) anſwere with a meere ſmile any moouing ſhape vppon the earth.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Gra.</speaker>
               <p>Nay, that's moſt certaine, I haue heard of Sea-hor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes, Sea-calues, and Sea-monſters.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Acut.</speaker>
               <p>Oh, they are monſtrous madde, merrie wenches, and they are monſters <hi>Graccus,</hi> they call them Sea-maides or Mermaides ſinging ſweetelye, but none dares truſt them, and are verie like our Land-wenches, deuouring Serpents from the middle downeward.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Acut.</speaker>
               <p>Thou haſt euen giuen me ſatisfaction: but haſt thou this by proofe?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Grac.</speaker>
               <p>Not by my trauels (ſo God helpe me) marrie ile bring ye fortie Saylers will ſweare they haue ſeene them.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <pb facs="tcp:20970:4"/>
               <speaker>Acut.</speaker>
               <p>In truth!</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Grac.</speaker>
               <p>In truth or otherwiſe.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Acu.</speaker>
               <p>Faith they are not vnlike our land monſters, elſe why ſhould this Maximilian Lord, for whom theſe ſhoots and noyſes befits thus, forſake his honours, to ſing a Lullabye?</p>
               <l>Theſe ſeeming Saints, alluring euils,</l>
               <l>That make earth Erebus, and mortals deuils.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Gra.</speaker>
               <p>Come, thou art Sea-ſicke, and will not be well at eaſe til thou haſt tane a vomit, vp with't.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Acu.</speaker>
               <l>Why ifaith I muſt, I can not ſoothe the world</l>
               <l>With veluet words, and oyly flatteries,</l>
               <l>And kiſſe the ſweatie feete of magnitude,</l>
               <l>To purchaſe ſmiles, or a deade mans office,</l>
               <l>I cannot holde to ſee a rib of man</l>
               <l>A moytie of it ſelfe, commaund the whole</l>
               <l>Bafful, and bend to muliebritie</l>
               <l>Of female ſcandals; obſerue, doe but obſerue,</l>
               <l>Heere one walks ore-growne in weeds of pride,</l>
               <l>The earth wants ſhape, to apply a ſimile,</l>
               <l>A body priſoned vp with walles of wyer,</l>
               <l>With bones of whales, ſomewhat allyed to fiſh</l>
               <l>But from the waſt declining, more looſe doth hang,</l>
               <l>Then her wanton dangling laſciuious locke</l>
               <l>Thats whirld and blowne with euerie luſtfull breath.</l>
               <l>Her necke in chaines, all naked lyes her breſt,</l>
               <l>Her body lighter then the feathered creſt.</l>
               <l>Another powtes and ſcoules, and hangs the lip,</l>
               <l>Euen as the banckrout credit of her huſband,</l>
               <l>Cannot equall her with honors liuerie,</l>
               <l>What doth ſhe care, if for to decke her braue,</l>
               <l>Hee's carryed from a Gate-houſe to his graue.</l>
               <l>Another in a rayling pulppet key,</l>
               <l>Drawes through her noſe the accent of her voice,</l>
               <l>And in the preſence of her good man Goate,</l>
               <l>Cries fye, now fye vppon theſe wicked men.</l>
               <pb facs="tcp:20970:4"/>
               <l>That vſe ſuch beaſtly and inhumane talke:</l>
               <l>When being in priuate, all her ſtudies warne,</l>
               <l>To make him enter into Capricorne.</l>
               <l>Another as ſhe goes, treads a Canarie pace,</l>
               <l>Iets it ſo fine, and minces ſo demure,</l>
               <l>As miſtris Bride vpon her marriage day:</l>
               <l>Her heeles are Corke, her body Atlas,</l>
               <l>Her Beautie bought, her ſoule an Atomus.</l>
               <l>Another with a ſpleene deuoured face,</l>
               <l>Her eies as hollow as Anatomy:</l>
               <l>Her tung more venome then a Serpents ſting,</l>
               <l>Which when it wagges within her chap-faln iawes,</l>
               <l>Is noiſe more horrid then a cry of hounds</l>
               <l>With open mouthes, purſuing of their game,</l>
               <l>Wants ſhe but ritch attire or coſtly dyet,</l>
               <l>With her the Deuill can nere liue in quiet.</l>
               <l>Yet theſe are weaker veſſels, heauen doth knowe,</l>
               <l>Lay on them ought but eaſe, you doe them wrong:</l>
               <l>They are as weake as water, and indeede as ſtrong,</l>
               <l>And then like mightie ſhips, when pellets ſincke,</l>
               <l>To them lay more men, ſheele neuer ſhrinke.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Boſſ.</speaker>
               <p>Miſtris, that face wants a freſh Gloſſe.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Gent.</speaker>
               <p>Prethee dib it in well Bos.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Acut.</speaker>
               <l>Pigmaleon, Pigmaleon, I coniure thee appeare,</l>
               <l>To worke, to worke, make more Marble Ingles,</l>
               <l>Nature, thou art a foole, Art is aboue thee:</l>
               <l>Belzebub, paint thy face, there's ſome will loue thee.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Boſ.</speaker>
               <p>Rare, Miſtris, heeres a cheeke like a Camelion or a blaſing Star: you ſhall heere me blaze it, heere's two ſau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cers ſanguine in a ſable field, pomegranet, a pure penda<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t, Ready to drop out of the ſtable, a pin and web argent in hayre de Roy.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Grac.</speaker>
               <p>And a fooles head in the Creſt.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Boſ.</speaker>
               <p>In the Creſt? oh ſweete Vermilion miſtris! tis pit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie the Vermilion Wormes ſhould eate thee, ile ſet it with pretious ſtones and ye will.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <pb facs="tcp:20970:5"/>
               <speaker>Gent.</speaker>
               <p>Enough ſweete <hi>Boſſe,</hi> throwe a little water to ſpurt's face and lets away.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Bo.</speaker>
               <p>Hold vp, ſo ſir now away: oh Miſtris your ſcant<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling, moſt ſweete miſtris moſt derydent ſtarre.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Acut.</speaker>
               <p>Then moſt rydent ſtarres faire fall ye.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Grac.</speaker>
               <p>Nay ſure tis the Moone her ſelfe, for there's her man and her Dogge before.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Boſſe.</speaker>
               <p>I ſir, but the man is not in the moon, &amp; my buſhis before me, <hi>ergo</hi> not at my backe, <hi>et ergo,</hi> not moone ſir.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Gent.</speaker>
               <p>What's your will ſir?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Accut.</speaker>
               <p>That you would leaue vs.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Boſſ.</speaker>
               <p>Leaue you, zoundes ſir, we ſcorne their compa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nies, come, they are ſtill, doe not open to them, we haue no Conies to catch.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Acut.</speaker>
               <l>Away, keepe no diſtance, euen both together,</l>
               <l>For wit, ye may be Coacht together.</l>
               <l>What ſleeke browde Saint can ſee this Idiotiſme,</l>
               <l>The ſhape and workemanſhip of omnipotency,</l>
               <l>To be ſo blinde with drugs of beaſtlineſſe,</l>
               <l>And will not bend the browe, and bite the lippe,</l>
               <l>Trouble his quiet ſoule, with venome ſpleene,</l>
               <l>And feare leaſt the all ouer-ſeeer,</l>
               <l>Can without vengeance, ſee theſe ignomies.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Grac.</speaker>
               <p>Why therfore are they belooued like Sargeants, and entertained like Beggars, think'ſt thou but any ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>norable Gate but will be ſhut againſt theſe Butter-flies?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Accut.</speaker>
               <l>Oh <hi>Graecus!</hi> thou beguil'ſt opinion,</l>
               <l>The Gates of great men ſtand more wide</l>
               <l>To entertaine a foole, then <hi>Creſus</hi> armes,</l>
               <l>To hug his Golden God: and faſter bard</l>
               <l>Againſt neceſſitie, then Diues entrance</l>
               <l>At Olympus gate.</l>
            </sp>
            <stage>Enter Sernulas, Scillicet, Philantus and Boy.</stage>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Sernu.</speaker>
               <p>Fa, la, ſol, laſol: Boy a Glaſſe;</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <pb facs="tcp:20970:5"/>
               <speaker>Boy.</speaker>
               <p>Tis but one and all ſir.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Acut.</speaker>
               <p>Angels protect vs, what haue we heare?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Boy.</speaker>
               <p>Ye haue a good memorie Sir, for they are fiue mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nutes ere windefall of your Glaſſe.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Ser.</speaker>
               <p>Sir, be credible, tis ballanſt to be a ſuperlatiue po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liticke cuſtome in theſe houres to dwell in ſhallowe ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>coutrements, as a defence for the abilitie of his purſſe, from the infringed Oath of ſome impudent face, that will borrowe a gentlema<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s reuenewes, if he be veſtally adornd: Ile tell you ſir, by this bright Horriſon—</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Scil.</speaker>
               <p>A word I pray yee ſir ere ye goe any further: Boy my Tables?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Boy.</speaker>
               <p>Your Tables are ready Sir, and all the men ye keep which is indeede halfe a Boy, <hi>Scillicet, Videlicet.</hi>
               </p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Scil.</speaker>
               <p>I pray ye let me requeſt that oath of you.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Sern.</speaker>
               <p>A gracefull enquirie, and well obſeru'd: Sir my company ſhal make ye copious of nouelties, let your Ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bles befriend your memorie: write, by this bright Horri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Phy.</speaker>
               <p>Here's none but only I, ſing: Boy, how lik'ſt thou my head of hayre?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Boy.</speaker>
               <p>Your Glaſſe may flatter ye, but truely I will not, your head is not a hayre better then it ſhould be.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Phy.</speaker>
               <p>Is there any ſcarcitie of haire Boy?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Boy.</speaker>
               <p>Somewhat thin, and yet there is more hayre then wit.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Phy:</speaker>
               <p>How Boy?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Boy.</speaker>
               <p>Then wit of man can number ſir, take it i'th right ſence I pray yee.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Phy.</speaker>
               <p>Moſt ingenious!</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Acu.</speaker>
               <l>O muffle, muffle good <hi>Graccûs,</hi> doe not taint thy ſence,</l>
               <l>With ſight of theſe infectious animalles,</l>
               <l>Leaſt reaſon in thee haue the vpper hand</l>
               <l>To gouerne ſence, to ſee and ſhun the ſight:</l>
               <l>Here's new diſcouered ſins, paſt all the reſt,</l>
               <l>Men ſtriue by practiſe how to ſweare the beſt.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <pb facs="tcp:20970:6"/>
               <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                  <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb facs="tcp:20970:6"/>
               <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                  <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb facs="tcp:20970:7"/>
               <speaker>Scil.</speaker>
               <p>I haue quoted it ſir, by this bright Hore, Hore ſon, pronounce ye ſir.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Seru:</speaker>
               <p>Horiſon</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Scil:</speaker>
               <p>Horiſon the Widowes mite Sir?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Sern.</speaker>
               <p>Not for the Soldans crowne ſir.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Scil.</speaker>
               <p>Indeede yee ſhall, by this bright horiſon ye ſhall, beleeue me if I ſweare, I thinke my ſelfe behol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding, for I know it to be no common oath.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Seru.</speaker>
               <p>Were it common, it paſt not theſe doores: Sir, I ſhift my oathes as I waſh my hands, twice in the artifici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>al day, for in dialoguiſing, tis to be obſeru'd, your ſenten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces muſt ironically, metaphorically, and altogether figu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ratiuely mixt with your morning oathes.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Scil:</speaker>
               <p>Faith tis verie true.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Accu.</speaker>
               <p>That he neither knowes what he ſaies, nor thou vnderſtandeſt.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Seru:</speaker>
               <p>As for example, by this illuminate welkin.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Scel:</speaker>
               <p>Oh excellent! it ſhall downe to.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Accut.</speaker>
               <l>There's another Ducket, he vtters his oathes apace.</l>
               <l>Sure this Villaine has no ſoule, and for golde</l>
               <l>Heele damme his body too, hee's at peace with hell,</l>
               <l>And brings his Marchandiſe from thence to ſell.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Boy.</speaker>
               <p>I haue heere two Miſtreſſes, but if the beſt were choſen out, if <hi>Poliphemus</hi> tother eye were out, his choice might be as good as <hi>Argus</hi> broade waking, ſo difficult is the difference.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Phy.</speaker>
               <p>Boy, ſleepe wayward thoughts.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Boy.</speaker>
               <p>Sir.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Phy.</speaker>
               <p>Is it not now moſt amyable and faire?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Boy.</speaker>
               <p>Yes ſir God be praiſed.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Phy.</speaker>
               <p>What meanſt thou Boy?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Boy.</speaker>
               <p>The weather ſir.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Phy.</speaker>
               <p>I meane my haire and face Boy.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Boy:</speaker>
               <p>Twere amiable if it would not alter.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Phy.</speaker>
               <p>Wherfore, I often repaire it.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <pb facs="tcp:20970:7"/>
               <speaker>Boy:</speaker>
               <p>Me thinkes that ſhould weare it the ſooner.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Phy.</speaker>
               <p>Not ſo Boy, for to trimme the Hayre well, is a rare qualitie: to bee rarelye quallified is to be wiſe, apply Boy.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Boy.</speaker>
               <p>That you are wiſe in trimming your hayre Mai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Phy.</speaker>
               <p>Right, to be wiſe is to be rare, for it is rare to ſee a wiſe man.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Boy.</speaker>
               <p>True Maiſter: but if youle ſee a foole looke in your Glaſſe maiſter.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Phy.</speaker>
               <p>Goe to, I muſt correct you Boy.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Boy</speaker>
               <p>You can correct no more then is your own, I am but halfe yours to commaund, if you ſteale away any parte that is not your owne, you are ſo farre in daunger as the ſtriking of an other mans ſeruant.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Phy:</speaker>
               <p>By this illuminate welkin moſt ſincere and ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gular, as a ſmall remembrance.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Seru,</speaker>
               <p>Not for to winne the faire Angelica.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Scillicet:</speaker>
               <p>By this illuminate Welkin ye ſhall now.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Seru:</speaker>
               <p>Sir, I doe not beſtowe it for that I thinke you haue neede of it, for if you had, by this bright Horizon I would not giue it, for I know tis no credit to giue to the poore, by this illuminate welkin, I haue (ſince I tooke vpon me this fleſhie deſire of a Gentleman) throwne out of a window for a huntſvp, when I had as leef haue heard the grinding of a Muſtard Mill, for thoſe are thinges are heere too day and gone to morrowe: this will ſticke by a man, and doe him credit where ere hee goes.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Acut:</speaker>
               <l>I, when the foole is clad in clay,</l>
               <l>It will ſticke ſore vnto thy ſoule for aye.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Phy:</speaker>
               <p>Signior <hi>Scillicet,</hi> I aſſure you I haue diſcouered the moſte queint and new-found deuice for the en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>counter of the Ladies at the enteruiew, tis in pricke-ſong.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <pb facs="tcp:20970:8"/>
               <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                  <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb facs="tcp:20970:8"/>
               <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                  <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb facs="tcp:20970:9"/>
               <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                  <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb facs="tcp:20970:9"/>
               <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                  <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb facs="tcp:20970:10"/>
               <speaker>Scil.</speaker>
               <p>That's excellent and rare.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Phi.</speaker>
               <p>I, for prick-ſong to Ladies is moſte pleaſant and delightfull, as thus for your congie, All hayle to my be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>looued: then for your departure, ſad diſpaire doth driue me hence: for all muſt be to effect.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Grac.</speaker>
               <p>Nay, prethee raiſe no quarrels.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Acut.</speaker>
               <p>I can holde no longer, heare you ſir, are not you a foole? and you an Aſſe? and you a knaue?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Phy.</speaker>
               <p>zoundes an Aſſe?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Scil.</speaker>
               <p>A Foole?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Ser.</speaker>
               <p>A Knaue without reſpect?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Acut.</speaker>
               <p>I, for an Aſſe can beare, a Foole abide, and a Knaue deſerue:</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Omn.</speaker>
               <p>Helpe, helpe!</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Gra.</speaker>
               <p>Prethee lets away.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Acut.</speaker>
               <p>Fooles oftentimes brings wiſemen to trouble, Farwell, another time ile pay ye double.
<stage>Exit.</stage>
               </p>
            </sp>
            <stage>Enter Hoſt, Hoſteſſe,</stage>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Hoſt.</speaker>
               <p>Bring your Clubs out of doores, there goe in my fine hoſtes, ile talke to the proudeſt: what knaues are i'th ſtreete, my dore is my dore, my houſe is my caſtell, goe in dame Helena, let thine hoſt alon with this: he that knocks at my hobby, while I haue Ale in my houſe, ſhall pay for a Surgeon: the honeſt ſhal come in, the knaues ſhall go by: bring Clubs I ſay.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Scil.</speaker>
               <p>Nay ſir, the heare is paſt, they that did it haue tooke them to their heeles, for indeede heere are of vs—</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Hoſt.</speaker>
               <p>Away with your Clubs then, welcome my braue Bullies, my Gueſts ſhal take no wrong, but welcome my Bullies.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Scil.</speaker>
               <p>Indeede ſir I am a man of few words, I haue put vp a little blood ſhed, marrie I hope it ſhall be no ſtaine to my manhoode, if I keepe it out of my clothes.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Hoſt.</speaker>
               <p>He ſhall pay for the blood-ſhed, my gueſtes ſhal take no wrong: mine Hoſt will ſpend his Cruſe as franke
<pb facs="tcp:20970:10"/> as an Emperor: welcome my braue bullies.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Ser.</speaker>
               <p>Sir, be pacificall, the fellowe was poſſeſt with ſome critique frenzie, and wee impute it to his madnes.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Scil:</speaker>
               <p>Madde! by Gods ſlid if he were as madde as a wea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer, I can hardly put it vp: for my blow: I care not ſo much, but he cald me foole: ſlid if I liue till I dye, the one of vs ſhall proue it.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Hoſt:</speaker>
               <p>Some prophane Villaine, ile warrant him.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Scil.</speaker>
               <p>Doe you thinke I may not haue an action againſt him?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Hoſt:</speaker>
               <p>There's ſo many ſwaggerers, but alaſſe, how fel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ye out?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Scil:</speaker>
               <p>By the welkin I gaue him not a foule word: firſt he calles me foole, then he makes a full blowe at my body, and if by good chance I had not warded it with my head, he might haue ſpoild me.</p>
            </sp>
            <stage>Enter Prentices.</stage>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Hoſt.</speaker>
               <p>There, there, my fine fil-pots: giue the word as you paſſe: anon anon ſir, anon: heere and there in the twinckling, looke well to the barre, there againe my little Mercuries, froath them vp to the brimme, and fill as tis needefull: if their pates be full of Wine, let your Pottles be three quarters, trip and goe, here and there: now any braue Lad waſh thy woundes with good Wine: bidde am welcom my little Sybil: put ſugar in his hole there, I muſt in to my gueſts, ſleepe ſoundly till morning: Canarie is a Iewell, and a Figge for Browne-baſtard.
<stage>Exit.</stage>
               </p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Hoſtes.</speaker>
               <p>Gentlemen, ye are welcom, though my huſba<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d be a little talkatiue, yet truly he is an vnreaſonable honeſt man, yee ſhall finde his words and his ſayings all one.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Scil:</speaker>
               <p>I thinke no leſſe, yet I would deſire to enter as time and place ſhall ſerue.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Hoſtes:</speaker>
               <p>Ile lead the way forſooth.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Phy.</speaker>
               <p>Nay pray ye Hoſteſſe a word, I ſay little, but i'me ſure I haue ſuſtained the moſt wrong; by this light, I
<pb facs="tcp:20970:11"/> had rather he had broke my head in three places, I pray you lend me a bruſh, hee has put my hat quite out of fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhion.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Hoſt.</speaker>
               <p>That ſhall ye ſir, a bruſh there hoe!</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Bos</speaker>
               <p>
                  <hi>Salue, ſis ſaluus,</hi> I pray yee which of you fiue is the Hoſtis of the houſe?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Boy:</speaker>
               <p>Thats eaſily diſcernd, for foure weare breeches.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Bos:</speaker>
               <p>Nere the ſooner for that my diminitiue youth, for women now adaies weare breeches as well as men, mary the difference lies in the bawble.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Hoſtis</speaker>
               <p>Well ſir, to open the ttuth I am the Hoſteſſe.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Bos</speaker>
               <p>The fruit is knowne by the Tree at the firſt view, as the Author writes learnedly, come, <hi>baſilus manus.</hi>
               </p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Scil.</speaker>
               <p>This kiſſing becomes a Gentleman, ile vſe it ſuret</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Bos:</speaker>
               <p>Secondly, Miſtris Hoſteſſe, I would knowe what lodging ye haue for my Lady and her traine.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Hoſtis:</speaker>
               <p>What will ſerue your turne ſir?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Bos</speaker>
               <p>Ile call my ſelfe to account and ſpecifie thus: my Lady and her Dogge that's two viſible: then there's the Dogge and my Lady, that's foure inuiſible: then there's my Ladies dogge and I quoth the dogge, that's ſix: then there's ſequence of three, viz. the Dogge and I and my Lady: then there's a paire of Knaues, viz the Dogge &amp; my ſelfe, &amp; my Lady turnd vp: viz my Lady ſequence of three: a paire of knaues, &amp; my Lady turn'd vp to play vpon, we can haue no leſſe then fiue beds.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Hoſtis.</speaker>
               <p>Truely you muſt lye cloſe together, (the Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uants I meane) for I am ſo thruſt with Gueſt I an hardly ſpare ſo many.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Bos</speaker>
               <p>Faith weele lie together as cloſe as we can: there's my Lady and her dogge lye al together, and I at the beds feete, and there's all our family of Loue.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Hoſtis:</speaker>
               <p>How farre is your miſtris behinde?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Bos</speaker>
               <p>The truth is, the fatall ſiſters haue cut the thred of her Corke-ſhoe, &amp; ſhee's ſtept aſide into a Coblers ſhop to take a true ſtitch, whether I meane to ſend my ſelfe as
<pb facs="tcp:20970:11"/> a Court of Guard to conduct her: but ſee, oh, inconſtant fortune! ſee where ſhee comes <hi>ſolus.</hi>
               </p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Gent,</speaker>
               <p>
                  <hi>Bos,</hi> you ſerue me well to let me waite vpon my ſelfe.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Bos.</speaker>
               <p>Of two euils the leaſt is to be choſen, I had a care of your puppie being leſſe then your ſelfe.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Scil,</speaker>
               <p>Gentlewoman you haue an excellent Ch: I haue an appetite as a man would ſay.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Gent,</speaker>
               <p>What's your will ſir?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Scil,</speaker>
               <p>Truth will to light, and the truth is, I haue an ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>petite to kiſſe you.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Phil:</speaker>
               <p>This point would become a Gentleman ſure, I pray who trim'd it ſo?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Gent,</speaker>
               <p>My man forſooth.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Phy,</speaker>
               <p>Sir, I deſire your acquaintance, tis excellent rare.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Gent;</speaker>
               <p>You would haue ſaide ſo, had you ſeene it an houre ſince.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Ser.</speaker>
               <l>Heeres game for me,</l>
               <l>I hunt for fooles, and haue ſprung a couey.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Hoſtis.</speaker>
               <p>Gentles, pleaſe you draw neere? leade the way into the chambers.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Bos;</speaker>
               <p>Bos is the name of a thing may be ſeene, felt, heard, or vnderſtood, and the nominatiue caſe goes before, my Miſtris the Verbe, my miſtris requires an accuſatiue caſe to follow, as <hi>vſus feminae pro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ptus facit. Exeunt al but Hoſtis</hi>
               </p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Hoſtis;</speaker>
               <p>Oh fye vpont, who would be an hoſtis, &amp; could do otherwiſe? Ladie, as the moſte laſciuious life, conges and kiſſes, the tyre, the hood, the rebato, the looſe bodyed Gowne, the pin in the haire, and euerie day change, when an Hoſtis muſt come and go at euerye mans pleaſure: and what's a Lady more then another body? wee haue legs and hands, rowling eyes, hanging lips, ſleek browes, &amp; che<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie cheeks, &amp; other things as Ladies haue, but the faſhion carries it away.
<stage>Prentices paſſe ouer.</stage>
               </p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Hoſt;</speaker>
               <p>There, there my little Lacky boies, againe, again, my fine fil-pots, where is my fine Hoſtis? come, come my litle dido, ſet your corks on a creaking, my knaues are vn<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>thrifty, dance not your canaries, heere, vp &amp; down, look about to my Gueſts I ſay.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <pb facs="tcp:20970:12"/>
               <speaker>Hoſtis:</speaker>
               <p>I, I haue much ioy, an Hoſteſſe!</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Hoſt.</speaker>
               <p>What, abides my Penenelope? heere ſtand thy Vliſſes, ile tarry with thee ſtil, thou ſhalt wa<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t for no coſt, ile buy thee a braue whiſtle, looke about to my Gueſtes I ſay.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Hoſtis.</speaker>
               <p>I, Hoſteſſes will bee knowne ſhortlye as their Signes, ſtill in one weather-beaten ſuite, as though none weare hoodes but Monkes and Ladies: and feathers, but fore-horſes, and Waiting Gentlewomen: or chaines but priſoners and Courtiers: no Perywigges but Players and Pictures, but the weakeſt muſt to the wall ſtill.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Hoſt.</speaker>
               <p>Tuſh tuſh, theſe are toies, ile none of theſe Flip-flaps, ile haue no <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>oping, no puffes, nor no Cobwebs: no busks nor burbarrels: thou ſhalt wear thine own haire, &amp; fine cloath of Sheep-skins: thy colour ſhal be Dow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>las, as white as a Lillie: ile kiſſe theſe chop-cheries, thou ſhalt goe Goſſip at Shroue-tide, look about to my Gueſts then.
<stage>Exit.</stage>
               </p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Hoſtis.</speaker>
               <p>I, twas my hard fortune to be an Hoſteſſe, time was I might haue done otherwiſe.</p>
            </sp>
            <stage>Enter Cittizens Wife.</stage>
            <sp>
               <speaker>City w:</speaker>
               <p>Why how now Woman, a'th olde diſeaſe ſtill? will it neuer be better? cannot a Woman finde one kinde man amongſt twentie? ah the daies: I haue ſeen, when a Womans will was a lawe: if I had had a minde to ſuch a thing, or ſuch a thing, I could haue had it, but twa's neuer better ſince men were Purſe-bearers.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Hosty.</speaker>
               <p>Mine is eene the vnnaturalliſt man to his Wife</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Citie wi:</speaker>
               <p>Truely, and commonly are all ſuch fat men: ile tell thee Goſſip, I haue buried ſixe, I ſixe husbands, but if I ſhould liue to haue as many more, as I know not what may happen, but ſure ide neuer haue ſuch a fatte man: they be the moſte vnweldy men, that women ſhall not want a ſore ſtomack that's troubled with them I war<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rant her.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <pb facs="tcp:20970:12"/>
               <speaker>Hoſtis</speaker>
               <p>And hee maintaines me heare like I knowe not what.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>City w.</speaker>
               <p>I, and what ſay, they are their wiues head, well, if he be the head, ſhee's the body, and the body is to beare the head, and the body is to beare the purſſe.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Hoſtis</speaker>
               <p>They cannot miſſe vs, yet they regard vs not.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Citty wife.</speaker>
               <p>Miſſe vs! no faith, but would all wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men were of my minde, they call vs the weaker veſſels: they ſhould finde veſſels of vs, but no weake veſſels I warrant them.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Pren.</speaker>
               <p>Miſtris my Maiſter, cals for ye.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Hoſtis.</speaker>
               <p>Goe, ile come anon, hee's not ſo haſtie to giue me what I want I warrant ye,</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>City w.</speaker>
               <p>No, would he were, little thinkes the husband what goes through the wiues hand, waſhing, wringing and rubbing, vp earely, downe late, &amp; a thouſand things they looke not too.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Hoſtis.</speaker>
               <p>And yet they muſt haue the gouernment of all.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Citty w.</speaker>
               <p>And great reaſon they haue for it, but a wiſe man will put in a Womans hand, what? ſheele ſaue that hee ſpends.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Hoſtis</speaker>
               <p>You haue a prettie Ruffe, how deepe is it?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Citty w.</speaker>
               <p>Nay this is but ſhallowe, marrie I haue a Ruffe is a quarter deepe, meaſured by the yard.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Hoſtis</speaker>
               <p>Indeede by the yard!</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Citty w.</speaker>
               <p>By the ſtandard, you haue a pretty ſet too: how big is the ſteele you ſet it with?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Hoſtis.</speaker>
               <p>As bigge as a reaſonable ſufficient—</p>
            </sp>
            <stage>Enter Prentice.</stage>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Pren.</speaker>
               <p>Miſtris, my Maiſter would deſire you to come in.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Citty w.</speaker>
               <p>What? ſhe ſhall not come yet, if you lay down the bucklers you loſe the victorie.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Hoſtis.</speaker>
               <p>By my troth I muſt goe, wee ſhall haue ſuch a coyle elſe.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <pb facs="tcp:20970:13"/>
               <speaker>City w.</speaker>
               <p>A coyle! why haue you not a tongue in your head? faith if ye win not all at that weapon, yee are not worthy to be a Woman, you heare not the news abroade:</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Hoſtis:</speaker>
               <p>No, what newes?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Citty wife.</speaker>
               <p>No, I warrant ye, you neuer come abroad, this is to be troubled with a fatte man, he neuer comes a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>broad himſelfe, nor ſuffers his wife out of his ſight: yee ſhal euer haue a fatte Hoſt, either on his be<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ch at the dore, or in his chair in the chimney, &amp; there he ſpits &amp; ſpaules a roome like twentie Tobacco takers, oh fye on them beaſts.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Hoſtis.</speaker>
               <p>But I prethee what newes?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Citty w.</speaker>
               <p>Oh woman! the moſte hard fauourd newes, and without al conſcience, they ſay there's a ſtatute made any woman that buries her husband, is not to marrie a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gaine of two monethes after.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Hoſtis.</speaker>
               <p>A teadious time by Lady, a month were enough.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Cittie w.</speaker>
               <p>I halfe a month, winter nights are long, and colde, ile tell ye, I haue buried ſixe, and I thank my good fortune, I euer knewe the next ere the other was in his winding ſheete.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Pre.</speaker>
               <p>Miſtris, my maiſter is angrie, and the Gueſts cal for their Hoſteſſe.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Hoſtis.</speaker>
               <p>Goe, I come, Goſſip when ſhall I ſee you age<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Citty wi.</speaker>
               <p>Nay, when ſhall I ſee you abroad, ſildome i'me ſure.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Hoſtis</speaker>
               <p>I muſt needes away, God buy you Goſſip.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Cittie w.</speaker>
               <p>God buy ye, Gods ſo, I haue forgot wherefore I came: a word ere you goe, the partie yee wott on com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mendes him vnto ye, he that met the other party in the white felt, the yellowe ſcarfe, and the round Venetian, when the other party kiſt you, and I broake the ieſt on him: when hee ſaide, kiſſes kindeles Coales, and loue ſearches.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Hoſtis.</speaker>
               <p>Oh! I remember him, yes faith, hee's prettie well ſet: hee ha's the right tricke with the tongue in his
<pb facs="tcp:20970:13"/> kiſſe, and hee dances reaſonably comely, but he fals hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uie.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Citty w.</speaker>
               <p>He ſauours of a kinde of Gallant, but not of a Courtyer.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Hoſtis</speaker>
               <p>Well, weele haue a night ont, god be with ye Goſſip.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Cittie wife.</speaker>
               <p>God buy ye.
<stage>Exeunt</stage>
               </p>
            </sp>
            <stage>Enter Lentulus and Tulley.</stage>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Len.</speaker>
               <l>Not yours nor her owne <hi>Terentia,</hi> your's in mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deſtie <hi>Flauia,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>See <hi>Tulley</hi> what an actiue paſſiue loue hath plaide,</l>
               <l>I loue, and am againe beloued, but at the ſhrine</l>
               <l>Where I doe offer vp my Cordiall ſacrifice,</l>
               <l>I am returnd with peremptorie ſcorne,</l>
               <l>And where I ſtand but as a gazer,</l>
               <l>Viewing all alike, I am purſude</l>
               <l>With violent paſſions a ſpeaking eye</l>
               <l>Bindes fauours, and now diſcouering lines,</l>
               <l>Thy counſell now deere friend, for at</l>
               <l>Thy direction ſtands my thrall or freedome.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Tul.</speaker>
               <l>Oh my Lord, affection is vnlimited,</l>
               <l>Daring all dangers, hauing nor tipe nor</l>
               <l>figure, but beyond all arte,</l>
               <l>Then tye not that (great Lord) to <hi>Tullies</hi> awe,</l>
               <l>Fancy forſweares all reaſon, loue all lawe.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Lent.</speaker>
               <l>How well thy power can ſhun, that which</l>
               <l>I followe with obedience, too true yfaith,</l>
               <l>Thou mightſt as well put out the eie of day,</l>
               <l>Or couer ſinne from heauen, or to erect</l>
               <l>A towre of ſand, on the vncertaine ſurge,</l>
               <l>Or any thing that were more inficient,</l>
               <l>Then to remooue one doting thought of mine</l>
               <l>From her diſdaine, thy aide deere <hi>Tulley.</hi>
               </l>
               <pb facs="tcp:20970:14"/>
               <l>Be thou an Orratour for <hi>Lentulus,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>My tongue ſtands tund to a harſher method,</l>
               <l>Breath in her eares thoſe Organs of receite,</l>
               <l>A quinteſſence diſtild of honny words,</l>
               <l>And charme with a beguiling lullabye,</l>
               <l>Her free conſent to thine and my requeſt.</l>
               <l>Which done, that's done, which is my ſole delight,</l>
               <l>Which done, that's done, that I can neuer quite.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Tull:</speaker>
               <l>All which to me are problematique mines,</l>
               <l>Obſcurde enigmaes, and to my ſtudies</l>
               <l>Incognite language: yet if my powers,</l>
               <l>Haue power to cloath my tongue in loue,</l>
               <l>Ile be a Louer, and in loue ſo pleade,</l>
               <l>As if that <hi>Tully</hi> loued Terentia.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Lent.</speaker>
               <l>Thankes ſweete <hi>Cicero,</hi> this day wee dine with olde <hi>Flamiuius,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>The forward Father of my Aukeward loue.</l>
               <l>His willing minde doth ſtriue to make the peace,</l>
               <l>Betwixt our diſcord thoughts: his free conſent</l>
               <l>Is giuen to <hi>Lentulus,</hi> there <hi>Tulley</hi> taketh on holde,</l>
               <l>And when a Sunne of thy intent ſhines fayre,</l>
               <l>On ſet loues fort, with polliticke aſſaults,</l>
               <l>And conquer conqueſt in obtaining that,</l>
               <l>Where victors are repulſt: but ſee,</l>
               <l>Our talke hath ouer-tane our way, ſee olde <hi>Flaminius</hi>
               </l>
               <l>Comes to welcome vs,</l>
               <l>With him a looke, looke the bright orient verge,</l>
               <l>At the vpriſing of Auroraes ſhine.</l>
            </sp>
            <stage>Enter Flaminius, Terentia and Flauia.</stage>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Flam.</speaker>
               <p>And my good Lord, y'are happily met.</p>
               <p>Heartily welcome: young Tullie welcome to, yee come wel to eaſe my charge, theſe Ladies finde fault with their Guardian, I goe too ſoftly for them: old blood is ſtiffe, &amp; young Ladies wil not beare with age: I reſigne, I reſigne to you that followe.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Lent.</speaker>
               <l>If they admit vs for their Guardian,</l>
               <pb facs="tcp:20970:14"/>
               <l>Weele dare dangers ere we part from them.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Flam.</speaker>
               <p>Why well ſaide my Lords, Soldiers will not flye indeede, I haue ſeene the day I could haue crackt a tree of yew, made my bowſtring, whiſper in mine care if they twang: toſt my pike luſtilye: tis ſince the ſiedge of Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thia, bith' mas a great while, I was luſtie then, at the ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uice was done there, yet I loue the diſcourſe: come my Lord, I chuſe your companye, leaue Tulley to the Ladies, he can tell them tales of <hi>Venus</hi> and <hi>Adonis,</hi> and that beſt pleaſeth them. Now I muſt heere of raps and blowes, and Bils and Guns, and ſwords and bucklers: I loued it once, come, our Cookes are backeward, diſcourſe will begette ſtomacks, y'are like to tarrie long for leane Cates.
<stage>Exit</stage>
               </p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Lent.</speaker>
               <l>Now gentle Tulley, aduocate my ſuite,</l>
               <l>Her fore-amazing perſon makes me mute.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Cicero.</speaker>
               <l>Ile beare theſe Ladies company,</l>
               <l>If they ſhall deeme acceptance.
<stage>Exit</stage>
               </l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Teren.</speaker>
               <p>With intereſt of thankes to Cicero,</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Flau:</speaker>
               <p>Faith I like not this ods of female, an equallitie were better: yet of both twere fitter the woman ſhould vndergoe the oddes, I had rather a ſaid three men to one woman, then two women to one man: heeres Tulley ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dreſt to Terentia, Terentia drawing neere to Tully: her's ſmal comfot left for <hi>Flaeuia,</hi> wel gentles, ile leaue ye to the Goddeſſe: ſo ho my Lords, take me with ye.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Teren.</speaker>
               <l>Nay, ſtay good Flauia,</l>
               <l>Youle not looſe the ſight of Lentulus.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Fla.</speaker>
               <p>Nor you of Tulley, come if you tel, ile blab.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Cice.</speaker>
               <p>But ſweete Lady, Tully is not heere.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Fla.</speaker>
               <p>But Cicero is, his nere friend, that's as good.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Cice.</speaker>
               <p>He was Lady, till hee changed his habit, by put<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting on the office of an vnskilfull Seruingman, intending to garde Terentia to her fathers houſe.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Fla.</speaker>
               <p>Then Flauia muſt gard her ſelfe: wel, vſe good words, and good action, and ſtalke well before your La<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>die, ſhee's kindey faith, and a litele thing will pleaſe her.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <pb facs="tcp:20970:15"/>
               <speaker>Terent.</speaker>
               <p>Will it pleaſe <hi>Flauia</hi> to partake?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Fla.</speaker>
               <p>Oh fye, twere an iniurie, I could brook my ſelf ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore, ile leaue ye, but be breefe, ſtand not on pointes, cut them all firſt, &amp; if ye fall to kiſſing, kiſſe not to long for feare ye kiſſe the poſt.
<stage>Exit</stage>
               </p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Teren.</speaker>
               <l>Goe to, youle ſtill be a wagge <hi>Flauia.</hi>
               </l>
               <l>But what ſaies <hi>Tulley</hi> to <hi>Terentia?</hi>
               </l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Cicero.</speaker>
               <l>Lady I muſt maintaine my former argument,</l>
               <l>Tullie's not heere, but heere is <hi>Tullies</hi> friend,</l>
               <l>For ere I ſpeake, I muſt intreate, you wil</l>
               <l>Transforme poore <hi>Tulley</hi> into <hi>Lentulus.</hi>
               </l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Teren.</speaker>
               <l>I haue no power of Metamorphoſing,</l>
               <l>If <hi>Tulley</hi> be not heere, you muſt conceale,</l>
               <l>I cannot make of <hi>Tulley Lentulus.</hi>
               </l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Cice.</speaker>
               <l>Nor can the world make <hi>Cicero</hi> ſo worthy,</l>
               <l>Yet for an houre diſcourſe a Peſants ſhape,</l>
               <l>Nay repreſent the perſon of a king.</l>
               <l>Then in the perſon of great <hi>Lentulus,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>I doe ſalute Sunne-bright <hi>Terentia,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>Lady, vouchſafe a Saint-like ſmile on him,</l>
               <l>From that angell forme, whoſe honord minde</l>
               <l>Lies proſtrate lowly at <hi>Terentias</hi> feete,</l>
               <l>Who hath put off a Golden victors honour,</l>
               <l>And left the Parthyan ſpoyle to <hi>Lepido,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>Whome many Ladies haue bedeckt with fauours,</l>
               <l>Of rich eſteeme, oh proud! he deignd to weare them,</l>
               <l>Yet guiftes and giuers hee did ſlight eſteeme.</l>
               <l>For why? the purpoſe of his thoughts were bent,</l>
               <l>To ſeeke the loue of faire <hi>Terentia.</hi>
               </l>
               <l>The choce is ſuch, as choiſer cannot bee,</l>
               <l>Euen with a nimble eye his vertues, through</l>
               <l>His ſmile is like the Meridian Sol,</l>
               <l>Diſcern'd a dauncing in the burbling brook:</l>
               <l>His frowne out-dares the Auſtereſt face,</l>
               <l>Of warre or Tyranny: to ſeaſe vpon</l>
               <l>His ſhape might force the Virgine huntreſſe</l>
               <pb facs="tcp:20970:15"/>
               <l>With him for euer liue a veſtall life,</l>
               <l>His minde is vertues ouer-matcht, yet this &amp; more</l>
               <l>Shall dye, if this and more want force,</l>
               <l>To winne the loue of faire <hi>Terentia,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>Then gentle Lady, giue a gentle dome,</l>
               <l>Neuer was breſt the Landlord to a heart,</l>
               <l>More louing, faithfull, or more loyall,</l>
               <l>Then is the breſt of noble.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Teren:</speaker>
               <p>Tullie.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Tul:</speaker>
               <p>
                  <hi>Lentulus!</hi>
               </p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Ter.</speaker>
               <p>And why not <hi>Tullie?</hi>
               </p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Tul.</speaker>
               <p>It ſtands not aptly.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Tere:</speaker>
               <p>It wants a ſillible.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Tul.</speaker>
               <p>It doth.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Tere.</speaker>
               <p>Then noble <hi>Cicero.</hi>
               </p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Tul:</speaker>
               <p>Thats too deere.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Tere.</speaker>
               <l>Gentle is as good,</l>
               <l>Then ſay the beſt of gentle <hi>Cicero.</hi>
               </l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Tul.</speaker>
               <l>Good Lady wrong not your honour ſo,</l>
               <l>To ſeate vnworthy <hi>Tulley</hi> with your worth,</l>
               <l>Oh looke vpon the worth of <hi>Lentulus,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>Let your faire hand be beame vnto the ballance,</l>
               <l>And with a ſtedded peyze, lift vp that beame,</l>
               <l>In on the ſcale, put the worth of <hi>Lentulus</hi>
               </l>
               <l>His ſtate, his honors, and his reuenewes,</l>
               <l>Againſt that heauy waite: put pouertie,</l>
               <l>The poore and naked name of <hi>Cicero,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>A partner of vnregarded Orators,</l>
               <l>Then ſhall you ſee with what celeritie,</l>
               <l>One title of his worth will ſoone pull vp,</l>
               <l>Poore <hi>Tullies</hi> dignitie.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Tere:</speaker>
               <l>Iuſt to the height of <hi>Terentias</hi> heart,</l>
               <l>Where I will keepe and Character that name,</l>
               <l>And to that name my heart ſhall adde that loue,</l>
               <l>That ſhall wey downe the worth of <hi>Lentulus.</hi>
               </l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Tul:</speaker>
               <p>Deare Madam.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <pb facs="tcp:20970:16"/>
               <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                  <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb facs="tcp:20970:16"/>
               <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                  <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb facs="tcp:20970:17"/>
               <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                  <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb facs="tcp:20970:17"/>
               <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                  <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb facs="tcp:20970:18"/>
               <speaker>Ter.</speaker>
               <l>Speake ſtill if thou wilt, but not for him,</l>
               <l>The more thou ſpeak'ſt, the more augments my loue,</l>
               <l>If that thou canſt adde more to infinite,</l>
               <l>The more thou ſpeakeſt, the more decreaſeth his,</l>
               <l>If thou canſt take away, ought from nothing,</l>
               <l>Thinke <hi>Tulley,</hi> if <hi>Lentulus</hi> can loue me,</l>
               <l>So much and more, <hi>Terentia</hi> doth loue thee.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Tull:</speaker>
               <l>Oh Madam!</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Tulley</hi> is poore, and poore is counted baſe.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Ter:</speaker>
               <p>Vertue is ritch and blots a poore diſgrace.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Tul.</speaker>
               <l>
                  <hi>Lentulus</hi> is great, his frowne's my woe,</l>
               <l>And of a friend he will become my foe.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Ter.</speaker>
               <l>As he is friend, we will intreate his loue,</l>
               <l>As he is great, his threatnings ſhall not make me loue.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Tul.</speaker>
               <p>Your fathers graunt, makes <hi>Lentulus</hi> your Lord,</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Teren.</speaker>
               <l>But if thereto his daughter not accord,</l>
               <l>That graunt is cancel'd, fathers may commaund,</l>
               <l>Life before loue, for life to true loue's paund.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Tul:</speaker>
               <p>How will <hi>Flaminius</hi> brooke my pouertie?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Ter.</speaker>
               <l>VVell, when <hi>Flaminius</hi> ſee's no remedie,</l>
               <l>Lord how woman like are men, when they are woe'd?</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Tully,</hi> weigh me not light, nere did immodeſt bluſh</l>
               <l>Colour theſe cheekes, but ardent.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Tul:</speaker>
               <p>Silence ſweete Lady, heere comes Flauia.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Fla.</speaker>
               <p>Fie, fie, how teadious ye are: yonders great loo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king for <hi>Tulley,</hi> the olde Senate has put on his ſpectacles, and <hi>Lentulus</hi> and hee are turning the leaues of a dog-hay, leaues of a worme eaten Chronicle, and they want <hi>Tullies</hi> iudgement.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Tul:</speaker>
               <p>About what ſweete Lady?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Fla:</speaker>
               <p>To know what yeare it was the ſhowers of raine fell in Aprill:</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Tul:</speaker>
               <p>I can reſolue it by rote Lady, twas that yeare the Cuckoo ſung in May: another token Lady, there raigned in Rome a great Tyrant that yere, and many Maides loſt their heads for vſing fleſh on Fiſh daies.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <pb facs="tcp:20970:18"/>
               <speaker>Fl.</speaker>
               <p>And ſome were ſacrificed as a burnt offering to the Gods of Hoſpitallitie, were they not?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Tul.</speaker>
               <p>Y'are a wag <hi>Flauia,</hi> but talk and you, muſt needes haue a parting blowe.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Flau.</speaker>
               <p>No matter ſo we ſtand out and cloſe not.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Tull:</speaker>
               <p>Or part faire at the cloſe and too 't againe.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Flau:</speaker>
               <p>Nay, if we ſhould too 't againe <hi>Terentia</hi> would growe iealous.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Tul.</speaker>
               <l>Ladies, I take my leaue,</l>
               <l>And my loue.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Ter.</speaker>
               <p>Take heede ye ſigh not, nor looke red at the ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble Tully.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Flau.</speaker>
               <p>Your ſhoe wrings you Lady.
<stage>Exit.</stage>
               </p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Ter.</speaker>
               <p>Go to, ye are a wanton <hi>Flauia.</hi>
               </p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Fla.</speaker>
               <l>How now <hi>Terentia,</hi> in your nine Muſes?</l>
               <l>There's none muſt pleade in your caſe but an Orator.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Ter.</speaker>
               <p>I want one indeede Wench, but thou haſt two, and the gentle deſtinies may ſend thee three, nere bluſh: for ſmoke and the fire of a womans loue cannot bee hid. oh a fine tongue, dipt in <hi>Helicon,</hi> a comedian tongue is the onely perſwaſiue ornament to win a Lady, why his diſcourſe is as pleaſant—</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Fla:</speaker>
               <p>As how I prethee?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Ter.</speaker>
               <p>And keepes as good decorum; his prologue with obedience to the skirt, a rough Sceane of ciuill Warres, with a clapping concluſion, perhappes a Iigge, if not the Tragicomicall Tale of <hi>Mars</hi> and <hi>Venus,</hi> then muſt ſhee take the Tale by the end, where hee defending <hi>Mars,</hi> &amp; ſhe <hi>Venus,</hi> muſt fall from billing to byting, from byting to blowes, to get the ſupremacie.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Fla:</speaker>
               <l>A good policie to praiſe <hi>Cicero,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>For feare I rob you of your <hi>Lentulus.</hi>
               </l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Ter.</speaker>
               <p>Faith a Souldier is not for thy humor, now I crie a Warrier, he fights ſtoutlye in a field bed, diſcharges his worke ſure, vnder his Curtaines would I fight, but come, our Louers melt while wee meditate; thou for thy
<pb facs="tcp:20970:19"/> ſcholler, I for my fouldier: and if we cannot pleaſe them ſo, weele ſhake off this looſe habit, and turne Pages to pleaſe their humors.
<stage>Exeunt.</stage>
               </p>
            </sp>
            <stage>Enter Accutus and Graccus.</stage>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Grac.</speaker>
               <p>Come <hi>Accutus,</hi> diſcharge your follower let's leaue rubbing a while, ſince the by as runs ſo much the wrong way: Sirra, theſe bowles which we roule and turn in our lower ſpher, are by vſe made wodden worldlings right for euery one ſtriues who ſhal lye neereſt the miſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ris.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Ac.</speaker>
               <p>They poſt indeed, as their nature is, in an euen way, but they are cowards, theile abide no danger, they rub at euerie mole-hil, and if they tyre in going vp a hill, they retire and come backe againe.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Grac.</speaker>
               <p>Well, let them alley, bet all, then to reſt, away, begone.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Scil.</speaker>
               <p>S foote <hi>Graccus,</hi> heeres a couple of our old gam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſters, oh for quicke conceite to beget a ieſt: here's two that either a man muſt be acquainted or quarrell with, &amp; of two euils ile choſe the latter, I hope to make it the leſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſer: if I ſhould be acquainted, the foole will haunt me: if I quarrell, I may be ſo bleſt as to be rid of a foole.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Grae.</speaker>
               <p>I haue a womans wit for a ſuddaine ſtratageme.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Scil:</speaker>
               <p>No by my troth, by this bright horriſon—</p>
            </sp>
            <stage>Enter Scil. and Sernulus.</stage>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Accut.</speaker>
               <p>An excellent Cuckoo, hee keepes his note in Winter.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Scil.</speaker>
               <p>I haue no appetite at all to liue in the countrie any more: now as they ſay, I haue got a ſmacke on the Cittie, ſlid I thinke (as the prouerbe goes) I was wrapt in my mothers mocke the day I was begotten, I thanke the Goddeſſe <hi>Cupid</hi> for it, I am ſo fauourd of the Women, my hoſtes loues me execrably.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Accut:</speaker>
               <p>Good reaſon, fooles make good ſport.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Grac:</speaker>
               <p>Seuer, ſeuer, ere wee bee diſcouered.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Ser.</speaker>
               <p>Sir, the reſpectiue regard of your well gouerned partes do challenge a mellifluous ſpecies of enduement,
<pb facs="tcp:20970:19"/> or contumelious eſtimation.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Grac:</speaker>
               <p>Gentles, God ſaue ye, well ouer-taken Gal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lants.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Scil.</speaker>
               <p>Welcome by the welkin.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Grac.</speaker>
               <p>Tis a verie pleaſant weather.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Ser.</speaker>
               <p>Sir, the ayre is frugall.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Grac.</speaker>
               <p>Is that Gentleman of your Company?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Scil.</speaker>
               <p>Our company ſir, no, we are no companions for lame Souldiers.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Grac.</speaker>
               <p>Propper man, pittie he is ſo regardles: a good legge, it ſeemes he has ſome greefe in it.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Scil.</speaker>
               <p>Nay, and he be lame ile talke to him, there's ſo many luſtie knaues walkes now a daies, will not ſticke to giue a man hard words, if he be not diſpoſed to charitie: harke ye ſir, I vnderſtand ye are a propper man, and that you haue a good legge.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Accut.</speaker>
               <p>And what of that Sir?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Scil.</speaker>
               <p>What of that? ſlid he anſweres me like a ſturdy beggar alreadie: by the fiue elements or ſences; I aske ye for no hurt, ide beſtowe my charitie as franke as—</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Acut.</speaker>
               <p>Stoope and looke out, zoundes a Gentleman cannot come by a misfortune in ſeruice or ſo, but eue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie foole wil ride him take that—
<stage>Exit.</stage>
               </p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Gra.</speaker>
               <p>Sirra, ſtay, ile combat thee in his defence.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Seru.</speaker>
               <p>Sir, be pacificall, the impotent muſt bee lightly regarded.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Grac.</speaker>
               <p>Giue mee leaue Gentlemen, ile follow him.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Scil.</speaker>
               <p>Nay, I pray you be malco<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tented, I haue no great hurt: but in reuenge hee's a raſcall for vſing mee ſo, hee may thank God, diſcretion gouerned me, tis wel known I haue alwaies bene a man of peace, ile not ſtrike yee the leaſt mouſe in anger, nor hurt the pooreſt Conney that goes in the ſtreet, for I know of fighting comes quarrel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling, of quarrelling comes brawling, and of brawling growes hard words, and as the learned <hi>puerelis</hi> writes, tis good ſleeping in a whole skin.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <pb facs="tcp:20970:20"/>
               <speaker>Grac.</speaker>
               <p>Sir, your diſcretion ſhall gouerne me at this time, your name I pray ye ſir?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Scil.</speaker>
               <p>My name is ſignior <hi>Scillicet.</hi>
               </p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Grac.</speaker>
               <p>Euen ſo ſir? nay ſir, I doe not forget your Argu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment.</p>
            </sp>
            <stage>Enter Accutus.</stage>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Acut;</speaker>
               <p>Saue ye ſir, ſaw you not a Gentleman come this way euen now, ſomewhat hurt in the one of his Legges?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Scil.</speaker>
               <p>He went by euen now ſir, is he a friend of yours?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Acu.</speaker>
               <p>A deare friend, and a propper Gentleman ſir.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Scil.</speaker>
               <p>By the horiſon hee's a propper man indeede, he gaue me the time of the day, as hee went by: I haue a gal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lon of wine for him at any time, If ye ſee any thing in me worth commendations, I pray ye commend me to him.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Acut.</speaker>
               <p>I will ſir, twere beſt you gaue me good words, but ile trie ye farther yet, fare ye well ſir.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Scil.</speaker>
               <p>I pray you remember me to him, you ſee my an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger is ouer already.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Grac.</speaker>
               <p>Sir, I did not note ye, what fellow was that?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Scil.</speaker>
               <p>Sir, hee's a friend of his, that ſtrooke mee euen now.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Grac.</speaker>
               <p>Would ye not ſtrike him? lets followe.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Scil.</speaker>
               <p>Indeede ye ſhall not, I hate it.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Ser.</speaker>
               <p>I will not be barren of my armorie, in my future perambulation for the lower element.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Grac.</speaker>
               <p>You are to patient in wrongs ſir, Zoundes I know not how to picke a quarrell.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Serr.</speaker>
               <p>Sir, the grieuous youth is inwardlye poſſeſt with a ſupple ſpirit, hee can brooke impugnying, but tis aduerſe to my ſpirit if I were armed.</p>
            </sp>
            <stage>Enter Accutus.</stage>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Accut.</speaker>
               <p>Saue ye gallants, ſawe ye not a fellowe come halting this way of late?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <pb facs="tcp:20970:20"/>
               <speaker>Scil:</speaker>
               <p>Hath he done any hurt, or is hee a friend of yours?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Accut.</speaker>
               <p>Hee's a Raſcall, and ile maintaine him ſo.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Scil:</speaker>
               <p>Hee's a verie Raſcall indeede, and hee vſed mee like a knaue: if ere I meete him I ſhall hardly put it vp, I haue it in blacke and blew to ſhew heere.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Serr,</speaker>
               <p>Say I breath defyance to his front.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Acut:</speaker>
               <p>Challenge him the field.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Scil:</speaker>
               <p>Dooſt thinke heele anſwere me? ile challenge him at the pich-forke, or the Flaile, or ile wraſtle a fall with him for a bloody noſe, anye weapon I haue bene brought vp in, ile—</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Accut:</speaker>
               <p>What will ye? heere he is, you minime that will be friend with friends, and foe with foes, and you that will defie <hi>Hercules,</hi> and out-braue <hi>Mars,</hi> and feares not the Deuill, paſſe bladder, ile make ye ſwell.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Scil:</speaker>
               <p>By Gods-lid if I had knowne it had bene you, I would not haue ſaide ſo to your face.
<stage>Exeunt</stage>
               </p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Accut:</speaker>
               <p>Away with your Champion, goe.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Grac.</speaker>
               <p>This was excellentlye performd, ifaith a better breathing then a game at bowles.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Accut.</speaker>
               <p>Theile giue you the good ſalue any time this month, for I am ſure they haue ſaluing enough for ſo long.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Grac:</speaker>
               <p>I pittie the foole yfaith, but the tother Horſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leach, I wiſh his blowes trebled: I conuerſt with him, but a Rogue ſo ſtuft with a lybrary of new minited words, ſo tearing the ſence, I neuer met with.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Accut.</speaker>
               <p>But now we haue ſpoilde our determinate dinner at my hoſteſſe of the Hobbye, we ſhall nowe bee knowne.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Grac:</speaker>
               <p>That holds well ſtill, I am taken for a prooued friend, and thou ſhalt be diſguiſed till I haue wrought a league by vertue of a pottle of Canarie.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Acut:</speaker>
               <p>Content, mine Hoſt ſhall be acceſſarie, and ile be a ſeruiter to obſerue myracles.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <pb facs="tcp:20970:21"/>
               <speaker>Gra.</speaker>
               <p>They are good ſubiects for idle houres: but ſoft what ſecond courſe is entring heere?</p>
            </sp>
            <stage>Enter Phy. Bos and Boy.</stage>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Phy.</speaker>
               <p>For I did but kiſſe her: Bos, how lik'ſt thou my reliſh?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Bos.</speaker>
               <p>Oh Sir, reliſh but your licour as you doe your ſong, you may goe drunke to bed any day in the weeke.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Phy.</speaker>
               <p>Siſter awake, cloſe not, &amp;c. does my face hold co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lour ſtill?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Bos</speaker>
               <p>I, and you would but ſcauiage the pauilion of your noſe.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Gra.</speaker>
               <p>I marrie <hi>Accutus</hi> how likſt thou this Gentlewo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man Gallant?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Accut.</speaker>
               <p>A good ſtateſ man, for common wealth of Browniſts, the Rogue hates a Church like a Counter?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Gra.</speaker>
               <p>I, and if my Ladie Argentile were dead, he wold rather liue vppon almes then fall to worke,</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Accut.</speaker>
               <l>So: he might haue tolleration,</l>
               <l>What, ſhal's cloſe with them?</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Gra.</speaker>
               <p>In any caſe, but in ſome milde imbrace, for if we ſhould continue thus rough, we ſhould be ſhund like an Appoplex.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Accut.</speaker>
               <p>Gallants, the fortune of the day runs with ye, what all at <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> chance? how iſt? how iſt?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Phy.</speaker>
               <p>Sir, I think twas you beſtowd ſome abuſe of me tother day.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Accu.</speaker>
               <p>Which I would wipe out of your memorie with ſatisfaction of a double curteſie.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Phy.</speaker>
               <p>I accept it yfaith ſir, I am not prone to anger, I aſſiſte ye the following night knewe not my anger: your acquaintance Signior.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Gra.</speaker>
               <p>Fye, without ceremony; lets yoake this triplicity as we did in the daies of olde, with mirth and melody.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Phy.</speaker>
               <p>I, ſay you ſo? then Coll her and clip her, &amp; kiſſe
<pb facs="tcp:20970:21"/> her too, &amp;c.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Bos</speaker>
               <p>The triplicitie, heere's thoſe has ſup: at an ordina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Accu.</speaker>
               <p>This gallant humors.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Gra.</speaker>
               <p>But the other walkes a looſe.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Bos</speaker>
               <p>The triplicitie, heere's thoſe has crackt Glaſſes, &amp; drawne blood of a Tapſter.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Gra.</speaker>
               <p>The viſitation of your hand ſir.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Bos</speaker>
               <p>The Triplicitie, will colours change?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Acut:</speaker>
               <p>Sir, take no offence I beſeech ye, we gaue onelye ſatisfaction for an olde iniurie, but in the degree of ami<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie your ſelfe ſits in the ſuperlatiue.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Bos</speaker>
               <p>Not ſo ſir, but in reſpect.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Gra.</speaker>
               <p>What kinde is your Dogge of Sir?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Bos:</speaker>
               <p>Verie kinde to any thing but his meate, that hee deuours with great alacritie.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Grac.</speaker>
               <p>Where was he bred?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Bos</speaker>
               <p>In a Bitch.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Gra.</speaker>
               <p>What countrie?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Bos</speaker>
               <p>A kinde of Mungrill, he will carrie, but not fetch, marrie hee is to be put to a dauncing ſchoole for inſtructi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Acut.</speaker>
               <p>The tricke of the rope were excellent in him, &amp; that ile teach him if I miſſe not my mark: come Gallants, we waſte time, the firſt Tauerne wee ariue at, weele ſee the race of an houre-glaſſe.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Phy.</speaker>
               <p>Can ye a part in a Song?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Gra.</speaker>
               <p>Verie tollerably.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Phy.</speaker>
               <p>Weele haue a catch then, if with ſol, ſol, la: Gen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tlemen, haue you any good herbe? you haue match boy,</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Boy:</speaker>
               <p>Your pipe ſhall want no fire ſir.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Acut:</speaker>
               <p>Oh without ceremony: now <hi>Graccus,</hi> if we can but pawne their ſences in Sacke and Sugar, let mee alone to purſue the ſequell.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Gra.</speaker>
               <p>Follow it, away.
<stage>Exeunt.</stage>
               </p>
            </sp>
            <stage>
               <pb facs="tcp:20970:22"/>
               <hi>Enter Hoſtis, Cittizens wife, Scruulus and Scillicet.</hi>
            </stage>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Hoſtis:</speaker>
               <p>Come, come, bring them out of the ayre: alas good hearts, what rogorous villaine would commit with him? ile tell ye Goſip, hee's eene as kinde an animall, he would not wrong them yfaith.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Citty wife.</speaker>
               <p>Tuſh, feare nothing woman, I hope to make him ſo againe: alacke, alacke, how fell you out, all at head? oh Butcher! are ye hurt in another place?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Hoſtis:</speaker>
               <p>Did he not throw you againſt the ſtones?</p>
               <p>If he did, doe not conceale, I dare ſay you gaue them not a foule word.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Scil.</speaker>
               <p>By the illuminate welkin not a word till my mouth was full of blood, and ſo made my words foule.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Citty wife.</speaker>
               <p>Is not this Gentleman hurt to?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Serr:</speaker>
               <p>Onelye the extrauagant Artire of my arme is bruſed.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Cittie wi:</speaker>
               <p>See, ſee, the extrauagant of his arme is bru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed to, alas how could ye quarrell ſo?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Serr:</speaker>
               <p>I will demonſtrate, in defence of the generous youth, I did appugne, my aduerſe let violently flie.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Citty wife:</speaker>
               <p>Ah good hearts! would I had ſtood betwen you when he let flie ſo violently.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Ser:</speaker>
               <p>We voide of hoſtile armes.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Hoſtis</speaker>
               <p>I, if they had had horſes, they had ſau'd their armes.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Serr:</speaker>
               <p>Be capable, I meane, voide of armorie.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Citty wife:</speaker>
               <p>Vntill ye had had armor on.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Serr:</speaker>
               <p>Had I bene accompained with my Toledo, or morglay—</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Cittie wife:</speaker>
               <p>I, your Dogge or Bitch:</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Serr:</speaker>
               <p>Continue I beſeech, I meane my ſword, ſole lye my ſword:</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Cittie wife:</speaker>
               <p>Or ſolely your ſword, better a bad toole then none at all.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <pb facs="tcp:20970:22"/>
               <speaker>Serr.</speaker>
               <p>In the concourſe.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Cittie w.</speaker>
               <p>Nay, the concourſe will light on him for it I warrant.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Serr.</speaker>
               <p>I, for the tuition of my Capitall, did mount my Semiſphere three degrees, that as a ſtrong &amp; ſtony guard did defend my Capitall.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Citty wi.</speaker>
               <p>Twas well yee kept him out, for if hee had entred on your ſtony Guard, he wold haue ſpoilde your Capitall.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Serr.</speaker>
               <p>In fine being mortally aſſaild, he did preambu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>late or walke off.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Scil:</speaker>
               <p>Yes faith, he did preambulate, and walke mee finely.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Cittie w</speaker>
               <p>Good heartes, how many were there of them?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Serr.</speaker>
               <p>About the number of ſeauen.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Scil.</speaker>
               <p>I there was ſeauen.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Serr.</speaker>
               <p>Or eight.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Scil.</speaker>
               <p>Or eight.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Serr.</speaker>
               <p>Rather more.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>City w.</speaker>
               <p>I more at leaſt I warrant ye.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Hoſtis.</speaker>
               <p>A laſſe ye cannot chuſe but be more hurt, but ile ſearch you throughly be aſſured.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Citty w:</speaker>
               <p>And if ſhe cannot helpe ye, fewe can, ſhee knowes what belongs to a Tent or a bruſe, and experi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence is good in thoſe caſes.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Serr.</speaker>
               <p>I haue a concupiſcent forme of truſt in your skil, it will malladiſe.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Citty wi.</speaker>
               <p>I feare not, put both your concupiſences in me for that matter.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Serr.</speaker>
               <p>The generous will diſburſe coynage for ſatis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>faction of your metaphiſicall endeuour.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Scil.</speaker>
               <p>Yes, yes, I will diſcharge all.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Cittie wife:</speaker>
               <p>Wee make no doubt of that, come into a chamber, ye ſhall lye downe a while, perhaps youle bee ſtiffe anon, then you ſhall vſe your legges, the more you ſtriue with it, the better, alas good hearts.
<stage>Exeunt</stage>
               </p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <pb facs="tcp:20970:23"/>
               <speaker>Phy.</speaker>
               <p>Sol, ſol, la, Tapſter, giue attendance Gentlemen, I hope all we are friends, the welkin is skie colour ſtill, and men muſt growe by degrees, you muſt pardon me, I muſt ſp—ſpeake my minde.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Grac:</speaker>
               <p>The vttermoſt of your minde at this time can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not be offenſiue.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Phy.</speaker>
               <p>The fryer was in the ſol, ſol, draw the tother quart, I hope you are not angrie gallants? and yee come to my lodging, ye ſhall be welcome, my Hoſtes ſhall bid you welcome: ſhee's a good wench, if I ſay the word, ſhe wil fa—full fill it.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Acut.</speaker>
               <p>Sirra drawer, for the other thats a ſleepe, let him ſo remaine: for the Dog let him be bound to a poſt for his appearance, till I take order for his vndooing.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Draw.</speaker>
               <p>The foole and the Dogge ſhall both take reſt at your commaund Sir.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Phy.</speaker>
               <p>Gentlemen, I hope we are all friends, ſol, ſol, ſhals haue a catch?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Grac:</speaker>
               <p>I, come come, euerie one catch a part.
<stage>Sing</stage>
               </p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Phy.</speaker>
               <p>Hey good boies ifaith, now a three mans ſong, or the olde downe a downe: well, things muſt be as they may, fils the other quart, muskadine with an egge is fine, theres a time for all things, <hi>bonos nocthus.</hi>
                  <stage>Sleepe</stage>
               </p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Grac.</speaker>
               <p>Good night to you ſir.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Accut.</speaker>
               <l>So, now <hi>Graccus</hi> ſee, what a polluted lumpe,</l>
               <l>A deformed <hi>Chaos</hi> of vnſteddy earth</l>
               <l>Man is, being in this ill kinde vnma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d, ſeeming ſomthing</l>
               <l>Beſtiall man, brutiſh animall: well tis thus decreede</l>
               <l>He ſhall be what he ſeemes, that's deade.</l>
               <l>For what in him ſhowes life, but a breathing ayre,</l>
               <l>Which by a free conſtraint it ſelfe ingenders</l>
               <l>In things without life: as twixt a paire of bellowes</l>
               <l>We feele a forcible aire, hauing of it ſelfe</l>
               <l>Force &amp; being, no more is this breathing block,</l>
               <l>But for his vſe in kinde: giue out in ſome burſſe or co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>gre<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>gation</l>
               <l>Among the multitude, <hi>Philantus</hi> death.</l>
               <l>Let all the cuſtomarie rights of funerall,</l>
               <pb facs="tcp:20970:23"/>
               <l>His knell or what elſe be ſolemnly obſerued,</l>
               <l>Ile take order for his winding ſheete:</l>
               <l>And further, to furniſh it with further ſuertie,</l>
               <l>Ile haue a potion, that for twentie houres,</l>
               <l>Shall quench the motion of his breath.</l>
               <l>Goe, ſpread, let me alone to effect it.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Gra.</speaker>
               <p>Ile ſow it I warrant thee, thou talkſt of burſſe, I haue away worth ten on't, ile firſt giue it out in my Barbers ſhop, then at my ordinarie, and that's as good as a broad: and as I croſſe Tiber, my waterman ſhall attach it, heele ſend it away with the tide, then let it come out to an Oy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter wenches eare, and ſheele crie it vp and downe the ſtreetes.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Acut:</speaker>
               <p>Let's firſt ſecure him from eyes, and at night he ſhall be portered to our chamber: ſo, now away.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Grac.</speaker>
               <p>Oh a couple that would ſpred earely, let's giue it for loues ſake.</p>
            </sp>
            <stage>Enter Hoſtis &amp; Citizens wife.</stage>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Acut:</speaker>
               <p>Call, call,</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Grac.</speaker>
               <p>Hem, hem.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Cittiy wife.</speaker>
               <p>A pox on your hemmings, doe you think we care for your hemmings,</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Hoſtis:</speaker>
               <p>Tis ſome ſtinking troubleſome knaue I war<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rant ye.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Citty wife:</speaker>
               <p>Hang him, regard him not, theres hem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ming indeede like a Cat, (God bleſſe vs) with a burre in her throate.
<stage>Exeunt</stage>
               </p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Grac.</speaker>
               <p>S'hart, how we are ript vp for this?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Ac.</speaker>
               <p>Oh man, this hemming is the moſt hatefulſt thing, there's not the moſte publique punck, nor worme-eaten bawd that can abide it, and honeſtie would runne madde to heare it, but come, wee waſt, time, tis now about the mid of day, we muſt ſowe arethmatike by the houres, that let the morrowes height <hi>Philantus</hi> awake againe, at which time hee ſhall bee on his Hearſe, and all the Gueſtes of the Hobbye inuited
<pb facs="tcp:20970:24"/> to accompany his ghoſt, when being awake himſelfe, and all ſhall ſee, if drunkenneſſe be not mad miſterie.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Grac.</speaker>
               <p>But I prethee practiſe ſome milder behauiour at the ordinarie, be not al madman.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Acut.</speaker>
               <p>Puſh, ile bee all obſeruatiue, and yet ifaith I grieue to ſee this double garded age, all ſide coate, all foole, fye, thou keepeſt the ſports from the marke, away, and retunre what newes is now in progreſſe.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Grac:</speaker>
               <p>I haue the neweſt, Terentia Daughter to the olde Senate, thogh Lentulus left the field to come to her, yet ſhe hath forſaken him in the open field, and ſhee's for our young Oratour Tully, ſhe has vowd by <hi>Venus</hi> legge, and the little God of Loue, he ſhal be her captaine, ſheele ſerue vnder him till death vs depart, and thereto I plight thee my troth.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Acut.</speaker>
               <l>More Ladies Terentias, I crie ſtill,</l>
               <l>That priſe a Saint before a Silken foole,</l>
               <l>She that loues true learning and pompe diſdaines,</l>
               <l>Treades on Tartarus, and Olimpus gaines.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Grac.</speaker>
               <p>I marrie, but then would learning be in colours proud, proud, then would not foure nobles purchaſe a benefice, two Sermons in a yeare.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Accut.</speaker>
               <l>I <hi>Graccus,</hi> now thou hitſt the finger right,</l>
               <l>Vpon the ſhoulder of Ingratitude:</l>
               <l>Thou haſt clapt an action of flat felony</l>
               <l>Now ill be tide that partiall iudgement,</l>
               <l>That doomes a farmers rich, adultus,</l>
               <l>to the ſupremacy of a Deanrie.</l>
               <l>When needie, yet true grounded Diſcipline,</l>
               <l>Is gouern'd with a threed bare Vycarage.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Grac.</speaker>
               <p>I, thou ſpeak'ſt well of their ſides that are libe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rally ouerſeene in the ſciences, I take no hold on't, but were all men of thy minde, then would euerie Schoole<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maiſter bee a Senate, and there would neuer come Cobler to be Conſtable againe.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Accut.</speaker>
               <l>Ynough, ynough <hi>Graccus,</hi> let ſilence ſeale vp</l>
               <l>Our ſecret thoughts, and libertie ſay,</l>
               <pb facs="tcp:20970:24"/>
               <l>
                  <hi>Virtus ſola ſumma gloria,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Quae format homines, vera honore.</hi>
                  <stage>Exeunt</stage>
               </l>
            </sp>
            <stage>Enter Flaminius and Tully.</stage>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Flam.</speaker>
               <p>Goe to I ſay, vrge no more, tis Tauerne talk, for Tauerners Table talke for all, the vomit of rumor: what newes ſaies one? none ſo new as this, <hi>Tully</hi> ſhall be mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ried to <hi>Terentia:</hi> what newes ſaies another? the ſame, the ſame, whoſe conſent haue ye? not mine, I deny it, I muſt knowe of it, ile haue a hand, goe to, no more.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Tul.</speaker>
               <l>Gentle ſir,</l>
               <l>Lay not that leaden loade of foule reproach,</l>
               <l>Vpon ſo weake a prop, what's done is paſt recall,</l>
               <l>If ought is done, vnfitting to be done,</l>
               <l>The worſt is done, my life muſt anſwere it.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Flam.</speaker>
               <p>I, you ſhall anſwere it in the Senate houſe, the Emperor ſhall knowe it: if ſhe be my childe, I will rule her, ile bridle her: ile curbe her: ile raine her, if ſhe will not, let her goe, ſtarue, begge. hang, drawe, ſinck, ſwimme ſhe gets not a do it, a deneire, ile not owne her.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Tul.</speaker>
               <p>Reuerend Sir be more patient.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Flam.</speaker>
               <p>I am impatient: I am troubled: I am vext: I am ſcoft: I am pointed at: ile not endure it: ile not abide it: ile be reuenged, I wil: of her: of you both: proud boy: wanton giglot, a ſpyring hautie, knowe your equals, ſhee's not for ye, if ye perſiſt, by my holy maker you ſhall an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwere it, looke to it, you ſhall, you ſhall indeede.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Tull.</speaker>
               <l>I ſhall, I muſt, I will, I will indeede,</l>
               <l>Euen to the greateſt I will anſwere it:</l>
               <l>If great mens eares be ope to innocency,</l>
               <l>If greatneſſe be not partiall with greatneſſe,</l>
               <l>Euen to the greateſt I will anſwere it,</l>
               <l>Perhaps ſome ſhallowe cenſurer will ſay,</l>
               <l>The Orator was proud, he would climbe too hie,</l>
               <l>But heauen and truth will ſay the contrarie.</l>
               <pb facs="tcp:20970:25"/>
               <l>My greateſt griefe is, I haue my friend betraide,</l>
               <l>The treaſon's done, I, and the Traitor's free,</l>
               <l>Yet innocent Treaſon needes not to flee,</l>
               <l>His loyaltie bids me abide his frowne,</l>
               <l>And he hath power to raiſe, or hurle me downe.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Tere.</speaker>
               <l>What ailes my Tully, wherefore look'ſt thou ſad?</l>
               <l>What diſcontent hath ſtopt the crimſon current</l>
               <l>Which ran ſo cheerefully within that brow,</l>
               <l>And makes it ſullen like a ſtanding poole?</l>
               <l>Tell me, who iſt hath wrong my <hi>Cicero?</hi>
               </l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Tul.</speaker>
               <p>Oh wrong him not.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Tere.</speaker>
               <l>Who is it then that wrongs my <hi>Tully</hi> ſo?</l>
               <l>What hath <hi>Terentia</hi> ought offended thee?</l>
               <l>Dooſt thou recall thy former promiſes?</l>
               <l>Doſt thou repent thee of—</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Tul.</speaker>
               <p>Oh wrong me not.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Tere.</speaker>
               <l>What hath my Father done this iniurie?</l>
               <l>There, there, thy thoughts accord to ſay tis ſo,</l>
               <l>I will deny him then, hee's not my father,</l>
               <l>Hee's not my friend will enuie <hi>Cicero.</hi>
               </l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Tul.</speaker>
               <p>Wrong not thy ſelfe.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Teren.</speaker>
               <l>What heauie ſtring dooſt thou deuide vpon?</l>
               <l>Wrong not him, wrong not me, wrong not thy ſelfe,</l>
               <l>Where didſt thou learne that dolefull mandrakes note,</l>
               <l>To kill the hearers? <hi>Tully,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>Canſt thou not indure a little danger for my loue?</l>
               <l>The fierie ſpleene of an angrie Father,</l>
               <l>Who like a ſtorme will ſoone conſume it ſelfe,</l>
               <l>I haue indurde a thouſand iarring houres,</l>
               <l>Since firſt he did miſtruſt my fancies aime:</l>
               <l>And will indure a thouſand thouſand more,</l>
               <l>If life or diſcord either liue ſo long.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Tul.</speaker>
               <l>The like will I for ſweete <hi>Terentia,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>Feare not, I haue approoued armour on,</l>
               <l>Will bide the brunt of popular reproach,</l>
               <l>Or whatſoeuer.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <pb facs="tcp:20970:25"/>
               <speaker>Ter.</speaker>
               <p>Enough Tully, we are diſcouered.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Fla.</speaker>
               <p>Ye faith, are ye at it? what is there neuer a louing teare ſhed on neither ſide? nor you? nor you? <hi>Tullies</hi> are red, come, come ye fooles, be more breefe, I would haue buried three husbands before youle be married.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Tul.</speaker>
               <p>Why liues <hi>Flauia</hi> a Virgin ſtill?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Fla:</speaker>
               <p>Becauſe I haue vow'd virginitie til I can get a huſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>band</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Teren.</speaker>
               <p>Why <hi>Flauia</hi> you haue many ſuitors.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Flau.</speaker>
               <p>Oh I am loaden with ſuitors: for indeede I am faine to beare with any of them, I haue a dumbe ſhewe of all their pictures, each has ſent in his ſeuerall ſhadow, and I ſweare I had rather haue them then the ſubſtance of any of them.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Tul.</speaker>
               <p>Can you not deſcribe them in action?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Flau.</speaker>
               <p>Yes, and their action: I haue one honeſt man of the age of fortie fiue or there about, that trauerſes his ground three mile euerie morning to ſpeake to mee, and when hee is come; after the ſaluting ceremony of how do you Lady, hee falles to calculating the natiuitie of the Moone, prognoſticating what faire weather will follow, if it either ſnow or raine, ſometime with a gentle pinche by the fingar, intermixed with the valley of ſighes: hee falles to diſcourſing of the priſe of peaſe, and that is as pleaſing to me as a ſtinking breath.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Tul.</speaker>
               <p>A good deſcription.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Fla.</speaker>
               <p>Another bringes Letters of commendation from the Conſtable of the Pariſh, or the Church<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>warden, of his good behauiour and bringing vp, how hee could write and reade written hand: further, deſiring that his Father would requeſt my Father that his Fathers Sonne might marrie my Fathers Daughter, and heele make her a ioynter of a hundred pound a yeare, and beget three or foure fooles to boote.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Teren.</speaker>
               <p>Better and better.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Flau.</speaker>
               <l>
                  <hi>Vſus promptus facit.</hi>
               </l>
               <pb facs="tcp:20970:26"/>
               <l>
                  <hi>Faemina ludificantur viros,</hi> well, forward,</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Tul.</speaker>
               <p>I haue another, that I priſe derer then the reſt, amoſt ſweete youth, and if the winde ſtand with him I can ſmell him halfe a mile ere hee come at me, indeede hee weares a Musk-cat, what call ye it about him?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Tul.</speaker>
               <p>What doe you call it?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Flau:</speaker>
               <p>What ye will, but hee ſmels better then burnt Roſemarie, as well as a perfuming pan, and euerie night after his firſt ſleepe, writes loueſicke ſonnets, rayling a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt left handed fortune his foe, that ſuffers his ſweete heart to frowne on him ſo.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Tul.</speaker>
               <p>Then it ſeemes you graunt him no fauour.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Flau:</speaker>
               <p>Faith I dare not venture on him for feare hee ſhould be rotten: giue me nature, not arte.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Tere.</speaker>
               <p>Here comes Lord <hi>Lentulus.</hi>
               </p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Tul.</speaker>
               <p>Swift danger now ride poaſte through this paſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſage, health to your honour.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Len.</speaker>
               <p>And happines to you.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Tul.</speaker>
               <p>Tis heauen deere Lord, but—</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Lent.</speaker>
               <p>Tuſh, tuſh, on earth, come, come, I know your ſuite, tis graunted ſure what ere it be.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Tul.</speaker>
               <p>My ſute craues death for treaſon to my friend.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Teren.</speaker>
               <l>The Traitor liues while I haue breath to ſpend,</l>
               <l>Then let me die to ſatisfie your will.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Lent.</speaker>
               <l>Neither yfaith, kneele not, riſe, riſe, I pray</l>
               <l>You both confeſſe you haue offended me.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Both.</speaker>
               <p>We doe, we haue.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Lent.</speaker>
               <l>Then for this offence, be this your doome,</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Tulley</hi> muſt die, but not till fates decree</l>
               <l>To cut your vitall threed, or Terentia</l>
               <l>Finde in her heart to be your Deatheſ-man?</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Flau.</speaker>
               <p>Faith the Fates may doe as they may, but <hi>Teren<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tia</hi> will neuer finde in her heart to kill him, ſheele firſt burie him quick.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Len.</speaker>
               <l>The like is doomde to faire <hi>Terentai,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>How ſay you both, are yee content?</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <pb facs="tcp:20970:26"/>
               <speaker>Tere.</speaker>
               <p>My thoughts are plung'd in admiration.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Tul.</speaker>
               <p>But can your honour burie ſuch a wrong?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Len.</speaker>
               <l>I can, I can, heere <hi>Tully,</hi> take <hi>Terentia,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>Liue many happie yeares in faithfull loue,</l>
               <l>This is no more then friendſhips lawes allow,</l>
               <l>Thinke me thy ſelfe another <hi>Cicero.</hi>
               </l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Flau:</speaker>
               <p>Twere better my Lord, you did perſwade her to think you another <hi>Cicero,</hi> ſo you might claim ſome inte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reſt in her now and then.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Lent.</speaker>
               <p>That I would claime with you, faire Ladie, hark in your eare, nay, I muſt conclude with you.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Flau:</speaker>
               <p>Y'oule not bite my Lord?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Len.</speaker>
               <p>No, of my faith my Lady.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Tere.</speaker>
               <l>Thus far my loue, our hopes haue good ſucceſſe,</l>
               <l>One ſtorme more paſt, my griefes were much the leſſe.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Tul.</speaker>
               <l>Friendſhip it ſelfe hath beene more prodigal,</l>
               <l>Then a bolde face could begge vpon a friend.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Lent.</speaker>
               <p>Why then, theres a bargaine.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Flau.</speaker>
               <l>Strike hands vpon the ſame, I am yours to commaund.</l>
               <l>Ile loue with ye, ile lie with ye, ile loue with all my heart,</l>
               <l>With all my ſtrength, with all my power and vertue:</l>
               <l>Seald and deliuered in the preſence of vs:</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Lent.</speaker>
               <l>
                  <hi>Marcus, Tullius,</hi> and <hi>Cicero.</hi>
               </l>
               <l>Then you deliuer this as your act and deede?</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Flau.</speaker>
               <p>I doe, and ſeale it with this—</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Lent.</speaker>
               <l>Why well ſaid, tis done, ſee, we begin but now,</l>
               <l>And are as ready to goe to Church as you:</l>
               <l>What needes further ceremony?</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Flau.</speaker>
               <p>Yes, a little matrimony.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Lent.</speaker>
               <l>I Lady, come <hi>Tully</hi> and <hi>Terentia,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>One day ſhall ſhine on both our Nuptialls,</l>
               <l>Feare not, ile quench the fire of your Fathers heate</l>
               <l>With my conſent.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Flau.</speaker>
               <p>I prethee appoint the time.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Lent.</speaker>
               <p>About a weeke hence loue.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <pb facs="tcp:20970:27"/>
               <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                  <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb facs="tcp:20970:27"/>
               <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                  <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb facs="tcp:20970:28"/>
               <speaker>Flau.</speaker>
               <p>Oh, tis too intollerable long.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Lent.</speaker>
               <p>Then foure daies.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Flau.</speaker>
               <p>Foure daies is foure times foure &amp; twenty hours that's too long too.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Lent.</speaker>
               <p>We cannot ſooner be readie:</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Flau.</speaker>
               <p>Yes and vnreadie too, in a day and a halfe.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Lent.</speaker>
               <p>Well then two daies.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Flau.</speaker>
               <p>Til then weele feede on conceite, <hi>Tully</hi> thanke me but for your companye, I would not tarrie ſo long: come Tully ſince wee ſhall bee married all at one time, weele goe to bed ſo, and he ſhall be maiſter of the Cock<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pit, that bids his Goſſips firſt.
<stage>Exeunt</stage>
               </p>
            </sp>
            <stage>Enter Acutus and Graccus.</stage>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Acut.</speaker>
               <p>Nay quicke Graccus, leaſt our houre fore-ſtall vs, ile in and deale for your diſguiſe, tarrie thou, &amp; giue mine hoſt a ſhare of our intent, marry charge him to keep it as ſecret as his Garbage. Hee vndoes our drift and cloathes the foole in ſack-cloath during his life.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Gra.</speaker>
               <p>Ile warrant thee ile manage it with as good iudgement as a Conſtable his charge.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Acut.</speaker>
               <p>And I mine as a watchman his office.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Gra.</speaker>
               <p>Better I hope: well about it.
<stage>Exit.</stage>
               </p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Hoſt.</speaker>
               <p>There, there, my little lackey boyes, giue the word as ye paſſe, look about to my gueſts there, ſcore vp at the Bar there; again, agen my fine Mercuries; if youle liue in the facultie, be rulde by inſtructions: you muſt bee eyed like a Serieant, an eare like a Belfounder, your con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcience a Schoolemaiſter, a knee like a Courtier: a foole like a Lackey, and a tongue like a Lawyere, away, away, my braue bullies: welcome ſweete Signior, I cannot bow to thy knee. I'me as ſtout &amp; as ſtiff as a new made knight, but if I ſay the word mine Hoſt bids the Cobler—</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Gra.</speaker>
               <p>May I craue a word of you mine Hoſt?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Hoſt.</speaker>
               <p>Thou ſhalt, whiſper in mine eare, I will ſee and ſay little, what I ſay, du<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s the mouſe &amp; welcom my bullies.</p>
            </sp>
            <stage>
               <pb facs="tcp:20970:28"/>
               <hi>Enter Scillicet and Getica.</hi>
            </stage>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Scil.</speaker>
               <p>By the torrid zone (ſweet heart) I haue thought well of you euer ſince I loued ye, as a man wold ſay (like a young dauncer out of all meaſure) if it pleaſe you y<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>faith, any thing I haue promiſed you, ile performe it to a haire, ere to morrow night.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Get.</speaker>
               <p>I wounder I can heare no newes of my man and my puppie.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Scil.</speaker>
               <p>Doe you thinke ſweet heart, to be maried by day light or by torch-light.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Get.</speaker>
               <p>By night is more Lady-like, ile haue a cryer to crie my puppie ſure.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Scil.</speaker>
               <p>What thinke ye if we had an offering?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Get.</speaker>
               <p>That were moſt baſe yfaith.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Scil.</speaker>
               <p>Baſe, ſlid I cannot tel, if it were as baſe as a ſag but ile be ſworne tis as common as a whore, tis euen as com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon to ſee a Baſon at the Church doore as a box at a Playhouſe.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Get.</speaker>
               <p>It greeues me not ſo much for my man, as for my puppie, my man can ſhift for himſelfe, but my poor pup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pie, truely I thinke I muſt take Phiſicke euen for feare ſweete heart.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Hoſt.</speaker>
               <p>Tut, tut, I warrant thee, ile be as cloſe as a bawd, ile keepe mine owne counſell, be merrie and cloſe, merrie hart liues long, let my gueſts take no wrong, &amp; welcome my bullie.
<stage>Exit.</stage>
               </p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Grac.</speaker>
               <p>Theres none ment beleeue it ſir.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Scil:</speaker>
               <p>Signior, by the welk in well met, what, all three ſo luckely?</p>
            </sp>
            <stage>Enter Seruulus.</stage>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Ser.</speaker>
               <l>Gallants, ſauing the Ceremonie,</l>
               <l>Stroke your haire vp and admire, for ſweare ſacke.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <pb facs="tcp:20970:29"/>
               <speaker>Scil.</speaker>
               <p>Forſweare Sacke, ſlid not for the ſpending of two farmes more, if they were come into my hands once,</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Ser.</speaker>
               <p>I ſay be aſtoniſht, and forſweare ſacke, for by the cumbuſtion influence of ſacke fiue men lye breathleſſe, ready to be folded in the terreſtiall element.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Grac:</speaker>
               <p>Fiue ſlaine with Sacke, iſt poſſible?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Ser.</speaker>
               <p>Theſe eyes are teſtators.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Scil.</speaker>
               <p>Nay then tis ſo.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Getica:</speaker>
               <p>Sir, you haue not heard of a puppie in your trauels.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Grac:</speaker>
               <p>No, indeed, Gentlewoman.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Ser.</speaker>
               <p>Fiue beleeue me Sir.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Acu:</speaker>
               <l>Fiue of one, oh deuil! what limme of him but a complete Villaine,</l>
               <l>A tongue prophaner then Idolatrie:</l>
               <l>His eye a Beacon, fixed in his place:</l>
               <l>Diſcouering illes, but hood winckt vnto grace,</l>
               <l>Her heart a neſt of vice, kept by the Deuill,</l>
               <l>His good is none at all, his all, is euill,</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Hoſtis;</speaker>
               <p>Oh the father, Gallants, yonders the moſt hard fauourd newes walkes the ſtreetes, ſeauen men goeing to their graues that dyed with drinking and biſſeling.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Acut.</speaker>
               <p>Good ſtill, nay, then I ſee the deuill has ſome power ouer a woman more then a man, ſeauen! t'wll bee more anon.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Get.</speaker>
               <p>Now I beſeech <hi>Bacchus</hi> my puppie has not ouer ſeene himſelfe.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Scil.</speaker>
               <p>This is verie ſtrange.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Hoſtis.</speaker>
               <p>And as true a report I aſſure you.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Cittie wife:</speaker>
               <p>Out al as, where's my Goſip? oh woman! haue you not heard the newes?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Hoſtis</speaker>
               <p>Yes, I haue heard on't.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Cittie wife.</speaker>
               <p>Oh woman, did your childes childe euer ſee the like, nine men to bee buried too day, that drunke healthes laſt night.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Acut:</speaker>
               <p>Better and better, goodnes neuer mends ſo faſt
<pb facs="tcp:20970:29"/> in the carrying: nine!</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Cittie wife.</speaker>
               <p>They ſay one is your gueſt <hi>Philantus,</hi>
               </p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Acut.</speaker>
               <p>And all I dare ſweare, whome ile reuiue againe</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Cittie wife</speaker>
               <p>Well, he was a propper man yfaith.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Hoſtis:</speaker>
               <p>I, and had good skill in prick-ſong, yet hee had a fault in his humor, as none are without (but Puritans:) he would ſweare like an Elephant, and ſtampe and ſtare (God bleſſe vs) like a play-houſe book-keeper, when the actors miſſe their entrance.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Scil.</speaker>
               <p>Nay harke ye ſir, I can brooke much iniurie, but not that, meddle with me, but not with my trade, ſhee is mine owne, ſhee's <hi>meus, tuus, ſuus,</hi> no mans elſe, I aſſure ye we are ſure together.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Grac.</speaker>
               <p>Sure ye are together ſir, but is your wife, your trade? you meane to liue vpon your wife then.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Acut.</speaker>
               <p>The foole has ſome wit though his money bee gone.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Grac.</speaker>
               <p>Sir, I hope ye are not offended, I aſſure ye would be loath to offend the leaſt haire of your <hi>caput, ſiſſiput,</hi> or <hi>occiput.</hi>
               </p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Scil.</speaker>
               <p>
                  <hi>Occiput:</hi> what meane you by <hi>occiput?</hi>
               </p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Grac.</speaker>
               <p>The former part of your head.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Scil.</speaker>
               <p>The former part of your head, why I hope I haue not an <hi>occiput,</hi> in the former part of my head, Signior <hi>Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nulus,</hi> what meanes be by it?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Serr.</speaker>
               <p>The ſignification of the word onely a mounts to this, the former part of your head.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Accut.</speaker>
               <p>The foole is iealious, prethee feede it.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Scil.</speaker>
               <p>S'lid I cannot be ſo ſuſsified, I pray you Signior what meanes he by <hi>occuput?</hi>
               </p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Grac:</speaker>
               <p>No hurt veriely, onely, the word ſignifies, and the reaſon is (ſaith <hi>Varro</hi>) being a great deriuer from originals it is called <hi>occiput,</hi> for that the former part of the head looks likeſt the Oxe.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Scil:</speaker>
               <p>Likeſt the Oxe, by gad, if ere I come to talke with that <hi>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>arro,</hi> ile make him ſhow a better reaſon for it.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <pb facs="tcp:20970:30"/>
               <speaker>Grac.</speaker>
               <p>But howſoeuer, it proceeded from me all in kindenes.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Scil:</speaker>
               <p>Sir, I accept it ſo, for I tell ye I am of a mollifying nature, I can ſtrut, and againe in kindneſſe, I can ſuffer a man to breake my head, and put it vp without anger.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Accut.</speaker>
               <p>I claime that priuiledge ſir, I thinke I offended you once that way.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Scil.</speaker>
               <p>I loue ye then for it ſir, yet I cannot remember that euer a Tapſter broke my head, yet I call to minde I haue broke many Tapſters heads.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Accut.</speaker>
               <p>Not as a Tapſter, for I but borrow this habyt.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Scil</speaker>
               <p>The fruite is knowne by the tree, by gad I knewe by your aporn ye were a gentleman, but ſpeciallye by your flat cap.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Serr.</speaker>
               <p>I call to memorie, let vs vnite with kinde im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brace.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Cittie wife.</speaker>
               <p>Now well fare your harts, by my truth tis ioy to a woman, to ſee men kinde, faith you courtiers are mad fellowes, you care not in your humors to ſtab man or woman that ſtandes in your way, but in the end your kindenes appeares.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Hoſtis.</speaker>
               <p>You can reſolue vs ſir, we hear of great reuels to be at Court ſhortly.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Grac.</speaker>
               <p>At the marriage of Lentulus, and the Orator: verie true.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Hoſtis</speaker>
               <p>Might not a company of Wiues be beholding to thee for places that would be there without their hus<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bands knowledge if neede were?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Grac.</speaker>
               <p>A moitie of friendſhip that, ile place ye where ye ſhall ſit and ſee all.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Cittie wife:</speaker>
               <p>Sit, nay if there were but good ſtandinges, we care not.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Acu:</speaker>
               <p>S'foot <hi>Graccus</hi> we tarrie too long I feare, the houre wil ouer take vs, tarrie thou and inuite the Gueſts, and Ile goe ſee his courſe mounted.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Grac.</speaker>
               <p>About it.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <pb facs="tcp:20970:30"/>
               <speaker>Hoſtis.</speaker>
               <p>Whether goes that Gentleman?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Grac.</speaker>
               <l>About a needefull trouble: this gentleman</l>
               <l>Hath at the charges of his charitie,</l>
               <l>Preparde to inter, a friend of his,</l>
               <l>Though lately entertaind a friend of yours.</l>
               <l>Acquaintance to you all, Philantus: and would deſire</l>
               <l>You would with him accompany his ghoſt</l>
               <l>To funerall, which will be preſently on his iourney.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Cittie wife.</speaker>
               <p>Of his charge, dyed he not able to purchaſe a Winding ſheete?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Grac.</speaker>
               <p>Twere ſinne to wrong the dead, you ſhal heare the inuentorie of his pocket.</p>
               <p>
                  <table>
                     <row>
                        <cell>Inprimis, A bruſh and a Combe.</cell>
                        <cell>o</cell>
                        <cell>o</cell>
                        <cell>v.d.</cell>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <cell>Item, a looking Glaſſe.</cell>
                        <cell>o</cell>
                        <cell>o</cell>
                        <cell>i.d.ob.</cell>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <cell>Item, A caſe of Tobacco Pipes.</cell>
                        <cell>o</cell>
                        <cell>o</cell>
                        <cell>iiij.d.</cell>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <cell>Item, Tobacco halfe an ounz.</cell>
                        <cell>o</cell>
                        <cell>o</cell>
                        <cell>vj.d</cell>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <cell>Item, in money and golde.</cell>
                        <cell>o</cell>
                        <cell>o</cell>
                        <cell>iij.d</cell>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <cell cols="4">
                           <hi>Summa totalis.</hi> xix.d. halfe penny.</cell>
                     </row>
                  </table>
               </p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Hoſtis.</speaker>
               <p>What was his ſuite worth?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Grac:</speaker>
               <p>His ſute was colde, becauſe not his owne, and the owner cauſed it to be reſtored as part of recompence, hauing loſt the principall.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Acut:</speaker>
               <p>What, are they readie: the Corſe is on his iour<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ney hetherwards.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Grac.</speaker>
               <p>Tuſh, two womens tungs giue as loud report as a campe royall of double cannons.</p>
            </sp>
            <stage>Enter Host, Cornutus.</stage>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Hoſt.</speaker>
               <p>Tut, tut, thou art welcom, Cornutus is my neigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bour, I loue him as my ſelfe, tha'ſt a ſhrowe to thy wife, gaue her tongue to much ſtring, but let mine Hoſt giue thee counſell, heele teach thee a remedie.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Cornu.</speaker>
               <p>No, no, my good Hoſt, mum, mum, no words a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt my wife, ſhee's mine owne, one fleſh &amp; one blood, I ſhall feele her hurt, her tongue is her owne, ſo are her hands, mum, mum, no words againſt your wife.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <pb facs="tcp:20970:31"/>
               <speaker>Hoſt.</speaker>
               <p>Tut, tut, thou art a foole, keepe her cloſe from the poticarie, let her taſte of no licoras, twill make her long winded: no plums, nor no parſeneps, no peares, nor no Popperins, ſheele dreame in her ſleepe then, let her liue vpon Haſels, giue her nuts for her dyet while a toothe's in her head: giue her cheeſe for diſgeſtion: twil make her ſhort winded, if that will not ſerue, ſet fire to the pan, and blow her vp with Gun-powder.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Cittie wife</speaker>
               <p>I, I, mine Hoſt, you are well imployed to giue a man counſell againſt his wife, they are apt enough to ill I warrant ye.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Cornu:</speaker>
               <p>Mum, mum, my ſweete wife, I know the world wel enough, I haue an eare, but I heare not: an eye, but I ſee not: whats ſpoake againſt thee, I regard not: mum, mum, I knowe the world well enough.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Cittie wife.</speaker>
               <p>I, and twere more ſeemely you were at your owne houſe too, your wife cannot goe abroad but you muſt follow, husbands muſt bee fringed to their wiues Petticoates, I pray you tarrie you, ile goe home.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Cor.</speaker>
               <p>Not ſo my ſweet wife, I am gone, I am vaniſht, mum, mum, no anger ſhall ſtirre thee, no words, I know the world well inough.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Hoſtis.</speaker>
               <p>Twere better by thrice deuce-ace in a weeke eue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry woman could awe her husband ſo well as ſhe.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Gracc.</speaker>
               <p>Iſt poſſible, sfoot well, I thought it had bene but a fable al this while, that <hi>Iole</hi> ſhold make great <hi>Hercules</hi> ſpit on his thombes, &amp; ſpin, but now I ſee, if a man were as great as <hi>Caeſar, Iulius,</hi> or <hi>Auguſtus,</hi> or both in one, a woman may take him downe.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Hoſtis</speaker>
               <p>Goſſip, faith ile vſe a little of your counſel, but my husband is ſo fat, I feare I ſhall neuer bring him to it.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Grac.</speaker>
               <p>Now gentles, you that can prepare a few teares to ſhed, for now enters a ſad ſceane of ſorrowe.</p>
            </sp>
            <stage>
               <pb facs="tcp:20970:31"/>
               <hi>Enter Fryer and courſe.</hi>
            </stage>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Fryer.</speaker>
               <l>Man is fleſh, and fleſh is fraile,</l>
               <l>The ſtrongeſt man at length muſt faile,</l>
               <l>Man is fleſh, and fleſh is graſſe,</l>
               <l>Conſuming time as in a glaſſe.</l>
               <l>Now is vp, and now is downe,</l>
               <l>And is not purchaſt by a Crowne.</l>
               <l>Now ſeede, and now we are ſowen,</l>
               <l>Now we wither, now are mowen,</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Frater noſter</hi> heere doth lye,</l>
               <l>In <hi>panpertate</hi> he did die.</l>
               <l>And now is gone his <hi>viam longam,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>That leades vnto his <hi>requiem aeternam</hi>
               </l>
               <l>But dying needie, poore and bare,</l>
               <l>Wanting to diſcharge the Fryer,</l>
               <l>Vnto his graue, hees like to paſſe,</l>
               <l>Hauing neither Dirge nor Maſſe.</l>
               <l>So ſet forward, let him goe,</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Et benedicamus Domino.</hi>
               </l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Phy.</speaker>
               <p>And then to <hi>Apollo,</hi> hollo trees, hollo, Tapſter a few more cloathes to my feete.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Omnes</speaker>
               <p>Oh heauens!</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Acut.</speaker>
               <p>Gentles, keep your places, feare nothing: in the name of God what art thou?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Phy.</speaker>
               <p>My Hearſe and winding ſheete: what meanes this? why Gentles I am a liuing man.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Acut:</speaker>
               <p>Spirit thou ly'ſt, thou deludeſt vs.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Citty wife:</speaker>
               <p>Coniure him Fryer.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Fryer.</speaker>
               <l>
                  <hi>In nomino Domini,</hi> I thee charge,</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Reſponde mihi</hi> heere at large.</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Cuium pecus</hi> whence thou art:</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Et quam obrem,</hi> thou makeſt vs ſtart,</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>In ſpiritus</hi> of the gloomy night?</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Qui Venis huc</hi> vs to affright</l>
               <pb facs="tcp:20970:32"/>
               <l>
                  <hi>Per trinitatem</hi> I there charge thee,</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Quid tu vis hic</hi> to tell to me.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Phy.</speaker>
               <p>Why gentles, I am a liuing man <hi>Philantus,</hi> what inſtance ſhall I giue ye? heare me, I haue ſight, vnderſta<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding, I know mine hoſtes, I ſee that Gentlewoman, I can feele.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Scil.</speaker>
               <p>Feele this Gentlewoman! s'ild if yee were ten Ghoſts, ile not indure it.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Acut.</speaker>
               <p>Spirit thou deludeſt vs.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Phy.</speaker>
               <p>Why, what ſhould I ſay? will ye hsare my voice, heres none but—</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Scil.</speaker>
               <p>Nay, thats a lye, then tis a liuing ſpirit, ile haue a<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>bout with him.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Accut.</speaker>
               <l>Oh ſir, meddle not with ſhadowes, ſpirit thou lyeſt,</l>
               <l>I ſaw thee dead, ſo did many moe:</l>
               <l>We know ye wandring dwellers in the dark,</l>
               <l>Haue power to ſhape you like mortallitie,</l>
               <l>To beguile the ſimple, &amp; deceue their ſoules,</l>
               <l>Thou art a Deuill.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Phy.</speaker>
               <p>Sweet Gent, beholde I am fleſh and blood, heres my fleſh feele it.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Cittie wife</speaker>
               <p>By my troth methinkes hee ſhould be aliue, I could finde in my heart to feele his fleſh.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Grac.</speaker>
               <p>Trie with your Rapier <hi>Accutus,</hi> if he bleede hee liues.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Phy.</speaker>
               <p>If I bleed I die, ſweet Gentlemen draw no blood.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Accu.</speaker>
               <p>How ſhall wee knowe thou art fleſh and blood then?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Grac:</speaker>
               <p>Take heede Accutus heele blaſt thee.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Phy.</speaker>
               <p>What inſtance ſhall I giue ye? I am Phylantus, he that muſt needes confeſſe he was drunk in your compa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nies laſt day, ſweet Gentlemen conceiue me aright.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Accut.</speaker>
               <l>Why true, true, that we know, and thoſe ſwil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling bowels,</l>
               <l>Death did arreſt thee, many ſaw thee deade,</l>
               <l>Elſe needles were theſe rites of funeralls,</l>
               <l>And ſince that time till now, no breath was knowne.</l>
               <pb facs="tcp:20970:32"/>
               <l>Flye from you: and twentie times the houre-glaſſe,</l>
               <l>Hath turnd his vpſide downe: and twenty times</l>
               <l>The nimble current ſand hath left his vpper roome,</l>
               <l>To ly beneath, ſince ſparke of life appeard,</l>
               <l>In all which time, my care imploide it ſelfe,</l>
               <l>To giue the rights of buriall: now if you liue,</l>
               <l>Who ſo glad as I?</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Phy.</speaker>
               <p>Sir, your loue hath ſhowne it ſelfe aboundant, but the colde aire is a meanes to deuorce me from your companies: mine hoſt let me craue paſſage to my cha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ber.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Hoſt:</speaker>
               <p>Out of my dores knaue, thou entereſt not my dores, I haue no chalke in my houſe, my poſts ſhal not be garded with a little ſing ſong, <hi>ſi nihil attuleris ibis Homere foras.</hi>
               </p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Accut.</speaker>
               <l>Ha, how now man? ſee'ſt now any errors?</l>
               <l>Nay, this is no thing: he hath but ſhowne</l>
               <l>A patterne in himſelfe, what thou ſhalt finde</l>
               <l>In others: ſearch through the Globe of earth</l>
               <l>If there mongſt twentie, two thou dooſt finde</l>
               <l>Honeſter then himſelfe, ile be buried ſtraight,</l>
               <l>Now thinke what ſhame tis to be vilde,</l>
               <l>And how vilde to be drunk: looke round, where?</l>
               <l>Nay looke vp, beholde you Chriſtall pallace,</l>
               <l>There ſits an vbiquitarie Iudge,</l>
               <l>From whome <hi>arcana nulla abſcondita.</hi>
               </l>
               <l>That ſee's all and at pleaſure puniſheth,</l>
               <l>Thou canſt not ſcape ſcot free, how canſt thou?</l>
               <l>Why ſenceleſſe man, in that, ſinne will betray</l>
               <l>His father, brother, nay, him himſelfe: feares not</l>
               <l>To commit the worſt of euils: ſecure, if</l>
               <l>Thunder boults ſhould drop from heauen, dreading</l>
               <l>Nor heauen nor hell: indeede hss beſt ſtate</l>
               <l>Is worſe then leaſt, priſed at higheſt rate.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Ser.</speaker>
               <p>This critique is hoarſh, vnſauerie, and reproofeful, avoyd him.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Scil.</speaker>
               <p>Hee ſpeakes well, but I like not his diſpray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing
<pb facs="tcp:20970:33"/> of drunkennes: tis Phiſicke to me, and it makes mee to ſleep like a good horſe, with my noſe in the maunger, come ſweete heart.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Hoſtis</speaker>
               <p>Signior Philantus I pray ye a word.
<stage>Exit</stage>
               </p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Acut.</speaker>
               <p>How now, whiſpering? s'foot if they ſhould giue our purpoſe another croſſe point, where are wee then? note, note.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Hoſtis,</speaker>
               <p>Heere take the key, conuey your ſelfe into the Chamber, but in any caſe take heede my husband ſee you not.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Phy.</speaker>
               <p>Feare not: gentles, be thanks the guerden of your loue, till time giue better abilitie,
<stage>Exit.</stage>
               </p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Acut:</speaker>
               <p>Ha! nay s'foot, I muſt claw out another deuice: we muſt not part ſo, <hi>Graccus</hi> prethee keepe the ſceane til I fetch more actors to fill it fuller.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Gra.</speaker>
               <p>But prethee let me partake.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Acut:</speaker>
               <p>Not till I returne, pardon me,
<stage>Exit</stage>
               </p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Hoſtis</speaker>
               <p>By my troth goſſip I am halfe ſicke of a conceit</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Cittiy wife.</speaker>
               <p>What woman? paſſion of my heart, tel me your greefe?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Hoſtis</speaker>
               <p>I ſhall goe to court now, and attired like an old Darie woman, a Ruffe, holland of eight groates, three in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches-deepe of the olde cut, and a hat as farre out of faſhion as a cloſe placket.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Cittie wife.</speaker>
               <p>Why I hope your husband is able to main<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine you better: are there not nights as well as daies? does he not ſleepe ſome times? has hee no pockets about him? cannot you ſearch his breeches? anye thing you finde in his breeches is your owne.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Hoſtis</speaker>
               <p>But may a woman doe that with ſafetie?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Cittie wife.</speaker>
               <p>I and more, why ſhould ſhee not? why what is his is yours, what's yours, your owne:</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Hoſtis</speaker>
               <p>The beſt hope I haue is, you knowe my Gueſt Miſtris <hi>Gettica,</hi> ſhe has pawnd her Iewels to me already, and this night I look for her Hood, and her tyer, or if the worſt chance, I knowe I can intreate her to weare my
<pb facs="tcp:20970:33"/> cloathes, and let me goe in her attire to Court.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Cittie wife.</speaker>
               <p>Or if all faile, you may hire a good ſuite at a Iewes: or at a broakers, tis a common thing and ſpeci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ally among the common ſort.</p>
            </sp>
            <stage>Enter Hoſt and Constable.</stage>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Hoſt.</speaker>
               <p>To ſearch through my houſe, I haue no Varlets no knaues, no ſtewd prunes, no ſhe fierie phagies, my Chambers are ſwept, my ſinkes are all ſcowred, the ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſt ſhal come in, the knaues ſhall go by, yet wil I maiſter Conſtable, goe ſearch through my houſe, I care not a ſheepes skin.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Conſt.</speaker>
               <p>We are compeld to doe it mine hoſt, a Gentlema<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> is robd laſt night, &amp; we are to ſearch euery priuy corner.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Hoſt.</speaker>
               <p>Mine hoſt is true Mettall, a man of reputation, a true Holefernes, he loues iuice of grapes, and welcom maiſter Conſtable.
<stage>Exit</stage>
               </p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Acut.</speaker>
               <p>
                  <hi>Graccus,</hi> how likſt thou this?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Grac.</speaker>
               <p>Excellent, for now muſt he needes fall into the Conſtables hands: and if he haue any grace, twil appear in his face, when he ſhall be carried through the ſtreete in a white ſheet twill be a good penance for his fault.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Hoſtis.</speaker>
               <p>Now fortune fauour that my husband find him not</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Cittie wife.</speaker>
               <p>Heele be horne mad, &amp; neuer able to indure it: why woman if he haue but as much man in him as a Maribone, heele take the burthen vppon his own necke, and neuer diſcouer you</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Hoſtis</speaker>
               <p>Alas heere they come, lets away Goſſip.
<stage>Exeunt.</stage>
               </p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Gra.</speaker>
               <p>Fortune my foe, why dooſt, &amp;c.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Acut:</speaker>
               <p>Oh fye, that's bitter, pre the goe comfort him.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Grac.</speaker>
               <p>Faith he ſhould be innocent by his garment: Sig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nior, I grieue for this, but if I can help, looke for it.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Phy.</speaker>
               <p>I thanke ye ſir.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Conſt.</speaker>
               <p>We muſt contaminate our office, pray regard vs as little as ye can.
<stage>Exit</stage>
               </p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Accut.</speaker>
               <p>Me thinkes this ſhold put him quite out of tune: now ſo, let him goe, now to mine Hoſt, theres he, and hee,
<pb facs="tcp:20970:34"/> and h<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>e, theres ſhee, and ſhe, ile haue about with all: &amp; critiques, honnys ſweeteſt, mixt with gal.
<stage>Exeunt</stage>
               </p>
            </sp>
            <stage>Enter Hoſt Cornutus.</stage>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Hoſt;</speaker>
               <p>Goe to, there's knaues in my houſe, I know of no Varlets, I haue an eye has his ſence, a braine that can reach, I haue bene cald Polititian, my wife is my wife, I am her top, i'me her head: if mine Hoſt ſay the word, the Mouſe ſhall be dun.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Corn.</speaker>
               <p>Not ſo my ſweet Hoſt, mum, mum, no words a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt your wife, he that meanes to liue quiet, to ſleep in cleane ſheetes, a Pillowe vnder his head, his dyet dreſt cteanely, mum, mum, no words againſt his wife.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Hoſt,</speaker>
               <p>Thar't a foole, thar't a foole, bee rulde by mine hoſt, ſhew thy ſelf a braue man of the true ſeede of Troy; a gallant Agamemnon, tha'ſt a ſhrew to thy wife, if ſhee croſſe thy braue humors, kicke thy heele at her huckle bone.</p>
            </sp>
            <stage>Enter Accutus.</stage>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Acut.</speaker>
               <p>Gentles, moſt happily encountred, how good hap hath turnd two labours into one, I was addreſt to both, and at once haue met both, ſure I muſt intreate that you muſt not deny.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Hoſt.</speaker>
               <p>Say on my ſweete bullie, mine Hoſt will attend thee, ſpeake roundly to the purpoſe and welcome my bullie.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Accut.</speaker>
               <p>Marrie thus: there are are great reuels &amp; ſhews preparde to beautifie the nuptials of Lentulus and Tully, in which the Cittizens haue the leaſt ſhare, now would but you and ſome others that I ſhall collect, ioyne hands with me in ſome queint ieſt,</p>
               <p>Our ſhew ſhall deſerue grace, and braue the reſt.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Hoſt.</speaker>
               <p>I haue thee braue ſpirit, tha'rt of the true ſeed of Troy, lets bee merrie and wiſe, merrie hearts liue long mine Hoſt, my braue Hoſt with his neighbor Cornutus ſhall bee two of the Maskers, and the Morrice ſhall bee daunc'd,</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <pb facs="tcp:20970:34"/>
               <speaker>Cor:</speaker>
               <p>Not ſo mine Hoſt, I dare not doe ſo, t'wil deſtem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per my wife, my houſe will be vnquiet, mum, mum, I know the world well enough.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Hoſt.</speaker>
               <p>Thou ſhalt goe ſaies mine Hoſt, merrie hearts liue long, welcome bully, mine Hoſt ſhall make one, ſo ſhal my Cornutus, for if I ſay the word the mouſe ſhall be dun.
<stage>Enter Bos with Porters.</stage>
               </p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Porters.</speaker>
               <p>Saue ye mine Hoſt, heeres a parcell of Corne was directed to be deliuered at your houſe.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Hoſt:</speaker>
               <p>What ware my little Atlas, what ware is it?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>2. <hi>Por:</hi>
               </speaker>
               <p>I know not, but i'me ſure tis as heauie as a horſe and—</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>1 <hi>Por:</hi>
               </speaker>
               <p>I thinke tis a barrel of oyle, for it ſpurg'd at my backe.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Bos</speaker>
               <p>It was oyle, for I drew the Tap.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Grac.</speaker>
               <p>What Bos, what makſt thou heere?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Acc:</speaker>
               <p>Oh <hi>charadeum ſoboles magnum bouis increm entum!</hi> Bos art there there?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Bos:</speaker>
               <p>As ſure as you are there Signior.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Grac:</speaker>
               <p>Bos, will ye not forſake your Cabbin?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Bos</speaker>
               <p>Oh ſir, he that has not a tilde houſe muſt bee glad of a thatcht houſe: may I craue a ſuite of you ſignior?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Grac:</speaker>
               <p>What ſuite Bos?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Bos</speaker>
               <p>What you pleaſe, beggers muſt not chuſe.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Accut.</speaker>
               <p>Bos is growne miſticall, hee's too dark.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Bos</speaker>
               <p>I ſpeake hebrew indeed like <hi>Adam</hi> and <hi>Eue,</hi> before they fel to ſpinning: not a rag.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Grac.</speaker>
               <p>What, naked Bos?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Bos</speaker>
               <p>As ye ſee, will ye heare my ſuite ſignior?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Gra:</speaker>
               <p>Drunk &amp; his cloathes ſtoln, what theef wold do it?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Bos:</speaker>
               <p>Any theefe ſir, but no true man.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Gra.</speaker>
               <p>Wel Bos, to obtaine a ſuite at my handes, and to doe ſome pennance for your fault, you ſhal here maintaine an argument in the defence of drunkennes: mine Hoſt ſhall heare it ile be your oppoment, <hi>Acutus</hi> moderator: wilt thou doe it.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Hoſt:</speaker>
               <p>A mad merrie prig, all good ſpirits, wilt thou doe it Bos?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <pb facs="tcp:20970:35"/>
               <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                  <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb facs="tcp:20970:35"/>
               <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                  <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb facs="tcp:20970:36"/>
               <speaker>Bos.</speaker>
               <p>Ile doo't.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Grac.</speaker>
               <p>Seate yee, heres my place, now <hi>Bos</hi> propound.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Bos.</speaker>
               <p>Drunkennes is a vertue.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Gra:</speaker>
               <p>Your proofe.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Bos.</speaker>
               <l>Good drinke is full of vertue,</l>
               <l>Now full of good drinke is drunke,</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Erge,</hi> to be drunke is to be vertuous.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Grac.</speaker>
               <l>I deny it, good drinke is full of vice,</l>
               <l>Drinke takes away the ſences,</l>
               <l>Man that is ſenceleſſe is vitious,</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Ergo,</hi> good drinke is full of vice.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Bos</speaker>
               <l>I deny it ſtill, good drinke makes good bloud,</l>
               <l>Good blood needes no Barber,</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Ergo,</hi> tis good to drinke good drinke.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Accu.</speaker>
               <p>Hee holdes ye hard <hi>Graccus.</hi>
               </p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Bos.</speaker>
               <p>Heeres ſtronger proofe, drunkenneſſe ingenders with two of the morrall vertues, and ſixe of the lyberall ſciences.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Gra.</speaker>
               <p>Let him prooue that and Ile yeeld.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Hoſt:</speaker>
               <p>A mad ſpirit yfaith.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Bos.</speaker>
               <p>A drunkard is valiant and lyberall, heele out-face <hi>Mars,</hi> braue <hi>Hercules,</hi> and feares not the Deuill, then for the moſt part hee's liberal, for heele giue all the cloathes off his backe, though hee weepe like a Widowe all the day following: nay, for the ſciences, hee's a good phiſitian hee vomits himſelfe rarelie, and will giue any man elſe a vomit that lookes on him (if hee haue not a verie good ſtomacke) perfect in Geomitrie, for he hanges in the aire by his owne conceite, and feeles no ground: and hee's all muſicall, the world turnes round with him, euerie face in the painted cloath ſhewes like a Fairie dauncing about him, and euerie ſpar in the houſe a minſtrell.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Grac:</speaker>
               <p>Good: forward.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Bos</speaker>
               <p>Then hee's a good Lawyer, for hees neuer with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out a <hi>fierie facies,</hi> &amp; the leaſte <hi>Capias</hi> will take his <hi>habeas Corpus:</hi> beſides, another point of a Lawyere, heele raile
<pb facs="tcp:20970:36"/> and raue againſt his deareſt friends, and make the world think they are enemies, when the next day theile laugh, bee fat and drunk together: and a rare Aſtronomer, for he has ſtarres twinckling in his eyes, in the darkeſt night, when a wiſe man diſcernes none in the firmanent, and will take great paines in the practiſe: for lay him on his backe in the open fields ouer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>night, and you ſhall be ſure to finde him there in the morning: haue I ſed well, or ſhall I giue you a ſtronger proofe? an honeſt man will be as good as his word: Signior Graccus is an honeſt man, <hi>Ergo</hi> I muſt haue a new ſuite.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Accu:</speaker>
               <p>The moderator concludes ſo, Graccus is ouerthrown ſo far as the damage of a ſuite, ſo away with him, come, our fire will out, ſtrip vs, mine Hoſt and you wee expect your compa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nies, we muſt craue abſence a while, better to furniſhe our pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſes: the time of the day to ye.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Hoſt.</speaker>
               <p>Farwel my good bullies, mine Hoſt has ſed &amp; the mouſe is dun.</p>
            </sp>
            <stage>Enter the dumb ſhew of the marriage, Lentulus, Tully, and the rest. Enter Hoſtis in Getticaes apparel, Getic. in hers, &amp; Miſtris Dama.</stage>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Hoſtis.</speaker>
               <p>Come Goſſip, by my troth I cannot keepe my hood in frame.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Cittie wife.</speaker>
               <p>Let me helpe ye woman.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Get.</speaker>
               <p>Sir, we ſhall be troubleſome to ye.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Gra:</speaker>
               <p>Oh vrge not that I pray ye.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Get.</speaker>
               <p>I pray yee what ſhowe will be heere to night? I haue ſeen the Babones already, the Cittie of new Niniuie, and <hi>Iulius Caeſar</hi> acted by the Mammets.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Grac.</speaker>
               <p>Oh gentlewoman, thoſe are ſhowes for thoſe places they are vſed in, marry here you muſt expect ſome rare deuice as <hi>Diana</hi> bathing her ſelfe, being diſcouered or occulated, by <hi>Acteon,</hi> he was tra<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>figured to a hart, &amp; werried to death with his own dogs.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Cit. w.</speaker>
               <p>Thats prettie in good truth, &amp; muſt <hi>Diana</hi> be naked?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Gra.</speaker>
               <p>Oh of neceſſitie, if it be that ſhow.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Hoſtis.</speaker>
               <p>And <hi>Acteon</hi> too? thats prettie ifaith.</p>
            </sp>
            <stage>Enter Caeſar, Lent. Tully, Teren, Flauia.</stage>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Caeſ.</speaker>
               <l>Now gallant Bridegroomes, and your louely Brides,</l>
               <l>That haue ingeminate, in endleſſe league,</l>
               <l>Your troth-plight hearts in your nuptial vowes,</l>
               <l>Tyed true loue knots, that nothing can diſolue,</l>
               <pb facs="tcp:20970:37"/>
               <l>Till death that meager purſeuant of Ioue,</l>
               <l>That Cancels all bonds: we are to clowdie,</l>
               <l>My ſpirit a typtoe nothing I could chid ſo much,</l>
               <l>As winged time that gins to free a paſſage,</l>
               <l>To his turrent glaſſe, and crops our day-light</l>
               <l>That miſtie night will ſummon vs to reſt,</l>
               <l>Before we feele the burthen of our ey-lids.</l>
               <l>The time is teadious, wants varietie,</l>
               <l>But that I may ſhew what delightfull raptures,</l>
               <l>Combats my ſoule, to ſee this vnion,</l>
               <l>And with what boundles ioy I doe imbrace it,</l>
               <l>We heere commaund all priſon gates flye ope,</l>
               <l>Freeing all priſoners, (traitors all except,</l>
               <l>That poore mens prayers may increaſe our daies,</l>
               <l>And writers circle ye with wreathes of bayes.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Grac.</speaker>
               <p>S'foot <hi>Accutus</hi> lets lay hold of this, to free our captiue.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Acu:</speaker>
               <p>Content; ile proſecute it.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Tul.</speaker>
               <l>Dreade ſoueraigne, heauen witneſſe with me,</l>
               <l>With what bended ſpirit I haue attainde</l>
               <l>This height of happineſſe: and how vnwillingly,</l>
               <l>Till heauens decree, <hi>Terentias</hi> loue, and your</l>
               <l>Faire conſents, did meet in one, to make</l>
               <l>Me Lord thereof: nor ſhall it adde one ſcruple,</l>
               <l>Of high thought to my lowly minde.</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Tully</hi> is <hi>Tully,</hi> parentage poore, the beſt,</l>
               <l>An Orator, but equall with the leaſt.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Lent.</speaker>
               <l>Oh no doubt <hi>Accutus,</hi> be the attempt,</l>
               <l>My perill, his royall promiſe is paſt</l>
               <l>In that behalfe: my ſoueraigne, this Gentlemans</l>
               <l>Requeſt, takes holde vpon your gatious promiſe,</l>
               <l>For the releaſement of a priſoner.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Caeſ.</speaker>
               <p>My promiſe is irreuocable, take it: but what is hee and the qualitie of his fault?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Acut:</speaker>
               <p>A gentleman, may it pleaſe your grace, his fault ſuſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, and moſt likely innocent.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Caeſ.</speaker>
               <l>He hath freedome, and I prethee let him be brought hither</l>
               <l>Perhaps in his preſence we ſhall win ſome ſmiles,</l>
               <l>For I haue noted oft in a ſimple braine</l>
               <l>(Only ſtriuing to excell it ſelfe)</l>
               <pb facs="tcp:20970:37"/>
               <l>Hath corrupted language that hath turnd</l>
               <l>To pleaſant laughter, in iuditious eares;</l>
               <l>Such may this prooue, for now me thinkes</l>
               <l>Each minute, wanting ſport doth feeme</l>
               <l>As long and teadious, as a feauer: but who doth knowe</l>
               <l>The true condition of this <hi>Accutus?</hi>
               </l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Tully:</speaker>
               <l>My Leige, of him ſomething my knowledge,</l>
               <l>Can diſcouer, his ſpirit is free as aire,</l>
               <l>His temper temperate, if ought's vneeuen,</l>
               <l>His ſpleene waies downe lenitie: but how</l>
               <l>Stird by reproofe, and then hee's bitter, and like</l>
               <l>His name, <hi>Acute,</hi> vice to him is a foule eye-ſore.</l>
               <l>And could he ſtifle it in bittereſt words, he would,</l>
               <l>And who ſo offends, to him is paralell,</l>
               <l>He will as ſoone reprooue the <hi>Caedar</hi> ſtate,</l>
               <l>As the lowe ſhrub.
<stage>Enter Acut. and Philant.</stage>
               </l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Phy.</speaker>
               <p>Nay good <hi>Accutus</hi> let me not enter the preſence:</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Accut.</speaker>
               <p>Oh ſir, I aſſure you your preſence wil be more accep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>table in the preſence at this time, then a farre ritcher preſent: May it pleaſe your maieſtie, this is the man.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Caeſ.</speaker>
               <p>Let him ſtand forward.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Cit. w.</speaker>
               <p>Alas we ſhal ſee nothing, would I were neere now hee ſtands forwards.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Cittie wife.</speaker>
               <p>What qualities hath he Accutus?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Accut.</speaker>
               <p>Few good ones (may it pleaſe you) he handles a comb wel, a bruſh better, and will drink Downe a Dutchman, &amp; has good skill in prickſong.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Hoſtis.</speaker>
               <p>I, ile be ſworne, he had when he was my Gueſt,</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Acut:</speaker>
               <p>Pleaſe it your Maieſtie to commaund him?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Caeſ.</speaker>
               <p>Oh, we can no otherwiſe ſo well be pleaſed.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Phy.</speaker>
               <p>I beſeech your Maieſtie, I cannot ſing.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Tul.</speaker>
               <p>Nay, your denyall will breed but greater expectation of your skill.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Acut.</speaker>
               <p>I, I, pleaſe it your grace to heare? now he begins.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Phy.</speaker>
               <p>My loue can ſing no other ſong, but ſtill complaines I did her. &amp;c. I beſeech your Maieſtie to let me goe.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Caeſ:</speaker>
               <p>With all our heart, <hi>Acutus</hi> giue him libertie.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Accut.</speaker>
               <p>Goe, and for voice ſake yee ſhall ſing Ballads in the ſuburbes, and if euer heereafter ye chance to purchaſe a ſuite by what your friends ſhal leaue ye, or the credit of your friend, be not drunk again, &amp; giue him hard words for his labour.
<stage>Exit</stage>
               </p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <pb facs="tcp:20970:38"/>
               <speaker>Caeſ:</speaker>
               <p>What, iſt effected Graccus?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Gra.</speaker>
               <p>I haue wrought the foole, <hi>Scilicet</hi> comes alone, &amp; his Lady keeps the women company.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Accu.</speaker>
               <p>Tuſh, weele haue a room ſcantly furniſht with lights that ſhall further it.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Caeſ:</speaker>
               <p>What ſound is that?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Acut:</speaker>
               <p>I, would ye ſo faine enter? ile further it: pleaſe it your Maieſtie to accept what is not worth acceptance? heere are a company to Gratulate theſe nuptials, haue prepard a ſhow, I feare not worth the ſight, if you ſhall deeme to giue them the beholding of it.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Caeſ.</speaker>
               <p>Elſe ſhould we wrong their kindnes much: <hi>Accutus,</hi> be it your care to giue them kindeſt welcome, we cannot recom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pence their loues without much beholdings.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Acut.</speaker>
               <p>Now for the cunning vizarding of them, &amp; tis done.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Hoſtis:</speaker>
               <p>Now we ſhall beholde the ſhowes.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Get</speaker>
               <p>
                  <hi>Acteon</hi> and his Dogs I pray Iupiter.</p>
               <stage>
                  <hi>Enter the maſke and the Song,</hi>
                  <l>Chaunt birds in euerie buſh</l>
                  <l>The Blackbird and the Thruſh</l>
                  <l>The chirping Nightingale.</l>
                  <l>The Mauis and Wagtaile,</l>
                  <l>The Linnet and the Larke</l>
                  <l>Oh how they begin, harke, harke!</l>
               </stage>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Scil:</speaker>
               <p>Sli'd there's one bird I doe not like her voice.</p>
            </sp>
            <stage>Sing againe &amp; Exeunt.</stage>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Hoſtis.</speaker>
               <p>By my troth me thought one ſhould be my huſband, I could euen diſcerne his voice thorough his vizard.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Cittie wife:</speaker>
               <p>And truely by his head one ſhould be mine.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Get:</speaker>
               <p>And ſurely by his eares one ſhould be my ſweet heart.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Caeſ.</speaker>
               <l>Accutus, you haue deſerued much of our loue,</l>
               <l>But might we not breake the law of ſport ſo farre,</l>
               <l>As to know to whome our thankes is due,</l>
               <l>By ſeeing them vnmaskt, and the reaſon of their habits?</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Acut:</speaker>
               <p>Moſt willingly my Soueraigne, ile cauſe their returne.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Hoſtis.</speaker>
               <p>Oh excellent! now we ſhal ſee them vnmaskt.
<stage>Exit</stage>
               </p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Get.</speaker>
               <p>In troth I had good hope the formoſt had bene Acteon when I ſaw his hornes.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Cit. wif.</speaker>
               <p>Sure the middlemoſt was my husband, ſee if he haue not a wen in his fore-head.</p>
            </sp>
            <stage>
               <pb facs="tcp:20970:38"/>
               <hi>Enter Maskers</hi>
            </stage>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Hoſt:</speaker>
               <p>God bleſſe thee noble Caeſar, &amp; all theſe braue bride<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>groomes with their fine little dy-doppers, that looke before they ſleep to throw away their maiden heads: I am hoſt of the Hobbie, Cornut is my neighbour, but wele pull of his bopee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per, thou't know me by my noſe, I am a mad merie grig, come to make thy grace laugh, ſir <hi>Scillicet</hi> my gueſt, all true canaries that loue iuce of grapes, god bleſſe thy Maieſtie.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Acut.</speaker>
               <p>How now mine Hoſt?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Hoſt.</speaker>
               <p>Ha, ha, I ſpie a ieſt, ha ha, Cornutus, Cornutus.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Acut.</speaker>
               <p>Nay mine hoſt, heeres a moate in your eye to.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Scil:</speaker>
               <p>Sl'id I hope they haue not ſeru'd me ſo: by the torrid y'are an aſſe, a flat Aſſe, but the beſt is I know who did it, t'was ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther you or ſome body elſe, for I was in no company of man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kinde elſe, by gad I remember it as wel as if it were done now.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Hoſt:</speaker>
               <p>Tou ſhalt anſwere it to my leige, ile not be ſo miſuſed, ye haue a wrong element, there's fire in my face, weele mou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t and aſcend.</p>
               <l>I'me miſuſd the mad comrades haue plaide the knaues,</l>
               <l>Iuſtice my braue Caeſar.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Accut.</speaker>
               <l>Ile anſwere ye mine Hoſt: pardon greate Caeſar,</l>
               <l>The intent was merriment, the reaſon this:</l>
               <l>A true brow bends, to ſee good things amiſſe,</l>
               <l>Men turnd to beaſts, and ſuch are you mine Hoſt</l>
               <l>See you this, this repreſents a beaſt,</l>
               <l>That cannot ſee his ſhame, &amp; ſuch are you mine Hoſt.</l>
               <l>Ile ſhow you elſe, you are a Goate, looke heere!</l>
               <l>Now come you, this is your's, you know it, doe you not?</l>
               <l>How old are you? are you not a Goate now?</l>
               <l>Shall I teach thee how to vſe a wife and keepe her?</l>
               <l>In the ranke of goodnes linke her to thy ſoule,</l>
               <l>Deuide not <hi>indiuidium,</hi> be her and ſhee thee,</l>
               <l>Keepe her from the Serpent, let her not Gad</l>
               <l>To euerie Goſſips congregation,</l>
               <l>For there is bluſhing modeſtie laide out,</l>
               <l>And a free reyne to ſenſual turpitude,</l>
               <l>Giuen out at length and lybidinous acts,</l>
               <l>Free chat, each giuing counſell and ſenſure.</l>
               <pb facs="tcp:20970:39"/>
               <l>
                  <hi>Capream maritum facere,</hi> ſuch art thou Goate,</l>
               <l>Be not ſo ſecure: and you my graund Cornutus,</l>
               <l>Thou Ram, thou ſeeſt thy ſhame a pent-houſe</l>
               <l>To thy eye-browes: dooſt not glorie in it, dooſt?</l>
               <l>Thou'lt lye in a Trucklebed, at thy wiues bed feete,</l>
               <l>And let her goe a Goſſiping while thou ſweepeſt the ktchin,</l>
               <l>Look, ſhe ſhall witneſſes againſt thee.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Corn:</speaker>
               <p>My wife there? I muſt be gone then.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Acut.</speaker>
               <p>Oh fie, betray not thy ſelfe ſo groſſely.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Cor.</speaker>
               <p>I Pray ye pardon me.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Accut:</speaker>
               <p>I dare not.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Cor:</speaker>
               <l>I ſir, but afterward may come after claps,</l>
               <l>I know the world well enough.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Accut.</speaker>
               <p>Miſchiefe of the Deuill, be man not all beaſt, doe not lye, —both ſheetes doe not.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Cit. w:</speaker>
               <p>I warrant this fellow has as many eies as a Lamprey, hee could neuer ſee ſo farre into the world elſe.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Accu.</speaker>
               <p>And thou pure aſſe, meere aſſe, thy eares become thee well yfaith</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Scil.</speaker>
               <p>I think you ment to make a Muſition of me, you fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſh me with a good eare.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Accut.</speaker>
               <p>Thou deſerudſt it, thou't make thy ſelfe a Cucckold be it but for company ſake, thou haſt long eares, and thinkeſt them hornes, thy conceites cuckolds thee, thou art iealious if thou ſeeſt thy wiues — With another mans palme.</p>
               <p>And foole, thy ſtate in that ſence is the beſt: thou art claſpt with ſimplicitie, (a great badge of honeſtie) for ſhe poore foole has paund her cloathes to redeeme thy vnthriftines: be Iealious no more, vnleſſe thoult weare thine eares ſtill, for all ſhall be well and you ſhall haue your puppie againe.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Get.</speaker>
               <p>Shall I? by my troth I ſhall be beholding to you then.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Acu:</speaker>
               <l>Now to ye all, be firmaments to ſtars,</l>
               <l>Be ſtars to Firmaments, and as you are</l>
               <l>Splendent, ſo be fixed, not wandring, nor</l>
               <l>Irregular, both keeping courſe together,</l>
               <l>Shine not in pride, and gorgeous attire,</l>
               <l>When clouds doe faile, the pole where thou art fixt.</l>
               <l>Obey, cheriſh, honor, be kinde enough,</l>
               <l>But let them weare no changeable ſtuffe,</l>
               <l>Keepe them, as ſhall become your ſtate,</l>
               <pb facs="tcp:20970:39"/>
               <l>Comely, and to creepe ere they goe.</l>
               <l>Let them partake your ioyes, and weep with you,</l>
               <l>Curle not the ſnarles that dwel vpon theſe browes,</l>
               <l>In all things be you kinde of all enough,</l>
               <l>But let them weare no changeable ſtuffe.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Hoſt:</speaker>
               <p>Fore God a mad ſpirit.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Hoſtis</speaker>
               <p>Will ye beleeue, what ſuch a bisket brain'd fellow as this ſaies? he has a mouth like a double cannon, the report will be heard all ore the towne.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Cittie wife:</speaker>
               <p>I warrant he ranne mad for loue, becauſe no good face could endure the ſight of him, and euer ſince he railes a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt women like a whot ſhot.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Len.</speaker>
               <l>Nay, nay, we muſt haue all friendes.</l>
               <l>Iarring diſcords are no marriage muſick,</l>
               <l>Throw not Hymen in a cuckſtoole, dimple</l>
               <l>Your furrowed browes, ſince all but mirth was ment,</l>
               <l>Let vs not then conclude in diſcontent.</l>
               <l>Say, ſhall we all in friendly ſtraine</l>
               <l>Meaſure our paces to bed-ward?</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Tul.</speaker>
               <p>Will <hi>Terentia</hi> follow?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Teren:</speaker>
               <p>If <hi>Tully</hi> be her Leader.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Host:</speaker>
               <p>Good bloods, good ſpirits, let me anſwere for all, none ſpeake but mine Hoſt, hee has his pols and his aedypols, his times and his tricks, his quirkes and his quilits, and his demiſe and dementions, God bleſſe thee Noble Caeſar, and all theſe braue ſpirits, I am Hoſt of the Hobby, Cornutus is my neigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bour: Graccus a mad ſpirit, <hi>Accutus</hi> is my friend, Sir <hi>Scillicet</hi> is my gueſt, al mad comrades of the true ſeed of troy, that loue iuice of Grapes: we are all true friends, merrie harts liue long, let the Pipers ſtrike vp ile daunce my cinquepace, cut a loft my braue capers, whirle about my toe, doe my tricks aboue grou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d, ile kiſſe my ſweet hoſteſſe, make a curteſie to thy grace, God bleſſe thy Maieſtie, and the Mouſe ſhall be dun.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Cor:</speaker>
               <p>Come wife, will you dance?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Wife:</speaker>
               <p>Ile not daunce I, muſt you come to the Court to haue hornes ſet on your head? I could haue done that at home.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Hoſt:</speaker>
               <p>I, I, be rulde at this time, what, for one merrie day wele finde a whole moone at mid-ſommer.</p>
            </sp>
            <stage>
               <pb facs="tcp:20970:40"/>
               <hi>Daunce.</hi>
            </stage>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Caeſ.</speaker>
               <p>Gentles, wee thanke yee all, the night hath ſpent his youth, and drowſie Morpheus bids vs battell,</p>
               <l>We will defie him ſtill, weele keepe him out</l>
               <l>While we haue power to doe it, ſound your lowdeſt noiſe,</l>
               <l>Set forward to our chamber.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Gra.</speaker>
               <p>Aduance your light.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Caeſ.</speaker>
               <p>Good reſt to all.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Omn.</speaker>
               <p>God giue your grace God night.
<stage>Exeunt</stage>
               </p>
            </sp>
            <trailer>FINIS</trailer>
            <pb facs="tcp:20970:40"/>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
