<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>The valiant and most laudable fight performed in the Straights, by the Centurion of London against fiue Spanish gallies. Who is safely returned this present moneth of May. Anno. D. 1591.</title>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1591</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 8 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 4 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2014-11">2014-11 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A18330</idno>
            <idno type="STC">STC 4911.7</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC S112571</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99847819</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99847819</idno>
            <idno type="VID">12880</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online text creation partnership.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A18330)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 12880)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 465:05)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>The valiant and most laudable fight performed in the Straights, by the Centurion of London against fiue Spanish gallies. Who is safely returned this present moneth of May. Anno. D. 1591.</title>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>6 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>J. Charlewood,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>[London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1591]</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>A3v reads: Present at this fight, Maister Iohn Hawes Marchant, and sundry others of good account.</note>
                  <note>Printer's name and publication date from STC.</note>
                  <note>With woodcut title vignette.</note>
                  <note>Formerly STC 12941.</note>
                  <note>Identified as STC 12941 on UMI microfilm.</note>
                  <note>Some print show-through.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the Bodleian Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Hawes, John, --  merchant.</term>
               <term>Centurion (Ship: London, England) --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2013-07</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-08</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-10</date>
            <label>Olivia Bottum</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-10</date>
            <label>Olivia Bottum</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2014-03</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:12880:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:12880:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>THE Valiant and moſt lauda<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble fight performed in the Straights, by <hi>the Centurion of London, against fiue Spanish Gallies.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Who is ſafely returned this preſent Moneth of May. <hi>Anno. D.</hi> 1591.</p>
            <figure/>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb facs="tcp:12880:2"/>
            <pb n="3" facs="tcp:12880:2"/>
            <head>
               <g ref="char:leaf">❧</g> The valiant and moſt laudable fight performed on the Sea, by the <hi>Centurion</hi> of London.</head>
            <p>
               <hi>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg>N the moneth of <hi>Nouember</hi> laſt</hi> paſt, there were ſundry Shyps appertay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning to ſeuerall Marchants of <hi>London,</hi> which were rigde and fraught, forth with marchandize, ſome for <hi>Spaine,</hi> and ſome for ſundry other places of traffique, who together hauing wind and wether, which oft-time fell out very vncertaine, arriued ſafely in ſhort ſpace, at ſuch places as they deſired, among whom was the <hi>Centurion</hi> of <hi>London,</hi> a very tall Shyppe of burden, yet but weakely manned, as appeareth by this Hiſtorie enſuing; wherein God ſhewed a moſt wonderfull accident of his mercifull loue and fauour towards them, giuing them the victory, and deliuering them from the hands of their E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nemies, at ſuch time as it was thought vnpoſſible for them to eſcape.</p>
            <p>Thys aforeſaid Shyp called the <hi>Centurion,</hi> ſafely arri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued at <hi>Marſeelis,</hi> where after they had deliuered their goods, they ſtaied about the ſpace of fiue wéekes, and better, and then tooke in lading, intending to returne to England.</p>
            <p>Now when the <hi>Centurion</hi> was ready to come away fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> 
               <hi>Marſeelis,</hi> there were ſundry other ſhyps of ſmaller burden, entreated the Maiſter thereof, whoſe name is <hi>Robert Brad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhawe,</hi>
               <pb n="4" facs="tcp:12880:3"/> dwelling at the <hi>Lime-houſe,</hi> to ſtay a day or two for them, vntill they were in a readines to depart with them, thereby perſwading them, that it would be farre better for them to ſtay and goe together in reſpect of their aſſiſtance, then to depart of themſelues without company, and ſo hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pily for want of ayde fall into the hands of theyr Enemies in the Spaniſh Gallies. Vpon which reaſonable perſwaſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, notwithſtanding that thys Ship was of ſuch ſufficiencie as they might hazard her in the danger of the Sea, yet they ſtayed for thoſe little Ships according to theyr requeſt, who together did put to Sea from <hi>Marſeelis,</hi> and vowed in gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall not to flie one from another, if ſo they ſhould happen to meete with any Spaniſh Gallies, beeing reſolute rather to fight it out, then once to be taken by the <hi>Spaniards</hi> to endure their accuſtomed crueltie.</p>
            <p>Theſe ſmall Shippes accompanied with the <hi>Centurion,</hi> ſayling along the Coſte of <hi>Spaine,</hi> was vpon Eſter day laſt in the ſtraights of <hi>Iebualtare</hi> ſuddainly becalmed, where im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mediatly they ſawe ſundry Gallies make towards them, in very valiant and couragious ſorte: the chiefe Leaders and Souldiours in thoſe Gallies, brauely apparrelled in ſilke Coates, with ſiluer whiſtles about theyr necks, and great plumes of Feathers in theyr Hafs, who with theyr Calli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uers, ſhotte at the <hi>Centurion</hi> ſo faſt as they might: ſo that by tenne of the clock and ſomewhat before, they had boorded the <hi>Centurion,</hi> who before theyr comming, had prepared for them, and intended to giue them ſo ſower a welcom as they might. And thereupon hauing prepared theyr cloſe fights, &amp; al things in a readines, they called vpon God, on who<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> onely they truſted: and hauing made theyr prayers, and cheered vp one another to fight ſo long as life endured, they began to diſcharge theyr great Ordinaunce vpon the Gallies, but the little Shyps durſt not come forward, but lay aloofe, while fiue Gallies had hoorded them, yea and with theyr grapling yrons made theyr Gallies faſt to the ſaid Shippe called the <hi>Centurion.</hi>
            </p>
            <pb n="5" facs="tcp:12880:3"/>
            <p>The Gallies were grapled to the <hi>Centurion</hi> in thys manner, two lay on one ſide, and two on another, and the Admirall lay full in the ſterne, which galled &amp; battered the <hi>Centurion</hi> ſo ſore, that her maine Maſt was greatly weake<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned, her ſayles filled with many holes, and the Mizzen and ſterne made almoſt vnſeruiceable.</p>
            <p>During which time there was a ſore and deadly fight on both ſides, in which, the Trumpet of the <hi>Centurion,</hi> ſown<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded forth the deadly points of war, &amp; encouraged the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> to fight manfully againſt their aduerſaries: on the contrary part, there was no warlike Muſicke in the Spaniſh Gallies, but onely their whyſtles of ſiluer, which they ſounded foorth to theyr owne contentment: in which fight many a Spaniard was turned into the ſea, and they in multitudes came crau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling and hung vpon the ſide of the ſhippe, intending to haue entred into the ſame, but ſuch was the courage of the Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſhmen, that ſo faſt as the Spaniards did come to enter, they gaue them ſuch entertainment, that ſome of them were gladde to tumble aliue into the ſea, beeing remediles for e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer to gette vp aliue. In the <hi>Centurion</hi> there was in all, of men and boyes, forty and eyght, who together fought moſt valiantly, and ſo galled the enemy, that many a braue and luſty Spaniard loſt his life in that place.</p>
            <p>The <hi>Centurian</hi> was fyred fyue ſeuerall times, with wilde fyre and other prouiſion, which the Spaniards threw in for that purpoſe: yet God be thanked, by the great and dilligent fore-ſight of the Maſter it did no harme at all.</p>
            <p>In euery of the Gallies there was about fiue or ſixe hundereth Souldiours: who together with the ſhotte, ſpoyled, rent, and battered the <hi>Centurion</hi> very ſore: ſhotte through her maine Maſt, and ſlew foure of the men in the ſayde ſhippe, the one of them béeing the Maſters mate.</p>
            <p>Ten other perſons were hurt, by meanes of ſplinters which the Spaniards ſhotte: yea, in the ende when their prouiſion was almoſt ſpent, they were conſtrayned to ſhoote at them hammers, and the chaines from theyr ſlaues,
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:12880:4"/> and yet God be thanked, they receiued no more domage: but by ſpoyling and ouer wearying of the Spaniards, the Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſhmen conſtrayned them to vngrapple themſelues, and gette them going, and ſure if there had béene any other freſh ſhyp or ſuccour to haue releiued and aſſiſted the <hi>Centurion,</hi> they had ſlayne, ſuncke, or taken all thoſe Gallies and theyr Souldiours.</p>
            <p>The <hi>Dolphin</hi> lay a loofe of and durſt not come neere, while the other two ſmall ſhyppes fledde away, ſo that one of the Gallyes went from the <hi>Centurion</hi> and ſette vpon the <hi>Dolphin,</hi> which ſhyppe immediatly was ſet on fire with theyr owne powder, wherby both men and ſhyppe periſhed: but whether it was with theyr good wills or no, that was not knowne vnto the <hi>Centurion,</hi> but ſure if it had come for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward, and beene an ayde vnto the <hi>Centurion,</hi> it is to be ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſed that it hadde not periſhed.</p>
            <p>Fiue houres and a halfe this fight continued, in which time both were glad to depart onely to breath themſelues, but when the Spaniards were gonne, they neuer durſt re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turne to fight: yet the next day ſixe other Gallies came and looked at them, but durſt not at any hand meddle with them. Thus God deliuered them from the hands of their enemies, and gaue them the victory: for which they hartily prayſed God, and are now ſafely arriued in London.</p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
            <trailer>
               <hi>Preſent at this fight, Maiſter <hi>John Hawer</hi> Marchant, and ſundry other of good account.</hi>
            </trailer>
            <pb facs="tcp:12880:4"/>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
