<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>The raigne of King Edvvard the third as it hath bin sundrie times plaied about the citie of London.</title>
            <title>Edward III (Drama)</title>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1596</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 156 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 38 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-04">2011-04 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A21144</idno>
            <idno type="STC">STC 7501</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC S106297</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99842015</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99842015</idno>
            <idno type="VID">6638</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A21144)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 6638)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 337:07)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>The raigne of King Edvvard the third as it hath bin sundrie times plaied about the citie of London.</title>
                  <title>Edward III (Drama)</title>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[74] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed [by T. Scarlet] for Cuthbert Burby,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1596.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Misattributed to William Shakespeare.</note>
                  <note>In verse.</note>
                  <note>Printer's name from STC.</note>
                  <note>Signatures: [A]⁴ B-I⁴ K²  (-[A]1).</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the Henry E. Huntington Library and Art Gallery.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Edward --  III, --  King of England, 1312-1377 --  Drama.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2007-03</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2007-03</date>
            <label>Apex CoVantage</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-01</date>
            <label>Simon Charles</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-01</date>
            <label>Simon Charles</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-04</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:6638:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:6638:1"/>
            <p>THE RAIGNE OF KING EDVVARD the third: As it hath bin ſundrie
times plaied about the Citie of London.</p>
            <p>LONDON, Printed for Cuthbert Burby. 1596.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb facs="tcp:6638:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:6638:2"/>
            <head>THE RAIGNE OF K: Edward the third.</head>
            <stage>Enter King Edward, Derby, Prince Edward, Audely and
Artoys.</stage>
            <sp>
               <speaker>King.</speaker>
               <l>RObert of Artoys baniſht though thou be,</l>
               <l>From Fraunce thy natiue Country, yet with vs,</l>
               <l>Thou ſhalt retayne as great a Seigniorie:</l>
               <l>For we create thee Earle of Richmond heere,</l>
               <l>And now goe forwards with our pedegree,</l>
               <l>Who next ſucceeded Phillip of Bew,</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Ar.</speaker>
               <l>Three ſonnes of his, which all ſucceſſefully,</l>
               <l>Did ſit vpon their fathers regall Throne:</l>
               <l>Yet dyed and left no iſſue of their loynes:</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>King:</speaker>
               <l>But was my mother ſiſter vnto thoſe:</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Art:</speaker>
               <l>Shee was my Lord, and onely Iſſabel,</l>
               <l>Was all the daughters that this Phillip had,</l>
               <l>Whome afterward your father tooke to wife:</l>
               <l>And from the fragrant garden of her wombe,</l>
               <l>Your gratious ſelfe the flower of Europes hope:</l>
               <l>Deriued is inheritor to Fraunce.</l>
               <l>But not the rancor of rebellious mindes:</l>
               <l>When thus the lynage of Bew was out;</l>
               <l>The French obſcurd your mothers Priuiledge,</l>
               <l>And though ſhe were the next of blood, proclaymed</l>
               <l>Iohn of the houſe of Valoys now their king:</l>
               <l>The reaſon was, they ſay the Realme of Fraunce,</l>
               <l>Repleat with Princes of great parentage,</l>
               <l>Ought not admit a gouernor to rule,</l>
               <l>Except he be diſcended of the male,</l>
               <l>And thats the ſpeciall ground of their contempt:</l>
               <l>Where with they ſtudy to exclude your grace:</l>
               <l>But they ſhall finde that forged ground of theirs,</l>
               <l>
                  <pb facs="tcp:6638:3"/>To be but duſty heapes, of brittile ſande.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Art:</speaker>
               <l>Perhaps it will be thought a heynous thing,</l>
               <l>That I a French man ſhould diſcouer this,</l>
               <l>But heauen I call to recorde of my vowes,</l>
               <l>It is not hate nor any priuat wronge,</l>
               <l>But loue vnto my country and the right,</l>
               <l>Prouokes my tongue thus lauiſh in report.</l>
               <l>You are the lyneal watch men of our peace,</l>
               <l>And Iohn of Valoys, in directly climbes,</l>
               <l>What then ſhould ſubiects but imbrace their King,</l>
               <l>Ah where in may our duety more be ſeene,</l>
               <l>Then ſtryuing to rebate a tyrants pride,</l>
               <l>And place the true ſhepheard of our comonwealth,</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>King:</speaker>
               <l>This counſayle Artoyes like to fruictfull ſhewers,</l>
               <l>Hath added growth vnto my dignitye,</l>
               <l>And by the fiery vigor of thy words,</l>
               <l>Hot courage is engendred in my breſt,</l>
               <l>Which heretofore was rakt in ignorance,</l>
               <l>But nowe doth mount with golden winges of fame,</l>
               <l>And will approue faire Iſſabells diſcent,</l>
               <l>Able to yoak their ſtubburne necks with ſteele,</l>
               <l>That ſpurne againſt my ſouereignety in France. 
<stage>ſound a horne</stage>
               </l>
               <l>A meſſenger, Lord Awdley know from whence,</l>
            </sp>
            <stage>Enter a meſſenger Lorragne,</stage>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Aud:</speaker>
               <l>The Duke of Lorrayne, hauing croſt the ſeas,</l>
               <l>In treates he may haue conference with your highnes.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>King:</speaker>
               <l>Admit him Lords, that we may heare the newes.</l>
               <l>Say Duke of Lorrayne wherefore art thou come.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Lor:</speaker>
               <l>The moſt renowned prince K. Iohn of France,</l>
               <l>Doth greete thee Edward, and by me commandes,</l>
               <l>That for ſo much as by hi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> liberall gift,</l>
               <l>The Guyen Dukedome is entayld to thee,</l>
               <l>Thou do him lowly homage for the ſame.</l>
               <l>And for that purpoſe here I ſomon thee,</l>
               <l>Repaire to France within theſe forty daies,</l>
               <l>That there according as
<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>he couſtome is.</l>
               <l>Thou mayſt be ſworne true liegeman to our King,</l>
               <l>
                  <pb facs="tcp:6638:3"/>Or elſe thy title in that prouince dyes,</l>
               <l>And hee him ſelf will repoſſeſſe the place.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>K. Ed:</speaker>
               <l>See how occaſion laughes me in the face,</l>
               <l>No ſooner minded to prepare for France,</l>
               <l>But ſtraight I am inuited, nay with threats,</l>
               <l>Vppon a penaltie inioynd to come:</l>
               <l>Twere but a childiſh part to ſay him nay,</l>
               <l>Lorrayne returne this anſwere to thy Lord,</l>
               <l>I meane to viſit him as he requeſts,</l>
               <l>But how? not ſeruilely diſpoſd to bend,</l>
               <l>But like a conquerer to make him bowe,</l>
               <l>His lame vnpoliſht ſhiſts are come to light,</l>
               <l>And trueth hath puld the viſard from his face,</l>
               <l>That ſett a glaſſe vpon his arrogannce,</l>
               <l>Dare he commaund a fealty in mee,</l>
               <l>Tell him the Crowne that hee vſurpes, is myne,</l>
               <l>And where he ſets his foote he ought to knele,</l>
               <l>Tis not a petty Dukedome that I claime,</l>
               <l>But all the whole Dominions, of the Realme,</l>
               <l>Which if with grudging he refuſe to yeld,</l>
               <l>Ile take away thoſe borrowed plumes of his,</l>
               <l>And ſend him naked to the wildernes.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Lor:</speaker>
               <l>Then Edward here in ſpight of all thy Lords,</l>
               <l>I doe pronounce defyaunce to thy face.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Pri:</speaker>
               <l>Defiance French man we rebound it backe,</l>
               <l>Euen to the bottom of thy maſters throat,</l>
               <l>And be it ſpoke with reuerence of the King,</l>
               <l>My gratious father and theſe other Lordes,</l>
               <l>I hold thy meſſage but as ſcurrylous,</l>
               <l>And him that ſent thee like the lazy droane,</l>
               <l>Crept vp by ſtelth vnto the Eagles neſt,</l>
               <l>From whence wele ſhake him with ſo rough a ſtorme,</l>
               <l>As others ſhalbe warned by his harme,</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>War:</speaker>
               <l>Byd him leaue of the Lyons caſe he weares,</l>
               <l>Leaſt meeting with the Lyon in the feeld,</l>
               <l>He chaunce to teare him peecemede for his pride.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Art:</speaker>
               <l>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>e ſoundeſt
counſell I can giue his grace,</l>
               <l>
                  <pb facs="tcp:6638:4"/>Is to ſurrender ere he be conſtraynd.</l>
               <l>A voluntarie miſchiefe hath leſſe ſcorne,</l>
               <l>Then when reproch with violence is borne,</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Lor.</speaker>
               <l>Regenerate Traytor, viper to the place,</l>
               <l>Where thou was foſtred in thine infancy:</l>
               <l>Beareſt thou a part in this conſpiracy?</l>
               <stage>He drawes his Sword.</stage>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>K. Ed.</speaker>
               <l>Lorraine behold the ſharpnes of this ſteele:</l>
               <l>Feruent deſire that ſits againſt my heart,</l>
               <l>Is farre more thornie pricking than this blade.</l>
               <l>That with the nightingale I ſhall be
<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>ard:</l>
               <l>As oft as I diſpoſe my ſelfe to reſt,</l>
               <l>Vntill my collours be diſplaide in Fraunce:</l>
               <l>This is thy finall Anſwere, ſo be gone.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Lor.</speaker>
               <l>It is not that nor any Engliſh braue,</l>
               <l>Afflicts me ſo, as doth his poyſoned view,</l>
               <l>That is moſt falſe, ſhould moſt of all be true.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>K. Ed.</speaker>
               <l>Now Lord our fleeting Barke is vnder ſayle:</l>
               <l>Our gage is throwne, and warre is ſoone began,</l>
               <l>But not ſo quickely brought vnto an end.</l>
            </sp>
            <stage>Enter Mountague.</stage>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Moun.</speaker>
               <l>But wherefore comes Sir william Mountague?</l>
               <l>How ſtands the league betweene the Scot and vs?</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Mo.</speaker>
               <l>Crackt and diſſeuered my renowned Lord:</l>
               <l>The treacherous King no ſooner was informde,</l>
               <l>Of your with drawing of your army backe:</l>
               <l>But ſtraight forgetting of his former othe,</l>
               <l>He made inuaſion on the bordering Townes:</l>
               <l>Barwicke is woon, Newcaſtle ſpoyld and loſt,</l>
               <l>And now the tyrant hath beguirt with ſeege,</l>
               <l>The Caſtle of Rocksborough, where incloſd,</l>
               <l>The Countes Salsbury is like to periſh:</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>King.</speaker>
               <l>That is thy daughter Warwicke is it not?</l>
               <l>Whoſe husband hath in Brittayne ſerud ſo long,</l>
               <l>About the planting of Lord Mouneford there?</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>VVar.</speaker>
               <l>It is my Lord.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <pb facs="tcp:6638:4"/>
               <speaker>Ki:</speaker>
               <l>Ignoble Dauid haſt thou none to greeue,</l>
               <l>But ſilly Ladies with thy threatning armes:</l>
               <l>But I will make you ſhrinke your ſnailie hornes,</l>
               <l>Firſt therefore Audley this ſhalbe thy charge,</l>
               <l>Go leuie footemen for our warres in Fraunce;</l>
               <l>And Ned take muſter of our men at armes,</l>
               <l>In euery ſhire elect a ſeuerall band,</l>
               <l>Let them be Souldiers of a luſtie ſpirite,</l>
               <l>Such as dread nothing but diſhonors blot,</l>
               <l>Be warie therefore ſince we do comence,</l>
               <l>A famous Warre, and with ſo mighty a nation:</l>
               <l>Derby be thou Embaſſador for vs,</l>
               <l>Vnto our Father in Law the Earle of Henalt:</l>
               <l>Make him acquainted with our enterpriſe,</l>
               <l>And likewiſe will him with our owne allies,</l>
               <l>That are in Flaundsrs, to ſolicite to,</l>
               <l>The Emperour of Almaigne in our name:</l>
               <l>Myſelfe whilſt you are ioyntly thus employd,</l>
               <l>Will with theſe forces that I haue at hand,</l>
               <l>March, and once more repulſe the trayterous Scot:</l>
               <l>But Sirs be reſolute, we ſhal haue warres</l>
               <l>On euery ſide, and Ned, thou muſt begin,</l>
               <l>Now to forget thy ſtudy and thy bookes,</l>
               <l>And yre thy ſhoulders to an Armors weight.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Pr.</speaker>
               <l>As cheereful ſounding to my youthfull ſpleene,</l>
               <l>This tumult is of warres increaſing broyles,</l>
               <l>As at the Coronation of a king,</l>
               <l>The ioyfull clamours of the people are,</l>
               <l>When <hi>Aue C<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1+ letters">
                        <desc>•…</desc>
                     </gap>ſar</hi> they pronounce alowd;</l>
               <l>Within this ſchoole of honor I ſhal learne,</l>
               <l>Either to ſacrifice my foes to death,</l>
               <l>Or in a rightfull quarrel ſpend my breath,</l>
               <l>Then cheerefully forward ech a ſeuerall way,</l>
               <l>In great affaires tis nought to vſe delay.</l>
               <stage>Exunt.</stage>
            </sp>
            <stage>
               <pb facs="tcp:6638:5"/>Enter the Counteſſe.</stage>
            <sp>
               <l>Alas how much in vaine my poore eyes gaze,</l>
               <l>For ſouccour that my ſoueraigne ſhould ſend;</l>
               <l>A co ſin Mountague, I feare thou wants,</l>
               <l>The liuely ſpirirt ſharpely to ſolicit,</l>
               <l>W<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>th vehement ſute
the king in my behalfe:</l>
               <l>Thou doſt not tell him what a griefe it is,</l>
               <l>To be the ſcornefull captiue to a Scot,</l>
               <l>Either to be wooed with broad vntuned othes,</l>
               <l>Or forſt by rough inſulting barbariſme:</l>
               <l>Thou doeſt not tell him if he heere preuaile,</l>
               <l>How much they will deride vs in the North,</l>
               <l>And in their vild vnſeuill skipping giggs,</l>
               <l>Bray foorth their Conqueſt, and our ouerthrow,</l>
               <l>Euen in the barraine, bleake and fruitleſſe aire,</l>
            </sp>
            <stage>Enter Dauid and Douglas, Lorraine.</stage>
            <sp>
               <l>I muſt withdraw, the euerlaſting ſoe,</l>
               <l>Comes to the wall, Ile cloſely ſtep aſide,</l>
               <l>And liſt their babble blunt and full of pride.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>K. Da:</speaker>
               <l>My Lord of Lorrayne, to our brother of Fraunce,</l>
               <l>Commend vs as the man in Chriſtendome,</l>
               <l>That we muſt reuerence and intirely loue,</l>
               <l>Touching your embaſſage, returne and ſay,</l>
               <l>That we with England will not enter parlie,</l>
               <l>Nor neuer make faire wether, or take truce,</l>
               <l>But burne their neighbor townes and ſo perſiſt</l>
               <l>With eager Rods beyond their Citie Yorke,</l>
               <l>And neuer ſhall our bonny riders reſt:</l>
               <l>Nor ruſt in canker, haue the time to eate,</l>
               <l>Their light borne ſnaffles, nor their nimble ſpu</l>
               <l>Nor lay a ſide their Iacks of Gymould mayle,</l>
               <l>Nor hang their ſtaues of grayned Scottiſh aſh,</l>
               <l>In peacefull wiſe, vpon their Citie wals,</l>
               <l>Nor from their buttoned tawny leatherne belts,</l>
               <l>Diſmiſſe their byting whinyards, till your King,</l>
               <l>
                  <pb facs="tcp:6638:5"/>Cry out enough, ſpare England now for pittie,</l>
               <l>Farewell, and tell him that you leaue vs heare,</l>
               <l>Before this Caſtle, ſay you came from vs,</l>
               <l>Euen when we had that yeelded to our hands,</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Lor:</speaker>
               <l>take my leaue and fayrely will returne</l>
               <l>Your acceptable greeting to my king.</l>
               <stage>Exit Lor.</stage>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>K. D:</speaker>
               <l>Now Duglas to our former taske again,</l>
               <l>For the deuiſion of this certayne ſpoyle.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Dou:</speaker>
               <l>My liege I craue the Ladie and no more,</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>King.</speaker>
               <l>Nay ſoft ye ſir, firſt I muſt make my choyſe,</l>
               <l>And firſt I do beſpeake her for my ſelf,</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Da.</speaker>
               <l>Why then my liege let me enioy her iewels,</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>King.</speaker>
               <l>Thoſe are her owne ſtill liable to her,</l>
               <l>And who inherits her, hath thoſe with all.</l>
            </sp>
            <stage>Enter a Scot in haſt.</stage>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Meſ:</speaker>
               <l>My liege, as we were pricking on the hils,</l>
               <l>To fetch in booty, marching hitherward,</l>
               <l>We might diſcry a mighty hoſt of men,</l>
               <l>The Sunne reflicting on the armour ſhewed,</l>
               <l>A field of plate, a wood of pickes aduanced:</l>
               <l>Bethinke your highnes ſpeedely herein,</l>
               <l>An eaſie march within foure howres will bring,</l>
               <l>The hindmoſt rancke, vnto this place my liege.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>King:</speaker>
               <l>Diſlodge, diſlodge, it is the king of England.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Dug:</speaker>
               <l>Iemmy my man, ſaddle my bonny blacke.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>King:</speaker>
               <l>Meanſt thou to fight, Duglas we are to weake.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Du:</speaker>
               <l>I know it well my liege, and therefore flie.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Cou:</speaker>
               <l>My Lords of Scotland will ye ſtay and drinke:</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>King:</speaker>
               <l>She mocks at vs Duglas, I cannot endure it.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Count,</speaker>
               <l>Say good my Lord, which is he muſt haue the Ladie,</l>
               <l>And which her iewels, I am ſure my Lords</l>
               <l>Ye will not hence, till you haue ſhard the ſpoyles.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>King:</speaker>
               <l>Shee heard the meſſenger, and heard our talke.</l>
               <l>And now that comfort makes her ſcorne at vs.</l>
            </sp>
            <stage>Annother meſſenger.</stage>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Meſ:</speaker>
               <l>Arme my good Lord, O we are all ſurpriſde<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <pb facs="tcp:6638:6"/>After the French embaſſador my liege,</l>
               <l>And tell him that you dare not ride to Yorke,</l>
               <l>Excuſe it that your bonnie horſe is lame.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>K.</speaker>
               <l>He heard that to, intollerable griefe:</l>
               <l>Woman farewell although I do not ſtay.</l>
               <stage>Exunt Scots.</stage>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Count:</speaker>
               <l>Tis not for feare, and yet you run away,</l>
               <l>O happie comfort welcome to our houſe,</l>
               <l>The confident and boyſtrous boaſting Scot,</l>
               <l>That ſwore before my walls they would not backe,</l>
               <l>For all the armed power of this land,</l>
               <l>With faceleſſe feare that euer turnes his backe:</l>
               <l>Turnd hence againe the blaſting North-eaſt winde:</l>
               <l>Vpon the bare report and name of Armes.</l>
            </sp>
            <stage>Enter Mountague.</stage>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Mo:</speaker>
               <l>O Sommers day, ſee where my Coſin comes:</l>
               <l>How fares my Aunt? we are not Scots,</l>
               <l>Why do you ſhut your gates againſt your friends?</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Co:</speaker>
               <l>Well may I giue a welcome Coſin to thee:</l>
               <l>For thou con<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ſt
well to chaſe my foes from hence.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Mo:</speaker>
               <l>The king himſelfe is come in perſon hither:</l>
               <l>Deare Aunt diſcend and gratulate his highnes.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Co:</speaker>
               <l>How may I entertayne his Maieſtie,</l>
               <l>To ſhew my duety, and his dignitie.</l>
            </sp>
            <stage>Enter king Edward, VVarwike, Artoyes, with others.</stage>
            <sp>
               <speaker>K. Ed:</speaker>
               <l>What are the ſtealing Foxes fled and gone</l>
               <l>Before we could vncupple at their heeles.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>War:</speaker>
               <l>They are my liege, but with a cheereful cry,</l>
               <l>Hot hunds and hardie chaſe them at the heeles.</l>
            </sp>
            <stage>Enter Counteſſe.</stage>
            <sp>
               <speaker>K. Ed:</speaker>
               <l>This is the Counteſſe Warwike, is it not.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>War:</speaker>
               <l>Euen ſhee liege, whoſe beauty tyrants feare,</l>
               <l>As a May bloſſome with pernitious winds,</l>
               <l>Hath ſullied, withered ouercaſt and donne.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>K. Ed:</speaker>
               <l>Hath ſhe been fairer Warwike then ſhe is?</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>War:</speaker>
               <l>My gratious King, faire is ſhe not at all,</l>
               <l>If that her ſelfe were by to ſtaine herſelfe,</l>
               <l>
                  <pb facs="tcp:6638:6"/>As I haue ſeene her when ſhe was her
ſelfe.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>K. Ed:</speaker>
               <l>What ſtrange enchantment lurke in thoſe her eyes?</l>
               <l>When they exceld this excellence they haue,</l>
               <l>That now her dym declyne hath power to draw,</l>
               <l>My ſubiect eyes from perſing maieſtie,</l>
               <l>To gaze on her with doting admiration.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Count:</speaker>
               <l>In duetie lower then the ground I kneele,</l>
               <l>And for my dul knees bow my feeling heart,</l>
               <l>To witnes my obedience to your highnes,</l>
               <l>With many millions of a ſubiects thanks.</l>
               <l>For this your Royall preſence, whoſe approch,</l>
               <l>Hath driuen war and danger from my gate.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>K.</speaker>
               <l>Lady ſtand vp, I come to bring thee peace,</l>
               <l>How euer thereby I haue purchaſt war.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Co:</speaker>
               <l>No war to you my liege, the Scots are gone,</l>
               <l>And gallop home toward Scotland with their hate,</l>
               <l>Leaſt yeelding heere, I pyne in ſhamefull loue:</l>
               <l>Come wele perſue the Scots, Artoyes away.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Co:</speaker>
               <l>A little while my gratious ſoueraigne ſtay,</l>
               <l>And let the power of a mighty king</l>
               <l>Honor our roofe: my husband in the warres,</l>
               <l>When he ſhall heare it will triumph for ioy.</l>
               <l>Then deare my liege, now niggard not thy ſtate,</l>
               <l>Being at the wall, enter our homely gate.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>King.</speaker>
               <l>Pardon me counteſſe, I will come no neare,</l>
               <l>I dreamde to night of treaſon and I feare.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Co:</speaker>
               <l>Far from this place let vgly treaſonly.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>K:</speaker>
               <l>No farther off, then her conſpyring eye,</l>
               <l>Which ſhoots infected poyſon in my heart.</l>
               <l>Beyond repulſe of wit or cure of Art.</l>
               <l>Now in the Sunne alone it doth not lye,</l>
               <l>With light to take light, from a mortall eye.</l>
               <l>For here to day ſtars that myne eies would ſee,</l>
               <l>More then the Sunne ſteales myne owne light from mee:</l>
               <l>Contemplatiue deſire, deſire to be,</l>
               <l>In contemplation that may maſter thee.</l>
               <l>
                  <pb facs="tcp:6638:7"/>Warwike, Artoys, to horſe and lets away.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Co:</speaker>
               <l>What might I ſpeake to make my ſoueraigne ſtay?</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>King:</speaker>
               <l>What needs a tongue to ſuch a ſpeaking eie,</l>
               <l>That more perſwads then winning Oratorie.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Co:</speaker>
               <l>Let not thy preſence like the Aprill ſunne,</l>
               <l>Flatter our earth, and ſodenly be done:</l>
               <l>More happie do not make our outward wall,</l>
               <l>Then thou wilt grace our inner houſe withall,</l>
               <l>Our houſe my liege is like a Country ſwaine,</l>
               <l>Whoſe habit iude, and wanners blunt and playne,</l>
               <l>Preſageth nought yet inly beautified,</l>
               <l>With bounties riches; and faire hidden pride:</l>
               <l>For where the golden Ore doth buried lie,</l>
               <l>The ground vndect with natures tapeſtrie,</l>
               <l>Seemes barrayne, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>re,
vnfertill, f<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>uctles dry,</l>
               <l>And where the vpper turfe of earth doth boaſt,</l>
               <l>His pride perfumes, and party colloured coſt,</l>
               <l>Delue there, and find this iſſue and their pride,</l>
               <l>To ſpring from ordure, and corruptions ſide:</l>
               <l>But to make vp my all to long compare,</l>
               <l>Theſe ragged walles no teſtomie are,</l>
               <l>What is within, b<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>t
like a cloake doth hide,</l>
               <l>From weathers Weſt, the vnder garniſht pride:</l>
               <l>More gratious then my tearmes can let thee be,</l>
               <l>Intreat thy ſelfe to ſtay a while with mee.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Kin:</speaker>
               <l>As wiſe as faire, what fond fit can be heard,</l>
               <l>When wiſedome keepes the gate as beuties gard,</l>
               <l>Counteſſe, albeit my buſines vrgeth me,</l>
               <l>Yt ſhall attend, while I attend on thee:</l>
               <l>Come on my Lords, heere will I hoſt to night.</l>
               <stage>Exeunt.</stage>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Lor:</speaker>
               <l>I might perceiue his eye in her eye loſt,</l>
               <l>His care to drinke her ſweet tongues vtterance,</l>
               <l>And changing paſſion like inconſtant clouds:</l>
               <l>That racke vpon the carriage of the windes,</l>
               <l>Increaſe and die in his diſturbed cheekes:</l>
               <l>Loe when ſhee bluſht, euen then did he looke pale,</l>
               <l>
                  <pb facs="tcp:6638:7"/>As if her cheekes by ſome inchaunted power,</l>
               <l>Attracted had the cherie blood from his,</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>A</hi> none with reuerent feare, when ſhe grewpale,</l>
               <l>His cheeke put on their ſcarlet ornaments,</l>
               <l>But no more like her oryent all red,</l>
               <l>Then Bricke to Corrall, or liue things to dead,</l>
               <l>Why did he then thus counterfeit her lookes,</l>
               <l>If ſhe did bluſh twas tender modeſt ſhame,</l>
               <l>Being in the ſacred preſent of a King.</l>
               <l>If he did bluſh, twas red immodeſt ſhame,</l>
               <l>To waile his eyes amiſſe being a king:</l>
               <l>If ſhe lookt pa<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>e,
twas ſilly womans feare,</l>
               <l>To beare her ſelfe in preſence of a king:</l>
               <l>If he lookt pa<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>e, it
was with guiltie feare,</l>
               <l>To dote a mi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ſe
being a mighty king,</l>
               <l>Then Scottiſh warres farewell, I feare twill prooue</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>A</hi> lingring Engliſh ſeege of peeuiſh loue,</l>
               <l>Here comes his highnes walking all alone.</l>
            </sp>
            <stage>Enter King Edward.</stage>
            <sp>
               <speaker>King:</speaker>
               <l>Shee is growne more fairer far ſince I came thither,</l>
               <l>Her voice more ſiluer euery word then other,</l>
               <l>Her wit more fluent, what a ſtrange diſcourſe,</l>
               <l>Vnfolded ſhe of Dauid and his Scots:</l>
               <l>Euen thus quoth ſhe, he ſpake, and then ſpoke broad,</l>
               <l>With epithites and accents of the Scot:</l>
               <l>But ſomewhat better then the Scot could ſpeake,</l>
               <l>And thus quoth ſhe, and anſwered then herſelfe,</l>
               <l>For who could ſpeake like her but ſhe herſelfe:</l>
               <l>Breathes from the wall, an Angels note from Heauen:</l>
               <l>Of ſweete defiance to her barbarous foes,</l>
               <l>When ſhe would talke of peace me thinkes her tong,</l>
               <l>Commanded war to priſon: when of war,</l>
               <l>It wakened Caeſar from his Romane graue,</l>
               <l>To heare warre beautified by her diſcourſe,</l>
               <l>Wiſedome is fooliſhnes, but in her tongue,</l>
               <l>Beauty a ſlander but in her faire face,</l>
               <l>There is no ſummer, but in her cheerefull lookes,</l>
               <l>
                  <pb facs="tcp:6638:8"/>Nor froſty winter, but in her diſdayne,</l>
               <l>I cannot blame the Scots that did beſiege her,</l>
               <l>For ſhe is all the Treaſure of our land:</l>
               <l>But call them cowards that they ran away,</l>
               <l>Hauing ſo rich and faire a cauſe to ſtay.</l>
               <l>Art thou thete Lodwicke, giue me incke and paper?</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Lo:</speaker>
               <l>I will my liege.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>K:</speaker>
               <l>And bid the Lords hold on their play at Cheſſe,</l>
               <l>For wee will walke and meditate aloue.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Lo:</speaker>
               <l>I will my ſoueraigne.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Ki:</speaker>
               <l>This fellow is well read in poetrie,</l>
               <l>And hath a luſtie and perſwaſiue ſpirite:</l>
               <l>I will acquaint him with my paſſion,</l>
               <l>Which he ſhall ſhadow with a vaile of lawne,</l>
               <l>Through which the Queene of beauties Queene ſhall ſee,</l>
               <l>Herſelfe the ground of my infirmitie.</l>
            </sp>
            <stage>Enter Lodwike.</stage>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Ki:</speaker>
               <l>Haſt thou pen, inke and paper ready Lodowike,</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Lo:</speaker>
               <l>Ready my liege.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Ki:</speaker>
               <l>Then in the ſommer arber ſit by me,</l>
               <l>Make it our counſel houſe or cabynet:</l>
               <l>Since greene our thoughts, greene be the conuenticle,</l>
               <l>Where we will caſe vs by disburdning them:</l>
               <l>Now Lodwike inuocate ſome golden Muſe,</l>
               <l>To bring thee hither an inchanted pen,</l>
               <l>That may for ſighes, ſet downe true ſighes indeed:</l>
               <l>Talking of griefe, to make thee ready grone,</l>
               <l>And when thou writeſt of teares, encouch the word,</l>
               <l>Before and after with ſuch ſweete laments,</l>
               <l>That it may rayſe drops in a Torterseye,</l>
               <l>And make a flynt heart Sythian pytifull,</l>
               <l>For ſo much moouing hath a Poets pen:</l>
               <l>Then if thou be a Poet moue thou ſo,</l>
               <l>And be enriched by thy ſoueraigne loue:</l>
               <l>For if the touch of ſweet concordant ſtrings,</l>
               <l>Could force attendance in the eares of hel:</l>
               <l>
                  <pb facs="tcp:6638:8"/>How much more ſhall the ſtraines of poets
wit,</l>
               <l>Beguild and rauiſh ſoft and humane myndes.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Lor:</speaker>
               <l>To whome my Lord ſhal I direct my ſtile.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>King:</speaker>
               <l>To one that ſhames the faire and ſots the wiſe,</l>
               <l>Whoſe bodie is an abſtract or a breefe,</l>
               <l>Containes ech generall vertue in the worlde,</l>
               <l>Better then bewtifull thou muſt begin,</l>
               <l>Deuiſe for faire a fairer word then faire,</l>
               <l>And euery ornament that thou wouldeſt praiſe,</l>
               <l>Fly it a pitch aboue the ſoare of praiſe,</l>
               <l>For flattery feare thou not to be conuicted,</l>
               <l>For were thy admiration ten tymes more,</l>
               <l>Ten tymes ten thouſand more thy worth exceeds,</l>
               <l>Of that thou art to praiſe their praiſes worth,</l>
               <l>Beginne I will to contemplat the while,</l>
               <l>Forget not to ſet downe how paſſionat,</l>
               <l>How hart ſicke and how full of languiſhment,</l>
               <l>Her beautie makes mee,</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Lor:</speaker>
               <l>Writ I to a woman?</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>King:</speaker>
               <l>What bewtie els could triumph on me,</l>
               <l>Or who but women doe our loue layes greet,</l>
               <l>What thinekſt thou I did bid thee praiſe a horſe.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Lor,</speaker>
               <l>Of what condicion or eſtate ſhe is,</l>
               <l>Twere requiſit that I ſhould know my Lord,</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>King:</speaker>
               <l>Of ſuch eſtate, that hers is as a throane,</l>
               <l>And my eſtate the footſtoole where ſhee treads,</l>
               <l>Then maiſt thou iudge what her condition is,</l>
               <l>By the proportion of her mightines,</l>
               <l>Write on while I peruſe her in my thoughts,</l>
               <l>Her voice to muſicke or the nightingale,</l>
               <l>To muſicke euery ſommer leaping ſwaine,</l>
               <l>Compares his ſunburnt louer when ſhee ſpeakes,</l>
               <l>And why ſhould I ſpeake of the nightingale,</l>
               <l>The nightingale ſinges of adulterate wrong,</l>
               <l>And that compared is to ſatyrical,</l>
               <l>For ſinne though fynne would not be ſo eſteemd,</l>
               <l>
                  <pb facs="tcp:6638:9"/>But rather vertue ſin, ſynne vertue deemd,</l>
               <l>Her hair far ſoftor then the ſilke wormes twiſt,</l>
               <l>Like to a flattering glas doth make more faire,</l>
               <l>The ye low Amber like a flattering glas,</l>
               <l>Comes in to ſoone: for writing of her eies,</l>
               <l>Ile ſay that like a glas they catch the ſunne,</l>
               <l>And thence the hot reflection doth rebounde,</l>
               <l>Againſt my breſt and burnes my hart within,</l>
               <l>Ah what a world of deſcant makes my ſoule,</l>
               <l>Vpon this voluntarie ground of loue,</l>
               <l>Come Lodwick haſt thou turnd thy inke to golde,</l>
               <l>If not, write but in letters Capitall my miſtres name,</l>
               <l>And it wil guild thy paper, read Lorde, reade,</l>
               <l>Fill thou the emptie hollowes of mine eares,</l>
               <l>With the ſweete hearing of thy poetrie.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Lo:</speaker>
               <l>I haue not to a period brought her praiſe.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>King:</speaker>
               <l>Her praiſe is as my loue, both infinit,</l>
               <l>Which apprehend ſuch violent extremes,</l>
               <l>That they diſdaine an ending period.</l>
               <l>Her bewtie hath no match but my affection,</l>
               <l>Hers more then moſt, myne moſt, and more then more,</l>
               <l>Hers more to praiſe then tell the ſea by drops,</l>
               <l>Nay more then drop the maſſie earth by ſands,</l>
               <l>And ſaid, by ſaid, print them in memorie,</l>
               <l>Then wherefore talkeſt thou of a period,</l>
               <l>To that which craues vnended admiration.</l>
               <l>Read let vs heare,</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Lo:</speaker>
               <l>More faire and chaſt then is the queen of ſhades:</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>King:</speaker>
               <l>That loue hath two falts groſſe and palpable,</l>
               <l>Compareſt thou her to the pale queene of night,</l>
               <l>Who being ſet in da<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ke ſeemes therefore light,</l>
               <l>What is ſhe, when the ſunne lifts vp his head,</l>
               <l>But like a fading taper dym and dead.</l>
               <l>My loue ſhall braue the ey of heauen at noon,</l>
               <l>And being vnmaskt outſhine the golden ſun,</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Lo:</speaker>
               <l>What is the other faulte, my ſoueraigne Lord,</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <pb facs="tcp:6638:9"/>
               <speaker>King.</speaker>
               <l>Readeore the line againe,</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Lo:</speaker>
               <l>More faire and chaſt,</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>King:</speaker>
               <l>I did not bid thee talke of chaſtitie,</l>
               <l>To ranſack ſo the treaſon of her minde,</l>
               <l>For I had rather haue her chaſed then chaſt,</l>
               <l>Out with the moone line, I wil none of it,</l>
               <l>And let me haue hir likened to the ſun,</l>
               <l>Say ſhee hath thrice more ſplendour then the ſun,</l>
               <l>That her perfections emulats the ſunne,</l>
               <l>That ſhee breeds ſweets as plenteous as the ſunne,</l>
               <l>That ſhee doth thaw cold winter like the ſunne,</l>
               <l>That ſhe doth cheere freſh ſommer like the ſunne,</l>
               <l>That ſhee doth dazle gazers like the ſunne,</l>
               <l>And in this application to the ſunne,</l>
               <l>Bid her be free and generall as the ſunne,</l>
               <l>Who ſmiles vpon the baſeſt weed that growes,</l>
               <l>As louinglie as on the fragrantroſe,</l>
               <l>Lets ſee what followes that ſame moonelightline,</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Lo:</speaker>
               <l>More faire and chaſt then is the louer of ſhades,</l>
               <l>More bould in conſtancie.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>King:</speaker>
               <l>In conſtancie then who,</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Lo:</speaker>
               <l>Then Iudith was,</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>King:</speaker>
               <l>O monſtrousline, put in the next a ſword</l>
               <l>And I ſhall woo her to cut of my head</l>
               <l>Blot, blot, good Lodwicke let vs heare the next.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Lo:</speaker>
               <l>Theres all that yet is donne.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>King:</speaker>
               <l>I thancke thee then thou haſt don litle ill,</l>
               <l>But what is don is paſſing paſſing ill,</l>
               <l>No let the Captaine talke of boyſtrous warr,</l>
               <l>The priſoner of emured darke conſtraint,</l>
               <l>The ſick man beſt ſets downe the pangs of death,</l>
               <l>The man that ſtarues the ſweetnes of a feaſt,</l>
               <l>The frozen ſoule the benefite of fire,</l>
               <l>And euery griefe his happie oppoſite,</l>
               <l>Loue cannot ſound well but in louers toungs,</l>
               <l>Giue me the pen and paper I will write,</l>
            </sp>
            <stage>
               <pb facs="tcp:6638:10"/>Enter Countes.</stage>
            <sp>
               <l>But ſo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>t here comes
the treaſurer of my ſpirit,</l>
               <l>Lodwick thou knowſt not how to drawe a battell,</l>
               <l>Theſe wings, theſe flankars, and theſe ſquadrons,</l>
               <l>Argue in thee defectiue diſcipline,</l>
               <l>Thou ſhouldeſt haue placed this here, this other here,</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Co.</speaker>
               <l>Pardon my boldnes my thrice gracious Lords,</l>
               <l>Let my intruſion here be cald my duetie,</l>
               <l>That comes to ſee my ſoueraigne how he fares,</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Kin:</speaker>
               <l>Go draw the ſame I tell thee in what forme.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Lor:</speaker>
               <l>I go.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Con:</speaker>
               <l>Sorry I am to ſee my liege ſo ſad,</l>
               <l>What may thy ſubiect do to driue from thee.</l>
               <l>Thy gloomy conſort, ſullome melancholie,</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>King:</speaker>
               <l>Ah Lady I am blunt and cannot ſtrawe,</l>
               <l>The flowers of ſolace in a ground of ſhame,</l>
               <l>Since I came hither Countes I am wronged.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Cont:</speaker>
               <l>Now God forbid that anie in my howſe</l>
               <l>Should thinck my ſoueraigne wrong, thrice gentle King:</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>King:</speaker>
               <l>Acquant me with theyr cauſe of diſcontent.</l>
               <l>How neere then ſhall I be to remedie.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Cont:</speaker>
               <l>As nere my Liege as all my womans power,</l>
               <l>Can pawne it ſelfe to buy thy remedy.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>King:</speaker>
               <l>Yf thou ſpeakſt true then haue I my redreſſe,</l>
               <l>Ingage thy power to redeeme my Ioyes,</l>
               <l>And I am ioyfull Countes els I die.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Coun:</speaker>
               <l>I will my Liege.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>King:</speaker>
               <l>Sweare Counties that thou wilt.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Coun:</speaker>
               <l>By heauen I will,</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>King:</speaker>
               <l>Then take thy ſelfe a litel waie a ſide,</l>
               <l>And tell thy ſelf a King doth dote on thee,</l>
               <l>Say that within thy power doth lie.</l>
               <l>To make him happy, and that thou haſt ſworne,</l>
               <l>To giue him all the Ioy within thy power,</l>
               <l>Do this and tell me when I ſhall be happie.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <pb facs="tcp:6638:10"/>
               <speaker>Coun:</speaker>
               <l>All this is done my thrice dread ſouereigne,</l>
               <l>That power of loue that I haue power to giue.</l>
               <l>Thou haſt with all deuout obedience,</l>
               <l>Inploy me how thou wilt in profe therof,</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>King.</speaker>
               <l>Thou hearſt me ſaye that I do dote on thee,</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Coun:</speaker>
               <l>Yfon my beauty take yt if thou canſt,</l>
               <l>Though litle I do priſe it ten tymes leſſe,</l>
               <l>If on my vertue take it if thou canſt,</l>
               <l>For vertues ſtore by giuing doth augment,</l>
               <l>Be it on what it will that I can giue,</l>
               <l>And thou canſt take awaie inherit it.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>King.</speaker>
               <l>It is thy beauie that I woulde enioy,</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Count.</speaker>
               <l>O were it painted I would wipe it of,</l>
               <l>And diſpoſſe my ſelfe to giue it thee,</l>
               <l>But ſouereigne it is ſouldered to my life,</l>
               <l>Take one and both for like an humble ſhaddow,</l>
               <l>Yt hauntes the ſunſhine of my ſummers life,</l>
               <l>But thou maiſt leue it me to ſport with all,</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Count:</speaker>
               <l>As eaſie may my intellectual ſoule,</l>
               <l>Be lent awaie and yet my bodie liue,</l>
               <l>As lend my bodie pallace to my ſoule,</l>
               <l>Awaie from her and yet retaine my ſoule,</l>
               <l>My bodie is her bower her Courther abey,</l>
               <l>And ſhee an Angell pure deuine vnſpotted,</l>
               <l>If I ſhould leaue her houſe my Lord to thee,</l>
               <l>I kill my poore ſoule and my poore ſoule me,</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>King.</speaker>
               <l>Didſt thou not ſwere to giue me what I would,</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Count:</speaker>
               <l>I did my liege ſo what you would I could.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>King:</speaker>
               <l>I wiſh no more of thee then thou maiſt giue,</l>
               <l>Nor beg I do not but I rather buie,</l>
               <l>That is thy loue and for that loue of thine,</l>
               <l>In rich exchaunge I tender to thee myne,</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Count.</speaker>
               <l>But that your lippes were ſacred my Lord,</l>
               <l>You would prophane the holie name of loue,</l>
               <l>That loue you offer me you cannot giue,</l>
               <l>For Caeſar owes that tribut to his Queene,</l>
               <l>
                  <pb facs="tcp:6638:11"/>That loue you beg of me I cannot giue,</l>
               <l>For Sara owes that duetie to her Lord,</l>
               <l>He that doth clip or counterfeit your ſtamp,</l>
               <l>Shall die my Lord, and will your ſacred ſelfe,</l>
               <l>Comit high treaſon againſt the King of heauen,</l>
               <l>To ſtamp his Image in forbidden mettel,</l>
               <l>For getting your alleageance, and your othe,</l>
               <l>In violating mariage ſecred law,</l>
               <l>You breake a greater honor then your ſelfe,</l>
               <l>To be a King is of a yonger houſe,</l>
               <l>Then to be maried, your progenitour</l>
               <l>Sole ragning Adam on the vniuerſe,</l>
               <l>By God was honored for a married man,</l>
               <l>But not by him annointed for a king,</l>
               <l>It is a pennalty to breake your ſtatutes,</l>
               <l>Though not enacted with your highnes hand,</l>
               <l>How much more to infringe the holy act,</l>
               <l>Made by the mouth of God, ſeald with his hand,</l>
               <l>I know my ſouereigne in my husbands loue,</l>
               <l>Who now doth loyall ſeruice in his warrs,</l>
               <l>Doth but to try the wife of Salisbury,</l>
               <l>Whither ſhee will heare a wantons tale or no,</l>
               <l>Leſt being therein giulty by my ſtay,</l>
               <l>From that not from my leige I tourne awaie:</l>
               <stage>Exit.</stage>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>King:</speaker>
               <l>Whether is her bewtie by her words dyuine,</l>
               <l>Or are her words ſweet chaplaines to her bewtie,</l>
               <l>Like as the wind doth beautifie a ſaile,</l>
               <l>And as a ſaile becomes the vnſeene winde,</l>
               <l>So doe her words her bewties, bewtie wordes,</l>
               <l>O that I were a honie gathering bee,</l>
               <l>To beare the combe of vertue from his flower,</l>
               <l>And not a poiſon ſucking enuious ſpider,</l>
               <l>To turne the vice I take to deadlie venom,</l>
               <l>Religion is auſtere and bewty gentle,</l>
               <l>To ſtricke a gardion for ſo faire a weed,</l>
               <l>O that ſhee were as is the aire to mee,</l>
               <l>
                  <pb facs="tcp:6638:11"/>Why ſo ſhe is, for when I would embrace
her,</l>
               <l>This do I, and catch nothing but my ſelfe,</l>
               <l>I muſt enioy her, for I cannot beate</l>
               <l>With reaſon and reproofe fond loue awaie.</l>
            </sp>
            <stage>Enter Warwicke.</stage>
            <sp>
               <l>Here comes her father I will worke with him,</l>
               <l>To beare my collours in this feild of loue.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>War:</speaker>
               <l>How is it that my ſouereigne is ſo ſad,</l>
               <l>May I with pardon know your highnes griefe,</l>
               <l>And that my old endeuor will remoue it,</l>
               <l>It ſhall not comber long your maieſtie,</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>King:</speaker>
               <l>A kind and voluntary giift thou profereſt.</l>
               <l>That I was forwarde to haue begd of thee,</l>
               <l>But O thou world great nurſe of flatterie,</l>
               <l>Whie doſt thou tip mens tongues with golden words,</l>
               <l>And peiſe their deedes with weight of heauie leade,</l>
               <l>That faire performance cannot follow promiſe,</l>
               <l>O that a man might hold the hartes cloſe booke,</l>
               <l>And choke the lauiſh tongue when it doth vtter</l>
               <l>The breath of falſhood not carectred there:</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>War:</speaker>
               <l>Far be it from the honor of my age,</l>
               <l>That I ſhould owe bright gould and render lead,</l>
               <l>Age is a cyncke, not a flatterer,</l>
               <l>I ſaye againe, that I if knew your griefe,</l>
               <l>And that by me it may be leſned,</l>
               <l>My proper harme ſhould buy your highnes good,</l>
               <l>Theſe are the vulger tenders of falſe men,</l>
               <l>That neuer pay the duetie of their words,</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Kin:</speaker>
               <l>Thou wilt not ſticke to ſweare what thou haſt ſaid,</l>
               <l>But when thou knoweſt my greifes condition,</l>
               <l>This raſh diſgorged vomit of thy word,</l>
               <l>Thou wilt eate vp againe and leaue me helples.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>War.</speaker>
               <l>By heauen I will not though your maieſtie,</l>
               <l>Did byd me run vpon your ſworde and di<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <pb facs="tcp:6638:12"/>Say that my greefe is no way
<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap>dicinable,</l>
               <l>But by the loſſe and bruiſing
<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap>e honour,</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>War:</speaker>
               <l>Yf nothing but that loſſe may vantage you,</l>
               <l>I would accompliſh that loſſe my vauntage to,</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>King.</speaker>
               <l>Thinkſt that thou canſt anſwere thy oth againe,</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>War:</speaker>
               <l>I cannot nor I would not if I could.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>King.</speaker>
               <l>But if thou doſt <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>hat ſhal I ſay to thee,</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>War:</speaker>
               <l>What may be ſaid to anie periurd villane,</l>
               <l>That breake the ſacred warrant of an oath,</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>King.</speaker>
               <l>What wilt thou ſay to one that breaks an othe,</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>War.</speaker>
               <l>That hee hath broke his faith with God and man,</l>
               <l>And from them both ſtandes excommunicat,</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>King.</speaker>
               <l>What office were it to ſuggeſt a man,</l>
               <l>To breake a lawfull and religious vowe.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>War.</speaker>
               <l>An office for the deuill not for man,</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Ki.</speaker>
               <l>That deſtilles office muſt thou do for me,</l>
               <l>Or breake thy oth or cancell all the bonde<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>,</l>
               <l>Of loue and duetie twixt thy ſelf and mee,</l>
               <l>And therefore Warwike if thou art thy ſelfe,</l>
               <l>The Lord and maſter of thy word and othe,</l>
               <l>Go to thy daughter and in my behalfe,</l>
               <l>Comaund her, woo her, win her
<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> wares,</l>
               <l>To be my miſtres and my ſecret loue,</l>
               <l>I will not ſtand to heare thee make reply,</l>
               <l>Thy oth breake hers or let thy ſouereigne dye.</l>
               <stage>Exit,</stage>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>King:</speaker>
               <l>O doting King, or deteſtable office,</l>
               <l>Well may I tempt my ſelf to wrong my ſelf,</l>
               <l>When he hath ſworne me by the name of God,</l>
               <l>To breake a vowe made by the name of God,</l>
               <l>What if I ſweare by this right hand of mine,</l>
               <l>To cut this right hande of the better waie,</l>
               <l>Were to prophaine the Idoll then confound it,</l>
               <l>But neither will I do Ile keepe myne oath,</l>
               <l>And to my daughter make a recantation,</l>
               <l>Of all the vertue I haue preacht to her,</l>
               <l>
                  <pb facs="tcp:6638:12"/>Ile ſay ſhe muſt forget her hu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>and Salisbury,</l>
               <l>If ſhe remember to embrace the king,</l>
               <l>Ile ſay an othe may eaſily be broken,</l>
               <l>But not ſo eaſily pardoned being broken:</l>
               <l>Ile ſay it is <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>ue
charitie to loue,</l>
               <l>But not true loue to be ſo charitable;</l>
               <l>Ile ſay his greatnes may beare out the ſhame,</l>
               <l>But not his kingdome can buy out the ſinne;</l>
               <l>Ile ſay it is my duety to perſwade,</l>
               <l>But not her honeſtie to giue conſent.</l>
            </sp>
            <stage>Enter Counteſſe.</stage>
            <sp>
               <l>See where ſhe comes, was neuer father had,</l>
               <l>Againſt his child, an embaſſage ſo bad.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Co:</speaker>
               <l>My Lord and father, I haue ſought for you:</l>
               <l>My mother and the Peeres importune you,</l>
               <l>To keepe in promiſe of his maieſtie.</l>
               <l>And do your beſt to make his highnes merrie.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>War:</speaker>
               <l>How ſhall I enter in this graceleſſe arrant,</l>
               <l>I muſt not call her child, for wheres the father,</l>
               <l>That will in ſuch a ſute ſeduce his child:</l>
               <l>Then wife of Salisbury ſhall I ſo begin:</l>
               <l>No hees my friend, and where is found the friend</l>
               <l>That will doe friendſhip ſuch indammagement:</l>
               <l>Neither my daughter, nor my deare friends wife,</l>
               <l>I am not Warwike as thou thinkſt I am,</l>
               <l>But an atturnie from the Court of hell:</l>
               <l>That thus haue houſd my ſpirite in his forme,</l>
               <l>To do a meſſage to thee from the king:</l>
               <l>The mighty king of England dotes on thee:</l>
               <l>He that hath power to take away thy life,</l>
               <l>Hath power to take thy honor, then conſent,</l>
               <l>To pawne thine honor rather then thy life;</l>
               <l>Honor is often loſt and got againe,</l>
               <l>But life once gon, hath no recouerie:</l>
               <l>The Sunne that withersheye goth nouriſh graſſe,</l>
               <l>The king that would diſtaine thee, will aduance thee.</l>
               <l>
                  <pb facs="tcp:6638:13"/>The Poets write that great Achilles ſpeare,</l>
               <l>Could heale the wound it made: the morrall is,</l>
               <l>What mighty men miſdoo, they can amend:</l>
               <l>The Lyon doth become his bloody iawes,</l>
               <l>And grace his <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>orragement by being milde,</l>
               <l>When vaſſell feare lies trembling at his feete,</l>
               <l>The king will in his glory hide thy ſhame,</l>
               <l>And thoſe that gaze on him to finde out thee,</l>
               <l>Will looſe their eie-ſight looking in the Sunne:</l>
               <l>What can one drop of poyſon harme the Sea,</l>
               <l>Whoſe hugie vaſtures can digeſt the ill,</l>
               <l>And make it looſe his operation:</l>
               <l>The kings great name will temper their miſdeeds,</l>
               <l>And giue the bitter portion of reproch:</l>
               <l>A ſugred ſweet, and moſt delitious taſt:</l>
               <l>Beſides it is no harme to do the thing,</l>
               <l>Which without ſhame, could not be left vndone;</l>
               <l>Thus haue I in his maieſties behalfe,</l>
               <l>Apparraled ſin, in vertuous ſentences,</l>
               <l>And dwel vpon thy anſwere in his ſute.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Cou:</speaker>
               <l>Vnnaturall beſeege, woe me vnhappie,</l>
               <l>To haue eſcapt the danger of my foes,</l>
               <l>And to be ten times worſe in<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>erd by friends:</l>
               <l>Hath he no meanes to ſtayne my honeſt blood,</l>
               <l>But to corrupt the author of my blood,</l>
               <l>To be his ſcandalous and vile ſoliciter:</l>
               <l>No maruell though the braunches be then infected,</l>
               <l>When poyſon hath encompaſſed the roote:</l>
               <l>No maruell though the leprous infant dye,</l>
               <l>When the ſterne dame inuennometh the Dug:</l>
               <l>Why then giue ſinne a paſport to offend,</l>
               <l>And youth the dangerous reigne of liberty:</l>
               <l>Blot out the ſtrict forbidding of the law,</l>
               <l>And cancell euery cannon that preſcribes,</l>
               <l>A ſhame for ſhame, or pennance for offence,</l>
               <l>No let me die, if his too boyſtrous will,</l>
               <l>
                  <pb facs="tcp:6638:13"/>Will haue it ſo, before I will conſent,</l>
               <l>To be an actor in his graceleſſe luſt.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Wa:</speaker>
               <l>Why now thou ſpeakſt as I would haue thee ſpeake,</l>
               <l>And marke how I vnſaie my words againe,</l>
               <l>An honorable graue is more eſteemd,</l>
               <l>Then the polluted cloſet of a king,</l>
               <l>The greater man, the greater is the thing,</l>
               <l>Be it good or bad that he ſhall vndertake,</l>
               <l>An vnreputed mote, flying in the Sunne,</l>
               <l>Preſents a greater ſubſtaunce then it is:</l>
               <l>The freſheſt ſummers day doth ſooneſt taint,</l>
               <l>The lothed carrion that it ſeemes to kiſſe:</l>
               <l>Deepe are the blowes made with a mightie Axe,</l>
               <l>That ſinne doth ten times agreuate it ſelfe,</l>
               <l>That is committed in a holie place,</l>
               <l>An euill deed done by authoritie,</l>
               <l>Is ſin and ſubbornation: Decke an Ape</l>
               <l>In tiſſue, and the beautie of the robe,</l>
               <l>Adds but the greater ſcorne vnto the beaſt:</l>
               <l>A ſpatious field of reaſons could I vrge,</l>
               <l>Betweene his gloomie daughter and thy ſhame,</l>
               <l>That poyſon ſhewes worſt in a golden cup,</l>
               <l>Darke night ſeemes darker by the lightning flaſh,</l>
               <l>Lillies that feſter, ſmel far worſe then weeds,</l>
               <l>And euery glory that inclynes to ſin,</l>
               <l>The ſhame is treble, by the oppoſite,</l>
               <l>So leaue I with my bleſſing in thy boſome,</l>
               <l>Which then conuert to a moſt heauie curſe,</l>
               <l>When thou conuerteſt from honors golden name,</l>
               <l>To the blacke faction of bed blotting, ſhame.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Coun:</speaker>
               <l>Ils follow thee, and when my minde turnes ſo,</l>
               <l>My body ſinke, my ſoule in endles woo.</l>
               <stage>Exeunt.</stage>
            </sp>
            <stage>Enter at one doore Derby from Eraunce, At an other doore,
Audley with a Drum.</stage>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Der.</speaker>
               <l>Thrice noble Audley, well incountred heere,</l>
               <l>How is it with our ſoueraigne and his peeres?</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <pb facs="tcp:6638:14"/>
               <speaker>Aud.</speaker>
               <l>Tis full a fortnight ſince I ſaw his highnes,</l>
               <l>What time he ſent me forth to muſter men,</l>
               <l>Which I accordingly haue done and bring them hither,</l>
               <l>In faire aray before his maieſtie:</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>King:</speaker>
               <l>What newes my Lord of Derby from the Emperor.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Der.</speaker>
               <l>As good as we deſire: the Emperor</l>
               <l>Hath yeelded to his highnes friendly ayd,</l>
               <l>And makes our king leiuetenant generall</l>
               <l>In all his lands and large dominions,</l>
               <l>Then <hi>via</hi> for the ſpatious bounds of Fraunce;</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Aud.</speaker>
               <l>What doth his highnes leap to heare theſe newes?</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Der.</speaker>
               <l>I haue not yet found time to open them,</l>
               <l>The king is in his cloſet malcontent,</l>
               <l>For what I know not, but he gaue in charge,</l>
               <l>Till after dinner, none ſhould interrupt him:</l>
               <l>The Counteſſe Salisbury, and her father Warwike,</l>
               <l>Artoyes, and all looke vnderneath the browes.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Aud:</speaker>
               <l>Vndoubtedly then ſome thing is a miſſe.</l>
            </sp>
            <stage>Enter the King.</stage>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Dar.</speaker>
               <l>The Trumpets ſound, the king is now abroad,</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Ar.</speaker>
               <l>Hhere comes his highnes.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Der.</speaker>
               <l>Befall my ſoueraigne, all my ſoueraignes wiſh,</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>King.</speaker>
               <l>Ah that thou wert a Witch to make it ſo.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Der.</speaker>
               <l>The Emperour greeteth you.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Kin.</speaker>
               <l>Would it were the Counteſſe.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Der.</speaker>
               <l>And <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>th accorded to
your highnes ſuite,</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>King.</speaker>
               <l>Thou lyeſt ſhe hath not, but I would ſhe had,</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Au.</speaker>
               <l>All loue and duety to my Lord the King.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Kin.</speaker>
               <l>Well all but one is none, what newes with you?</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Au.</speaker>
               <l>I haue my liege, leuied thoſe horſe and foote,</l>
               <l>According as your charge, and brought them hither.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Kin.</speaker>
               <l>Then let thoſe foote trudge hence vpon thoſe horſe,</l>
               <l>According too our diſcharge and be gonne:</l>
               <l>Darby Ile looke vpon the Counteſſe minde anone,</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Dar</speaker>
               <l>The Counteſſe minde my liege.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Kin.</speaker>
               <l>I meane the Emperour, leaue me alone,</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Au.</speaker>
               <l>What is his mind?</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <pb facs="tcp:6638:14"/>
               <speaker>Dar:</speaker>
               <l>Lets leaue him to his humor.</l>
               <stage>Exunt.</stage>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Ki:</speaker>
               <l>Thus from the harts aboundant ſpeakes the tongue,</l>
               <l>Counteſſe for Emperour, and indeed why not?</l>
               <l>She is as imperator ouer me, and I to her</l>
               <l>Am as a kneeling vaſſaile that obſerues,</l>
               <l>The pleaſure, or diſpleaſure of her eye</l>
            </sp>
            <stage>Enter Lodwike.</stage>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Ki:</speaker>
               <l>What ſaies the more then Cleopatras match,</l>
               <l>To Caeſar now?</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Lo:</speaker>
               <l>That yet my liege ere night,</l>
               <l>She will reſolue your maieſtie.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Ki:</speaker>
               <l>What drum is this that thunders forth this march,</l>
               <l>To ſtart the tender Cupid in my boſome,</l>
               <l>Poore ſhipskin how it braules with him that beateth it:</l>
               <l>Go breake the thundring parchment bottome out,</l>
               <l>And I will teach it to conduct ſweete lynes,</l>
               <l>Vnto the boſome of a heauenly Nymph,</l>
               <l>For I will vſe it as my writing paper,</l>
               <l>And ſo reduce him from a ſcoulding drum,</l>
               <l>To be the herald and deare counſai<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>e bearer,</l>
               <l>Betwixt a goddeſſe, and a mighty king:</l>
               <l>Go bid the diummer learne to touch the Lute,</l>
               <l>Or hang him in the braces of his drum,</l>
               <l>For now we thinke it an vnciuill thing,</l>
               <l>To trouble heauen wrth ſuch harſh reſounds, Away. 
<stage>Exit.</stage>
               </l>
               <l>The quarrell that I haue requires no armes,</l>
               <l>But theſe of myne, and theſe ſhall meete my foe,</l>
               <l>In a deepe march of penytrable grones,</l>
               <l>My eyes ſhall be my arrowes, and my ſighes</l>
               <l>Shall ſerue me as the vantage of the winde,</l>
               <l>To wherle away my ſweeteſt artyilerie:</l>
               <l>Ah but alas ſhe winnes the ſunne of me,</l>
               <l>For that is ſhe her ſelfe, and thence it comes,</l>
               <l>That Poets tearme, the wanton warriour blinde:</l>
               <l>But loue hath eyes as iudgement to his ſteps,</l>
               <l>Till two much loued glory dazies them?</l>
               <l>
                  <pb facs="tcp:6638:15"/>How now.</l>
            </sp>
            <stage>Enter Lodwike.</stage>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Lo.</speaker>
               <l>My liege the drum that ſtroke the luſty march,</l>
               <l>Stands with Prince Edward your thrice valiant ſonne.</l>
            </sp>
            <stage>Enter Prince Edward.</stage>
            <sp>
               <speaker>King.</speaker>
               <l>I ſee the boy, oh how his mothers face,</l>
               <l>Modeld in his, corrects my ſtraid deſire,</l>
               <l>And rates my heart, and chides my theeuiſh eie,</l>
               <l>Who being rich ennough in ſeeing her,</l>
               <l>Yet ſeeke, elſewhere and baſeſt theft is that,</l>
               <l>Which cannot cloke it ſelfe on pouertie.</l>
               <l>Now boy, what newes?</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Pr. E.</speaker>
               <l>I haue aſſembled my deare Lord and father,</l>
               <l>The choyſeſt buds of all our Engliſh blood,</l>
               <l>For our affaires to Fraunce, and heere we come,</l>
               <l>To take direction from your maieſtie.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Kin:</speaker>
               <l>Still do I ſee in him deliniate,</l>
               <l>His mothers viſage, thoſe his eies are hers,</l>
               <l>Who looking wiſtely on me, make me bluſh:</l>
               <l>For faults againſt themſelues, giue euidence,</l>
               <l>Luſt as a fire, and me like lanthorne ſhow,</l>
               <l>Light luſt within themſelues; euen through them
ſelues:</l>
               <l>Away looſe <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>lkes or
wauering vanitie,</l>
               <l>Shall the large limmit of faire Brittayne.</l>
               <l>By me be ouerthrowne, and ſhall I not,</l>
               <l>Maſter this little manſion of my ſelfe;</l>
               <l>Giue me an Armor of eternall ſteele,</l>
               <l>I go to conquer kings, and ſhall I not then</l>
               <l>Subdue my ſelfe, and be my enimies friend,</l>
               <l>It muſt not be, come boy forward, aduaunce,</l>
               <l>Lets with our coullours ſweete the Aire of Fraunce.</l>
            </sp>
            <stage>Enter Lodwike.</stage>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Lo.</speaker>
               <l>My liege, the Counteſſe with a ſmiling cheere.</l>
               <l>Deſires acceſſe vnto your Maieſtie.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>King.</speaker>
               <l>Why there it goes, that verie ſmile of hers,</l>
               <l>
                  <pb facs="tcp:6638:15"/>Hath ranſomed captiue Fraunce, and ſet the
King,</l>
               <l>The Dolphin and the Peeres at liberty,</l>
               <l>Goe leaue me Ned, and reuell with thy friends. 
<stage>Exit Pr.</stage>
               </l>
               <l>Thy mother is but blacke, and thou like her.</l>
               <l>Doſt put it in my minde how foule ſhe is,</l>
               <l>Goe fetch the Counteſſe hether in thy hand, 
<stage>Exit Lod.</stage>
               </l>
               <l>And let her chaſe away theſe winter clouds,</l>
               <l>For ſhee giues beautie both to heauen and earth,</l>
               <l>The ſin is more to hacke and hew poore men,</l>
               <l>Then to embrace in an vnlawfull bed,</l>
               <l>The regiſter of all rarieties,</l>
               <l>Since Letherne Adam, till this youngeſt howre.</l>
            </sp>
            <stage>Enter Counteſſe.</stage>
            <sp>
               <speaker>King.</speaker>
               <l>Goe Lodwike, put thy hand into thy purſe,</l>
               <l>Play, ſpend, giue, ryot, waſt, do what thou wilt,</l>
               <l>So thou wilt hence awhile and leaue me heere.</l>
               <l>Now my ſoules plaiefellow art thou come,</l>
               <l>To ſpeake the more then heauenly word of yea,</l>
               <l>To my obiection in thy beautious loue.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Count.</speaker>
               <l>My father on his bleſſing hath commanded.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>King.</speaker>
               <l>That thou ſhalt yeeld to me.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Coun:</speaker>
               <l>I deare my liege, your due.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>King.</speaker>
               <l>And that my deareſt loue, can be no leſſe,</l>
               <l>Then right for right, and render loue for loue.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Count:</speaker>
               <l>Then wrong for wrong, and endles hate for hate:</l>
               <l>But fith I ſee your maieſtie ſo bent,</l>
               <l>That my vnwillingnes, my husbands loue,</l>
               <l>Your high eſtate, nor no reſpect reſpected,</l>
               <l>Can be my helpe, but that your mightines:</l>
               <l>Will ouerbeare and awe theſe deare regards,</l>
               <l>I bynd my diſcontent to my content,</l>
               <l>And what I would not, Ile compell I will,</l>
               <l>Prouided that your ſelfe remoue thoſe lets,</l>
               <l>That ſtand betweene your highnes loue and mine,</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>King:</speaker>
               <l>Name then faire Counteſſe, and by heauen I will.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Co:</speaker>
               <l>It is their liues that ſtand betweene our loue,</l>
               <l>
                  <pb facs="tcp:6638:16"/>That I would haue chokt vp my ſoueraigne.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Ki.</speaker>
               <l>Whoſe liues my Lady?</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Co.</speaker>
               <l>My thrice loning liege,</l>
               <l>Your Queene, and Salisbury my wedded husband,</l>
               <l>Who liuing haue that tytle in our loue,</l>
               <l>That we cannot beſtow but by their death,</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Ki:</speaker>
               <l>Thy oppoſition is beyond our Law,</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Co.</speaker>
               <l>So is your deſire, if the law</l>
               <l>Can hinder you to execute the one,</l>
               <l>Let it forbid you to attempt the other:</l>
               <l>I Cannot thinke you loue me as you ſay,</l>
               <l>Vnleſſe you do make good what you haue ſworne.</l>
               <l>No mo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>, ethy husband
and the Queene ſhall dye,</l>
               <l>Fairer thou art by farre, then Hero was,</l>
               <l>Beardles Leander not ſo ſtrong as I:</l>
               <l>He ſwome an eaſie curraunt for his loue,</l>
               <l>But I will throng a hellie ſpout of bloud,</l>
               <l>To arryue at Ceſtus where my Hero lyes.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Co:</speaker>
               <l>Nay youle do more, youle make the Ryuerto,</l>
               <l>With their hart bloods, that keepe our loue aſunder,</l>
               <l>Of which my husband, and your wife are twayne.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Ki.</speaker>
               <l>Thy beauty makes them guilty of their death,</l>
               <l>And giues in euidence that they ſhall dye,</l>
               <l>Vpon which verdict I their Iudge condemne them.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Co:</speaker>
               <l>O periurde beautie, more corrupted Iudge:</l>
               <l>When to the great Starre-chamber ore our heads,</l>
               <l>The vniuerſell Seſſions cals to count,</l>
               <l>This packing euill, we both ſhall tremble for it.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Ki.</speaker>
               <l>VVhat ſaies my faire loue, is ſhe reſolute?</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Co.</speaker>
               <l>Reſolute to be diſſolude, and therefore this,</l>
               <l>Keepe but thy word great king, and I am thine,</l>
               <l>Stand where thou doſt, ile part a little from thee</l>
               <l>And ſee how I will yeeld me to thy hands:</l>
               <l>Here by my ſide doth hang my wedding knifes,</l>
               <l>Take thou the one, and with it kill thy Queene</l>
               <l>And learne by me to finde her where ſhe lies</l>
               <l>
                  <pb facs="tcp:6638:16"/>And with this other, Ile diſpatch my loue,</l>
               <l>Which now lies faſt a ſleepe within my hart,</l>
               <l>When they are gone, then Ile conſent to loue:</l>
               <l>Stir not laſciuious king to hinder me,</l>
               <l>My reſolution is more nimbler far,</l>
               <l>Then thy preuention can be in my reſcue,</l>
               <l>And if thou ſtir, I ſtrike, therefore ſtand ſtill,</l>
               <l>And heare the choyce that I will put thee to:</l>
               <l>Either ſweare to leaue thy moſt vnholie ſute,</l>
               <l>And neuer hence forth to ſolicit me,</l>
               <l>Or elſe by heauen, this ſharpe poynted knyfe,</l>
               <l>Shall ſtaine thy earth, with that which thou would
ſtaine:</l>
               <l>My poore chaſt blood, ſweare Edward ſweare,</l>
               <l>Or I will ſtrike and die before thee heere.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>King.</speaker>
               <l>Euen by that power I ſweare that giues me now,</l>
               <l>The power to be aſhamed of my ſelfe,</l>
               <l>I neuer meane to part my lips againe,</l>
               <l>In any words that tends to ſuch a ſute.</l>
               <l>Ariſe true Engliſh Ladie, whom our Ile</l>
               <l>May better boaſt of then euer Romaine might,</l>
               <l>Of her whoſe ranſackt treaſurie hath taskt,</l>
               <l>The vaine indeuor of ſo many pens:</l>
               <l>Ariſe and be my fault, thy honors fame,</l>
               <l>Which after ages ſhall enrich thee with,</l>
               <l>I am awaked from this idle dreame,</l>
               <l>Warwike, my Sonne, Darby, Artoys and Audley,</l>
               <l>Braue warriours all, where are you all this while?</l>
            </sp>
            <stage>Enter all.</stage>
            <sp>
               <l>Warwike, I make thee Warden of the North,</l>
               <l>Thou Prince of Wales, and Audley ſtraight to Sea,</l>
               <l>Scoure to New-hauen, ſome there ſtaie for me:</l>
               <l>My ſelfe, Artoys and Darby will through Flaunders,</l>
               <l>To greete our friends there, and to craue their aide,</l>
               <l>This night will ſcarce ſuffice me to diſcouer,</l>
               <l>My follies ſeege againſt a faithfull louer,</l>
               <l>For ere the Sunne ſhal guide the eſteme skie,</l>
               <l>
                  <pb facs="tcp:6638:17"/>Wele wake him with our Marſhall harmonie.</l>
               <stage>Exeunt.</stage>
            </sp>
            <stage>Enter King Iohn of Fraunce, his two ſonnes, Charles of
Nor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mandie, and Phillip, and the Duke of Lorraine.</stage>
            <sp>
               <speaker>King Iohn.</speaker>
               <l>Heere till our Nauie of a thouſand and ſaile,</l>
               <l>Haue made a breakfaſt to our foe by Sea,</l>
               <l>Let vs incampe to wait their happie ſpeede:</l>
               <l>Lorraine what readines is Edward in?</l>
               <l>How haſt thou heard that he prouided is</l>
               <l>Of marſhiall furniture for this exployt.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Lo:</speaker>
               <l>To lay aſide vnneceſſary ſoothing,</l>
               <l>And not to ſpend the time in circumſtaunce,</l>
               <l>Tis bruted for a certenty my Lord,</l>
               <l>That hees exceeding ſtrongly fortified,</l>
               <l>His ſubiects flocke as willingly to warre,</l>
               <l>As if vnto a tryumph they were led.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Ch:</speaker>
               <l>England was wont to harbour malcontents,</l>
               <l>Blood thirſty, and ſeditious Catelynes,</l>
               <l>Spend thrifts, and ſuch as gape for nothing elſe,</l>
               <l>But changing and alteration of the ſtate,</l>
               <l>And is it poſſible,</l>
               <l>That they are now ſo loyall in them ſelues?</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Lo:</speaker>
               <l>All but the Scot, who ſollemnly proteſts,</l>
               <l>As heere to fore I haue enformd his grace,</l>
               <l>Neuer to ſheath his Sword, or take a truce.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Io:</speaker>
               <l>Ah, thats the anchredge of ſome better hope,</l>
               <l>But on the other ſide, to thinke what friends,</l>
               <l>King Edward hath retaynd in Netherland,</l>
               <l>Among thoſe euer-bibbing Epicures:</l>
               <l>
                  <pb facs="tcp:6638:17"/>Thoſe frothy Dutch men, puft with double
beere,</l>
               <l>That drinke and ſwill in euery place they come,</l>
               <l>Doth not a little aggrauate mine ire,</l>
               <l>Beſides we heare the Emperor conioynes,</l>
               <l>And ſtalls him in his owne authoritie:</l>
               <l>But all the mightier that their number is,</l>
               <l>The greater glory reapes the victory,</l>
               <l>Some friends haue we beſide drum ſtricke power,</l>
               <l>The ſterne Polonian and the warlike Dane:</l>
               <l>The king of Bohemia, and of Cycelie.</l>
               <l>Are all become confederates with vs,</l>
               <l>And as I thinke are marching hither apace,</l>
               <l>But ſoft I heare the muſicke of their drums.</l>
               <l>By which I geſſe that their approch is neare.</l>
            </sp>
            <stage>Enter the King of Bohemia with Danes, and a Polonian Captaine
with other ſoldiers another way.</stage>
            <sp>
               <speaker>King of Boheme.</speaker>
               <l>King Iohn of Fraunce, as league and neighborhood,</l>
               <l>Requires when friends are any way diſtreſt,</l>
               <l>I come to aide thee with my countries force,</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Pol. Cap.</speaker>
               <l>And from great Muſco fearefull to the Turke,</l>
               <l>And lofty Poland, nurſe of hardie men,</l>
               <l>I bring theſe ſeruitors to fight for thee,</l>
               <l>Who willingly will venture in thy cauſe.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>K. Io:</speaker>
               <l>Welcome Bohemian king, and welcome all,</l>
               <l>This your great kindneſſe I will not forget.</l>
               <l>Beſides your plentiful rewards in Crownes,</l>
               <l>That from our Treaſory ye ſhall receiue,</l>
               <l>There comes a hare braind Nation deckt in pride,</l>
               <l>The ſpoyle of whome will be a trebble game,</l>
               <l>And now my hope is full, my ioy complete,</l>
               <l>
                  <pb facs="tcp:6638:18"/>At Sea we are as puiſſant as the force;</l>
               <l>Of Agamemnon in the Hauen of Troy:</l>
               <l>By land with Zerxes we compare of ſtrength,</l>
               <l>Whoſe ſouldiers drancke vp riuers in their thirſt:</l>
               <l>Then Bayard like, blinde ouerweaning Ned,</l>
               <l>To reach at our imperiall dyadem,</l>
               <l>Is either to be ſwallowed of the waues,</l>
               <l>Or hackt a peeces when thou comeſt a ſhore.</l>
            </sp>
            <stage>Enter.</stage>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Mar.</speaker>
               <l>Neere to the coſt I haue diſcribde my Lord,</l>
               <l>As I was buſie in my watchfull charge.</l>
               <l>The proud Armado of king Edwards ſhips,</l>
               <l>Which at the firſt far off when I did ken,</l>
               <l>Seemd as it were a groue of withered pines,</l>
               <l>But drawing neere, their glorious bright aſpect,</l>
               <l>Their ſtreaming Enſignes wrought of coulloured ſilke,</l>
               <l>Like to a meddow full of ſundry flowers,</l>
               <l>Adornes the naked boſome of the earth.</l>
               <l>Maieſticall the order of their courſe,</l>
               <l>Figuring the horned Circle of the Moone,</l>
               <l>And on the top gallant of the Admirall,</l>
               <l>And likewiſe all the handmaides of his trayne:</l>
               <l>The Armes of England and of Fraunce vnite,</l>
               <l>Are quartred equally by Heralds art;</l>
               <l>Thus titely carried with a merrie gale,</l>
               <l>They plough the Ocean hitherward amayne:</l>
               <l>Dare he already crop the Flewer de Luce:</l>
               <l>I hope the hony being gathered thence,</l>
               <l>He with the ſpider afterward approcht</l>
               <l>Shall ſucke forth deadly venom from the leaues,</l>
               <l>But wheres out Nauy, how are they prepared,</l>
               <l>To wing them ſelues againſt this flight of Rauens.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Ma.</speaker>
               <l>They hauing knowledge, brought them by the ſcouts,</l>
               <l>Did breake from Anchor ſtraight, and puft with rage,</l>
               <l>No otherwiſe then were their ſailes with winde,</l>
               <l>Made forth, as when the empty Eagle flies,</l>
               <l>
                  <pb facs="tcp:6638:18"/>To ſatifie his hungrie griping mawe.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Io:</speaker>
               <l>Thees for thy newes, returne vnto thy barke,</l>
               <l>And if thou ſcape the bloody ſtrooke of warre,</l>
               <l>And do ſuruiue the conflict, come againe,</l>
               <l>And let vs heare the manner of the fight, 
<stage>Exit.</stage>
               </l>
               <l>Meane ſpace my Lords, tis beſt we be diſperſt,</l>
               <l>To ſeuerall places leaſt they chaunce to land:</l>
               <l>Firſt you my Lord, with your Bohemian Troupes,</l>
               <l>Shall pitch your battailes on the lower hand,</l>
               <l>My eldeſt ſonne the Duke of Normandie,</l>
               <l>Togeither with this aide of Muſcouites,</l>
               <l>Shall clyme the higher ground an other waye:</l>
               <l>Heere in the middle coſt betwixt you both,</l>
               <l>Phillip my youngeſt boy and I will lodge,</l>
               <l>So Lords begon, and looke vnto your charge. 
<stage>Exunt.</stage>
               </l>
               <l>You ſtand for Fraunce, an Empire faire and large,</l>
               <l>Now tell me Phillip, what is their concept,</l>
               <l>Touching the challenge that the Engliſh make.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Ph:</speaker>
               <l>I ſay my Lord, clayme Edward what he can,</l>
               <l>And bring he nere ſo playne a pedegree,</l>
               <l>Tis you are in poſſeſſion of the Crowne,</l>
               <l>And thats the ſureſt poynt of all the Law:</l>
               <l>But were it not, yet ere he ſhould preuaile,</l>
               <l>Ile make a Conduit of my deareſt blood,</l>
               <l>Or chaſe thoſe ſtragling vpſtarts home againe,</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>King:</speaker>
               <l>Well ſaid young Phillip, call for bread and Wine,</l>
               <l>That we may cheere our ſtomacks with repaſt, 
<stage>The battell hard a farre off.</stage>
               </l>
               <l>To looke our foes more ſternely in the face.</l>
               <l>Now is begun the heauie day at Sea,</l>
               <l>Fight Frenchmen, fight, be like the fielde of Beares,</l>
               <l>VVhen they defend their younglings in their Caues:</l>
               <l>Stir angry Nemeſis the happie helme,</l>
               <l>That with the ſulphur battels of your rage,</l>
               <l>The Engliſh Fleete may be diſperſt and ſunke,</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Ph.</speaker>
               <l>O Father how this eckoing Cannon ſhot. 
<stage>Shot.</stage>
               </l>
               <l>Like ſweete hermonie diſgeſts my cates.</l>
               <l>
                  <pb facs="tcp:6638:19"/>Now boy thou heareſt what thundring terror
tis,</l>
               <l>To buckle for a kingdomes ſouerentie,</l>
               <l>The earth with giddie trembling when it ſhakes,</l>
               <l>Or when the exalations of the aire,</l>
               <l>Breakes in extremitie of lightning flaſh,</l>
               <l>Affrights not more then kings when they diſpoſe,</l>
               <l>To ſhew the rancor of their high ſwolne harts,</l>
               <l>Retreae is ſounded, one ſide hath the worſe, 
<stage>Retreate.</stage>
               </l>
               <l>O if it be the French, ſweete fortune turne,</l>
               <l>And in thy turning change the forward winds,</l>
               <l>That with aduantage of a ſauoring skie,</l>
               <l>Our men may vanquiſh and thither flie.</l>
            </sp>
            <stage>Enter Marriner.</stage>
            <sp>
               <l>My hart miſgiues, ſay mirror of pale death,</l>
               <l>To whome belongs the honor of this day,</l>
               <l>Relate I pray thee, if thy breath will ſerue,</l>
               <l>The ſad diſcourſe of this diſcomfiture.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Mar.</speaker>
               <l>I will my Lord.</l>
               <l>My gratious ſoueraigne, Fraunce hath t<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ne the foyle,</l>
               <l>And boaſting Edward triumphs with ſucceſſe;</l>
               <l>Theſe Iron harted Nauies,</l>
               <l>When laſt I was reporter to your grace,</l>
               <l>Both full of angry ſpleene of hope and feare:</l>
               <l>Haſting to meete each other in the face,</l>
               <l>At laſt conioynd, and by their Admirall,</l>
               <l>Our Admirall encountred manie ſhot,</l>
               <l>By this the other that beheld theſe twaine,</l>
               <l>Giue earneſt peny of a further wracke,</l>
               <l>Like fiery Dragons tooke their haughty flight,</l>
               <l>And like wiſe meeting, from their ſmoky wombes,</l>
               <l>Sent many grym Embaſſadors of death,</l>
               <l>Then gan the day to turne to gloomy night,</l>
               <l>And darkenes did aſwel incloſe the quicke,</l>
               <l>As thoſe that were but newly reft of life,</l>
               <l>No leaſure ſerud for friends to bid farewell,</l>
               <l>And if it had, the hideous noiſe was ſuch,</l>
               <l>
                  <pb facs="tcp:6638:19"/>As ech to other ſeemed deafe and dombe,</l>
               <l>Purple the Sea whoſe channel fild as faſt,</l>
               <l>With ſtreaming gore that from the maymed fell,</l>
               <l>As did her guſhing moyſture breake into,</l>
               <l>The cranny cleftures of the through ſhot planks,</l>
               <l>Heere flew a head diſſuuered from the tronke,</l>
               <l>There mangled armes and legs were toſt a loft,</l>
               <l>As when a wherle winde takes the Summer duſt,</l>
               <l>And ſcatters it in middle of the aire,</l>
               <l>Then might ye ſee the reeling veſſels ſplit,</l>
               <l>And tottering ſink into the ruthleſſe floud,</l>
               <l>Vntill their lofty tops were ſeene no more.</l>
               <l>All ſhifts were tried both for defence and hurt,</l>
               <l>And now the effect of vallor and of force,</l>
               <l>Of reſolution and of a cowardize:</l>
               <l>We liuely pictured, how the one for fame;</l>
               <l>The other by compulſion laid about;</l>
               <l>Much did the <hi>N<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>m
per illa,</hi> that braue ſhip,</l>
               <l>So did the blacke ſnake of Bullen, then which</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>A</hi> bonnier veſſel neuer yet ſpred ſayle,</l>
               <l>But all in vaine, both Sunne, the Wine and tyde,</l>
               <l>Reuolted all vnto our foe mens ſide,</l>
               <l>That we perforce were fayne to giue them way,</l>
               <l>And they are landed, thus my tale is donne,</l>
               <l>We haue vntimly loſt, and they haue woone.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>K. Io:</speaker>
               <l>Then reſts there nothing but with preſent ſpeede,</l>
               <l>To ioyne our ſeueral forces al in one,</l>
               <l>And bid them battaile ere they raingc to farre,</l>
               <l>Come gentle Phillip, let vs hence depart,</l>
               <l>This ſouldiers words haue perſt thy fathers hart.</l>
               <stage>Exeunt</stage>
            </sp>
            <stage>Enter two French men, a woman and two little Children, meet
them another Citizens.</stage>
            <sp>
               <speaker>One:</speaker>
               <l>Wel met my maſters: how now, whats the newes,</l>
               <l>And wherefore are ye laden thus with ſtuffe:</l>
               <l>What is it quarter daie that you remoue,</l>
               <l>And carrie bag and baggage too?</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <pb facs="tcp:6638:20"/>
               <speaker>Two:</speaker>
               <l>Quarter day, I and quartering pay I feare:</l>
               <l>Haue we not heard the newes that flies abroad?</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>One:</speaker>
               <l>What newes?</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Three:</speaker>
               <l>How the French Nauy is deſtroyd at Sea,</l>
               <l>And that the Engliſh Armie is arriued.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>One:</speaker>
               <l>What then?</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Two:</speaker>
               <l>What then quoth you? why iſt not time to flie,</l>
               <l>When enuie and deſtruction is ſo nigh,</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>One.</speaker>
               <l>Content thee man, they are farre enough from hence,</l>
               <l>And will be met I warrant ye to their coſt,</l>
               <l>Before they breake ſo far into the Realme.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Two:</speaker>
               <l>I ſo the Graſhopper doth ſpend the time,</l>
               <l>In mirthfull iollitie till Winter come,</l>
               <l>And then too late he would redeeme his time,</l>
               <l>When frozen cold hath nipt his careleſſe head:</l>
               <l>He that no ſooner will prouide a Cloake,</l>
               <l>Then when he ſees it doth begin to raigne,</l>
               <l>May peraduenture for his negilgence,</l>
               <l>Be throughly waſhed when he ſuſpects it not,</l>
               <l>We that haue charge, and ſuch a trayne as this,</l>
               <l>Muſt looke in time, to looke for them and vs,</l>
               <l>Leaſt when we would, we cannot be relieued.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>One:</speaker>
               <l>Be like you then diſpaire of ill ſucceſſe,</l>
               <l>And thinke your Country will be ſubiugate.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Three.</speaker>
               <l>We cannot tell, tis good to feare the worſt.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>One:</speaker>
               <l>Yet rather fight, then like vnnaturall ſonnes,</l>
               <l>For ſake your louing parents in diſtreſſe.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Two.</speaker>
               <l>Tuſh they that haue already taken armes,</l>
               <l>Are manie fearefull millions in reſpect</l>
               <l>Of that ſmall handfull of our enimies:</l>
               <l>But tis a rightfull quarrell muſt preuaile,</l>
               <l>Edward is ſonnne vnto our late kings ſiſter,</l>
               <l>Where Iohn Valoys, is three degrees remoued.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Wo:</speaker>
               <l>Beſides, there goes a Propheſie abroad,</l>
               <l>Publiſhed by one that was a Fryer once,</l>
               <l>Whoſe Oracles haue many times prooued true,</l>
               <l>
                  <pb facs="tcp:6638:20"/>And now he ſayes the tyme will ſhortly
come,</l>
               <l>When as a Lyon rowſed in the weſt,</l>
               <l>Shall carie hence the fluerdeluce of France,</l>
               <l>Theſe I can tell yee and ſuch like ſurmiſes,</l>
               <l>Strike many french men cold vnto the heart:</l>
            </sp>
            <stage>Enter a French man.</stage>
            <sp>
               <l>Flie cuntry men and cytizens of France,</l>
               <l>Sweete flowring peace the roote of happie life,</l>
               <l>Is quite a bandoned and expulſt the lande,</l>
               <l>Inſted of whome ranſackt conſtraining warre,</l>
               <l>Syts like to Rauens vppon your houſes topps,</l>
               <l>Slaughter and miſchiefe walke within your ſtreets.</l>
               <l>And vnreſtrained make hauock as they paſſe,</l>
               <l>The forme whereof euen now my ſelfe beheld,</l>
               <l>Vpon this faire mountaine whence I came,</l>
               <l>For ſo far of as I directed mine eies,</l>
               <l>I might perceaue fiue Cities all on fire,</l>
               <l>Come fieldes and vineyards burning like an ouen,</l>
               <l>And as the leaking vapour in the wind,</l>
               <l>I tourned but a ſide I like wiſe might diſſerne.</l>
               <l>The poore inhabitants eſcapt the flame,</l>
               <l>Fall numberles vpon the ſouldiers pikes,</l>
               <l>Three waies theſe dredfull miniſters of wrath,</l>
               <l>Do tread the meaſures of their tragicke march,</l>
               <l>Vpon the right hand comes the conquering King,</l>
               <l>Vpon the lefte is hot vnbridled ſonne,</l>
               <l>And in the midſt our nations glittering hoaſt,</l>
               <l>All which though diſtant yet conſpire in one,</l>
               <l>To leaue a deſolation where they come,</l>
               <l>Flie therefore Citizens if you be wiſe,</l>
               <l>Seeke out ſom habitation further of,</l>
               <l>Here if you ſtaie your wiues will be a buſed,</l>
               <l>Your treaſure ſharde before your weeping eies,</l>
               <l>Shelter you your ſelues for now the ſtorme doth
riſe<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <pb facs="tcp:6638:21"/>Away, away, me thinks I heare their drums,</l>
               <l>Ah wreched France, I greatly feare thy fal,</l>
               <l>Thy glory ſhaketh like a tottering wall.</l>
            </sp>
            <stage>Enter King Edward and the Erle of Darby With Souldiors, and
Gobin de Graie.</stage>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Kin:</speaker>
               <l>Wheres the French man by whoſe cunning guide,</l>
               <l>We found the ſhalow of this Riuer Sone,</l>
               <l>And had direction how to paſſe the ſea.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Go:</speaker>
               <l>Here my good Lord.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Kin:</speaker>
               <l>How art thou calde, tell me thy name.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Go:</speaker>
               <l>Gobin de Graie if pleaſe your excellence,</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Kin:</speaker>
               <l>Then Gobin for the ſeruice thou haſt done,</l>
               <l>We here inlarge and giue thee liberty,</l>
               <l>And for recompenc beſide this good,</l>
               <l>Thou ſhalt receiue fiue hundred markes in golde,</l>
               <l>I know not how we ſhould haue met our ſonne,</l>
               <l>Whom now in heart I wiſh I might behold.</l>
            </sp>
            <stage>Enter Artoyes.</stage>
            <sp>
               <l>Good newes my Lord the prince is hard at hand,</l>
               <l>And with him comes Lord Awdley and the reſt,</l>
               <l>Whome ſince our landing we could neuer meet.</l>
            </sp>
            <stage>Enter Prince Edward, Lord Awdley and Souldiers.</stage>
            <sp>
               <speaker>K. E:</speaker>
               <l>Welcome faire Prince, how haſt thou ſped my ſonne,</l>
               <l>Since thy arriuall on the coaſte of Fraunce?</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Pr. Ed:</speaker>
               <l>Succeſfullie I thanke the gratious heauens,</l>
               <l>Some of their ſtrongeſt Cities we haue wonne,</l>
               <l>As Harſlen, Lie, Crotag, and Carentigne,</l>
               <l>And others waſted, leauing at our heeles,</l>
               <l>A wide apparant feild and beaten path,</l>
               <l>For ſollitarines to progreſſe in,</l>
               <l>Yet thoſe that would ſubmit we kindly pardned,</l>
               <l>For who in ſcorne refuſed our poffered peace,</l>
               <l>Indurde the penaltie of ſharpe reuenge.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Ki. Ed:</speaker>
               <l>Ah Fraunce, why ſhouldeſt thou be this obſtinate,</l>
               <l>Agaynſt the kind imbracement of thy friends,</l>
               <l>
                  <pb facs="tcp:6638:21"/>How gently had we thought to touch thy breſt,</l>
               <l>And ſet our foot vpon thy tender mould,</l>
               <l>But that in froward and diſdainfull pride</l>
               <l>Thou like a skittiſh and vntamed coult,</l>
               <l>Doſt ſtart aſide and ſtrike vs with thy heeles,</l>
               <l>But tel me Ned, in all thy warlike courſe,</l>
               <l>Haſt thou not ſeene the vſurping King of Fraunce.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Pri.</speaker>
               <l>Yes my good Lord, and not two owers ago,</l>
               <l>With full a hundred thouſand fighting men,</l>
               <l>Vppon the one ſide with the riuers banke,</l>
               <l>And on the other both his multitudes,</l>
               <l>I feard he would haue cropt our ſmaller power,</l>
               <l>But happily perceiuing your approch,</l>
               <l>He hath with drawen himſelfe to Creſſey plaines,</l>
               <l>Where as it ſeemeth by his good araie.</l>
               <l>He meanes to byd vs battaile preſently,</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Kin. Ed:</speaker>
               <l>He ſhall be welcome thats the thing we craue.</l>
            </sp>
            <stage>Enter King Iohn, Dukes of Normanndy and Lorraine, King of
Boheme, yong Phillip, and Souldiers.</stage>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Iohn.</speaker>
               <l>Edward know that Iohn the true king of Fraunce,</l>
               <l>Muſing thouſt o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ldſt incroach vppon his land,</l>
               <l>And in thy tyranous proceeding ſlay,</l>
               <l>His faithfull ſubiects, and ſubuert his Townes,</l>
               <l>Spits in thy face, and in this manner folowing,</l>
               <l>Obraids thee with thine arrogant intruſion,</l>
               <l>Firſt I condeme thee for a fugitiue,</l>
               <l>A theeuiſh pyrate, and a needie mate,</l>
               <l>One that hath either no abyding place,</l>
               <l>Or elſe inhabiting ſome barraine ſoile,</l>
               <l>Where neither hea<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>b
or f<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>utfull graine is had,</l>
               <l>Doeſt altogether liue by pilfering,</l>
               <l>Next, inſomuch thou haſt infringed thy faith,</l>
               <l>Broke leage and ſolemne couenant made with mee,</l>
               <l>I hould thee for a falſe pernitious wretch,</l>
               <l>And laſt of all, although I ſcorne to cope</l>
               <l>
                  <pb facs="tcp:6638:22"/>With one ſuch inferior to my ſelfe,</l>
               <l>Yet in reſpect thy thirſt is all for golde,</l>
               <l>They labour rather to be feared then loued,</l>
               <l>To ſatiſfie thy luſt in either parte</l>
               <l>Heere am I come and with me haue I brought,</l>
               <l>Exceding ſtore of treaſure, perle, and coyne,</l>
               <l>Leaue therfore now to perſecute the weake,</l>
               <l>And armed entring conflict with the armd,</l>
               <l>Let it be ſeene mongeſt other pettie thefts,</l>
               <l>How thou canſt win this pillage manfully.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>K: Ed:</speaker>
               <l>If gall or wormwood haue a pleaſant taſt,</l>
               <l>Then is thy ſallutation hony ſweete,</l>
               <l>But as the one hath no ſuch propertie,</l>
               <l>So is the other moſt ſatiricall:</l>
               <l>Yet wot how I regarde thy worthles tants,</l>
               <l>If thou haue vttred them to foile my fame,</l>
               <l>Or dym the reputation of my birth,</l>
               <l>Know that thy woluiſh barking cannot hurt,</l>
               <l>If ſlylie to inſinuate with the worlde,</l>
               <l>And with a ſtrumpets artifitiall line,</l>
               <l>To painte thy vitious and deformed cauſe,</l>
               <l>Bee well aſſured the counterfeit will fade,</l>
               <l>And in the end thy fowle defects be ſeene,</l>
               <l>But if thou didſt it to prouoke me on,</l>
               <l>As who ſhould ſaie I were but timerous,</l>
               <l>Or coldly negligent did need a ſpurre,</l>
               <l>Bethinke thy ſelfe howe ſlacke I was at ſea,</l>
               <l>Now ſince my landing I haue wonn no townes,</l>
               <l>Entered no further but vpon the coaſt,</l>
               <l>And there haue euer ſince ſecurelie ſlept,</l>
               <l>But if I haue bin other wiſe imployd,</l>
               <l>Imagin Valoys whether I intende</l>
               <l>Toſkirmiſh, not for pillage but for the Crowne,</l>
               <l>Which thou doſt weare and that I vowe to haue,</l>
               <l>Or one of vs ſhall fall in to this graue,</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <pb facs="tcp:6638:22"/>
               <speaker>Pri Ed:</speaker>
               <l>Looke not for croſſe inuectiues at our hands,</l>
               <l>Or rayling execrations of deſpight,</l>
               <l>Let creeping ſerpents hide in hollow banckes,</l>
               <l>Sting with theyr tongues; we haue remorſeles ſwordes,</l>
               <l>And they ſhall pleade for vs and our affaires,</l>
               <l>Yet thus much breefly by my fathers leaue,</l>
               <l>As all the immodeſt poyſon of thy throat,</l>
               <l>Is ſcandalous and moſt notorious lyes,</l>
               <l>And our pretended quarell is truly iuſt,</l>
               <l>So end the battaile when we meet to daie,</l>
               <l>May eyther of vs proſper and preuaile,</l>
               <l>Or luckles curſt, receue eternall ſhame.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Kin Ed:</speaker>
               <l>That needs no further queſtion, and I knowe</l>
               <l>His conſcience witneſſeth it is my right,</l>
               <l>Therfore Valoys ſay, wilt thou yet reſigne,</l>
               <l>Before the ſickles thruſt into the Corne,</l>
               <l>Or that inkindled fury, turne to flame:</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Ioh:</speaker>
               <l>Edward I know what right thou haſt in France,</l>
               <l>And ere I baſely will reſigne my Crowne,</l>
               <l>This Champion field ſhallbe a poole of bloode,</l>
               <l>And all our proſpect as a ſlaughter houſe,</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Pr Ed:</speaker>
               <l>I that approues thee tyrant what thou art,</l>
               <l>No father, king, or ſhepheard of thy realme,</l>
               <l>But one that teares her entrailes with thy handes,</l>
               <l>And like a thirſtie tyger ſuckſt her bloud.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Aud:</speaker>
               <l>You peeres of France, why do you follow him,</l>
               <l>That is ſo prodigall to ſpend your liues?</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Ch:</speaker>
               <l>Whom ſhould they follow, aged impotent,</l>
               <l>But he that is their true borne ſoueraigne?</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Kin:</speaker>
               <l>Obraidſt thou him, becauſe within his face,</l>
               <l>Time hath ingraud deep caracters of age:</l>
               <l>Know that theſe graue ſchollers of experience,</l>
               <l>Like ſtiffe growen oakes, will ſtand unmouable,</l>
               <l>When whirle wind quickly turnes vp yonger trees.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Dar.</speaker>
               <l>Was euer anie of thy fathers houſe king,</l>
               <l>But thy ſelfe, before this preſent time,</l>
               <l>Edwards great linage by the mothers ſide,</l>
               <l>
                  <pb facs="tcp:6638:23"/>Fiue hundred yeeres hath helde the ſcepter
vp,</l>
               <l>Iudge then conſpiratours by this deſcent,</l>
               <l>Which is the true borne ſoueraigne this or that.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Pri:</speaker>
               <l>Father range your battailes, prate no more,</l>
               <l>Theſe Engliſh fame would ſpend the time in wodrs,</l>
               <l>That night approching, they might eſcape vnfought.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>K Ioh:</speaker>
               <l>Lords and my louing Subiects knowes the time,</l>
               <l>That your intended force muſt bide the touch,</l>
               <l>Therfore my frinds conſider this in breefe,</l>
               <l>He that you fight for is your naturall King,</l>
               <l>He againſt whom you fight a forrener:</l>
               <l>He that you fight for rules in clemencie,</l>
               <l>And fames you with a mild and gentle byt,</l>
               <l>He againſt whome you fight if hee preuaile,</l>
               <l>Will ſtraight in throne himſelfe in tyrranie,</l>
               <l>Make ſlaues of you, and with a heauie hand</l>
               <l>Curtall and courb your ſweteſt libertie.</l>
               <l>Then to protect your Country and your King,</l>
               <l>Let but the haughty Courrage of your hartes,</l>
               <l>Anſwere the number of your able handes,</l>
               <l>And we ſhall quicklie chaſe theis fugitiues,</l>
               <l>For whats this Edward but a belly god,</l>
               <l>A tender and laſciuious wantonnes,</l>
               <l>That thother daie was almoſt dead for loue,</l>
               <l>And what I praie you is his goodly gard,</l>
               <l>Such as but ſcant them of their chines of beefe,</l>
               <l>And take awaie their downie featherbedes,</l>
               <l>And preſently they are as reſty ſtiffe,</l>
               <l>As twere a many ouer ridden iades,</l>
               <l>Then French men ſcorne that ſuch ſhould be your Lords</l>
               <l>And rather bind ye them in captiue bands,</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>All Fra:</speaker>
               <l>Viue le Roy, God ſaue King Iohn of France.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Io:</speaker>
               <l>Now on this plaine of Creſſie ſpred your ſelues,</l>
               <l>And Edward when thou dareſt, begin the fight:</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Ki. Ed:</speaker>
               <l>We preſently wil meet thee Iohn of Fraunce,</l>
               <l>And Engliſh Lordes let vs reſolue the daie,</l>
               <l>Either to cleere vs of that ſcandalous cryme,</l>
               <l>
                  <pb facs="tcp:6638:23"/>Or be intombed in our innocence,</l>
               <l>And Ned, becauſe this battell is the firſt,</l>
               <l>That euer yet thou foughteſt in pitched field,</l>
               <l>As ancient cuſtome is of Martialiſts,</l>
               <l>To dub thee with the tipe of chiualrie,</l>
               <l>In ſolemne manner wee will giue thee armes,</l>
               <l>Come therefore Heralds, orderly bring forth,</l>
               <l>A ſtrong attirement for the prince my ſonne.</l>
            </sp>
            <stage>Enter foure Heraldes bringing in a coate armour, a helmet, a
lance, and a ſhield.</stage>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Kin:</speaker>
               <l>Edward Plantagenet, in the name of God,</l>
               <l>As with this armour I impall thy breaſt,</l>
               <l>So be thy noble vnrelenting heart,</l>
               <l>Wald in with flint of matchleſſe fortitude,</l>
               <l>That neuer baſe affections enter there,</l>
               <l>Fight and be valiant, conquere where thou comſt,</l>
               <l>Now follow Lords, and do him honor to.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Dar:</speaker>
               <l>Edward Plantagenet prince of Wales,</l>
               <l>As I do ſet this helmet on thy head,</l>
               <l>Where with the chamber of this braine is fenſt,</l>
               <l>So may thy temples with Bellonas hand,</l>
               <l>Be ſtill adornd with lawrell victorie,</l>
               <l>Fight and be valiant, conquer where thou comſt.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Aud.</speaker>
               <l>Edward Plantagenet prince of Wales,</l>
               <l>Receiue this lance into thy manly hand,</l>
               <l>Vſe it in faſhion of a braſen pen,</l>
               <l>To drawe forth bloudie ſtratagems in France,</l>
               <l>And print thy valiant deeds in honors booke,</l>
               <l>Fight and be valiant, vanquiſh where thou comſt.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Art:</speaker>
               <l>Edward Plantagener prince of Wales,</l>
               <l>Hold take this target, weare it on thy arme,</l>
               <l>And may the view thereof like Perſcus ſhield,</l>
               <l>Aſtoniſh and transforme thy gazing foes</l>
               <l>To ſenſeleſſe images of meger death,</l>
               <l>Fight and be valiant, couquer where thou comſt.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Ki.</speaker>
               <l>Now wants there nought but knighthood, which deferd</l>
               <l>
                  <pb facs="tcp:6638:24"/>Wee leaue till thou haſt won it in the
fielde,</l>
               <l>My gratious father and yee forwarde peeres,</l>
               <l>This honor you haue done me animates,</l>
               <l>And chears my greene yet ſcarſe appearing ſtrength,</l>
               <l>With comfortable good perſaging ſignes,</l>
               <l>No otherwiſe then did ould Iacobes wordes,</l>
               <l>When as he breathed his bleſſings on his ſonnes,</l>
               <l>Theſe hallowed giftes of yours when I prophane,</l>
               <l>Or vſe them not to glory of my God,</l>
               <l>To patronage the fatherles and poore,</l>
               <l>Or for the benefite of Englands peace,</l>
               <l>Be numbe my ioynts, waxe feeble both mine armes,</l>
               <l>Wither my hart that like a ſaples tree,</l>
               <l>I may remayne the map of infamy.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>K. Ed:</speaker>
               <l>Then this our ſteelde Battailes ſhall be rainged,</l>
               <l>The leading of the vowarde Ned is thyne,</l>
               <l>To dignifie whoſe luſty ſpirit the more</l>
               <l>We temper it with Audlys grauitie,</l>
               <l>That co<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>age and
experience ioynd in one,</l>
               <l>Your manage may be ſecond vnto none,</l>
               <l>For the mayne battells I will guide my ſelfe,</l>
               <l>And Darby in the rereward march behind,</l>
               <l>That orderly diſpoſd and ſet in ray,</l>
               <l>Let vs to horſe and God graunt vs the daye.</l>
               <stage>Exeunt:</stage>
            </sp>
            <stage>Alarum. Enter a many French men flying. After them Prince
Edward runing.</stage>
            <stage>Then enter King Iohn and Duke of Loraine.</stage>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Iohn.</speaker>
               <l>Oh Lorrain ſay, what meane our men to fly,</l>
               <l>Our nomber is far greater then our foes,</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Lor.</speaker>
               <l>The garriſon of Genoacs my Lorde,</l>
               <l>That cam from Paris weary with their march,</l>
               <l>Grudging to be ſoddenly imployd,</l>
               <l>No ſooner in the forefront tooke their place.</l>
               <l>But ſtraite retyring ſo diſmaide the reſt,</l>
               <l>As likewiſe they betook themſelues to flight</l>
               <l>In which for haſt to make a ſafe eſcape,</l>
               <l>
                  <pb facs="tcp:6638:24"/>More in the cluſtering throng are preſt to
death,</l>
               <l>Then by the ennimie a thouſand fold.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>K. Io:</speaker>
               <l>O hapleſſe fortune, let vs yet aſſay,</l>
               <l>If we can counſell ſome of them to ſtay.</l>
            </sp>
            <stage>Enter King Edward and Audley.</stage>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Ki, E:</speaker>
               <l>Lord Audley, whiles our ſonne is in the chaſe,</l>
               <l>With draw our powers vnto this little hill,</l>
               <l>And heere a ſeaſon let vs breath our ſelues,</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Au.</speaker>
               <l>I will my Lord.</l>
               <stage>Exit, ſound Retreat.</stage>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>K. Ed.</speaker>
               <l>Iuſt dooming heauen, whoſe ſecret prouidence,</l>
               <l>To our groſſe iudgement is inſcrutable,</l>
               <l>How are we bound to praiſe thy wondrous works,</l>
               <l>That haſt this day giuen way vnto the right,</l>
               <l>And made the wicked ſtumble at them ſelues.</l>
            </sp>
            <stage>Enter Artoys.</stage>
            <sp>
               <l>Reſcue king Edward, reſcue, for thy ſonne,</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Kin:</speaker>
               <l>Reſcue Artoys, what is he priſoner?</l>
               <l>Or by violence fell beſide his horſe.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Ar.</speaker>
               <l>Neither my Lord, but narrowly beſet,</l>
               <l>With turning Frenchmen, whom he did perſue,</l>
               <l>As tis impoſſible that he ſhould ſcape.</l>
               <l>Except your highnes preſently deſcend.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Kin:</speaker>
               <l>Tut let him fight, we gaue him armes to day.</l>
               <l>And he is laboring for a knighthood man.</l>
            </sp>
            <stage>Enter Derby.</stage>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Da:</speaker>
               <l>The Prince my Lord, the Prince, oh ſuccour him,</l>
               <l>Hees cloſe incompaſt with a world of odds.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Ki:</speaker>
               <l>Then will he win a world of honor to,</l>
               <l>If he by vallour can redeeme him thence,</l>
               <l>If not, what remedy, we haue more ſonnes,</l>
               <l>Then one to comfort our declyning age.</l>
            </sp>
            <stage>Enter Audley.</stage>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Au,</speaker>
               <l>Renowned Edward, giue me leaue I pray,</l>
               <l>To lead my ſouldiers where I may releeue,</l>
               <l>Your Graces ſonne, in danger to be ſlayne,</l>
               <l>The ſnares of French, like Emmets on a banke,</l>
               <l>
                  <pb facs="tcp:6638:25"/>Muſter about him whileſt he Lion like,</l>
               <l>Intangled in the net of their aſſaults,</l>
               <l>Frantiquely wrends and byts the wouen toyle,</l>
               <l>But all in vaine, he cannot free him ſelfe.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>K: Ed:</speaker>
               <l>Audley content, I will not haue a man,</l>
               <l>On paine of death ſent forth to ſuccour him:</l>
               <l>This is the day, ordaynd by deſteny,</l>
               <l>To ſeaſon his courage with thoſe greeuous thoughts,</l>
               <l>That if he breaketh out, Neſtors yeares on earth,</l>
               <l>Will make him ſauor ſtill of this exployt.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Dar:</speaker>
               <l>Ah but he ſhall not liue to ſee thoſe dayes,</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Ki:</speaker>
               <l>Why then his Ephitaph, is laſting prayſe.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>An:</speaker>
               <l>Yet good my Lord, tis too much wilfulnes,</l>
               <l>To let his blood be ſpilt that may be ſaude,</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Kin.</speaker>
               <l>Exclayme no more, for none of you can tell,</l>
               <l>Whether a borrowed aid will ſerue or no,</l>
               <l>Perhapps he is already ſlayne or tane:</l>
               <l>And dare a Falcon when ſhees in her flight,</l>
               <l>And euer after ſheele be huggard like:</l>
               <l>Let Edward be deliuered by our hands,</l>
               <l>And ſtill in danger hele expect the like,</l>
               <l>But if himſelfe, himſelfe redeeme from thence,</l>
               <l>He wil haue vanquiſht cheerefull death and feare,</l>
               <l>And euer after dread their force no more,</l>
               <l>Then if they were but babes or Captiue ſlaues.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Aud.</speaker>
               <l>O cruell Father, farewell Edward then.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Da:</speaker>
               <l>Farewell ſweete Prince, the hope of chiualry,</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Art:</speaker>
               <l>O would my life might ranſome him from death.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>K. Ed:</speaker>
               <l>But ſoft me thinkes I heare,</l>
               <l>The diſmall charge of Trumpets loud retreat:</l>
               <l>All are not ſlayne I hope that went with him,</l>
               <l>Some will returne with tidings good or bad.</l>
            </sp>
            <stage>Enter Prince Edward in tryumph, bearing in his hande hit
ſhiuered Launce, and the King of Boheme, borne before, wrapt in the
Coullours: They runne and imbrace him.</stage>
            <sp>
               <pb facs="tcp:6638:25"/>
               <speaker>Aud,</speaker>
               <l>O ioyfull ſight, victorious Edward liues.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Der:</speaker>
               <l>Welcome braue Prince.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Ki:</speaker>
               <l>Welcome Plantagenet.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Pr.</speaker>
               <l> 
                  <stage>kneele and kiſſe his fathers hand</stage> Firſt
hauing donne my duety as beſeemed</l>
               <l>Lords I<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>e greet you
all with harty thanks,</l>
               <l>And now behold after my winters toyle,</l>
               <l>My paynefull voyage on the boyſtrous ſea,</l>
               <l>Of warres deuouring gulphes and ſteely rocks,</l>
               <l>I bring my fraught vnto the wiſhed port,</l>
               <l>My Summers hope, my trauels ſweet reward:</l>
               <l>And heere with humble duety I preſent,</l>
               <l>This ſacrifice, this firſt fruit of my ſword,</l>
               <l>Cropt and cut downe euen at the gate of death:</l>
               <l>The king of Boheme father whome I ſlue,</l>
               <l>Whom you ſayd, had intrencht me round about,</l>
               <l>And laye as thicke vpon my battered creſt,</l>
               <l>As on an Anu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ll with
their ponderous glaues,</l>
               <l>Yet marble courage, ſtill did vnderprop,</l>
               <l>And when my weary armes with often blowes,</l>
               <l>Like the continuall laboring Wood-mans Axe,</l>
               <l>That is enioynd to fell a load of Oakes,</l>
               <l>Began to faulter, ſtraight I would recouer:</l>
               <l>My gifts you gaue me, and my zealous vow,</l>
               <l>And then new courage made me freſh againe,</l>
               <l>That in deſpight I c<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>d my paſſage
forth.</l>
               <l>And put the multitude to ſpeedy flyght: 
<stage>his Sword borne by a Soldier.</stage>
               </l>
               <l>Lo this hath Edwards hand fild your requeſt,</l>
               <l>And done I hope the duety of a Knight</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Ki:</speaker>
               <l>I well thou haſt deſerud a knight-hood Ned,</l>
               <l>And therefore with thy ſword, yet reaking warme,</l>
               <l>With blood of thoſe that fought to be thy bane,</l>
               <l>Ariſe Prince Edward, truſty knight at armes,</l>
               <l>This day thou haſt confounded me with ioy,</l>
               <l>And proude thy ſelfe fit heire vnto a king:</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Pr:</speaker>
               <l>Heere is a note my gratious Lord of thoſe,</l>
               <l>That in this conflict of our foes were ſlaine,</l>
               <l>
                  <pb facs="tcp:6638:26"/>Eleuen Princes of eſteeme, Foure ſcore
Barons,</l>
               <l>A hundred and twenty knights, and thirty thouſand</l>
               <l>Common ſouldiers, and of our men a thouſand.</l>
               <l>Our God be praiſed, Now Iohn of Fraunce I hope,</l>
               <l>Thou knoweſt King Edward for no wantoneſſe,</l>
               <l>No loue ſicke cockney nor his ſouldiers iades,</l>
               <l>But which way is the fearefull king eſcapt?</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Pr:</speaker>
               <l>Towards Poyctiers noble father, and his ſonnes,</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>King.</speaker>
               <l>Ned, thou and Audley ſhall purſue them ſtill,</l>
               <l>Myſelfe and Derby will to Calice ſtreight;</l>
               <l>And there begyrt that Hauen towne with ſeege:</l>
               <l>Now lies it on an vpſhot, therefore ſtrike,</l>
               <l>And wiſtlie follow whiles the games on foote.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Ki.</speaker>
               <l>What Pictures this.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Pr:</speaker>
               <l>A Pellican my Lord,</l>
               <l>Wounding her boſome with her crooked beak,</l>
               <l>That ſo her neſt of young ones might be fed,</l>
               <l>With drops of blood that iſſue from her hart,</l>
               <l>The motto <hi>Sic &amp; vos,</hi> and ſo ſhould you,</l>
               <stage>Exeunt.</stage>
            </sp>
            <stage>Enter Lord Mountford with a Coronet in his hande, with him the
Earle of Salisbury.</stage>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Mo:</speaker>
               <l>My Lord of Salisbury ſince by our aide,</l>
               <l>Mine ennemie Sir Charles of Bloys is ſlaine,</l>
               <l>And I againe am quietly poſſeſt,</l>
               <l>In Btittaines Dukedome, knowe that I reſolue,</l>
               <l>For this kind furtherance of your king and you,</l>
               <l>To ſweare allegeance to his maieſty:</l>
               <l>In figne where of receiue this Coronet,</l>
               <l>Beare it vnto him, and with all mine othe,</l>
               <l>Neuer to be but Edwards faithful friend.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Sa:</speaker>
               <l>I take it Mountſort, thus I hope eare long,</l>
               <l>The whole Dominions of the Realme of Fraunce</l>
               <l>Wilbe ſurrendred to his conquering hand: 
<stage>Exit</stage>
               </l>
               <l>Now if I knew but ſafely how to paſſe,</l>
               <l>I would to Calice gladly meete his Grace,</l>
               <l>Whether I am by letters certified.</l>
               <l>
                  <pb facs="tcp:6638:26"/>Yet he intends to haue his hoſt remooude,</l>
               <l>It ſhal be ſo, this pollicy will ſerue,</l>
               <l>Ho whoſe within? bring Villiers to me.</l>
            </sp>
            <stage>Enter Villeirs.</stage>
            <sp>
               <l>Villiers, thou knoweſt thou art my priſoner,</l>
               <l>And that I might for ranſome if I would,</l>
               <l>Require of thee a hundred thouſand Francks,</l>
               <l>Or elſe retayne and keepe thee captiue ſtill:</l>
               <l>But ſo it is, that for a ſmaller charge,</l>
               <l>Thou maiſt be quit and if thou wilt thy ſelfe,</l>
               <l>And this it is, procure me but a paſport,</l>
               <l>Of Charles the Duke of Normandy, that I,</l>
               <l>Without reſtraint may haue recourſe to Callis,</l>
               <l>Through all the Countries where he hath to doe.</l>
               <l>Which thou maiſt eaſely obtayne I thinke,</l>
               <l>By reaſon I haue often heard thee ſay,</l>
               <l>He and thou were ſtudents once together:</l>
               <l>And then thou ſhalt be ſet at libertie,</l>
               <l>How ſaieſt thou, wilt thou vndertake to do it?</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Vil.</speaker>
               <l>I will my Lord, but I muſt ſpeake with him.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Sa.</speaker>
               <l>Why ſo thou ſhalt, take Horſe and poſt from hence,</l>
               <l>Onely before thou goeſt, ſweare by thy faith,</l>
               <l>That if thou canſt not compaſſe my deſire,</l>
               <l>Thou wilt returne my priſoner backe againe,</l>
               <l>And that ſhalbe ſufficient warrant for mee.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Vil:</speaker>
               <l>To that condition I agree my Lord,</l>
               <l>And will vnfaynedly performe the ſame.</l>
               <stage>Exit.</stage>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Sal:</speaker>
               <l>Farewell Villiers,</l>
               <l>Thus once I meane to trie a French mans faith.</l>
               <stage>Exit.</stage>
            </sp>
            <stage>Enter King Edward and Derby with Souldiers.</stage>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Kin:</speaker>
               <l>Since they refuſe our profered league my Lord,</l>
               <l>And will not ope their gates and let vs in,</l>
               <l>We will intrench our ſelues on euery ſide,</l>
               <l>That neither vituals, nor ſupply of men,</l>
               <l>May come to ſuccour this accurſed towne,</l>
               <l>Famine ſhall combate where our ſwords are ſtopt.</l>
            </sp>
            <stage>
               <pb facs="tcp:6638:27"/>Enter ſixe poore Frenchmen.</stage>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Der.</speaker>
               <l>The promiſed aid that made them ſtand aloofe,</l>
               <l>Is now retirde and gone an other way:</l>
               <l>It will repent them of their ſtubborne will,</l>
               <l>But what are theſe poore ragged ſlaues my Lord?</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Ki: Edw:</speaker>
               <l>Aske what they are, it ſeemes they come from Callis.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Der.</speaker>
               <l>You wretched patterns of diſpayre and woe,</l>
               <l>What are you liuing men, er glyding ghoſts,</l>
               <l>Crept from your graues to walke vpon the earth,</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Poore:</speaker>
               <l>No ghoſts my Lord, but men that breath a life,</l>
               <l>Farre worſe then is the quiet ſleepe of death:</l>
               <l>Wee are diſtreſſed poore inhabitants,</l>
               <l>That long haue been deſeaſed, ſicke and lame;</l>
               <l>And now becauſe we are not fit to ſerue,</l>
               <l>The Captayne of the towne hath thruſt vs foorth,</l>
               <l>That ſo expence of victuals may be ſaued.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>K. Ed.</speaker>
               <l>A charitable deed no doubt, and worthy praiſe:</l>
               <l>But how do you imagine then to ſpeed?</l>
               <l>We are your enemies in ſuch a caſe,</l>
               <l>We can no leſſe but put ye to the ſword,</l>
               <l>Since when we proffered truce, it was refuſde,</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>So:</speaker>
               <l>And if your grace no otherwiſe vouchſafe,</l>
               <l>As welcome death is vnto vs as life.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Ki:</speaker>
               <l>Poore ſilly men, much wrongd, and more diſtreſt,</l>
               <l>Go Derby go, and ſee they be relieud,</l>
               <l>Command that victuals be appoynted them,</l>
               <l>And giue to euery one fiue Crownes a peece:</l>
               <l>The Lion ſcornes to touch the yeelding pray,</l>
               <l>And Edwards ſword muſt freſh it ſelfe in ſuch,</l>
               <l>As wilfull ſtubbornnes hath made peruerſe.</l>
            </sp>
            <stage>Enter Lord Pearſie.</stage>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Ki:</speaker>
               <l>Lord Perſie welcome: whats the newes in England:</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Per:</speaker>
               <l>The Queene my Lord comes heere to your Grace,</l>
               <l>And from hir highneſſe, and the Lord vicegerent,</l>
               <l>
                  <pb facs="tcp:6638:27"/>I bring this happie tidings of ſucceſſe,</l>
               <l>Dauid of Scotland lately vp in armes,</l>
               <l>Thinking belike he ſooneſt ſhould preuaile,</l>
               <l>Your highnes being abſent from the Realme,</l>
               <l>Is by the fruitfull ſeruice of your peeres,</l>
               <l>And painefull trauell of the Queene her ſelfe:</l>
               <l>That big with child was euery day in armes,</l>
               <l>Vanquiſht, ſubdude, and taken priſoner.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Ki:</speaker>
               <l>Thanks Perſie for thy newes with all my hart,</l>
               <l>What was he tooke him priſoner in the field.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Per.</speaker>
               <l>A Eſquire my Lord, Iohn Copland is his name:</l>
               <l>Who ſince intreated by her Maieſtie,</l>
               <l>Denies to make ſurrender of his prize,</l>
               <l>To anie but vnto your grace alone:</l>
               <l>Whereat the Queene is greououſly diſpleaſd.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Ki:</speaker>
               <l>Well then wele haue a Purſiuaunt diſpatch,</l>
               <l>To ſummon Copland hither out of hand,</l>
               <l>And with him he ſhall bring his priſoner king.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Per:</speaker>
               <l>The Queene my Lord her ſelfe by this at Sea,</l>
               <l>And purpoſeth as ſoone as winde will ſerue,</l>
               <l>To land at Callis, and to viſit you,</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Ki:</speaker>
               <l>She ſhall be welcome, and to wait her comming,</l>
               <l>Ile pitch my tent neere to the ſandy ſhore.</l>
            </sp>
            <stage>Enter a Captayne.</stage>
            <sp>
               <l>The Burgeſſes of Callis mighty king,</l>
               <l>Haue by a counſell willingly decreed,</l>
               <l>To yeeld the towne and Caſtle to your hands,</l>
               <l>Vpon condition it will pleaſe your grace,</l>
               <l>To graunt them benefite of life and goods.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>K. Ed.</speaker>
               <l>They wil ſo: Then belike they may command,</l>
               <l>Diſpoſe, elect, and gouerne as they liſt,</l>
               <l>No ſirra, tell them ſince they did refuſe,</l>
               <l>Our princely clemencie at firſt proclaymed,</l>
               <l>They ſhall not haue it now although they would,</l>
               <l>
                  <pb facs="tcp:6638:28"/>Will accept of nought but fire and ſword,</l>
               <l>Except within theſe two daies ſixe of them</l>
               <l>That are the welthieſt marchaunts in the towne,</l>
               <l>Come naked all but for their linnen ſhirts,</l>
               <l>With each a halter hangd about his necke,</l>
               <l>And proſtrate yeeld themſelues vpon their knees,</l>
               <l>To be afflicted, hanged, or what I pleaſe,</l>
               <l>And ſo you may informe their maſterſhips.</l>
               <stage>Exeunt</stage>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Cap.</speaker>
               <l>Why this it is to truſt a broken ſtaffe.</l>
               <l>Had we not been perſwaded Iohn our King,</l>
               <l>Would with his armie haue releeud the towne,</l>
               <l>We had not ſtood vpon defiance ſo:</l>
               <l>But nowt's paſt that no man can recall,</l>
               <l>And better ſome do go to wrack then all.</l>
               <stage>Exit.</stage>
            </sp>
            <stage>Enter Charles of Normandy and Villiers</stage>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Ch:</speaker>
               <l>I wounder Villiers, thou ſhouldeſt importune me</l>
               <l>For one that is our deadly ennemie.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Vil:</speaker>
               <l>Not for his ſake my gratious Lord ſo much,</l>
               <l>Am I become an earneſt aduocate,</l>
               <l>As that thereby my ranſome will be quit,</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Ch:</speaker>
               <l>Thy ranſome man: why needeſt thou talke of that?</l>
               <l>Art thou not free? and are not all occaſions,</l>
               <l>That happen for aduantage of our foes,</l>
               <l>To be accepted of, and ſtood vpon?</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Vil:</speaker>
               <l>No good my Lord except the ſame be iuſt,</l>
               <l>For profit muſt with honor be comixt,</l>
               <l>Or elſe our actions are but ſcandalous:</l>
               <l>But letting paſſe theſe intricate obiections,</l>
               <l>Wilt pleaſe your highnes to ſubſcribe or no?</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Ch.</speaker>
               <l>Villiers I will not, nor I cannot do it,</l>
               <l>Salisbury ſhall not haue his will ſo much,</l>
               <l>To clayme a paſport how it pleaſeth himſelfe,</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Vil:</speaker>
               <l>Why then I know the extremitie my Loid,</l>
               <l>I muſt returne to priſon whence I came,</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Ch</hi> Returne, I hope thou wilt not,</l>
               <l>What bird that hath eſcapt the fowlers gin,</l>
               <l>
                  <pb facs="tcp:6638:28"/>Will not beware how ſhees inſnard againe:</l>
               <l>Or what is he ſo ſenceles and ſecure,</l>
               <l>That hauing hardely paſt a dangerous gulfe,</l>
               <l>Will put him ſelfe in perill there againe.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Vil:</speaker>
               <l>Ah but it is mine othe my gratious Lord,</l>
               <l>Which I in conſcience may not violate,</l>
               <l>Or elſe a kingdome ſhould not draw me hence.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Ch:</speaker>
               <l>Thine othe, why that doth bind thee to abide:</l>
               <l>Haſt thou not ſworne obedience to thy Prince?</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Vil:</speaker>
               <l>In all things that vprightly he commands:</l>
               <l>But either to perſwade or threaten me,</l>
               <l>Not to performe the couenant of my word,</l>
               <l>Is lawleſſe, and I need not to obey.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Ch:</speaker>
               <l>Why is it lawfull for a man to kill,</l>
               <l>And not to breake a promiſe with his foe?</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Vil:</speaker>
               <l>To kill my Lord when warre is once proclaymd,</l>
               <l>So that our quarrel be for wrongs receaude,</l>
               <l>No doubt is lawfully permitted vs:</l>
               <l>But in an othe we muſt be well aduiſd,</l>
               <l>How we do ſweare, and when we once haue ſworne,</l>
               <l>Not to infringe it though we die therefore:</l>
               <l>Therefore my Lord, as willing I returne,</l>
               <l>As if I were to flie to paradiſe.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Ch:</speaker>
               <l>Stay my Villeirs, thine honorable minde,</l>
               <l>Deſerues to be eternally admirde,</l>
               <l>Thy ſute ſhalbe no longer thus deferd:</l>
               <l>Giue me the paper, Ile ſubſcribe to it,</l>
               <l>And wheretofore I loued thee as Villeirs,</l>
               <l>Heereafter Ile embrace thee as my felfe,</l>
               <l>Stay and be ſtill in fauour with thy Lord.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Vil:</speaker>
               <l>I humbly thanke your grace, I muſt diſpatch,</l>
               <l>And ſend this paſport firſt vnto the Earle,</l>
               <l>And then I will attend your highnes pleaſure.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Ch.</speaker>
               <l>Do ſo Villeirs, and Charles when he hath neede,</l>
               <l>Be ſuch his ſouldiers, howſoeuer he ſpeede.</l>
               <stage>Exit Villeirs.</stage>
            </sp>
            <stage>Enter King Iohn.</stage>
            <sp>
               <speaker>K. Io:</speaker>
               <l>Come Charles and arme thee, Edward is intrapt,</l>
               <l>The Prince of Wales is falne into our hands,</l>
               <l>
                  <pb facs="tcp:6638:29"/>And we haue compaſt him he cannot ſcape.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Ch:</speaker>
               <l>But will your highnes fight to day.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Io:</speaker>
               <l>What elſe my ſon, hees ſcar<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> eight thouſand ſtrong</l>
               <l>and we are threeſcore thouſand at the leaſt,</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Ch:</speaker>
               <l>I haue a prophecy my gratious Lord,</l>
               <l>Wherein is written what ſucceſſe is like</l>
               <l>To happen vs in this outragious warre,</l>
               <l>It was deliuered me at Creſſes field,</l>
               <l>By one that is an aged Hermyt there,</l>
               <l>when fethered ſoul ſhal make thine army tremble,</l>
               <l>and flint ſtones riſe and breake the battell ray:</l>
               <l>Then thinke on him that doth not now diſſemble</l>
               <l>For that ſhalbe the haples dreadfull day,</l>
               <l>Yet in the end thy foot thou ſhalt aduance,</l>
               <l>as farre in England, as thy foe in Fraunce,</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Io:</speaker>
               <l>By this it ſeemes we ſhalbe fortunate:</l>
               <l>For as it is impoſſible that ſtones</l>
               <l>Should euer riſe and breake the battaile ray,</l>
               <l>Or airie foule make men in armes to quake,</l>
               <l>So is it like we ſhall not be ſubdude:</l>
               <l>Or ſay this might be true, yet in the end,</l>
               <l>Since he doth promiſe we ſhall driue him hence,</l>
               <l>And forrage their Countrie as they haue don ours</l>
               <l>By this reuenge, that loſſe will ſeeme the leſſe,</l>
               <l>But all are fryuolous, fancies, toyes and dreames,</l>
               <l>Once we are ſure we haue inſnard the ſonne,</l>
               <l>Catch we the father after how we can.</l>
               <stage>Exeunt.</stage>
            </sp>
            <stage>Enter Prince Edward, Audley and others.</stage>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Pr:</speaker>
               <l>Audley the armes of death embrace vs round,</l>
               <l>And comfort haue we none ſaue that to die,</l>
               <l>We pay ſower earneſt for a ſweeter life,</l>
               <l>At Creſſey field our Clouds of Warlike ſmoke,</l>
               <l>chokt vp thoſe French mouths, &amp; diſſeuered them</l>
               <l>But now their multitudes of millions hide</l>
               <l>Masking as twere the beautious burning Sunne,</l>
               <l>Leauing no hope to vs but ſullen darke,</l>
               <l>
                  <pb facs="tcp:6638:29"/>And eie leſſe terror of all ending night.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Au.</speaker>
               <l>This ſuddaine, mightie, and expedient head,</l>
               <l>That they haue made, faire Prince is wonderfull.</l>
               <l>Before vs in the vallie lies the king,</l>
               <l>Vantagd with all that heauen and earth can yeeld,</l>
               <l>His partie ſtronger battaild then our whole:</l>
               <l>His ſonne the brauing Duke of Normandie,</l>
               <l>Hath trimd the Mountaine on our right hand vp,</l>
               <l>In ſhining plate, that now the aſpiring hill,</l>
               <l>Shewes like a ſiluer quarrie, or an orbe</l>
               <l>Aloft the which the Banners bannarets,</l>
               <l>And new repleniſht pendants cuff the aire,</l>
               <l>And beat the windes, that for their gaudineſſe,</l>
               <l>Struggles to kiſſe them on our left handlies,</l>
               <l>Phillip the younger iſſue of the king,</l>
               <l>Coting the other hill in ſuch arraie,</l>
               <l>That all his guilded vpright pikes do ſeeme,</l>
               <l>Streight trees of gold, the pendant leaues,</l>
               <l>And their deuice of Antique heraldry,</l>
               <l>Quartred in collours ſeeming ſundy fruits,</l>
               <l>Makes it the Orchard of the Heſperides,</l>
               <l>Behinde vs two the hill doth beare his height,</l>
               <l>For like a halfe Moone opening but one way,</l>
               <l>It rounds vs in, there at our backs are lodgd,</l>
               <l>The fatall Crosbowes, and the battaile there,</l>
               <l>Is gouernd by the rough Chattillion,</l>
               <l>Then thus it ſtands, the valleie for our flight,</l>
               <l>The king binds in, the hils on either hand,</l>
               <l>Are proudly royalized by his ſonnes,</l>
               <l>And on the Hill behind ſtands certaine death,</l>
               <l>In pay and ſeruice with Chattillion.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Pr:</speaker>
               <l>Deathes name is much more mightie then his deeds,</l>
               <l>Thy parcelling this power hath made it more,</l>
               <l>As many ſands as theſe my hands can hold,</l>
               <l>are but my handful of ſo many ſands,</l>
               <l>Then all the world, and call it but a power:</l>
               <l>Eaſely tane vp and quickly throwne away,</l>
               <l>But if I ſtand to count them ſand by ſand</l>
               <l>
                  <pb facs="tcp:6638:30"/>The number would confound my memorie,</l>
               <l>And make a thouſand millions of a taske,</l>
               <l>Which briefelie is no more indeed then one,</l>
               <l>Theſe quarters, ſpuadrons, and theſe regements,</l>
               <l>Before, behinde vs, and on either hand,</l>
               <l>Are but a power, when we name a man,</l>
               <l>His hand, his foote, his head hath ſeuerall ſtrengthes,</l>
               <l>And being al but one ſelfe inſtant ſtrength,</l>
               <l>Why all this many, Audely is but one,</l>
               <l>And we can call it all but one mans ſtrength:</l>
               <l>He that hath farre to goe, tels it by miles,</l>
               <l>If he ſhould tell the ſteps, it kills his hart:</l>
               <l>The drops are infinite that make a floud,</l>
               <l>And yet thou knoweſt we call it but a Raine:</l>
               <l>There is but one Fraunce, one king of Fraunce,</l>
               <l>That Fraunce hath no more kings, and that ſame king</l>
               <l>Hath but the puiſſant legion of one king?</l>
               <l>And we haue one, then apprehend no ods,</l>
               <l>For one to one, is faire equalitie.</l>
            </sp>
            <stage>Enter an Herald from king Iohn.</stage>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Pr:</speaker>
               <l>What tidings meſſenger, be playne and briefe.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>He:</speaker>
               <l>The king of Fraunce my ſoueraigne Lord and maſter,</l>
               <l>Greets by me his fo, the Prince of Wals,</l>
               <l>If thou call forth a hundred men of name</l>
               <l>Of Lords, Knights, Eſquires and Engliſh gentlemen,</l>
               <l>And with thy ſelfe and thoſe kneele at his feete,</l>
               <l>He ſtraight will fold his bloody collours vp,</l>
               <l>And ranſome ſhall redeeme liues forfeited:</l>
               <l>If not, this day ſhall drinke more Engliſh blood,</l>
               <l>Then ere was buried in our Bryttiſh earth,</l>
               <l>What is the anſwere to his profered mercy?</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Pr,</speaker>
               <l>This heauen that couers Fraunce containes the mercy</l>
               <l>That drawes from me ſubmiſſiue orizons,</l>
               <l>That ſuch baſe breath ſhould vaniſh from my lips</l>
               <l>To vrge the plea of mercie to a man,</l>
               <l>The Lord forbid, returne and tell the king,</l>
               <l>
                  <pb facs="tcp:6638:30"/>My tongue is made of ſteele, and it ſhall
beg</l>
               <l>My mercie on his coward burgonet.</l>
               <l>Tell him my colours are as red as his,</l>
               <l>My men as bold, our Engliſh armes as ſtrong,</l>
               <l>returne him my defiance in his face.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>He.</speaker>
               <l>I go.</l>
            </sp>
            <stage>Enter another.</stage>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Pr:</speaker>
               <l>What newes with thee?</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>He.</speaker>
               <l>I he Duke of Normandie my Lord &amp; maſter</l>
               <l>Pittying thy youth is ſo ingirt with perill,</l>
               <l>By me hath ſent a nimble ioynted iennet,</l>
               <l>As ſwift as euer yet thou didſt beſtride,</l>
               <l>And therewithall he counſels thee to flie,</l>
               <l>Els death himſelf hath ſworne that thou ſhalt die.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>P:</speaker>
               <l>Back with the beaſt vnto the beaſt that ſent him</l>
               <l>Tell him I cannot ſit a cowards horſe,</l>
               <l>Bid him to daie beſtride the iade himſelfe,</l>
               <l>For I will ſtaine my horſe quite ore with bloud,</l>
               <l>And double guild my ſpurs, but I will catch him,</l>
               <l>So tell the capring boy, and get thee gone.</l>
            </sp>
            <stage>Enter another.</stage>
            <sp>
               <speaker>He:</speaker>
               <l>Edward of Wales, Phillip the ſecond ſonne</l>
               <l>To the moſt mightie chriſtian king of France,</l>
               <l>Seeing thy bodies liuing date expird,</l>
               <l>All full of charitie and chriſtian loue,</l>
               <l>Commends this booke full fraught with prayers,</l>
               <l>To thy faire hand, and for thy houre of lyfe,</l>
               <l>Intreats thee that thou meditate therein,</l>
               <l>And arme thy ſoule for hir long iourney towards.</l>
               <l>Thus haue I done his bidding, and returne.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Pr.</speaker>
               <l>Herald of Phillip greet thy Lord from me,</l>
               <l>All good that he can ſend I can receiue,</l>
               <l>But thinkſt thou not the vnaduiſed boy,</l>
               <l>Hath wrongd himſelfe in this far tendering me,</l>
               <l>Happily he cannot praie without the booke,</l>
               <l>I thinke him no diuine extemporall,</l>
               <l>Then render backe this common place of prayer,</l>
               <l>
                  <pb facs="tcp:6638:31"/>To do himſelfe good in aduerſitie,</l>
               <l>Beſides, he knows not my ſinnes qualitie,</l>
               <l>and therefore knowes no praiers for my auaile,</l>
               <l>Ere night his praier may be to praie to God,</l>
               <l>To put it in my heart to heare his praier,</l>
               <l>So tell the courtly wanton, and be gone.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>He.</speaker>
               <l>I go.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Pr.</speaker>
               <l>How confident their ſtrength and number makes them,</l>
               <l>Now Audley ſound thoſe ſiluer winges of thine,</l>
               <l>And let thoſe milke white meſſengers of time,</l>
               <l>Shew thy times learning in this dangerous time,</l>
               <l>Thy ſelfe art buſie, and bit with many broiles,</l>
               <l>And ſtratagems ſore paſt with yron pens,</l>
               <l>Are texted in thine honorable face,</l>
               <l>Thou art a married man in this diſtreſſe.</l>
               <l>But danger wooes me as a bluſhing maide,</l>
               <l>Teach me an anſwere to this perillous time.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Aud.</speaker>
               <l>To die is all as common as to liue,</l>
               <l>The one in choice the other holds in chaſe,</l>
               <l>For from the inſtant we begin to liue,</l>
               <l>We do purſue and hunt the time to die,</l>
               <l>Firſt bud we, then we blow, and after ſeed,</l>
               <l>Then preſently we fall, and as a ſhade</l>
               <l>Followes the bodie, ſo we ſollow death,</l>
               <l>If then we hunt for death, why do we feare it?</l>
               <l>If we feare it, why do we follow it?</l>
               <l>If we do teare, how can we ſhun it?</l>
               <l>If we do feare, with feare we do but aide</l>
               <l>The thing we feare, to ſeize on vs the ſooner,</l>
               <l>If wee feare not, then no reſolued proffer,</l>
               <l>Can ouerthrow the limit of our fate,</l>
               <l>For whether ripe or rotten, drop we ſhall,</l>
               <l>as we do drawe the lotterie of our doome.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Pri.</speaker>
               <l>Ah good olde man, a thouſand thouſand armors,</l>
               <l>Theſe wordes of thine haue buckled on my backe,</l>
               <l>Ah what an idiot haſt thou made of lyfe,</l>
               <l>To ſeeke the thing it feares, and how diſgraſt,</l>
               <l>The imperiall victorie of murdring death,</l>
               <l>
                  <pb facs="tcp:6638:31"/>Since all the liues his conquering arrowes
ſtrike,</l>
               <l>Seeke him, and he not them, to ſhame his glorie,</l>
               <l>I will not giue a pennie for a lyfe,</l>
               <l>Nor halfe a halfe penie to ſhun grim death,</l>
               <l>Since for to liue is but to ſeeke to die,</l>
               <l>And dying but beginning of new lyfe,</l>
               <l>Let come the houre when he that rules it will,</l>
               <l>To liue or die I hold indifferent.</l>
               <stage>Exeunt.</stage>
            </sp>
            <stage>Enter king Iohn and Charles.</stage>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Ioh:</speaker>
               <l>A ſodaine darknes hath defaſt the skie,</l>
               <l>The windes are crept into their caues for feare,</l>
               <l>the leaues moue not, the world is huſht and ſtill,</l>
               <l>the birdes ceaſe ſinging, and the wandring brookes,</l>
               <l>Murmure no wonted greeting to their ſhores,</l>
               <l>Silence attends ſome wonder, and expecteth</l>
               <l>That heauen ſhould pronounce ſome propheſie,</l>
               <l>Where or from whome proceeds this ſilence Charles?</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Ch:</speaker>
               <l>Our men with open mouthes and ſtaring eyes,</l>
               <l>Looke on each other, as they did attend</l>
               <l>Each others wordes, and yet no creature ſpeakes,</l>
               <l>A tongue-tied feare hath made a midnight houre,</l>
               <l>and ſpeeches ſleepe through all the waking regions.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Ioh:</speaker>
               <l>But now the pompeous Sunne in all his pride,</l>
               <l>Lookt through his golden coach vpon the worlde,</l>
               <l>and on a ſodaine hath he hid himſelfe,</l>
               <l>that now the vnder earth is as a graue,</l>
               <l>Darke, deadly, ſilent, and vncomfortable.</l>
               <l> 
                  <stage>A clamor of rauens</stage> Harke, what a deadly outcrie do
I heare?</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Ch.</speaker>
               <l>Here comes my brother Phillip.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Ioh.</speaker>
               <l>All diſmaid. What fearefull words are thoſe thy lookes
preſage?</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Pr.</speaker>
               <l>A flight, a flight.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Ioh:</speaker>
               <l>Coward what flight? thou lieſt there needs no flight.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Pr.</speaker>
               <l>A flight.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Kin:</speaker>
               <l>Awake thy crauen powers, and tell on</l>
               <l>the ſubſtance of that verie feare in deed,</l>
               <l>Which is ſo gaſtly printed in thy face,</l>
               <l>What is the matter?</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <pb facs="tcp:6638:32"/>
               <speaker>Pr.</speaker>
               <l>A flight of vgly rauens</l>
               <l>Do croke and houer ore our ſouldiers heads,</l>
               <l>And keepe in triangles and cornerd ſquares,</l>
               <l>Right as our forces are imbatteled,</l>
               <l>With their approach there came this ſodain fog,</l>
               <l>Which now hath hid the airie flower of heauen,</l>
               <l>And made at noone a night vnnaturall,</l>
               <l>Vpon the quaking and diſmaied world;</l>
               <l>In briefe, our ſouldiers haue let fall their armes,</l>
               <l>and ſtand like metamorphoſd images,</l>
               <l>Bloudleſſe and pale, one gazing on another.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Io:</speaker>
               <l>I now I call to mind the propheſie,</l>
               <l>But I muſt giue no enter<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap> to a feare,</l>
               <l>Returne and harten vp
<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> yeelding ſoules,</l>
               <l>Tell them the rauens ſeeing them in armes,</l>
               <l>So many faire againſt a famiſht few,</l>
               <l>Come but to dine vpon their handie worke,</l>
               <l>and praie vpon the carrion that they kill,</l>
               <l>For when we ſee a horſe laid downe to die,</l>
               <l>although not dead, the rauenous birds</l>
               <l>Sit watching the departure of his life,</l>
               <l>Euen ſo theſe rauens for the carcaſes,</l>
               <l>Of thoſe poore Engliſh that are markt to die,</l>
               <l>Houer about, and if they crie to vs,</l>
               <l>Tis but for meate that we muſt kill for them,</l>
               <l>Awaie and comfort vp my ſouldiers,</l>
               <l>and ſound the trumpets, and at once diſpatch</l>
               <l>This litle buſines of a ſilly fraude.</l>
               <stage>Exit Pr.</stage>
            </sp>
            <stage>Another noiſe, Salisbury brought in by a French
Captaine.</stage>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Cap:</speaker>
               <l>Behold my liege, this knight and fortie mo,</l>
               <l>Of whom the better part are ſlaine and ſled,</l>
               <l>With all indeuor ſought to breake our rankes,</l>
               <l>And make their wa<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>e
to the incompaſt prince,</l>
               <l>Diſpoſe of him as pleaſe your maieſtie.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Io:</speaker>
               <l>Go, &amp; the next bough, ſouldier, that thou ſeeſt,</l>
               <l>Diſgrace it with his bodie preſently,</l>
               <l>Eor I doo hold a tree in France too good,</l>
               <l>
                  <pb facs="tcp:6638:32"/>To be the gallowes of an Engliſh theefe.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Sa:</speaker>
               <l>My Lord of Normandie, I haue your paſſe,</l>
               <l>And warrant for my ſafetie through this land.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Ch.</speaker>
               <l>Villiers procurd it for thee, did he not?</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Sal:</speaker>
               <l>He did.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Ch:</speaker>
               <l>And it is currant, thou ſhalt freely paſſe.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>En: Io:</speaker>
               <l>I freely to the gallows to be hangd,</l>
               <l>Without deniall or impediment.</l>
               <l>Awaie with him.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Vil.</speaker>
               <l>I hope your highnes will not ſo diſgrace me,</l>
               <l>and daſh the vertue of my ſeale at armes,</l>
               <l>He hath my neuer broken name to ſhew,</l>
               <l>Carectred with this princely hande of mine,</l>
               <l>and rather let me leaue to be a prince,</l>
               <l>Than break the ſtable verdict of a prince,</l>
               <l>I doo beſeech you let him paſſe in quiet,</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Ki:</speaker>
               <l>Thou and thy word lie both in my command,</l>
               <l>What canſt thou promiſe that I cannot breake?</l>
               <l>Which of theſe twaine is greater infamie,</l>
               <l>To diſobey thy father or thy ſelfe?</l>
               <l>Thy word nor no mans may exceed his power,</l>
               <l>Nor that ſame man doth neuer breake his worde,</l>
               <l>That keepes it to the vtmoſt of his power.</l>
               <l>The breach of faith dwels in the ſoules conſent,</l>
               <l>Which if thy ſelfe without conſent doo breake,</l>
               <l>Thou art not charged with the breach of faith,</l>
               <l>Go hang him, for thy liſence lies in mee,</l>
               <l>and my conſtraint ſtands the excuſe for thee.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Ch.</speaker>
               <l>VVhat am I not a ſoldier in my word?</l>
               <l>Then armes adieu, and let them fight that liſt,</l>
               <l>Shall I not giue my girdle from my waſt,</l>
               <l>But with a gardion I ſhall be controld,</l>
               <l>To ſaie I may not giue my things awaie,</l>
               <l>Vpon my ſoule, had Edward prince of VVales</l>
               <l>Ingagde his word, writ downe his noble hand,</l>
               <l>For all your knights to paſſe his fathers land,</l>
               <l>The roiall king to grace his warlike ſonne,</l>
               <l>VVould not alone ſafe conduct giue to them<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <pb facs="tcp:6638:33"/>But with all bountie ſeaſted them and
theirs.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Kin:</speaker>
               <l>Dwelſt thou on preſidents, then be it ſo,</l>
               <l>Say Engliſhman of what degree thou art.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Sa:</speaker>
               <l>An Earle in England, though a priſoner here,</l>
               <l>And thoſe that knowe me call me Salisburie.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Kin:</speaker>
               <l>Then Salisburie, ſay whether thou art bound.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Sa.</speaker>
               <l>To Callice where my liege king Edward is.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Kin:</speaker>
               <l>To Callice Salisburie, then to Callice packe,</l>
               <l>and bid the king prepare a noble graue,</l>
               <l>To put his princely ſonne blacke Edward in,</l>
               <l>and as thou trauelſt weſtward from this place,</l>
               <l>Some two leagues hence there is a loftie hill,</l>
               <l>Whoſe top ſeemes topleſſe, for the imbracing skie,</l>
               <l>Doth hide his high head in her a zure boſome,</l>
               <l>Vpon whoſe tall top when thy foot attaines,</l>
               <l>Looke backe vpon the humble vale beneath,</l>
               <l>Humble of late, but now made proud with armes,</l>
               <l>and thence behold the wretched prince of Wales,</l>
               <l>Hoopt with a bond of yron round about,</l>
               <l>After which ſight to Callice ſpurre amaine,</l>
               <l>and ſaie the prince was ſmoothered, and not ſlaine,</l>
               <l>and tell the king this is not all his ill,</l>
               <l>For I will greet him ere he thinkes I will,</l>
               <l>Awaie be gone, the ſmoake but of our ſhot,</l>
               <l>Will choake our foes, though bullets hit them not.</l>
               <stage>Exit.</stage>
            </sp>
            <stage>Allarum. Enter prince Edward and Artoys.</stage>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Art:</speaker>
               <l>How fares your grace, are you not ſhot my Lord?</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Pri:</speaker>
               <l>No deare Artoys, but choakt with duſt and ſmoake,</l>
               <l>And ſtept aſide for breath and freſher aire.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Art.</speaker>
               <l>Breath then, and too it againe, the amazed French</l>
               <l>are quite diſtract with gazing on the crowes,</l>
               <l>and were our quiuers full of ſhafts againe,</l>
               <l>Your grace ſhould ſee a glorious day of this,</l>
               <l>O for more arrowes Lord, thats our want.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Pri.</speaker>
               <l>Courage Artoys, a fig for feathered ſhafts,</l>
               <l>When feathered foules doo bandie on our ſide,</l>
               <l>What need we fight, and ſweate, and keepe a coile,</l>
               <l>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap> outſcolde our
aduerſaries</l>
               <l>
                  <pb facs="tcp:6638:33"/>Vp, vp Artoys, the ground it ſelfe is armd,</l>
               <l>Fire containing flint, command our bowes</l>
               <l>To hurle awaie their pretie colored Ew,</l>
               <l>and to it with ſtones, awaie Artoys, awaie,</l>
               <l>My ſoule doth propheſie we win the daie.</l>
               <stage>Exeunt.</stage>
            </sp>
            <stage>Allarum. Enter king Iohn.</stage>
            <sp>
               <l>Our multitudes are in themſelues confounded,</l>
               <l>Diſmayed, and diſtraught, ſwift ſtarting feare</l>
               <l>Hath buzd a cold diſmaie through all our armie,</l>
               <l>and euerie pettie diſaduantage promptes</l>
               <l>The feare poſſeſſed abiect ſoule to flie,</l>
               <l>My ſelfe whoſe ſpirit is ſteele to their dull lead,</l>
               <l>What with recalling of the propheſie,</l>
               <l>and that our natiue ſtones from Engliſh armes</l>
               <l>Rebell againſt vs, finde my ſelfe attainted</l>
               <l>With ſtrong ſurpriſe of weake and yeelding feare.</l>
            </sp>
            <stage>Enter Charles.</stage>
            <sp>
               <l>Fly father flie, the French do kill the French,</l>
               <l>Some that would ſtand, let driue at ſome that flie,</l>
               <l>Our drums ſtrike nothing but diſcouragement,</l>
               <l>Our trumpets ſound diſhonor, and retire,</l>
               <l>The ſpirit of feare that feareth nought but death,</l>
               <l>Cowardly workes confuſion on it ſelfe.</l>
            </sp>
            <stage>Enter Phillip.</stage>
            <sp>
               <l>Plucke out your eies, and ſee not this daies ſhame,</l>
               <l>An arme hath beate an armie, one poore Dauid</l>
               <l>Hath with a ſtone foild twentie ſtout Goliahs,</l>
               <l>Some twentie naked ſtaruelings with ſmall flints,</l>
               <l>Hath driuen backe a puiſant hoſt of men,</l>
               <l>Araid and fenſt in all accomplements,</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Ioh:</speaker>
               <l>Mordiu they quait at vs, and kill vs vp,</l>
               <l>No leſſe than fortie thouſand wicked elders,</l>
               <l>Haue fortie leane ſlaues this daie ſtoned to death.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Ch:</speaker>
               <l>O that I were ſome other countryman,</l>
               <l>This daie hath ſet deriſion on the French,</l>
               <l>and all the world wilt blurt and ſcorne at vs.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Kin:</speaker>
               <l>What is there no hope left?</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Pr:</speaker>
               <l>No hope but death to burie vp our ſhame,</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <pb facs="tcp:6638:34"/>
               <speaker>Ki.</speaker>
               <l>Make vp once more with me the twentith part</l>
               <l>Of thoſe that liue, are men in ow to quaile,</l>
               <l>The feeble handfull on the aduerſe part.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Ch.</speaker>
               <l>Then charge againe, if heauen be not oppoſd</l>
               <l>VVe cannot looſe the daie.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Kin.</speaker>
               <l>On awaie.</l>
               <stage>Exeunt</stage>
            </sp>
            <stage>Enter Audley wounded, &amp; reſcued by two ſquirs.</stage>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Eſq.</speaker>
               <l>How fares my Lord;</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Aud.</speaker>
               <l>Euen as a man may do</l>
               <l>That dines at ſuch a bloudie feaſt as this.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Eſq.</speaker>
               <l>I hope my Lord that is no mortall ſcarre,</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Aud.</speaker>
               <l>No matter if it be, the count is caſt,</l>
               <l>and in the worſt ends but a mortall man,</l>
               <l>Good friends conuey me to the princely Edward</l>
               <l>That in the crimſon brauerie of my bloud,</l>
               <l>I may become him with ſaluting him,</l>
               <l>Ile ſmile and tell him that this open ſcarre,</l>
               <l>Doth end the harueſt of his Audleys warre.</l>
               <stage>Ex.</stage>
            </sp>
            <stage>Enter prince Edward, king Iohn, Charles, and all with
Enſignes ſpred.</stage>
            <stage>Retreat ſounded.</stage>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Pri.</speaker>
               <l>Now Iohn in France, &amp; lately Iohn of France,</l>
               <l>Thy bloudie Enſignes are my captiue colours,</l>
               <l>and you high vanting Charles of Normandie,</l>
               <l>That once to daie ſent me a horſe to flie,</l>
               <l>are now the ſubiects of my clemencie.</l>
               <l>Fie Lords, is it not a ſhame that Engliſh boies,</l>
               <l>VVhoſe early daies are yet not worth a beard,</l>
               <l>Should in the boſome of your kingdome thus,</l>
               <l>One againſt twentie beate you vp together.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Kin.</speaker>
               <l>Thy fortune, not thy force hath conquerd vs.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Pri.</speaker>
               <l>an argument that heauen aides the right,</l>
               <l>See, ſee, Artoys doth bring with him along,</l>
               <l>the late good counſell giuer to my ſoule,</l>
               <l>VVelcome Artoys, and welcome Phillip to,</l>
               <l>VVho now of you or I haue need to praie,</l>
               <l>Now is the prouerbe verefied in you,</l>
               <l>Too bright a morning breeds a
<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap>ing daie.</l>
            </sp>
            <stage>
               <pb facs="tcp:6638:34"/>Sound Trumpets, enter Audley.</stage>
            <sp>
               <l>But ſay, what grym diſcoragement comes heere,</l>
               <l>Alas what thouſand armed men of Fraunce,</l>
               <l>Haue writ that note of death in Audleys face:</l>
               <l>Speake thou that wooeſt death with thy careles ſmile</l>
               <l>and lookſt ſo merrily vpon thy graue,</l>
               <l>As if thou wert enamored on thyne end,</l>
               <l>What hungry ſword hath ſo bereaud thy face,</l>
               <l>And lopt a true friend from my louing ſoule:</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Au.</speaker>
               <l>O Prince thy ſweet bemoning ſpeech to me.</l>
               <l>Is as a morneful knell to one dead ſicke.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Pr:</speaker>
               <l>Deare Audley if my tongue ring out thy end:</l>
               <l>My armes ſhalbe the graue, what may I do,</l>
               <l>To win thy life, or to reuenge thy death,</l>
               <l>If thou wilt drinke the blood of captyue kings,</l>
               <l>Or that it were reſtoritiue, command</l>
               <l>A Heath of kings blood, and Ile drinke to thee,</l>
               <l>If honor may diſpence for thee with death,</l>
               <l>The neuer dying honor of this daie,</l>
               <l>Share wholie Audley to thy ſelfe and liue.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Aud:</speaker>
               <l>Victorious Prince, that thou art ſo, behold</l>
               <l>A Caeſars fame in kings captiuitie;</l>
               <l>If I could hold dym death but at a bay,</l>
               <l>Till I did ſee my liege thy loyall father,</l>
               <l>My ſoule ſhould yeeld this Caſtle of my fleſh,</l>
               <l>This mangled tribute with all willingnes;</l>
               <l>To darkenes conſummation, duſt and Wormes.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Pr:</speaker>
               <l>Cheerely bold man, thy ſoule is all to proud,</l>
               <l>To yeeld her Citie for one little breach,</l>
               <l>Should be diuorced from her earthly ſpouſe,</l>
               <l>By the ſoft temper of a French mans ſword:</l>
               <l>Lo, to repaire thy life, I giue to thee,</l>
               <l>Three thouſand Marks a yeere in Engliſh land.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Au:</speaker>
               <l>I take thy gift to pay the debts I owe:</l>
               <l>Theſe two poore Eſquires redeemd me from the French</l>
               <l>With luſty &amp; deer hazzard of their liues;</l>
               <l>What thou haſt giuen me I giue to them,</l>
               <l>And as thou loueſt me Prince, lay thy conſent.</l>
               <l>
                  <pb facs="tcp:6638:35"/>To this bequeath in my laſt teſtament.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Pr:</speaker>
               <l>Renowned Audley, liue and haue from mee,</l>
               <l>This gift twiſe doubled to theſe Eſquires and thee</l>
               <l>But liue or die, what thou haſt giuen away,</l>
               <l>To theſe and theirs ſhall laſting freedome ſtay,</l>
               <l>Come gentlemen, I will ſee my friend beſtowed,</l>
               <l>With in an eaſie Litter, then wele martch,</l>
               <l>Proudly toward Callis with tryumphant pace,</l>
               <l>Vnto my royall father, and there bring,</l>
               <l>The tribut of my wars, faire Fraunce his king.</l>
               <stage>Ex.</stage>
            </sp>
            <stage>Enter ſixe Citizens in their Shirts, bare foote, with
halters about their necks.</stage>
            <stage>Enter King Edward, Queen Phillip, Derby, ſoldiers.</stage>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Ed.</speaker>
               <l>No more Queene Phillip, pacifie your ſelfe,</l>
               <l>Copland, except he can excuſe his fault,</l>
               <l>Shall finde diſpleaſure written in our lookes,</l>
               <l>And now vnto this proud reſiſting towne,</l>
               <l>Souldiers aſſault, I will no longer ſtay,</l>
               <l>To be deluded by their falſe delaies,</l>
               <l>Put all to ſword, and make the ſpoyle your owne.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>All:</speaker>
               <l>Mercy king Edward, mercie gratious Lord.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Ki:</speaker>
               <l>Gontemptuous villaines, call ye now for truce?</l>
               <l>Mine eares are ſtopt againſt your booteleſſe cryes,</l>
               <l>Sound drums allarum, draw threatning ſwords?</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>All:</speaker>
               <l>Ah noble Prince, take pittie on this towne,</l>
               <l>And heare vs mightie king:</l>
               <l>We claime the promiſe that your highnes made,</l>
               <l>The two daies reſpit is not yet expirde,</l>
               <l>And we are come with willingnes to beare,</l>
               <l>What tortering death or puniſhment you pleaſe,</l>
               <l>So that the trembling multitude be ſaued,</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Ki:</speaker>
               <l>My promiſe, wel I do confeſſe as much;</l>
               <l>But I require the cheefeſt Citizens,</l>
               <l>And men of moſt account that ſhould ſubmit,</l>
               <l>You peraduenture are but ſeruile groomes,</l>
               <l>Or ſome fellonious robbers on the Sea,</l>
               <l>Whome apprehended law would execute,</l>
               <l>Albeit ſeuerity lay dead in vs,</l>
               <l>
                  <pb facs="tcp:6638:35"/>No no ye cannot ouerreach vs thus,</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Two:</speaker>
               <l>The Sun dread Lord that in the weſtern fall,</l>
               <l>Beholds vs now low brought through miſerie,</l>
               <l>Did in the Orient purple of the morne,</l>
               <l>Salute our comming forth when we were knowne</l>
               <l>Or may our portion be with damned fiends,</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Ki:</speaker>
               <l>If it be ſo, then let our couenant ſtand,</l>
               <l>We take poſſeſſion of the towne in peace,</l>
               <l>But for your ſelues looke you for no remorſe,</l>
               <l>But as imperiall iuſtice hath decreed,</l>
               <l>Your bodies ſhalbe dragd about theſe wals,</l>
               <l>And after feele the ſtroake of quartering ſteele,</l>
               <l>This is your dome, go ſouldiets ſee it done.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Qu:</speaker>
               <l>Ah be more milde vnto theſe yeelding men,</l>
               <l>It is a glorious thing to ſtabliſh peace,</l>
               <l>And kings approch the neareſt vnto God,</l>
               <l>By giuing life and fafety vnto men,</l>
               <l>As thou intendeſt to be king of Fraunce,</l>
               <l>So let her people liue to call thee king,</l>
               <l>For what the ſword cuts down or fire hath ſpoyld</l>
               <l>Is held in reputation none of ours.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Ki:</speaker>
               <l>Although experience teach vs, this is true,</l>
               <l>That peacefull quietnes brings moſt delight,</l>
               <l>When moſt of all abuſes are controld,</l>
               <l>Yet inſomuch, it ſhalbe knowne that we,</l>
               <l>Aſwell can maſter our affections,</l>
               <l>As conquer other by the dynt of ſword,</l>
               <l>Phillip preuaile, we yeeld to thy requeſt,</l>
               <l>Theſe men ſhall liue to boaſt of clemencie,</l>
               <l>And tyrannie ſtrike terror to thy ſelfe.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Two:</speaker>
               <l>long liue your highnes, happy be your reigne</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Ki:</speaker>
               <l>Go get you hence, returne vnto the towne,</l>
               <l>And if this kindnes hath deſerud your loue,</l>
               <l>Learne then to reuerence Edw. as your king. 
<stage>Ex.</stage>
               </l>
               <l>Now might we heare of our affaires abroad,</l>
               <l>We would till glomy Winter were ore ſpent,</l>
               <l>Diſpoſe our men in garriſon a while,</l>
               <l>But who comes heere?</l>
            </sp>
            <stage>
               <pb facs="tcp:6638:36"/>Enter Copland and King Dauid.</stage>
            <sp>
               <speaker>De,</speaker>
               <l>Copland my Lord, and Dauid King of Scots;</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Ki:</speaker>
               <l>Is this the proud preſumtious Eſquire of the North,</l>
               <l>That would not yeeld his priſoner to my Queen,</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Cop:</speaker>
               <l>I am my liege a Northen Eſquire indeed,</l>
               <l>But neither proud nor inſolent I truſt.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Ki:</speaker>
               <l>What moude thee then to be ſo obſtinate,</l>
               <l>To contradict our royall Queenes deſire?</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Co.</speaker>
               <l>No wilfull diſobedience mightie Lord,</l>
               <l>But my deſert and publike law at armes.</l>
               <l>I tooke the king my ſelfe in ſingle fight,</l>
               <l>and like a ſouldier would be loath to looſe</l>
               <l>The leaſt preheminence that I had won.</l>
               <l>And Copland ſtraight vpon your highnes charge,</l>
               <l>Is come to Fraunce, and with a lowly minde,</l>
               <l>Doth vale the bonnet of his victory:</l>
               <l>Receiue dread Lorde the cuſtome of my fraught,</l>
               <l>The wealthie tribute of my laboring hands,</l>
               <l>Which ſhould long ſince haue been ſurrendred vp</l>
               <l>Had but your gratious ſelfe bin there in place,</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Q</speaker>
               <l>But Copland thou didſt ſcorne the kings com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mand</l>
               <l>Neglecting our commiſſion in his name.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Cop.</speaker>
               <l>His name I reuerence, but his perſon more,</l>
               <l>His name ſhall keepe me in alleagaunce ſtill,</l>
               <l>But to his perſon I will bend my knee.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>King.</speaker>
               <l>I praie thee Phillip let diſpleaſure paſſe:</l>
               <l>This man doth pleaſe mee, and I like his words,</l>
               <l>For what is he that will attmpt great deeds</l>
               <l>and looſe the glory that enſues the ſame,</l>
               <l>all riuers haue recourſe vnto the Sea,</l>
               <l>and Coplands faith relation to his king,</l>
               <l>Kneele therefore downe, now riſe king Edwards knight,</l>
               <l>and to maintayne thy ſtate I freely giue,</l>
               <l>Fiue hundred marks a yeere to thee and thine</l>
               <l>welcomlord Salisburie, what news from Brittaine</l>
            </sp>
            <stage>Enter Salsbury.</stage>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Sa:</speaker>
               <l>This mightie king, the Country we haue won,</l>
               <l>
                  <pb facs="tcp:6638:36"/>And Charles de Mountford regent of that place,</l>
               <l>Preſents your highnes with this Coronet,</l>
               <l>Proteſting true allegeaunce to your Grace.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Ki:</speaker>
               <l>We thanke thee for thy ſeruice valient Earle</l>
               <l>Challenge our fauour for we owe it thee:</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Sa:</speaker>
               <l>But now my Lord, as this is ioyful newes,</l>
               <l>So muſt my voice be tragicall againe,</l>
               <l>and I muſt ſing of dolefull accidents,</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Ki:</speaker>
               <l>What haue our men the ouerthrow at Poitiers,</l>
               <l>Oris our ſonne beſet with too much odds?</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Sa.</speaker>
               <l>He was my Lord, and as my worthleſſe ſelfe,</l>
               <l>With fortie other ſeruiceable knights,</l>
               <l>Vnder ſafe conduct of the Dolphins ſeale,</l>
               <l>Did trauaile that way, finding him diſtreſt,</l>
               <l>A troupe of Launces met vs on the way,</l>
               <l>Surpriſd and brought vs priſoners to the king,</l>
               <l>Who proud of this, and eager of reuenge,</l>
               <l>Commanded ſtraight to cut of all our heads,</l>
               <l>And ſurely we had died but that the Duke,</l>
               <l>More full of honor then his angry ſyre,</l>
               <l>Procurd our quicke deliuerance from thence,</l>
               <l>But ere we went, ſalute your king, quoth hee,</l>
               <l>Bid him prouide a funerall for his ſonne,</l>
               <l>To day our ſword ſhall cut his thred of life,</l>
               <l>And ſooner then he thinkes wele be with him:</l>
               <l>To quittance thoſe diſpleaſures he hath done,</l>
               <l>This ſaid, we paſt, not daring to reply,</l>
               <l>Our harts were dead, our lookes diffuſd and wan,</l>
               <l>Wandring at laſt we clymd vnto a hill,</l>
               <l>From whence although our griefe were much be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore</l>
               <l>Yet now to ſee the occaſion with our eies,</l>
               <l>Did thrice ſo much increaſe our heauines,</l>
               <l>For there my Lord, oh there we did deſcry</l>
               <l>Downe in a vallie how both armies laie:</l>
               <l>The French had caſt their trenches like a ring,</l>
               <l>And euery Barricados open front,</l>
               <l>Was thicke imboſt with braſen ordynaunce.</l>
               <l>
                  <pb facs="tcp:6638:37"/>Heere ſtood a battaile of ten thouſand
horſe,</l>
               <l>There twiſe as many pikes in quadrant wiſe,</l>
               <l>Here Crosbowes and deadly wounding darts,</l>
               <l>And in the midſt like to a ſlender poynt,</l>
               <l>Within the compaſſe of the horiſon,</l>
               <l>as twere a riſing bubble in the ſea.</l>
               <l>A Haſle wand a midſt a wood of Pynes,</l>
               <l>Or as a beare faſt chaind vnto a ſtake,</l>
               <l>Stood famous Edward ſtill expecting when</l>
               <l>Thoſe doggs of Fraunce would faſten on his fleſh</l>
               <l>Anon the death procuring knell begins,</l>
               <l>Off goe the Cannons that with trembling noyſe,</l>
               <l>Did ſhake the very Mountayne where they ſtood,</l>
               <l>Then ſound the Trumpets clangor in the aire,</l>
               <l>The battailes ioyne, and when we could no more,</l>
               <l>Diſcerne the difference twixt the friend and ſo,</l>
               <l>So intricate the darke confuſion was,</l>
               <l>Away we turnd our watrie eies with ſighs,</l>
               <l>as blacke as pouder fuming into ſmoke,</l>
               <l>And thus I feare, vnhappie haue I told,</l>
               <l>The moſt vntimely tale of Edwards fall.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Qu:</speaker>
               <l>Ah me, is this my welcome into Fraunce:</l>
               <l>Is this the comfort that I lookt to haue,</l>
               <l>When I ſhould meete with my belooued ſonne:</l>
               <l>Sweete Ned, I would thy mother in the ſea</l>
               <l>Had been preuented of this mortall griefe.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Ki:</speaker>
               <l>Content thee Phillip, tis not teares will ſerue,</l>
               <l>To call him backe, if he be taken hence,</l>
               <l>Comfort thy ſelfe as I do gentle Queene,</l>
               <l>With hope of ſharpe vnheard of dyre reuenge,</l>
               <l>He bids me to prouide his funerall.</l>
               <l>And ſo I will, but all the Peeres in Fraunce,</l>
               <l>Shall mourners be, and weepe out bloody teares,</l>
               <l>Vntill their emptie vaines be drie and ſere</l>
               <l>The pillers of his hearſe ſhall be his bones,</l>
               <l>The mould that couers him, their Citie aſhes,</l>
               <l>His knell the groning cryes of dying men,</l>
               <l>
                  <pb facs="tcp:6638:37"/>And in the ſtead of tapers on his tombe,</l>
               <l>an hundred fiftie towers ſhall burning blaze,</l>
               <l>While we bewaile our valiant ſonnes deceaſe.</l>
            </sp>
            <stage>After a flouriſh ſounded within, enter an herald.</stage>
            <sp>
               <speaker>He.</speaker>
               <l>Reioyce my Lord, aſcend the imperial throne</l>
               <l>The mightie and redoubted prince of Wales,</l>
               <l>Great ſeruitor to bloudie Mars in armes,</l>
               <l>The French mans terror and his countries fame,</l>
               <l>Triumphant rideth like a Romane peere,</l>
               <l>and lowly at his ſtirop comes a foot</l>
               <l>King Iohn of France, together with his ſonne,</l>
               <l>In captiue bonds, whoſe diadem he brings</l>
               <l>To crowne thee with, and to proclaime thee king</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Ki.</speaker>
               <l>Away with mourning Phillip, wipe thine eies</l>
               <l>Sound Trumpets, welcome in Plantaginet.</l>
            </sp>
            <stage>Enter Prince Edward, king Iohn, Phillip, Aud<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ley,
Artoys.</stage>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Ki:</speaker>
               <l>As things long loſt when they are found again,</l>
               <l>So doth my ſonne reioyce his fathers heart,</l>
               <l>For whom euen now my ſoule was much perplext</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Q.</speaker>
               <l>Be this a token to expreſſe my ioy, 
<stage>kiſſe him.</stage>
               </l>
               <l>For inward paſſions will not let me ſpeake.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Pr.</speaker>
               <l>My gracious father, here receiue the gift,</l>
               <l>This wreath of conqueſt, and reward of warre,</l>
               <l>Got with as mickle perill of our liues,</l>
               <l>as ere was thing of price before this daie,</l>
               <l>Inſtall your highnes in your proper right,</l>
               <l>and heere withall I render to your hands</l>
               <l>Theſe priſoners, chiefe occaſion of our ſtrife.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Kin:</speaker>
               <l>So Iohn of France, I ſee you keepe your word</l>
               <l>You promiſt to be ſooner with our ſelfe</l>
               <l>Then we did thinke for, and tis ſo in deed,</l>
               <l>But had you done at firſt as now you do,</l>
               <l>How many ciuill townes had ſtoode vntoucht,</l>
               <l>That now are turnd to ragged heaps of ſtones?</l>
               <l>How many peoples liues mightſt thou haue ſaud,</l>
               <l>that are vntimely ſunke into their graues.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Io:</speaker>
               <l>Edward, recount not things irreuocable,</l>
               <l>
                  <pb facs="tcp:6638:38"/>Tell me what ranſome thou requireſt to
haue?</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Kin:</speaker>
               <l>Thy ranſome Iohn, hereafter ſhall be known</l>
               <l>But firſt to England thou muſt croſſe the ſeas,</l>
               <l>To ſee what intertainment it affords,</l>
               <l>How ere it fals, it cannot be ſo bad,</l>
               <l>as ours hath bin ſince we ariude in France,</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Ioh:</speaker>
               <l>Accurſed man, of this I was fortolde,</l>
               <l>But did miſconſter what the prophet told.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Pri:</speaker>
               <l>Now father this petition Edward makes,</l>
               <l>To thee whoſe grace hath bin his ſtrongeſt ſhield</l>
               <l>That as thy pleaſure choſe me for the man,</l>
               <l>To be the inſtrument to ſhew thy power,</l>
               <l>So thou wilt grant that many princes more,</l>
               <l>Bred and brought vp within that little Iſle,</l>
               <l>May ſtill be famous for lyke victories:</l>
               <l>and for my part, the bloudie ſcars I beare,</l>
               <l>The wearie nights that I haue watcht in field,</l>
               <l>The dangerous conflicts I haue often had,</l>
               <l>The fearefull menaces were proffered me,</l>
               <l>The heate and cold, and what elſe might diſpleaſe</l>
               <l>I wiſh were now redoubled twentie fold,</l>
               <l>So that hereafter ages when they reade</l>
               <l>The painfull traffike of my tender youth</l>
               <l>Might thereby be inflamd with ſuch reſolue,</l>
               <l>as not the territories of France alone,</l>
               <l>But likewiſe Spain, Turkie, and what countries els</l>
               <l>That iuſtly would prouoke faire Englands ire,</l>
               <l>Might at their preſence tremble and retire.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Kin:</speaker>
               <l>Here Engliſh Lordes we do proclaime a reſt</l>
               <l>an interceſſion of our painfull armes,</l>
               <l>Sheath vp your ſwords, refreſh your weary lims,</l>
               <l>Peruſe your ſpoiles, and after we haue breathd.</l>
               <l>a daie or two within this hauen towne,</l>
               <l>God willing then for England wele be ſhipt,</l>
               <l>VVhere in a happie houre I truſt we ſhall</l>
               <l>Ariue three kings, two princes, and a queene.</l>
            </sp>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
            <pb facs="tcp:6638:38"/>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
