<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Landgartha a tragie-comedy as it was presented in the new theater in Dublin with good applause, being an ancient story / written by H.B.</title>
            <author>H. B. (Henry Burnell), fl. 1641.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1641</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 174 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 41 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-04">2011-04 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A30315</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing B5751</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R30260</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">11276859</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 11276859</idno>
            <idno type="VID">47257</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A30315)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 47257)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 1456:27)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>Landgartha a tragie-comedy as it was presented in the new theater in Dublin with good applause, being an ancient story / written by H.B.</title>
                  <author>H. B. (Henry Burnell), fl. 1641.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>73 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>[s.n.],</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>Printed at Dublin :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1641.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Pages 11-16 repeated.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the Harvard University Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2007-12</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2008-01</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-07</date>
            <label>Lauren Proux</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-07</date>
            <label>Lauren Proux</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-09</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:47257:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:47257:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>Landgartha.</p>
            <p>A Tragie-Comedy, as it was preſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted in the new Theater in <hi>Dublin,</hi> with good applauſe, being an Ancient ſtory,</p>
            <p>
               <hi>VVritten by</hi> H. B.</p>
            <q>
               <bibl>HORAT.</bibl>
               <p>Hunc ſocci cepere pedem, grandeſ<expan>
                     <am>
                        <g ref="char:abque"/>
                     </am>
                     <ex>que</ex>
                  </expan> cothurni.</p>
            </q>
            <p>Printed at <hi>Dublin</hi> Anno 1641.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="dramatis_personae">
            <pb facs="tcp:47257:2" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <head>The perſons of the Play.</head>
            <list>
               <item>
                  <hi>Frollo</hi> King of <hi>Sweland</hi> and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>queror of <hi>Norway.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Haſmond</hi> and <hi>Gotar,</hi> two cour<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiers to <hi>Frollo.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Landgartha,</hi> a <hi>Norwegian</hi> Lady.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Scania,</hi> ſiſter to <hi>Landgartha.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Elſinora</hi> Aunt to both.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Fatyma,</hi> couſin to <hi>Land.</hi> &amp; <hi>Scan.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Marfiſa,</hi> an humorous gentlewo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man, couſin to <hi>Fatyma.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Fredericke</hi> and <hi>Wermond,</hi> two noble men of <hi>Norway.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Reyner</hi> King of <hi>Denmarke.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Valdemar,</hi> neer couſin to <hi>Reyner.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Inguar,</hi> a <hi>Daniſh</hi> noble man.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Hubba,</hi> an humorous merry <hi>Da<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſh</hi> Captaine.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Cowſell</hi> and <hi>Radgee,</hi> two fooliſh Coxcombes.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Rolfo,</hi> a Drawer.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Harrold,</hi> a competitor for <hi>Den<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>marke.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Eric,</hi> his brother.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Lothaire,</hi> a <hi>German</hi> noble man.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Vraca,</hi> daughter to <hi>Frollo.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Two poſts, a Scout,</hi> &amp; <hi>two Gentl,</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Phoebus, Pallas, Pryam, Hector.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Achylles,</hi> and <hi>Satyres,</hi> in a maske: which may be Acted by the forenam'd perſons.</item>
            </list>
         </div>
         <div type="dedication">
            <pb facs="tcp:47257:2"/>
            <head>THE EPISTLE Dedicatorie.</head>
            <opener>
               <salute>To all faire, indifferent faire, vertuous, that are not faire and magnanimous Ladies.</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg> Have here plac'd a patterne, yea, more then one (Ladies) for you to imitate Chaſtity and other vertues joyn'd to beauty, vertue ſingle and manly fortitude in the female Sexe, doe here preſent themſelves unto you. What you cannot reach one way take another: &amp; know that the form &amp; faculties of the minde, doe farre excell in worth thoſe of the body. Yet, both joyn'd (as in <hi>Landgartha</hi>) is of all the moſt excellent: in regard that that exter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nall beauty allures (nay commands) the minde of man (that affects viſible objects) to the love of ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tue, which it ſelfe do's poſſeſſe, and ſuffers (as moſt coveted) greater combats in the reſiſting of vice. Bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dily force too in a woman (were it but to defend it's owne Fort) is a perfection; though it cannot be ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pected but from a few of you, it will be ſufficient, that you never fall willingly, but in the way of ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour.
<pb facs="tcp:47257:3"/>
If I have not draw'n this faire viſage, as a chiefe Arts man: I hope yet (you will ſay) that I have made it indifferent handſome, and that my good will to effect it after the beſt faſhion for your ſakes: will notwithſtanding my weakneſſe, purchaſe an excuſe at leaſt for my boldneſſe, both in undertaking the worke and in offering of it (in part a poore braine borne Infant of mine, that covets to looke at the light) to be cheriſh'd by ſuch hands as yours, to kneele at the feete of your pietie. Whatſoever it be, or whoſoever got it: let it be yours, as is</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>The affectionate honourer of your perfections <hi>Henry Burnell.</hi>
               </signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="encomium">
            <pb facs="tcp:47257:3"/>
            <head>Patri ſuo Chariſsimo operis Encomium.</head>
            <lg>
               <l>M<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ltiplici rations, ſator, mea carmina (quamvis</l>
               <l>Non limata) tuis jungo; nempe ipſe petiſti,</l>
               <l>Cui teneor parere libens; formoſa virago</l>
               <l>Huc me veſtra movet, virtutis dotibus exors,</l>
               <l>In fraecte potius carnis qua compede ſolvi</l>
               <l>Certa fuit, foedat a foret quam crimine; cujus</l>
               <l>Iactatis <hi>Pyrrhae</hi> decus immortale reſurgit</l>
               <l>Nobilitus geſtis; ad quod praecordia magna</l>
               <l>Laetitia diffufa mihi, quando auribus hauſi</l>
               <l>Arrectis (genitor) te (per quem eſſentia, &amp; à quo</l>
               <l>Impetrata mihi, fruor &amp; quibus, omnia) culte,</l>
               <l>Conſulto, graviter, cum ſuavitate, venuſte,</l>
               <l>Praegnantem cauſam peragiſſe. Sed indere amoris</l>
               <l>Non probo delicias: quod te feciſſe ſequntum</l>
               <l>Hiſtori<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>normam; belle, ſcite<expan>
                     <am>
                        <g ref="char:abque"/>
                     </am>
                     <ex>que</ex>
                  </expan> jocantem</l>
               <l>Latificando alie<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>, non te, mens certa revolvit.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <head>Aliud.</head>
               <l>Melpomena tua tela (parens) contexta Thalia et,</l>
               <l>judicio quamvis non trutinanda meo eſt:</l>
               <l>Me tua ſed certam ſolers facundia, verax</l>
               <l>expertorum hominum &amp; fama diurna facit,</l>
               <l>Te nullis potuiſſe tuis errare, decorum</l>
               <l>omnimodo Scenis, ſed tenniſſe triplex;</l>
               <l>Nempe modum retinendo (docent ut ſcripta ſagacit</l>
               <l>Flacci) perſonae, temporis, at<expan>
                     <am>
                        <g ref="char:abque"/>
                     </am>
                     <ex>que</ex>
                  </expan> loci.</l>
               <l>Ad te à Invernis flexit victoria vatem.</l>
               <l>partibus his cedunt Brutiginae<expan>
                     <am>
                        <g ref="char:abque"/>
                     </am>
                     <ex>que</ex>
                  </expan> tibi.</l>
               <l>Fama quidem tendet, quacun<expan>
                     <am>
                        <g ref="char:abque"/>
                     </am>
                     <ex>que</ex>
                  </expan> auratus Apollo</l>
               <l>ſe tua: tu vives dum vehet amnis aquas.</l>
               <l>Tu pater Aenio deducens vertice muſas,</l>
               <l>gloria (non fallor) poſteritatis eris.</l>
               <l>Terra tuas certum est exhauriet extera laudes;</l>
               <l>clareſcet ſcriptis inſula noſtra tuis.</l>
            </lg>
            <closer>
               <signed>Eleonora Burnell.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="encomium">
            <pb facs="tcp:47257:4"/>
            <head>To his worthy to be much honoured Couſin <hi>Henry Burnell</hi> Eſq. on this his Tragie-Comedy, &amp;c.</head>
            <l>THough my prayſe cannot adde ought here: Yet, give</l>
            <l>Me leave (Couſin) to rayſe my ſelfe, and live</l>
            <l>Paſt time with thee; for, what thou writ'ſt is fine,</l>
            <l>Pleaſant, profound, chaſte, morall, and divine;</l>
            <l>Beyond the childiſh flaſhes of this age,</l>
            <l>Affected non-ſence, and <hi>Canarian</hi> rage;</l>
            <l>Or <hi>Garagantuan</hi> ſoppery. Not one word</l>
            <l>That's immateriall do'ſt thou affoord,</l>
            <l>Vaine, or ſuperfiuous. Thy phraſe is good;</l>
            <l>Nay, ſtrong, and elegant, though underſtood</l>
            <l>Not by light-headed ignorance that do's admire</l>
            <l>Strange language only. Wave, vote, flames, and fire,</l>
            <l>Tempeſts and whirlewinds, <hi>Scorpions,</hi> and <hi>Hags,</hi>
            </l>
            <l>Are ſtuffe that take ſuch, though indeed but rags,</l>
            <l>Baſe rags that they patch on, and thou do'ſt ſcorne;</l>
            <l>Or any dialect that is much worne,</l>
            <l>Though by the beſt; thy words thou mak'ſt to fit</l>
            <l>(Not contrary) th' Conceptions of thy wit.</l>
            <l>And, though thou <hi>England</hi> never ſaw'ſt: Yet, this</l>
            <l>(Let others boaſt of their owne faculties,</l>
            <l>Or being Sonne to <hi>Iohnſon</hi>) I dare ſay,</l>
            <l>That thou art farre more like to <hi>Ben</hi>
               <g ref="char:punc">▪</g> then they</l>
            <l>That lay clayme as heires to him, wrongfully:</l>
            <l>For he ſurvives now only, but in thee</l>
            <l>And his owne lines; the reſt degenerate.</l>
            <l>Nay, I can more affirme (and truly) that</l>
            <l>In ſome things thou do'ſt paſſe him: being more ſweet,</l>
            <l>More modeſt, mylde, leſſe tedious; Thy owne feer</l>
            <l>Goe thou on ſtoutly then: if thou proceed,</l>
            <l>Him (though 't be much) in all points thou'lt exceed.</l>
            <closer>
               <signed>Io. Bermingham.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="encomium">
            <pb facs="tcp:47257:4"/>
            <head>Ad nobiliſsimum ingenioſiſsimum, diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſertiſsimum<expan>
                  <am>
                     <g ref="char:abque"/>
                  </am>
                  <ex>que</ex>
               </expan> ſuum amicum Dominum <hi>Henricum Burnellum</hi> operis Elogium.</head>
            <l>VEllera laturus ſignorum principis, anceps</l>
            <l>Auſonides lecto milite cepit iter:</l>
            <l>Mox longos tentare ſinus, voto<expan>
                  <am>
                     <g ref="char:abque"/>
                  </am>
                  <ex>que</ex>
               </expan> potiri,</l>
            <l>Aeolios cives, Ionium<expan>
                  <am>
                     <g ref="char:abque"/>
                  </am>
                  <ex>que</ex>
               </expan> domans.</l>
            <l>Maſcula, caſta, decens, ſuaviſ<expan>
                  <am>
                     <g ref="char:abque"/>
                  </am>
                  <ex>que</ex>
               </expan>, (<hi>Henrice</hi>) virago</l>
            <l>Sola tibi invicta pubis ad inſtar adeſt.</l>
            <l>Ergo procelloſae Niſeidis, at<expan>
                  <am>
                     <g ref="char:abque"/>
                  </am>
                  <ex>que</ex>
               </expan> Charibdis</l>
            <l>Securus turbae, carbaſa pande Notis.</l>
            <l>Pande palam cedro tua digna volumina, Meci,</l>
            <l>Multorum<expan>
                  <am>
                     <g ref="char:abque"/>
                  </am>
                  <ex>que</ex>
               </expan> prius penſa bilance virûm.</l>
            <l>Pande nihil mancum: nil non laudabile: uil, quod</l>
            <l>Sympathicum non eſt, ſymmetriae<expan>
                  <am>
                     <g ref="char:abque"/>
                  </am>
                  <ex>que</ex>
               </expan> tenor.</l>
            <l>Currum Phoebus equis ſic, ſic robuſta Bootes</l>
            <l>Septem concordi plauſtra Trione regit.</l>
            <l>Magnes gnarorum: in rabiem Marpeſia cautes,</l>
            <l>Quorum Cerberea toxica fauce ſluunt.</l>
            <l>Carmine ſublimi morum icon, ſtilus honeſti,</l>
            <l>Calcar virtuti es, criminibuſ<expan>
                  <am>
                     <g ref="char:abque"/>
                  </am>
                  <ex>que</ex>
               </expan> jugum.</l>
            <l>Per<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>g Minervali tutus munimine: fiet</l>
            <l>Nobilior ſtudijs gens tua clara tuis.</l>
            <l>Munera, vive, tibi fulvo mage grata metallo,</l>
            <l>Aequora dum biberint proxima ſigna polo.</l>
            <closer>
               <signed>Philippus Patricius</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="prologue">
            <pb facs="tcp:47257:5"/>
            <head>Prologue delivered by an <hi>Amazon</hi> with a Battle-Axe in her hand.</head>
            <l>THe beſt of Engliſh Poets for the Stage</l>
            <l>(Such was the envie, niceneſſe, and the rage</l>
            <l>Of pettiſh weakelings, and detracting fooles,</l>
            <l>That could prayſe no man; and, I' th' muddie pooles</l>
            <l>Of their owne vices, were o'rwhelm'd) was faine</l>
            <l>An armed Prologue to produce, on paine</l>
            <l>Of being tongue-ſtrucke Therefore, marvell not</l>
            <l>The preſent author (having not forgot</l>
            <l>How in 's firſt Play, he met with too much ſpite)</l>
            <l>Sho'd ſend an armed <hi>Amazon,</hi> t' invite</l>
            <l>(If it be poſſible) all minds to affect</l>
            <l>What of himſelfe, he could not well expect</l>
            <l>From his detractors: Or, to let thoſe know,</l>
            <l>He cares not each of them prove ſtill a foe.</l>
            <l>Yet, this his ſecond (as that firſt) he made</l>
            <l>To pleaſe you, not for Money; to invade</l>
            <l>Your wills for your owne profit. For, if his minde</l>
            <l>He had ſought by it to content, you 'd finde</l>
            <l>Another method in't; and not a word</l>
            <l>Of any mirth or love wo'd he afford</l>
            <l>To make you laugh or languiſh. All, rich ſtuffe</l>
            <l>(Though not ſo pleaſing) he'd expoſe, to cuffe</l>
            <l>(And generally too) the monſter vice;</l>
            <l>Which he performes but gently, in this piece.</l>
            <l>Yet, it's beleev'd 't will pleaſe the moſt and beſt,</l>
            <l>In all the paſſages; and for the reſt,</l>
            <l>Let 'em (if they will needs) in pudles ſwim:</l>
            <l>For, he ſleights them more, then they can wrong him.</l>
         </div>
         <div type="body_of_play">
            <pb facs="tcp:47257:5"/>
            <head>Landgartha.</head>
            <div n="1" type="act">
               <head>The firſt Act.</head>
               <stage>Enter Fredericke and Wermond.</stage>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Fred.</speaker>
                  <l>
                     <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg>T's a noble, noble act!</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Wer.</speaker>
                  <l>And cannot</l>
                  <l>But vex the bloudy uſurper, let him put</l>
                  <l>Ever ſo good a face on't, though they were</l>
                  <l>But women only, that conſpire againſt him.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Fred.</speaker>
                  <l>It ſtirs him not: for ſince his conqueſt made</l>
                  <l>On us, and murdring of our lawfull Prince,</l>
                  <l>Things have ſucceeded ſo to all his wiſhes,</l>
                  <l>That he's grow'n careleſſe: nay blindly beſotted</l>
                  <l>By ſecurity, and ſelfe-perſwaſion,</l>
                  <l>Lock'd by the tempeſt of his luſt; ſo as</l>
                  <l>He feares no force of man; much leſſe weake women,</l>
                  <l>As he is pleaſd to tearme 'em; he minds nothing</l>
                  <l>But whom to kill, or foulely raviſh: and</l>
                  <l>The converſation of his Bawds, and Spintries.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Wer.</speaker>
                  <l>Is't poſsible, heſho'd be ſo ſecure,</l>
                  <l>And paſſe away in ſuch a dying ſlumber?</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Fred.</speaker>
                  <l>He thinkes the gods doe ſlumber too, or winke</l>
                  <l>
                     <pb facs="tcp:47257:6"/>At what he do's, or rather ſnore ſupinely;</l>
                  <l>Or that there are no gods, and what's ſpoke of 'em</l>
                  <l>Is but a meere fooliſh fable; He'll beleeve</l>
                  <l>No mans intelligence, not his owne ſpyes,</l>
                  <l>That this fleet of Denmarke, now lanch'd forth, ſho'd move</l>
                  <l>Againſt him hither.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Wer.</speaker>
                  <l>It's not all the power,</l>
                  <l>He for the preſent can command that will</l>
                  <l>Reſiſt it, if it doe; joyn'd to the valiant</l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Landgartha,</hi> with her faire ſock'd troope of Ladies:
<stage>Muſicke of Recorders.</stage>
                  </l>
                  <l>But, let's be ſilent; here the wretch himſelfe comes.</l>
               </sp>
               <stage>Enter Frollo leading a weeping Lady, Haſmond and Gotar.</stage>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Fr.</speaker>
                  <l>Come my pretty ſweet-heart, dry up thoſe pleaſing</l>
                  <l>Eyes; this liquor's too precious to be ſpilt</l>
                  <l>In ſuch a cauſe, for a loſt Maydenhead,</l>
                  <l>And to a King that will become thy ſlave for't,</l>
                  <l>And for more of that ſport: who to pleaſe thee</l>
                  <l>In that, and whatſoever elſe thou canſt conceive,</l>
                  <l>To rayſe content to thee, and varri'd to thought,</l>
                  <l>Will ranſacke Kingdomes.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Lady,</speaker>
                  <l>Leave me yet blacke Devill,
<stage>Breakes from him</stage>
                  </l>
                  <l>Thy words ſound farre worſe than the voyce of Hell.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Fr.</speaker>
                  <l>Some kicke the Spyder out at the Court gates;</l>
                  <l>An angry ſcratching Cat. We wold not be</l>
                  <l>So vex'd another night with ſuch a foole. <stage>Exeunt Fred. and Wer. with the Lady.</stage>
                  </l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Got.</speaker>
                  <l>She'll ſoone repent Sir, and turne backe, to offer</l>
                  <l>Her dainty body to your mylder uſage.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Haſm.</speaker>
                  <l>I rather thinke, ſhe<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ll to the mad <hi>Langartha</hi>;</l>
                  <l>And there make one among her furious troope</l>
                  <l>Of Furies, that will yet endure no horſing,</l>
                  <l>Though they manage bravely.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Fr.</speaker>
                  <l>There's a Wench indeed,</l>
                  <l>What lucke had I, never to lay my hands</l>
                  <l>On her? They ſay ſhe's very faire and handſome.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Haſm.</speaker>
                  <l>The clappers of mens tongues proclayme that; and</l>
                  <l>
                     <pb facs="tcp:47257:6"/>Speake ſtrange things of her.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Fr.</speaker>
                  <l>We ſhall finde'em (the beſt</l>
                  <l>Is of it) altogether, to make a royall</l>
                  <l>Choyce. We meane to ſingle forty at leaſt,</l>
                  <l>Of the moſt buxome (of which ſhe ſhall be</l>
                  <l>Chiefe generall, as now ſhe is) for our</l>
                  <l>Owne private pallat.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Haſm.</speaker>
                  <l>I may hope (Sir) you'll grant</l>
                  <l>Me halfe the number, with her wiſe and modeſt</l>
                  <l>Aunt <hi>Elſinora,</hi> to precede: Or her fine</l>
                  <l>Valorous ſiſter <hi>Scania,</hi> for I muſt</l>
                  <l>Imitate your manly vertue, Sir, as neere</l>
                  <l>As I can.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Fr.</speaker>
                  <l>Marke we'l what I ſay now: for thy</l>
                  <l>Good ſervice as my honeſt ſmocke Atturney</l>
                  <l>(Though ſometime, yet thou did'ſt begin to us, thou'lt ſay</l>
                  <l>For feare they'd beene diſeas'd:) thou ſhalt not have</l>
                  <l>One woman (wert thou e'er ſo willing) more</l>
                  <l>Or leſſe than thirty.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Haſm.</speaker>
                  <l>O Prodigious!
<stage>Ieeringly.</stage>
                  </l>
                  <l>I doe beſeech you, Sir, to heare me ſpeake,</l>
                  <l>Like ſo many Baſilisks (with angry ſhots</l>
                  <l>From their ſharpe venom'd eyes) they'd ſtrike me dead:</l>
                  <l>Or (as the Porcupyne) ſend fether'd arrowes</l>
                  <l>At me, for my ſlackneſſe.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Fr.</speaker>
                  <l>You muſt have thirty,</l>
                  <l>Or none.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Haſm.</speaker>
                  <l>Nay, If I muſt, I ſhall: and that's</l>
                  <l>As bad.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Got.</speaker>
                  <l>You will not (Sir) be altogether
<stage>Solemnely.</stage>
                  </l>
                  <l>Unmindefull of my good endeavours.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Fr.</speaker>
                  <l>By no meanes, good Sir, thou ſhalt poſſeſſe for thy</l>
                  <l>Share, twenty five; with the pretty ſmugge <hi>Fatyma,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>To leade'em.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Gotar.</speaker>
                  <l>I humbly thanke your grace, though I</l>
                  <l>Sho'd not covet ſo many deſperate femals:</l>
                  <l>Yet, with the aſſiſtance of my kindeſt friends,</l>
                  <l>I ſhall be ſtrongly back'd.
<stage>Enter Wermond.</stage>
                  </l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <pb facs="tcp:47257:7"/>
                  <speaker>Wermond.</speaker>
                  <l>May it pleaſe you, Sir,</l>
                  <l>Here are arriv'd two poſts at once, all full</l>
                  <l>Of ſweat and durt; and bring bad newes, it's fear'd.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Fr.</speaker>
                  <l>Curſe on thy feares, Goe, ſend 'em hither to us;
<stage>Exit.</stage>
                  </l>
                  <l>It's but theſe women that affright fooles thus.
<stage>Enter firſt poſt.</stage>
                  </l>
                  <l>What newes? be briefe.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Gotar.</speaker>
                  <l>He's full of durt, indeed!</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>1. <hi>Poſt.</hi>
                  </speaker>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Landgartha</hi> with a mighty troope of women,</l>
                  <l>Gatherd to her from all the parts of <hi>Norway,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>Make havocke of your ſouldiers, ſir; and killing</l>
                  <l>All the Swed<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> they light vpon, they likewiſe threaten,</l>
                  <l>They will grant you (ere long) no better quarter.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Fr.</speaker>
                  <l>My Sweds and I will make ſome, here in <hi>Norway,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>Pay dearely for that vant. Come, doe thou croake too
<stage>
                        <hi>Enter</hi> 2. <hi>poſt.</hi>
                     </stage>
                  </l>
                  <l>The worſt tale thou canſt.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>2. <hi>Poſt.</hi>
                  </speaker>
                  <l>You had neede, Sir, make quicke</l>
                  <l>Reſiſtance, or ſhift for your ſelfe: for, the King</l>
                  <l>Of <hi>Denmarke,</hi> with a mighty fleete, has now</l>
                  <l>Put in at <hi>Maſtrand</hi>; and begins to land</l>
                  <l>His forces, to joyne with <hi>Landgartha's</hi>: who</l>
                  <l>With maine ſpeede, marches to meete him thither.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Fr.</speaker>
                  <l>Which he ſhall ſoone repent, and ſo ſhall that</l>
                  <l>Male-harted Traytreſſe, withall the curll'd knot</l>
                  <l>Of rebels that attend her; We are not</l>
                  <l>So unprovided, as they doe ſuppoſe yet,</l>
                  <l>Fly therefore <hi>Haſmomd,</hi> gather thou our troopes</l>
                  <l>Within and neere the Citie. <hi>Gotar,</hi> thou</l>
                  <l>Haſte to the quarters further of; and with</l>
                  <l>All poſſible ſpeed draw unto us. Away</l>
                  <l>When need compels, men muſt uſe no delay.
<stage>Exeunt omnes:</stage>
                  </l>
               </sp>
               <stage>A march, then enter Landgartha, Scania, Elſinora, Fatyma, and one or two Ladies more, all attyr'd like Amazons, wtih Battle-axes in their hands and Swords on.</stage>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Land.</speaker>
                  <l>We now (ſweet Ladies and deare ſiſters) march not</l>
                  <l>Againſt th'intemperate <hi>Frollo</hi>: but aſcend</l>
                  <l>The milkie way, that leads to immortall fame,</l>
                  <l>
                     <pb facs="tcp:47257:7"/>Not to be rank'd among the ſtarre-made harlots:</l>
                  <l>But ſtated in the high'ſt Empyrcall heaven,</l>
                  <l>To ſide the gods, where <hi>Pallas</hi> and chaſt <hi>Phoebe</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>(Arm'd chiefely with the weapons of their vertues)</l>
                  <l>Keepe all the Maſculin deities in awe.</l>
                  <l>This our deſigne may well exalt us thither,</l>
                  <l>As their good deeds did them: that in defence</l>
                  <l>Of that all ſho'd hold deareſt, our honours, Ladies,</l>
                  <l>Doe now expoſe our ſelves to death, and what</l>
                  <l>A cruell, vicious, revengefull Tyrant</l>
                  <l>May inflict on us, if vanquiſh'd. Yet, this act</l>
                  <l>Of ours we muſt not vainely boaſt of: for,</l>
                  <l>The little birds will (with their beaks and wings)</l>
                  <l>Offend the raviſhers of their young iſſue.</l>
                  <l>What then ſhould we performe thinke you, that farre</l>
                  <l>Paſſe theſe? yeild up your bodies baſely to</l>
                  <l>Foule rape and luſt, and ſo to infamie</l>
                  <l>For ever? No, no: farre be this from us</l>
                  <l>Honour'd virgins, that have ſuch armes to wield</l>
                  <l>Theſe cutting weapons, being (too) to fight authoriz'd,</l>
                  <l>By the examples of the nobleſt women,</l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Semiramis, Zenobia,</hi> faire <hi>Cinana</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>Siſter unto great <hi>Macedon,</hi> ſtout <hi>Alvilda,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Cumilla,</hi> and the Amazonian Queenes,</l>
                  <l>Great <hi>Mithridates</hi> Queene, and ſeverall others,</l>
                  <l>Are patterns now for us to imitate;</l>
                  <l>O moſt brave patterns! Yet this we may ſay,</l>
                  <l>That our chaſt glories ſhall paſſe theirs, as farre</l>
                  <l>As th' worth of our intentions doth exceed</l>
                  <l>The cauſe they undertooke: nor ought you doubt it.</l>
                  <l>Let then the King of <hi>Denmarke</hi> fight where he liſt:</l>
                  <l>We will purſue no other than our worſt</l>
                  <l>And ſtrongeſt adverſary in's owne ſquadron;</l>
                  <l>Where I, as firſt, will looſe my life, or give</l>
                  <l>A ſuddaine end to his blacke purpoſes,</l>
                  <l>That fought a conqueſt on our chaſtities.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Elſinor.</speaker>
                  <l>Thy vertues and example, Neece: that are not</l>
                  <l>To be reach'd by any imitation</l>
                  <l>
                     <pb facs="tcp:47257:8"/>(At leaſt of our endeavours) doe farre more</l>
                  <l>Excite our courages, then <hi>Hermes</hi> could,</l>
                  <l>Were he now here, to play the Orator:</l>
                  <l>Lead on then; you ſhall find us no bad ſeconds.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Scania.</speaker>
                  <l>I have more than a womans longing to begin.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Land.</speaker>
                  <l>I know <hi>Fatyma,</hi> though ſhe be not great,</l>
                  <l>Has not the leaſt deſire to fight among us.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Fatyma.</speaker>
                  <l>Stay till you ſee me knocke ſome great ones downe;</l>
                  <l>Untill when, I ſhall well remit your prayſes.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Land.</speaker>
                  <l>Then follow me; and as you ſee me wooe</l>
                  <l>The <hi>Swediſh</hi> King, to his doe you ſo too.
<stage>Exeunt. A march.</stage>
                  </l>
               </sp>
               <stage>Enter Reyner, Valdemar, Inguar, Hubba, and one or two or more Souldiers with Axes.</stage>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Reyner.</speaker>
                  <l>It's my chiefe comfort, noble <hi>Cymbrians,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>Subjects and friends, to be your guide to day,</l>
                  <l>Againſt a valiant, wicked adverſary;</l>
                  <l>And for our right, th' inheritance of this kingdome,</l>
                  <l>To ſhew that vertue and the cauſe, doe more</l>
                  <l>Prevayle than any humane fortitude,</l>
                  <l>Or ſetl'd Councels, when they're joyn'd to vice;</l>
                  <l>And by injuſtice ſeeke to advance their ſtates:</l>
                  <l>Which wiſely our forefathers mask'd beneath</l>
                  <l>The fables of the <hi>Titans</hi> 'gainſt the gods.</l>
                  <l>But it ſho'd ſeeme the vertue of our foes</l>
                  <l>(Wiſedome and valour) has forſooke'em, by</l>
                  <l>Their palliardiſe, by eaſe, and hourely ryot;</l>
                  <l>This kingdome being more fatall unto them,</l>
                  <l>Then <hi>Capua</hi> was to <hi>Hannibal</hi>: and therefore,</l>
                  <l>Not worth your meaneſt feares: I muſt not then</l>
                  <l>Inlarge my ſelfe in words too farre, becauſe</l>
                  <l>You need 'em not; nor need you be beholding,</l>
                  <l>Unto the fames of your brave Anceſtors,</l>
                  <l>Thoſe valiant <hi>Cymbrians,</hi> that almoſt gave</l>
                  <l>An end to <hi>Rome,</hi> the Miſtris of the world,</l>
                  <l>And not in her declyning dayes, when her</l>
                  <l>Owne vices had confounded her; as when</l>
                  <l>
                     <pb facs="tcp:47257:8"/>The <hi>Gothes</hi> and <hi>Vandals</hi> (now our enemies)</l>
                  <l>Did trample on her, being downe before.</l>
                  <l>She liv'd full man, when great King <hi>Beleus</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>Did (on the borders of rich <hi>Jtaly</hi>)</l>
                  <l>Vanquiſh three of her braveſt Generals,</l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Sylanus, Coepio,</hi> and <hi>Manilius.</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>This (if you pleaſe) you may conſider; and</l>
                  <l>That our foes are more famous for their whoredomes,</l>
                  <l>Than conquering of <hi>Norway.</hi> Reflect alſo</l>
                  <l>How for this cauſe, we are aſſiſted by</l>
                  <l>An Angel troope, of chaſt and noble Ladies:</l>
                  <l>Whom neyther loſſe of life, or other evils</l>
                  <l>Can fright, from ſeeking to revenge the wrongs</l>
                  <l>Done to their Sex, their parents, and their friends.</l>
                  <l>Then, let's not ſhame our ſelves now in their preſence,</l>
                  <l>Or to poſteritie: by being out-gone</l>
                  <l>By women in a battle. Laſtly, conſider</l>
                  <l>The everlaſting honour due to vertue;</l>
                  <l>Of which we now ſhall make a glorious purchaſe.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Hub.</speaker>
                  <l>I am affraid you will conſider (ſir,)</l>
                  <l>So long of theſe women; untill you forget</l>
                  <l>What you applaud ſo feelingly, your vertue.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Rey.</speaker>
                  <l>Thou 'rt alwayes merry, <hi>Hubba,</hi> honeſt withall;</l>
                  <l>And from my heart I wiſh, that each man here</l>
                  <l>Performe a Souldiers parts, no worſe than thou;</l>
                  <l>We ſhall not then be beaten.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Vald.</speaker>
                  <l>Let's march on, ſir:</l>
                  <l>And you ſhall quickly find the meaneſt of 'em,</l>
                  <l>Valiant and ſtrong to purchaſe what's your birth-right.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Rey.</speaker>
                  <l>Then let us move; and proſper too, as we</l>
                  <l>Affect injuſtice, or impietie.
<stage>Exeunt. A march</stage>
                  </l>
               </sp>
               <stage>Enter Frollo, Haſmond, Gotar, and two or three more with Axes.</stage>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Frollo.</speaker>
                  <l>We muſt not looſe our confidence, brave Warriors,</l>
                  <l>Though we be taken ſomewhat tardy, by</l>
                  <l>A ſort of raw freſh-water ſouldiers, weake</l>
                  <l>
                     <pb facs="tcp:47257:9"/>Unmartiall women fitter for night encounters,</l>
                  <l>And ſome poore fugitive <hi>Norwegian</hi> rebels,</l>
                  <l>Conquer'd and beaten oft by us before.</l>
                  <l>What then although our numbers be the leſſe?</l>
                  <l>Yet not by much: the glory of the adventure,</l>
                  <l>Would not be worth the paines we under tooke elſe.</l>
                  <l>Beſides, if we conſider what our Anceſtors</l>
                  <l>Have (by their never-equall'd vallors) oft</l>
                  <l>Perform'd againſt the nobleſt nations of</l>
                  <l>The world, this our deſigne is nothing: nothing</l>
                  <l>To what they did: What we have done our ſelves,</l>
                  <l>And meane to doe hereafter. Notwithſtanding,</l>
                  <l>Let me commend unto your memories,</l>
                  <l>After a generall faſhion (for now</l>
                  <l>The time exacts deeds more than words) what ſome</l>
                  <l>Of their large conqueſts were, not onely in</l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Europe,</hi> Which was all theirs a moſt: but in</l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Affricke,</hi> a third and richeſt part of th'world;</l>
                  <l>Which from the <hi>Ocean</hi> unto <hi>Nyle</hi> they won;</l>
                  <l>And from the <hi>Mid-land</hi> Sea, to the torrid <hi>Zone.</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>Great <hi>Rome</hi> her ſelfe (that wiſedome boaſted moſt,</l>
                  <l>And next her vallor) was by our fathers taken,</l>
                  <l>Pillag'd, and burnt foure times at leaſt; and her</l>
                  <l>Large Empyre brought to nothing. She maſter'd all:</l>
                  <l>We maſter'd her;</l>
                  <l>And will not now degenerate firſt of ours.</l>
                  <l>What though men ſay, we are not religious?</l>
                  <l>Religion is but a toy, and firſt invented</l>
                  <l>By politicke States, to keepe fooles in awe;</l>
                  <l>And of all men obſerved leaſt by themſelves,</l>
                  <l>If ſhe but thwart the leaſt of their intendments.</l>
                  <l>They glorifie her much for their owne ends;</l>
                  <l>And that's even almoſt all: and ſo may we.</l>
                  <l>Yet, honour by warre, riches, and our pleaſure,</l>
                  <l>Shall be the Altars, and the gods we'll bow to</l>
                  <l>In our free mindes; and what we gaine we'l keepe.</l>
                  <l>King <hi>Reyner</hi> therefore was not wiſe, in ſeeking</l>
                  <l>To diſpoſſeſſe the braveſt Nation breathing,</l>
                  <l>
                     <pb facs="tcp:47257:9"/>Of what they have atchiev'd by the right of conqueſt;</l>
                  <l>And ſhall (I hope) in ſnatching at our Crowne,</l>
                  <l>By your more pow'rfull armes, ſoone miſſe his own.
<stage>Ex. Allarums.</stage>
                  </l>
               </sp>
               <stage>A good while after the allarums are begun, Enter Frolle and a gentleman.</stage>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Frol.</speaker>
                  <l>Furies and plagues: theſe wild, wild bloudy whores,</l>
                  <l>Fight like ſo many Tygers: without the leaſt</l>
                  <l>Apprehenſion of feare, or any kind</l>
                  <l>Of mercy: the purſie <hi>Danes</hi> come nothing neere 'em.</l>
                  <l>Having cut off our vauntgard, and right wing,</l>
                  <l>They preſſe on our maine battle too; and force</l>
                  <l>It to give ground. Goe, fly thou: and charge <hi>Haſmond</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>To fetch the reare with ſpeed up; that we may
<stage>Exit gentl.</stage>
                  </l>
                  <l>(There being no other hope for ſafety left us)</l>
                  <l>Upon one deſperat onſlaught hazard all.
<stage>Enter Scania.</stage>
                  </l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Scan.</speaker>
                  <l>I am glad I've met you, ſir.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Frol.</speaker>
                  <l>A pretty fine peece,
<stage>aſide.</stage>
                  </l>
                  <l>I wo'd faine ſave this. I ſho'd preferre</l>
                  <l>Thy beautie, unto ought that's ours; prove kind</l>
                  <l>And gentle unto thee, ſweet-heart: if thou 'lt</l>
                  <l>But yeeld —</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Scania.</speaker>
                  <l>To thy imbraces, that muſt 'a' had</l>
                  <l>My ſiſter, me and forty more. We now</l>
                  <l>Shall ſee what you can doe 'gainſt one. Come quickly</l>
                  <l>Then, vnto your guard ſir: or I ſhall ſoone ſend forth</l>
                  <l>Your too hot bloud, to coole your luſtfull heart.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Frol.</speaker>
                  <l>Plague on you for a company of ſpitefull,</l>
                  <l>Venomous tong'd bitches. Ye had rather lye</l>
                  <l>With the worſt Hynde of your owne, than the beſt of us.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Scan.</speaker>
                  <l>Villaine, I'll anſwer thee another way.
<stage>Offers to fight on which Land. enters.</stage>
                  </l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Land.</speaker>
                  <l>Hold ſiſter. This muſt only be my mate:</l>
                  <l>Goe, ſeeke you out another ſomewhere elſe?
<stage>Exit Scania.</stage>
                  </l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Frol.</speaker>
                  <l>Art thou <hi>Landgartha</hi>? or ſome ſupernall goddeſſe,</l>
                  <l>Deſcended in her fairer ſhape, to make</l>
                  <l>A conqueſt now on <hi>Frollo,</hi> that muſt yeeld</l>
                  <l>Himſelfe thy captive?</l>
               </sp>
               <pb facs="tcp:47257:10"/>
               <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                  <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb facs="tcp:47257:10"/>
               <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                  <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb facs="tcp:47257:11"/>
               <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                  <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb facs="tcp:47257:11"/>
               <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                  <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb facs="tcp:47257:12"/>
               <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                  <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb facs="tcp:47257:12"/>
               <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                  <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <sp>
                  <pb facs="tcp:47257:13"/>
                  <speaker>Land.</speaker>
                  <l>Thou once call'dſt me ſubject;</l>
                  <l>And I am come to tender my alleageance,</l>
                  <l>To your ungracious wickedneſſe, thus —
<stage>ſtricks at him.</stage>
                  </l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Frol.</speaker>
                  <l>Hold, for heavens ſake hold, and patiently</l>
                  <l>But take my faithfull vow. Doe thou withdraw</l>
                  <l>Thy troopes from our defeat: and by the <hi>Olympian</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>Gods, I ſhall no ſooner</l>
                  <l>Have ſtrucke King <hi>Reyner</hi> with his punie <hi>Danes,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>But I'll make thee my Queene.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Land.</speaker>
                  <l>Thy Concubyne.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Frol.</speaker>
                  <l>All miſeries light on me then for ever;</l>
                  <l>Or if I ever mixe with woman but</l>
                  <l>Thy ſelfe: for thou art worthy of a <hi>Mars.</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>A <hi>Hercules,</hi> or <hi>Iupiter.</hi>
                  </l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Land.</speaker>
                  <l>And have</l>
                  <l>Fully reſolv'd never to kiſſe any man,</l>
                  <l>But him that ſhall firſt maſter me in fight:</l>
                  <l>You are beſt therefore looke well to your ſelfe, ſir;</l>
                  <l>Or I ſhall quickly marry your hearts bloud</l>
                  <l>To this weapon.
<stage>They fight &amp; he's hurt.</stage>
                  </l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Frol.</speaker>
                  <l>I bleed you ſee: let which</l>
                  <l>Serve as an offering, to appeaſe thy wrath</l>
                  <l>Conceiv'd againſt a wretch, that now repents
<stage>Here Rey. Vald. Inguar. &amp; Hubb. are diſcovered.</stage>
                  </l>
                  <l>(Unfainedly) his former evill life.</l>
                  <l>May the gods chiefe attribute then (mercy)</l>
                  <l>Find roome for me (a Convertite) in thy</l>
                  <l>Noble and vertuous ſoule: and I ſhall ſtill</l>
                  <l>Become thy pious imitator: be</l>
                  <l>Govern'd by thee in all thing, and thy husband,</l>
                  <l>By heaven and all, I will.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Land.</speaker>
                  <l>But I hope you ſhall not:</l>
                  <l>For I muſt try your manhood once againe.
<stage>They fight, and ſhe ſtrikes him downe.</stage>
                  </l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Reyn.</speaker>
                  <l>O brave mayde!</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Frol.</speaker>
                  <l>Faire <hi>Furie,</hi> thou haſt kill'd me,</l>
                  <l>Hell take thee for 't my love is now cool'd indeed.</l>
                  <l>But I will be reveng'd. I cannot, cannot riſe:</l>
                  <l>The loſſe of bloud, and paine, ſtrike faint my pow'rs:</l>
                  <l>That I were now on high transform'd <hi>Atlas:</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <pb facs="tcp:47257:13"/>This being no fable, but a truth: that I</l>
                  <l>Might cut the axle-tree of heaven in two:</l>
                  <l>And tumble downe the gods, and breake their necks,</l>
                  <l>Proud gods, if ſuch there be. Then, like <hi>Enceladus</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>(Loaden with flaming <hi>Etna</hi>) I ſho'd turne,</l>
                  <l>And ſhake out all the ſtarres: The ſunne, and with</l>
                  <l>That fire, burne all to cinders. Thus I'd turne:</l>
                  <l>O divels, I cannot: but doe feele a pitchy</l>
                  <l>Cloud (darker than night) hang o'r my drowſie temples:</l>
                  <l>And muſt (there is no remedy) deſcend, to ſtalke</l>
                  <l>A long th'infernall waves, or wafted over,</l>
                  <l>Grapple with the damned <hi>Furies,</hi> receive my ſoule</l>
                  <l>You beaſtly Hags, then: that ſhall torment you more,</l>
                  <l>Than you can any.
<stage>Dyes.</stage>
                  </l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Land.</speaker>
                  <l>The gods are now reveng'd</l>
                  <l>On thee, by me, libidinous Woolfe, foule Tyrant.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Rey.</speaker>
                  <l>And rid me (worthy Lady,) of a dangerous</l>
                  <l>Adverſary.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Land.</speaker>
                  <l>I doe beſeech, ſir:
<stage>Kneels on one knee.</stage>
                  </l>
                  <l>As my duty onely to receive that,</l>
                  <l>Vnto them and your grace, though a woman.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Rey.</speaker>
                  <l>This to me (Madame) is too great an honour.</l>
                  <l>Pray ſtand up. I ſhould rather kneele to you,</l>
                  <l>Whoſe beauty and incomparable vertues,</l>
                  <l>Exact no ſlender adoration,</l>
                  <l>From all thoſe that love goodneſſe; or the image</l>
                  <l>Of heaven in your face. We muſt acknowledge,</l>
                  <l>Notwithſtanding our right to the crowne of <hi>Norway,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>What pow'r ſoe'r we have in't, gain'd and confirm'd</l>
                  <l>Chiefly by you, that are our ſtrongeſt friend.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Land.</speaker>
                  <l>Your poore and humble vaſſall, that deſires</l>
                  <l>No other recompence for her ſmall ſervice,</l>
                  <l>Than your Kingly licence, to remaine</l>
                  <l>(When your foes are wholly vanquiſh'd) from all</l>
                  <l>Imployment ſever'd: to leade a ſolitary</l>
                  <l>Quiet life, being compell'd (in the defence</l>
                  <l>Of what I ever moſt eſteemed) to match</l>
                  <l>Thus amongſt men; which I did not covet, but</l>
                  <l>
                     <pb facs="tcp:47257:14"/>The contrary.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Rey.</speaker>
                  <l>You will not wrong the world</l>
                  <l>(The race of man, ſweet Lady,) ſo to robb it</l>
                  <l>Of ſuch luſtre: nay of all light, by</l>
                  <l>Dedicating of what is onely good in't,</l>
                  <l>Your ſelfe, to ſolitude.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Land.</speaker>
                  <l>I muſt no be</l>
                  <l>Compell'd to any ſtate of life, ſir.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Rey.</speaker>
                  <l>You cannot</l>
                  <l>Madame, I ſee that; and (by your force my foes</l>
                  <l>Now put to flight) I ſhall continue alwayes,</l>
                  <l>Not onely a meere ſervant, but for ever</l>
                  <l>Your bondman; not to offend you i' th' leaſt thought.
<stage>Enter Sca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nia, Elſino<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ra, &amp; Fat.</stage>
                  </l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Vald.</speaker>
                  <l>Here be other noble friends (ſir) to whom you</l>
                  <l>Stand bound in no ſmall ſummes.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Elſinor.</speaker>
                  <l>Of Princely favour</l>
                  <l>Onely.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Rey.</speaker>
                  <l>Riſe faire Ladies, you ſhall command</l>
                  <l>Vs, being your creature. <hi>Hub.</hi> they're delicate fine wenches, pretty youths.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Land.</speaker>
                  <l>You are now, ſir</l>
                  <l>To conſider, how to uſe your victory.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Scania.</speaker>
                  <l>For us, we ſhall hereafter (we doubt not)</l>
                  <l>Partake the fruits of your moſt Royall bounty,</l>
                  <l>Which we ſhall begge more, for the generall</l>
                  <l>Good, than our particular intereſts, ſir.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Rey.</speaker>
                  <l>You ſhall be the Law-makers, to your ſelves:</l>
                  <l>For thoſe, by whom we raigne, ſhall be our guides:</l>
                  <l>In the meane time, thou <hi>Valdemar</hi> and <hi>Inguar,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>Purſue the flying foe, but moſt with mercie,</l>
                  <l>Not of circumſpection; yet, leaſt th' Van</l>
                  <l>Turne by ſome accident, by us not thought on;</l>
                  <l>Save all that yeeld, whom we doe meane to ſend</l>
                  <l>Home ranſomeleſſe; to ſee if that benefit</l>
                  <l>May worke a peace betwixt us. If it doe not,</l>
                  <l>We ſhall the next time be the more excus'd,</l>
                  <l>In our extending of ſeveritie.</l>
                  <l>Come Ladies, we'll to counſell to conclude</l>
                  <l>Concerning what we have (by you) ſubdu'd.</l>
               </sp>
            </div>
            <div n="2" type="act">
               <pb facs="tcp:47257:14"/>
               <head>The ſecond Act.</head>
               <stage>Enter Valdemar, and Jnguar.</stage>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Vald.</speaker>
                  <l>It's a ſtrange humor that has ſeaz'd upon him;</l>
                  <l>whatſoever the cauſe be.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Inguar.</speaker>
                  <l>When you are</l>
                  <l>Ignorant of it, all others muſt be ſo.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Vald.</speaker>
                  <l>He diſcovers nothing to me ſave onely</l>
                  <l>That he is full (and that he often ſayes)</l>
                  <l>Of griefe and heavineſſe; and ſometimes ſicke.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Ing.</speaker>
                  <l>His ſickneſſe may (in time) prove dangerous,</l>
                  <l>If ſome fit remedy be not apply'd.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ald.</speaker>
                  <l>He'll heare of none; I urg'd his Phyſitians,</l>
                  <l>At which he ſtorm'd, and bad me leave him to</l>
                  <l>Himſelfe; and ſince I dare not come in ſight.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Ingar.</speaker>
                  <l>It's a deadly malady, that will admit</l>
                  <l>Of no cure We are beſt put Captaine <hi>Hubba,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>Or the wiſe <hi>Cowſell</hi> on him: for the wit</l>
                  <l>Of the one and th'others folly may remove</l>
                  <l>More of that griefe he ſpeaks on, than good counſell.
<stage>Enter Rey.</stage>
                  </l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Vald.</speaker>
                  <l>Here comes the man himſelfe, in his uſuall</l>
                  <l>Meditation: and therefore let's away.
<stage>Exeunt ambo,</stage>
                  </l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Reyn.</speaker>
                  <l>She is divinely faire, and in her mind</l>
                  <l>The nobleſt vertues keepe their reſidence,</l>
                  <l>As in their loveli'ſt habitation,</l>
                  <l>Being all in love with her, I thinke, as I am,</l>
                  <l>From my ſad heart warme teares (teares of affliction)</l>
                  <l>The fire of my affection doth ſend up</l>
                  <l>Into my eyes, that thence diſtill in ſtreames,</l>
                  <l>Which yet to me, are torrents of ſweet joyes,</l>
                  <l>Ioyes, that this is for her, my griefe proceeds</l>
                  <l>From a profound feare I ſhall never gaine her,</l>
                  <l>Injoy that unpeer'd modell of perfection.</l>
                  <l>There is no way but one to pull the fruit</l>
                  <l>
                     <pb facs="tcp:47257:15"/>
                     <hi>Jove</hi> would turne Gooſe, taſte: ſhe's ſo reſerv'd</l>
                  <l>To the leaſt vicious acts; Wretch, that hope</l>
                  <l>Is not (yet) left thee: For, being nobly borne</l>
                  <l>(Though ſhe no fit match be for us, in lieu</l>
                  <l>Of worldly ſubſtance, being in her ſelfe</l>
                  <l>An ample dowry for a richer Prince)</l>
                  <l>We ſho'd (and gladly) ſue to be her husband.</l>
                  <l>But a report goes, ſhe will joyne with no man,</l>
                  <l>In ſuch an obligation, which (that ſhe</l>
                  <l>Will not at all have me) is that which ſtriks</l>
                  <l>A blacke deſpaire into my ſoule, and will</l>
                  <l>(Vnleſſe I meete ſome comfort) quickly kill me;</l>
                  <l>Being ſicke in body, as in mind already.
<stage>Enter Hub &amp; Cowſell.</stage>
                  </l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Hub.</speaker>
                  <l>See, where he ſtalks. Doe you but put him out</l>
                  <l>Of his ſad humor; and thou ſha't have—</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Cow.</speaker>
                  <l>O Captaine,</l>
                  <l>I am afraid, for he looks ſowre upon't.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Hub.</speaker>
                  <l>No matter: feare you nothing, but proceed;</l>
                  <l>And care not what you ſay, ſo you ſay ſomething;</l>
                  <l>It's your fooles faſhion, and you now muſt ſeeme one.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Cow.</speaker>
                  <l>But hearke, you, Captaine. How ſho'd I begin?</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Hub.</speaker>
                  <l>Say that you come from the Ladies: ſo I leave you.
<stage>Exit Hub. &amp; peeps.</stage>
                  </l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Rey.</speaker>
                  <l>Sirra, what make you here?</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Cow.</speaker>
                  <l>Come from the Ladies.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Rey.</speaker>
                  <l>Well ſayd, ſpeake that againe.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Cow.</speaker>
                  <l>Come from the Ladies.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Rey.</speaker>
                  <l>Very good, and what of them?</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Cow.</speaker>
                  <l>Come from the Ladies.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Rey.</speaker>
                  <l>What, againe. Pray tell me, what did occaſion</l>
                  <l>Your ſo kind friendly viſit to the Ladies?</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Cow.</speaker>
                  <l>I went thither (being ſome two myle of)</l>
                  <l>To be joviall with a new acquaintance</l>
                  <l>Of mine, my brother <hi>Radger.</hi>
                  </l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Rey.</speaker>
                  <l>Some ſuch wiſe man,</l>
                  <l>As thou art.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Cow.</speaker>
                  <l>He's a very honeſt man.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Rey.</speaker>
                  <l>And takes his cup ſoundly, I warrant.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Cowſell.</speaker>
                  <l>So</l>
                  <l>
                     <pb facs="tcp:47257:15"/>Doe many honeſt men beſide him; and</l>
                  <l>Keepe wenches too, that's more.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Rey.</speaker>
                  <l>And yet are honeſt.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Cow.</speaker>
                  <l>'s honeſt and faire-condition'd gentlemen,</l>
                  <l>As live, I know ſeverall of 'em, my ſelfe.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Rey.</speaker>
                  <l>The Ladies are well. How did they uſe thee? tell.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Cow.</speaker>
                  <l>They're all exceeding well: and us'd me kindly</l>
                  <l>For your ſake; gave me a banquet, ſtrawberries</l>
                  <l>And creame; we drunke helter-skelter too; the Ladies</l>
                  <l>Tooke your health themſelves, and ask'd me how you did;</l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Landgartha</hi> ſay'd, you were a good man, and that</l>
                  <l>She lov'd you with all her heart.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Rey.</speaker>
                  <l>Let me imbrace
<stage>Jmbraces him.</stage>
                  </l>
                  <l>Thee from my heart for that good newes.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Hub.</speaker>
                  <l>Sweet King,</l>
                  <l>Have I found your malady?</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Cow.</speaker>
                  <l>O kind Prince!
<stage>Aſide.</stage>
                  </l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Rey.</speaker>
                  <l>What ſayeſt? are they not delicate fine creatures?</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Cow.</speaker>
                  <l>Indifferent handſome, paſſable, and ſo forth —</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Hub.</speaker>
                  <l>You 'll with a knocke be ſent forth, I ſee that.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Rey.</speaker>
                  <l>I was not from thy want of wit, to expect</l>
                  <l>Any true cenſure. But yet, tell me truely:</l>
                  <l>Which of 'em all doſt thou thinke is the faireſt?</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Cow.</speaker>
                  <l>The Lady <hi>Elſinora</hi> in my opinion,</l>
                  <l>Is th' rich Pearle amongſt 'em; <hi>Landgartha</hi> to her</l>
                  <l>Is but a meere milkemayde.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Rey.</speaker>
                  <l>He makes me ſicke,</l>
                  <l>A dunce to wrong the worlds chiefe ornament.
<stage>Kicks, &amp; beats him.</stage>
                  </l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Cow.</speaker>
                  <l>Oh, oh my bum! my bum!
<stage>Exit, and enter Hubba.</stage>
                  </l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Hub.</speaker>
                  <l>I perceive I muſt</l>
                  <l>Venture a beating too.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Rey.</speaker>
                  <l>Thou mett'ſt a foole</l>
                  <l>Going out that way.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Hub.</speaker>
                  <l>And he complaines of ſomething</l>
                  <l>Vnder favour.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Rey.</speaker>
                  <l>We gave ſome cauſe for 't, but</l>
                  <l>Doe now repent it. Prethee <hi>Hubba</hi> call him;</l>
                  <l>He ſayd ſome at of the Ladies.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <pb facs="tcp:47257:16"/>
                  <speaker>Hub.</speaker>
                  <l>I can tell</l>
                  <l>You more of 'em than he: for, I was lately too</l>
                  <l>Where they (like a companie of fine ducklings)</l>
                  <l>Wag together.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Rey.</speaker>
                  <l>Thy words are baſe.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Hub.</speaker>
                  <l>What wo'd</l>
                  <l>You have me ſay? they are all very valiant;</l>
                  <l>And made King <hi>Frollo</hi> pay for ſeeking (and</l>
                  <l>But in's good will) to domineere a little</l>
                  <l>Over 'em; he loſt his life and kingdomes by 't.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Rey.</speaker>
                  <l>We therefore ought the better to love them.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Hub.</speaker>
                  <l>As your ſubjects onely, ſir, but not to caſt</l>
                  <l>Vnder you on a bed, couch, or cleane mat;</l>
                  <l>You know what fine <hi>Furies</hi> they are, if you vex 'em.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Rey.</speaker>
                  <l>We are not ſo unwiſe, as to conſult</l>
                  <l>Of their diſhonour.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Hub.</speaker>
                  <l>Nor ſo farre (I hope)</l>
                  <l>Miſtaken to marry any of 'em.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Rey.</speaker>
                  <l>Why <hi>Hubba</hi>? are they not faire and vertuous,</l>
                  <l>Think'ſt thou?</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Hub.</speaker>
                  <l>I doe admire, ſir you ſho'd talke</l>
                  <l>So much of vertue: a thing th'arranteſt Aſſe</l>
                  <l>Will ſcorne, if Money be not joyn'd to it;</l>
                  <l>And then (although he hate it, and the poſſeſſor</l>
                  <l>Of it) he will prayſe 't.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Rey.</speaker>
                  <l>Thou 'rt now in thy old humors.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Hub.</speaker>
                  <l>Beſides, you thinke <hi>Landgartha</hi> faire: but I ſay,</l>
                  <l>Th' Emperors daughter's worth a thouſand of her.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Rey.</speaker>
                  <l>I 'de loathly beat thee <hi>Hubba</hi>: yet, I tell thee;</l>
                  <l>Were <hi>Charlemaine</hi> (the Emperors father) now</l>
                  <l>Alive, and in his Pryme of youth and glory,</l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Landgartha</hi> (being his Paralell in vallor;</l>
                  <l>By vertue much more) were a wiſe enough good</l>
                  <l>For him; were ſhe not neere ſo faire as ſhe is.</l>
                  <l>But all, all being joyn'd <hi>Hubba</hi>; I ſuppoſe</l>
                  <l>He wo'd eſteeme her his chiefe eat thy bleſſing.</l>
                  <l>I, I, and more, a Paradiſe on earth.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Hub.</speaker>
                  <l>Were ſhe ten times better: you cannot have her.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <pb facs="tcp:47257:16"/>
                  <speaker>Rey.</speaker>
                  <l>Thou ſhoot'ſt a ſuddaine feare (colder then death)</l>
                  <l>Into me; You were beſt give no bad reaſon,</l>
                  <l>For what you ſay.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Hub.</speaker>
                  <l>She has vow'd Chaſtity,</l>
                  <l>Unto the gods: which bond though you ſho'd be</l>
                  <l>Content to forfeyt, it is ſure ſhe will not.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Rey.</speaker>
                  <l>The ſtrongeſt poyſon could not ſincke me deader,</l>
                  <l>Then thy ſad tongue has.
<stage>Exit.</stage>
                  </l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Hub.</speaker>
                  <l>Flunge away in a rage:</l>
                  <l>Well; I was to blame to tell him, what I was not</l>
                  <l>Sure on: For now I truely doe conceive</l>
                  <l>There is no plaſter but one, that can cure him;</l>
                  <l>And that the faire <hi>Landgartha</hi> muſt apply too;</l>
                  <l>No garden hearbs will doe it, any one</l>
                  <l>That has as much braine as a Wood-cocke, may now</l>
                  <l>Finde that, that knowes what his diſeaſe is. He's worſe</l>
                  <l>Then horne-mad already; I 'll therefore after him,</l>
                  <l>And what betwixt lyes and true tales, I ſhall goe very neere</l>
                  <l>To fetch him to himſelfe, and hope againe.
<stage>Exit.</stage>
                  </l>
                  <stage>Enter Inguar in the middle.</stage>
                  <l>The King ſtretch'd on his Couch, ſtrangely diſtemper'd,</l>
                  <l>And moſt unlike himſelfe (his courage loſt)</l>
                  <l>He pules and whynes moſt pitifully: Good heaven,</l>
                  <l>What ſtrange diſeaſe ſho'd render ſo devicted</l>
                  <l>Such a man? So valiant? So each way noble?</l>
                  <l>We ſee no outward cauſe, that ſho'd diſtract him;</l>
                  <l>Sho'd it be love?
<stage>Enter Vald. to Inguar.</stage>
                  </l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Vald.</speaker>
                  <l>Lord <hi>Inguar,</hi> I have newes</l>
                  <l>For you.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Ing.</speaker>
                  <l>I long to heare'em: For your count'nance</l>
                  <l>(Showing alacrity) ſpeaks comfort to the King.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Vald.</speaker>
                  <l>Did you never heare of a little blind</l>
                  <l>Boy, that wounded many a proper man?</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Ing.</speaker>
                  <l>Has <hi>Cupid</hi> ſhot his Highneſſe?</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Vald.</speaker>
                  <l>No mortall man,</l>
                  <l>Nor god ſo deepe, 't will be proclaym'd in open</l>
                  <l>
                     <pb facs="tcp:47257:17"/>Market ſhortly.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Inguar.</speaker>
                  <l>Who ſhould the object be?</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Vald.</speaker>
                  <l>Who but <hi>Volſca de gente Camilla?</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>Th'faireſt and beſt of women, brave, <hi>Landgartha</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Hubba</hi> is ſent (on paine of his beſt joynt)</l>
                  <l>To fetch her hither: from whence ere ſhe part,</l>
                  <l>Her duty and th'Kings gracious affection</l>
                  <l>Conſider'd, ſhe may be glad to yeeld to his</l>
                  <l>Commands; as I hope her ſiſter will, to my</l>
                  <l>Intreaties to ſerve her.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Inguar.</speaker>
                  <l>I beleeve, you 'ill finde</l>
                  <l>Your ſelfe miſtaken in thoſse vertuous Ladies.</l>
                  <stage>Enter the foure Ladies in womans apparell with Swords on, and Hubba.</stage>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Land.</speaker>
                  <l>The gods defend ſo good, and mercifull</l>
                  <l>A Prince; I know it's but a cold that troubles</l>
                  <l>His grace.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Hub.</speaker>
                  <l>Not ſo (Madame) I can aſſure you;</l>
                  <l>His diſeaſe proceeds rather of heate. He burnes</l>
                  <l>Extreamely; and its thought by ſome, that his</l>
                  <l>Phyſitians cannot cure him.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Land.</speaker>
                  <l>I hope</l>
                  <l>They are deceiv'd that thinke ſo.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Vald.</speaker>
                  <l>Welcome to Court,</l>
                  <l>Faire Ladies, Which, till now (that you lighten it</l>
                  <l>With the divine ſplendor of your beauties)</l>
                  <l>Was darker than a dungeon: and but a Hell</l>
                  <l>Compar'd unto the Paradiſe of the Campe,</l>
                  <l>Where in the fruition of your pleaſing'ſt</l>
                  <l>Converſations, being rapt beyond our ſelves</l>
                  <l>With hope of future favours, we in you</l>
                  <l>Plac'd the whole ſumme of our felicities.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Land.</speaker>
                  <l>You are merrily diſpos' itd ſeemes, ſir,</l>
                  <l>Which (to be plaine) becomes you but moſt foulely,</l>
                  <l>The King being ſicke, when all (and chiefly you)</l>
                  <l>Sho'd (and not for ceremony onely) put</l>
                  <l>
                     <pb facs="tcp:47257:17"/>A darke face of ſorrow on; and contayne</l>
                  <l>Their ſlippery tongues, from talking over-idlely;</l>
                  <l>Some may conceive your mirth proceeds, from being</l>
                  <l>Next heire to him in bloud.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Vald.</speaker>
                  <l>It rather ſprings</l>
                  <l>(Sweet Lady) from your comming now to cure him</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Land.</speaker>
                  <l>Which, with a joyfull heart, I ſho'd performe</l>
                  <l>If I knew how: Pray you therefore, kind ſir,</l>
                  <l>Be ſomewhat cleerer in what you conceive.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Vald.</speaker>
                  <l>'ts quickly learnt; nature will teach you Madame,</l>
                  <l>His grace will ſhew you too; you will not prove
<stage>Ieeringly.</stage>
                  </l>
                  <l>Perverſe.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Land.</speaker>
                  <l>Are you ſo blinde a Goate, to forget
<stage>Gives him a box, on which all draw, and Scania ſteps in.</stage>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Frollo</hi> ſo ſoone? to open your eyes take that.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Scan.</speaker>
                  <l>Pray ſiſter hold. What doe you meane to quarell</l>
                  <l>On a ſurmiſe? I know the Lord <hi>Valdemars</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>Intents are noble, and much more the Kings.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Elſin.</speaker>
                  <l>Y' are to blame, Neece, to be ſo ſuddaine in ſuch</l>
                  <l>A fond conceit.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Land.</speaker>
                  <l>Doe we come to be abus'd?</l>
                  <l>I'll backe agen. For your part ſir, you ſhall
<stage>Exit, and the other three follow her.</stage>
                  </l>
                  <l>Not fayle to meete me, when and where you liſt.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Hub.</speaker>
                  <l>His grace will now run mad indeed.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Vald.</speaker>
                  <l>Lord <hi>Inguar,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>As you love me, follow that ſevere Lady;</l>
                  <l>And reduce her (if ever you did ought for</l>
                  <l>A friend) to mildneſſe, and this way backe; or I</l>
                  <l>Am loſt for ever to the King and people:
<stage>Exit Inguar</stage>
                  </l>
                  <l>Captaine, goe thou too once more, for my ſake.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Hub.</speaker>
                  <l>And as you meane to doe, forſweare my ſelfe</l>
                  <l>That you meant no hurt. I have already told her</l>
                  <l>A hundred lyes at leaſt; and am now o' th' faith,</l>
                  <l>That double the number will ſcarce ſerve to quiet her;</l>
                  <l>It's ſuch another untoward piece of fleſh
<stage>Exit Hub.</stage>
                  </l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Vald.</speaker>
                  <l>She is an excellent Miſtris, and has taught
<stage>Ieeringly.</stage>
                  </l>
                  <l>Me ſuch a Leſſon, I have cauſe to thanke her:</l>
                  <l>For ſhe has given me patience, and wiſedome;</l>
                  <l>Honeſty too I thinke. The flat truth is</l>
                  <l>
                     <pb facs="tcp:47257:18"/>She has wrought ſtrangely with me, very ſtrangely,</l>
                  <l>The raviſhing notes of a <hi>Cycilian Cyren,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>Could not ſo have taken my Eare (and from thence</l>
                  <l>My heart) with a moſt alluring kinde of</l>
                  <l>Delight, as the ſmart-touch of her white hand has:</l>
                  <l>It ſtrucke into me ſuch a love,</l>
                  <l>To her ſiſter I meane, that came ſo kindly</l>
                  <l>Betwixt us, as I doe now account my ſelfe,</l>
                  <l>A gainer by the blow; in hope to gaine</l>
                  <l>What I now love ſo much, and nobly too.</l>
                  <l>Well, they will come backe this way againe, I know;</l>
                  <l>And I muſt ſing a very dolefull ditty,</l>
                  <l>A Palinode; or pray, where they may ſee me,</l>
                  <l>Being a thing I 've onely done but twice</l>
                  <l>Theſe ſeven yeares: once, that I went to ſea:</l>
                  <l>Secondly and laſtly, before the laſt battle.
<stage>Exit.</stage>
                  </l>
               </sp>
               <stage>Reyner is diſcover'd on a Couch, and a gentleman with him.</stage>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Rey.</speaker>
                  <l>Are th' Ladies come yet to Court?</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Gent.</speaker>
                  <l>They are ſir,</l>
                  <l>And will ſoone be here.
<stage>Enter Inguar &amp; Hubb.</stage>
                  </l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Rey.</speaker>
                  <l>Whoſe that?</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Gent.</speaker>
                  <l>My Lord <hi>Inguar.</hi>
                  </l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Rey.</speaker>
                  <l>Where have you left the Ladies?</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Ing.</speaker>
                  <l>Comming after (Sir,)</l>
                  <l>Sad and much troubl'd for your want of health.
<stage>
                        <hi>Enter the</hi> 4. <hi>Ladies.</hi>
                     </stage>
                  </l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Scan.</speaker>
                  <l>You'll be extreamely hated, if you uſe</l>
                  <l>So much exception, on ſo little cauſe.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Land.</speaker>
                  <l>If he accoſt me any more, with his</l>
                  <l>Baſe jeering countenance, and whoriſh language;</l>
                  <l>My ſword ſhall (for ſuch kindneſſe) kiſſe his middriſſe.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Fat.</speaker>
                  <l>Pray pacifie your minde, you need not ſtand</l>
                  <l>At ſo much diſtance.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Rey.</speaker>
                  <l>Are not they come yet?</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Hub.</speaker>
                  <l>They now are here, by much adoe.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Rey.</speaker>
                  <l>Good <hi>Inguar,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <pb facs="tcp:47257:18"/>Intreat 'em to approach.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Inguar.</speaker>
                  <l>Madame, the King</l>
                  <l>Deſires you wo'd be pleas'd to draw neerer.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Rey.</speaker>
                  <l>You honour me, ſweet Ladies, in this viſit:</l>
                  <l>Which, beyond expreſſion adds comfort</l>
                  <l>Vnto a wretched ſickely man. Chayres there,</l>
                  <l>Pray you ſit downe; y' are all exceeding welcome.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Land.</speaker>
                  <l>Our duty charg'd us (ſir,) to obey your ſummons:</l>
                  <l>Yet, our affection to your grac's welfare,</l>
                  <l>And to that depends of it (the generall good</l>
                  <l>Of the republicke) were the chiefe motives</l>
                  <l>To our journey.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Scan.</speaker>
                  <l>And being able (ſir,) to ſtead you</l>
                  <l>In loving wiſhes onely, we muſt expect</l>
                  <l>(With griefe to ſee his weakneſſe, whoſe good health</l>
                  <l>We moſt deſire) your highneſſe royall pleaſure.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Rey.</speaker>
                  <l>Thankes worthy Ladies. We muſt alſo pay</l>
                  <l>You in good wiſhes; being otherwiſe</l>
                  <l>Too indigent to cancell what we are</l>
                  <l>Ingag'd to you for many wayes.</l>
                  <l>We have beene ſtill oppreſt ſince your departure</l>
                  <l>From us (whoſe vertuous preſence, was all</l>
                  <l>The comfort we had) with a heavy ſadneſſe,</l>
                  <l>Nouriſh'd by griefe; nor doe we ever hope</l>
                  <l>To ſee the Sunne againe, but at a window.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Land.</speaker>
                  <l>The gods defend you (ſir,) from giving way</l>
                  <l>To ſuch deſpayre.
<stage>Enter Vald.</stage>
                  </l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Vald.</speaker>
                  <l>I follow after (like</l>
                  <l>A Theefe) aloofe, to ſee what good ſucceſſe</l>
                  <l>The King has in his love ſuite; and to venter</l>
                  <l>For my particular, as he makes his voyage.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Scan.</speaker>
                  <l>Your Majeſtie muſt never entertayne</l>
                  <l>Darke melancholy thoughts, but quite caſhire 'em.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Vald.</speaker>
                  <l>Her voyce founds ſweeter, then the celeſtiall ſpheres,</l>
                  <l>In their harmonious motion. I am more</l>
                  <l>Then raviſh'd when I heare it; and thinke I ſhall</l>
                  <l>Fall ſicke too, or runne franticke, ere 't belong.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Fat.</speaker>
                  <l>I heard no meane Phyſitian often ſay, Sir,</l>
                  <l>
                     <pb facs="tcp:47257:19"/>That Muſicke and mirth were good for ſickely men.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Rey.</speaker>
                  <l>Bid the Boy ſing the Song we made of Love.</l>
               </sp>
               <lg type="song">
                  <head>Song.</head>
                  <l>Love's farre more pow'rfull than a King,</l>
                  <l>And wiſer then moſt Stateſmen are:</l>
                  <l>For it commands him, and doth ſpring</l>
                  <l>In them strange thoughts; in both much care</l>
                  <l>(Beſide th'affaires o' th' Common-wealth)</l>
                  <l>To crouch and to obey. Nay more;</l>
                  <l>It makes 'em looſe all joy and health,</l>
                  <l>And not be the men they were before;</l>
                  <l>Vntill wiſe love, all pow'rfull love,</l>
                  <l>The gracious Phyſitian prove.</l>
               </lg>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Land.</speaker>
                  <l>This is a very loving ſong,</l>
                  <l>Your grace made: but the contents of it, not</l>
                  <l>To be apply'd to you ſir, that may command</l>
                  <l>(If pow'r and perſon can compell) the beſt</l>
                  <l>And faireſt Lady i' th'world to be yours,</l>
                  <l>In a noble way; and otherwiſe your vertue forbids it.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Rey.</speaker>
                  <l>It does indeed forbid us what is vicious.</l>
                  <l>And ſeeing we doe not hope for life, we muſt</l>
                  <l>Crave your kinde pardon now, to heare us tell</l>
                  <l>Th'occaſion of our ſickneſſe, briefly thus:</l>
                  <l>You are the onely cauſe on't.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Land.</speaker>
                  <l>How? I my liege?</l>
                  <l>My knowledge ſayes not ſo.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Rey.</speaker>
                  <l>Your beautie, vallor,</l>
                  <l>And all the perfections (parted to others,</l>
                  <l>But) in you conjoyn'd, proteſt it: and I</l>
                  <l>For one can ſweare it. But, being repell'd</l>
                  <l>By a ſeverely-awing rigor from your brow</l>
                  <l>(Yet ſweet withall, though killing) and being told</l>
                  <l>Of a ſad purpoſe y' have, never to marry;</l>
                  <l>We now are fall'n thus low, beneath the Center</l>
                  <l>Of deepe deſpaire and ſorrow: and deſire,</l>
                  <l>You will ſay ſomething, eyther to haſten our death,</l>
                  <l>
                     <pb facs="tcp:47257:19"/>Or to recall it by a loving ſentence.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Land.</speaker>
                  <l>I muſt take ſometime then to deliberate</l>
                  <l>Aſide.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Rey.</speaker>
                  <l>Being yours, in that you may command us.
<stage>She goes aſide &amp; the Ladies with her.</stage>
                  </l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Land.</speaker>
                  <l>We expected no ſuch entertaynment.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Elſin.</speaker>
                  <l>My minde foretold me ſtill of ſome diſaſter.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Scan.</speaker>
                  <l>Notwithſtanding your reſolution,</l>
                  <l>Not to marry: you have not vow'd againſt</l>
                  <l>Obedience to a man, in that friendly</l>
                  <l>Yoake of Wedlocke. The Kings ſound affection</l>
                  <l>Is not then to be rejected, if you ever</l>
                  <l>Take any.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Land.</speaker>
                  <l>If I doe, he ſhall be the man.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Fatyma.</speaker>
                  <l>You muſt not ſtudy now long for ſome anſwer.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Elſin.</speaker>
                  <l>He's deſperatly ill: and if you ſho'd</l>
                  <l>Give him a flat deniall, we might be</l>
                  <l>All ſeazed on heere at Court, and ſome villanie</l>
                  <l>Committed on us; being to defend our ſelves,</l>
                  <l>Too few by many.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Scan.</speaker>
                  <l>They ſhall take our lives,</l>
                  <l>Ere we'll endure to be defil'd.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Fatyma.</speaker>
                  <l>And with</l>
                  <l>The loſſe of ſome of theirs.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Rey.</speaker>
                  <l>Have you conſider'd</l>
                  <l>Yet, of the doome y' are to pronounce?</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Elſinora.</speaker>
                  <l>All ſtand</l>
                  <l>Warily on their guard.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Land.</speaker>
                  <l>Your poore ſubjects (ſir)</l>
                  <l>Muſt rather expect (in duty) your commands.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Rey.</speaker>
                  <l>Nay ſweet Lady. Doe not increaſe my torment,</l>
                  <l>By adding affliction to miſery,</l>
                  <l>With a complement: but ſomething ſay, that</l>
                  <l>May appertaine to th' matter, to rid me</l>
                  <l>Quickely of my paine.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Land.</speaker>
                  <l>It's ſure; I have not</l>
                  <l>(Although I ever meant it) bound my ſelfe,</l>
                  <l>Unto a ſingle life.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Rey.</speaker>
                  <l>Then deareſt Lady,</l>
                  <l>
                     <pb facs="tcp:47257:20"/>Conſider who I am; and what I now am,</l>
                  <l>Lodg'd thus: for though I clayme you not as by deſert,</l>
                  <l>Or dutie: Yet, being your Prince, you owe me</l>
                  <l>Some regard; and all, I e'r muſt glory in,</l>
                  <l>Shall be to make you Queene of what is ours.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Land.</speaker>
                  <l>May it pleaſe you, Sir.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Rey.</speaker>
                  <l>Pray you ſit and ſpeake;</l>
                  <l>Or I muſt riſe, if weakeneſſe will permit.
<stage>She ſits, and the reſt ſtand.</stage>
                  </l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Land.</speaker>
                  <l>Had I beene ambitious, when you were not</l>
                  <l>Crown'd King of <hi>Norway</hi>: I could then perchance</l>
                  <l>Have written Queene, unto your prejudice.</l>
                  <l>But, for that <hi>Frollo</hi> once intended foulely,</l>
                  <l>I (that could not affect vice) did refuſe</l>
                  <l>What he with earneſtneſſe, and many Oathes</l>
                  <l>Sought to confirme; and was his bane at laſt,</l>
                  <l>Though I beleev'd that what he ſaid, he meant.</l>
                  <l>Now therefore (Sir,) your affection (grounded</l>
                  <l>In way of honour, without taint of baſeneſſe;</l>
                  <l>With ſuch exterior ſignes too, of deepe love</l>
                  <l>To me, unworthy of ſo great a Prince:)</l>
                  <l>I cannot (nor will my heart permit it) but</l>
                  <l>In way of gratefulneſſe, reciprocally</l>
                  <l>Requite with love againe, as dutie binds;</l>
                  <l>Nay, more then ſo. But yet, gracious Sir,</l>
                  <l>I (that am meane and poore to be your Conſort;</l>
                  <l>And that things of this kinde are oft repented)</l>
                  <l>Doe now beſeech you, to decline a while</l>
                  <l>The vehemencie of your fleete deſires;</l>
                  <l>And take full time to thinke on what you doe:</l>
                  <l>Were 't but to take a neerer view of me,</l>
                  <l>And that in all points. For know ſir, the honour</l>
                  <l>You now affoord me, compar'd to th'infamie</l>
                  <l>That would redound to both of us, and to others</l>
                  <l>(By whom you are to be advis'd) if ought</l>
                  <l>Sho'd chance amiſſe, when things were conſumate,</l>
                  <l>Is nothing: would but heighten your diſgrace.</l>
                  <l>Your wiſe demurre too, I ſhall take as full payment</l>
                  <l>For all my ſervices; and reſt devoted</l>
                  <l>
                     <pb facs="tcp:47257:20"/>More deepely yours: and evermore continue</l>
                  <l>Your loyall ſubject onely, ſir.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Rey.</speaker>
                  <l>I was ſure</l>
                  <l>(Nobleſt and beſt of Ladies:) That your words</l>
                  <l>(Being ſuch as now they are) could not but worke</l>
                  <l>A cure upon me. See, I can ſtand up:</l>
                  <l>Nay, goe; I 'll throw my Cap off too. Some of you</l>
                  <l>Give me a Hat; I will walke with you forth</l>
                  <l>Into the Gallery, and tell you there,</l>
                  <l>I have conſider'd ſo much what you are,</l>
                  <l>Though not to your full value this being</l>
                  <l>Impoſſible: that if you thinke me not</l>
                  <l>Unworthy (as indeed I am for you)</l>
                  <l>We ſhall ſoone be Man and Wife. To morrow</l>
                  <l>I 'll wayte on you further, into the Garden.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Hub.</speaker>
                  <l>And there (in one of the little bawdy houſes)
<stage>Aſide.</stage>
                  </l>
                  <l>Seale the Covenant, if it be receiv'd,</l>
                  <l>Though he were ſure to die in an houre after.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Elſin.</speaker>
                  <l>I ſee ſhe does affect him in good earneſt.
<stage>Aſide.</stage>
                  </l>
                  <l>But wiſedome bids be ſilent; This poore kingdome</l>
                  <l>Being already torne too much, by tyrannie and troubles.</l>
                  <l>Things paſt our helpe, with patience muſt be borne,</l>
                  <l>Untill a fit time.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Rey.</speaker>
                  <l>Lady <hi>Elſinora,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>Me thinkes you doe not ſigne our loving motion,</l>
                  <l>With a friendly countenance.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Elſin.</speaker>
                  <l>I hope, great Sir,</l>
                  <l>You will be pleas<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>d to entertayne farre better thoughts</l>
                  <l>Of your humbleſt hand-mayd.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Rey.</speaker>
                  <l>I hope we ſhall.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Land.</speaker>
                  <l>In licenſing our departure, for ſome ſmall time</l>
                  <l>(Dayes five or ſixe, and for a private Cauſe:)</l>
                  <l>You will for ever bind us (ſir) to your commands;</l>
                  <l>And to returne with all convenient ſpeed,</l>
                  <l>To obey your Highneſſe pleaſure in all points.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Rey.</speaker>
                  <l>That ask'd agen, would throw me on my Couch;</l>
                  <l>Never to riſe.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Vald.</speaker>
                  <l>Madame, I ſho'd make bold</l>
                  <l>
                     <pb facs="tcp:47257:21"/>To ſtop your journey, though the King were pleas'd</l>
                  <l>To grant his licence: for you (I muſt ſay</l>
                  <l>Somewhat roughly) ſaluted my left eare</l>
                  <l>With your right hand, as theſe can witneſſe for me.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Land.</speaker>
                  <l>For which, you are reſolv'd to challenge me:</l>
                  <l>But not to be your wife; I gave you no</l>
                  <l>Such promiſe.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Vald.</speaker>
                  <l>I muſt have ſatisfaction.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Land.</speaker>
                  <l>You may declare what that is, when you liſt.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Vald.</speaker>
                  <l>Nay, you ſhall know it now; and thus it ſounds:</l>
                  <l>That you perſwade this Lady, to become
<stage>Takes Scan. by the hand.</stage>
                  </l>
                  <l>My ſecond. For, love has ſtrucke me too, ſo ſore</l>
                  <l>A cuffe (caus'd by her beautie, and what elſe</l>
                  <l>Is good in her, in my opinion</l>
                  <l>Superlatively:) that I ſhall ne'r be rid</l>
                  <l>O' th' paine on't; unleſſe you that are like to be</l>
                  <l>My Coſſen, advance me higher, to the honour</l>
                  <l>To be your brother. We ſhall then be kind friends.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Land.</speaker>
                  <l>She is not my warde; and may take whom ſhe fancies;</l>
                  <l>I may my ſelfe repent, to be perſwaded.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Rey.</speaker>
                  <l>Speake Ladie, doe you like the man? He is</l>
                  <l>As good a Gentleman as We are: Say,</l>
                  <l>Will you have him?</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Scan.</speaker>
                  <l>You make me bluſh (ſir,) to aske</l>
                  <l>Me ſuch a queſtion.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Vald.</speaker>
                  <l>Nay then, it's granted.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Scan.</speaker>
                  <l>I will not grant at firſt; nor ſhall you ſay</l>
                  <l>Hereafter I deceiv'd you.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Fat.</speaker>
                  <l>You deceive</l>
                  <l>Your ſelfe. Well Madame, I perceive we two
<stage>To Elſin.</stage>
                  </l>
                  <l>Muſt mateleſſe home to prove the Veſtals.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Ing.</speaker>
                  <l>Not, ſweet Lady, if you'll daigne to grace me, with</l>
                  <l>The title husband.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Fat.</speaker>
                  <l>For your good will, ſir,</l>
                  <l>I thanke you: but will heare of no more coupling.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Ing.</speaker>
                  <l>I yet muſt love you ſtill.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Rey.</speaker>
                  <l>Then let's from hence,</l>
                  <l>To entertayne heavens happy influence.
<stage>Exeunt.</stage>
                  </l>
               </sp>
            </div>
            <div n="3" type="act">
               <pb facs="tcp:47257:21"/>
               <head>The third Act.</head>
               <stage>Enter Fredericke and a Servant at the dore.</stage>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Fred.</speaker>
                  <l>Let 'em not preſſe ſo faſt in, to behold</l>
                  <l>A ſemi-maske; for now 't can be no more,</l>
                  <l>For want of fitting Actors here at Court;</l>
                  <l>The Warre and want of Money, is the cauſe on't.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Serv.</speaker>
                  <l>Stand further off, my maſters, or I ſhall—</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Fred.</speaker>
                  <l>Let fly amongſt 'em.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Vald.</speaker>
                  <l>Pray you my Lord, have a care
<stage>Enter Vald. and Lady.</stage>
                  </l>
                  <l>(For my ſake) of this Lady; a kinſ-woman</l>
                  <l>Of my wives.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Fred.</speaker>
                  <l>(I know you are Vxorious.)</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Land.</speaker>
                  <l>He ſhall not need: for I will have a care</l>
                  <l>Of my ſelfe.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Fred.</speaker>
                  <l>I ſho'd gladly ſerve your Highneſſe:</l>
                  <l>But can hardly yet from hence.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Vald.</speaker>
                  <l>Come Couſin,</l>
                  <l>I will be your Gentleman uſher my ſelfe.
<stage>Exeunt ambo.</stage>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Cowſell</hi> within, make roome I ſay there, for me and my brother.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Fred.</speaker>
                  <l>What kinde Coſſens are thoſe?</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Serv.</speaker>
                  <l>A payre of Coxcombes,</l>
                  <l>So individuall by the littleneſſe</l>
                  <l>Of their underſtandings, they cannot be parted.
<stage>Enter Cow. &amp; Rad.</stage>
                  </l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Cow.</speaker>
                  <l>Come away brother <hi>Radgar,</hi> we'd need make haſte,</l>
                  <l>To take our places.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Rad.</speaker>
                  <l>I ſhall be proud brother,</l>
                  <l>To be ſeated after you.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Cow.</speaker>
                  <l>And I fortunate</l>
                  <l>To ſit next before you.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Rad.</speaker>
                  <l>It ſhall be my ambition brother, to</l>
                  <l>Be ſtill (as now) your moſt humble ſervant,</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <pb facs="tcp:47257:22"/>
                  <speaker>Cow.</speaker>
                  <l>It muſt be all my ſtudy then, brother; To</l>
                  <l>Command things onely pleaſing: for marke you</l>
                  <l>Deere brother. I muſt ſtrive chiefly to precede,</l>
                  <l>But — in my affection.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Fred.</speaker>
                  <l>A pretty Antimaſque:</l>
                  <l>I will ſit downe, and heare what it concludes.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Rad.</speaker>
                  <l>But hearke you now, brother. Shall we have any</l>
                  <l>Drinke, Banquets, or ſo —</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Cow.</speaker>
                  <l>Not a drop betwixt meales, brother,</l>
                  <l>That's but a ſimple Countrey faſhion.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Fred.</speaker>
                  <l>Are they already fall'n from complement?</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Rad.</speaker>
                  <l>Yet, me thinkes brother, 't were n't amiſſe to lay</l>
                  <l>The pots hard by; and let him drinke that wo'd.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Cow.</speaker>
                  <l>I ſho'd a part keepe with you, in that Catch</l>
                  <l>brother, but now (with griefe enough) I ſay 't</l>
                  <l>(Wo'd I co'd not ſay 't:) I cannot now (being puff'd</l>
                  <l>Vp here for want of ayre) drinke nere as much,</l>
                  <l>As when I liv'd abroad i' th' Countrie; nor eate</l>
                  <l>The quarter quantitie.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Rad.</speaker>
                  <l>That muſt be beleev'd</l>
                  <l>Generally, as a Maxime infallible:</l>
                  <l>For to day brother, the ſtinke of your perfum'd</l>
                  <l>And ſtuffing meates, tooke my ſtomacke quite away</l>
                  <l>From me. Yet, we drunke pretty well you know.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Cow.</speaker>
                  <l>It's certaine (brother,) thoſe that cannot eate,</l>
                  <l>Muſt drinke, and I can drinke indifferent well ſtill</l>
                  <l>But, time there was I could 'a' payde it ſoundly.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Rad.</speaker>
                  <l>As, how much? Pray ſweet brother.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Cow.</speaker>
                  <l>It is ſcarce</l>
                  <l>Credible, I now ſhall tell you: at one ſhort</l>
                  <l>Sitting, I'd a drunke you of Wine ſixe Flaggons,</l>
                  <l>And two dozen of Beere at leaſt, all at eight draughts;</l>
                  <l>And never 'a' ſeene the colour of my face,</l>
                  <l>In a Chamber pot; or ſought eaſe, by viſiting</l>
                  <l>My kind friend <hi>Aiax.</hi>
                  </l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Rad.</speaker>
                  <l>That's more by a little,</l>
                  <l>Then I ever could vent the right way. But yet,</l>
                  <l>I dare ſpeake it brother, we are very neere</l>
                  <l>
                     <pb facs="tcp:47257:22"/>As good drinkers, as you be here i' th' Citie:</l>
                  <l>For you ſee, when we come to Towne, we doe</l>
                  <l>Nothing but runne from Taverne, to Taverne;</l>
                  <l>Oft to blind Ale-houſes, to viſit the fine</l>
                  <l>Wenches, of purpoſe there plac'd, to draw cuſtome;</l>
                  <l>Now and then to ſee a Play, when we want</l>
                  <l>Other exerciſe; and once a weeke (upon</l>
                  <l>A holy day, when all doores are ſhut up)</l>
                  <l>To a godly exhortation, and ſleepe out</l>
                  <l>(At leaſt) three parts on't.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Cow.</speaker>
                  <l>Eſpecially if you</l>
                  <l>Take your liquor before hand.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Rad.</speaker>
                  <l>Right brother, but</l>
                  <l>To morrow we will both from hence, to th' Countrey.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Cow.</speaker>
                  <l>Wo'd this night were over once.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Rad.</speaker>
                  <l>We've excellent Mayds with us,</l>
                  <l>And while my Ladies dance and feaſt it here,</l>
                  <l>Both night and day: We both will keepe Court there;</l>
                  <l>Throw out the houſe at th' windowes, and fetch in</l>
                  <l>All our Towne-fidlers, with all the young fellowes</l>
                  <l>In fifteene villages about us; is 't not good?</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Fred.</speaker>
                  <l>O rare!</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Fred.</speaker>
                  <l>I' th' meane time Sir, let me perſwade you</l>
                  <l>To conduct your brother to a place: For I</l>
                  <l>Am weary of your company. <hi>Cow,</hi> 'thanke your Lordſhip.
<stage>Exeunt ambo.</stage>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Hubba</hi> within, give way there.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Fred.</speaker>
                  <l>What luſty Gentleman's that?</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Serv.</speaker>
                  <l>Mad Captaine <hi>Hubba,</hi> and as luſty a</l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Virago</hi> with him.</l>
               </sp>
               <stage>Enter Hubba and Marfiſa in an Iriſh Gowne tuck'd up to mid-legge, with a broad basket-hilt Sword on, hanging in a great Belt, Broags on her feet, her hayre diſhevell'd, and a payre of long neck'd big-rowll'd Spurs on her heels.</stage>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Hub.</speaker>
                  <l>Come my brave <hi>Marfiſa,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>You are but juſt now come to Towne you ſay?</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <pb facs="tcp:47257:23"/>
                  <speaker>Mar.</speaker>
                  <l>That you may well perceive ſir, by my ſpurs.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Fr.</speaker>
                  <l>Here's handſome Cheeſe and Butter, and a Sword.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Hub.</speaker>
                  <l>They're a payre of excellent ginglers, but pray</l>
                  <l>Tell me: Did you ride ſideling, or like a man?</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Mar.</speaker>
                  <l>Howſoever, there ſhall ne'r a <hi>Dane</hi> ride i' my Saddle.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Hub.</speaker>
                  <l>What? not i' the way of honeſty? as you love me,</l>
                  <l>Say not ſo; I hope you'll be pleas'd to thinke of my ſervice.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Mar.</speaker>
                  <l>I ſho'd rejoyce to be well pleas'd i' th' way</l>
                  <l>Of honeſty: Yet, your faire words ſhall not</l>
                  <l>Deceive me. As firſt try, then take on liking.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Hub.</speaker>
                  <l>But, with your favour I thinke 't were better try:</l>
                  <l>Leaſt you ſho'd chance repent too late hereafter.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Mar.</speaker>
                  <l>You will not put me ſir, to uſe my Sword:
<stage>Puts hand to her ſword.</stage>
                  </l>
                  <l>If you doe, you muſt firſt begin at that.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Fr.</speaker>
                  <l>I thinke ſhe meanes to make him marry her</l>
                  <l>Perforce; I ſhall have my part o' th' Maske here.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Hub.</speaker>
                  <l>Pray Lady, take patience along with you;</l>
                  <l>I am fairely yours.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Fr.</speaker>
                  <l>You had (on my knowledge)</l>
                  <l>But need to ſay ſo, if ſhe be in earneſt.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Mar.</speaker>
                  <l>Then leade me to ſome honeſt place, where I may</l>
                  <l>Unſpurre, untucke my Gowue, waſh, and ſo forth —</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Hub.</speaker>
                  <l>Moſt willingly, my faire <hi>Marfiſa,</hi> thou ſha't</l>
                  <l>Have a looking-glaſſe too; I ever tooke</l>
                  <l>A ſtrange liking to thee, ſince firſt I ſaw</l>
                  <l>Thee fight i' th' battle like a Lyoneſſe.</l>
                  <l>Y' are Coffen-german to th' Lady <hi>Fatyma?</hi>
                  </l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Mar.</speaker>
                  <l>Her ſelfe dare not deny it, ſir.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Hub.</speaker>
                  <l>I doe not
<stage>Goes about her.</stage>
                  </l>
                  <l>Onely marke your ſweet face, but all things elſe</l>
                  <l>About you. Y' have a fine legge. The faſhion</l>
                  <l>Of this Gowne, likes me well too; I thinke you had</l>
                  <l>The patterne on't from us, as we from <hi>Ireland.</hi>
                  </l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Mar.</speaker>
                  <l>That I know not, but am ſure a handſome woman</l>
                  <l>Lookes as well in 't, as in any dreſſe, or habit</l>
                  <l>Whatſoever.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Hub.</speaker>
                  <l>So it ſeemes by thee, my</l>
                  <l>Beautifull Miſtris: For by that name, I muſt</l>
                  <l>
                     <pb facs="tcp:47257:23"/>Stile you henceforth. Come, let your loving ſquire</l>
                  <l>Conduct you. <hi>Mar,</hi> on before, I'll follow.
<stage>Exeunt ambo.</stage>
                  </l>
                  <l>Lowd Muſicke. <stage>Enter Reyner, Landgartha, Valdemar, Scania, Elſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nora, Inguar, and Fatyma. The Ladies attir'd like women onely</stage>
                  </l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Rey.</speaker>
                  <l>My Queene and I, <hi>Valdemar,</hi> are much bound</l>
                  <l>To thy free <hi>Genius,</hi> for this thy ſecond Maske</l>
                  <l>After our nuptials; She more: but moſt</l>
                  <l>Of all, thy owne Lady. For, it's for her ſake</l>
                  <l>Thou ſo affect'st both us.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Scan.</speaker>
                  <l>I could not wiſh</l>
                  <l>To 'a' met a kinder man.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Land.</speaker>
                  <l>His kindneſſe makes</l>
                  <l>You oft aſham'd, you ſay; nor wo'd I have</l>
                  <l>The King ſo over fond of me.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Vald.</speaker>
                  <l>You ſtand</l>
                  <l>Confirm'd, Madame, in the pow'r your merits</l>
                  <l>Hold, to charme his faculties to your obeyſance.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Land.</speaker>
                  <l>You deliver that, ſir, to picke a thanke from</l>
                  <l>My Siſter; at whom you point in that language.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Scan.</speaker>
                  <l>I doe beleeve he does: which yet, muſt be</l>
                  <l>Conceiv'd onely to proceed, from his ill-plac'd</l>
                  <l>Affection; not my deſert to anſwer</l>
                  <l>His; much leſſe your perfections: being</l>
                  <l>But a poore Pigmie, compar'd to the greatneſſe</l>
                  <l>Of the worth in you.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Rey.</speaker>
                  <l>This friendly Complement</l>
                  <l>We will paſſe over: and now <hi>Valdemar,</hi> 
                     <note place="margin">Heere they take their places, but the King and the Queene under a Canopie.</note>
                  </l>
                  <l>To apt our apprehenſions the more</l>
                  <l>To the true underſtanding of your Maske:</l>
                  <l>You may tell us ſomewhat of your ſcope in 't.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Vald.</speaker>
                  <l>That is ſufficiently inform'd i' the thing</l>
                  <l>It ſelfe; though lame it be. The matter (being</l>
                  <l>All propheticall) I found in an old</l>
                  <l>Worme-eaten Booke, in the Lady <hi>Elſinora's</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>Library. And I ſho'd wrong your judgement;</l>
                  <l>
                     <pb facs="tcp:47257:24"/>And my owne labour, though of little value,</l>
                  <l>By ſtaling of it before hand.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Fr.</speaker>
                  <l>It's a fine tale;</l>
                  <l>And cannot but pleaſe, unleſſe it meet ſuch minds,</l>
                  <l>As are not to be pleas'd.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Elſin.</speaker>
                  <l>There is no Fuſtian,</l>
                  <l>Non ſenſe, Winde, or fopperie in't.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Rey.</speaker>
                  <l>It matters not</l>
                  <l>What ſome odd envious foole ſayes; that grieves moſt</l>
                  <l>At th' goodneſſe of what he diſprayſes: and wo'd</l>
                  <l>Be glad 't were worſe. We deſpiſe affected ſtuffe;</l>
                  <l>Or a ſtrayn'd kind of Eloquence; being the ſmoake</l>
                  <l>And fruits or a vaineglorious, and an empty braine,</l>
                  <l>No flattery dwels we know in this. Let it begin.</l>
                  <l>The Maske.
<stage>First enter ſix Satyrs and dance a ſhort nimble an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticke to no Muſicke, or at moſt to a ſingle Violine: at the end of which enter Phoebus with Bow and Arrowes.</stage>
                  </l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Phoeb.</speaker>
                  <l>A way unmanner'd deities, though hope</l>
                  <l>Rayſe you unto this mirth, for <hi>Troy</hi>: Your ſcope</l>
                  <l>In 't (form'd at the counſell of the higher gods)</l>
                  <l>Makes not the iſſue of their Periods,</l>
                  <l>So fortunate as you doe now ſuppoſe</l>
                  <l>(In your inferior knowledges) to diſpoſe</l>
                  <l>For <hi>Hectors</hi> ſafetie: whom <hi>Aracides</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>(Madded for his lov'd <hi>Menetiades</hi>)</l>
                  <l>Flyes to deſtroy. Nor can the <hi>Fates</hi> divert,</l>
                  <l>But that fierce horrid man, will ſoone convert</l>
                  <l>All unto ſad deſtruction; unleſſe</l>
                  <l>We the pryme gods and demi-gods ſuppreſſe</l>
                  <l>His force, not otherwiſe to be reſiſted.</l>
                  <l>Get you away from hence then<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> and in stead</l>
                  <l>Of friskings, in theſe pleaſant vales of <hi>Ide,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>Expoſe your aydes (to th' utmoſt can be try'd)</l>
                  <l>For <hi>Pryam</hi> and his iſſue, ne'r till now</l>
                  <l>In danger of an utter overthrow.</l>
                  <l>
                     <pb facs="tcp:47257:24"/>And my owne labour, though of little value,</l>
                  <l>By ſtaling of it before hand.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Fr.</speaker>
                  <l>It's a fine tale;</l>
                  <l>And cannot but pleaſe, unleſſe it meet ſuch minds,</l>
                  <l>As are not to be pleas'd.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Elſin.</speaker>
                  <l>There is no Fuſtian,</l>
                  <l>Non ſenſe, Winde, or fopperie in't.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Rey.</speaker>
                  <l>It matters not</l>
                  <l>What ſome odd envious foole ſayes; that grieves moſt</l>
                  <l>At th' goodneſſe of what he diſprayſes: and wo'd</l>
                  <l>Be glad 't were worſe. We deſpiſe affected ſt<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ffe;</l>
                  <l>Or aſtrayn'd kind of Eloquence; being the ſmoake</l>
                  <l>And fruits of a vaineglorious, and an empty braine,</l>
                  <l>No flattery dwels we know in this. Let it begin.</l>
               </sp>
               <stage>The Maske. <hi>First enter ſix Satyrs and dance a ſhort nimble an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticke to no Muſicke, or at moſt to a ſingle Violine<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> at the end of which enter Phoebus with Bow and Arrowes.</hi>
               </stage>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Phoeb.</speaker>
                  <l>Away unmanner'd deities though hope</l>
                  <l>Rayſe you unto this mirth, for <hi>Troy</hi>: Your ſcope</l>
                  <l>In 't (form'd at the counſell of the higher gods)</l>
                  <l>Makes not the iſſue of their Periods,</l>
                  <l>So fortunate as you doe now ſuppoſe</l>
                  <l>(In your inferior knowledges) to diſpoſe</l>
                  <l>For <hi>Hectors</hi> ſafetie: whom <hi>Aracides</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>(Madded for his lov'd <hi>Menetiades</hi>)</l>
                  <l>Flyes to deſtroy. Nor can the <hi>Fates</hi> divert,</l>
                  <l>But that fierce horrid man, will ſoone convert</l>
                  <l>All unto ſad deſtruction; unleſſe</l>
                  <l>We the pryme gods and demi-gods ſuppreſſe</l>
                  <l>His force, not otherwiſe to be reſiſted.</l>
                  <l>Get you away from hence then. and inſtead</l>
                  <l>Of friskings, in theſe pleaſant vales of <hi>Ide,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>Expoſe your aydes (to th' utmoſt can be try'd)</l>
                  <l>For <hi>Pryam</hi> and his iſſue, ne'r till now</l>
                  <l>In danger of an utter overthrow.</l>
               </sp>
               <pb facs="tcp:47257:25"/>
               <lg type="song">
                  <head>Song.</head>
                  <l>Though <hi>Hector</hi> now be dead, his name</l>
                  <l>And memory ſhall laſt, while fame</l>
                  <l>Sounds her low'd Trumpet, lov'd, admir'd;</l>
                  <l>By his example ſhall be fir'd</l>
                  <l>To acts heroicke, future ages:</l>
                  <l>And Prophets (ſacred in their rages)</l>
                  <l>Shall by his vertues be inſtall'd;</l>
                  <l>And he by all a worthy call'd.</l>
               </lg>
               <stage>Hectors <hi>body is taken away about the middle of the Song: after the end of it, Enter Phoebus and Pryam.</hi>
               </stage>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Phoeb.</speaker>
                  <l>Much honour'd and deere old man, did'ſt not heare,</l>
                  <l>How the <hi>Jdalian</hi> deities forbeare</l>
                  <l>Not (ſacred loving <hi>Nymphs,</hi> and griev'd like thee)</l>
                  <l>To chant a mirthfull pleaſing melody?</l>
                  <l>Glad for the future glory of thy ſonne,</l>
                  <l>Reaſon ſho'd governe: and a faire fame wonne,</l>
                  <l>Is of mans humane life the chiefeſt part,</l>
                  <l>Chiefeſt in <hi>Hector,</hi> and ſhall not depart</l>
                  <l>From thy for-ever-moſt-fam'd houſe: For, know</l>
                  <l>Th' gods on thy line (of <hi>Dardunus</hi>) will beſtow</l>
                  <l>The largeſt Empyres; which to thee I'll now</l>
                  <l>Show for thy comfort: that thou ſho'dſt not bow</l>
                  <l>(Too much dejected in thy minde) to what</l>
                  <l>They in their Counſels doe predeſtinat.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Pry.</speaker>
                  <l>Heavens brighteſt eye, I 'll doe what lyes in me,</l>
                  <l>To obey thy will, and my ſowre deſtinie.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Phoeb.</speaker>
                  <l>My tale in two parts, I doe thus impart:</l>
                  <l>A Prince from <hi>Troy</hi> hereafter ſhall depart,</l>
                  <l>When <hi>Troy</hi> takes end (as all dominion.</l>
                  <l>Of mortals muſt:) whoſe chance will fetch him on</l>
                  <l>The <hi>Lybian</hi> ſhores, and upon <hi>Latium</hi> next.</l>
                  <l>Before which time and after, though oft vex'd</l>
                  <l>By the high-minded <hi>Juno,</hi> for her hates</l>
                  <l>Conceiv'd againſt the <hi>Troians:</hi> Yet, the <hi>Fates</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>Have deſtin'd him that throne of <hi>Latium,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <pb facs="tcp:47257:25"/>Marrying the daughter of its King. From him</l>
                  <l>(The Royall ſeate firſt chang'd to <hi>Alba</hi>) ſhall</l>
                  <l>Deſcend two Princes, twins; for which, a fall</l>
                  <l>Their mother takes from <hi>Mars,</hi> a votreſſe ſhe,</l>
                  <l>Compell'd unto that ſtate. Impietie</l>
                  <l>In an ambitious kinſman, to be drown'd</l>
                  <l>Sends both the Infants: who (ſav'd by chance) are found</l>
                  <l>Of a ſhe-woolfe, and nouriſh'd with her Teats;</l>
                  <l>Till by a ſheepheard found, and by brave feats</l>
                  <l>Made know'n to be themſelves, they build a Towne</l>
                  <l>Which ſhall be call'd <hi>Rome</hi>; and ſhall weare the Crowne</l>
                  <l>Of the worlds Monarchy, hundreds of yeares.</l>
                  <l>This is the firſt part of my tale.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Pry.</speaker>
                  <l>My feares</l>
                  <l>And ſorrow (which till now I did ſuppoſe</l>
                  <l>Could not be done) th' haſt heal'd. Diſcloſe</l>
                  <l>The other part (deare god) that's left untould.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Phoeb.</speaker>
                  <l>Which (in no obſcure termes) I doe unfould:</l>
                  <l>A Prince call'd <hi>Brutus</hi> (of the <hi>Troian</hi> race)</l>
                  <l>Third to the firſt ſpoke of, being in the chace</l>
                  <l>Of wild beaſts, by unlucky fate he kils</l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Sylvius</hi> his Father, with the ſhaft he drils</l>
                  <l>At other game: Which fact, ſo much doth bend</l>
                  <l>The <hi>Latines</hi> againſt <hi>Brutus,</hi> him they ſend</l>
                  <l>To ſad exile. Who (after a time) arrives</l>
                  <l>At a brave ſpatious Iland (that derives</l>
                  <l>Her name from white rocks, being a little world)</l>
                  <l>With other <hi>Troians</hi> before met, and hurl'd</l>
                  <l>Too on misfortunes. A towne call'd new <hi>Troy</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>He builds here th' Land cals <hi>Brutaine</hi>: doth enjoy</l>
                  <l>The whole as King; and his poſteritie</l>
                  <l>For many ages, ſhall raigne there, as he.</l>
                  <l>Sometimes (in pow'r and plentie) conquering</l>
                  <l>The neighbor Nations: ſometimes theſe (for nothing</l>
                  <l>But 's ſubject unto change on earth) afflict</l>
                  <l>Againe <hi>Troy's Brutaines,</hi> in their owne diſtrict.</l>
                  <l>Of which a certaine people, and call'd <hi>Danes</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>(<hi>Cymbrians</hi> by ſome) will prove their worſt of banes.</l>
                  <l>
                     <pb facs="tcp:47257:26"/>But ſhall be beaten backe; not without paine.</l>
                  <l>At length (in proceſſe of much time) ſhall raigne</l>
                  <l>In this faire Ile, a Prince (one way deſcended</l>
                  <l>Of <hi>Troian</hi> race: I' th' other ſide extended</l>
                  <l>Vp by the Royall bloud of <hi>Danes,</hi> unto</l>
                  <l>A warlike King call'd <hi>Reyner,</hi> that ſhall wooe</l>
                  <l>And wed a Lady Amazonian,</l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Landgartha</hi> nam'd) which Prince ſhall be the man</l>
                  <l>(Having his ſubjects in their loves combyn'd;</l>
                  <l>Who ſhall to evils onely be confin'd</l>
                  <l>By their owne ſad diſſentions, being of all</l>
                  <l>Earths men, the propereſt and moſt martiall)</l>
                  <l>To exalt thy bloud. He ſhall (by 's right) enjoy</l>
                  <l>The Land of <hi>Danes</hi>; and in this place where <hi>Troy</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>Now ſtands, ſhall Conquer, and build it againe.</l>
                  <l>Will alſo Conquer <hi>Greece,</hi> and there reſtrayne</l>
                  <l>Th' impieties of wicked men. Thus, <hi>Fate</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>I have layd ope' to thee, to conſolate</l>
                  <l>Thy ſelfe and ſad Queene; Now I muſt away:</l>
                  <l>For, from the gods I've made too long a ſtay.
<stage>
                        <hi>Exeunt amb<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap>.</hi>
                     </stage>
                  </l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Vald.</speaker>
                  <l>Your Majeſties have now ſeene all; even as</l>
                  <l>I found recorded in the foreſayd Booke:</l>
                  <l>How true heaven onely knowes. Yet, all may prove true</l>
                  <l>(Being not impoſſible) if men be wiſe.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Rey.</speaker>
                  <l>And not deſtroy themſelves, as it's there ſpoke.</l>
                  <l>Our part on't has hit right; and ſo may that.</l>
                  <l>And now (<hi>Valdemar</hi>) to requite thy love,
<stage>All riſe.</stage>
                  </l>
                  <l>My Queene and I will make your Maske compleate,</l>
                  <l>By being your dancers.
<stage>Enter Hub. &amp; Marf. without her ſword, &amp; her Gowne untuck'd.</stage>
                  </l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Hub.</speaker>
                  <l>I muſt firſt beg your</l>
                  <l>Pardon, to leade the meaſure, ſir, for I have</l>
                  <l>Brought a fine friendly dancer with me; and</l>
                  <l>We will ſo foot it —</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Rey.</speaker>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Hubba,</hi> thou alwayes comm'ſt in pudding time.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Land.</speaker>
                  <l>Let's ſtand; I long to ſee <hi>Marfiſa</hi> dance.
<stage>Here Hubba and Marfiſa Dance the whip of Donboyne merrily.</stage>
                  </l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Rey.</speaker>
                  <l>This was excellent. We ſhall but ſhame ourſelves,</l>
                  <l>In following of you; Come let us begin.</l>
               </sp>
               <stage>
                  <pb facs="tcp:47257:26"/>
                  <hi>Here they dance the grand Dance in foure Couple, Reyner and Landgartha, Valdemar and Scania, Fredericke and Elſinora, Inguar and Fatyma.</hi>
               </stage>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Rey.</speaker>
                  <l>So Couſin, we have made you ſome amends,</l>
                  <l>For your part of the Maske: and now you ſhall</l>
                  <l>(Being ſo kinde a husband) conduct your Lady</l>
                  <l>Unto her Chamber; and there uſe her kindly</l>
                  <l>Too as ſhe deſerves. Our Aunt and Couſin may</l>
                  <l>(After all this noyſe) alſo retyre; and ſay</l>
                  <l>(In ſolitude and ſilence) th' many prayers</l>
                  <l>They have omitted all the day. As for</l>
                  <l>The Queenes grace: ſhe muſt give me leave,</l>
                  <l>To uſher her to bed.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Land.</speaker>
                  <l>Muſt That, in ſuch</l>
                  <l>A ſervant, were too peremptory. But</l>
                  <l>If you plead your title King; I'll anſwer</l>
                  <l>That I know how to fight: and have ere now</l>
                  <l>Stoop'd a too haſty Prince. Therefore, good ſir,</l>
                  <l>You are beſt ſpeake me faire; or I may put you</l>
                  <l>Beſide your ſweet hopes;</l>
                  <l>And give you ſome what of the ſowre to taſte.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Rey.</speaker>
                  <l>That, and to kill me, were all one: For which,</l>
                  <l>I now (and ever will) humbly intreat,</l>
                  <l>As a poore ſuppliant with you to treat.
<stage>Exeunt omnes.</stage>
                  </l>
               </sp>
            </div>
            <div n="4" type="act">
               <head>The fourth Act.</head>
               <stage>Enter Reyner muſing at one doore, and Hubba to him at the other.</stage>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Rey.</speaker>
                  <l>Is <hi>Jnguar</hi> yet return'd from th' Fleet?</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Hub.</speaker>
                  <l>Not yet ſir.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Rey.</speaker>
                  <l>Let him be quickly ſent for then: be gone.
<stage>Exit Hubba.</stage>
                  </l>
                  <l>A poore gentlewoman, an ordinary</l>
                  <l>
                     <pb facs="tcp:47257:27"/>Noble mans daughter, to have catch'd me thus;</l>
                  <l>Whom <hi>Ceſar</hi> would rejoyce, to have made his ſonne,</l>
                  <l>Some horrid plague confound her modeſty,</l>
                  <l>And her for me, for now I care not for her;</l>
                  <l>Though I diſſemble it: becauſe I dare not</l>
                  <l>(She is ſo damn'd valiant) doe otherwiſe</l>
                  <l>Till I have got from hence: For ſhe (being</l>
                  <l>So belov'd too of the <hi>Norwegians</hi>) might</l>
                  <l>Cut ſhort my life and paſſage. But yet, <hi>Reyner,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>Thinke how exceeding worthy ſhe is of love;</l>
                  <l>And of a Prince: thinke of her vertue, doe:</l>
                  <l>Thinke of her beautie, myldneſſe, vallor, and</l>
                  <l>What elſe: no, no, I will not; will not love her:</l>
                  <l>For I have tooke enough of what I moſt lov'd;</l>
                  <l>Which, I confeſſe could not but pleaſe my Palat
<stage>Enter <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ald.</stage>
                  </l>
                  <l>But here comes <hi>Valdemar,</hi> who like an Aſſe</l>
                  <l>Still dotes on his wife, I 'll not therefore truſt him.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Vald.</speaker>
                  <l>Your reſolution to be gone for <hi>Denmarke,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>Men doe admire; and I muſt tell you, ſir,</l>
                  <l>(Seeing you will needs be conſtant, in ſo bad</l>
                  <l>A purpoſe) ſome doe feare your projects are</l>
                  <l>Ignoble. I then (as one that lov'd you once;</l>
                  <l>And will doe ſtill, unleſſe you forfeyte your ſelfe)</l>
                  <l>Wo'd be your adviſer, if you dare take advice.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Rey.</speaker>
                  <l>Y' are too ſawcie; and what I have reſolv'd on,</l>
                  <l>I will not alter. Muſt we be curb'd by you,</l>
                  <l>In tendering the welfare of our ſubjects?</l>
                  <l>Shall <hi>Denmarke</hi> be ſtill forgotten?</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Vald.</speaker>
                  <l>That colour</l>
                  <l>Dyes but very poorely; though you ſtalke with it.</l>
                  <l>The fall of your obſtreperous paſſion, to</l>
                  <l>Your Queene (ſir) people take notice of: though ſhe,</l>
                  <l>Poore Lady, (a ſliam'd to be deceiv'd or ſcorn'd)</l>
                  <l>Say nothing of it; reſtrayn'd too, by her love</l>
                  <l>To you. But, we that are your Countriemen</l>
                  <l>(Whom you mainely diſhonour in't) can have</l>
                  <l>No ſuch patience.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Rey.</speaker>
                  <l>Our affection to our</l>
                  <l>
                     <pb facs="tcp:47257:27"/>Lov'd faire Conſort (though you be pleas'd to doubt it)</l>
                  <l>Will not be queſtion'd, but by your ſlanderous tongue</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ald.</speaker>
                  <l>You cannot, ſir. Nay ſhall not, maske your blacke</l>
                  <l>Intentions ſo from me; they doe appeare</l>
                  <l>Too many. And ſhe whom you moſt wrong, is more</l>
                  <l>Then worthy of you; had you but the wiſedome</l>
                  <l>And grace to thinke ſo ſtill. But be aſſur'd</l>
                  <l>(When ſhe is rid o' th' burthen ſhe now carries)</l>
                  <l>She 'll be reveng'd at full for her diſhonour;</l>
                  <l>And ſnatch the Crownes you weare from of your trech'rous Temples.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Rey.</speaker>
                  <l>You will not play the Traytor, in</l>
                  <l>Conſpiring with her?</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Vald.</speaker>
                  <l>Though I ſho'd not, ſir,</l>
                  <l>You need not doubt but <hi>Harrolld</hi> will; who thinkes</l>
                  <l>His right to <hi>Denmarke,</hi> as good as yours to <hi>Norway.</hi>
                  </l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Rey.</speaker>
                  <l>That Chriſtian dog-ſhead and yours too, had beene</l>
                  <l>chopt off ere this, had I not beene a foole.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Vald.</speaker>
                  <l>If you durſt (you make me now beleeve) that had</l>
                  <l>Beene ſo. But I'll make ſhift to ſave one of 's;
<stage>Enter Ing. &amp; Hubba.</stage>
                  </l>
                  <l>And thinke you 'll hardly ſave your ſelfe from t' other.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Rey.</speaker>
                  <l>You may doe what you lift; and ſo will I,</l>
                  <l>Are all the Shipping ready?</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Ing.</speaker>
                  <l>They are ſir, but —</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Rey.</speaker>
                  <l>Come, ſpare your breath; I know what you wo'd ſay.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Hub.</speaker>
                  <l>Wo'd all the Cables and Sayles were burnt:</l>
                  <l>You brought us hither with the hazard of our lives,</l>
                  <l>To gaine this kingdome for you; and now you have it,</l>
                  <l>You 'll wiſely gi' 't away; and fetch 'em all</l>
                  <l>Upon our backes.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Rey.</speaker>
                  <l>Who made you a Counſeller?</l>
                  <l>There's your reward.
<stage>ſtrikes him.</stage>
                  </l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Hub.</speaker>
                  <l>I ſhall take more then this</l>
                  <l>Ere long if I ſticke to you.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Vald.</speaker>
                  <l>You doe well</l>
                  <l>To practiſe before hand.
<stage>Offers to draw, ſo does Vald. &amp; Ing. ſteps in.</stage>
                  </l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Rey.</speaker>
                  <l>Traytor, doe you upbrayd us?</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Ing.</speaker>
                  <l>I beſeech you ſir, to ſuppreſſe your paſſion;</l>
                  <l>
                     <pb facs="tcp:47257:28"/>And not to rayſe a tumult here: knowing</l>
                  <l>How truely-loyall the Prince <hi>Valdemar,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>Has ever beene to you, ſir, and now pleads</l>
                  <l>Strongly againſt himſelfe; in ſeeking to</l>
                  <l>Detaine you, with your gracious noble Queene.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Vald.</speaker>
                  <l>He accounts his friends, his neereſt enemies,</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Rey.</speaker>
                  <l>We take heaven to witneſſe, we are wrong'd.
<stage>Enter Land, with Childe and Scania not ſo.</stage>
                  </l>
                  <l>But peace; here ſhe comes.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Land.</speaker>
                  <l>Will you needs be gone, ſir,</l>
                  <l>And leave me thus?</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Rey.</speaker>
                  <l>It is but two houres ſayling,</l>
                  <l>In a faire day; and we ſhall ſoone be backe.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Land.</speaker>
                  <l>I doe not uſe to weepe: But now I muſt;
<stage>Weeps.</stage>
                  </l>
                  <l>My heavy minde fore-ſpeakes ſome future evill.</l>
                  <l>Death (which ſhall be welcome) I know 's not farre from me.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Rey.</speaker>
                  <l>May the gods grant to haſten it.
<stage>Aſide.</stage>
                  </l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Scan.</speaker>
                  <l>The time was</l>
                  <l>When ſhee, ſir, could with a nod a' forc'd your fancie,</l>
                  <l>In a farre greater matter, then your ſtay</l>
                  <l>For ſome ſmall time.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Rey.</speaker>
                  <l>And ſhall againe ſweet Siſter,</l>
                  <l>But the meere neceſſitie of our departure,</l>
                  <l>Is ſuch: that we muſt needs away, at this</l>
                  <l>Very inſtant.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Land.</speaker>
                  <l>Then give me leave (deare ſir,)</l>
                  <l>To ſhare the worſt may happen in your voyage.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Rey.</speaker>
                  <l>So to indanger your life, we'd looſe ours firſt,</l>
                  <l>You ſhall by no meanes ſtirre, my only ſoule, Come:</l>
                  <l>We will conduct you to your Chamber, and there</l>
                  <l>Leave you (with your friends and mine) to be guided</l>
                  <l>By your accuſtomed vertue, and ſtrong heart.
<stage>Exeunt.</stage>
                  </l>
               </sp>
               <stage>Enter Cowſell and Radger.</stage>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Cow.</speaker>
                  <l>O brother, brother, I know the very griefe on't,</l>
                  <l>Will kill me out right, as dead as a Herring.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Rad.</speaker>
                  <l>O deare, loving brother. I ſhall fare no better,</l>
                  <l>I'm ſure o' that; wo'd I had never ſeene you.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <pb facs="tcp:47257:28"/>
                  <speaker>Cow.</speaker>
                  <l>Beſides brother, I tooke ſuch an affection</l>
                  <l>To the women, fine, courteous, honeſt cre'tures.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Rad.</speaker>
                  <l>And we to you brother, and to all the <hi>Daues.</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>You came not to pray on's, but to deliver</l>
                  <l>Us from the <hi>Swedes.</hi>
                  </l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Cow.</speaker>
                  <l>We ought to love each other,</l>
                  <l>Brother, being ſo neere neighbors, and friends.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Rad.</speaker>
                  <l>So we doe, deare brother, all thoſe are good and honeſt.</l>
                  <l>Who wo'd 'a' thought his grace ſho'd leave the Queene</l>
                  <l>So abruptly, i' the latter end of her time too?</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Cow.</speaker>
                  <l>Hard againſt our wils: but ſayes, he 'll ſoone be backe.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Rad.</speaker>
                  <l>I' th' meane time brother, and before we part,</l>
                  <l>We are beſt take t' other cup.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Cow.</speaker>
                  <l>I thought to 'a'</l>
                  <l>Made that now my motion brother, we ſhall</l>
                  <l>Remember you in <hi>Denmarke.</hi>
                  </l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Rad.</speaker>
                  <l>And when we</l>
                  <l>Forget you brother, may the gods forget us.</l>
                  <l>Ho! drawer, <hi>Rolfo,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Within,</hi> Anon anon ſir.
<stage>Enter Rolfo.</stage>
                  </l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Rad.</speaker>
                  <l>Honeſt <hi>Rolfo,</hi> one flaggon more of that</l>
                  <l>You gave us laſt, the very ſame I charge thee,</l>
                  <l>Without tricks or mixture.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Rol.</speaker>
                  <l>By <hi>Love</hi> ſir, you ſhall:</l>
                  <l>What? Doe you thinke I 'll uſe you like a ſtranger?</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Cow.</speaker>
                  <l>Prithee kinde <hi>Rolfo,</hi> let not us be forc'd</l>
                  <l>To knocke agen.
<stage>Exit Rolfo.</stage>
                  </l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Rad.</speaker>
                  <l>Captaine <hi>Hubba</hi> (as I</l>
                  <l>Conceive brother) goes not along with you;</l>
                  <l>I met him ſpurring to our houſe, as I came.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Cow.</speaker>
                  <l>The Princeſſe <hi>Scania,</hi> by much intreatie</l>
                  <l>Got leave of the Lord <hi>Inguar,</hi> his Coronell,</l>
                  <l>To ſtay onely two dayes; and he is gone</l>
                  <l>A viſit to his Miſtris.
<stage>Enter Rolfo.</stage>
                  </l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Rad.</speaker>
                  <l>Welcome <hi>Rolfo.</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>Come, give it me: for we ſhall need no glaſſes.
<stage>They drinke at the Lines.</stage>
                  </l>
                  <l>Here worthy brother, halfe to your good journey</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Cow.</speaker>
                  <l>Let me ſee brother, <note n="*" place="bottom">Peeps into the pot.</note> you have drunke the full halfe—</l>
                  <l>
                     <pb facs="tcp:47257:29"/>Here <hi>Rolfo,</hi> fill 't agen.
<stage>Exit Rolfo.</stage>
                  </l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Rad.</speaker>
                  <l>O ſweet brother, that you co'd ſtay all night,</l>
                  <l>I ſho'd never be weary of your company.
<stage>Enter Rolfo.</stage>
                  </l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Cow.</speaker>
                  <l>Nor I of yours brother, and now from the deepe</l>
                  <l>Bottome of my heart to th' wide mouth of my ſtomacke</l>
                  <l>I ſpeake it deareſt brother, here's a whole one,</l>
                  <l>To our next merry meeting —</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Rad.</speaker>
                  <l>Quickely <hi>Rolfo,</hi>
                     <stage>Exit Rolfo.</stage>
                  </l>
                  <l>Fetch it, and be honeſt. O ſweet brother,</l>
                  <l>That I co'd imbrace you thus for ever, ever.
<stage>They imbrace.</stage>
                  </l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Cow.</speaker>
                  <l>I muſt kiſſe at parting.
<stage>They kiſſe.</stage>
                  </l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Rolf.</speaker>
                  <l>Y' are a couple of th' arranteſt kind gentlemen.
<stage>Ent. Rolf.</stage>
                  </l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Rad.</speaker>
                  <l>Give me the pot: I ne'r drunke i' my life</l>
                  <l>With more ſorrow, and a better deſire. —</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Cow.</speaker>
                  <l>Here, take Money <hi>Rolfo,</hi> my brother payd laſt,</l>
                  <l>I muſt kiſſe thee too <hi>Rolfo,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Within, Rolfo.</hi> Rogue.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Rolfo.</speaker>
                  <l>Anon, anon, ſir.
<stage>As they kiſſe.</stage>
                  </l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Rad.</speaker>
                  <l>Nay <hi>Rolfo,</hi> for all</l>
                  <l>Your haſte: I muſt (for my brothers ſake) take</l>
                  <l>Off that kiſſe, from thy now ſweet (though greaſie) lips.
<stage>They kiſſe</stage>
                  </l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Cow.</speaker>
                  <l>And now farewell, but not for ever, my deareſt</l>
                  <l>And beſt of friends. <hi>Rad.</hi> we 'll part at t'other Taverne.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Cow.</speaker>
                  <l>Then arme in arme let 's march, moſt worthy brother.
<stage>Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eunt.</stage>
                  </l>
               </sp>
               <stage>Enter Hubba and Marfiſa.</stage>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Hub.</speaker>
                  <l>I could not otherwiſe chuſe, Miſtris (though</l>
                  <l>Your diſtruſt of my unfayn'd affection,</l>
                  <l>Kept me thus long from injoying, what I</l>
                  <l>Moſt deſir'd in a noble way) but come</l>
                  <l>(Vrg'd by that love, that ever ſhall remaine</l>
                  <l>With me, whereſoe'r I goe) to tender</l>
                  <l>The duty of a ſervant, in taking leave</l>
                  <l>Of you, before my ſuddaine departure.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Mar.</speaker>
                  <l>It 's indeed too ſuddaine: and I doe now</l>
                  <l>Repent the not imbracing, what I was not</l>
                  <l>Enough good to accept, your love. For, I confeſſe</l>
                  <l>
                     <pb facs="tcp:47257:29"/>Though ſomewhat late, I lov'd you more then you</l>
                  <l>Did me; and ever ſhall unleſſe the fault</l>
                  <l>Be onely yours, in proving (which I doe</l>
                  <l>Not yet ſuſpect) a changling. I ſhall for</l>
                  <l>My part, puniſh ſeverely in my ſelfe,</l>
                  <l>Th' offence of not being yours, by a continu'd</l>
                  <l>Sadneſſe and griefe, till once agen I ſee you.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Hub.</speaker>
                  <l>And though I have beene too much noted for</l>
                  <l>My mirth (which yet, was never ſawe'd with ſpite,</l>
                  <l>Or other bad condition:) I promiſe</l>
                  <l>(Por my misfortune in thus miſſing of you)</l>
                  <l>Not to laugh once (unleſſe againſt my will,</l>
                  <l>At ſome unlucky chance) till I poſſeſſe</l>
                  <l>The treaſure I moſt covet.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Mar.</speaker>
                  <l>That (if you</l>
                  <l>Meane me) ſhall be yours when we meete next, and</l>
                  <l>Safely kept for you, untill then. I' th' meane time,</l>
                  <l>I ſhall charily preſerve (though but a poore</l>
                  <l>Satisfaction for you) your image in</l>
                  <l>Th' interior of my minde.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Hub.</speaker>
                  <l>Which overpay's,</l>
                  <l>With much advantage, all my ſervices.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Mar.</speaker>
                  <l>'t was a ſtrange reſolution of the King,</l>
                  <l>To leave his Queene, ſhe being ſo much againſt it;</l>
                  <l>And he ſo ſtrangely fond of her at firſt:</l>
                  <l>Which ſhe deſerv'd, being a Lady the world</l>
                  <l>Cannot match.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Hub.</speaker>
                  <l>He is theſe thirtie houres in <hi>Denmarke</hi>:</l>
                  <l>Where if he prove unkinde to her, that cannot</l>
                  <l>(In true judgement) condemne others, that like not</l>
                  <l>Such proceeding.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Mar.</speaker>
                  <l>He had neede be circumſpect</l>
                  <l>In what he do's; or he may ſoone repent it,</l>
                  <l>And perchance,</l>
                  <l>When matters prove paſt remedy to him,</l>
                  <l>Yet, while I find you ſound: no alien faults</l>
                  <l>Shall make me hate, what once I ſo affected,</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Hub.</speaker>
                  <l>Reſting on that aſſurance, I muſt now</l>
                  <l>
                     <pb facs="tcp:47257:30"/>Crave the kind, favour of a parting kiſſe.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Mar.</speaker>
                  <l>That you ſhall have <note n="*" place="margin">they kiſſe</note> and halfe a dozen more,</l>
                  <l>When you come to your Ship: For, ſo farre I</l>
                  <l>Will with you; and wo'd along to <hi>Denmarke,</hi> but to try</l>
                  <l>If I may build upon your conſtancie.
<stage>Exeunt.</stage>
                  </l>
               </sp>
               <stage>Enter Harold and Eric.</stage>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Har.</speaker>
                  <l>It's now but need, we both looke to our ſelves:</l>
                  <l>Or we may pay the forfeyt of our ſlackeneſſe</l>
                  <l>(With the loſſe of both our heads) upon a Scaffold.</l>
                  <l>For, <hi>Reyner</hi> having caſt the faire <hi>Landgartha</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>Off, (of whom he was not worthy:) and by</l>
                  <l>A dreadfull precipice, fall'n from much goodneſſe:</l>
                  <l>He will not ſtop at his firſt fault. But (hurri'd</l>
                  <l>By the guiltineſſe of his Conſcience)</l>
                  <l>Runne headlong downe the hill, upon the rocke</l>
                  <l>Of dangerous miſchiefe; to which he 's now ingag'd.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Eric.</speaker>
                  <l>She is a Lady of ſo ſtout a heart,</l>
                  <l>That when ſhe finds him baſe (although ſhe lov'd him</l>
                  <l>Exceedingly) ſhee cannot but be reveng'd</l>
                  <l>For her repudiation, and diſgrace.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Har.</speaker>
                  <l>And may prove our ſtrong friend to ruine him;</l>
                  <l>That has threatned (and that not privatly)</l>
                  <l>To rid himſelfe on us.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Eric.</speaker>
                  <l>And will, if he can:</l>
                  <l>You may by his death then, that wo'd be yours,</l>
                  <l>Settle your ſelfe ſecurely in his kingdomes,</l>
                  <l>By matching and partaking now with her.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Har.</speaker>
                  <l>Brother, the man whoſe deitie we adore</l>
                  <l>(And who to give us reſt, ſtill liv'd without it)</l>
                  <l>Can witneſſe for me, could I but perſwade</l>
                  <l>My minde by any probabilitie,</l>
                  <l>'t were poſſible, for me to live in peace here,</l>
                  <l>And not have my throat cut: although my right</l>
                  <l>Unto the Crowne of <hi>Denmarke</hi> be apparant,</l>
                  <l>My title while I ſlept or wak'd, ſho'd ſleepe;</l>
                  <l>As when King <hi>Reyner</hi> liv'd a vertuous kind man.</l>
                  <l>
                     <pb facs="tcp:47257:30"/>For I delight not in th' expence of bloud;</l>
                  <l>Though I feare not to ſpend my owne in a</l>
                  <l>Iuſt cauſe. But ſeeing all reſt is deni'd me:</l>
                  <l>As the ſtrong law of nature binds, I muſt</l>
                  <l>Shift for my ſelfe, the beſt I may. Which ſhall not</l>
                  <l>Be effected by baſe trechery, or murder.</l>
                  <l>Nor doe I chiefly yet meane to rely</l>
                  <l>On th' brave <hi>Landgartha's</hi> aſſiſtance; whom the</l>
                  <l>Love of a wife, and hope of reconcilement,</l>
                  <l>May urge beyond all ſpirit of revenge.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Eric.</speaker>
                  <l>What is 't you meane to plot then for our ſafetie?</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Har.</speaker>
                  <l>We'll to the pious Chriſtian Emperor,</l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Lewis</hi> the <hi>Debonaire</hi>; who (as you know)</l>
                  <l>Do's oft ſolicite me to plead my right</l>
                  <l>To th' Crowne, by dent of ſword; that being the beſt</l>
                  <l>(Nay onely) Patent, <hi>Reyner</hi> has to ſhow for 't.</l>
                  <l>Though he from 's father got it: which doth leſſen</l>
                  <l>Much his guilt.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Eric.</speaker>
                  <l>It's not his guilt that now moſt troubles him;</l>
                  <l>But by more ſinne to guard it.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Har.</speaker>
                  <l>Twelve thouſand.</l>
                  <l>Expert Souldiers (that lye neere here, o' th' borders</l>
                  <l>Of <hi>Germany</hi>) I may have when I liſt;</l>
                  <l>To adde (with all ſpeed) to our owne ſure friends.</l>
                  <l>And unto others that will fall in troopes,</l>
                  <l>From now diſhonour'd <hi>Reyner,</hi> for his baſe</l>
                  <l>Adultery intended with <hi>Vraca,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>To ſtrengthen himſelfe againſt his wife and me.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Eric.</speaker>
                  <l>Vnheard of madneſſe, ſo vilely to betray</l>
                  <l>(And to 's owne ruine) a poore and vertuous Lady;</l>
                  <l>That but for him, and his damn'd ſhameleſſe lyes,</l>
                  <l>Had never marry'd any. Being withall</l>
                  <l>(As 't is reported) moſt extreamely faire,</l>
                  <l>Farre, farre beyond the other,</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Har.</speaker>
                  <l>Such are the follies</l>
                  <l>Of humane nature, when it is forſaken</l>
                  <l>Of him that made it: But we'll now make uſe on't.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Eric.</speaker>
                  <l>You ſho'd be ſuddaine, leaſt we be layd hold on;</l>
                  <l>
                     <pb facs="tcp:47257:31"/>And to take him unprepar'd.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Har.</speaker>
                  <l>When night aſcends</l>
                  <l>Her ſable charyot, we will both of us</l>
                  <l>(Mounted on our beſt horſes) poſt away;</l>
                  <l>And be (I hope) cre we be miſs'd, paſs'd danger.</l>
                  <l>Come, let us therefore in, and looſe no time:</l>
                  <l>Which, in neceſſitie 's a fatall crime.
<stage>Exeunt.</stage>
                  </l>
               </sp>
            </div>
            <div n="5" type="act">
               <head>The fift Act.</head>
               <stage>Enter Valdomar and Jnguar.</stage>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Vald.</speaker>
                  <l>You are happy beyond expectation</l>
                  <l>In your Embaſſage: for all men did conceive</l>
                  <l>(And very probably) the Queene would ayde</l>
                  <l>With th' utmoſt of her pow'r, <hi>Harrold</hi> in his</l>
                  <l>Deſigne for <hi>Denmarke.</hi> But, ſhe noble Lady,</l>
                  <l>(Although in outward ſhow, ſhe have not granted</l>
                  <l>What you demand) I know (ſuch is her vertue</l>
                  <l>And loving nature) is comming in her minde,</l>
                  <l>Now to aſſiſt your moſt ungracious King.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Ing.</speaker>
                  <l>For which in chiefe he is to you beholding;</l>
                  <l>Though he deſerv'd it not, at his departure.</l>
                  <l>But now, Contrition has wipt off his guilt,</l>
                  <l>Though not the puniſhment, before the gods.</l>
                  <l>Nor is there any hope left us on earth,</l>
                  <l>But what we now may gaine here by your meanes</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Vald.</speaker>
                  <l>Had you but beene a witneſſe of her griefes</l>
                  <l>(Able to rive a heart of ſteele) you had</l>
                  <l>Melted (as we almoſt did) into teares:</l>
                  <l>Eſpecially when ſhe heard of th' infamous</l>
                  <l>Marryage, with <hi>Swealands</hi> daughter (told her by</l>
                  <l>A whiſpering flatterer:) how then ſhe tore</l>
                  <l>Her golden hayre, and us'd ſuch cruelty</l>
                  <l>On her faire limmes, which had wellneere ended her</l>
                  <l>(Notwithſtanding what we could doe to hinder 't:)</l>
                  <l>
                     <pb facs="tcp:47257:31"/>Curſing the time when ſhe e'r ſaw a <hi>Dane</hi>;</l>
                  <l>Not for her husbands renogading moſt:</l>
                  <l>But the loſſe of her virginitie, and foule</l>
                  <l>Diſgrace.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Ing.</speaker>
                  <l>We heard of all: Yet, were compell'd</l>
                  <l>By ſtrong neceſſitie (perforce) to build</l>
                  <l>On her heroicke goodneſſe, and your worth.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Vald.</speaker>
                  <l>'t was well conceiv'd; and better put to tryall,</l>
                  <l>That compulſion may worke peace agen.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Ing.</speaker>
                  <l>Here the divine Lady comes (her ſelfe) unto us.
<stage>Enter Land<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gartha, Scania, Elſino<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ra, Fatyma, &amp; Marfi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſa in womans apparell with Swords on.</stage>
                  </l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Land.</speaker>
                  <l>Although (Lord <hi>Inguar,</hi>) your ſoveraigne, and my</l>
                  <l>Unkind husband, were rather to expect</l>
                  <l>Sharpe warre and hate then any ayde from me</l>
                  <l>In his diſtreſſe: having (as farre as 't lay</l>
                  <l>In him) diſgrac'd me by his flight; and as</l>
                  <l>I 'd us'd falſe play with others: yet, my love</l>
                  <l>To him (deepely engraven in my heart.)</l>
                  <l>Ioyn'd to my owne innocence and merit, has</l>
                  <l>(As all may ſee) got the upper-hand; and ſtopt</l>
                  <l>My once intended courſe of ſtrict revenge;</l>
                  <l>Though he enjoy another wife, now the Miſtris</l>
                  <l>Of what is mine by bond.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Ing.</speaker>
                  <l>Moſt gracious Queene,</l>
                  <l>I can ſay nothing, to excuſe his guilt;</l>
                  <l>Or leſſen it: but that your vertue ſhines</l>
                  <l>The brighter for his deepe ingratitude,</l>
                  <l>Which now 's the greateſt Corroſive to himſelfe,</l>
                  <l>And cauſe of all his evils, by the loſſe</l>
                  <l>Of in a manner all was his before:</l>
                  <l>And that his act, has render'd both of you</l>
                  <l>Famous to all the world, in different manners:</l>
                  <l>You as the glorious mirrour of all worth,</l>
                  <l>But him (with griefe I ſpeake it) for 's offence.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Scan.</speaker>
                  <l>Which now (deare Madame) as it is repented,</l>
                  <l>Exacts your mercy more then puniſhment.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Elſin.</speaker>
                  <l>To prove a laſting Pyramid to all</l>
                  <l>Succeeding times, of ſuch a noble act.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Vald.</speaker>
                  <l>It can yeeld you no benefit to ruine</l>
                  <l>
                     <pb facs="tcp:47257:32"/>Him and his poore ſubjects, being alſo yours;</l>
                  <l>And in their loves, they're yours.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Fat.</speaker>
                  <l>Much more then his</l>
                  <l>I doe beleeve.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Ing.</speaker>
                  <l>Madame. I can depoſe it.
<stage>To Fatyma.</stage>
                  </l>
                  <l>And that they 've ever deem'd it their chiefe glory,</l>
                  <l>To have had her for their Queene; their hearts he loſt,</l>
                  <l>When he loſt her: nor is there ought can rayſe</l>
                  <l>The minds o' th' few, that now ſticke to him, but her</l>
                  <l>Strong aſſiſtance, and the try'd vallor of the</l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Norwegian</hi> Ladies, that before</l>
                  <l>Gave us the victory againſt the <hi>Swedes.</hi>
                  </l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Land.</speaker>
                  <l>King <hi>Reyner</hi> and your ſelfe (Lord <hi>Inguar)</hi> have</l>
                  <l>Too many friends here, to be deni'd in what</l>
                  <l>Our pow'r may ſtead him, or you demand.</l>
                  <l>And I'm the more induc'd to pardon his fault,</l>
                  <l>That I acknowledge my ſelfe faultie too</l>
                  <l>(And which my heart has oft accus'd me for,</l>
                  <l>With no ſmall griefe) in granting that to him</l>
                  <l>Vnder the flattering title of marryage, which I</l>
                  <l>Reſolv'd ne'r to 'a' loſt; and which he durſt not</l>
                  <l>Seeke to have forc'd from me. But it 's now paſt helpe.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Scan.</speaker>
                  <l>There 's one way yet left (Madame) to helpe all.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Land.</speaker>
                  <l>He then tranſported, by his fierce deſire,</l>
                  <l>Which ſlav'd him: by craft (I'll give it no worſe</l>
                  <l>A name) did that wrong to my modeſtie,</l>
                  <l>Which I (being not ſo deepe in paſſion)</l>
                  <l>Might well have hinder'd; and by yeelding to it,</l>
                  <l>Have given ſcope for others to condemne me.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Ing.</speaker>
                  <l>Which none can juſtly doe: For, I'm aſſur'd,</l>
                  <l>Madame (though you have cauſe not to beleeve it)</l>
                  <l>That his intents to your grace, were ſincere</l>
                  <l>At firſt, as now they are: and therefore (deare Queene,)</l>
                  <l>You are to meete his paſt ill, with your goodneſſe.</l>
                  <l>Which, if you doe not ſpeedily: there will be</l>
                  <l>No time, nor meanes hereafter, left for you</l>
                  <l>To exerciſe your vallor in this cauſe.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Land.</speaker>
                  <l>When we behold our neighbors houſe on fire,</l>
                  <l>
                     <pb facs="tcp:47257:32"/>The Proverbe ſayes we ought looke to our owne:</l>
                  <l>This you conceive; and I ſuppoſe you are</l>
                  <l>Inform'd by theſe that love you, that we have</l>
                  <l>As many valiant men and women, in</l>
                  <l>A readineſſe, as may, if heaven be pleas'd</l>
                  <l>(For we are pleas'd in 't) reinthrone your King;</l>
                  <l>And chaſe thoſe rebels that now urge his flight.</l>
                  <l>Let then my brother (the Prince <hi>Valdemar)</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>And you, make all the haſte you can before us;</l>
                  <l>With newes of our approach. And, one thing more</l>
                  <l>I muſt intreat you doe for me: which is</l>
                  <l>To deliver this Letter, unto him that</l>
                  <l>Caus'd my ſorrow; and left me great with child.</l>
                  <l>Which fruit of his, he ſhall ſoone looke on, young <hi>Frideſlaus.</hi>
                  </l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Vald.</speaker>
                  <l>He ſho'd 'a' ſtayd, to have got</l>
                  <l>Such another.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Scan.</speaker>
                  <l>In honeſty, he could</l>
                  <l>Have done no leſſe.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Ing.</speaker>
                  <l>Your graces Letter, I hope</l>
                  <l>Within theſe three houres, he ſhall reade at furtheſt.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Vald.</speaker>
                  <l>You 'll give me leave to goe before, to provide</l>
                  <l>A lodging for you?</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Scan.</speaker>
                  <l>Yes: for I meane to be</l>
                  <l>Your bedfellow to morrow night.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Vald.</speaker>
                  <l>And I ſhall ſtrayne my ſelfe, to bid you welcome.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Ing.</speaker>
                  <l>The King will doe as much too, for your Highneſſe.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Land.</speaker>
                  <l>Fy, not ſo ſoone man, that were a ſhame indeed,</l>
                  <l>People wo'd then ſay, that I went to aske it.
<stage>ſmilingly</stage>
                  </l>
                  <l>Nor does he neede me; having one (at leaſt)</l>
                  <l>Already to keepe him warme.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Ing.</speaker>
                  <l>He thinkes of none,</l>
                  <l>But your Grace.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Vald.</speaker>
                  <l>We muſt be now abrupt in our</l>
                  <l>Leave taking?</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Land.</speaker>
                  <l>Be gone <hi>Scania,</hi> fare you well. <hi>Inguar,</hi> may all</l>
                  <l>The gods be your guides.
<stage>Exeunt ambo.</stage>
                  </l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Land.</speaker>
                  <l>And now <hi>Marfiſa.</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <pb facs="tcp:47257:33"/>Silence declares with you, how gladly your heart</l>
                  <l>Conſents, to goe for <hi>Denmarke.</hi>
                  </l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Mar.</speaker>
                  <l>I meane to doe</l>
                  <l>Your Majeſtie ſome ſervice there, now that</l>
                  <l>You meaſure my affection by your owne.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Scan.</speaker>
                  <l>But what, if you come to weare the Willow garland,</l>
                  <l>By the inconſtancie of Captaine <hi>Hubba</hi>?</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Mar.</speaker>
                  <l>Not (doe as the Queene did) forgive the offence.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Fat.</speaker>
                  <l>No leſſe then 's life would ſatisfie your anger.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Mar.</speaker>
                  <l>Doe you make doubt on't?</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Elſin.</speaker>
                  <l>I beleeve him honeſt.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Land.</speaker>
                  <l>What is your owne opinion? <hi>Marfiſa.</hi>
                  </l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Mar.</speaker>
                  <l>I ſtill ſuppoſe the beſt.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Land.</speaker>
                  <l>Then wayte upon</l>
                  <l>My couſin <hi>Fatyma</hi>: and both of you make haſte</l>
                  <l>To ſummon with all ſpeede (on paine of death)</l>
                  <l>All our troops (both men and women) in <hi>Anſtoy,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Saltſburge,</hi> and thereabouts. Our Siſter and Aunt</l>
                  <l>Shall to the neerer quarters; whilſt I prepare</l>
                  <l>Here all things requiſite for our departure.</l>
                  <l>And as we once made no ſmall haſte to meete</l>
                  <l>King <hi>Reyner,</hi> when he brought us ayde againſt</l>
                  <l>Our foes: let's doe the ſame in gratitude</l>
                  <l>(And with more honour) now, in aſſiſting of him.</l>
                  <l>Thoſe which we leave, will keepe ſafe here. Away.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Fat.</speaker>
                  <l>The truſt impos'd on us, we 'll not betray.
<stage>Exeunt omnes ſeverally.</stage>
                  </l>
               </sp>
               <stage>A march. <hi>Then enter Harrold, Eric, and Lothaire arm'd.</hi>
               </stage>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Har.</speaker>
                  <l>We muſt make haſte, Lord <hi>Lothaire,</hi> (now that by</l>
                  <l>The helpe of heaven, for which we chiefly move:</l>
                  <l>And the aſſiſtance which you Lord and ours,</l>
                  <l>The noble Emperor <hi>Lewis,</hi> true inheritor</l>
                  <l>Of his great fathers vertues did afford us,</l>
                  <l>We are aſcended to what is our right,</l>
                  <l>Being thereto lifted by your manly worth too)</l>
                  <l>To make all ſure, by joyning our laſt iſſue</l>
                  <l>
                     <pb facs="tcp:47257:33"/>With <hi>Reyner,</hi> ere the brave <hi>Landgartha</hi> come</l>
                  <l>(Whom he once more thinkes to deceive:) For, where</l>
                  <l>Shee leads, all goes to wracke i' th' other ſide.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Loth.</speaker>
                  <l>It 's ſtrange ſo ſtout a minde as hers, ſho'd ever</l>
                  <l>Yeeld love or obedience to a man that has</l>
                  <l>So baſely dealt to her.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Eric.</speaker>
                  <l>She ſquares all her</l>
                  <l>Actions by the rule of goodneſſe, not</l>
                  <l>Of paſſion; and thinkes this deede of hers,</l>
                  <l>A very gratefull offering to her gods,</l>
                  <l>Yet, we doe hope to ſend (before ſhe land here:</l>
                  <l>Her husbands rancke ſoule, to great <hi>Belzebub.</hi>
                  </l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Har.</speaker>
                  <l>Then let's march on with ſpeede; and truſt our cauſe</l>
                  <l>To him, that only gives life by his lawes.
<stage>Exeunt a march.</stage>
                  </l>
               </sp>
               <stage>After the march, Enter Reyner and Hubba.</stage>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Rey.</speaker>
                  <l>Heare you no newes from <hi>Inguar</hi> (<hi>Hubba</hi>) yet</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Hub.</speaker>
                  <l>Not a word: But a ſhip is now on entring</l>
                  <l>In at the haven; and we hope it 's his.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Rey.</speaker>
                  <l>No, no. We are of all the world forſaken,</l>
                  <l>But moſt of heaven: For, we have deſerv'd it,</l>
                  <l>And our repentance now comes too too late.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Hub.</speaker>
                  <l>I doe beſeech you ſir, not to yeeld to</l>
                  <l>Such weake, unmanly diffidence.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Rey.</speaker>
                  <l>We wrong'd</l>
                  <l>Thee (<hi>Hubba</hi>) too; and now thy loyaltie</l>
                  <l>And kindneſſe wounds our ſoule deeper, then if thou hadſt</l>
                  <l>Prov'd falſe, all turnes to my confuſion.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Hub.</speaker>
                  <l>It was your paſſion and not you, ſtrucke me, ſir.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Rey.</speaker>
                  <l>Would I were quickly dead, or never borne,</l>
                  <l>To ſee the evils which I have occaſion'd,</l>
                  <l>And muſt needs feele, if I but live a while.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Hub.</speaker>
                  <l>Your noble Queene <hi>Landgartha,</hi> will I doubt not</l>
                  <l>(If i' th' meane time ſir, you doe what lyes in you,</l>
                  <l>With patience) ſoone rid you of thoſe feares;</l>
                  <l>And State you as before; and in her love too.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Rey.</speaker>
                  <l>I ne'r ſhall ſee that <hi>Halcyon</hi> day againe,</l>
                  <l>
                     <pb facs="tcp:47257:34"/>To ſee her, <hi>Hubba,</hi> though you all ſuppoſe</l>
                  <l>The contrary; and caus'd me ſend to move</l>
                  <l>Her goodneſſe. She is too magnanimous</l>
                  <l>Ever to looke at ſuch a wretch as I am,</l>
                  <l>That deceiv'd her once ſo foulely.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Hub.</speaker>
                  <l>You'll finde</l>
                  <l>Your ſelfe deceiv'd, I hope ſir, in that ere long.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Rey.</speaker>
                  <l>Had I but faithfull prov'd to her, as ſhe</l>
                  <l>Deſerv'd (thou know'ſ it <hi>Hubba,</hi>) I might then</l>
                  <l>'a' playd at ſtoole-ball with young children, or</l>
                  <l>Have waſted time more idlely, if I'd liſted;</l>
                  <l>And have my eſtate multiply'd to many</l>
                  <l>Kingdomes. Now, thou ſeeſt, we are not worth one</l>
                  <l>Province, Stricke me heaven.
<stage>Enter Valdemar and Inguar.</stage>
                  </l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Vald.</speaker>
                  <l>Honeſt Captaine, I</l>
                  <l>Am glad to meete you alive.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Hub.</speaker>
                  <l>Your Highneſſe poore ſervant.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Ing.</speaker>
                  <l>The King walkes ſtrangely ſad.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Hub.</speaker>
                  <l>He's not himſelfe: and therefore, whatſoever</l>
                  <l>Newes you bring; y' had neede uſe your accuſtomed</l>
                  <l>Diſcretion in the relating of it.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Rey.</speaker>
                  <l>You are both as welcome hither, as my</l>
                  <l>Diſtraction will give me leave to bid you.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Vald.</speaker>
                  <l>I never knew you (ſir) too much exalted</l>
                  <l>At flatt'ring Fortunes ſmiles, or when you Conquer'd:</l>
                  <l>And (now ſhe frownes) you ſtill ought to preſerve</l>
                  <l>A valiant indifferencie.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Rey.</speaker>
                  <l>Healthy men</l>
                  <l>Know how t' afford good counſell unto others,</l>
                  <l>Whoſe forces being too weake, to beare the blowes</l>
                  <l>Of their diſeaſes, yeeld and languiſh under</l>
                  <l>The waight that 's inſupportable.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Jng.</speaker>
                  <l>The weaker</l>
                  <l>Their minds are, the more they yeeld; beyond</l>
                  <l>Neceſſitie: and thereby become chiefe Actors</l>
                  <l>In their owne Tragedies.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Rey.</speaker>
                  <l>I know you ſpeake this,</l>
                  <l>To prepare my minde, for the bad newes you bring.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <pb facs="tcp:47257:34"/>
                  <speaker>Ing.</speaker>
                  <l>Your vertue will now moſt conſiſt, in not</l>
                  <l>Being over joy'd, when you read this Letter,</l>
                  <l>Written and ſent by her, that ſayes ſhe loves you.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Rey.</speaker>
                  <l>Let me ſee 't. I know the hand, it's hers,</l>
                  <l>O let me, let me kiſſe it, kiſſe it ſtill,
<stage>Kiſſes the Letter.</stage>
                  </l>
                  <l>And not preſume to looke what it contaynes,</l>
                  <l>To plague my guiltie conſcience. <hi>Vald.</hi> reade and be rul'd.</l>
                  <stage>Reyner opens and Reads.</stage>
                  <floatingText type="letter">
                     <body>
                        <p>If this my ſecond duty, may prove as happy in the recovery of thy kingdomes, as my firſt was against a Tyrant; yet honouring thee with the victory; J ſhall account my travell well beſtow'd. Make head bravely (as wiſedome permits) againſt the enemie: for I am comming with all ſpeed, to let him know, that <hi>Landgartha</hi> (being thy Queenne and only lawfull Wife) is a warrior: and will prove ſo to his prejudice, and thy advantage: having from her heart (notwithſtanding thy unkindneſſe) abſolv'd thee of all the wrongs thou did'ſt her.</p>
                        <closer>
                           <signed>Landgartha,</signed>
                        </closer>
                     </body>
                  </floatingText>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Rey.</speaker>
                  <l>A gracious language! O you gods defend me,</l>
                  <l>From turning altogether foole at this. For, my</l>
                  <l>Frayle veſſell is not able to contayne,</l>
                  <l>The forcible exceſſe of this ſweet comfort.</l>
                  <l>My ſoule reſults ſo ſtrangely, mounts, mounts up,</l>
                  <l>That I have much adoe, to keepe from dancing:</l>
                  <l>My nimble ſpirit elevats my body,</l>
                  <l>And my very life (I thinke) will now with joy</l>
                  <l>Forſake me, fly away.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Vald.</speaker>
                  <l>Be not in extreames,</l>
                  <l>So like a meere franticke Pray recall your wits,</l>
                  <l>Before ſhe comes, you may looſe all; your ſelfe, and us.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Rey.</speaker>
                  <l>Excuſe me, worthy Couſin, you feele not</l>
                  <l>The force of my impulſion. Yet, I confeſſe</l>
                  <l>I'm (but as others are) a poore weake man;</l>
                  <l>Subject to many changes 'gainſt my will.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Ing.</speaker>
                  <l>Collect your ſelfe, were 't but in obedience
<stage>Enter ſcout.</stage>
                  </l>
                  <l>To your wiſe and noble Queene. What newes with you?</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Scout.</speaker>
                  <l>That <hi>Harrold</hi> and his brother <hi>Eric,</hi> with</l>
                  <l>A mighty pow'r of <hi>Danes</hi> and <hi>Germans,</hi> march</l>
                  <l>
                     <pb facs="tcp:47257:35"/>Hither with ſpeed, doubtleſſe to force a battle.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Ing.</speaker>
                  <l>Which we muſt decline, till our beſt ſouldier</l>
                  <l>Come: and then we are for 'em.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Vald.</speaker>
                  <l>Lead us from hence,</l>
                  <l>To guard your works; and doe not now forget</l>
                  <l>(Your wiſh'd ayde being ſo neere you) your old vallor;</l>
                  <l>And judgement to command.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Ray.</speaker>
                  <l>I hope we ſhall not.
<stage>Exeunt.</stage>
                  </l>
               </sp>
               <stage>A march. <hi>Enter Harrold, Eric, Lothaire, and one or two more with Battle-axes.</hi>
               </stage>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Har.</speaker>
                  <l>Our foes have fortifi'd themſelves ſo ſtrongly,</l>
                  <l>With Waggons, Carts, huge tymber, and deepe trenches:</l>
                  <l>As 'tis impoſſible almoſt to force 'em.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Eric.</speaker>
                  <l>Which if you doe not, you'll finde it a worſe taske,</l>
                  <l>To quayle <hi>Landgartha</hi>; whoſe fleet's now at ſea;</l>
                  <l>Nay hard on landing.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Loth.</speaker>
                  <l>Th' preſent attempt will not</l>
                  <l>Perchance, prove ſo dangerous, as to th' eye</l>
                  <l>It ſeemes; if we valiantly ingage</l>
                  <l>Our ſelves in th' onſet.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Har.</speaker>
                  <l>Let us boldly on then;</l>
                  <l>And to conclude what hitherto, we have</l>
                  <l>So proſperouſly atchiev'd. I will beginne:</l>
                  <l>And die, rather then looſe what I have wonne.
<stage>Exeunt.</stage>
                  </l>
               </sp>
               <stage>Allarums, <hi>A while after which is begun, enter Reyner and Valdemar with Battle-axes.</hi>
               </stage>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Rey.</speaker>
                  <l>All 's loſt beyond recoverie, they are broke</l>
                  <l>Vpon us in, and fight like hungry Lyons,</l>
                  <l>Tearing our men to peeces, that now leave,</l>
                  <l>In foule diſorder.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Vald.</speaker>
                  <l>Doe you (whil'ſt I charge up,</l>
                  <l>To give ſome ſtop unto their furie) rally</l>
                  <l>And hearten yours, the beſt you may. For, if</l>
                  <l>We can hold out, but one full houre: the noble</l>
                  <l>
                     <pb facs="tcp:47257:35"/>
                     <hi>Landgartha</hi> (that with ſpeed incredible,</l>
                  <l>Has almoſt landed all her forces) will be</l>
                  <l>With us, to mend all agen.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Rey.</speaker>
                  <l>She ſhall never meet me flying.
<stage>Exeunt. allarums.</stage>
                  </l>
               </sp>
               <stage>Enter Landgartha, Scania, Elſinora, Fatyma, and Marfiſa: The foure Ladies, like Amazons. Marfiſa with her Gowne tuck'd to th' midleg, ſpurs, &amp;c. As in the firſt of the third Act; Bat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tle-axes withall.</stage>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Land.</speaker>
                  <l>You heare this Muſicke, Ladies, and perceive</l>
                  <l>What need our friends have of our ſwift aſſiſtance.</l>
                  <l>We are not therefore now, to inſiſt upon
<stage>Here the Allarums ſound as farre off.</stage>
                  </l>
                  <l>A tedious conſultation; or on words</l>
                  <l>By me deliver'd, to encourage thoſe</l>
                  <l>Whoſe worths I know already. Doe you Aunt</l>
                  <l>(Aſſiſted by <hi>Fatyma</hi> and <hi>Marfiſa</hi>)</l>
                  <l>Lead halfe our Armie: and wheele round about</l>
                  <l>(With ſpeed and ſilence) to charge ſtrongly home,</l>
                  <l>Upon our enemies backes. My ſiſter and I</l>
                  <l>Will to our Husbands, that are hardly preſt;</l>
                  <l>Their men all routed, and a number ſlaine.</l>
                  <l>Farewell, I hope that we ſhall meete againe.
<stage>Exeunt ſverally allarums.</stage>
                  </l>
               </sp>
               <stage>Allarums. <hi>Then enter Reyner at one doore, and Har<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>old at the other.</hi>
               </stage>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Rey.</speaker>
                  <l>Stand Traytor!</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Har.</speaker>
                  <l>Thou uſurper, I will ſtand;</l>
                  <l>And could afford you other glorious titles:</l>
                  <l>But that I meane not (having met you) to</l>
                  <l>Waſte time in words, untill your fooliſh ſweet-heart</l>
                  <l>(Whom you wo'd ſtill deceive) come to your reſcue.</l>
                  <l>But now, I hope you never ſhall enjoy her,</l>
                  <l>You know how.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Rey.</speaker>
                  <l>You ſhall know ſomewhat from me, howſoever.</l>
               </sp>
               <stage>
                  <pb facs="tcp:47257:36"/>
                  <hi>Here they fight, and Harrold beats Reyner under him; on which Landgartha enters, beats in Harrold and returns.</hi>
               </stage>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Land.</speaker>
                  <l>Is it you? I were not beholding, to
<stage>Land. Exit.</stage>
                  </l>
                  <l>Have done this for you now. Goe, look to your ſelfe &amp; people.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Rey.</speaker>
                  <l>Deare heaven, where am I? or, is this a dream?
<stage>Reyner riſes as ſhe beats in Harrold.</stage>
                  </l>
                  <l>It was <hi>Landgartha</hi> ſure. O no, it was not,</l>
                  <l>That glory and great miracle of the world,</l>
                  <l>Could not afford ſuch grace to me, the meere</l>
                  <l>Fall'n dregs of villanie. But yet, 't was ſhe,</l>
                  <l>The figure of her heavenly face, was once</l>
                  <l>(And ſtill is) ſo imprinted in my ſoule,</l>
                  <l>As 't is impoſſible I ſho'd forget her,</l>
                  <l>Therefore you gods, heape all thoſe mountaynes on me,</l>
                  <l>Which the impious Gyants lifted againſt you,</l>
                  <l>Or ſincke me downe into the very Center,</l>
                  <l>That I may ne'r behold her any more,</l>
                  <l>That is ſo like you, both in ſhape and goodneſſe.</l>
                  <l>For, both I have contemn'd, and my moſt baſe</l>
                  <l>Ingratitude, never appear'd at full;</l>
                  <l>Till now. O <hi>Iove,</hi> pownd pownd me with thy thunder,</l>
                  <l>For, my confuſion is the worſt of torments.
<stage>Enter Scania and Valdemar.</stage>
                  </l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Scan.</speaker>
                  <l>The King 's in danger; and we had need make haſte</l>
                  <l>To diſingage him.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Vald.</speaker>
                  <l>That 's done (I hope) already.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Rey.</speaker>
                  <l>Welcome deare Siſter, I am aſham'd to looke</l>
                  <l>You in the face.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Scan.</speaker>
                  <l>We heard (ſir) you were in danger.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Rey.</speaker>
                  <l>I was: But now may (when I liſt) goe take</l>
                  <l>A nap. Wo'd the infernall dogs would teare</l>
                  <l>My limbs to callops: or adde ſome worſe torment</l>
                  <l>Unto my minds affliction.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Scan.</speaker>
                  <l>You neede not</l>
                  <l>Afflict your ſelfe ſo much, for ought we ſee:</l>
                  <l>For, now the wheele is turn'd to your advantage;</l>
                  <l>My Siſter is friends with you too, ſir.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Rey.</speaker>
                  <l>She ſay'd</l>
                  <l>
                     <pb facs="tcp:47257:36"/>My life, when I was downe; and ready to</l>
                  <l>Receive the laſt (and mortall) blow. But then,</l>
                  <l>Gave me ſo ſad a looke, O loving Siſter,</l>
                  <l>That life which is her gift, if I muſt keepe</l>
                  <l>In her diſpleaſure, is much worſe then death.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Scan.</speaker>
                  <l>Sir, if you will be rul'd by me, you muſt not</l>
                  <l>Expreſſe too much, thoſe vehement affections:</l>
                  <l>For, ſhe's acquainted but too well already,</l>
                  <l>With your ſad paſſion, and the continuance of it.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Rey.</speaker>
                  <l>Seeing you (deare Lady,) in love and wiſedome,</l>
                  <l>Eſteeme that my beſt courſe: I ſhall be dumbe</l>
                  <l>As night, calme as the calm'ſt evening after</l>
                  <l>A ſtormy day. <hi>Scania,</hi> let's follow, where ſhe went then.
<stage>Exeunt.</stage>
                  </l>
               </sp>
               <stage>Enter Harrold and Eric.</stage>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Har.</speaker>
                  <l>After our loſſe and watching theſe two nights,</l>
                  <l>I cannot brother (the toyle of our journey,</l>
                  <l>Lying ſo heavy too, on my tyr'd body)</l>
                  <l>But ſleepe a little, though it be dangerous.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Eric.</speaker>
                  <l>My neede's no leſſe; a little ſleepe will ſerve.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Har.</speaker>
                  <l>Let's take it here then, the place being ſolitary.</l>
               </sp>
               <stage>They ſleepe, and a ſweet ſolemne Muſicke of Recorders is heard, then enter an Angel.</stage>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Ang.</speaker>
                  <l>Heaven has decreed, another day</l>
                  <l>Shall gaine what you have loſt. Your way</l>
                  <l>Take both (as you were forc'd before)</l>
                  <l>Unto the pious Emperor.</l>
                  <l>One of you ſhall be King: whoſe ſeed</l>
                  <l>Shall be ſo too, untill 't all bleed.</l>
                  <l>Then (when that iſſue is extinct)</l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Norway</hi> and <hi>Denmarkes</hi> whole precinct</l>
                  <l>Shall be rul'd by <hi>Landgartha's</hi> line,</l>
                  <l>And <hi>Reyners.</hi> Her the pow'rs divine</l>
                  <l>Will (for her Morall vertues) turne</l>
                  <l>A Chriſtian, ere ſhe come to th' Urne:</l>
                  <l>
                     <pb facs="tcp:47257:37"/>Yeeld faith to this: For, without doubt,</l>
                  <l>What I have ſayd ſhall come about.
<stage>Exit Ang. then Eric ſtirs and wakes Har.</stage>
                  </l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Eric.</speaker>
                  <l>Sir, you ſleepe exceeding ſoundly: Pray wake.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Har.</speaker>
                  <l>I now am freſh enough; Come let's be gone.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Eric.</speaker>
                  <l>Dream't you nothing, while you ſlept?</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Har.</speaker>
                  <l>No, did you?</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Eric.</speaker>
                  <l>Me thought I heard a moſt heavenly Muſicke;</l>
                  <l>And that an Angel did appeare: and wiſh'd us,</l>
                  <l>Betake our ſelves againe to th' Emperor,</l>
                  <l>That what we loſt, another day ſho'd purchaſe;</l>
                  <l>And that the faire <hi>Landgartha</hi> (as the reward</l>
                  <l>Of her Morall vertues) would be made Chriſtian,</l>
                  <l>Before ſhe di'd.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Har.</speaker>
                  <l>Though we afford no credit</l>
                  <l>Vnto ſuch dreames: Yet, we muſt ſteere our courſe</l>
                  <l>That way; there being (after ſo great a loſſe)</l>
                  <l>No comfort left, where our foes are ſo ſtrong.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Eric.</speaker>
                  <l>Heaven will in time (I hope) revenge our wrong.
<stage>Exeunt</stage>
                  </l>
               </sp>
               <stage>Enter Cowſell and Radgee.</stage>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Cow.</speaker>
                  <l>Come brother <hi>Radgee,</hi> it is now concluded,</l>
                  <l>We ſhall never part agen.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Rad.</speaker>
                  <l>O deare brother,</l>
                  <l>I never had a good day on't (much leſſe</l>
                  <l>A good night) ſince (being barr'd the comfort of your</l>
                  <l>Sweet converſation) you parted from me.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Cow.</speaker>
                  <l>Nay brother, I can howle the ſame ſad Madrigall</l>
                  <l>Too: For looke you brother, we were all ſo frighted</l>
                  <l>By thoſe fat-foggy <hi>Germans</hi> (who men ſay</l>
                  <l>Are nothing but fleſh and belly:) that we durſt</l>
                  <l>Allow no time for mirth and drinking.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Rad.</speaker>
                  <l>Very</l>
                  <l>Strange that brother. For, they ſay themſelves are</l>
                  <l>Exceeding good fellowes.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Cow.</speaker>
                  <l>Iuſt of that ſeize.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Rad.</speaker>
                  <l>I'll tell you more what I heard ſpoken of 'em,</l>
                  <l>Brother, they 're ſowre: and never worth the truſting,</l>
                  <l>
                     <pb facs="tcp:47257:37"/>Or honeſt i' their bargaines, untill they</l>
                  <l>Be drunke, or at leaſt halfe drunke.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Cow.</speaker>
                  <l>That's as true,</l>
                  <l>Brother, as that you and I drunke halfe a ſcore</l>
                  <l>Flaggons yeſternight a peece. The North winde</l>
                  <l>Is not ſo bitter in a morning, till he</l>
                  <l>Has tooke a buttrum, or his Wine.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Rad.</speaker>
                  <l>And then,</l>
                  <l>Makes as good Muſicke, as a Bag-pipe when it's</l>
                  <l>Full blow'n. What doe you thinke of the <hi>Swedes</hi>? brother<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
                  </l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Cow.</speaker>
                  <l>They are not (yet) altogether ſo good drinkers,</l>
                  <l>As th' <hi>Germans</hi> are: but well fall'n to 't of late.</l>
                  <l>Which makes me ſuppoſe, brother, they'll be beaten</l>
                  <l>Out too. For beſides, the King will no more kiſſe</l>
                  <l>The Queene <hi>Vraca,</hi> as't is ſpoken: But ſticke</l>
                  <l>To 's owne old Camrade, being indeed the fairer.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Rad.</speaker>
                  <l>Yet, in my opinion brother: his Grace</l>
                  <l>Being marry'd to both, ſho'd doe exceeding well,</l>
                  <l>To keepe both ſtill: Sleepe betwixt both 'a' nights.</l>
                  <l>And imbrace both by turnes. What ſay you brother?</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Cow.</speaker>
                  <l>What? But to concurre with you? and for many</l>
                  <l>Good, and convincing reaſons. 's for example:</l>
                  <l>The King being kept ſo warme on both ſides, by</l>
                  <l>Two ſuch delicate cre'tures, 't were impoſſible</l>
                  <l>He ſho'd catch cold; I, or perchance be troubl'd</l>
                  <l>With Coughs, Scyaticas, or other bone-ach;</l>
                  <l>And to have <hi>Swealand</hi> and <hi>Norway</hi> at command,</l>
                  <l>Were a matter of no ſmall importance,</l>
                  <l>You conceive me, brother.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Cow.</speaker>
                  <l>Few wiſe men better,</l>
                  <l>In part. But, ſtand aſide: themſelves are comming.
<stage>Floriſh.</stage>
                  </l>
               </sp>
               <stage>Enter Reyner, Landgartha, Valdemar, Vraca, Scania, Inguar, Elſino<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ra Fatyma, Hubba and Marfiſa; the Norwegian Ladies in womans apparell, with Swords on; Marfiſa with her Gown untuck'd and ſword on.</stage>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Ing.</speaker>
                  <l>You will not (gracious Madame) thus deceive</l>
                  <l>
                     <pb facs="tcp:47257:38"/>The expectations of your poore, and loving</l>
                  <l>People: whoſe whole hopes, comfort, ſafetie (nay all</l>
                  <l>We can for the preſent, or hereafter call ours)</l>
                  <l>Are but benefits deriv'd from the fountaine</l>
                  <l>Of your warme bountie; at whoſe goodneſſe yet,</l>
                  <l>We moſt rejoyce. Doe not then (deare Empreſſe,) ſtrike</l>
                  <l>Sorrow to our lately bleeding hearts; that ſtill</l>
                  <l>Pant (and not ſlowly) by our former feares;</l>
                  <l>And the ſore ſtripes we tooke: Which, but for you,</l>
                  <l>For ever were incurable; and now</l>
                  <l>By your forſaking of us, will feſter worſe</l>
                  <l>Then before.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Land.</speaker>
                  <l>That you neede not feare, Lord <hi>Inguar.</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>For, I ſhall ne'r be wanting in my care,</l>
                  <l>And love unto this Nation. Leaving here</l>
                  <l>The beſt halfe of our Army, now behinde us;</l>
                  <l>To prevent all future miſchiefes.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Jng.</speaker>
                  <l>Our diſhonour</l>
                  <l>In your departure, we ſhall ne'r recover.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Rey.</speaker>
                  <l>My offence (which now 's my worſt affliction,</l>
                  <l>With what it does occaſion) all may ſee,</l>
                  <l>Tooke origen and iſſue, more of humane</l>
                  <l>Frayltie, and fooliſh pride: then want of love</l>
                  <l>To you; or of deſert in you, to merit</l>
                  <l>A better and more pow'rfull man then I am;</l>
                  <l>Th' worlds onely Monarch, if there were but one,</l>
                  <l>For which, I (without your mercie to reſtore me</l>
                  <l>Once more unto your heart, as to my kingdomes)</l>
                  <l>Muſt ſpend my dayes (which ſhall not then be many)</l>
                  <l>Like to a ſickely beaſt without a ſoule.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Land.</speaker>
                  <l>My heart ſhall ſtill receive you: But, on my word,</l>
                  <l>Th' reſt of my body you ſhall not enjoy, ſir,</l>
                  <l>I now am gaunt you ſee,</l>
                  <l>All though you muſt not have a feeling of it;</l>
                  <l>And if I doe play falſe, my belly will ſhow't</l>
                  <l>Queſtionleſſe: For, I am fruitfull if</l>
                  <l>I ſho'd be touch'd.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Vald.</speaker>
                  <l>Although but weakly, Madame.</l>
                  <l>
                     <pb facs="tcp:47257:39"/>On you, and this your kinde friend: but that I wav'd</l>
                  <l>Him for my husband, that deſpis'd me as</l>
                  <l>His honeſt Mate; and wo'd 'a' lov'd me for</l>
                  <l>By-blowes. Therefore, enjoy him ſtill: for, I ſuppoſe</l>
                  <l>You are a Hen, that muſt be trod.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Vrac.</speaker>
                  <l>That 's more then you know; or I hope ſhall finde.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Rey.</speaker>
                  <l>She ſhall ne'r enjoy me; nor has not</l>
                  <l>Of a long time I'll ſweare, if that will ſerve.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Land.</speaker>
                  <l>It ſhall not ſir) beleeve it. Yet, ne'r feare</l>
                  <l>You ſhall be arm'd i' th' front by me; which is</l>
                  <l>A wrong this other Lady cannot doe you,</l>
                  <l>If ſhe wo'd.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Vrac.</speaker>
                  <l>I'll leave that now for you, that have</l>
                  <l>The abler bodie.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Land.</speaker>
                  <l>And you the frayler minde.</l>
                  <l>But if you chop words with me thus, or inſult:</l>
                  <l>I may (for a farwell) cracke your birds necke,</l>
                  <l>Before we part.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Vrac.</speaker>
                  <l>I muſt not ſtand ſo neere</l>
                  <l>You then.
<stage>She ſteps behinde Reyner, and holds him betwixt Langartha and her ſelfe.</stage>
                  </l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Rey.</speaker>
                  <l>Nor I prove any ſafeguard for you.
<stage>Steps from be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>twixt them.</stage>
                  </l>
                  <l>But ſho'd take part with her, whom I love beſt;</l>
                  <l>And has beſt right unto me.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>rac.</speaker>
                  <l>That you ſay</l>
                  <l>To flatter her, and for meere feare. But if</l>
                  <l>I had you in private, I know what you</l>
                  <l>Wo'd ſing; and play too, if I ſho'd but yeeld.
<stage>Land. runs at her, and Elſinora ſteps in.</stage>
                  </l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Elſin.</speaker>
                  <l>What doe you meane?</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Land.</speaker>
                  <l>That I will ne'r have him,</l>
                  <l>That is reſolv'd.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Elſin.</speaker>
                  <l>Your reſolution</l>
                  <l>(I muſt ſay) in that, is worſe then madneſſe.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Land.</speaker>
                  <l>I'll not quarrell with you, Aunt. Yet, doe admire</l>
                  <l>A Lady of your know'n modeſtie, ſhould be</l>
                  <l>So farre miſtaken, and in ſuch a cauſe.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Elſin.</speaker>
                  <l>It's you that are miſtaken: I confeſſe.</l>
                  <l>I was at firſt an oppoſit in your love</l>
                  <l>
                     <pb facs="tcp:47257:39"/>Vnto the King: but, ſeeing you would needs</l>
                  <l>Yeeld (then) your virgin Forte unto his Higneſſe:</l>
                  <l>I now wo'd have you take what wives doe uſe;</l>
                  <l>And let me ſtill live chaſte, that doe profeſſe it.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Scan.</speaker>
                  <l>My Aunt ſayes more (to me I am ſure ſhe did:)</l>
                  <l>All ought to live according their vocation.</l>
                  <l>And not prepoſterouſly prove aliens to it.</l>
                  <l>Nor will it ſerve to ſay he tore the bond,</l>
                  <l>Now that he's ſorry for't: For, ſtill the generall good</l>
                  <l>Muſt be preferr'd to all particular</l>
                  <l>Merit; or that devotion that may</l>
                  <l>By fooliſh zeale, prove a too great offence.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Land.</speaker>
                  <l>I muſt heare more opinions, ere I part</l>
                  <l>From my ſtrong purpoſe: therefore ſir, adieu.</l>
                  <l>Be mercifull in chiefe, unto your ſubjects;</l>
                  <l>To allure their hearts, by love: that being the tye</l>
                  <l>That will hold ſtrongeſt; never can be broken,</l>
                  <l>Vnleſſe by fooles, or mad men. For, that partie</l>
                  <l>That ſho'd tend any miſchiefe, 'gainſt a good Prince:</l>
                  <l>Were firſt to kill all his ſubjects, being the Kings friends;</l>
                  <l>Or periſh himſelfe, by his fatall and bad</l>
                  <l>Purpoſe. Be juſt and vertuous, and you neede not</l>
                  <l>Feare poyſon, poynards, or conſpiracie.</l>
                  <l>To end: <hi>Norway</hi> ſhall be preſerv'd for your young ſonne;</l>
                  <l>And as for me (though yours:) I'll end my life,</l>
                  <l>An honeſt widdow, or forſaken wife:
<stage>Exit with Elſinora, Fatyma, &amp; Marfiſa</stage>
                  </l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Vald.</speaker>
                  <l>I muſt take leave too.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Rey.</speaker>
                  <l>Farewell, worthieſt Couſin.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Scan.</speaker>
                  <l>You know the way to <hi>Norway,</hi> Sir, and if</l>
                  <l>I might adviſe ſo wiſe a King to follow</l>
                  <l>Us thither, and not ſlowly: that honourable</l>
                  <l>Obligation would ſo bind your Queene</l>
                  <l>(Being ſeconded by us your friends, and reaſon)</l>
                  <l>That I beleeve what now ſhe does denie,</l>
                  <l>She wo'd then grant; eſpecially, when ſhe</l>
                  <l>Perceives you conſtant in your vow'd affection:</l>
                  <l>For this perchance ſhe do's to tempt and try you.</l>
                  <l>Nay, I am ſure ſhe do's; and that ſhe will be</l>
                  <l>
                     <pb facs="tcp:47257:40"/>Yours againe, if you perſever in your love to her,</l>
                  <l>In the meane time, I ſhall not fayle to prove,</l>
                  <l>Your grace's faithfull, loving advocate.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Rey.</speaker>
                  <l>In you the anchor of my truſt lyes only fix'd,</l>
                  <l>Deare ſiſter. I muſt follow your adviſe.
<stage>kiſſes her.</stage>
                  </l>
               </sp>
               <stage>Exit Scania &amp; Valdemar.</stage>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Rad.</speaker>
                  <l>O brother, brother: muſt we part at laſt?
<stage>They imbrace. Exeunt Cow. &amp; Radgee.</stage>
                  </l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Cow.</speaker>
                  <l>No, no: get afore; I'll ſteale along with you.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Rey.</speaker>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Inguar,</hi> Did'ſt thinke our hopes ſho'd end in this?</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Ing.</speaker>
                  <l>It may prove better; and I hope it will ſit.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Rey.</speaker>
                  <l>Accurſed <hi>Fate</hi> of man, of fooliſh man,</l>
                  <l>That cannot prize a Iewell while he has it,</l>
                  <l>Till it be loſt, and then his griefe is vaine,</l>
                  <l>Vaine and unprofitable, when no hope</l>
                  <l>Is left to finde it, which I feare's my caſe;</l>
                  <l>Our miſerie the mirror's made, by which</l>
                  <l>We onely ſee our faults, our dangerous wounds.</l>
                  <l>Which likely then can never be recur'd:</l>
                  <l>Being Gangreene filthy ſores, that doe Corrode</l>
                  <l>So farre into the very ſoule of man,</l>
                  <l>That they hale to ſad deſperation.</l>
                  <l>To which point I'm almoſt arriv'd, the Gemme</l>
                  <l>I loſt, being ſo rich, as all earths Potentates</l>
                  <l>A richer could not boaſt. Which if I finde not</l>
                  <l>(Strucke with my dyre misfortune) my owne hand</l>
                  <l>Shall ſend my ſpirit to the <hi>Stygian</hi> ſtrand.
<stage>Exit with Ing. &amp; Hub.</stage>
                  </l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Vrac.</speaker>
                  <l>And ſeeing I've walk'd aſtray, I will from hence:</l>
                  <l>By future good to expiate my offence.
<stage>Exit in the middle.</stage>
                  </l>
               </sp>
            </div>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
         <div type="epilogue">
            <pb facs="tcp:47257:40"/>
            <head>EPILOGVE.</head>
            <head type="sub">Scania (that ſpoke the Prologue) now delivers the Epilogue, apparelled as in the laſt Scene, with her Sword and Belt in her hand.</head>
            <l>THough our Author cares not, how his Play may take:</l>
            <l>Yet, cauſe he purpoſes not to forſake</l>
            <l>In his affection, any Worthy here;</l>
            <l>He hath ſent me 'fore the Court breake up, to appeare</l>
            <l>For him agen; to ſee how it hath pleas'd:</l>
            <l>For, notwithſtanding he meanes to be eas'd;</l>
            <l>For ever of th' like taske: Yet, from his heart</l>
            <l>He wiſhes, you and he ſho'd fairely part.</l>
            <l>And this he more (for him) deſir'd me ſay:</l>
            <l>Where others ſpend a yeare about a Play</l>
            <l>(Picking a ſentence here, a word from thence)</l>
            <l>This Tragie-Comedy with the expence</l>
            <l>Of leſſe then two Moneths time he pen'd: For he</l>
            <l>'s not too ambitious of the dignitie</l>
            <l>Of a prime Poet; which he needs muſt know,</l>
            <l>The Muſes chiefe (<hi>Apollo</hi>) doth beſtow</l>
            <l>But very rarely. Himſelfe he knowes too</l>
            <l>Better i' th' Art, then ſome that to be ſo</l>
            <l>Thought worthy, maligne him. If this pleaſe you,</l>
            <l>It's all he 'll aske of <hi>Hellicon:</hi> Adieu.</l>
         </div>
      </body>
      <back>
         <div type="authors_note">
            <pb facs="tcp:47257:41"/>
            <p>Some (but not of beſt judgements) were offended at the Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cluſion of this Play, in regard <hi>Landgartha</hi> tooke not then, what ſhe was perſwaded to by ſo many, the Kings kind night-imbraces. To which kind of people (that know not what they ſay) I anſwer (omitting all other reaſons:) that a Tragie-Comedy ſho'd neither end Comically or Tragically, but betwixt both: which <hi>Decorum</hi> I did my best to obſerve, not to goe againſt Art, to pleaſe the over-amorous. To the reſt of bablers, I de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpiſe any anſwer.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="license">
            <p>This Play was firſt Acted on <hi>S. Patricks</hi> day, 1639. with the allowance of the Maſter of Revels.</p>
            <pb facs="tcp:47257:41"/>
         </div>
      </back>
   </text>
</TEI>
