<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>The tragedy of Thierry, King of France, and his brother Theodoret as it was diverse times acted at the Blacke-Friers by the Kings Maiesties servants / written by John Fletcher, gent.</title>
            <author>Fletcher, John, 1579-1625.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1648</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 170 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 21 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2014-11">2014-11 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A39810</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing F1352</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R30457</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">11323591</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 11323591</idno>
            <idno type="VID">47462</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online text creation partnership.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A39810)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 47462)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 1460:40)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>The tragedy of Thierry, King of France, and his brother Theodoret as it was diverse times acted at the Blacke-Friers by the Kings Maiesties servants / written by John Fletcher, gent.</title>
                  <author>Fletcher, John, 1579-1625.</author>
                  <author>Massinger, Philip, 1583-1640.</author>
                  <author>Beaumont, Francis, 1584-1616.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[38] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed for Humphrey Mosely, and are to be sold at his shop ...,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1648.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>By Fletcher, assisted by Massinger and others. cf Dict. Nat. Biog.</note>
                  <note>Other eds. have Francis Beaumont on t.p. as joint author.</note>
                  <note>Imperfect: Pages cropped, also print showthrough, with loss of print.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in the Harvard University Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2012-11</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-12</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-04</date>
            <label>Colm MacCrossan</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-04</date>
            <label>Colm MacCrossan</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2014-03</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:47462:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:47462:1"/>
            <p>THE TRAGEDY OF THIERRY King of <hi>France,</hi> and his Brother THEODORET. As it was diverſe times acted at the <hi>Blacke-Friers hy the Kings Maieſties</hi> Servants. Written by JOHN FLETCHER Gent.</p>
            <figure>
               <figDesc>printer's device of Humphrey Mosley, featuring a fleur-de-lis seeding (c.f. McKerrow 263-272)</figDesc>
               <head>
                  <q>IN DOMINO CONFIDO</q>
               </head>
            </figure>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON,</hi> Printed for <hi>Humphrey Moſely,</hi> and are to be ſold at his Shop at the <hi>Princes Armes</hi> in St. <hi>Pauls</hi> Church-yard. 1648.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="play">
            <pb facs="tcp:47462:2" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:47462:2"/>
            <head>THE TRAGEDIE OF THIERRIE AND THEODORET.</head>
            <div n="1" type="act">
               <head>
                  <hi>Act.</hi> 1.</head>
               <div n="1" type="scene">
                  <head>
                     <hi>Scoe.</hi> 1.</head>
                  <stage>Enter <hi>Theodoret, Brunhalt, Bawdber.</hi>
                  </stage>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>BRVNHALT.</speaker>
                     <l>TAxe me with theſe hot tainters?</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Theodoret.</speaker>
                     <l>You are too ſudaine;</l>
                     <l>I doe but gently tell you what be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>comes you,</l>
                     <l>And what may bend your honor! how theſe courſes</l>
                     <l>Of looſe and lazie pleaſures; not ſuſpected</l>
                     <l>But done and knowne, your mind that grants no limit</l>
                     <l>And all your Actions followes, which looſe people</l>
                     <l>That ſee but through a miſt of circumſtance</l>
                     <l>Dare terme ambitious; all your wayes hide ſores</l>
                     <l>Opening in the end to nothing but vlcers.</l>
                     <l>Your inſtruments like theſe may call the world</l>
                     <l>And with a fearfull clamour, to examine</l>
                     <l>Why, and to what we governe. From exam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple</l>
                     <l>If not for vertues ſake yee may be honeſt:</l>
                     <l>There have been great ones, good ones, and 'tis neceſſary</l>
                     <l>Becauſe you are your ſelfe, and by your ſelfe</l>
                     <l>A ſelfe-peece from the touch of power and Iuſtice,</l>
                     <l>You ſhould command your ſelf, you may ima<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gine</l>
                     <l>Which cozens all the world, but chiefly women.</l>
                     <l>The name of greatneſſe glorifies your actions</l>
                     <l>And ſtrong power like a pent-houſe, pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſse</l>
                     <l>To ſhade you from opinion; take heed mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther,</l>
                     <l>And let us all take heede theſe moſt abuſe us</l>
                     <l>The ſinnes we doe, people behold through opticks,</l>
                     <l>Which ſhewes them ten times more than common vices,</l>
                     <l>And often multiplyes them: then what juſtice</l>
                     <l>Dare we inflict upon the weake offenders</l>
                     <l>When we are theeves our ſelves?</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Brun.</speaker>
                     <l>This is, <hi>Martell,</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>Studied and pend unto you, whoſe baſe per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon</l>
                     <l>I charge you by the love you owe a mother</l>
                     <l>And as you hope for bleſſings from her prayers,</l>
                     <l>Neither to give beliefe to, nor allowance,</l>
                     <l>Next I tell you Sir, you from whome obedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence</l>
                     <l>Is ſo farre fled, that you dare taxe a mother;</l>
                     <l>Nay further, brand her honour with your ſlanders,</l>
                     <l>And breake into the treaſures of her credit,</l>
                     <l>Your eaſineſſe is abuſed, your faith fraited</l>
                     <l>With lyes, malitious lyes, your merchant miſchiefe,</l>
                     <l>He that never knew more trade then Tales, and tumbling</l>
                     <l>Suſpitious into honeſt harts; what you or hee,</l>
                     <l>Or all the world dare lay upon my worth,</l>
                     <pb facs="tcp:47462:3" rendition="simple:additions"/>
                     <l>This for your poore opinions: I am ſhee,</l>
                     <l>And ſo will beare my ſelfe, whoſe truth and whiteneſſe</l>
                     <l>Shall ever ſtand as far from theſe detections</l>
                     <l>As you from dutie; get you better ſervants</l>
                     <l>People of honeſt actions without ends,</l>
                     <l>And whip theſe knaves away, they eate your favours,</l>
                     <l>And turne em unto poyſons: my knowne credite</l>
                     <l>Whom all the Courts a this fide <hi>Nile</hi> have envied,</l>
                     <l>And happy ſhee could fite mee, brought in queſtion</l>
                     <l>Now in my houres of age and reverence,</l>
                     <l>When rather ſuperſtition ſhould be rendred</l>
                     <l>And by a Ruſh that one dayes warmth</l>
                     <l>Hath ſhot up to this ſwelling; give me juſtice,</l>
                     <l>Which is his life.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Theod.</speaker>
                     <l>This is an impudence,</l>
                     <l>And he muſt tell you, that till now mother</l>
                     <l>Brought yee a ſonnes obedience, and now breakes it</l>
                     <l>Above the ſufferance of a ſonne.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Bawd.</speaker>
                     <l>Bleſſe us?</l>
                     <l>For I doe now begin to feele my ſelfe</l>
                     <l>Turning into a halter, and the ladder</l>
                     <l>Turning from me, one pulling at my legs too.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Theod.</speaker>
                     <l>Theſe truths are no mans tales, but all mens troubles,</l>
                     <l>They are, though your ſtrange greatneſſe would out ſtare v'm:</l>
                     <l>Witneſſe the daily Libels, almoſt Ballads</l>
                     <l>In every place, almoſt in every Province,</l>
                     <l>Are made upon your luſt, Taverne diſcour<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes,</l>
                     <l>Crowds cram'd with whiſpers; Nay, the holy Temples,</l>
                     <l>Are not without your curſes: Now you would bluſh,</l>
                     <l>But your blacke tainted blood dare not ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peare</l>
                     <l>For feare I ſhould fright that too.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Brun.</speaker>
                     <l>O ye gods!</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Theod.</speaker>
                     <l>Do not abuſe their names: they ſee your actions,</l>
                     <l>And your conceald ſinnes, though you work like Moles,</l>
                     <l>Lyes levell to their juſtice.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Brun.</speaker>
                     <l>Art thou a ſonne?</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Theod.</speaker>
                     <l>The more my ſhame is of ſo bad a mother,</l>
                     <l>And more your wretchedneſſe you let me be ſo;</l>
                     <l>But woman, for a mothers name hath left me</l>
                     <l>Since you have left your honour; mend theſe ruines,</l>
                     <l>And build againe that broken fame, and fairely;</l>
                     <l>Your moſt intemperate fires have burnt, and quickly</l>
                     <l>Within theſe ten dayes take a Monaſterie,</l>
                     <l>A moſt ſtrickt houſe, a houſe where none may whiſper,</l>
                     <l>Where no more light is knowne but what may make yee</l>
                     <l>Beleeve there is a day where no hope dwels,</l>
                     <l>Nor comfort but in teares.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Brun.</speaker>
                     <l>O miſerie!</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Theod.</speaker>
                     <l>And there to cold repentance, and ſtarv'd penance</l>
                     <l>Tye your ſucceeding dayes; or curſe me heaven</l>
                     <l>If all your guilded knaves, brokers, and bed<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders.</l>
                     <l>Even he you built from nothing, ſtrong <hi>Portalyde,</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>Be not made ambling Geldings; all your maydes,</l>
                     <l>If that name doe not ſhame vm, fed with ſpunges</l>
                     <l>To ſucke away their ranckneſſe; and your ſelfe</l>
                     <l>Onely to empty Pictures and dead Arras</l>
                     <l>Offer your old deſires.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Brun.</speaker>
                     <l>I will not curſe you,</l>
                     <l>Nor lay a propheſie upon your pride,</l>
                     <l>Though heaven might grant me both: un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thankfull, no,</l>
                     <l>I nouriſh'd yee, 'twas I, poore I groand for you,</l>
                     <l>'Twas I felt what you ſufferd, I lamented</l>
                     <l>When ſickneſſe or ſad houres held backe your ſwetneſſe;</l>
                     <l>Twas I payd for your ſleepes, I watch your wakings:</l>
                     <l>My daily cares and feares, that rid, plaid, walkt,</l>
                     <l>Diſcourſd, diſcoverd, fed and faſhioned you</l>
                     <l>To what you are, and am I thus rewarded,</l>
                  </sp>
                  <pb facs="tcp:47462:3" rendition="simple:additions"/>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Theod.</speaker>
                     <l>But that I know theſe teares I could dote on em,</l>
                     <l>And kneele to catch vm as they fall, then knit vm</l>
                     <l>Into an Armlet, ever to be honourd;</l>
                     <l>But woman they are dangerous drops, de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceitfull,</l>
                     <l>Full of the weeper, anger and ill nature.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Brun.</speaker>
                     <l>In my laſt houres deſpiſd.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Theod.</speaker>
                     <l>That Text ſhould tell,</l>
                     <l>How ugly it becomes you to erre thus;</l>
                     <l>Your flames are ſpent, nothing but ſmoake maintaines ye;</l>
                     <l>And thoſe your favour and your bounty ſuffers</l>
                     <l>Lye not with you, they do but lay luſt on you,</l>
                     <l>And then imbrace you as they caught a pal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſie;</l>
                     <l>Your power they may love, and like ſpaniſh Iennetts</l>
                     <l>Commit with ſuch a guſt.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Bawd.</speaker>
                     <l>I would take whipping,</l>
                     <l>And pay a fine now.
<stage>Exit Bawdber</stage>
                     </l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Theod.</speaker>
                     <l>But were yee once diſgraced,</l>
                     <l>Or fallen in wealth, like leaves they would flie from you,</l>
                     <l>And become browſe for every beaſt; you will'd me</l>
                     <l>To ſtocke my ſelfe with better friends, and ſervants</l>
                     <l>With what face dare you ſee mee, or any mankind,</l>
                     <l>That keepe a race of ſuch unheard of re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>licks,</l>
                     <l>Bawds, Leachers; Letches, femall fornicati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons,</l>
                     <l>And children in their rudiments to vices,</l>
                     <l>Old men to ſhew examples: and leſt Art</l>
                     <l>Should looſe her ſelfe in act, to call backe cuſtome,</l>
                     <l>Leave theſe, and live like <hi>Niobe.</hi> I told you how</l>
                     <l>And when your eyes have dropt away re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>membrance</l>
                     <l>Of what you were. I am your ſonne! per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forme it.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Brun.</speaker>
                     <l>Am I a woman, and no more power in me,</l>
                     <l>To tye this Tyger up, a ſoule to no end,</l>
                     <l>Have I got ſhame and loſt my will; <hi>Brun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>halt</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>From this accurſed houre, forget thou bor'ſt him,</l>
                     <l>Or any part of thy blood gave him living,</l>
                     <l>Let him be to thee an Antipathy,</l>
                     <l>A thing thy nature ſweates at, and turnes backward:</l>
                     <l>Throw all the miſchiefes on him that thy ſelf,</l>
                     <l>Or women worſe than thou art, have in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vented,</l>
                     <l>And kill him drunke, or doubtfull.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <stage>Enter Bawdber, Protaldie, Lecure.</stage>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Bawd.</speaker>
                     <l>Such a ſweat,</l>
                     <l>I never was in yet, clipt of my minſtrels;</l>
                     <l>My toyes to prick up wenches withall; up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hold me,</l>
                     <l>It runnes like ſnowballs through me.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Brun.</speaker>
                     <l>Now my varlets,</l>
                     <l>My ſlaves, my running thoughts, my execu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Baw.</speaker>
                     <l>Lord how ſhee lookes!</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Brun.</speaker>
                     <l>Hell take yee all.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Baw.</speaker>
                     <l>We ſhall be gelt.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Brun.</speaker>
                     <l>Your Miſtreſſe,</l>
                     <l>Your old and honord Miſtreſſe, you tyr'd curtals</l>
                     <l>Suffers for your baſe ſinnes; I muſt bee cloyſter'd,</l>
                     <l>Mew'd up to make mee vertuous who can helpe this,</l>
                     <l>Now you ſtand ſtill like Statues; Come <hi>Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taldye,</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>One kiſſe before I periſh, kiſſe me ſtrongly</l>
                     <l>Another, and a third.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Lecure.</speaker>
                     <l>I feare not gelding</l>
                     <l>As long as ſhee holds this way.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Brun.</speaker>
                     <l>The young courſer,</l>
                     <l>That unlickt lumpe of mine, will winne thy Miſtris;</l>
                     <l>Muſt I bee chaſt <hi>Protaldye?</hi>
                     </l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Fro.</speaker>
                     <l>Thus and thus Lady:</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Brun.</speaker>
                     <l>It ſhall bee ſo, let him ſeeke fooles for Veſtalls,</l>
                     <l>Here is my Cloyſter.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Lecure.</speaker>
                     <l>But what ſafety Madam</l>
                     <l>Find you in ſtaying here?</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Brun.</speaker>
                     <l>Thou haſt hit my meaning,</l>
                     <l>I will to <hi>Thierry</hi> ſonne of my bleſſings,</l>
                     <l>And there complnine mee, tell my tale ſo ſubtilly,</l>
                     <l>That the cold ſtones ſhall ſweat; and Statues mourne,</l>
                     <l>And thou ſhalt weepe <hi>Protaldye</hi> in my wit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe,</l>
                     <pb facs="tcp:47462:4" rendition="simple:additions"/>
                     <l>And there forſweare.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Bawd.</speaker>
                     <l>Yes, any thing but gelding,</l>
                     <l>I am not yet in quiet Noble Lady,</l>
                     <l>Let it bee done to night, for without doubt</l>
                     <l>To morrow we are capons.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Brun.</speaker>
                     <l>Sleepe ſhall not ſeize me,</l>
                     <l>Nor any food befriend me but thy kiſſes.</l>
                     <l>E're I forſake this deſart, I live honeſt;</l>
                     <l>He may as well bid dead men walke, I hum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bled,</l>
                     <l>Or bent below my power? let night-dogs teare me,</l>
                     <l>And goblins ride me in my ſleep to jelly,</l>
                     <l>Ere I forſake my ſpheare.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Lecure.</speaker>
                     <l>This place you will.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Brun.</speaker>
                     <l>What's that to you, or any,</l>
                     <l>Yee doſſe, you powder'd pigsbones, rubarbe gliſter:</l>
                     <l>Muſt you know my deſignes, a colledge on you,</l>
                     <l>The proverbe makes but fools.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Prota.</speaker>
                     <l>But Noble Lady.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Brun.</speaker>
                     <l>You a ſawcie aſſe too, off I will not,</l>
                     <l>If you but anger me, tell a ſow-gelder</l>
                     <l>Have cut you all like colts, hold mee and kiſſe me,</l>
                     <l>For I am too much troubled; make up my treaſure,</l>
                     <l>And get me horſes private, come about it.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <stage>Exeunt.</stage>
               </div>
               <div n="2" type="scene">
                  <head>
                     <hi>Act.</hi> 1. <hi>Scoe.</hi> 2.</head>
                  <stage>Enter Theodoret, Martell. &amp;c.</stage>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Theod.</speaker>
                     <l>Though I aſſure my ſelf
<stage>(Martell)</stage> your counſell</l>
                     <l>Had no end but allegeance and my honour:</l>
                     <l>Yet I am jealous, I have paſs'd the bounds</l>
                     <l>Of a ſons duty; for ſuppoſe her worſe</l>
                     <l>Then you report, not by bare circumſtance,</l>
                     <l>But evident proofe confirm'd ha's given her out:</l>
                     <l>Yet ſince all weakneſſes in a kingdome, are</l>
                     <l>No more to be ſeverely puniſhed than</l>
                     <l>The faults of Kings are by the Thunderer</l>
                     <l>As oft as they offend, to be reveng'd:</l>
                     <l>If not for piety, yet for policie,</l>
                     <l>Since ſome are of neceſſitie to be ſpar'd,</l>
                     <l>I might, and now I wiſh I had not look'd</l>
                     <l>With ſuch ſtrict eyes into her follies.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Mart.</speaker>
                     <l>Sir, a duty well diſcharg'd is never follow'd</l>
                     <l>By ſad repentance, nor did your Highneſſe ever</l>
                     <l>Make payment of the debt you ow'd her, better</l>
                     <l>Than in your late reproofes not of her, but</l>
                     <l>Thoſe crimes that made her worthy of re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proofe.</l>
                     <l>The moſt remarkeable point in which Kings differ</l>
                     <l>From private men, is that they not alone</l>
                     <l>Stand bound to be in themſelves innocent,</l>
                     <l>But that all ſuch as are allyde to them</l>
                     <l>In neerneſſe, or dependance, by their care</l>
                     <l>Should be free from ſuſpition of all crime;</l>
                     <l>And you have reap'd a double benefit</l>
                     <l>From this laſt great act: firſt in the reſtraint</l>
                     <l>Of her loſt pleaſures, you remove th'example</l>
                     <l>From others of the like licentiouſneſſe,</l>
                     <l>Then when 'tis known that your ſeveritie</l>
                     <l>Extended to your mother, who dares hope for</l>
                     <l>The leaſt indulgence or connivence in</l>
                     <l>The eaſieſt ſlips that may prove dangerous</l>
                     <l>To you or to the Kingdome?</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Theod.</speaker>
                     <l>I muſt grant</l>
                     <l>Your reaſons good
<stage>(Martell)</stage> if as ſhe is</l>
                     <l>My mother, ſhe had been my ſubject, or</l>
                     <l>That only here ſhe could make challenge to</l>
                     <l>A place of being; but I know her temper</l>
                     <l>And feare (if ſuch a word become a King,)</l>
                     <l>That in diſcovering her, I have let looſe</l>
                     <l>A Tygres, whoſe rage being ſhut up in darkneſſe,</l>
                     <l>Was grievous onely to her ſelfe; which brought</l>
                     <l>Into the view of light, her cruelty,</l>
                     <l>Provok'd by her owne ſhame, will turne on him</l>
                     <l>That fooliſhly preſum'd to let her ſee</l>
                     <l>The loath'd ſhape of her owne deformitie.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Mart.</speaker>
                     <l>Beaſts of that nature, when rebellili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous threats</l>
                     <l>Begin to appeare only in their eyes,</l>
                     <l>Or any motion that may give ſuſpition</l>
                     <l>Of the leaſt violence ſhould be chaind up;</l>
                     <l>Their fangs and teeth, and all their meanes of hurt,</l>
                     <l>Par'd off, and knockt out, and ſo made unable</l>
                     <l>To do ill; they would ſoon begin to loath it.</l>
                     <pb facs="tcp:47462:4" rendition="simple:additions"/>
                     <l>I'le apply nothing, but had your Grace done,</l>
                     <l>Or would doe yet, what your leſſe forward zeale</l>
                     <l>In words did onely threaten, far leſſe danger</l>
                     <l>Would grow from acting it on her, then may</l>
                     <l>Perhaps have being from her apprehenſion</l>
                     <l>Of what may once bee practiſ'd: for be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leeve it,</l>
                     <l>Who confident of his own power, preſumes</l>
                     <l>To ſpend threats on an enemy, that hath meanes</l>
                     <l>To ſhun the worſt they can effect, gives armor</l>
                     <l>To keepe off his owne ſtrength; nay more, diſarmes</l>
                     <l>Himſelfe, and lyes unguarded 'gainſt all harmes,</l>
                     <l>Or doubt, or malice may produce.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Theod.</speaker>
                     <l>'Tis true.</l>
                     <l>And ſuch a deſperate cure I would have us'd,</l>
                     <l>If the intemperate patient had not been</l>
                     <l>So neer me as a mother; but to her,</l>
                     <l>And from me gentle unguents only were</l>
                     <l>To be appli'd: and as phyſicians</l>
                     <l>When they are ſick of feavers, eate them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves</l>
                     <l>Such viands as by their directions are</l>
                     <l>Forbid to others though alike diſeas'd;</l>
                     <l>So ſhee conſidering what ſhee is, may chal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lenge</l>
                     <l>Thoſe cordialls to reſtore her, by her birth,</l>
                     <l>And priviledge, which at no ſuit muſt be</l>
                     <l>Granted to others.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Mart.</speaker>
                     <l>May your pious care</l>
                     <l>Effect but what it aimd at, I am ſilent.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <stage>Enter Devitty.</stage>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Theod.</speaker>
                     <l>What laught you at Sir?</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Vitry.</speaker>
                     <l>I have ſome occaſion,</l>
                     <l>I ſhould not elſe; and the ſame cauſe per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>haps</l>
                     <l>That makes me do ſo, may beget in you</l>
                     <l>A contrary effect.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Theod.</speaker>
                     <l>Why, what's the matter?</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Vitry.</speaker>
                     <l>I ſee and joy to ſee that ſometimes poore men,</l>
                     <l>(And moſt of them are good) ſtand more indebted</l>
                     <l>For meanes to breathe to ſuch as are held vitious,</l>
                     <l>Than thoſe that weare like Hypocrites on their foreheads,</l>
                     <l>Th'ambitious titles of juſt men and ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuous.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Mart.</speaker>
                     <l>Speake to the purpoſe.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Vitry.</speaker>
                     <l>Who would e'rehave thought</l>
                     <l>The good old Queene, your Highneſſe reve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rend mother,</l>
                     <l>Into whoſe houſe (which was an Academ,)</l>
                     <l>In which all principles of luſt were pra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctis'd:</l>
                     <l>No ſouldier might preſume to ſet his foot;</l>
                     <l>At whoſe moſt bleſſed interceſſion</l>
                     <l>All offices in the ſtate, were charitably</l>
                     <l>Confer'd on Panders, o're-worne chamber wreſtlers,</l>
                     <l>And ſuch phyſicians as knew how to kill</l>
                     <l>With ſafety under the pretence of ſaving,</l>
                     <l>And ſuch like children of a monſtrous peace,</l>
                     <l>That ſhe I y ſhould at the length provid</l>
                     <l>That men of warre, and honeſt younger brothers,</l>
                     <l>That would not owe their feeding to their cod-peece,</l>
                     <l>Should be eſteem'd of more than mothers or drones,</l>
                     <l>Or idle vagabonds.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Theod.</speaker>
                     <l>I am glad to heare it,</l>
                     <l>Prethee what courſe takes ſhee to doe this?</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Vitry.</speaker>
                     <l>One that cannot faile, ſhee and vertuous traine,</l>
                     <l>With her jewels, and all that was worthy the carrying,</l>
                     <l>The laſt night left the court, and as 'tis more</l>
                     <l>Then ſaid, for 'tis confirm'd by ſuch as met her.</l>
                     <l>She's fled unto your brother.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Theod.</speaker>
                     <l>How?</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Vitry.</speaker>
                     <l>Nay ſtorme not,</l>
                     <l>For if that wicked tongue of hers hath not</l>
                     <l>Forgot its pace, and <hi>Thierry</hi> be a Prince</l>
                     <l>Of ſuch a fiery temper, as report</l>
                     <l>Has given him out for; you ſhall have cauſe to uſe</l>
                     <l>Such poore men as my ſelfe; and thanke us too</l>
                     <l>For comming to you, and without petitions;</l>
                     <l>Pray heaven reward the good old woman for't.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Mirt.</speaker>
                     <l>I foreſaw this.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Theod.</speaker>
                     <l>I heare a tempeſt comming,</l>
                     <l>That ſings mine &amp; my kingdomes ruine, haſt,</l>
                     <pb facs="tcp:47462:5" rendition="simple:additions"/>
                     <l>And cauſe a troope of horſe to fetch her back:</l>
                     <l>Yet ſtay, why ſhould I uſe meanes to bring in</l>
                     <l>A plague that of her ſelfe hath left me? Muſter</l>
                     <l>Our Souldiers up, we'ele ſtand upon our gard,</l>
                     <l>For we ſhall be attempted; yet forbeare</l>
                     <l>The inequality of our powers will yeeld me</l>
                     <l>Nothing but loſſe in their defeature: ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing</l>
                     <l>Muſt be done, and done ſuddainly, ſave your labor,</l>
                     <l>In this i'le uſe no counſell but mine owne,</l>
                     <l>That courſe though dangerous is beſt. Command</l>
                     <l>Our daughter be in readineſſe, to attend us:</l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Martell,</hi> your company, and honoſt <hi>Vitry,</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>Thou wilt along with me.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Virty.</speaker>
                     <l>Yes any where,</l>
                     <l>To be worſe then I am here, is paſt my feare.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <stage>Exeunt</stage>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div n="2" type="act">
               <head>
                  <hi>Act.</hi> 2.</head>
               <div n="1" type="scene">
                  <head>
                     <hi>Scoe.</hi> 1.</head>
                  <stage>Enter Thierry, Brunhalt, Bawdber, Lecure, &amp;c.</stage>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Thier.</speaker>
                     <l>You are here in a ſanctuary; and that viper</l>
                     <l>(Who ſince he hath forgot to be a ſonne,</l>
                     <l>I much diſdaine to thinke of as a brother)</l>
                     <l>Had better in deſpight of all the gods,</l>
                     <l>To have raized their Temples, and ſpurn'd downe their altars,</l>
                     <l>Then in his impious abuſe of you,</l>
                     <l>To have called on my juſt anger.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Brun.</speaker>
                     <l>Princely ſonne;</l>
                     <l>And in this worthy of a neere name,</l>
                     <l>I have in the relation of my wrongs</l>
                     <l>Been modeſt, and no word my tongue de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>livered</l>
                     <l>I expreſſe my inſupportable injuries,</l>
                     <l>But gave my heart a wound: nor has my grief</l>
                     <l>Being from what I ſuffer; but that he</l>
                     <l>Degenerate as he is, ſhould be the actor</l>
                     <l>Of my extreames; and force me to devide</l>
                     <l>The fiers of brotherly affection,</l>
                     <l>Which ſhould make but one flame.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Thier.</speaker>
                     <l>That part of his</l>
                     <l>As it deſerves ſhall burne no more, if or</l>
                     <l>The teares of Orphans, widdows, or all ſuch</l>
                     <l>As dare acknowledge him to be their Lord,</l>
                     <l>Ioyned to your wrongs, with his heart blood have powre</l>
                     <l>To put it out: and you, and theſe your ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vants,</l>
                     <l>Who in our favours ſhal finde cauſe to know</l>
                     <l>In that they left not you, how deere we hold them;</l>
                     <l>Shall give <hi>Theodoret</hi> to underſtand,</l>
                     <l>His ignorance of the prizeleſſe Iewel, which</l>
                     <l>He did poſſeſſe in you, mother in you,</l>
                     <l>Of which I am more proud to be the doner,</l>
                     <l>Then if the abſolute rule of all the world</l>
                     <l>Were offer'd to this hand; once more you are welcome,</l>
                     <l>Which with all ceremony due to greatneſſe</l>
                     <l>I would make knowne, but that our juſt re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venge</l>
                     <l>Admits not of delay; your hand Lord Gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <stage>Enter Protaldie, with ſouldiers.</stage>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Brun.</speaker>
                     <l>Your favour and his merit I may ſay</l>
                     <l>Have made him ſuch but I am jelious how</l>
                     <l>Your ſubjects will receive it.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Thier.</speaker>
                     <l>How my ſubjects?</l>
                     <l>What doe you make of me? Oh heaven! my ſubjects!</l>
                     <l>How baſe ſhould I eſteeme the name of Prince</l>
                     <l>If that poore duſt, were any thing before</l>
                     <l>The whirlewinde of my abſolute command?</l>
                     <l>Let them be happy and reſt ſo contented?</l>
                     <l>They pay the tribute of their harts &amp; knees,</l>
                     <l>To ſuch a Prince that not alone has power,</l>
                     <l>To keepe his owne but to increaſe it; that</l>
                     <l>Although he hath a body may adde too</l>
                     <l>The fam'd night labour of ſtrong <hi>Hercules:</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>Yet is the maſter of a continence</l>
                     <l>That ſo can temper it, that I forbeare</l>
                     <l>Their daughters, and their wives, whoſe hands though ſtrong,</l>
                     <l>As yet have never drawne by unjuſt meane</l>
                     <l>Their proper wealth into my treaſury,</l>
                     <l>But I grow glorious, and let them beware</l>
                     <l>That in their leaſt repining at my pleaſures,</l>
                     <l>They change not a milde Prince, (for if pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vok'd</l>
                     <l>I dare and will be ſo) into a Tyrant.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Brun.</speaker>
                     <l>You ſee there's hope that we ſhall rule againe,</l>
                     <l>And your falne fortunes riſe.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <pb facs="tcp:47462:5" rendition="simple:additions"/>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Bawdb.</speaker>
                     <l>I hope your Highneſſe</l>
                     <l>Is pleas'd that I ſhould ſtill hold my place with you</l>
                     <l>For I have been ſo long us'd to provide you</l>
                     <l>Freſh bits of fleſh ſince mine grew ſtale, that ſurely</l>
                     <l>If caſhir'd now, I ſhall prove a bad Cator</l>
                     <l>In the Fiſh-market of cold chaſtity,</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Lecure.</speaker>
                     <l>For me I am your owne, nor ſince I firſt</l>
                     <l>Knew what it was to ſerve you, have remem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bred</l>
                     <l>I had a ſoule, but ſuch a one whoſe eſſence</l>
                     <l>Depended wholy on your Highneſſe plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure,</l>
                     <l>And therefore Madam—</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Brun.</speaker>
                     <l>Reſt aſſur'd you are,</l>
                     <l>Such inſtruments we muſt not loſe.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Lecure-Bawdb.</speaker>
                     <l>Our ſervice.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Thier.</speaker>
                     <l>You have view'd them then, what's your opinion of them?</l>
                     <l>In this dull time of peace, we have pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>par'd them</l>
                     <l>Apt for the war. Ha?</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Prota</speaker>
                     <l>Sir, they have limbes</l>
                     <l>That promiſe ſtrength ſufficient, and rich armors</l>
                     <l>The Souldiers beſt lov'd wealth: more it ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peares</l>
                     <l>They have beene drill'd, nay very prettily drill'd</l>
                     <l>For many of them can diſcharge their muſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kets</l>
                     <l>Without the danger of throwing off their heads,</l>
                     <l>Or being offenſive to the ſtanders by,</l>
                     <l>By ſweating too much backwards; nay I finde</l>
                     <l>They know the right, and left hand file, and may</l>
                     <l>With ſome impulſion no doubt be brought</l>
                     <l>To paſſe the <hi>A, B, C,</hi> of war, and come</l>
                     <l>Vnto the Horne-booke.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Thier.</speaker>
                     <l>Well, that care is yours;</l>
                     <l>And ſee that you effect it.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Prota.</speaker>
                     <l>I am ſlow</l>
                     <l>To promiſe much; but if within ten dayes,</l>
                     <l>By precepts and examples, not drawne from</l>
                     <l>Worme eaten preſidents of the <hi>Roman</hi> wars</l>
                     <l>But from mine owne, I make them not tran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcend</l>
                     <l>All that e're yet bore armes, let it be ſaid,</l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Protaldye</hi> bragges, which would be unto me</l>
                     <l>As hatefull as to be eſtem'd a coward:</l>
                     <l>For Sir, few Captaines know the way to win him,</l>
                     <l>And make the ſouldiers valiant. You ſhall ſeeme</l>
                     <l>Lie with them in their trenches, talke, and drinke,</l>
                     <l>And be together drunke; and what ſeemes ſtranger,</l>
                     <l>We'le ſometimes wench together, which once practiſ'd</l>
                     <l>And with ſome other care and hidden acts,</l>
                     <l>They being al made mine, i'le breath into the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                     </l>
                     <l>Such feareleſſe reſolution and ſuch fervor,</l>
                     <l>That though I brought them to beſeege a fort,</l>
                     <l>Whoſe walls were ſteeple high, and cannon proofe,</l>
                     <l>Not to be undermind, they ſhould fly up,</l>
                     <l>Like ſwallowes, and the parapet once wonne;</l>
                     <l>For proofe of their obedience, if I willed them</l>
                     <l>They ſhould leape downe againe and what is more,</l>
                     <l>By ſome directions they ſhould have from me,</l>
                     <l>Not breake their neckes.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Thi.</speaker>
                     <l>This is above beleefe.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Brun.</speaker>
                     <l>Sir, on my knowledge though he hath ſpoke much,</l>
                     <l>He's able to do more.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Lecure.</speaker>
                     <l>She meanes on her.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Brun.</speaker>
                     <l>And howſoever in his thankfulneſſe,</l>
                     <l>For ſome few favors done him by my ſelfe,</l>
                     <l>He left <hi>Auſtracia,</hi> not <hi>Theodoret,</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>Though he was chiefely aim'd at, could have laid</l>
                     <l>Withall his Dukedomes power, that ſhame upon him,</l>
                     <l>Which in his barbarous malice to my honor,</l>
                     <l>He ſwore with threats to effect.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Thier.</speaker>
                     <l>I cannot but</l>
                     <l>Beleeve you Madam, thou art one degree</l>
                     <l>Growne neerer to my hart, and I am proud</l>
                     <l>To have in thee ſo glorious a plant</l>
                     <l>Tranſported hither; in thy conduct, we</l>
                     <l>Go on aſſur'd of conqueſt our remove</l>
                     <l>Shall be with the next ſunne.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <stage>Enter Theoderet, Memberge, Martell, Devitry.</stage>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Lecure.</speaker>
                     <l>Amazement leave me, 'tis hee.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Bawdb.</speaker>
                     <l>We are againe undone.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Prot.</speaker>
                     <l>Our guilt hath no aſſurance nor defence.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <pb facs="tcp:47462:6" rendition="simple:additions"/>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Bawdb.</speaker>
                     <l>If now your ever ready wit faile to protect us,</l>
                     <l>We ſhall be all diſcoverde</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Brun.</speaker>
                     <l>Be not ſo</l>
                     <l>In your amazement and your fooliſh feares,</l>
                     <l>I am prepared for't.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Theod.</speaker>
                     <l>How? Not one poore welcome,</l>
                     <l>In anſwer of ſo long a jorney made</l>
                     <l>Onely to ſee your brother.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Thier.</speaker>
                     <l>I have ſtood</l>
                     <l>Silent thus long, and am yet unreſolu'd</l>
                     <l>Whether to entertaine thee on my ſword,</l>
                     <l>As fits a parricide of a mothers honor;</l>
                     <l>Or whether being a Prince, I yet ſtand bound</l>
                     <l>(Though thou art here condemn'd) to give thee hearing</l>
                     <l>Before I axecute. What fooliſh hope,</l>
                     <l>(Nay pray you forbeare) or deſperate mad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe rather,</l>
                     <l>(Vnleſſe thou comeſt aſſurde, I ſtand in debt</l>
                     <l>As far to all impiety as thy ſelfe)</l>
                     <l>Has made thee bring thy neck unto the axe?</l>
                     <l>Since looking onely here, it cannot but</l>
                     <l>Draw freſh blood from thy ſear'd up con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcience,</l>
                     <l>To make thee ſencible of that horror, which</l>
                     <l>They ever beare about them, that like <hi>Nero,</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>Like ſaid I? thou are worſe: ſince thou dareſt ſtrive</l>
                     <l>In her defame to murther thine alive.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Theod.</speaker>
                     <l>That ſhe that long ſince had the boldnes to</l>
                     <l>Be a bad woman, (though I wiſh ſome other</l>
                     <l>Should ſo report her) could not want the cunning,</l>
                     <l>(Since they go hand in hand) to lay faire co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lours</l>
                     <l>On her blacke crimes, I was reſolu'd before,</l>
                     <l>Nor make I doubt but that ſhee hath impoyſon'd</l>
                     <l>Your good opinion of me, and ſo far</l>
                     <l>Incens'd your rage againſt me, that too late</l>
                     <l>I come to plead my innocence.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Brun.</speaker>
                     <l>To excuſe thy impious ſcandalls rather.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Prot.</speaker>
                     <l>Rather forc'd with feare to be compel'd to come.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Thierry</speaker>
                     <l>Forbeare.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Theod.</speaker>
                     <l>This moves not mee, and yet had I not beene</l>
                     <l>Tranſported on my owne integrity,</l>
                     <l>I neither am ſo odious to my ſubjects,</l>
                     <l>Nor yet ſo barren of defence, but that</l>
                     <l>By force I could have juſtified my guilt,</l>
                     <l>Had I been faulty, but ſince innocence</l>
                     <l>Is to it ſelfe an hundred thouſand gardes,</l>
                     <l>And that there is no ſonne, but though he owe</l>
                     <l>That name to an ill mother, but ſtands bound</l>
                     <l>Rather to take away with his owne danger</l>
                     <l>From the number of her faults, then for his owne</l>
                     <l>Security, to adde unto them This,</l>
                     <l>This hath made me to prevent th'expence</l>
                     <l>Of bloud on both ſides, the injuries, the rapes,</l>
                     <l>(Pages, that ever waite upon the war:)</l>
                     <l>The accompt of all which, ſince you are the cauſe,</l>
                     <l>Believe it, would have been required from you;</l>
                     <l>Rather I ſay to offer up my daughter,</l>
                     <l>Who living onely could revenge my death,</l>
                     <l>With my hart blood a ſacrifice to your anger</l>
                     <l>Then that you ſhould draw on your head more curſes</l>
                     <l>Then yet you have deſerved.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Thier.</speaker>
                     <l>I do begin</l>
                     <l>To feele an alteration in my nature,</l>
                     <l>And in his full ſail'd confidence, a ſhowre</l>
                     <l>Of gentle raine, that falling on the fire</l>
                     <l>Of my hot rage hath quenched it, ha! I would</l>
                     <l>Once more ſpeake roughly to him, and I will</l>
                     <l>Yet there is ſome thing whiſpers to me, that</l>
                     <l>I have ſaid too much. How is my heart de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vided</l>
                     <l>Betweene the duty of a ſonne, and love</l>
                     <l>Due to a brother! yet I am ſwayed heere,</l>
                     <l>And muſt aske of you, how tis poſſible</l>
                     <l>You can effect me that have learned to hate,</l>
                     <l>Where you ſhould pay all love?</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Theod.</speaker>
                     <l>Which joynde with duty,</l>
                     <l>Vpon my knees I ſhould be proud to tender,</l>
                     <l>Had ſhe not us'd her ſelfe ſo many ſwords</l>
                     <l>To cut thoſe bonds that title me to it.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Thier.</speaker>
                     <l>Fie no more of that.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Theod.</speaker>
                     <l>Alas it is a theame,</l>
                     <l>I take no pleaſure to diſcourſe of; would</l>
                     <l>It could aſſoone be buried to the world,</l>
                     <l>As it ſhould die to me: nay more, I wiſh</l>
                     <l>(Next to my part of heaven) that ſhee would ſpend</l>
                     <pb facs="tcp:47462:6" rendition="simple:additions"/>
                     <l>The laſt part of her life ſo here, that all</l>
                     <l>Indifferent Judges might condemne me, for</l>
                     <l>A moſt malicious ſlanderer, nay texde it</l>
                     <l>Vpon my forehead, if you hate me mother,</l>
                     <l>Put me to ſuch a ſhame, pray you do, believe it</l>
                     <l>There is no glory that may fall upon me,</l>
                     <l>Can equall the delight I ſhould receive</l>
                     <l>In that diſgrace; provided the repeale</l>
                     <l>Of your long baniſh'd vertues, and good name,</l>
                     <l>Vſher'd me to it.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Thier.</speaker>
                     <l>See, ſhe ſhewes her ſelfe</l>
                     <l>An eaſie mother, which her teares confirme.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Theod.</speaker>
                     <l>Tis a good ſigne, the comfortableſt raine</l>
                     <l>I ever ſaw.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Thier.</speaker>
                     <l>Embrace: why this is well,</l>
                     <l>May never more but love in you, and duty</l>
                     <l>On your part riſe between you.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Baudb.</speaker>
                     <l>Do you heare Lord Generall,</l>
                     <l>Does not your new ſtamped honor on the ſuddaine</l>
                     <l>Begin to grow ſicke?</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Prota.</speaker>
                     <l>Yes J finde it fit,</l>
                     <l>That putting off my armor J ſhould think of</l>
                     <l>Some honeſt hoſpitall to retire to.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Bawdb.</speaker>
                     <l>Sure although J am a bawd, yet being a Lord.</l>
                     <l>They cannot whip me for't, what's your o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pinion?</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Lecure.</speaker>
                     <l>The beadle will reſolve you, for J cannot,</l>
                     <l>There is ſomething that more neer concerns my ſelfe,</l>
                     <l>That calls upon me.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Mart.</speaker>
                     <l>Note but yonder ſcarabes,</l>
                     <l>That liude upon the dunge of her baſe plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſures,</l>
                     <l>How from the feare that ſhe may yet prove honeſt</l>
                     <l>Hange downe their wicked heads.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Vitry.</speaker>
                     <l>What is that to me?</l>
                     <l>Though they and all the polcats of the Court,</l>
                     <l>Were truſt together, I perceive not how</l>
                     <l>Jt can advantage me a cardekue,</l>
                     <l>To helpe to keepe me honoſt.
<stage>A horne.</stage>
                     </l>
                  </sp>
                  <stage>Enter a Poſt.</stage>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Thier.</speaker>
                     <l>How, from whence?</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Poſt.</speaker>
                     <l>Theſe letters will reſolve your grace.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Thier.</speaker>
                     <l>What ſpeake they?
<stage>Reades:</stage>
                     </l>
                     <l>How all things meete to make me this day hppy?</l>
                     <l>See mother, brother, to your reconcilement</l>
                     <l>Another bleſſing almoſt equall to it,</l>
                     <l>Js comming towards me; my contracted wife</l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Ordella</hi> daughter of wife <hi>Dataricke</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>The King of <hi>Aragon</hi> is on our confines;</l>
                     <l>Then to arrive at ſuch a time, when you</l>
                     <l>Are happily here to honor with your pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſence</l>
                     <l>Our long defer'd, but much wiſhed nuptiall,</l>
                     <l>Falls out above expreſſion; heaven be plea'd</l>
                     <l>That J may uſe theſe bleſſings powerd on me</l>
                     <l>With moderation.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Brun.</speaker>
                     <l>Hell and furies ayde me,</l>
                     <l>That J may have power to avert the plagues</l>
                     <l>That preſſe upon me.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Thier.</speaker>
                     <l>Two dayes journy ſayeſt thou,</l>
                     <l>We will ſet forth to meete her, in the meane time</l>
                     <l>See all things be preparde to entertaine her</l>
                     <l>Nay let me have your companies, there's a Forreſt</l>
                     <l>Jn the mid way ſhall yeild us hunting ſport,</l>
                     <l>To eaſe our travale, ile not have a brow</l>
                     <l>But ſhall weare mirth upon it, therefore cleer them.</l>
                     <l>We'ele waſh away, all ſorrow in glad feaſts</l>
                     <l>And the war we meane to men, we'le make on beaſts.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <stage>Exeunt omnes, praeter Brun. Bawdber, Portaldy, Lecure.</stage>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Brun.</speaker>
                     <l>Oh that I had the Magicke to trans<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forme you</l>
                     <l>Into the ſhape of ſuch, that your own hounds</l>
                     <l>Might teare you peece meale; are you ſo ſtupid?</l>
                     <l>No word of comfort? have I fed you mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers</l>
                     <l>From my exceſſe of moyſture, with ſuch coſt</l>
                     <l>And can you yeild no other retribution,</l>
                     <l>But to devour your maker, pandar ſponge,</l>
                     <l>Impoyſner, all growne barren?</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Prota.</speaker>
                     <l>You your ſelfe</l>
                     <l>That are our mover, and for whom alone</l>
                     <l>Wee live, have fail'd your ſelf ingiving way</l>
                     <l>To the reconcilement of your ſonnes.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Lecure.</speaker>
                     <l>Which if</l>
                     <l>You had prevented, or would teach us how</l>
                     <l>They might againe be ſeverd, we could eaſily</l>
                     <l>Remove all other hindrances that ſtop</l>
                     <l>The paſſage of your pleaſures.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Bawdb.</speaker>
                     <l>And for me,</l>
                     <l>If I faile in my office to provide you</l>
                     <l>Freſh delicates hang me.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <pb facs="tcp:47462:7" rendition="simple:additions"/>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Brun.</speaker>
                     <l>Oh you are dull, and finde not</l>
                     <l>The cauſe of my vexation; their recon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cilement</l>
                     <l>Is a mock caſtle built upon the ſand</l>
                     <l>By children, which when I am pleas'd to o'rethrow,</l>
                     <l>I can with eaſe ſpurne downe.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Lecure.</speaker>
                     <l>If ſo, from whence</l>
                     <l>Growes your affliction?</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Brun.</speaker>
                     <l>My griefe comes along</l>
                     <l>With the new Queene, in whoſe grace all my power</l>
                     <l>Muſt ſuffer ſhipwrack: for me now,</l>
                     <l>That hitherto have kept the firſt, to know</l>
                     <l>A ſecond place, or yeeld the leaſt prece<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence</l>
                     <l>To any others death; to have my ſleepes</l>
                     <l>Leſſe enquir'd after, or my riſing up</l>
                     <l>Saluted with leſſe reverence, or my gates</l>
                     <l>Empty of ſuitors, or the Kings great fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vours</l>
                     <l>To paſſe through any hand but mine, or hee</l>
                     <l>Himſelfe to be directed by another,</l>
                     <l>Would bee to mee: doe you underſtand mee, yet</l>
                     <l>No meanes to prevent this.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Prota.</speaker>
                     <l>Fame gives her out</l>
                     <l>To be a woman of chaſtity</l>
                     <l>Not to bee wrought upon; and therefore Madam</l>
                     <l>For mee, though I have pleas'd you, to at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tempt her</l>
                     <l>Were to no purpoſe.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Brun.</speaker>
                     <l>Tuſh, ſome other way.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Bawdb.</speaker>
                     <l>Faith I know none elſe, all my bringing up</l>
                     <l>Aim'd at no other learning.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Lecure.</speaker>
                     <l>Give me leave,</l>
                     <l>If my art faile mee not, I have thought on</l>
                     <l>A ſpeeding project.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Brun.</speaker>
                     <l>What i'ſt? but effect it,</l>
                     <l>And thou ſhalt be my <hi>Aeſculapius,</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>Thy image ſhall be ſet up in pure gold,</l>
                     <l>To which i'le fall downe and worſhip it.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Lecure.</speaker>
                     <l>The Lady is faire.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Brun.</speaker>
                     <l>Exceeding faire.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Lecure.</speaker>
                     <l>And young.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Brun.</speaker>
                     <l>Some fifteene at the moſt.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Lecure.</speaker>
                     <l>And loves the King with equall ardor.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Brun.</speaker>
                     <l>More, ſhe dotes on him.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Lecure.</speaker>
                     <l>Well then, what thinke you if I make a drinke</l>
                     <l>Which given unto him on the bridall night</l>
                     <l>Shall for five dayes ſo rob his faculties,</l>
                     <l>Of all ability to pay that duty,</l>
                     <l>Which new made wives expect, that ſhe ſhall ſweare</l>
                     <l>She is not match'd to a man.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Prota.</speaker>
                     <l>'Twere rare.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Lecure.</speaker>
                     <l>And then,</l>
                     <l>If ſhe have any part of woman in her,</l>
                     <l>She'le or fly our, or at leaſt give occaſion</l>
                     <l>Of ſuch a breach which nere can bee made up,</l>
                     <l>Since he that to all elſe did never faile</l>
                     <l>Of as much as could be perform'd by man</l>
                     <l>Proves only ice to her.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Brun.</speaker>
                     <l>Tis excellent.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Bawdb.</speaker>
                     <l>The Phyſician</l>
                     <l>Helps ever at a dead lift; a fine calling,</l>
                     <l>That can both raiſe, and take downe, out upon thee.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Brun.</speaker>
                     <l>For this one ſervice I am ever thine,</l>
                     <l>Prepare it; ile give it him my ſelfe, for you <hi>Protaldye,</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>By this kiſſe, and our promiſ'd ſport at night,</l>
                     <l>(Doe coniure you to beare up, not minding</l>
                     <l>The oppoſition of <hi>Theodoret,</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>Or any of his followers; what ſo ere</l>
                     <l>You are, yet appeare valiant, and make good</l>
                     <l>The opinion that is had of you: for my ſelfe</l>
                     <l>In the new Queenes remove, being made ſecure,</l>
                     <l>Feare not, ile make the future building ſure,</l>
                  </sp>
                  <stage>Exeunt.</stage>
                  <stage>Wind hornes.</stage>
                  <stage>Enter Theodoret, Thierry.</stage>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Theod.</speaker>
                     <l>This Stag ſtood well, and cun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ningly.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Thierry</speaker>
                     <l>My horſe;</l>
                     <l>I am ſure, has found it, for her ſides are</l>
                     <l>Blooded from flanke to ſhoulder, where's the troope?</l>
                  </sp>
                  <stage>Enter Martell.</stage>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Theodoret.</speaker>
                     <l>Paſt homeward, weary and tir'd as we are,</l>
                     <l>Now <hi>Martell,</hi> have you remembred what we thought of?</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Mart.</speaker>
                     <l>Yes Sir, I have ſnigled him, and if there be</l>
                     <pb facs="tcp:47462:7" rendition="simple:additions"/>
                     <l>Any deſert in his blood, beſide the itch,</l>
                     <l>Or manly heat, but what decoctions</l>
                     <l>Leaches, and calliſes have cram'd into him,</l>
                     <l>Your Lordſhip ſhall know perfect.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Thier.</speaker>
                     <l>What's that, may not I know too?</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Theod.</speaker>
                     <l>Yes Sir,</l>
                     <l>To that end we caſt the project.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Thierry.</speaker>
                     <l>What i'ſt?</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Mart.</speaker>
                     <l>A deſire Sir,</l>
                     <l>Upon the gilded flag your Graces favour</l>
                     <l>Has ſtuck up for a Generall, and to in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forme you,</l>
                     <l>For this houre hee ſhall paſſe the teſt, what valour,</l>
                     <l>Staid judgement, ſoule, or ſafe diſcre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion</l>
                     <l>Your mothers wandring eyes, and your obedience</l>
                     <l>Have flung upon us, to aſſure your knowledge,</l>
                     <l>Hee can bee, dare bee, ſhall bee, muſt bee nothing,</l>
                     <l>Loade him with piles of honours; ſet him off</l>
                     <l>With all the cunning foyles that may de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive us:</l>
                     <l>But a poore, cold, unſpirited, unmanner'd,</l>
                     <l>Unhoneſt, unaffected, undone, foole,</l>
                     <l>And moſt unheard of coward, a meere lumpe</l>
                     <l>Made to loade beds withall, and like a night-mare,</l>
                     <l>Ride Ladies that forger to ſay their prayers,</l>
                     <l>One that dares onely bee diſeaſed, and in debt,</l>
                     <l>Whoſe body mewes more plaiſters every month,</l>
                     <l>Than women doe old faces.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Thier.</speaker>
                     <l>No more, I know him,</l>
                     <l>I now repent my error, take yourtime</l>
                     <l>And try him home, ever thus far reſerv'd,</l>
                     <l>You tie your anger up.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Mart.</speaker>
                     <l>I loſt it elſe Sir.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Thier.</speaker>
                     <l>Bring me his ſword fair taken with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out violence.</l>
                     <l>For that will beſt declare him.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Theod.</speaker>
                     <l>That's the thing.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Thier.</speaker>
                     <l>And my beſt horſe is thine.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Mart.</speaker>
                     <l>Your Graces ſervant.
<stage>Exit.</stage>
                     </l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Theod.</speaker>
                     <l>You'le hunt no more Sir.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Thier.</speaker>
                     <l>Not to day, the weather</l>
                     <l>Is growne too warme, beſides the dogs are ſpent,</l>
                     <l>Wee'l take a cooler morning, let's to horſe,</l>
                     <l>And hollow in the troope.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <stage>Exeunt.</stage>
                  <stage>Wind hornes.</stage>
                  <stage>
                     <hi>Enter</hi> 2 <hi>Huntſmen.</hi>
                  </stage>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>1.</speaker>
                     <l>I marry Twainer,</l>
                     <l>This woman gives indeed, theſe are the Angels</l>
                     <l>That are the keepers ſaints.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>2.</speaker>
                     <l>I like a woman</l>
                     <l>That handles the deeres dowſets with diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cretion;</l>
                     <l>And payes us by proportion.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>1.</speaker>
                     <l>Tis no treaſon</l>
                     <l>To thinke this good old Lady has a ſtump yet</l>
                     <l>That may require a corrall.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>2.</speaker>
                     <l>And the bells too.</l>
                     <stage>Enter Protaldye.</stage>
                     <l>Shee has loſt a friend of mee elſe, but here's the clarke,</l>
                     <l>No more for feare ath bell-ropes.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Prota.</speaker>
                     <l>How now Keepers,</l>
                     <l>Saw you the King?</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>1.</speaker>
                     <l>Yes Sir, hee's newly mounted,</l>
                     <l>And as we take't ridden home.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Pro.</speaker>
                     <l>Farewell then.</l>
                     <stage>Exit. Keepers</stage>
                     <stage>Enter Martell.</stage>
                     <l>My honour'd Lord, Fortune has made mee happy</l>
                     <l>To meet with ſuch a man of men to fide me.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Protald.</speaker>
                     <l>How ſir, I know ye not</l>
                     <l>Nor what your fortune meanes.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Mart.</speaker>
                     <l>Few words ſhall ſerve, I am be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>traide Sir:</l>
                     <l>Innocent and honeſt; malice and violence.</l>
                     <l>Are both againſt mee, baſely and fowlely layd for;</l>
                     <l>For my life Sir, danger is now about me,</l>
                     <l>Now in my throat Sir.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Protald.</speaker>
                     <l>Where ſir?</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Mart.</speaker>
                     <l>Nay I feare not,</l>
                     <l>And let it now powre downe in ſtormes upon me,</l>
                     <l>I have met with a noble guard,</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Prot.</speaker>
                     <l>Your meaning Sir,</l>
                     <l>For I have preſent buſineſſe.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Mart.</speaker>
                     <l>O my Lord,</l>
                     <pb facs="tcp:47462:8" rendition="simple:additions"/>
                     <l>Your honour cannot leave a gentleman</l>
                     <l>At leaſt a faire deſigne of this brave nature,</l>
                     <l>To which your worth is wedded, your pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſion</l>
                     <l>Hatch't in, and made one peece in ſuch a perill,</l>
                     <l>There are but ſix my Lord.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Prot.</speaker>
                     <l>What fix?</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Mart.</speaker>
                     <l>Six villaines ſworne, and in pay to kill mee.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Protaldye.</speaker>
                     <l>Six?</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Mart.</speaker>
                     <l>Alas Sir, what can ſix doe, or ſixe ſcore now you are preſent,</l>
                     <l>Your name will blow em off, ſay they have ſhot too,</l>
                     <l>Who dare preſent a peece? your valour's proofe Sir.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Prot.</speaker>
                     <l>No, i'le aſſure you Sir, nor my diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cretion</l>
                     <l>Againſt a multitude; 'Tis true, I dare fight</l>
                     <l>Enough, and well enough, and long e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nough:</l>
                     <l>But wiſedome Sir, and weight of what is on me,</l>
                     <l>In which I am no more mine owne, nor yours Sir,</l>
                     <l>Nor as I take it any ſingle danger,</l>
                     <l>But what concerns my place, tels me directly,</l>
                     <l>Beſide my perſon, my faire reputation,</l>
                     <l>If I thruſt into crowds, and ſeeke occaſions</l>
                     <l>Suffers opinion, ſix? Why <hi>Hercules</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>Avoyded two men, yet not to give example:</l>
                     <l>But only for your preſent dangers ſake Sir,</l>
                     <l>Were there but foure Sir, I car'd not if I killd them,</l>
                     <l>They will ſerve to whet my ſword.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Mart.</speaker>
                     <l>There are but foure Sir,</l>
                     <l>I did miſtake them, but foure ſuch as <hi>Europe</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>Excepting your great valour.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Prot.</speaker>
                     <l>Well conſiderd,</l>
                     <l>I will not meddle with um, foure in honour,</l>
                     <l>Are equall with foureſcore, beſides they are people</l>
                     <l>Only directed by their fury.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Mart.</speaker>
                     <l>So much nobler ſhall bee your way of juſtice.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Prot.</speaker>
                     <l>That I find not.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Mart.</speaker>
                     <l>You will not leave me thus?</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Prot.</speaker>
                     <l>I would not leave you, but looke you Sir,</l>
                     <l>Men of my place and buſineſſe, muſt not</l>
                     <l>Be queſtioned thus.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Mart.</speaker>
                     <l>You cannot paſſe Sir,</l>
                     <l>Now they have ſeene mee with you with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out danger.</l>
                     <l>They are here Sir within hearing, take but two.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Prot.</speaker>
                     <l>Let the law take um take a tree Sir,</l>
                     <l>Ile take my horſe, that you may keepe with ſafety,</l>
                     <l>If they have brought no hand-ſawes, within this houre</l>
                     <l>Ile ſend you reſcue, and a toyle to take um.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Mart.</speaker>
                     <l>You ſhall not goe ſo poorely, ſtay but one Sir.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Prot.</speaker>
                     <l>I have beene ſo hamperde with theſe reſcues,</l>
                     <l>So hewde and torturde, that the truth is Sir,</l>
                     <l>I have mainely vowde againſt um, yet for your ſake,</l>
                     <l>If as you ſay there be but one, ile ſtay.</l>
                     <l>And ſee faire play a both ſides.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Mart.</speaker>
                     <l>There is no</l>
                     <l>More Sir, and as I doubt a baſe one too.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Prot.</speaker>
                     <l>Fie on him, goe lugge him out by the eares.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Mart.</speaker>
                     <l>Yes,</l>
                     <l>This is he Sir, the baſeſt in the kingdome.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Prot.</speaker>
                     <l>Doe you know me?</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Mart</speaker>
                     <l>Yes, for a generall foole,</l>
                     <l>A knave, a coward, and upſtart ſtallion bawb.</l>
                     <l>Beaſt, barking puppy, that dares not bite.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Prot.</speaker>
                     <l>The beſt man beſt knowes patience</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Mart.</speaker>
                     <l>Yes,</l>
                     <l>This way Sir, now draw your ſword, and right you,</l>
                     <l>Or render it to me, for one you ſhall doe.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Pro.</speaker>
                     <l>If wearing it may do you any honor,</l>
                     <l>I ſhall be glad to grace you, there it is Sir.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Mart.</speaker>
                     <l>Now get you home, and telll your Lady Miſtris,</l>
                     <l>Shee has ſhot up a ſweet muſhrump, quit your place too,</l>
                     <l>And ſay you are counſelde well, thou wilt be beaten elſe</l>
                     <l>By thine owne lancepriſadoes; when they know thee,</l>
                     <l>That tunns of oyl of roſes will not cure thee;</l>
                     <l>Goe get you to your foyning worke at Court,</l>
                     <l>And learne to ſweat againe, and eat dry mutton;</l>
                     <l>An armor like a froſt will ſearch your bones,</l>
                     <l>And make you roare you rogue; not a reply,</l>
                     <l>For if you doe, your eares goe off.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <pb facs="tcp:47462:8" rendition="simple:additions"/>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Prot.</speaker>
                     <l>Stil patience. <stage>Exeunt.</stage>
                     </l>
                  </sp>
                  <stage>Loud muſick, A Banquet ſet out.</stage>
                  <stage>Enter Trierry, Ordella, Brunhalt, Theo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>doret, Lecure, Bawdber. &amp;c.</stage>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Thier.</speaker>
                     <l>It is your place, and though in all things elſe</l>
                     <l>You may and ever ſhall command mee, yet</l>
                     <l>In this ile bee obeyde.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Ordella.</speaker>
                     <l>Sir, the conſent,</l>
                     <l>That made me yours, ſhall never teach me to</l>
                     <l>Repent I am ſo, yet bee you but pleaſde</l>
                     <l>To give mee leave to ſay ſo much; the honour</l>
                     <l>You offer mee were better given to her,</l>
                     <l>To whom you owe the power of giving.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Thier,</speaker>
                     <l>Mother,</l>
                     <l>You heare this and rejoyce in ſuch a bleſſing</l>
                     <l>That payes to you ſo large a ſhare of duty,</l>
                     <l>But he no more, for as you hold a place</l>
                     <l>Neerer my heart than ſhee, you muſt ſit neereſt</l>
                     <l>To all thoſe graces, that are in the power</l>
                     <l>Of Majeſty to beſtow.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Brun.</speaker>
                     <l>Which ile provide,</l>
                     <l>Shall bee ſhort liude, <hi>Lecure.</hi>
                     </l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Lecure.</speaker>
                     <l>I have it ready.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Brun.</speaker>
                     <l>'Tis well, waite on our cup.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Lecure.</speaker>
                     <l>You honour me.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Thier.</speaker>
                     <l>We are dull,</l>
                     <l>No object to provoke mirth.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Theod.</speaker>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Martell,</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>If you remember Sir, will grace your Feaſt</l>
                     <l>With ſome thing that will yeld matter of mirth,</l>
                     <l>Fit for no common view.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Thier.</speaker>
                     <l>Touching <hi>Protaldye.</hi>
                     </l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Theod.</speaker>
                     <l>You have it.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Brun.</speaker>
                     <l>What of him, I feare his baſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe <stage>aſide</stage>
                     </l>
                     <l>In ſpight of all the titles that my favours</l>
                     <l>Have cloth'd him, which will make diſcovery</l>
                     <l>Of what is yet conceal'd.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <stage>Enter Martell.</stage>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Theod.</speaker>
                     <l>Looke Sir, he has it,</l>
                     <l>Nay wee ſhall have peace when ſo great a ſouldier</l>
                     <l>As the renoun d <hi>Protaldye,</hi> will give up</l>
                     <l>His ſword rather then uſe it.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Brun.</speaker>
                     <l>'Twas thy plot,</l>
                     <l>Which I will turn on thine own head. <stage>aſide</stage>
                     </l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Thier.</speaker>
                     <l>Pray you ſpeake,</l>
                     <l>How wonne you him to part from 't?</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Mart.</speaker>
                     <l>Wonne him Sir,</l>
                     <l>He would have yielded it upon his knees</l>
                     <l>Before hee would have hazarded the ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>change</l>
                     <l>Of a phillip of the forehead: had you will'd mee,</l>
                     <l>I durſt have undertooke he ſhould have ſent you</l>
                     <l>His noſe, provided that the loſſe of it</l>
                     <l>Might have ſav'd the reſt of his face: hee is Sir</l>
                     <l>The moſt unutterable coward that ere nature</l>
                     <l>Bleſt with hard ſhoulders, which were onley given him,</l>
                     <l>To the ruine of baſtinados.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Thierry</speaker>
                     <l>Poſſible.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Theod.</speaker>
                     <l>Obſerve but how ſhe frets.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Mart.</speaker>
                     <l>Why beleeve it:</l>
                     <l>But that I know the ſhame of this diſgrace,</l>
                     <l>Will make the beaſt to live with ſuch, and never</l>
                     <l>Preſume to come more among men; i'le hazard</l>
                     <l>My life upon it, that a boy of twelve</l>
                     <l>Should ſcourge him hither like a pariſh top,</l>
                     <l>And make him dance before you.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Brun.</speaker>
                     <l>Slave thou lieſt,</l>
                     <l>Thou dar'ſt aſwell ſpeake treaſon in the hearing</l>
                     <l>Of thoſe that have the power to puniſh it,</l>
                     <l>As the leaſt ſillable of this before him,</l>
                     <l>But 'tis thy hate to me.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Martell.</speaker>
                     <l>Nay, pray you Madam,</l>
                     <l>I have no eares too heare you, though a foote</l>
                     <l>To let you underſtand what he is,</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Brun</speaker>
                     <l>Villaine.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Theod.</speaker>
                     <l>You are to violent.</l>
                     <stage>Enter Protaldye.</stage>
                     <l>The worſt that can come</l>
                     <l>Is blanketting; for beating, and ſuch vertues</l>
                     <l>I have been long acquainted with.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Mart.</speaker>
                     <l>Oh ſtrange!</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Bawdb.</speaker>
                     <l>Behold the man you talke of,</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Brun.</speaker>
                     <l>Give me leave,</l>
                     <l>Or free thy (ſelfe think in what place you are)</l>
                     <l>From the foule imputation that is laid</l>
                     <l>Vpon thy valour (be bold, i'le protect you)</l>
                     <l>Or here I vow (deny it or forſweare it)</l>
                     <l>Theſe honours which thou weareſt unwor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thily,</l>
                     <pb facs="tcp:47462:9" rendition="simple:additions"/>
                     <l>Which be but impudent enough and keepe them,</l>
                     <l>Shall be torne from thee with thy eyes.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Prot.</speaker>
                     <l>I have it,</l>
                     <l>My valour! is there any here beneath,</l>
                     <l>The ſtile of king, dares queſtion it?</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Thier.</speaker>
                     <l>This is rare.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Prot.</speaker>
                     <l>Which of my actions, which have ſtill been noble,</l>
                     <l>Has rendred me ſuſpected?</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Thierry.</speaker>
                     <l>Nay <hi>Martell,</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>You muſt not fall off.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Mart.</speaker>
                     <l>Oh Sir, feare it not,</l>
                     <l>Doe you know this ſword?</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Prot.</speaker>
                     <l>Yes.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Mart.</speaker>
                     <l>Pray you on what termes</l>
                     <l>Did you part with it?</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Prota.</speaker>
                     <l>Part with it ſay you?</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Mert.</speaker>
                     <l>So.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Thier.</speaker>
                     <l>Nay ſtudy not an anſwer, confeſſe freely.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Prota.</speaker>
                     <l>Oh I remember't now, at the ſtags falls,</l>
                     <l>As we to day were hunting, a poore fellow,</l>
                     <l>And now I view you better, I may ſay</l>
                     <l>Much of your pitch: this ſilly rech I ſpoke of</l>
                     <l>With his petition falling at my feet,</l>
                     <l>(Which much againſt my will he kiſt,) deſir'd</l>
                     <l>That as a ſpecial meanes for his preferment,</l>
                     <l>I would vochſafe to let him uſe my ſword,</l>
                     <l>To cut off the ſtags head,</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Brun.</speaker>
                     <l>Will you heare that?</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Bawdb.</speaker>
                     <l>This lie beares a ſimilitude of truth.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Prota.</speaker>
                     <l>I ever courteous, (a great weake<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe in me)</l>
                     <l>Granted his humble ſuite.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Mart.</speaker>
                     <l>Oh impudence?</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Thier.</speaker>
                     <l>This change is excellent,</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Mart.</speaker>
                     <l>A word with you,</l>
                     <l>Denie it not, I was that man diſguiſde,</l>
                     <l>You know my temper, and as you reſpect</l>
                     <l>A dayly cudgelling for one whole yeare,</l>
                     <l>Without a ſecond pulling by the eares,</l>
                     <l>Or tweakes by the noſe, or the moſt pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tious balme</l>
                     <l>You us'd of patience, patience do you marke me,</l>
                     <l>Confeſſe before theſe kings with what baſe feare</l>
                     <l>Thou didſt deliver it.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Prot.</speaker>
                     <l>Oh! I ſhall burſt,</l>
                     <l>And if I have not inſtant liberty</l>
                     <l>To teare this fellow limbe by limbe, the wrong.</l>
                     <l>Will breake my hart, although <hi>Herculean,</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>And ſomewhat bigger, there's my gage, pray you here</l>
                     <l>Let me redeeme my credit.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Thierry.</speaker>
                     <l>Ha, ha, forbeare.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Mart.</speaker>
                     <l>Pray you let me take it up, and if I do not</l>
                     <l>Againſt all ods of armor and of weapons,</l>
                     <l>VVith this make him confeſſe it on his knees</l>
                     <l>Cut off my head.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Prot.</speaker>
                     <l>No, that is my office.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Bawdb.</speaker>
                     <l>Fie, you take the hangmans place.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Ordella.</speaker>
                     <l>Nay good my Lord</l>
                     <l>Let me attone this difference, do not ſuffer</l>
                     <l>Our bridall night to be the Centaures feaſt,</l>
                     <l>You are a knight and bound by oath to grant</l>
                     <l>All juſt ſuits unto Ladies; for my ſake</l>
                     <l>Forget your ſuppos'd wrong.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Prot.</speaker>
                     <l>Well, let him thanke you,</l>
                     <l>For your ſake he ſhall live, perhaps a day,</l>
                     <l>And may be, on ſubmiſſion longer,</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Theod.</speaker>
                     <l>Nay, <hi>Martell,</hi> you muſt be patient.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Mart.</speaker>
                     <l>I am yours,</l>
                     <l>And this ſlave ſhall be once more mine.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Thier.</speaker>
                     <l>Sit all;</l>
                     <l>One health, and ſo to bed, for I too long</l>
                     <l>Deferre my choiſeſt delicates.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Brun.</speaker>
                     <l>Which if poyſon.</l>
                     <l>Have any Power, thou ſhalt like <hi>Tantalus</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>Behold and never taſte; be carefull.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Lecure.</speaker>
                     <l>Feare not.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Brun.</speaker>
                     <l>Though it be rare in our ſex, yet for once</l>
                     <l>I will begin a health.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Thier.</speaker>
                     <l>Let it come freely.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Brun.</speaker>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Lecure,</hi> the cup; heere to the ſonne we hope</l>
                     <l>This night ſhall be an Embrion.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Thierry.</speaker>
                     <l>You have nam'd</l>
                     <l>A bleſſing that I moſt deſir'd, I pledge you,</l>
                     <l>Give me a larger cup, that is too little</l>
                     <l>Vnto ſo great a god.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Brun.</speaker>
                     <l>Nay, then you wrong me,</l>
                     <l>Follow as I began.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Thierry.</speaker>
                     <l>Well as you pleaſe.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Brun.</speaker>
                     <l>Iſt done?</l>
                  </sp>
                  <pb facs="tcp:47462:9" rendition="simple:additions"/>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Lecure.</speaker>
                     <l>Vnto your wiſh, I warrant you,</l>
                     <l>For this night I durſt truſt him with my mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Their.</speaker>
                     <l>So, 'tis gone round, lights.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Brun.</speaker>
                     <l>Pray you uſe my ſervice.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Ordella.</speaker>
                     <l>'Tis that which I ſhall ever owe you Madam,</l>
                     <l>And muſt have none from you, pray you par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>don me.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Thier.</speaker>
                     <l>Good reſt to all.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Theod.</speaker>
                     <l>And to you pleaſant labour.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Mart.</speaker>
                     <l>Your company, Madam good night</l>
                  </sp>
                  <stage>Exeunt all, but Brunhalt, Portal Lecure, Bawdber.</stage>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Brun.</speaker>
                     <l>Nay you have cauſe to bluſh, but I will hide it,</l>
                     <l>And what's more I forgive you; iſt not pitty</l>
                     <l>That thou that art the firſt to enter combat</l>
                     <l>With any woman, and what is more, ore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come her,</l>
                     <l>In which ſhee is beſt pleas'd, ſhould be ſo fearefull</l>
                     <l>To meete a man.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Prot.</speaker>
                     <l>Why would you have me loſe</l>
                     <l>That bloud that is dedicated to your ſervice</l>
                     <l>In any other qaurrell.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Brun.</speaker>
                     <l>No, reſerve it.</l>
                     <l>As I will ſtudy to preſerve thy credit,</l>
                     <l>You ſirha; be't your care to find out on</l>
                     <l>That is poore though valiant, that at any rate</l>
                     <l>Will, to redeeme my ſervants reputation,</l>
                     <l>Receive a publique baffling.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Bawdb.</speaker>
                     <l>VVould your Highneſſe</l>
                     <l>VVere pleas'd to informe mee better of your purpoſe.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Brun</speaker>
                     <l>VVhy one Sir, that would thus be box'd</l>
                     <l>Or kick'd, doe you apprehend me now?</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Bawdb.</speaker>
                     <l>I feele you Madam,</l>
                     <l>The man that ſhall receive this from my Lord,</l>
                     <l>Shall have a thouſand crownes.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Prot.</speaker>
                     <l>Hee ſhall,</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Bawd.</speaker>
                     <l>beſides</l>
                     <l>His day of baſtinadoing paſt o're,</l>
                     <l>Hee ſhall not loſe your Grace, nor your good favour.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Brun.</speaker>
                     <l>That ſhall make way to it.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Bawdb.</speaker>
                     <l>It muſt be a man</l>
                     <l>Of credit in the Court, that is to be</l>
                     <l>The foyle unto your valour.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Brot.</speaker>
                     <l>True, it ſhould.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Bawdb.</speaker>
                     <l>And if hee have place there, 'tis not the worſe.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Brun.</speaker>
                     <l>'Tis much the better.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Bawdb.</speaker>
                     <l>If he be a Lord,</l>
                     <l>'Twill be the greater grace</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Brun.</speaker>
                     <l>Thou art in the right.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Bawdb.</speaker>
                     <l>Why then behold that valiant man and Lord,</l>
                     <l>That for your ſake will take a cudgelling,</l>
                     <l>For be aſſu'd when it is ſpread abroad</l>
                     <l>That you have dealt with mee, they'le give you out</l>
                     <l>For one of the nine Worthies.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Brun.</speaker>
                     <l>Out you pandar,</l>
                     <l>Why to beate thee is only exerciſe</l>
                     <l>For ſuch as doe affect it, loſe not time</l>
                     <l>In vaine replies, but doe it: come my ſollace</l>
                     <l>Let us to bed, and our deſires once quench'd</l>
                     <l>Weele there determine of <hi>Theodorets</hi> death</l>
                     <l>For he's the Engine us'd to ruine us;</l>
                     <l>Yet one worke more, <hi>Lecure,</hi> art thou aſſurde</l>
                     <l>The potion will worke,</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Lecure.</speaker>
                     <l>My life upon it,</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Brun.</speaker>
                     <l>Come my <hi>Protaldye,</hi> then glut mee with</l>
                     <l>Thoſe beſt delights of man, that are deni'd</l>
                     <l>To her that does expect them, being a bride.</l>
                  </sp>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div n="3" type="act">
               <head>
                  <hi>Act.</hi> 3.</head>
               <div n="1" type="scene">
                  <head>
                     <hi>Scoe.</hi> 1.</head>
                  <stage>Enter Thierry and Ordella, as from bed.</stage>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Thier.</speaker>
                     <l>Sure I have drunke the blood of Elephants.</l>
                     <l>The teares of mandrake and the marble dew,</l>
                     <l>Mixt in my draught, have quencht my naturall heate,</l>
                     <l>And left no ſparke of fire but in mine eyes,</l>
                     <l>With which I may behold my miſeries:</l>
                     <l>Yee wretched flames which play upon my ſight,</l>
                     <l>Turne inward, make mee all one peece, though earth.</l>
                     <l>My teares ſhall overwhelme you elſe too.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Ordella.</speaker>
                     <l>What moves my Lord to this ſtrange ſadneſſe?</l>
                     <l>If any late diſcerned want in me,</l>
                     <l>Give cauſe to your repentance, care and duty</l>
                     <l>Shall find a painefull way to recompence.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Thier.</speaker>
                     <l>Are you yet frozen veines, feele you a breath,</l>
                     <l>Whoſe temperate heate would make the North ſtarre reele,</l>
                     <l>Her icie pillars thaw'd, and do you not melt?</l>
                     <l>Draw neerer, yet neerer,</l>
                     <l>That from thy barren kiſſe thou maiſt con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſe</l>
                     <pb facs="tcp:47462:10" rendition="simple:additions"/>
                     <l>I have not heate enough to make a bluſh.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Ordella.</speaker>
                     <l>Speake neerer to my underſtanding, like a huſband,</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Thier.</speaker>
                     <l>How ſhould he ſpeak the language of a huſband,</l>
                     <l>Who wants the tongue and organs of his voice?</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Ordella.</speaker>
                     <l>It is a phraſe will part with the ſame eaſe</l>
                     <l>From you with that you now deliver.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Thier.</speaker>
                     <l>Bind not his eares up with ſo dull a charme</l>
                     <l>Who hath no other ſence left, open; why ſhould thy words</l>
                     <l>Find more reſtraint than thy free ſpeak<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing actions,</l>
                     <l>Thy cloſe imbraces and thy mid-night ſighes</l>
                     <l>The ſilent orators to ſlow deſire?</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Ordella</speaker>
                     <l>Strive not to winne content from ignorance</l>
                     <l>Which muſt be loſt in knowledge: heaven can witneſſe</l>
                     <l>My fartheſt hope of good reacht at your pleaſure,</l>
                     <l>VVhich ſeeing alone may in your looke bee read:</l>
                     <l>Adde not a doubtfull comment to a text</l>
                     <l>That in it ſelfe is direct and eaſie.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Thier.</speaker>
                     <l>Oh thou haſt drunke the juice of hemlocke too,</l>
                     <l>Or did upbraided nature make this paire</l>
                     <l>To ſhew ſhee had not quite forgot lier firſt</l>
                     <l>Juſtly prais'd workemanſhip, the firſt chaſt couple</l>
                     <l>Before the want of joy, taught guilty ſight</l>
                     <l>A way through ſhame and ſorrow to delight:</l>
                     <l>Say, may we mixe as in their innocence</l>
                     <l>VVhen turtles kiſt, to confirme happineſſe,</l>
                     <l>Not to beget it.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Ordella.</speaker>
                     <l>I know no bar.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Thier.</speaker>
                     <l>Should I beleeve thee, yet thy pulſe beates woman,</l>
                     <l>And ſayes the name of wife did promiſe thee</l>
                     <l>The bleſt reward of duty to thy mother,</l>
                     <l>VVho gave ſo often witneſſe of her joy,</l>
                     <l>VVhen ſhee did boaſt thy likeneſſe to her Husband.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Ordella.</speaker>
                     <l>'Tis true, that to bring forth a ſecond to your ſelfe,</l>
                     <l>VVas only worthy of my Virgin loſſe;</l>
                     <l>And ſhould I prize you leſſe unpattern'd Sir,</l>
                     <l>Then being exemplified, i'ſt not more honor</l>
                     <l>To be poſſeſſor of unequal'd vertue,</l>
                     <l>Then what is parallel'd? give me beleife,</l>
                     <l>The name of mother knowes no way of good,</l>
                     <l>More then the end in mee: who weds for luſt</l>
                     <l>Is oft a widow; when I married you,</l>
                     <l>I loſt the name of maide to gaine a title</l>
                     <l>Above the wiſh of change, which that part can</l>
                     <l>Only maintaine, is ſtill the ſame in man,</l>
                     <l>His vertue and his calme ſociety,</l>
                     <l>Which no gray haires can threaten to diſſolve,</l>
                     <l>Nor wrinkles bury.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Thier.</speaker>
                     <l>Confine thy ſelfe to ſilence, leſt thou take.</l>
                     <l>That part of reaſon from me is only left</l>
                     <l>To give perſwaſion to me, I am a man:</l>
                     <l>Or ſay thou haſt never ſeene the rivers haſte</l>
                     <l>With glad-ſome ſpeed to meete the amomorous ſea.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Ordella.</speaker>
                     <l>We are but to praiſe the coole<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe of their ſtreames.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Thier.</speaker>
                     <l>Nor view'd the kids taught by their luſtfull ſires,</l>
                     <l>Purſue each other through the wanton lawnes,</l>
                     <l>And lik't the ſport.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Ordella.</speaker>
                     <l>As it made way unto their en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vied reſt</l>
                     <l>With weary knots binding their harmleſſe eyes.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Thier.</speaker>
                     <l>Nor doe you know the reaſon why the Dove,</l>
                     <l>One of the paire your hands wont hourely ſeed,</l>
                     <l>So often clipt and kiſt her happy mate.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Ordella.</speaker>
                     <l>Unleſſe it were to welcome his wiſht ſight,</l>
                     <l>VVhoſe abſence onely gave her mourning voice.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Thierry.</speaker>
                     <l>And you could dove-like to a ſingle object</l>
                     <l>Binde your looſe ſpirits to one, nay ſuch a one</l>
                     <l>VVhom only eyes and ears muſt flatter good,</l>
                     <l>Your ſurer ſence made uſeleſſe, my ſelfe, nay</l>
                     <l>As in my all of good already knowne.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Ordella.</speaker>
                     <l>Let proofe plead for mee, let me be mew'd up</l>
                     <l>VVhere never eye may reach mee but your owne;</l>
                     <l>And when I ſhall repent, but in my lookes, if ſigh,</l>
                  </sp>
                  <pb facs="tcp:47462:10" rendition="simple:additions"/>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Thier.</speaker>
                     <l>Or ſhed a teare that's warme.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Ordella.</speaker>
                     <l>But in your ſadneſſe.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Thier.</speaker>
                     <l>Or when you heare the birds call for their mates.</l>
                     <l>Aske if it be St. <hi>Valentine,</hi> their coupling day.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Ordella.</speaker>
                     <l>If any thing may make a thought ſuſpected</l>
                     <l>Of knowing any happineſſe but you,</l>
                     <l>Divorce mee by the title of moſt falſhood.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Thier.</speaker>
                     <l>Oh who would know a wife, that might have ſuch a friend?</l>
                     <l>Poſterity henceforth loſe the name of bleſſing</l>
                     <l>And leave the earth inhabited to people heaven.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <stage>Enter Theodoret, Brunhalt, Martell, Protaldye.</stage>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Mart.</speaker>
                     <l>All happineſſe to <hi>Thierry</hi> and <hi>Or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>della.</hi>
                     </l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Thier.</speaker>
                     <l>'Tis a deſire but borrowed from me, my happineſſe</l>
                     <l>Shall be the period of all good mens wiſhes,</l>
                     <l>VVhich friends, nay dying fathers ſhall be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>queath,</l>
                     <l>And in my one give all: is there a duty</l>
                     <l>Belongs to any power of mine, or love</l>
                     <l>To any vertue I have right to? here, place it heare,</l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Ordellas</hi> name ſhall onely beare command,</l>
                     <l>Rule, title, ſoverainty.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Brun.</speaker>
                     <l>What paſſion ſwayes my ſon?</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Thier.</speaker>
                     <l>O mother, ſhe has doubled every good</l>
                     <l>The travaile of your blood made poſſible</l>
                     <l>To my glad being.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Prot.</speaker>
                     <l>He ſhould have done</l>
                     <l>Little to her, he is ſo light harted;</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Thier.</speaker>
                     <l>Brother, friends, if honor unto ſhame</l>
                     <l>If wealth to want in large the preſent ſence,</l>
                     <l>My joyes are unbounded, inſteed of queſtion</l>
                     <l>Let it be envy, not bring a preſent</l>
                     <l>To the high offering of our mirth, banquets, and maskes;</l>
                     <l>Keepe waking our delights, mocking nights malice,</l>
                     <l>Whoſe darke brow would fright pleaſure from us,</l>
                     <l>Our court be but one ſtange of Revells, and each ye</l>
                     <l>The ſceane where our content moves.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Theod.</speaker>
                     <l>There ſhall want</l>
                     <l>Nothing to expreſſe our ſhares in your de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>light Sir.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Mart.</speaker>
                     <l>Till now I ne're repented the eſtate</l>
                     <l>Of widdower.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Thier.</speaker>
                     <l>Muſique, why art thou ſo ſlow voycte? it ſtaies thy preſence</l>
                     <l>My <hi>Ordella,</hi> this chamber is a ſpheare</l>
                     <l>Too narrow for thy al-moving vertue.</l>
                     <l>Make way, free way I ſay;</l>
                     <l>Who muſt alone, her ſexes want ſupply,</l>
                     <l>Had need to have a roome both large and high.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Mart.</speaker>
                     <l>This paſſion's above utterance.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Theod.</speaker>
                     <l>Nay credulity.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <stage>Exit all but Thierry, Brunhalt.</stage>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Brun.</speaker>
                     <l>Why ſonne what meane you, are you a man?</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Thier.</speaker>
                     <l>No mother I am no man, were I a man?</l>
                     <l>How could I be thus happy?</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Brun.</speaker>
                     <l>How can a wife be author of this joy then?</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Thier.</speaker>
                     <l>That being no man, I am married to no woman;</l>
                     <l>The beſt of men in full ability,</l>
                     <l>Can onely hope to ſatisfie a wife,</l>
                     <l>And for that hope ridiculous, I in my want</l>
                     <l>And ſuch defective poverty, that to her bed</l>
                     <l>From my firſt cradell brought no ſtrength but thought,</l>
                     <l>Have met a temperance beyond hers that rockt me,</l>
                     <l>Neceſſity being her bar; where this</l>
                     <l>Is ſo much ſenceleſſe of my depriv'd fire,</l>
                     <l>She knowes it not a loſſe by her deſire.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Brun.</speaker>
                     <l>It is beyond my admiration.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Thier,</speaker>
                     <l>Beyond your ſexes faith,</l>
                     <l>The unripe virgins of our age to hear't</l>
                     <l>Will dreame themſelves to women, and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vert</l>
                     <l>The example to a miracle.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Brun.</speaker>
                     <l>Alas 'tis your defect moves my a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mazement,</l>
                     <l>But what ill can be ſeperate from ambition?</l>
                     <l>Cruell <hi>Theodoret.</hi>
                     </l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Thierry.</speaker>
                     <l>What of my brother?</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Brun.</speaker>
                     <l>That to his name your barreneſſe adds rule;</l>
                     <l>Who loving the effect, would not be ſtrange</l>
                     <l>In favouring the cauſe; looke on the profit,</l>
                     <l>And gaine will quickly point the miſchiefe out.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Thier.</speaker>
                     <p>The name of father to what I poſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeſſe
<pb facs="tcp:47462:11" rendition="simple:additions"/> is ſhame and care.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Brun.</speaker>
                     <l>Were we begot to ſingle happineſſe</l>
                     <l>I grant you; but from ſuch a wife, ſuch virtue</l>
                     <l>To get an heire, what hermet would not finde</l>
                     <l>Deſerving argument to breake his vow</l>
                     <l>Even in his age of chaſtity?</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Thier.</speaker>
                     <l>You teach a deafe man language.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Brun.</speaker>
                     <l>The cauſe found out, the malady may ceaſe,</l>
                     <l>Have you heard of one <hi>Forts?</hi>
                     </l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Thier.</speaker>
                     <l>A learn'd Aſtronomer, great Magi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cian,</l>
                     <l>Who lives hard by retir'd.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Brun.</speaker>
                     <l>Repaire to him, with the juſt houre and place</l>
                     <l>Of your nativity; fooles are amaz'd at fate,</l>
                     <l>Griefes but conceal'd are never deſperate.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Thier.</speaker>
                     <l>You have timely wakn'd me, nor ſhall I ſleepe</l>
                     <l>Without the ſatisfaction of his art</l>
                  </sp>
                  <stage>Exit Thierry.</stage>
                  <stage>Enter Lecure.</stage>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Brun.</speaker>
                     <l>Wiſedome prepares you to'r, <hi>Le<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cure,</hi> met happily.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Lecure.</speaker>
                     <l>The ground anſwers your purpoſe, the conveniance</l>
                     <l>Being ſecure and eaſie, falling juſt</l>
                     <l>Behind the ſtate ſet for <hi>Theodoret.</hi>
                     </l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Brun.</speaker>
                     <l>'Tis well, your truſt invites you to a ſecond charge,</l>
                     <l>You know <hi>Lefortes</hi> cell.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Lecure.</speaker>
                     <l>Who conſtellated your faire birth</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Brun.</speaker>
                     <l>Enough, I ſee thou knowſt him, where's <hi>Bawdber?</hi>
                     </l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Lecur.</speaker>
                     <l>I left him carefull of the project caſt,</l>
                     <l>To raiſe <hi>Protaldies</hi> credit.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Brun.</speaker>
                     <l>A ſore that muſt be plaſter'd, in whoſe wound</l>
                     <l>Others ſhall find their graves, thinke themſelves ſound,</l>
                     <l>Your eare, and quickeſt apprehenſion.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <stage>Exeunt.</stage>
                  <stage>Enter Bawdber, and a ſervant.</stage>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Bawdb.</speaker>
                     <l>This man of war will advance.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Lecure.</speaker>
                     <l>His houres upon the ſtroake.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Bawdb.</speaker>
                     <l>Wind him backe as you favour my eares,</l>
                     <l>I have no noyſe in my head, my braines have hitherto</l>
                     <l>Bin imploy'd in ſilent buſineſſes.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <stage>Enter Devitry.</stage>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Lecure.</speaker>
                     <l>The gentleman is within your reach Sir.
<stage>Exit.</stage>
                     </l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Bawdb</speaker>
                     <l>Give ground whilſt I drill my wits to the encounter,</l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Devitry,</hi> I take it.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Devitry.</speaker>
                     <l>All that's left of him.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Bawdb.</speaker>
                     <l>Is there another parcell of you, if it be at pawne</l>
                     <l>I will gladly redeeme it to make you wholy mine.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Vitry</speaker>
                     <l>You ſeeke too hard a penyworth.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Bawdb.</speaker>
                     <l>You to ill to keepe ſuch diſtance, your parts have been long knowne</l>
                     <l>To me, howſoever you pleaſe to forget ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quaintance</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Vitry.</speaker>
                     <l>I muſt confeſſe I have bin ſubject, to leawd company.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Bawdb.</speaker>
                     <l>Thankes for your good remem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brance,</l>
                     <l>You have bin a ſouldier <hi>Devitry,</hi> and borne armes.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Vitry.</speaker>
                     <p>A couple of unprofitable ones, that have onely ſerv'd to get me a ſtomacke to my dinner.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Bawdb.</speaker>
                     <l>Much good may it doe you Sir.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Vitry.</speaker>
                     <p>You ſhould have heard me ſay I had din'd firſt, I have built on an unwholſome ground, rais'd up a houſe before I knew a te<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nant, matcht to meere wearineſſe, ſought to find want and hunger.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Bawdb.</speaker>
                     <p>It is time you put up your ſword, and runne away for meate ſir, nay if I had not withdrawne ere now, I might have kept thee; faſt with you: but ſince the way to thrive is never late, what is the neereſt courſe to profit thinke you?</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Vitry.</speaker>
                     <p>It may be your worſhip will ſay bawdry.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Bawdb.</speaker>
                     <p>True ſence, bawdry.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Vitry.</speaker>
                     <p>Why is there five kinds of them, I never knew but one.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Bawdb.</speaker>
                     <p>Ile ſhew you a new way of proſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tution, fall backe, further yet, further, there is fifty crownes, do but as much to <hi>Protaldye</hi> the Queenes favoret, they are doubled.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Vitry.</speaker>
                     <p>But thus much.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Bawdb.</speaker>
                     <p>Give him but an affront as he comes to the preſence, and in his drawing make way like a true bawde to his valour, the ſon's thy owne; if you take a ſcratch in the
<pb facs="tcp:47462:11" rendition="simple:additions"/> arme or ſo, every drop of blood weighes downe a ducket.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Vitry.</speaker>
                     <p>After that rate, I and my friends would begger the kingdome. Sir you have made me bluſh to ſee my want, whoſe cure is ſuch a cheape and eaſie purchaſe, this is male bawdery belike.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <stage>Enter Protaldy, a Lady, and Revellers.</stage>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Bawdb.</speaker>
                     <p>See, you ſhall not belong earning your wages, your worke's before your eyes.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Vitry.</speaker>
                     <p>Leave it to my handling, ile fall up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on't inſtantly.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Bawdb.</speaker>
                     <l>What opinion will the managing of this affaire</l>
                     <l>Bring to my wiſedome? my invention tickles</l>
                     <l>With apprehenſion on't:</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Pro.</speaker>
                     <l>Theſe are the joyes of marriage Lady,</l>
                     <l>VVhoſe fights are able to diſſolve virginity.</l>
                     <l>Speake freely, do you not envy the brides felicity?</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Lady.</speaker>
                     <l>How ſhould I, being partner of't?</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Protall.</speaker>
                     <l>VVhat you enjoy is but the ban<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quets view,</l>
                     <l>The taſte ſtands from your pallate; if he impart</l>
                     <l>By day ſo much of his content, thinke what night gave?</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Vitry.</speaker>
                     <l>VVill you have a relliſh of wit Lady?</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Bawdb.</speaker>
                     <l>This is the man.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Lady.</speaker>
                     <l>If it be not deare Sir.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Vitry.</speaker>
                     <p>If you affect cheapneſſe, how can you prize this ſullied ware ſo much? mine is freſh, my owne, not retail'd.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Prot</speaker>
                     <l>You are ſawcy firra.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Vitry.</speaker>
                     <p>The fitter to be in the diſh with ſuch dry ſtockfiſh as you are, how ſtrike?</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Bawdb.</speaker>
                     <p>Remember the condition as you looke for payment.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Vitry.</speaker>
                     <l>That boxe was left out of the bar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gaine.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Prot.</speaker>
                     <l>Helpe, helpe, helpe.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Bawdb.</speaker>
                     <l>Plague of the ſcriveners running hand,</l>
                     <l>VVhat a blow is this to my reputation?</l>
                  </sp>
                  <stage>Enter Thierry, Theodoret, Brunhalt, Or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>della, Memberge, Martell.</stage>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Thier.</speaker>
                     <l>VVhat villaine dares this outrage?</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Devitry.</speaker>
                     <p>Heare me Sir, this creature hir'd me with fifty crownes in hand, to let <hi>Protal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dye</hi> have the better of mee at ſingle rapier on a made quarrell; he miſtaking the wea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pon, layes mee over the chops with his club<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fiſt, for which I was bold to teach him the art of memory.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Omnes.</speaker>
                     <l>Ha, ha, ha, ha.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Theod.</speaker>
                     <l>Your Generall, mother, will diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>play himſelfe.</l>
                     <l>Spight of our peace I ſee.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Thier</speaker>
                     <l>Forbeare theſe civill jarres, fie <hi>Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taldy,</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>So open in your projects, avoyd our preſence ſirra.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Devi.</speaker>
                     <l>VVillingly, if you have any more wages to earne,</l>
                     <l>You ſee I can take paines.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Theod.</speaker>
                     <l>There's ſomewhat for thy labour,</l>
                     <l>More than was promis'd, ha, ha, ha.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Bawdb</speaker>
                     <l>Where could I wiſh my ſelfe now? in the Iſle of dogs,</l>
                     <l>So I might ſcape ſcratching, for I ſee by her cats eyes</l>
                     <l>I ſhall bee claw'd fearefully.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Thier.</speaker>
                     <l>Wee'l heare no more on't,
<stage>ſoft muſick</stage>
                     </l>
                     <l>Muſick drowne all ſadneſſe;</l>
                     <l>Command the Revellers in, at what a rate I doe purchaſe</l>
                     <l>My mothers abſence to give my ſpleene full liberty.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Brun.</speaker>
                     <l>Speake not a thoughts delay, it names thy ruine,</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Prot.</speaker>
                     <l>I had thought my life had borne more value with you.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Brun.</speaker>
                     <l>Thy loſſe carries mine with't, let that ſecure thee.</l>
                     <l>The vault is ready, and the doore conveyes roo't,</l>
                     <l>Falls juſt behind his chaire, the blow once given,</l>
                     <l>Thou art unſeene.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Prot</speaker>
                     <l>I cannot feele more than I feare, ime ſure.
<stage>withdraws</stage>
                     </l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Brun.</speaker>
                     <l>Be gone, and let them laugh their owne deſtruction.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Thier:</speaker>
                     <l>You will adde unto her rage.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Theod.</speaker>
                     <l>Foot I ſhall burſt unleſſe I vent my ſelfe, ha, ha, ha.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Brun.</speaker>
                     <l>Me Sir, you never could</l>
                     <l>Have found a time to invite more wilingneſs</l>
                     <l>In my diſpoſe to pleaſure.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Memb.</speaker>
                     <l>Would you would pleaſe to make ſome other choiſe.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Revel.</speaker>
                     <l>'Tis a diſgrace would dwell upon me Lady,</l>
                     <pb facs="tcp:47462:12" rendition="simple:additions"/>
                     <l>Should you refuſe.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Memb.</speaker>
                     <l>Your reaſon conquers; my Grand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mothers lookes</l>
                     <l>Have turn'd all ayre to earth in mee, they ſit</l>
                     <l>Upon my heart like night charmes, black and heavy.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <stage>The Dance.</stage>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Thier.</speaker>
                     <l>You are too much libertine.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Theod.</speaker>
                     <l>The fortune of the foole perſwades my laughter</l>
                     <l>More than his cowardice; was ever ratt</l>
                     <l>Tane by the taile thus? ha, ha, ha.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Thier.</speaker>
                     <l>Forbeare I ſay.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Prot.</speaker>
                     <l>No eye looks this way, I will winke and ſtrike,
<stage>Behind the State</stage>
                     </l>
                     <l>Leſt I betray my ſelfe:
<stage>ſtubs Theodoret?</stage>
                     </l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Theod.</speaker>
                     <l>Ha, did you not ſee one neere me?</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Thier.</speaker>
                     <l>How neere you, why doe you look ſo pale brother?</l>
                     <l>Treaſon, treaſon.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Memb.</speaker>
                     <l>Oh my preſage! Father.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Ordella.</speaker>
                     <l>Brother,</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Mart.</speaker>
                     <l>Prince, noble Prince.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Thier.</speaker>
                     <l>Make the gates ſure, ſearch into e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>very angle</l>
                     <l>And corner of the Court; oh my ſhame! mother,</l>
                     <l>Your ſonne is ſlaine, <hi>Theodoret,</hi> noble <hi>Theodoret,</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>Here in my armes, too weake a ſanctuary</l>
                     <l>'Gainſt treachery and murder, ſay is the tray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tor taken?</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>1 <hi>Guard.</hi>
                     </speaker>
                     <l>No man hath paſt the chamber on my life Sir.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Thier.</speaker>
                     <l>Set preſent fire unto the place, that all unſeene</l>
                     <l>May periſh in this miſchiefe, who moves flow to't,</l>
                     <l>Shall adde unto the flame.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Brun.</speaker>
                     <l>What meane you? give mee your private hearing.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Thier.</speaker>
                     <l>Perſwaſion is a partner in the crime,</l>
                     <l>I will renounce my claime unto a mother,</l>
                     <l>If you make offer on't.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Brun.</speaker>
                     <l>Ere a torch can take flame, I will produce</l>
                     <l>The author of the fact.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Thier.</speaker>
                     <l>Withdraw but for your lights.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Memb.</speaker>
                     <l>O my too true ſuſpition.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <stage>Exeunt Martell, Memberg.</stage>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Thier.</speaker>
                     <l>Speake, where's the engine to this horrid act?</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Brun.</speaker>
                     <l>Here you doe behold her, upon whom make good</l>
                     <l>Your cauſeleſſe rage; the deed was done by my incitement,</l>
                     <l>Not yet repented.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Thier.</speaker>
                     <l>Whether did nature ſtart, when you conceiv'd</l>
                     <l>A birth ſo unlike woman? ſay, what part</l>
                     <l>Did not conſent to make a ſon of him,</l>
                     <l>Reſerv'd it ſelfe within you to his ruine.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Brun.</speaker>
                     <l>Ha, ha, a ſon of mine! doe not diſſever</l>
                     <l>Thy fathers duſt, ſhaking his quiet urne,</l>
                     <l>To which my breath would ſend ſo foule an iſſue.</l>
                     <l>My ſon, thy brother?</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Thier.</speaker>
                     <l>Was not <hi>Theodoret</hi> my brother, or is thy tongue</l>
                     <l>Confederate with thy heart, to ſpeak and doe</l>
                     <l>Only things monſtrous?</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Brun.</speaker>
                     <l>Heare mee, and thou ſhalt make thine owne beliefe,</l>
                     <l>Thy ſtill with ſorrow mention'd, father liv'd</l>
                     <l>Three carefull yeares in hope of wiſhed heires,</l>
                     <l>When I conceiv'd, being from his jealous feare,</l>
                     <l>Injoyn'd to quiet home, one fatall day:</l>
                     <l>Tranſported with my pleaſure to the chaſe,</l>
                     <l>I forc't command, and in purſuit of game,</l>
                     <l>Fell from my horſe, loſt both my child and hopes.</l>
                     <l>Deſpaire which only in his love ſaw life</l>
                     <l>Worthy of being, from a gardners armes</l>
                     <l>Snatcht this unlucky brat, and call'd it mine,</l>
                     <l>When the next yeare repaid my loſſe with thee:</l>
                     <l>But in thy wrongs preſerv'd my miſerie,</l>
                     <l>Which that I might diminiſh, though not end,</l>
                     <l>My fighes and wet eies from thy fathers will,</l>
                     <l>Bequeath this largeſt part of his Dominions</l>
                     <l>Of <hi>France,</hi> unto thee, and only left</l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Auſtracia</hi> unto that changeling, whoſe life affords</l>
                     <l>Too much of ill 'gainſt mee to prove my words,</l>
                     <l>And call him ſtranger.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Thier</speaker>
                     <l>Come, doe not weep, I muſt, nay doe beleeve you,</l>
                     <l>And in my fathers ſatisfaction count it</l>
                     <pb facs="tcp:47462:12" rendition="simple:additions"/>
                     <l>Merit, not wrong, or loſſe:</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Brun.</speaker>
                     <l>You doe but flatter, there's anger yet flames</l>
                     <l>In your eyes.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Thier.</speaker>
                     <l>See, I will quench it, and confeſſe that you</l>
                     <l>Have ſuffer'd double travaile for me.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Brun.</speaker>
                     <l>You will not fire the houſe then?</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Thier.</speaker>
                     <l>Rather reward the author, who gave cauſe</l>
                     <l>Of knowing ſuch a ſecret, my oath and duty</l>
                     <l>Shall be aſſurance on't.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Brun.</speaker>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Protaldye,</hi> riſe good faithfull ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vant, heaven knowes</l>
                     <l>How hardly he was drawne to this attempt.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <stage>Enter Protaldye.</stage>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Thier.</speaker>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Protaldye?</hi> he had a gardners fate i'le ſweare</l>
                     <l>Tell by thy hand, Sir, we doe owe unto you for this ſervice.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Brun.</speaker>
                     <l>Why lookeſt thou ſo dejected?</l>
                  </sp>
                  <stage>Enter Martell.</stage>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Prot.</speaker>
                     <l>I want a little ſhift Lady, nothing elſe.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Mart.</speaker>
                     <l>The fires are ready, pleaſe it your grace withdraw,</l>
                     <l>Whilſt we performe your pleaſure.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Thier.</speaker>
                     <l>Reſerve them for the body; ſince he had the fate</l>
                     <l>To live and die a Prince, he ſhall not loſe</l>
                     <l>The title in his funerall.
<stage>Exit.</stage>
                     </l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Mart.</speaker>
                     <l>His fate to live a prince,</l>
                     <l>Thou old impiety, made up by luſt and miſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chiefe,
<stage>Exeunt with the body of Theod.</stage>
                     </l>
                     <l>Take up the body.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <stage>Enter Lecure, and a ſervant.</stage>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Lecure.</speaker>
                     <l>Doeſt thinke <hi>Lefortes</hi> ſure e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nough?</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Serva.</speaker>
                     <p>As bonds can make him, I have turn'd his eyes to the eaſt; and left him gap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing after the morning ſtarre, his head is a meere Aſtrolobe, his eyes ſtand for the poles, the gag in his mouth being the coach<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man, his five teeth have the neereſt reſem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>blance to <hi>Charles Waine.</hi>
                     </p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Lecure.</speaker>
                     <p>Thou haſt caſt a figure which ſhall raiſe thee, direct my haire a little; and in my likeneſſe to him reade a fortune ſuiting thy largeſt hopes.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Serva</speaker>
                     <l>You are ſo far 'bove likeneſſe you are the ſame,</l>
                     <l>If you love mirth, perſwade him from him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe.</l>
                     <l>'Tis but an Aſtronomer out of the way,</l>
                     <l>And lying will beare the better place for't</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Lecure.</speaker>
                     <l>I have profitabler uſe in hand, haſt to the Queene?</l>
                     <l>And tell her how you left me chang'd.</l>
                     <stage>Exit Servant.</stage>
                     <l>Who would not ſerve this vertuous active Queene?</l>
                     <l>She that loves miſchiefe 'bove the man that does it,</l>
                     <l>And him above her pleaſure, yet knowes no heaven elſe.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <stage>Enter Thierry.</stage>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Thier.</speaker>
                     <l>How well this loanes ſuits the art I ſeeke,</l>
                     <l>Diſcovering ſecret and ſucceeding fate,</l>
                     <l>Knowledge that puts all lower happineſſe on,</l>
                     <l>With a remiſſe and careleſſe hand,</l>
                     <l>Faire peace unto your meditations father.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Lecure.</speaker>
                     <l>The ſame to you, you bring Sir.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Thier.</speaker>
                     <l>Drawne by your much fam'd skill, I come to know</l>
                     <l>Whether the man who owes this character,</l>
                     <l>Shall ere have iſſue.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Lecure.</speaker>
                     <l>A reſolution falling with moſt eaſe</l>
                     <l>Of any doubt you could have named, he is a Prince</l>
                     <l>Whoſe fortune you enquire.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Thier.</speaker>
                     <l>He is nobly borne.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Lecure.</speaker>
                     <l>He had a dukedome lately falne unto him</l>
                     <l>By one call'd brother, who has left a daugh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Thier.</speaker>
                     <l>The queſtion is of heirs, not lands.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Lecure.</speaker>
                     <l>Heirs, yes he ſhall have heires.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Thier.</speaker>
                     <l>Begotten of his body, why look'ſt thou pale?</l>
                     <l>Thou canſt not ſuffer in his want.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Lecure</speaker>
                     <l>Nor thou, I neither can nor will</l>
                     <l>Give farther knowledge to thee.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Thier.</speaker>
                     <l>Thou muſt, I am the man my ſelfe,</l>
                     <l>Thy ſoveraigne, who muſt owe unto thy wiſedome</l>
                     <l>In the concealing of my barren ſhame.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Lecure.</speaker>
                     <l>Your grace doth wrong your ſtars; if this be yours,</l>
                     <l>You may have children.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <pb facs="tcp:47462:13" rendition="simple:additions"/>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Thier.</speaker>
                     <l>Speake it againe.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Lecure.</speaker>
                     <l>You may have fruitfull iſſue.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Thier.</speaker>
                     <l>By whom? when? how?</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Lecure.</speaker>
                     <l>It was the fatall meanes firſt ſtrooke my blood</l>
                     <l>With the cold hand of wonder, when I read it</l>
                     <l>Printed upon you birth.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Thier.</speaker>
                     <l>Can there be any way unſmooth, has end</l>
                     <l>So faire and good?</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Lecure.</speaker>
                     <l>Wee that behold the ſad aſpects of heaven,</l>
                     <l>Leading ſence blinded, men feele griefe enough</l>
                     <l>To know, though not to ſpeak their miſeries.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Thier.</speaker>
                     <l>Sorrow muſt loſt a name, where mine finds life;</l>
                     <l>If not in thee, at leaſt eaſe paine with ſpeed,</l>
                     <l>Which muſt know no cure elſe.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Lecure.</speaker>
                     <l>Then thus,</l>
                     <l>The firſt of females which your eye ſhall meete</l>
                     <l>Before the ſun next riſe, comming from out</l>
                     <l>The Temple of <hi>Diana,</hi> being ſlaine, you live</l>
                     <l>Father of many ſonnes.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Thier.</speaker>
                     <l>Callſt thou this ſadneſſe, can I beget a ſonne</l>
                     <l>Deſerving leſſe then to give recompence</l>
                     <l>Unto ſo poore a loſſe? what e're thou art,</l>
                     <l>Reſt peaceable bleſt creature, borne to bee</l>
                     <l>Mother of Princes, whoſe grave ſhall be more fruitfull</l>
                     <l>Then others marriage beds: me thinkes his art</l>
                     <l>Should give her forme and happy figure to mee,</l>
                     <l>I long to ſee my happineſſe, he is gone,</l>
                     <l>As I remember hee named my brothers daughter,</l>
                     <l>Were it my mother, 'twere a gainfull death</l>
                     <l>Could give <hi>Ordella's</hi> vertue living breath.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <stage>Exeunt.</stage>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div n="4" type="act">
               <head>
                  <hi>Act.</hi> 4.</head>
               <div n="1" type="scene">
                  <head>
                     <hi>Scoe.</hi> 1.</head>
                  <stage>Enter Thierry and Martell.</stage>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Mart.</speaker>
                     <l>Your Grace is early ſtirring.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Mart.</speaker>
                     <l>How can he ſleep,</l>
                     <l>Whoſe happineſſe is laid up in an houre.</l>
                     <l>Hee knowes comes ſtealing toward him, O <hi>Martell!</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>I'ſt poſſible the longing bride, whoſe wiſhes</l>
                     <l>Outrunnes her feares, can on that day ſhee is married</l>
                     <l>Conſume in ſlumbers, or his armes ruſt in eaſe,</l>
                     <l>That heares the charge, and ſees the honor'd purchaſe</l>
                     <l>Ready to gild his valour? Mine is more</l>
                     <l>A power above theſe paſſions; this day <hi>France,</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>France</hi> that in want of iſſue withers with us;</l>
                     <l>And like an aged river runnes his head</l>
                     <l>Into forgotten wayes, againe I ranſome,</l>
                     <l>And his faire courſe turne right: this day <hi>Thierry,</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>The ſonne of <hi>France,</hi> whoſe manly powers like priſoners</l>
                     <l>Have bin tied up, and fetter'd, by one death</l>
                     <l>Give life to thouſand ages; this day beauty</l>
                     <l>The envy of the world, pleaſure the glory,</l>
                     <l>Content above the world, deſire beyond it</l>
                     <l>Are made mine owne and uſefull.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Mart.</speaker>
                     <l>Happy woman</l>
                     <l>That dies to doe theſe things.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Thier.</speaker>
                     <l>But ten times happier</l>
                     <l>That lives to doe the greater; O <hi>Martell,</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>The Gods have heard mee now, and thoſe that ſcorn'd me</l>
                     <l>Mothers of many children, and bleſt fathers</l>
                     <l>That ſee their iſſues like the ſtarres unnumber'd,</l>
                     <l>Their comfort more then them, ſhall in my praiſes</l>
                     <l>Now teach their infants ſongs; and tell their ages</l>
                     <l>From ſuch a ſonne of mine, or ſuch a Queen,</l>
                     <l>That chaſt <hi>Ordella</hi> brings mee bleſſed marriage</l>
                     <l>The chaine that linkes two holy loves to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether</l>
                     <l>And in thee marriage, more then bleſt <hi>Ordella,</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>That comes ſo neere the ſacrament it ſelfe,</l>
                     <l>The Prieſts doubt whether purer.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Mart.</speaker>
                     <l>Sir, y'are loſt.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Thier.</speaker>
                     <l>I prethee let me be ſo.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Mart.</speaker>
                     <l>The day weares,</l>
                     <l>And thoſe that have beene offering early prayers,</l>
                     <l>Are now retiring homeward.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <pb facs="tcp:47462:13" rendition="simple:additions"/>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Thier.</speaker>
                     <l>Stand and marke then.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Mart.</speaker>
                     <l>Is it the firſt muſt ſuffer.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Thier.</speaker>
                     <l>The firſt woman.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Mart.</speaker>
                     <l>What hand ſhall doe it Sir?</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Thier.</speaker>
                     <l>This hand <hi>Martell,</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>For who leſſe dare preſume to give the gods</l>
                     <l>An incenſe of this offering?</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Mart.</speaker>
                     <l>Would I were ſhe,</l>
                     <l>For ſuch away to die, and ſuch a bleſſing</l>
                     <l>Can never crowne my parting.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <stage>
                     <hi>Enter</hi> 2 <hi>men paſſing over.</hi>
                  </stage>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Thier.</speaker>
                     <l>What are thoſe?</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Mart.</speaker>
                     <l>Men, men, Sir, men.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Thier.</speaker>
                     <l>The plagues of men light on vm,</l>
                     <l>They croſſe my hopes like hares, who's that?</l>
                  </sp>
                  <stage>Enter a Prieſt.</stage>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Mart.</speaker>
                     <l>A Prieſt Sir.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Thierry.</speaker>
                     <l>Would he were gelt.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Mart.</speaker>
                     <l>May not theſe raſcalls ſerve Sir,</l>
                     <l>Well hang'd and quarter'd?</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Thierry.</speaker>
                     <l>No.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Mart.</speaker>
                     <l>Here comes a woman.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <stage>Enter Ordella, vail'd.</stage>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Thier.</speaker>
                     <l>Stand and behold her then.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Mart.</speaker>
                     <l>I thinke a faire one.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Thier.</speaker>
                     <l>Move not whilſt I prepare her: may her peace</l>
                     <l>Like his whoſe innocence the gods are pleas'd with,</l>
                     <l>And offering at their altars, gives his ſoule</l>
                     <l>Far purer then thoſe fires; pull heaven up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on her,</l>
                     <l>You holy powers, no humane ſpot dwell in her,</l>
                     <l>No love of any thing but you and goodneſſe,</l>
                     <l>Tie her to earth, feare be a ſtranger to her,</l>
                     <l>And all weake bloods affections, but thy hope</l>
                     <l>Let her bequeath to women: heare me heaven,</l>
                     <l>Give her a ſpirit maſculine, and noble,</l>
                     <l>Fit for your ſelves to aske, and mee to offer.</l>
                     <l>O let her meete my blow, doate on her death;</l>
                     <l>And as a wanton vine bowes to the pruner,</l>
                     <l>That by his cutting off more may encreaſe,</l>
                     <l>So let her fall to raiſe me fruit; hale wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man.</l>
                     <l>The happieſt, and the beſt (if thy dull will</l>
                     <l>Do not abuſe thy fortune) <hi>France</hi> ere found yet.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Ordella.</speaker>
                     <l>She is more then dull Sir, leſſe and worſe then woman,</l>
                     <l>That may inherit ſuch an infinite</l>
                     <l>As you propound, a greatneſſe ſo neare good<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe;</l>
                     <l>And brings a will to rob her.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Thier.</speaker>
                     <l>Tell me this then,</l>
                     <l>Was there ere woman yet, or may be found,</l>
                     <l>That for faire ſame, unſpotted memory,</l>
                     <l>For vertues ſake, and onely for it ſelfe ſake</l>
                     <l>Has, or dare make a ſtory?</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Ordella.</speaker>
                     <l>Many dead Sir,</l>
                     <l>Living I thinke as many.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Thier.</speaker>
                     <l>Say, the kingdome</l>
                     <l>May from a womans will receive a bleſſing,</l>
                     <l>The king and kingdome, not a private ſafe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty.</l>
                     <l>A generall bleſſing Lady.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Ordella.</speaker>
                     <l>A generall curſe</l>
                     <l>Light on her heart denyes it.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Thier.</speaker>
                     <l>Full of honor;</l>
                     <l>And ſuch examples as the former ages</l>
                     <l>Were but dim ſhadowes of, and empty fi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gures.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Ordella.</speaker>
                     <l>You ſtrangely ſtir me Sir, and were my weakeneſſe</l>
                     <l>In any other fleſh but modeſt womans,</l>
                     <l>You ſhould not aske more queſtions may I do it?</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Thier.</speaker>
                     <l>You may, and which is more, you muſt.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Ordella.</speaker>
                     <l>I joy in't,</l>
                     <l>A bove a moderate gladneſſe, Sir, you pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſe</l>
                     <l>It ſhall be honeſt.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Thier.</speaker>
                     <l>As ever time diſcover'd.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Ordella.</speaker>
                     <l>Let it be what it may then, what it dare,</l>
                     <l>I have a minde will hazard it.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Thier.</speaker>
                     <l>But harke yee,</l>
                     <l>What may that woman merit, makes this bleſſing!</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Ordella.</speaker>
                     <l>Onely her duty Sir</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Thier.</speaker>
                     <l>'Tis terrible.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Ordella.</speaker>
                     <l>'Tis ſo much the more noble.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Thier.</speaker>
                     <l>'Tis full of fearefull ſhaddowes.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Ordella.</speaker>
                     <l>So is ſleepe Sir,</l>
                     <l>Or any thing that's meerely ours and mor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tall,</l>
                     <l>We were begotten gods elſe; but thoſe feares</l>
                     <pb facs="tcp:47462:14" rendition="simple:additions"/>
                     <l>Feeling but once the fiers of nobler thoughts,</l>
                     <l>Fly like the ſhapes of clouds we forme to nothing</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Thier.</speaker>
                     <l>Suppoſe it death.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Ordella.</speaker>
                     <l>I do.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Thier.</speaker>
                     <l>And endleſſe parting</l>
                     <l>With all we can call ours, with all our ſweetneſſe,</l>
                     <l>With youth, ſtrength, pleaſure, people, time, nay reaſon:</l>
                     <l>For in the ſilent grave, no converſation,</l>
                     <l>No joyfull tread of friends, no voyce of lovers,</l>
                     <l>No carefull fathers councell, nothing's hard,</l>
                     <l>Nor nothing is, but all oblivion,</l>
                     <l>Duſt and an endleſſe darkneſſe; and dare you woman</l>
                     <l>Deſire this place?</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Ordella.</speaker>
                     <l>'Tis of all ſleepes the ſweeteſt,</l>
                     <l>Children begin it to us, ſtrong men ſeeke it,</l>
                     <l>And kings from heigth of all their painted glories</l>
                     <l>Fall like ſpent exhaltations, to this center;</l>
                     <l>And thoſe are fooles that feare it, or ima<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gine</l>
                     <l>A few unhandſome pleaſures, or lifes profits</l>
                     <l>Can recompence this place; and mad that ſtaies it,</l>
                     <l>Till age blow out their lights, or rotten hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mors.</l>
                     <l>Bring them deſpers'd to the earth.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Thier.</speaker>
                     <l>Then you can ſuffer.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Ordella.</speaker>
                     <l>As willingly as ſay it.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Thier.</speaker>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Martell,</hi> a wonder,</l>
                     <l>Here is a woman that dares die, yet tel me,</l>
                     <l>Are you a wife?</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Ordella.</speaker>
                     <l>I am Sir.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Thier.</speaker>
                     <l>And have children,</l>
                     <l>She ſighes and weepes.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Ordella.</speaker>
                     <l>O none Sir.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Thier.</speaker>
                     <l>Dare you venter</l>
                     <l>For a poore barren praiſe you ne're ſhall heare,</l>
                     <l>To part with theſe ſweet hopes.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Ordella.</speaker>
                     <l>With all but Heaven;</l>
                     <l>And yet die full of children; he that reads me</l>
                     <l>When I am aſhes, is my ſon in wiſhes,</l>
                     <l>And thoſe chaſte dames that keepe my memory,</l>
                     <l>Singing my yearely requiems, are my daughters.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Thier.</speaker>
                     <l>Then there is nothing wanting but my knowledge,</l>
                     <l>And what I muſt doe Lady.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Ordella.</speaker>
                     <l>You are the King Sir,</l>
                     <l>And what you doe i'le ſuffer, and that bleſſing</l>
                     <l>That you deſire the Gods ſhowre on the Kingdome.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Thier.</speaker>
                     <l>Thus much before I ſtrike then, for I muſt kill you,</l>
                     <l>The Gods have will'd it ſo, they'r made the bleſſing</l>
                     <l>Muſt make <hi>France</hi> young againe, and mee a man,</l>
                     <l>Keepe up your ſtrength ſtill nobly.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Ordella.</speaker>
                     <l>Feare me not.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Thier.</speaker>
                     <l>And meet death like a meaſure.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Ordella.</speaker>
                     <l>I am ſtedfaſt.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Thier.</speaker>
                     <l>Thou ſhalt bee ſainted woman, and thy tombe</l>
                     <l>Cut out in Criſtall, pure and good as thou art;</l>
                     <l>And on it ſhall be graven every age,</l>
                     <l>Succeeding Peeres of <hi>France</hi> that riſe by thy fall,</l>
                     <l>Tell thou lieſt there like old and fruitfull nature.</l>
                     <l>Dareſt thou behold thy happineſſe?</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Ordella.</speaker>
                     <l>I dare Sir.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Thier.</speaker>
                     <l>Ha?
<stage>Pulls off her vaile, letts fall his ſword.</stage>
                     </l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Mar.</speaker>
                     <l>O Sir, you muſt not doe it.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Thier.</speaker>
                     <l>No, I dare not.</l>
                     <l>There is an Angell keepes that paradice,</l>
                     <l>A fiery Angell friend; O vertue, vertue,</l>
                     <l>Ever and endleſſe vertue.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Ordella.</speaker>
                     <l>Strike Sir, ſtrike;</l>
                     <l>And if in my poore death faire <hi>France</hi> may merit,</l>
                     <l>Give me a thouſand blowes, be killing mee</l>
                     <l>A thouſand dayes.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Thier.</speaker>
                     <l>Firſt let the earrh be barren,</l>
                     <l>And man no more remembred, riſe <hi>Or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>della,</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>The neereſt to thy maker, and the pureſt</l>
                     <l>That ever dull fleſh ſhewed us,— O my heart-ſtrings.
<stage>Exit.</stage>
                     </l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Mart.</speaker>
                     <l>I ſee you full of wonder, therefore nobleſt,</l>
                     <l>And trueſt amongſt women, I will tell you</l>
                     <pb facs="tcp:47462:14" rendition="simple:additions"/>
                     <l>The end of this ſtrange accident.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Ordella.</speaker>
                     <l>Amazement</l>
                     <l>Has ſo much wove upon my heart, that truly</l>
                     <l>I feele my ſelfe unfit to heare, O Sir,</l>
                     <l>My Lord has ſlighted me.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Mart.</speaker>
                     <l>O no ſweet Lady.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Ordella.</speaker>
                     <l>Rob'd me of ſuch a glory by his pitie</l>
                     <l>And moſt unprovident reſpect.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Mart.</speaker>
                     <l>Deare Lady,</l>
                     <l>It was not meant to you.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Ordella.</speaker>
                     <l>Elſe where the day is,</l>
                     <l>And houres diſtinguiſh time, time runnes to ages,</l>
                     <l>And ages end the world, I had been ſpoken.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Devi.</speaker>
                     <l>I'le tell you what it was, if but your patience</l>
                     <l>Will give me hearing.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Ordella.</speaker>
                     <l>If I have tranſgreſt,</l>
                     <l>Forgive me Sir.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Mart.</speaker>
                     <l>Your noble Lord was counſell'd,</l>
                     <l>Grieving the barrenneſſe betweene you both,</l>
                     <l>And all the Kingdome with him, to ſeeke out</l>
                     <l>A man that knew the ſecrets of the Gods,</l>
                     <l>Hee went, found ſuch a one, and had this anſwer,</l>
                     <l>That if hee woo'd have iſſue, on this mor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning,</l>
                     <l>For this houre was prefixt him, hee ſhould kill</l>
                     <l>The firſt hee met being female, from the temple;</l>
                     <l>And then hee ſhould have children, the miſtake</l>
                     <l>Is now too perfect Lady.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Ordella.</speaker>
                     <l>Still 'tis I Sir,</l>
                     <l>For may this worke bee done by common women,</l>
                     <l>Durſt any but my ſelfe that knew the bleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing,</l>
                     <l>And felt the benefit, aſſume this thing</l>
                     <l>In any other, t'ad bin loſt, and nothing,</l>
                     <l>A curſe and not a bleſſing; I was figur'd;</l>
                     <l>And ſhall a litle fondneſſe barre my pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chaſe?</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Mart.</speaker>
                     <l>Where ſhould he then ſeeke chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren?</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Ordella.</speaker>
                     <l>Where they are</l>
                     <l>In wombes ordain'd for iſſues, in thoſe beau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties</l>
                     <l>That bleſſe a marriage bed, and makes it proceed</l>
                     <l>With kiſſes that conceive, and fruitfull plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſures;</l>
                     <l>Mine like a grave, buries thoſe loyall hopes,</l>
                     <l>And to a grave it covets.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Mart.</speaker>
                     <l>You are too good,</l>
                     <l>Too excellent, too honeſt; robbe not us</l>
                     <l>And thoſe that ſhall hereafter ſeek example,</l>
                     <l>Of ſuch ineſtimable worthies in woman,</l>
                     <l>Your Lord of ſuch obedience, all of honor</l>
                     <l>In coveting a cruelty is not yours,</l>
                     <l>A will ſhort of your wiſedome; make not error</l>
                     <l>A tombe ſtone of your vertues, whoſe faire life</l>
                     <l>Deſerves a conſtellation: your Lord dare not,</l>
                     <l>He cannot, ought not, muſt not run this hazard,</l>
                     <l>He makes a ſeperation nature ſhakes at,</l>
                     <l>The Gods deny, and everlaſting juſtice</l>
                     <l>Shrinkes backe, and ſheathes her ſword at.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Ordella,</speaker>
                     <l>All's but talke Sir,</l>
                     <l>I find to what I am reſerv'd, and need<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full,</l>
                     <l>And though my Lords compaſſion makes me poore,</l>
                     <l>And leaves me in my beſt uſe, yet a ſtrength</l>
                     <l>Above mine owne, or his dull fondneſſe finds me,</l>
                     <l>The Gods have given it to mee.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <stage>Drawes a knife.</stage>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Mart.</speaker>
                     <l>Selfe deſtruction,</l>
                     <l>Now all good Angells bleſſe thee, O ſweet Lady,</l>
                     <l>You are abus'd, this is a way to ſhame you,</l>
                     <l>And with you all that knowes you, all that loves you,</l>
                     <l>To ruine all you build, would you bee famous,</l>
                     <l>Is that your end?</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Ordella.</speaker>
                     <l>I would be what I ſhould be.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Mart.</speaker>
                     <l>Live and confirme the Gods then, live and be loaden</l>
                     <l>With more than olive beare, or fruitfull Autumn;</l>
                     <l>This way you kill your merit, kill your cauſe,</l>
                     <pb facs="tcp:47462:15" rendition="simple:additions"/>
                     <l>And him you would raiſe life to, where, or how</l>
                     <l>Got you theſe bloudy thoughts? what De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vill durſt</l>
                     <l>Looke on that Angell face, and tempt? doe you know</l>
                     <l>What 'tis to dye thus, how you ſtrike the ſtarres,</l>
                     <l>And all good things above? doe you feele</l>
                     <l>What followes a ſelfe blood, whether you venter,</l>
                     <l>And to what puniſhment? excellent Lady,</l>
                     <l>Be not thus cozen'd, doe not foole your ſelf,</l>
                     <l>The Prieſt was never his owne ſacrifice,</l>
                     <l>But he that thought his hell here.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Ordella.</speaker>
                     <l>I am counſell'd,</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Mart.</speaker>
                     <l>And I am glad on't, lye I know you dare not.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Ordelld.</speaker>
                     <l>I never have done yet.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Mart.</speaker>
                     <l>Pray take my comfort,</l>
                     <l>Was this a ſoule to loſe? two more ſuch women</l>
                     <l>Would ſave their ſexe; ſee, ſhee repents and prayes,</l>
                     <l>O heare her, heare her, if there bee a faith</l>
                     <l>Able to reach your mercies, ſhe hath ſent it.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Ordella.</speaker>
                     <l>Now good <hi>Martell</hi> confirme me.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Mart.</speaker>
                     <l>I will Lady,</l>
                     <l>And every houre adviſe you, for I doubt</l>
                     <l>Whether this plot bee heavens, or hells; your mother</l>
                     <l>And I will find it, if it be in mankind</l>
                     <l>To ſearch the center of it: in the meane time</l>
                     <l>I'le give you out for dead, and by your ſelfe,</l>
                     <l>And ſhew the inſtrument, ſo ſhall I find</l>
                     <l>A joy that will betray her.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Ordella.</speaker>
                     <l>Doe what's fitteſt;</l>
                     <l>And I will follow you.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Mart.</speaker>
                     <l>Then ever live</l>
                     <l>Both able to ingroſſe all love, and give.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <stage>Exeunt.</stage>
                  <stage>Enter Brunhalt, Protaldye.</stage>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Brun.</speaker>
                     <l>I am in labour</l>
                     <l>To be delivered of that burthenous project</l>
                     <l>I have ſo long gone with; ha, here's the mid-wife,</l>
                     <l>Or life, or death.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <stage>Enter Lecure.</stage>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Lecure.</speaker>
                     <l>If in the ſuppoſition</l>
                     <l>Of her death in whoſe life you die, yo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap> aske me,</l>
                     <l>I thinke you are ſafe.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Brun.</speaker>
                     <l>Is ſhe dead?</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Lecure.</speaker>
                     <l>I have us'd</l>
                     <l>All meanes to make her ſo, I ſaw him waiting</l>
                     <l>At the temple doore, and us'd ſuch art within,</l>
                     <l>That only ſhe of all her ſexe, was firſt</l>
                     <l>Given up unto his fury.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Brun,</speaker>
                     <l>Which if love</l>
                     <l>Or feare made him forbeare to execute</l>
                     <l>The vengeance he determin'd, his fond pity</l>
                     <l>Shall draw it on himſelfe, for were there left</l>
                     <l>Not any man but hee to ſerve my pleaſures,</l>
                     <l>Or from mee to receive commands, which are</l>
                     <l>The joyes for which I love life, he ſhould be</l>
                     <l>Remov'd, and I alone left to bee Queene</l>
                     <l>O're any part of goodneſſe that's left in me.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Lecure.</speaker>
                     <l>If you are ſo reſolv'd, I have provided</l>
                     <l>A meanes to ſhip him hence: looke upon this,</l>
                     <l>But touch it ſparingly, for this once us'd.</l>
                     <l>Say but to dry a teare, will keepe the eye lyd</l>
                     <l>From cloſing, untill death performe that office.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Brun.</speaker>
                     <l>Giv't mee, I may have uſe of it, and on you</l>
                     <l>I'le make the firſt experiment: if one ſigh</l>
                     <l>Or heavy looke beget the leaſt ſuſpition,</l>
                     <l>Childiſh compaſſion can thaw the ice</l>
                     <l>Of your ſo long congeal'd and flinty hard<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe.</l>
                     <l>Slight, goe on conſtant, or I Shall.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Prot.</speaker>
                     <l>Beſt Lady,</l>
                     <l>Wee have no faculties which are not yours.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Lecure.</speaker>
                     <l>Nor will bee any thing with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out you.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Brun.</speaker>
                     <l>Be ſo, and we will ſtand or fall toge<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ther, for</l>
                     <l>Since wee, have gone ſo farre, that death muſt ſtay</l>
                     <l>The journey which we wiſh ſhould never end,</l>
                     <l>And innocent, or guilty we muſt die,</l>
                     <l>When we doe ſo, let's know the reaſon why.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <pb facs="tcp:47462:15" rendition="simple:additions"/>
                  <stage>Enter Thierry, and Courtiers.</stage>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Lecure.</speaker>
                     <l>The King.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Thier.</speaker>
                     <l>We'le be alone.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Prot.</speaker>
                     <l>I would I had</l>
                     <l>A convoy too, to bring me ſafe off,</l>
                     <l>For rage although it bee allaid with ſor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>row,</l>
                     <l>Appeares ſo dreadfull in him, that I ſhake</l>
                     <l>To looke upon it.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Brun.</speaker>
                     <l>Coward, I will meet it,</l>
                     <l>And know from whence t'as birth: ſonne, kingly <hi>Thierry.</hi>
                     </l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Thier.</speaker>
                     <l>Is cheating growne ſo common among men,</l>
                     <l>And thrives ſo well here, that the Gods endeavour</l>
                     <l>To practiſe it above?</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Brun.</speaker>
                     <l>Your mother.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Thier.</speaker>
                     <l>Ha! or are they onely carefull to revenge,</l>
                     <l>Not to reward? or when for your offences</l>
                     <l>We ſtudy ſatisfaction, muſt the cure</l>
                     <l>Be worſe then the diſeaſe?</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Brun.</speaker>
                     <l>Will you not heare me?</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Thier.</speaker>
                     <l>To loſe the ability to performe thoſe duties</l>
                     <l>For which I entertain'd the name of huſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>band,</l>
                     <l>Ask'd more then common ſorrow; but t'impoſe</l>
                     <l>For the redreſſe of that defect, a torture</l>
                     <l>In marking her to death, for whom alone</l>
                     <l>I felt that weakneſſe as a want, requires</l>
                     <l>More then the making the head bald? or falling</l>
                     <l>Thus flat upon the earth, or curſing that way,</l>
                     <l>Or praying this, oh ſuch a ſceane of griefe,</l>
                     <l>And ſo ſet downe, (the world the ſtage to act on)</l>
                     <l>May challenge a Tragedian better practis'd</l>
                     <l>Then I am to expreſſe it; for my cauſe</l>
                     <l>Of paſſion is ſo ſtrong, and my perfor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mance</l>
                     <l>So weake, that though the part bee good, I feare</l>
                     <l>Th'ill acting of it, will defraud it of</l>
                     <l>The poore reward it may deſerve, mens pity.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Brun.</speaker>
                     <l>I have given you way thus long, a King, and what</l>
                     <l>Is more, my ſonne, and yet a ſlave to that</l>
                     <l>Which onely triumphs over cowards ſor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>row</l>
                     <l>For ſhame looke up.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Thier.</speaker>
                     <l>I'ſt you, looke downe on me;</l>
                     <l>And if that you are capable to receive it,</l>
                     <l>Let that returne to you, that have brought forth</l>
                     <l>One mark'd out only for it: what are theſe?</l>
                     <l>Come they upon your priviledge, to tread on</l>
                     <l>The tombe of my afflictions?</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Prot.</speaker>
                     <l>No not wee Sir.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Thier.</speaker>
                     <l>How dare you then omit the ce<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>remony</l>
                     <l>Due to the funerall of all my hopes,</l>
                     <l>Or come unto the marriage of my ſorrowes,</l>
                     <l>But in ſuch colours as may ſort with them.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Prot.</speaker>
                     <l>Alas; we will weare any thing.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Brun.</speaker>
                     <l>This is madneſſe,</l>
                     <l>Take but my counſell.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Thier.</speaker>
                     <l>Yours? Dare you againe</l>
                     <l>Though arm'd with the authority of a mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther,</l>
                     <l>Attempt the donger that will fall on you</l>
                     <l>If ſuch another ſillable awake it?</l>
                     <l>Goe, and with yours be ſafe, I have ſuch cauſe</l>
                     <l>Of griefe, nay more, to love it, that I will not</l>
                     <l>Have ſuch as theſe be ſharers in it.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Lecure.</speaker>
                     <l>Madam.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Prot.</speaker>
                     <l>Another time were better.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Brun.</speaker>
                     <l>Doe not ſtirre,</l>
                     <l>For I muſt bee reſolv'd and will, be ſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tues.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <stage>Enter Martell.</stage>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Thier.</speaker>
                     <l>I, thou art welcome, and upon my ſoule</l>
                     <l>Thou art an honeſt man; doe you ſee, he has teares</l>
                     <l>To lend to him whom prodigall expence</l>
                     <l>Of ſorrow has made bankerout of ſuch treaſure,</l>
                     <l>Nay thou doeſt well.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Mart.</speaker>
                     <l>I would it might excuſe.</l>
                     <pb facs="tcp:47462:16" rendition="simple:additions"/>
                     <l>The ill I bring along.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Thier.</speaker>
                     <l>Thou makeſt me ſmile</l>
                     <l>In the height of my calamities, as if</l>
                     <l>There could be the addition of an Atome</l>
                     <l>To the gyant body of my miſeries.</l>
                     <l>But try, for I will heare thee; all ſit downe, 'tis death</l>
                     <l>To any that ſhall dare to interrupt him</l>
                     <l>In looke, geſture or word.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Mart.</speaker>
                     <l>And ſuch attention</l>
                     <l>As is due to the laſt, and the beſt ſtory</l>
                     <l>That ever was deliver'd, will become you,</l>
                     <l>The griev'd <hi>Ordella,</hi> (for all other titles</l>
                     <l>But take away from that) having from me</l>
                     <l>Prompted by your laſt parting groane, en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quir'd,</l>
                     <l>What drew it from you, and the cauſe ſoone learn'd:</l>
                     <l>For ſhee whom barbariſme could deny no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing,</l>
                     <l>With ſuch prevailing earneſtneſſe deſir'd it,</l>
                     <l>'Twas not in mee though it had beene my death,</l>
                     <l>To hide it from her; ſhe I ſay, in whom</l>
                     <l>All was, that <hi>Athens, Rome,</hi> or warlike <hi>Sparta,</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>Have regiſtred for good in their beſt wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men:</l>
                     <l>But nothing of their ill, knowing her ſelfe</l>
                     <l>Mark'd out, (I know not by what power, but ſure</l>
                     <l>A cruell one) to dye, to give you chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren;</l>
                     <l>Having firſt with a ſetled countenance</l>
                     <l>Look'd up to heaven, and then upon her ſelfe,</l>
                     <l>(It being the next beſt object) and then ſmil'd,</l>
                     <l>As if her joy in death to doe you ſervice,</l>
                     <l>Would break forth in deſpight of the much ſorrow</l>
                     <l>Shee ſhew'd ſhe had to leave you: and then taking</l>
                     <l>Mee by the hand, this hand which I muſt ever</l>
                     <l>Love better then I have done, ſince ſhee touch'd it,</l>
                     <l>Goe, ſaid ſhe, to my Lord, (and to goe to him</l>
                     <l>Is ſuch a happineſſe I muſt not hope for)</l>
                     <l>And tell him that hee too much priz'd a trifle</l>
                     <l>Made only worthy in his love, and her</l>
                     <l>Thankfull acceptance, for her ſake to robbe</l>
                     <l>The Orphan Kingdome of ſuch guardians, as</l>
                     <l>Muſt of neceſſitie deſcend from him;</l>
                     <l>And therefore in ſome part of recompence</l>
                     <l>Of his much love, and to ſhew to the world</l>
                     <l>That 'twas not her fault only, but her fate,</l>
                     <l>That did deny to let her be the mother</l>
                     <l>Of ſuch moſt certaine bleſſings: yet for proofe,</l>
                     <l>She did not envy her, that happy her,</l>
                     <l>That is appointed to them, her quick end</l>
                     <l>Should make way for her; which no ſoo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner ſpoke,</l>
                     <l>But in a moment this too ready engine</l>
                     <l>Made ſuch a battery in the choiſeſt caſtle</l>
                     <l>That ever nature made to defend life,</l>
                     <l>That ſtrait it ſhooke, and ſunke.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Thier.</speaker>
                     <l>Stay, dares any</l>
                     <l>Preſume to ſhed a teare before me? or</l>
                     <l>Aſcribe that worth unto themſelves to merit</l>
                     <l>To doe ſo for her? I have done, now on.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Mart.</speaker>
                     <l>Falne thus, once more ſhe ſmil'd, as if that death</l>
                     <l>For her had ſtudied a new way to ſever</l>
                     <l>The ſoule and body, without ſence of paine;</l>
                     <l>And then tell him quoth ſhee what you have ſeene,</l>
                     <l>And with what willingneſſe 'twas done: for which</l>
                     <l>My laſt requeſt unto him is, that he</l>
                     <l>Would inſtantly make choyce of one (moſt happy</l>
                     <l>In being ſo choſen) to ſupply my place,</l>
                     <l>By whom if heaven bleſſe him with a daughter,</l>
                     <l>In my remembrance let it beare my name</l>
                     <l>Which ſaid ſhe di'd.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Thier.</speaker>
                     <l>I heare this, and yet live;</l>
                     <l>Heart art thou thunder proofe, wil nothing breake thee?</l>
                     <l>Shee's dead, and what her entertainment may be</l>
                     <l>In th'other world without me is uncertaine,</l>
                     <l>And dare I ſtay here unreſolv'd?</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Mart.</speaker>
                     <l>Oh Sir!</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Brun.</speaker>
                     <l>Deare ſonne.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Pret.</speaker>
                     <l>Great King.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Thier.</speaker>
                     <l>Unhand me, am I falne</l>
                     <pb facs="tcp:47462:16" rendition="simple:additions"/>
                     <l>So low, that I have loſt the power to be</l>
                     <l>Diſpoſer of my owne life?</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Mart.</speaker>
                     <l>Be but pleas'd</l>
                     <l>To borrow ſo much time of ſorrow, as</l>
                     <l>To call to mind her laſt requeſt, for whom</l>
                     <l>(I muſt confeſſe a loſſe beyond expreſſion)</l>
                     <l>You turne your hand upon your ſelfe, 'twas hers</l>
                     <l>And dying hers, that you ſhould live and happy</l>
                     <l>In ſeeing little models of your ſelfe,</l>
                     <l>By matching with another, and will you</l>
                     <l>Leave any thing that ſhee deſir'd ungranted?</l>
                     <l>And ſuffer ſuch a life that was laid downe</l>
                     <l>For your ſake only to be fruitleſſe?</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Thier.</speaker>
                     <l>Oh thou doſt throw charmes up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on me, againſt which</l>
                     <l>I cannot ſtop my eares, beare witneſſe hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven</l>
                     <l>That not deſire of life, nor love of pleaſure</l>
                     <l>Nor any future comforts, but to give</l>
                     <l>Peace to her bleſſed ſpirit in ſatisfying</l>
                     <l>Her laſt demand, makes mee deferre our meeting,</l>
                     <l>Which in my choiſe, and ſuddaine choiſe ſhall bee</l>
                     <l>To all apparant,</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Brun.</speaker>
                     <l>How? doe I remove one miſchiefe</l>
                     <l>To draw upon my head a greater?</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Thier.</speaker>
                     <l>Goe, thou only good man, to whom for her ſelfe</l>
                     <l>Goodneſſe is deare, and prepare to interre it</l>
                     <l>In her that was; O my heart! my <hi>Ordella,</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>A monument worthy to be the casket</l>
                     <l>Of ſuch a jewell.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Mart.</speaker>
                     <l>Your command that makes way</l>
                     <l>Vnto my abſence is a welcome one,</l>
                     <l>For but your ſelfe there's nothing heere <hi>Martell</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>Can take delight to looke on; yet ſome comfort</l>
                     <l>Goes back with me, to her, who though ſhe want it</l>
                     <l>Deſerves all bleſſings.
<stage>Exit.</stage>
                     </l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Brun.</speaker>
                     <l>So ſoone to forget</l>
                     <l>The loſſe of ſuch a wife, beleeve it will</l>
                     <l>Be cenſur'd in the world.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Thier.</speaker>
                     <l>Pray you no more,</l>
                     <l>There is no argument you can uſe to croſſe it,</l>
                     <l>But does increaſe in me ſuch a ſuſpition</l>
                     <l>I would not cheriſh,—who's that?</l>
                  </sp>
                  <stage>Enter Memberge.</stage>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Memb.</speaker>
                     <l>One, no guard</l>
                     <l>Can put back from acceſſe, whoſe tongue no threats</l>
                     <l>Nor praiſes can ſilence, a bold ſuitor and</l>
                     <l>For that which if you are your ſelfe, a King,</l>
                     <l>You were made ſo to grant it, Juſtice, Juſtice.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Thier.</speaker>
                     <l>With what aſſurance dare you hope for that</l>
                     <l>Which is deni'd to me? or how can I</l>
                     <l>Stand bound to be juſt, unto ſuch as are</l>
                     <l>Beneath mee, that find none from thoſe that are</l>
                     <l>Above me.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Memb.</speaker>
                     <l>There is juſtice, 'twere unfit</l>
                     <l>That any thing but vengeance ſhould fall on him,</l>
                     <l>That by his giving way to more then mur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther,</l>
                     <l>For my deare fathers death was particide)</l>
                     <l>Makes it his owne.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Brun.</speaker>
                     <l>I charge you heare her not.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Memb.</speaker>
                     <l>Hell cannot ſtop juſt prayers from entring heaven,</l>
                     <l>I muſt and will be heard Sir; but remember</l>
                     <l>That he that by her plot fell, was your brother,</l>
                     <l>And the place where, your Palace, againſt all</l>
                     <l>Th'inviolable rites of Hoſpitality,</l>
                     <l>Your word, a Kings word, given up for his ſafety,</l>
                     <l>His innocence, his protection, and the Gods</l>
                     <l>Bound to revenge the impious breach of ſuch</l>
                     <l>So great and facred bonds; and can you wonder,</l>
                     <l>(That in not puniſhing ſuch a horrid mur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther</l>
                     <l>You did it) that heavens favour is gone from you?</l>
                     <l>Which never will returne untill his bloud</l>
                     <l>Be waſh'd away in hers.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Brun.</speaker>
                     <l>Drag hence the wretch.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Thier.</speaker>
                     <l>Forbeare: with what variety</l>
                     <l>Of torments doe I meete? Oh thou haſt open'd</l>
                     <pb facs="tcp:47462:17" rendition="simple:additions"/>
                     <l>A booke in which writ downe in bloudy letters,</l>
                     <l>My conſcience finds that I am worthy of</l>
                     <l>More then I undergoe, but i'le begin</l>
                     <l>For my <hi>Ordella's</hi> ſake, and for thine owne</l>
                     <l>To make leſſe heavens great anger: thou haſt loſt</l>
                     <l>A father, I to thee am ſo; the hope</l>
                     <l>Of a good husband, in mee have one; nor</l>
                     <l>Be fearfull I am ſtill no man, already</l>
                     <l>That weakneſſe is gone from me.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Brun.</speaker>
                     <l>That it might
<stage>aſide</stage>
                     </l>
                     <l>Have ever growne inſeparably upon thee,</l>
                     <l>What will you doe? Is ſuch a thing as this</l>
                     <l>Worthy the lov'd <hi>Ordella's</hi> place, the daughter</l>
                     <l>Of a poore Gardiner?</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Memb.</speaker>
                     <l>Your ſonne.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Thier.</speaker>
                     <l>The power</l>
                     <l>To take away that lowneſſe is in me.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Brun.</speaker>
                     <l>Stay yet, for rather then thou ſhalt adde</l>
                     <l>Inceſt unto thy other ſinnes, I will</l>
                     <l>With hazard of my owne life utter all</l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Theodoret</hi> was thy brother.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Thier.</speaker>
                     <l>You deni'd it,</l>
                     <l>Vpon your oath, nor will I now believe you,</l>
                     <l>Your Protean turnings cannot change my purpoſe.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Memb.</speaker>
                     <l>And for me, be aſſur'd the meanes to be.</l>
                     <l>Revenge on thee vile hag, admits no thought,</l>
                     <l>But what tends to it.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Brun.</speaker>
                     <l>Is it come to that?</l>
                     <l>Then have at the laſt refuge; art thou growne</l>
                     <l>Inſenſible in ill, that thou goeſt on</l>
                     <l>Without the leaſt compunction? there, take that</l>
                     <l>To witneſſe that thou hadſt a mother, which</l>
                     <l>Foreſaw thy cauſe of griefe, and ſad repentance,</l>
                     <l>That ſo ſoone after bleſt <hi>Ordella's</hi> death</l>
                     <l>Without a teare thou canſt imbrace another,</l>
                     <l>Forgetfull man.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Thier.</speaker>
                     <l>Mine eyes when ſhe is nam'd</l>
                     <l>Connot forget their tribute, and your gift</l>
                     <l>Is not unuſefull now</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Lecure.</speaker>
                     <l>He's paſt all cure, that onely touch is death.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Thier.</speaker>
                     <l>This night i'le keep it,</l>
                     <l>To morrow I will ſend it you, and full of my affliction.
<stage>Exit Thierry.</stage>
                     </l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Brun.</speaker>
                     <l>Is the poyſon mortall?</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Lecure.</speaker>
                     <l>Above the helpe of phyſick.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Brun.</speaker>
                     <l>To my wiſh,</l>
                     <l>Now for our owne ſecurity, you <hi>Protaldye</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>Shall this night poſt towards <hi>Auſtracia,</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>With letters to <hi>Theodorets</hi> baſtard ſonne,</l>
                     <l>In which wee will make knowne what for his riſing</l>
                     <l>We have done to <hi>Thierry:</hi> no deniall,</l>
                     <l>Nor no excuſe in ſuch acts muſt bee though of,</l>
                     <l>Which all diſlike, and all againe commend</l>
                     <l>When they are brought unto a happy end</l>
                  </sp>
                  <stage>Exeunt.</stage>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div n="5" type="act">
               <head>
                  <hi>Act.</hi> 5.</head>
               <div n="3" type="scene">
                  <head>
                     <hi>Scoe.</hi> 3.</head>
                  <stage>
                     <hi>Enter Devitry, and</hi> 4 <hi>Souldiers.</hi>
                  </stage>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Devitry.</speaker>
                     <p>No war, no money, no Maſter; baniſh't the Court, not truſted in the City, whipt out of the countrey, in what a triangle runnes our miſery: let mee heare which of you has the beſt voice to beg in, for other hopes or fortunes I ſee you have not; be not nice, nature provided you with tones for the purpoſe, the peoples charity was your heritage, and I would ſee which of you de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerves his birth-right.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Omnes.</speaker>
                     <p>Wee underſtand you not Cap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Devit.</speaker>
                     <p>You ſee this cardicue, the laſt and the only quinteſſence of 50 crownes, diſtill'd in the lembicke of your gardage, of which happy piece thou ſhalt be treaſurer: now he that can ſooneſt perſwade him to part with't, enjoyes it, poſſeſſes it, and with it, mee and my future countenance.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>1.</speaker>
                     <p>If they want art to perſwade it, I'le keepe it my ſelfe.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Devit.</speaker>
                     <p>So you be not a partiall judge in your owne cauſe, you ſhall.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Omnes.</speaker>
                     <p>A match.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>2.</speaker>
                     <p>I'le begin to you, brave Sir; be proud to make him happy by your liberality, whoſe tongue vouchſafes now to petition, was ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver heard before leſſe then to command. I
<pb facs="tcp:47462:17" rendition="simple:additions"/> am a ſouldier by profeſſion, a gentleman by birth, and an officer by place, whoſe pover<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty bluſhes to be the cauſe that ſo high a ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tue ſhould deſcend to the pitie of your cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritie.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>1.</speaker>
                     <p>In any caſe keep your high ſtile, it is not charity to ſhame any man, much leſſe a vertue of your eminence, wherefore pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerve your worth, and i'le preſerve my money.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>3.</speaker>
                     <p>You perſwade? you are ſhallow, give way to merit: ah by the bread of good man, thou haſt a bonny countenance and a blith, promiſing mickle good to a ſicker wombe, that has trod a long and a ſoare ground to meet with friends that will owe much to thy reverence, when they ſhall heare of thy cur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſie to their wandring countreyman.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>1.</speaker>
                     <p>You that will uſe your friends ſo hard<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly to bring them in debt Sir, will deſerve worſe of a ſtranger, wherefore pead on, pead on I ſay.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>4.</speaker>
                     <p>It is the welch muſt do't I ſee, comrade man of urſhip, St. <hi>Tavy</hi> be her patron, the Gods of the mountaines keepe her cow and her cupboard, may ſhe never want the green of the leeke and the fat of the onion, if ſhee part with her bounties to him that is a great deale away from her cozines, and has too big ſuites in law to recover her he<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritage.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>1.</speaker>
                     <p>Pardon me Sir, I will have nothing to doe with your ſuites, it comes within the ſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tute of maintenance: home to your cozines, and ſow garlick and hemp-ſeed, the one will ſtop your hunger, the other end your ſuites, <hi>gammawaſh comrade, gamma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>waſh.</hi>
                     </p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>4.</speaker>
                     <p>Foot he'le hoord all for himſelfe.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Vitry.</speaker>
                     <p>Yes, let him; now comes my turne, i'le ſee if he can anſwer mee: ſave you Sir, they ſay you have that I want, money.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>1.</speaker>
                     <p>And that you are like to want, for ought I perceive yet.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Vitry.</speaker>
                     <p>Stand, deliver.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>1.</speaker>
                     <p>Foot what meane you, you will not rob the Exchequer?</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Vitry.</speaker>
                     <p>Doe you prate?</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>1.</speaker>
                     <p>Hold, hold, here Captaine.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>2.</speaker>
                     <p>Why I could have done this before you.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>3.</speaker>
                     <p>And I.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>4.</speaker>
                     <p>And I.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Vitry.</speaker>
                     <p>You have done this, brave man he proud to make him happy, by the bread of God man thou haſt a bonny countenance, comrade man of u<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>ſhip, St. <hi>Tavy</hi> be her pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tron, cut upon you, you uncurried colts, walk<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing cans that have no ſouls in you, but a little roſin to keepe your ribs ſweet, and hold in liquor.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Omnes.</speaker>
                     <p>Why, what would you have us to doe Captaine?</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Devitry.</speaker>
                     <p>Beg, beg, and keepe Conſtables waking, weare out ſtocks and whipcord, man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der for buttermilke, dye of the jaundice, yet have the cure about you, lice, large lice, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>got of your owne duſt, and the heate of the brick-kills, may you ſtarve, and feare of the gallowes, which is a gentle conſumption to't, only preferre it, or may you fall upon your feare, and be hanged for ſelling thoſe purſes to keepe you from famine whoſe monies my valour empties, and be caſt without other e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vidence; here is my fort, my caſtle of de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fence, who comes by ſhall pay me tolle, the firſt purſe is your mittimus ſlaves.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>2.</speaker>
                     <p>The purſe, foot we'le ſhare in the mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ney Captaine, if any come within a furlong of our fingers.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>4.</speaker>
                     <p>Did you doubt but wee could ſteale as well as your ſelfe, did not I ſpeake welch?</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>3.</speaker>
                     <p>We are theeves from our cradles, an will dye ſo.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Vitry.</speaker>
                     <p>Then you will not beg againe.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Omnes?</speaker>
                     <p>Yes, as you did, ſtand, and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liver.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>2.</speaker>
                     <p>Harke, here comes handſell, 'tis a trade quickly ſet up, and as ſoone caſt downe.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Vitry.</speaker>
                     <p>Have goodneſſe in your minds var<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lets, and to't like men; he that has more mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ney than wee, cannet bee our friend, and I hope there is no law for ſpoyling the e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nemie.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>3.</speaker>
                     <p>You need not inſtruct us farther, your example pleads enough.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Devitry.</speaker>
                     <p>Diſperſe your ſelves, and as their company is, fall on.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>2.</speaker>
                     <p>Come, there are a band of them, i'le charge ſingle.
<stage>Exit ſouldiers.</stage>
                     </p>
                  </sp>
                  <pb facs="tcp:47462:18" rendition="simple:additions"/>
                  <stage>Enter Protaldye.</stage>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Prot.</speaker>
                     <p>'Tis wonderfull dark, I have loſt my man, and dare not call for him, leſt I ſhould have more followers then I would pay wages to; what throwes am I in, in this travaile? theſe be honourable adventure; had I that honeſt blood in my veines againe Queene, that your feats and theſe frights have drain'd from me, honour ſhould pull hard ere it drew me into theſe brakes.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Devitry.</speaker>
                     <p>Who goes there?</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Prot.</speaker>
                     <p>Hey ho, here's a pang of preferment.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Devi.</speaker>
                     <p>Hart, who goes there?</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Prot.</speaker>
                     <p>Hee that has no heart to your ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quaintance, what ſhall I doe with my jewels and my letter, my cod-peece, that's too looſe, good, my boots, who iſt that ſpoke to mee? here's a friend.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Devit.</speaker>
                     <p>We ſhall find that preſently, ſtand, as you love your ſafety ſtand.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Prot.</speaker>
                     <p>That unlucky word of ſtanding has brought me to all this, hold, or I ſhall never ſtand you.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Devitry.</speaker>
                     <p>I ſhould know that voice, de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liver.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <stage>Enter Souldiers.</stage>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Prot.</speaker>
                     <p>All that I have is at your ſervice Gentlemen, and much good may it doe you.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Devitry.</speaker>
                     <p>Zones downe with him, doe you prate?</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Prot.</speaker>
                     <p>Keepe your firſt word as you are Gentlemen, and let me ſtand, alas what doe you meane?</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>2.</speaker>
                     <p>To tye you to us Sir, bind you in the knot of friendſhip.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Prot.</speaker>
                     <p>Alas Sir, all the phyſick in <hi>Europe</hi> cannot bind me.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Devit.</speaker>
                     <p>You ſhould have jewels about you, ſtones, precious ſtones.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>1.</speaker>
                     <p>Captaine away, there's company with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in hearing, if you ſtay longer wee are ſur<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>priz'd.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Devitry.</speaker>
                     <p>Let the Devill come, i'le pillage this frigot a little better yet.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>2.</speaker>
                     <p>Foot we are loſt, they are upon us.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Devitry.</speaker>
                     <p>Ha, upon us, make the leaſt noiſe, 'tis thy parting gaſpe.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>3.</speaker>
                     <p>Which way ſhall we make Sir?</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Devitry.</speaker>
                     <p>Every man his owne; doe you heare, onely bind me before you goe, and when the companie's paſt, make to this place againe, this karvell ſhould have better ladine in him, you are ſlow, why doe you not tye harder?</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>1.</speaker>
                     <p>You are ſure enough I warrant you Sir.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Devitry.</speaker>
                     <p>Darkneſſe befriend you, away.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <stage>Exit ſouldiers.</stage>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Prot.</speaker>
                     <p>What tyrants have I met with? they leave me alone in the darke, yet would not have me cry. I ſhall grow wondrous melan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>choly if I ſtay long here without company; I was wont to get a nap with ſaying my pray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers, i'le ſee if they will worke upon me now; but then if I ſhould talk in my ſleep, and they heare me, they would make a Recorder of my windpipe, ſlit my throate: heaven bee prais'd, I heare ſome noiſe, it may bee new purchaſe, and then I ſhall have fellowes.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Devitry.</speaker>
                     <p>They are gone paſt hearing, now to taske <hi>Devitry,</hi> helpe, helpe, as you are men helpe, ſome charitable hand, relieve a poore diſtreſſed miſerable wretch; theeves, wicked theeves have rob'd me, bound me.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Prot.</speaker>
                     <p>Foot would they had gag'd you too, your noiſe will betray us, and fetch them a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gaine.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Devit.</speaker>
                     <p>What bleſſed tongue ſpake to me, where, where are you Sir?</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Prot.</speaker>
                     <p>A plague of your bawling throate, we are well enough, if you have the grace to be thankfull for't, doe but ſnore to mee, and 'tis as much as I deſire, to paſſe away time with till morning, then talke as loud as you pleaſe Sir, I am bound not to ſtir, therefore lie ſtill and ſnore I ſay.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Devit.</speaker>
                     <p>Then you have met with theeves too I ſee.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Prot.</speaker>
                     <p>And deſire to meet with no more of them.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Devit.</speaker>
                     <p>Alas what can wee ſuffer more? they are far enough by this time; have they not all, all that we have Sir?</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Prot.</speaker>
                     <p>No by my faith have they not Sir; I gave them one trick to boote for their lear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning, my bootes Sir, my bootes, I have ſav'd my ſtock, and my jewels in them, and there<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>fore deſire to heare no more of them.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Devit.</speaker>
                     <p>Now bleſſing on your wit Sir, what a dull ſlave was I, dreampt not of your conveyance? helpe to unbidd me Sir, and
<pb facs="tcp:47462:18" rendition="simple:additions"/> i'le undoe you, my life for yours no worſe theefe than my ſelfe meetes you againe this night.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Prot.</speaker>
                     <p>Reach me thy hands.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Devit.</speaker>
                     <p>Here Sir, here, I could beate my braines out, that could not thinke of bootes, bootes Sir, wide topt boots, I ſhall love them the better whilſt I live; but are you ſure your jewels are here Sir?</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Prot.</speaker>
                     <p>Sure ſayſt thou? ha, ha, ha.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Devit.</speaker>
                     <l>So ho, illo ho.
<stage>Within ſouldiers.</stage>
                     </l>
                     <l>Here Captaine, here.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Prot.</speaker>
                     <p>Foote what doe you meane Sir?</p>
                  </sp>
                  <stage>Enter Souldiers.</stage>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Devit.</speaker>
                     <p>A trick to boote, ſay you; here you dull ſlaves, purchaſe, purchaſe the ſoule of the rock, diamonds, ſparkling diamonds.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Prot.</speaker>
                     <p>I am betraid, loſt, paſt recovery loſt, as you are men.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Devit,</speaker>
                     <p>Nay Rooke, ſince you will be pra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting, wee'l ſhare your carion with you, have you any other conveyance now Sir?</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>1.</speaker>
                     <p>Foot here are letters, epiſtles, familiar epiſtles, wee'l ſee what treaſure is in them, they are ſeal'd ſure,</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Pro,</speaker>
                     <p>Gentlemen, as you are gentlemen ſpare my letters, and take all willingly, all: i'le give you a releaſe, a generall releaſe, and meete you here too morrow with as much more.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Devit.</speaker>
                     <p>Nay, ſince you have your trickes, and your conveyances, wee will not leave a wrinckle of you unſearcht.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Prot.</speaker>
                     <p>Harke, there comes company, you will be betraid, as you love your ſafeties beat out my braines, I ſhall betray you elſe.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Devitry.</speaker>
                     <p>Treaſon, unheard of treaſon monſtrous, monſtrous villanies.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Prot.</speaker>
                     <p>I confeſſe my ſelfe a traytor, ſhew your ſelves good ſubjects, and hang mee up for't.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>1.</speaker>
                     <p>If it be treaſon, the diſcovery will get our pardon Captaine.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Devit.</speaker>
                     <p>Would wee were all loſt, hang'd, quarter'd to ſave this one, one innocent Prince; <hi>Thierry</hi>'s poyſon'd, by his mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther poyſon'd, the Miſtris to this ſtallion, who by that poyſon ne're ſhall ſleep againe.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>2</speaker>
                     <p>Foot let us mince him by piecemeale, till he eate himſelfe up.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>3.</speaker>
                     <p>Let us dig out his heart with needles, and halfe broile him, like a muſſell.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Prot.</speaker>
                     <p>Such another and I prevent you, my blood's ſetled already.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Devit.</speaker>
                     <p>Here's that ſhall remove it, toade, viper, drag him unto <hi>Martell,</hi> unnaturall par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ricide, cruell, bloody woman.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Omnes.</speaker>
                     <p>On you dogfiſh, leech, caterpiller.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Deuit.</speaker>
                     <p>A longer ſight of him will make my rage turne pitie, and with his ſuddaine end prevent revenge and torture, wicked, wicked <hi>Brunhalt.</hi>
                        <stage>Exit.</stage>
                     </p>
                  </sp>
                  <stage>
                     <hi>Enter Bawdber, and</hi> 3. <hi>Courtiers.</hi>
                  </stage>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>1.</speaker>
                     <p>Not ſleep at all, no meanes.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>2.</speaker>
                     <p>No art can doe it.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Bawdb.</speaker>
                     <l>I will aſſure you hee can ſleep no more</l>
                     <l>Then a hooded hawke, a centinell to him,</l>
                     <l>Or one of the City Conſtables are tops.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>3.</speaker>
                     <l>How came he ſo?</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Bawdb.</speaker>
                     <l>They are too wiſe that dare know,</l>
                     <l>Somethings amiſſe, heaven helpe all.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>1.</speaker>
                     <l>What cures has he?</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Bawdb.</speaker>
                     <l>Armies of thoſe wee call Phyſici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans, ſome with gliſters,</l>
                     <l>Some with lettice caps, ſome poſſet drinkes ſome pills,</l>
                     <l>Twenty conſulting here about a drench,</l>
                     <l>As many here to blood him;</l>
                     <l>Then comes a Don of <hi>Spaine,</hi> and he pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcribes</l>
                     <l>More cooling opium then would kill a turk,</l>
                     <l>Or quench a whore i'th dogdayes; after him</l>
                     <l>A wife Italian, and he cries, tie unto him</l>
                     <l>A woman of foureſcore, whoſe bones are marble,</l>
                     <l>Whoſe blond ſnow water, not ſo much heate about her</l>
                     <l>As may conceive a prayer: after him</l>
                     <l>An Engliſh Doctor, with a bunch of pot hearbes,</l>
                     <l>And he cries out Endiffe and ſuckery,</l>
                     <l>With a few mallow rootes and buttermilke,</l>
                     <l>And talkes of oyle made of a Churchmans charity,</l>
                     <l>Yet ſtill he wakes.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>1.</speaker>
                     <l>But your good honour</l>
                     <l>Has a prayer in ſtore if all ſhould faile.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Bawdb.</speaker>
                     <l>I could have prayed, and hand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſomely,</l>
                     <l>But age and an ill memory.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <pb facs="tcp:47462:19" rendition="simple:additions"/>
                  <gap reason="duplicate" resp="#OXF" extent="1 page">
                     <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <pb facs="tcp:47462:19" rendition="simple:additions"/>
                  <gap reason="duplicate" resp="#OXF" extent="1 page">
                     <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <pb facs="tcp:47462:20" rendition="simple:additions"/>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>3.</speaker>
                     <l>Has ſpoll'd your primmer.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Bawdb.</speaker>
                     <l>Yet if there be a man of faith i'th Court,</l>
                     <l>An can pray for a penſion.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <stage>Enter Thierry on a bed, with Doctors and Attendants.</stage>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>2.</speaker>
                     <l>Here's the King Sir,</l>
                     <l>And thoſe that will pray without pay.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Bawdb.</speaker>
                     <l>Then pray for me too.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>1. <hi>Doct.</hi>
                     </speaker>
                     <l>How does your Grace feele your ſelfe now?</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Thier.</speaker>
                     <l>What's that?</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>1. <hi>Doct.</hi>
                     </speaker>
                     <l>Nothing at all Sir, but your fancy.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Thier.</speaker>
                     <l>Tell me,</l>
                     <l>Can ever theſe eyes more ſhut up in ſlum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bers,</l>
                     <l>Aſſure my ſoule there is ſleepe? is there night</l>
                     <l>And reſt for humane labours? doe not you</l>
                     <l>And all the world as I doe, out-ſtare time,</l>
                     <l>And live like funerall lampes never extin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guiſht?</l>
                     <l>Is there a grave, and doe not flatter me,</l>
                     <l>Nor feare to tell mee truth; and in that grave</l>
                     <l>Is there a hope I ſhall ſleepe, can I die,</l>
                     <l>Are not my miſeries immortall? oh</l>
                     <l>The happines of him that drinkes his water</l>
                     <l>After his weary day, and ſleepes for ever,</l>
                     <l>Why doe you crucifie mee thus with faces,</l>
                     <l>And gaping ſtrangely upon one another,</l>
                     <l>When ſhall I reſt?</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>2. <hi>Doct.</hi>
                     </speaker>
                     <l>O Sir be patient.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Thier.</speaker>
                     <l>Am I not patient? have I not en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dur'd</l>
                     <l>More then a maingy dog among your doſſes?</l>
                     <l>Am I not now your patient? ye can make</l>
                     <l>Unwholſome fooles ſleepe for a guarded foot-cloth,</l>
                     <l>Whores for a hot ſinne offering; yet I muſt crave</l>
                     <l>That feede ye, and protect ye, and pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clame ye,</l>
                     <l>Becauſe my power is farre above your ſearching,</l>
                     <l>Are my diſeaſes ſo? can ye cure none</l>
                     <l>But thoſe of equall ignorance, dare yee kill me?</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>1. <hi>Doct.</hi>
                     </speaker>
                     <l>We doe beſeech your grace bee more reclaim'd,</l>
                     <l>This talke doth but diſtemper you.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Thier.</speaker>
                     <l>Well, I will die</l>
                     <l>In ſpight of all your potions; one of you ſleepe,</l>
                     <l>Lie downe and ſleep here, that I may behold</l>
                     <l>What bleſſed reſt it is my eyes are rob'd of:</l>
                     <l>See, hee can ſleepe, ſleep any where, ſleep now,</l>
                     <l>When hee that wakes for him can never ſlumber,</l>
                     <l>I'ſt not a dainty eaſe?</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>2. <hi>Doct.</hi>
                     </speaker>
                     <l>Your Grace ſhall feele it.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Thier.</speaker>
                     <l>O never I, never, the eyes of heaven</l>
                     <l>See but their certaine motions, and then ſleepe,</l>
                     <l>The rages of the <hi>Ocean</hi> have their ſlumbers,</l>
                     <l>And quiet ſilver calmes; each violence</l>
                     <l>Crownes in his end a peace, but my fixt fires</l>
                     <l>Shall never, never ſet, who's that?</l>
                  </sp>
                  <stage>Enter Martell, Brunhalt, Devitry, Souldiers.</stage>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Mart.</speaker>
                     <l>No woman,</l>
                     <l>Mother of miſchiefe, no the day ſhall die firſt,</l>
                     <l>And all good things live in a worſe then thou art,</l>
                     <l>Ere thou ſhalt ſleepe, doſt thou ſee him?</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Brun.</speaker>
                     <l>Yes, and curſe him,</l>
                     <l>And all that love him foole, and all live by him.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Mart.</speaker>
                     <l>Why art thou ſuch a monſter?</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Brun.</speaker>
                     <l>Why art thou</l>
                     <l>So tame a knave to aske me?</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Mart.</speaker>
                     <l>Hope of hell,</l>
                     <l>By this faire holy light, and all his wrongs</l>
                     <l>Which are above thy yeares, almoſt thy <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                           <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                        </gap>
                     </l>
                     <l>Thou ſhalt not reſt, not feele more what is pity,</l>
                     <l>Know nothing neceſſary, meet no ſociety.</l>
                     <l>But what ſhall curſe and crucifie thee, feele in thy ſelfe</l>
                     <l>Nothing but what thou art, bane and bad conſcience,</l>
                     <l>Till this man reſt; but for whoſe reverence</l>
                     <l>Becauſe thou art his mother, I would ſay</l>
                     <l>Whore, this ſhall bee, doe ye nod? i'le wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken ye</l>
                     <pb facs="tcp:47462:20" rendition="simple:additions"/>
                     <l>With my ſwords point.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Brun.</speaker>
                     <l>I wiſh no more of heaven,</l>
                     <l>Nor hope no more, but a ſufficient anger</l>
                     <l>To torture thee.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Mart.</speaker>
                     <l>See, ſhe that makes you ſee Sir</l>
                     <l>And to your miſery ſtill ſee your mother,</l>
                     <l>The mother of your woes Sir, of your wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king,</l>
                     <l>The mother of your peoples cries and curſes,</l>
                     <l>Your murdering mother, your malicious mother.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Thier.</speaker>
                     <l>Phyſicians, halfe my ſtate to ſleepe an houre now;</l>
                     <l>Is it ſo mother?</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Brun.</speaker>
                     <l>Yes it is ſo ſonne;</l>
                     <l>And were it yet againe to doe, it ſhould be.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Mart.</speaker>
                     <l>She nods againe, ſwing her.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Thier.</speaker>
                     <l>But mother,</l>
                     <l>For yet I love that reverence, and to death</l>
                     <l>Dare not forget you have been ſo; was this,</l>
                     <l>This endleſſe miſerie, this cureleſſe malice,</l>
                     <l>This ſnatching from mee all my youth to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether,</l>
                     <l>All that you made mee for, and happy mothers</l>
                     <l>Crown'd with eternall time are proud to finiſh,</l>
                     <l>Done by your will?</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Brun.</speaker>
                     <l>It was, and by that will.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Thier.</speaker>
                     <l>O mother, doe not loſe your name, forget not</l>
                     <l>The touch of nature in you, tendernes</l>
                     <l>'Tis all the ſoule of woman, all the ſweetnes;</l>
                     <l>Forget not I beſeech you what are children,</l>
                     <l>Nor how you have gron'd for them, to what love</l>
                     <l>They are borne inheritors, with what care kept,</l>
                     <l>And as they riſe to ripeneſſe ſtill remember</l>
                     <l>How they impe out your age; and <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                           <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                        </gap> time calls you,</l>
                     <l>That as an Autumne flower you fall, forget not</l>
                     <l>How round about your hearſe they hang like penons.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Brun.</speaker>
                     <l>Holy foole,</l>
                     <l>Whoſe patience to prevent my wrongs has kill'd thee,</l>
                     <l>Preach not to me of puniſhments or feares,</l>
                     <l>Or what I ought to be, but what I am,</l>
                     <l>A woman in her liberall will defeated,</l>
                     <l>In all her greatnes croſt, in pleaſures blaſted,</l>
                     <l>My angers have beene laught at, my ends ſlighted,</l>
                     <l>And all thoſe glories that had crown'd my fortunes,</l>
                     <l>Suffer'd by blaſted vertue to be ſcatter'd,</l>
                     <l>I am the fruitfull mother of theſe angers,</l>
                     <l>And what ſuch have done, reade, and know thy ruine.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Thier.</speaker>
                     <l>Heaven forgive you.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Mart.</speaker>
                     <l>She tels you true, for millions of her miſchiefes</l>
                     <l>Are now apparent, <hi>Protaldye</hi> wee have taken</l>
                     <l>An equall agent with her, to whoſe care</l>
                     <l>After the damn'd defeat on you, ſhe truſted</l>
                     <stage>Enter Meſſenger.</stage>
                     <l>The bringing in of <hi>Leonor</hi> the baſtard</l>
                     <l>Sonne to your murder'd brother; her phy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſitian</l>
                     <l>By this time is attacht to that damn'd devill.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Meſſen.</speaker>
                     <l>'Tis like hee will bee ſo, for ere we came,</l>
                     <l>Fearing an equall juſtice for his miſchiefes,</l>
                     <l>He drench't himſelfe.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Brun.</speaker>
                     <l>He did like one of mine then.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Thier.</speaker>
                     <l>Muſt I ſtill ſee theſe miſeries, no night</l>
                     <l>To hide me from their horrors, that <hi>Protaldy</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>See juſtice fall upon.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Brun.</speaker>
                     <l>Now I could ſleepe too.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <stage>Enter Ordella</stage>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Mart.</speaker>
                     <l>Ile give you yet more poppy, bring the Lady</l>
                     <l>And heaven in her embraces; gives him quiet</l>
                     <l>Madam, unvaile your ſelfe.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Ordella.</speaker>
                     <l>I doe forgive you,</l>
                     <l>And though you ſought my blood, yet ile pray for you,</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Brun.</speaker>
                     <l>Art thou alive?</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Mart.</speaker>
                     <l>Now could you ſleepe.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Brun.</speaker>
                     <l>For ever.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Mart.</speaker>
                     <l>Go carry her without wink of ſleepe, or quiet,</l>
                     <l>Where her ſtrong knave <hi>Protaldy's</hi> broke oth wheele,</l>
                     <l>And let his cryes &amp; roares be muſick toner,</l>
                     <l>I mean to waken her.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Thier.</speaker>
                     <l>Do her no wrong.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <pb facs="tcp:47462:21" rendition="simple:additions"/>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Mart.</speaker>
                     <l>Nor right as you love juſtice.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Brun.</speaker>
                     <l>I will thinke,</l>
                     <l>And if there be new curſes in old nature,</l>
                     <l>I have a ſoule dare ſend them.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Mart.</speaker>
                     <l>Keepe her waking.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <stage>Exit Brunhalt.</stage>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Thier.</speaker>
                     <p>What's that appeares ſo ſweetly? their's that face.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Mart.</speaker>
                     <l>Be moderate Lady.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Their.</speaker>
                     <l>That angels face.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Mart.</speaker>
                     <l>Go neraer.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Thier.</speaker>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Martell,</hi> I cannot laſt long, ſee the ſoule,</l>
                     <l>I ſee it perfectly of my <hi>Ordella,</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>The heavenly figure of her ſweetneſſe there,</l>
                     <l>Forgive mee Gods, it comes, divineſt ſubſtance,</l>
                     <l>Kneele, kneele, kneele every one, Saint of thy ſexe,</l>
                     <l>If it be for my cruelty thou comeſt,</l>
                     <l>Do ye ſee her hoe?</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Mart.</speaker>
                     <l>Yes Sir, and you ſhall know her.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Thier,</speaker>
                     <l>Downe, downe againe, to bee re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veng'd for bloud,</l>
                     <l>Sweet ſpirit I am ready, ſhe ſmiles on me,</l>
                     <l>O bleſſed ſigne of peace.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Mart.</speaker>
                     <l>Goe neerer Lady.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Ordella.</speaker>
                     <l>I come to make you happy</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Thier.</speaker>
                     <l>Heare you that Sir?</l>
                     <l>She comes to crowne my ſoule away, get ſacrifice,</l>
                     <l>Whil'ſt I with holy honours.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Mart.</speaker>
                     <l>Shee's alive ſir.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Thier.</speaker>
                     <l>In everlaſting life I know it friend,</l>
                     <l>O happy, happy ſoule.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Ordella.</speaker>
                     <l>Alas I live Sir</l>
                     <l>A mortall woman ſtill.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Thier.</speaker>
                     <l>Can ſpirits weepe too?</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Mart.</speaker>
                     <l>Shee's no ſpirit Sir, pray kiſſe her; Lady,</l>
                     <l>Be very gentle to him.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Thier.</speaker>
                     <l>Stay, ſhe is warme,</l>
                     <l>And by my life the ſame lips tell me bright<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe,</l>
                     <l>Are you the ſame <hi>Ordella</hi> ſtill?</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Mart.</speaker>
                     <l>The ſame Sir.</l>
                     <l>Whom heavens and my good Angell ſtaid from ruine.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Thier.</speaker>
                     <l>Kiſſe me againe.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Ordella.</speaker>
                     <l>The ſame ſtill, ſtill your ſervant.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Thier.</speaker>
                     <l>'Tis ſhe, I know her now <hi>Martell;</hi> ſit downe ſweet,</l>
                     <l>O bleſt and happieſt woman, a dead ſlumber</l>
                     <l>Begins to creep upon me, O my jewell!</l>
                  </sp>
                  <stage>Enter Meſſenger and Memberge.</stage>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Ordella,</speaker>
                     <l>O ſleepe my Lord.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Thier.</speaker>
                     <l>My joyes are too much for me.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Meſſen.</speaker>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Brunhalt</hi> impatient of her con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtraint to fee</l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Protaldye</hi> tortur'd, has chokt her ſelfe.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Mort.</speaker>
                     <l>No more, her ſinnes goe with her.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Thier.</speaker>
                     <l>Love I muſt die, I faint, cloſe up my glaſſes.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>1. <hi>Doct.</hi>
                     </speaker>
                     <l>The Queen faints too, and deadly.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Thier.</speaker>
                     <l>One dying kiſſe.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Ordella.</speaker>
                     <l>My laſt Sir, and my deareſt, and now</l>
                     <l>Cloſe my eyes too.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Thier.</speaker>
                     <l>Thou perfect woman,</l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Martell,</hi> the Kingdome's yours, take <hi>Mem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>berge</hi> to you,</l>
                     <l>And keep my line alive; nay weep not Lady,</l>
                     <l>Take me, I goe.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Ordella.</speaker>
                     <l>Take mee too, farewell honour.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <stage>Dies both.</stage>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>2. <hi>Doct.</hi>
                     </speaker>
                     <l>They are gone for ever.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Mart.</speaker>
                     <l>The peace of happy ſoules goe af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter them,</l>
                     <l>Beare them to their laſt beds, whilſt I ſtudy</l>
                     <l>A tombe to ſpeake their loves; whilſt old time laſteth,</l>
                     <l>I am your King in ſorrowes.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Omnes.</speaker>
                     <l>We your ſubjects.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Mart.</speaker>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Devitry,</hi> for your ſervice, bee neere us,</l>
                     <l>Whip out theſe inſtruments of this mad mother</l>
                     <l>From Court, and all good people; and be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe</l>
                     <l>She was borne noble, let that title find her</l>
                     <l>A private grave, but neither tongue nor honour:</l>
                     <l>And now lead on, they that ſhall read this ſtory,</l>
                     <l>Shall find that vertue lives in good, not glory.
<stage>Exeunt Omnes.</stage>
                     </l>
                  </sp>
               </div>
            </div>
            <trailer>FINIS</trailer>
            <pb facs="tcp:47462:21"/>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
