<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>The fatal contract, a French tragedy as it vvas acted vvith great applause by Her Majesties servants / written by William Hemings ...</title>
            <author>Hemings, William, b. 1602?</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1653</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 160 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 36 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2012-10">2012-10 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A43306</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing H1422</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R12659</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">13311812</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 13311812</idno>
            <idno type="VID">98989</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A43306)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 98989)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 458:2)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>The fatal contract, a French tragedy as it vvas acted vvith great applause by Her Majesties servants / written by William Hemings ...</title>
                  <author>Hemings, William, b. 1602?</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[72] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>for J. M. ...,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>Printed at London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1653.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Dedication signed: A. T.; A. P.</note>
                  <note>Revived by Settle in 1675 as "Love and revenge", and reprinted in 1687, from text of 1653, under title: The eunuch.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in Huntington Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2008-08</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2008-10</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-08</date>
            <label>John Latta</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-08</date>
            <label>John Latta</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-05</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:98989:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:98989:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>THE Fatal Contract, A <hi>French</hi> TRAGEDY. As it was Acted vvith great Applauſe by her <hi>Majeſties</hi> SERVANTS.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Written by</hi> William Hemings, <hi>Maſter of Arts of</hi> Oxon.</p>
            <p>Printed by the Original Copy.</p>
            <p>Printed at <hi>London</hi> for <hi>J. M.</hi> in the Year, 1653.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="dedication">
            <pb facs="tcp:98989:2" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:98989:2"/>
            <head>To the Right Honourable, <hi>James Compton</hi> Earl of <hi>Northampton,</hi> and Lord <hi>Compton, &amp;c.</hi> and to <hi>Iſabella</hi> his vertuous Counteſſe.</head>
            <opener>
               <salute>My Lord,</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>This <hi>Poem</hi> was compoſed by a worthy Gentleman at hours of his receſs from happier employments. In his life he was above the Sphere of common Writers, and though at death he left greater Monuments of his worth and abilitie, yet this piece had juſtly gain'd an eſteem with men of excellent judgement; and having ſuffered very much by private Tranſcripts, where it paſt through many hands as a Curioſity of Wit and Language, it is now emergent from darkneſs, and appears in a publike dreſs, having ſhaken off ſome duſt and imperfections that too uſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ally waits upon multipli'd Copies.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>My Lord,</hi> If we had not confidence that the, merit of this <hi>Poem</hi> would excuſe the boldneſſe of this Dedication, we would not have attempted ſo great a flight as to your name. We humbly beſeech your Honour to peruſe it when you will deſcend to a recreation of this nature: And let not our Names that attend it, by our lowneſs and want of Or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nament, be thought a ſtain to what we have preſented; for though our ſails are not filled with ſo much happy air and breath of the World, yet our ſmall and plain Veſſels are fraught with as true faith &amp; humility to ſerve you, as that which carries more fire and noiſe to proclaim their devoti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons: And in the aſſurance that your mercy will vouchſafe us your protection, we cast our ſelves at your feet,</p>
            <closer>
               <salute>My Lord,</salute>
               <signed>
                  <hi>The humbleſt of thoſe that pray for your<lb/> Honours happineſſe.</hi>
                  <list>
                     <item>A. T.</item>
                     <item>A. P.</item>
                  </list>
               </signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="dramatis_personae">
            <pb facs="tcp:98989:3"/>
            <head>The Perſons of the Play.</head>
            <list>
               <item>
                  <hi>CHilderick,</hi> an old King of <hi>France.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Clotair,</hi> the Young King.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Clovis,</hi> the Monſieur.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Landrey,</hi> Favorite to the Queen, and raiſed by her fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vour to be Duke of <hi>France,</hi> and Maior of the Palace.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Briſſac,</hi> an old Peer of <hi>France.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Briſſac,</hi> his Sonne.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Lords</hi> for Attendants.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Lamot,</hi> two baniſhed Lords.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Dumain,</hi> two baniſhed Lords.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Martell,</hi> Noble men of <hi>France,</hi> and friends of the baniſhed Lords.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Bourbon,</hi> Noble men of <hi>France,</hi> and friends of the baniſhed Lords.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Lanove,</hi> Noble men of <hi>France,</hi> and friends of the baniſhed Lords.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Crotilda,</hi> by the name of <hi>Caſtrato,</hi> as an <hi>Eunuch.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Fredigond,</hi> the Queen.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Aphelia,</hi> Old <hi>Briſſac</hi>'s Daughter.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Iſabella,</hi> a Lady that waited on <hi>Aphelia.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Three <hi>Ladies</hi> for Attendance.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>A Cardinall</hi> for ſtate, when <hi>Aphelia</hi> is to be beheaded.</item>
               <item>Six <hi>Young men</hi> to bear the Herſe.</item>
               <item>Six of the <hi>Guard.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>A <hi>Headſman.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Muſicians.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>A <hi>Page</hi> to <hi>Briſſac.</hi> Jun.</item>
               <item>A <hi>Lackey.</hi>
               </item>
            </list>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="play">
            <pb facs="tcp:98989:3"/>
            <head>The Fatall Contract, A TRAGEDY.</head>
            <div n="1" type="act">
               <div n="1" type="scene">
                  <head>Actus Primus, Scena prima.</head>
                  <stage>Enter <hi>Lamot</hi> and <hi>Dumaine</hi> like Souldiers.</stage>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Dum.</speaker>
                     <l>
                        <seg rend="decorInit">W</seg>E are not ſafe <hi>Lamot;</hi> this bawdie peace</l>
                     <l>Begets a war within me; our ſwords worn</l>
                     <l>For Ornament, not uſe; the Drum &amp; Trumpet</l>
                     <l>Sing drunken Carrols, and the Canon ſpeaks</l>
                     <l>Health, not confuſion; Helmets turn'd to Cups;</l>
                     <l>Our bruiſed Armes adminiſter diſcourſe</l>
                     <l>For Tables and for Taverns, where the Souldier</l>
                     <l>Oft finds a pitty, not reliefe: I'l tell thee,</l>
                     <l>Wee'r walking images, the ſignes of men,</l>
                     <l>And bear about us nothing but the forme</l>
                     <l>Of man that's manly.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Lam.</speaker>
                     <p>Wee'r cold indeed.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Dum</speaker>
                     <l>Yes, and th'ungratefull time</l>
                     <l>As coldly doth rewards us, all our actions,</l>
                     <l>Attempts of valour, look'd into with eyes</l>
                     <l>Fil'd with contempt, when ye Gods ye know</l>
                     <l>It is our gifts they ſee yet: oh I am mad!</l>
                     <l>The very bread that lends them life to ſcorn us,</l>
                     <l>Our blood ha's paid for, yet demand a bit,</l>
                     <l>Or ask of this old ſatten belli'd ſir,</l>
                     <l>Or Madam toothleſs with her velvet ſconce,</l>
                     <l>And you ſhall hear their rotten lungs pronounce</l>
                     <l>The Whip and Whip-ſtock.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <pb facs="tcp:98989:4"/>
                     <speaker>Lam.</speaker>
                     <p>Prethee containe thy ſelfe.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Dum.</speaker>
                     <l>Thou knoweſt I can;</l>
                     <l>With what an equall temper did I breath</l>
                     <l>Under the frozen climate of the North,</l>
                     <l>Where in mine armes (the ſheets of war) I ſlept,</l>
                     <l>My bed being feather'd with the down of heaven?</l>
                     <l>I have lain down a man and riſe a ſnow-ball.</l>
                     <l>There theſe have been my paſtimes, which i've born</l>
                     <l>As willingly as I received them nobly.</l>
                     <l>The Queenes black envy which doth ſtill remaine,</l>
                     <l>And peeps through every limb ſhe bears about her,</l>
                     <l>Fated to ruine us, does not ſwell my Gall,</l>
                     <l>No nor this willing beggery I weare</l>
                     <l>To cloud me from her malice; by the Gods</l>
                     <l>This baſtard-betting peace unſpirits me,</l>
                     <l>A greater corraſive to my active ſoul,</l>
                     <l>Than all paſt ills what ever.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Lam.</speaker>
                     <l>As you are valiant be wiſe too, this is no time</l>
                     <l>To vent your paſſions like a woman in,</l>
                     <l>Your ſword, not tongue, ſhould ſpeak.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Dum.</speaker>
                     <l>You are an expert Tutor, and I thank you;</l>
                     <l>Our wrongs would add a ſpirit to the dead,</l>
                     <l>And make them ſight our quarrels;— but look here</l>
                  </sp>
                  <stage>
                     <hi>Enter</hi> Landrey, <hi>and two or three inſinuating Lords, buſie in conference, and three or foure</hi> Petitioners.</stage>
                  <sp>
                     <l>The minion of our Queen, oh what a traine</l>
                     <l>The painted Peacock bears! death, were I <hi>Jove</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>But onely for this Giant.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Peti.</speaker>
                     <l>Good your honor, our wives and Children,</l>
                     <l>Good your honour hear us.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Lan.</speaker>
                     <l>Where are our ſlaves? keep off theſe dregs of men,</l>
                     <l>The ſcum and out-caſt of the world; bring round my charict</l>
                     <l>To the poſtern Gate; theſe bell-mouth'd Raſcals</l>
                     <l>Split mine cares with noiſe, make haſt before</l>
                     <l>Leſt my great Miſtreſs wait my comming.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <stage>Exit.</stage>
                  <sp>
                     <pb facs="tcp:98989:4" rendition="simple:additions"/>
                     <speaker>Peti.</speaker>
                     <p>Good your honour.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <stage>Exeunt.</stage>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>1 Peti.</speaker>
                     <p>The devill take your worſhip; we muſt follow.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Dum.</speaker>
                     <l>Theſe are the fruits of baſe upſtarts and flatterers.</l>
                     <l>Tell me <hi>Lamot,</hi> can this ſame Merchpane man</l>
                     <l>Think, or commit a ſin though ne'r ſo horrid,</l>
                     <l>But it is candied o'r, and from his vice</l>
                     <l>Exceſſive praiſe and plaudites ariſe?</l>
                     <l>Were I the King, but he is wilful blind,</l>
                     <l>And by the hornes ſhe rocks him faſt aſleep,</l>
                     <l>Before the wanton and hot-blooded Queene</l>
                     <l>Should have the licence but to be ſuſpected</l>
                     <l>With ſuch a Knight of Ginger-bread as this,</l>
                     <l>A gilded fleſh-flie, I would lock her up,</l>
                     <l>Yea chain the evill Angel in a Box,</l>
                     <l>And houſe her like a ſilk-worme.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Lam.</speaker>
                     <p>Pardon me ſir, the good old King's unable.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Dum.</speaker>
                     <l>And therefore muſt admit an upſtart Page,</l>
                     <l>Now rais'd to honours by her lawleſs luſt,</l>
                     <l>Maior of the Palace, and the Duke of France,</l>
                     <l>The next ſtept is the Crown; now by my life</l>
                     <l>'Twere good the King would execute them both.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Lam.</speaker>
                     <l>Alas he dares not, for the no chaſt Queene,</l>
                     <l>Is as her birth, as great in faction,</l>
                     <l>Followed and ſainted by the multitude,</l>
                     <l>Whoſe judgement ſhe hath linck'd unto her Purſe,</l>
                     <l>And rather bought a love than found it:</l>
                     <l>She ha's a working ſpirit, an active braine,</l>
                     <l>Apt to conceive, and wary in her wiles;</l>
                     <l>Beſides, her Sons, the pillowes of the State,</l>
                     <l>Support her like an <hi>Atlas,</hi> where ſhe ſits,</l>
                     <l>And like the heavens commands our fates beneath her;</l>
                     <l>She is the greater light, the King a ſtar</l>
                     <l>That onely glares but through her influence.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <stage>A floriſh within,</stage>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Dum.</speaker>
                     <l>Hark, the thunder of the world, now out of tune,</l>
                     <l>This peace corrupting all things makes them ſpeak,</l>
                     <l>What means this moſt adulterate noiſe?</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <pb facs="tcp:98989:5"/>
                     <speaker>Lam.</speaker>
                     <l>Why, are you ignorant?</l>
                     <l>This is a night of jubile, and the King</l>
                     <l>Solemnly feaſts for his wars happle ſucceſſe,</l>
                     <l>Beſides his Sons and he are knit againe;</l>
                     <l>We ſhall have Masks and Revelling to night.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Dum.</speaker>
                     <l>Now the great Gods confound this pickthanck noiſe,</l>
                     <l>The Drums and Trumpets are turn'd flatterers,</l>
                     <l>And <hi>Mars</hi> himſelf a Bawd to grace their riot,</l>
                     <l>O I am mad, this grates my very Gall.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Lam.</speaker>
                     <l>What man, bear up;</l>
                     <l>Although I wiſh all civill diſcord hence,</l>
                     <l>Yet I do hope a time wherein we Souldiers,</l>
                     <l>Shall like a moving wall of living ſteel,</l>
                     <l>Defend this City that offends us now.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Dum.</speaker>
                     <l>My thoughts keep not your road, I think</l>
                     <l>The deviliſh ſpirit of the haughty Queen,</l>
                     <l>Will find imployment for us yet, her brain</l>
                     <l>Is very active in exploits that breed</l>
                     <l>The Souldiers harveſt, war and diſſenſion.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <stage>Enter the Eunuch with bags of Gold, gives to each of them one, and after a little pauſe departs.</stage>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Lam.</speaker>
                     <l>What viſion's this? 'tis Gold right and fair,</l>
                     <l>Sure I dreame not.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Dum.</speaker>
                     <l>I cannot tell, but he that takes this from me,</l>
                     <l>Shall ſoon perceive I do not ſleep nor ſlumber.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Lam.</speaker>
                     <p>It was the Eunuch.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Dum.</speaker>
                     <p>That needs no deciding.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Lam.</speaker>
                     <l>What ſpeaks the Paper left behind?</l>
                     <l>If it be <hi>Chorus</hi> to this dum ſhew, read it <hi>Dumaine.</hi>
                     </l>
                  </sp>
                  <floatingText type="letter" xml:lang="eng">
                     <body>
                        <head>The Letter.</head>
                        <p>As you are Souldiers truly valiant, I honor you, as poor, I pit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty you; therefore have ſent you that wil render you as com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pleat Courtiers, as undaunted Souldiers: we know your preſent fortunes ſhame your parentage, which was not onely great in it ſelf, but fortunate in ſo fair an off-ſpring: <hi>Dumaine, Lamot,</hi> let it ſuffice we know ye; for our eye is every
<pb facs="tcp:98989:5"/>where: whilſt I remember your worths, I ſhall forget your parents injuries; feare nothing, for your hitherto conceale<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, i'l get your pardons, and whilſt I breath, breath your kind Miſtreſs: if you dare truſt me, appear at Court to night ſo adorned, as ſhall become your honours, our friends.</p>
                        <closer>
                           <signed>Fredigond.</signed>
                        </closer>
                     </body>
                  </floatingText>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Lamot.</speaker>
                     <p>The Queene?</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Dum.</speaker>
                     <p>We are betraid <hi>Lamot,</hi> what ſhall we do?</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Lam.</speaker>
                     <l>Wee'l take the gracious proffer of the Queene,</l>
                     <l>Shee's princely vow'd our friend; beſides what ill</l>
                     <l>Can we expect from her, who might have ſent</l>
                     <l>Her murdering miniſters and ſlaine us here,</l>
                     <l>If ſhe intended foul play? but ſhe's noble.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Dum.</speaker>
                     <p>Noble, grant her ſo, yet—</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Lam.</speaker>
                     <p>What yet?</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Dum.</speaker>
                     <p>Her murdred Brothers memory.—</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Lam.</speaker>
                     <p>When he fell, we were too young for traytors.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Dum.</speaker>
                     <l>But not for torments, had we been apprehended;</l>
                     <l>For in the high diſpleaſure of the Queen,</l>
                     <l>All our poſterity was doom'd; ſome felt the wheel,</l>
                     <l>Some wrack'd, ſome hang'd, others impal'd on ſtakes,</l>
                     <l>With divers ſtrange and horrid formes of death,</l>
                     <l>That you'd have thought, and fitly thought it too,</l>
                     <l>That all the torments which the Poets feign</l>
                     <l>The damned ſpirits exerciſe in Hell,</l>
                     <l>Had here been put in execution;</l>
                     <l>And had not we been then in <hi>Witenburge,</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>Beyond the fury of her mortall ſpleen,</l>
                     <l>We had added to the number of the dead;</l>
                     <l>Then think you ſtill we ſhall not?</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Lam.</speaker>
                     <l>Now by my life it's murder to ſuſpect her,</l>
                     <l>Our lives are all that we can loſe, our fame,</l>
                     <l>Not time nor Art can murder, ſo wee'l venture.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <stage>Exeunt omnes.</stage>
               </div>
               <div n="2" type="scene">
                  <head>SCENA II.</head>
                  <stage>
                     <hi>Enter</hi> Fredigond <hi>the Queene, and the</hi> Eunuch.</stage>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Qu.</speaker>
                     <p>What conference did they maintain with thee?</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Eu.</speaker>
                     <l>None farther than the language of their eyes,</l>
                     <pb facs="tcp:98989:6"/>
                     <l> They look'd on me as if they ment me thanks,</l>
                     <l>Which their amazement rob'd me off.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Qu.</speaker>
                     <p>Spake they not then at all?</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Eu.</speaker>
                     <l>No not a word,</l>
                     <l>They ſeem'd to me as if they knew no language.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Qu.</speaker>
                     <p>You know them not?</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Eu.</speaker>
                     <l>No deareſt Lady, for th'appear'd to me</l>
                     <l>Like to the ſilent poſtures in the Arras,</l>
                     <l>Onely the form of men with ſtranger faces.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Qu.</speaker>
                     <l>Take u'm then, they are our enemies,</l>
                     <l>Whom I have angled with that golden bait;</l>
                     <l>Their parents waded in my Brothers blood,</l>
                     <l>For which i'l be reveng'd of all their kin,</l>
                     <l>Could they increaſe as oft as I would kill,</l>
                     <l>I'd ever kill that they might ſtill increaſe:</l>
                     <stage>Draw the cur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain and ſhew the picture.</stage>
                     <l>This picture drawn by an <hi>Italian</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>(Which ſtill I keep to whet mine anger)</l>
                     <l>Does repreſent the murder of my brother,</l>
                     <l>For raviſhing this beautious piece of ill;</l>
                     <l>A bloody and a terrible miſtake,</l>
                     <l>To murder <hi>Clodimir</hi> for <hi>Clotarrs</hi> fact,</l>
                     <l>For which behold how <hi>Fredigond's</hi> reveng'd,</l>
                     <l>This old <hi>Dumaine</hi> and father to this maid,</l>
                     <l>With all his kindred, ſociates and alies,</l>
                     <l>(Theſe brace of wicked ones, and that raviſht whore,</l>
                     <l>The fair and fatall cauſe of theſe events</l>
                     <l>Onely excepted) are here, here ini this picture:</l>
                     <l>Is't not a brave ſight, how doth the object like thee?</l>
                     <l>How prettily that babie hangs by th'heels,</l>
                     <l>Sprawling his Armes about his mothers wombe,</l>
                     <l>As if againe he ſought for ſhelter there?</l>
                     <l>Here's one bereft of hands, and this of tongue,</l>
                     <l>Finger thy Lute <hi>Maria,</hi> ſing out <hi>Iſabel:</hi>
                     </l>
                     <stage>Scopticè</stage>
                     <l>Hark, hark <hi>Castrato,</hi> the muſick of the Sphaeres,</l>
                     <l>O raviſhing touch, hark how the others voice</l>
                     <l>Ecchoes the Lute, is't not a divine ſoftneſſe?</l>
                     <l>Ha ah ha, I do expect they now ſhould rayle extremely;</l>
                     <l>I prethee ſcold at me good <hi>Iſabel,</hi>
                     </l>
                     <pb facs="tcp:98989:6"/>
                     <l> A little of the woman; no <hi>Maria;</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>Within the cloathed circle of mine eyes,</l>
                     <l>Anchor thy fingers, alas, thy nailes are par'd,</l>
                     <l>Nor has poor <hi>Iſabel</hi> a tongue to ſcold with,</l>
                     <l>And here's the Granddam with her glares out;</l>
                     <l>Saddle her noſe with ſpectacles, or elſe</l>
                     <l>Shee'l miſs her way to the infernall pit.</l>
                     <l>Tow horie Gray-berds in this angle lyes,</l>
                     <l>Will find their way to Hell without their eyes,</l>
                     <l>Villaines that kil'd my Brother; how does this like thee?</l>
                     <l>To execute men in picture, is't not rare?</l>
                     <stage>Stabs the picture</stage>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Eu.</speaker>
                     <l>Were but <hi>Chrotilda</hi> here, and theſe two youngſters,</l>
                     <l>It were a paſtime for the Gods to gaze on.</l>
                     <l>Oh were I but a man as others are,</l>
                     <l>As kind and open-handed nature made me,</l>
                     <l>With Organs apt and fit for womans ſervice.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Qu.</speaker>
                     <p>What if thou wert?</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Eu.</speaker>
                     <l>What if I were great Queene?</l>
                     <l>I'd ſearch the Deſerts, Mountaines, Vallies, Plaines,</l>
                     <l>Till I had met <hi>Chrotilda,</hi> whom by force</l>
                     <l>I'd make to mingle with theſe footie limbs,</l>
                     <l>Till I had got on her one like to me,</l>
                     <l>Whom I would nouriſh for the <hi>Dumaine</hi> line;</l>
                     <l>That time to come might ſtory to the world,</l>
                     <l>They had the Devil to their Grand-father.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Qu.</speaker>
                     <l>I find thee Eunuch apt for my imployments,</l>
                     <l>Therefore I will unclaſpe my ſoul to thee,</l>
                     <l>I've alwaies found thee truſty, and I love thee.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Eu.</speaker>
                     <l>With thanks I ever muſt acknowledge it,</l>
                     <l>And lay my life at my great Miſtreſs feet,</l>
                     <stage>Kneels.</stage>
                     <l>To ſpend it when ſhe pleaſes.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Qu.</speaker>
                     <l>We need it not</l>
                     <l>As yet <hi>Caſtrato,</hi> but we may hereafter.</l>
                     <l>See, their's the plat-forme of great <hi>Childricks</hi> death;</l>
                     <l>And they which muſt be thought his murderers,</l>
                     <l>Our Enemies, and now new Courtiers,</l>
                     <l>Whom hitherto I have reſerv'd for policy;</l>
                     <pb facs="tcp:98989:7"/>
                     <l> Firſt, that they take away the guilt from us;</l>
                     <l>Next, being apprehended, ſtudying deaths,</l>
                     <l>The heads of all our Engineers ſhall ſit</l>
                     <l>T'invent unheard of torments for the ſlaves;</l>
                     <l>I long to ſee them here, here in this frame,</l>
                     <l>Greeting their kindreds bones.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Eu.</speaker>
                     <p>You are the Goddeſs of invention.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Qu.</speaker>
                     <l>Then i'l commend thee to my elder Son,</l>
                     <l>Where thou ſhalt wind into his ſecret thoughts;</l>
                     <l>As for the younger Boy let me alone;</l>
                     <l>And when we have them on the hip, they ſhall</l>
                     <l>Follow their Fathers unto <hi>Hells-black-Hall</hi>
                     </l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Eu.</speaker>
                     <p>Still better.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Qu.</speaker>
                     <l>Will not this be brave? ha, how lik'ſt thou this?</l>
                     <l>Now by this light I'm taken ſtrangely with thee,</l>
                     <l>Come kiſs me, kiſs me ſirra, tremble not.</l>
                     <stage>(Queene kiſſes him.)</stage>
                     <l>Fie, what a January lip thou haſt,</l>
                     <l>A paire of Iſcicles, ſure thou haſt bought</l>
                     <l>A paire of caſt lips of the chaſt <hi>Diana's,</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>Thy blood's meere ſnow-broth, kiſs me again:</l>
                     <stage>(again)</stage>
                     <l>Now ſee if you can find theſe gallants forth,</l>
                     <l>And bring them to our preſence.</l>
                     <stage>Exit Eunuch.</stage>
                     <l>O ſir y'are welcome,</l>
                     <stage>
                        <hi>Enter</hi> Landrey.</stage>
                     <l>Your viſits have been freer, but I grow old,</l>
                     <l>And you command the beauties of the time.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Lan.</speaker>
                     <l>What means my noble Miſtreſs? think you the blood</l>
                     <l>Runnes ſo degenerate within theſe veins,</l>
                     <l>To ſtoop to an inferiour imbrace,</l>
                     <l>When I injoy the beſt.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Qu.</speaker>
                     <l>We are betraid:</l>
                     <l>I'l tell thee a good jeſt <hi>Landrey,</hi> pray marke;</l>
                     <l>This morning dreſſing my head my husband came,</l>
                     <l>And with his ſwitch (for he was then to hunt)</l>
                     <l>A gentle ſtroke he gave me on the back;</l>
                     <l>My fancy buſied then to make me fine,</l>
                     <l>Suppoſing it was you that ſported ſo,</l>
                     <l>(Not dreaming that the dotard was ſo neere)</l>
                     <pb facs="tcp:98989:7"/>
                     <l> Cri'd, well my <hi>Landrey,</hi> in ſtory we ſtill find,</l>
                     <l>The beſt Knights ſtrike before and not behind:</l>
                     <l>The King who alwaies underſtood too faſt,</l>
                     <l>Quits ſuddenly my Chambers, what he intends</l>
                     <l>I cannot gueſs, unleſs it be our deaths,</l>
                     <l>Which if he ſpeedily perform not, then</l>
                     <l>Know he ſhall never, for this night concludes him.</l>
                     <l>His Sons I weigh like him, they have rebell'd,</l>
                     <l>And taken ſpirit of late t'oppoſe my will,</l>
                     <l>And contradict my pleaſures in thy love,</l>
                     <l>For which it is not ſafe that they ſhould live;</l>
                     <l>The Kingdoms Heir ſhall be a boy of thine,</l>
                     <l>And Kings and Queens ſhall follow in thy Line.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Eu.</speaker>
                     <p>Madam, here are the Gentlemen.</p>
                     <stage>Enter Dumaine &amp; Lamot very brave, the Eunuck.</stage>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Qu.</speaker>
                     <l>Y'are welcome to the Court, and us, brave ſpirits y'are welcome.</l>
                     <l>Take a Queenes word y'are welcome.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Ambo.</speaker>
                     <p>Your highneſſe is as full of grace as mercy.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Qu.</speaker>
                     <p>Riſe and follow us, wee'l be your Guardian and Protectres.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Lan.</speaker>
                     <p>What are theſe?</p>
                     <stage>Aſide</stage>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Qu.</speaker>
                     <l>Sheep for my ſhambles, whom I have fatted up</l>
                     <l>Onely for ſlaughter; things are on foot decreed,</l>
                     <l>Shall make ſome ſmile to night, and others bleed.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <stage>Exeunt omnes</stage>
               </div>
               <div n="3" type="scene">
                  <head>SCENA III.</head>
                  <stage>
                     <hi>Enter</hi> Clovis <hi>at one door,</hi> Aphelia <hi>and a</hi> Page <hi>at the other with a Torch.</hi>
                  </stage>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Clo.</speaker>
                     <l>My beſt Miſtreſs,</l>
                     <l>What Angel brought you hither? for I know</l>
                     <l>Millions attend your goodneſs.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Aph.</speaker>
                     <p>My Lord?</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Clo.</speaker>
                     <l>Why do you caſt ſuch ſtranger eyes upon me?</l>
                     <l>You were not wont to cloth your browes with ſcorn,</l>
                     <l>Nor dart ſuch deadly looks; can my miſtreſs</l>
                     <l>Be angry with her ſervant? my offence,</l>
                     <l>If ſlowneſs in my viſits, i'l hereafter</l>
                     <pb facs="tcp:98989:8"/>
                     <l> Grow to your threſhold; why weep you now?</l>
                     <l>Truſt me divineſt fair thine eyes ſeed pearl,</l>
                     <l>Bracelets for Gods to wear about their armes.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Aph.</speaker>
                     <l>I am too fond, and yet he ſwears he loves me,</l>
                     <l>I have believ'd him too, for I have found</l>
                     <l>A Godlike nature in him, and a truth</l>
                     <l>Hitherto conſtant.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Clo.</speaker>
                     <p>Sweeteſt fair the cauſe?</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Aph.</speaker>
                     <l>If this ſhould be diſſembled, not your heart,</l>
                     <l>And having won my ſouls affection,</l>
                     <l>Should on a judgement more retir'd to ſtate,</l>
                     <l>Smile at your perjuries, and leave me in love,</l>
                     <l>What ill-bred tales the world would make of me.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Clo.</speaker>
                     <l>That jealouſie i'l ſtrangle; take this Ring,</l>
                     <l>As I that Diamond dazel'd by thine eyes,</l>
                     <l>Whoſe beauty ſickned' cauſe ecclips'd by thine;</l>
                     <l>Be theſe the mutual pledges of our love,</l>
                     <l>Our Marriage before our Marriage,</l>
                     <l>And curs'd be he that ſeparates our love,</l>
                     <l>Though <hi>France</hi> be one, or what is greater <hi>Jove.</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>Are your fears over now?</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Alp.</speaker>
                     <p>My Lord, I dare no ill, and therefore doubt none.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <stage>Enter King, Queen, Clotaire, Landrey, Dumain, Lamot, Eunuch, Lords, Ladyes, Guard.</stage>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>King.</speaker>
                     <l>Approach our perſon nearer, for methinks</l>
                     <l>Y'have honeſt faces, if your hearts keep touch</l>
                     <l>T'your outward ſemblance, y'are a pair</l>
                     <l>Nothing but death ſhall force from me.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Qu.</speaker>
                     <p>Good, good, this Phyſick works.</p>
                     <stage>aſide.</stage>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Eu.</speaker>
                     <p>Madam, is't done?</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Qu.</speaker>
                     <l>I my black Genius, ſuch a fatal dram</l>
                     <l>I have adminiſtred, will wing his ſoul</l>
                     <l>With expedition to the other world,</l>
                     <l>His part eſſential like a wearied Ghoſt</l>
                     <l>This night forſakes her Inn, when ſled and gone,</l>
                     <l>Who knows where it ſhall lodge: mark his looks,</l>
                     <l>See'ſt thou not death thron'd in his hollow eye,</l>
                     <pb facs="tcp:98989:8"/>
                     <l> Great tyrant over Nature?</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Eu.</speaker>
                     <l>With looks inquiſite I have beheld him.</l>
                     <l>But ſee no alteration.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Qu.</speaker>
                     <l>Thou art a fool, and wantſt the optique nerves</l>
                     <l>To pry into my Arts; where I lay trains,</l>
                     <l>Death comes before the grief, the ſulphurous match</l>
                     <l>Deſtroyes the powder with a motion ſlow</l>
                     <l>To what I work with; as Antumn aged leaf,</l>
                     <l>In youth the prime and glory of the Grove,</l>
                     <l>Not to be graſpt with hand, falls with a puff,</l>
                     <l>And what we could not touch but now, we tread on,</l>
                     <l>So <hi>Childrick —</hi>
                     </l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>King.</speaker>
                     <l>Lend me thine arm <hi>Dumain,</hi> I now not what,</l>
                     <l>But on the ſudden —</l>
                     <stage>Dumain &amp; Lamot about the King.</stage>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Qu.</speaker>
                     <l>How the Nats play and buz about the fire.</l>
                     <l>Muſt conſume them.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Eu.</speaker>
                     <p>'Tis rare, obſervant Cocks comes.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Clota.</speaker>
                     <l>What Star's unſhe'rd and walks upon the Earth,</l>
                     <l>Making our night a noon? methinks her ſight</l>
                     <l>Does cure blindneſſe, and lend darkneſſe light,</l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Caſtrato</hi> —</l>
                     <stage>Clotair pulls the Eunuch aſide.</stage>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Eu.</speaker>
                     <p>No more, we are obſerv'd, my Lord.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Clot.</speaker>
                     <p>What Ladyes that?</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Eu.</speaker>
                     <l>That French India with a mine upon her back,</l>
                     <l>With whom your Brother holds diſcourſe?</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Clot.</speaker>
                     <p>The ſame.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Eu.</speaker>
                     <p>The chaſt and beautifull <hi>Aphelia.</hi>
                     </p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Clot.</speaker>
                     <l>Indeed ſhee's wondrous fair, nature hath much</l>
                     <l>Befriended her, art ſure ſhee's honeſt?</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Eu.</speaker>
                     <l>Snow's not purer;</l>
                     <l>No veſtal Virgin at the Aultar bears</l>
                     <l>A ſoul ſo incorrupt, ſo void of flame</l>
                     <l>That's looſly active.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Clot.</speaker>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Caſtrato,</hi> be as our ſelf, get but that Lady for me;</l>
                     <l>Thou underſtand'ſt me.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Eu.</speaker>
                     <l>Shee dotes upon your Brother, by which means</l>
                     <l>I'l think upon ſome plot.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Clot.</speaker>
                     <p>The Maſque ended wee will talk further on't.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <pb facs="tcp:98989:9"/>
                     <speaker>King.</speaker>
                     <l>Defer our paſtimes till another night,</l>
                     <l>I am not well at caſe.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Duma.</speaker>
                     <p>Lights, lights for his Majeſty.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>
                        <hi>Clot.</hi> &amp; <hi>Clovis.</hi>
                     </speaker>
                     <p>How is it with your grace our Royal Father?</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Eu. Dumain, Lamot</speaker>
                     <l>Your feet are in the ſnare,</l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Fredigond</hi> hunts, and when ſhe hunts beware.</l>
                     <stage>
                        <hi>The</hi> Eunuch <hi>talks with</hi> Aphelia aſide.</stage>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Lam.</speaker>
                     <p>What ſayes the ſlave?</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Dum.</speaker>
                     <p>No matter what, mind we his Majeſty.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>King.</speaker>
                     <l>There is an <hi>Aetna</hi> in me,</l>
                     <l>The air I draw returnes illuminate,</l>
                     <l>Philoſophy thy Element of fire's here.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Qu.</speaker>
                     <l>His Grace grows worſe and worſe, ſupport him</l>
                     <l>Gently friends; O my dear Husband, O my gentle Lord.</l>
                     <stage>Eneunt omnes.</stage>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Aphe.</speaker>
                     <l>I credit your report, &amp; will obey,</l>
                     <stage>Manent Eunuch and Aphelia.</stage>
                     <l>His mind is honourable like his parentage;</l>
                     <l>His ſingle name has arm'd me, pray lead on.</l>
                     <stage>
                        <hi>Exe. Alp. &amp; Eu. Enter</hi> Lamot. <hi>Enter</hi> Clotaire.</stage>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Lam.</speaker>
                     <p>O woe, woe, woe.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Clot.</speaker>
                     <p>Horror and death.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Clo.</speaker>
                     <p>O diſmall fatal hour.</p>
                     <stage>Enter Clovis, Fredigond, the Queen Landry, Dumain, Guard Attendants.</stage>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Qu.</speaker>
                     <l>with <hi>Childrick</hi> end</l>
                     <l>The World.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Dum.</speaker>
                     <p>Have patience gentle Queen.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Qu.</speaker>
                     <l>Stand from me,</l>
                     <l>Preach patience to the Sea when the rude windes</l>
                     <l>Swell her ambitious billowes'bove the clouds,</l>
                     <l>And if thou tutor'ſt them to peace and ſilence,</l>
                     <l>I'l be as calm as they.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Clot.</speaker>
                     <l>The treaſon here, and not the Traytor,</l>
                     <l>Quite confounds me.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Qu.</speaker>
                     <l>Doubt ye the Traytors?</l>
                     <l>I've brougth a pair of Vipers to the Court,</l>
                     <l>Warm'd and reliev'd them with a ſting to kill us;</l>
                     <l>Who could be Authors of this dead but they?</l>
                     <l>His new boſome friends have ſlain him,</l>
                     <l>Lay hands upon the villains.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Dun.</speaker>
                     <p>We are betraid <hi>Lamot,</hi> baſely beſet with ſnares.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Lam.</speaker>
                     <p>Juſtice fight thou my cauſe with thine own ſword.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <pb facs="tcp:98989:9"/>
                     <speaker>Qu.</speaker>
                     <l>O villains, would ye let them ſcape?</l>
                     <l>Two men to paſſe the ſtrength of all our guard?</l>
                     <l>This mads me.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Clot.</speaker>
                     <l>Make after them and bring them back.</l>
                     <l>Or by my Fathers ſoul ye ſleep your laſt.</l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Aphelia,</hi> oh <hi>Aphelia,</hi> ſhee'l not from my mind,</l>
                     <l>I may command her now.</l>
                     <l>Come Mother, Brother, Friends, come let us go,</l>
                     <l>King ne'r receiv'd a Crown ſo full of woe.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <stage>Exe. omnes.</stage>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div n="2" type="act">
               <div n="1" type="scene">
                  <head>Actus Secundus Scena Prima.</head>
                  <stage>Enter <hi>Old Briſſac</hi> and the <hi>Page.</hi>
                  </stage>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Page.</speaker>
                     <l>I Left her mid'ſt th'amazed multitude,</l>
                     <l>Where doubtleſſe frighted with the ſudden horror</l>
                     <l>Of the unlook'd for murther of the Kings,</l>
                     <l>She has with other beauties of the Court,</l>
                     <l>Retir'd her ſelf until the morning ſtar.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>O. Briſ.</speaker>
                     <l>'Tis very likely ſo, yet d'ee hear—</l>
                     <l>I know not what to ſay, i'l not to bed,</l>
                     <l>My thoughts are full of tempeſts, diſmall thinkings;</l>
                     <l>Where is my Son, why went he not to Court?</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Page.</speaker>
                     <l>Your Son ſir <hi>Charles,</hi> ſir, is not yet in bed,</l>
                     <l>But why he went not to the Court I know not.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>O. Briſ.</speaker>
                     <l>Perhaps ſhe's ſafe, then why returns ſhe not?</l>
                     <l>Why ſends ſhe not glad meſſenges of health?</l>
                     <l>No, no, ſhe's loſt, and I undone forever.</l>
                     <l>Go to your bed, I will not trouble you,</l>
                     <l>Go take your reſt, yet pray be up betimes,</l>
                     <stage>Offers to go.</stage>
                     <l>Yet ſtay and watch with me, ſhe may come home,</l>
                     <l>She may come home, it's good to wait for her;</l>
                     <l>Yet now I've thought on't get you hence to bed,</l>
                     <l>And yet not ſo, run, run unto the Court,</l>
                     <l>O Villain how he moves; yet why ſo faſt,</l>
                     <stage>Offer to run.</stage>
                     <pb facs="tcp:98989:10"/>
                     <l> Let me deliberate, that were to give</l>
                     <l>The Courtiers notice I have loſt my Daughter,</l>
                     <l>Whom they will then ſuſpect, and call her fame</l>
                     <l>Into an ill conſtruction; no no no:</l>
                     <stage>Enter Charles Briſſac &amp; Clovis the Prince guiſed</stage>
                     <l>O ſir you'r welcome, where is your ſiſter?</l>
                     <l>I muſt have her ſirra, and I will; where is</l>
                     <l>She <hi>Charles,</hi> where is ſhe?</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Cha.</speaker>
                     <p>My noble Father.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>O. Briſ.</speaker>
                     <l>Tut tut tut, noble me nobles, nor Father me</l>
                     <l>No Fathers, where is your ſiſter ſirra?</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Cha.</speaker>
                     <p>My ſiſter?</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>O. Briſ.</speaker>
                     <l>Your ſiſter; this cunning ſhall not carry it;</l>
                     <l>Where is ſhe? ſpeak.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Cha.</speaker>
                     <l>Within fir, is ſhe not? otherwiſe this Gentleman</l>
                     <l>Ha's loſt his labour, he's come to viſit her.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>O. Briſ.</speaker>
                     <l>Hoyday, hoyday, hoyday, hoyday, to viſit her?</l>
                     <l>Plots, plots, meer fetches to delude me: to viſit her?</l>
                     <l>What at the dead of night, when the whole world</l>
                     <l>Is ſunck in ſlumber, and our luſtie youth</l>
                     <l>As quiet as the Grave? to viſit her?</l>
                     <l>O moſt ridiculous, to viſit her?</l>
                     <l>Pray Gentleman conſider, does your ſiſter keep</l>
                     <l>Times ſo prepoſterous for viſiting?</l>
                     <l>Makes ſhe day of night, or ha's been bred</l>
                     <l>As looſe as <hi>Lais,</hi> to love night Courtings?</l>
                     <l>Do not diſtract me; to viſit her?</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Cha.</speaker>
                     <l>Pray ſir collect your ſelf; this Gentleman</l>
                     <l>Even at that horrid point where the King fell—</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>O. Briſ.</speaker>
                     <l>I there's more miſchief too; God for his mercy.</l>
                     <l>What a world is this!</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Cha.</speaker>
                     <l>Saw a Ring drop from off my ſiſters ſinges,</l>
                     <l>And at his beſt advantage took it up,</l>
                     <l>Which he had then deliver'd, but that fright</l>
                     <l>Which renders men forgetful made him ſo,</l>
                     <l>But knowing where ſhe liv'd, (ſo he proteſts)</l>
                     <l>He could not ſleep until it were deliver'd.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>O. Briſ.</speaker>
                     <l>Pray let me ſee the Ring; yes it was hers.</l>
                     <l>And ſhe would ſay ſhe'd never part with it</l>
                     <pb facs="tcp:98989:10"/>
                     <l> But when ſhe ment to wed; if y'have married her,</l>
                     <l>Or have her promiſe rivited to yours,</l>
                     <l>Tell me but where ſhe is i'l be content,</l>
                     <l>For I in loſing her have loſt my joy.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Cha.</speaker>
                     <p>Is ſhe not then within?</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>O. Briſ.</speaker>
                     <l>Yes too much; oh no</l>
                     <l>The houſe containes her not, ſhe is not here,</l>
                     <l>Nor is for ought I know at all.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Clov.</speaker>
                     <p>O my prophetique ſoul, then 'tis no idle fear.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>O. Briſ.</speaker>
                     <p>How the Monſiure? what makes he here?</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Clov.</speaker>
                     <l>There's ſomething whiſpers me, go not to bed,</l>
                     <l>Go not to bed till thou haſt found her out,</l>
                     <l>Be'ſt thou my Genius or what power elſe</l>
                     <l>(Suggeſting lawful things) I will obey thee.</l>
                     <l>Still it cryes, ſleep not to night; had I tane Opium,</l>
                     <l>The drowſie Poppie, cold Mandragora,</l>
                     <l>Or all the ſleepie ſirrops of the world,</l>
                     <l>With ſuch a powerful ſpell thou work'ſt upon me,</l>
                     <l>That ſhould I take an everlaſting ſleep</l>
                     <l>Thould'ſt wake my ſcattered bones, and make them riſe</l>
                     <l>To watch the horror of this fatal night;</l>
                     <l>Sleep ever waking envie and miſtruſt,</l>
                     <l>Yes things which never knew what ſlumber ment;</l>
                     <l>Ghoſts keep your beds, ye Centinels of night,</l>
                     <l>Goblings and Specters do not walk your round;</l>
                     <l>A generall Lethargie ſeize on this hour,</l>
                     <l>Whilſt I alone the Watchman of the night</l>
                     <l>Will wake in ſpite of fate, <hi>Argus</hi> Thine eyes</l>
                     <l>To find <hi>Aphelia</hi> and her miſeries.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <stage>Exit.</stage>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>O. Briſ.</speaker>
                     <l>Pretty in good ſadneſſe, wondrous pretty;</l>
                     <l>Is he in earneſt?</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Cha.</speaker>
                     <l>Sure he diſſembles not, I little thought [When I did</l>
                     <l>Let him in, what perſon grac'd [Our Threſhold.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>O. Briſ.</speaker>
                     <l>Ah ſirra, what a Girl is this to be out of th'way,</l>
                     <l>He is in love that's certain; let me remember,</l>
                     <l>When I was firſt a lover as he is,</l>
                     <l>I'd juſt ſuch wild vagaries in my brain,</l>
                     <l>Such midnight madneſſe; this puling baggage</l>
                     <pb facs="tcp:98989:11"/>
                     <l> May loſe her ſelf for ever, and her fortunes,</l>
                     <l>For this hours abſence; go, begone,</l>
                     <l>Follow his royall perſon, comfort him,</l>
                     <l>Tell him my daughter will again be found;</l>
                     <l>And ſo good Angels grant we meet with her.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <stage>Exe. omnes.</stage>
               </div>
               <div n="2" type="scene">
                  <head>SCEN. II.</head>
                  <stage>Enter <hi>Aphelia</hi> and the <hi>Eunuch</hi> with a wax Taper.</stage>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Aph.</speaker>
                     <l>Into what Labyrinth doe you lead me ſir?</l>
                     <l>What by perplexed wayes? I ſhould much fear</l>
                     <l>Had you not us'd his name, which is to me</l>
                     <l>A ſtrength 'gainſt terror, and himſelf ſo good,</l>
                     <l>Occaſion cannot varie, nor the night,</l>
                     <l>Youth, nor his wild deſire, otherwiſe</l>
                     <l>A ſilent ſorrow from mine eyes would ſteal</l>
                     <l>And tell ſad ſtories for me.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Eu.</speaker>
                     <l>You are too tender of your honour Lady,</l>
                     <l>Too full of aguiſh trembling, the noble Prince</l>
                     <l>Is, as December, froſty in deſire,</l>
                     <l>Save what is lawful, he not owns that heat,</l>
                     <l>Which were you ſnow would thaw a tear from you.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Aph.</speaker>
                     <p>This is the place appointed, pray heavens all things go well.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Eu.</speaker>
                     <l>I will go call him, pleaſe you reſt your ſelf;</l>
                     <l>Here lies a book will bear you company</l>
                     <l>Till I return, which will be preſently.</l>
                     <l>Hither i'l ſend the King, not that I mean</l>
                     <stage>Aphelia reads in the book.</stage>
                     <l>To give him leave to cool his burning luſt,</l>
                     <l>For <hi>Clovis</hi> ſhall prevent him in the fact;</l>
                     <l>And thus I ſhall endear my ſelf to both:</l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Clovis</hi> inrag'd perhaps will kill the King,</l>
                     <l>Or by the King will periſh, if both fall,</l>
                     <l>Or either, both waies make for me;</l>
                     <l>The Queen as rootedly does hate her ſonnes,</l>
                     <l>As I her Ladyſhip, to ſee this fraie</l>
                     <l>She muſt be brought by me, ſhe'l ſteel them on</l>
                     <l>To one anothers damage, for her ſake</l>
                     <pb facs="tcp:98989:11"/>
                     <l> I'l ſay I ſet on foot this hopeful brawl.</l>
                     <l>Whilſt ſhe will hug and kiſſe me for the ſame;</l>
                     <l>Thus on all ſides the Eunuch will play foul,</l>
                     <l>And as his face is black he'l have his ſoul,</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Alph.</speaker>
                     <l>How witty ſorrow ha's found out diſcourſe</l>
                     <l>Fitting a midnight ſeaſon! here I ſee</l>
                     <l>One bath'd in Virgins tears, whoſe puritie</l>
                     <l>Might blanch a Blackmore, turn natures ſtream</l>
                     <stage>Enter Clotair.</stage>
                     <l>Back on it's ſelf; words pure and of that ſtrain</l>
                     <l>Might move the <hi>Parcae</hi> to bepittiful.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Clot.</speaker>
                     <l>Methinks I ſtand like <hi>Tarquin</hi> in the night,</l>
                     <l>When he defil'd the chaſtity of <hi>Rome,</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>Doubtful of what to do, and like a Thief</l>
                     <stage>ſhe ſtill reads on.</stage>
                     <l>I take each noiſe to be an Officer.</l>
                     <l>She ha's a raviſhing feature, and her mind</l>
                     <l>Is of a purer temper than her body:</l>
                     <l>Her vertues more than beauty raviſh't me,</l>
                     <l>And I commit even with her piety</l>
                     <l>A kind of inceſt with Religion;</l>
                     <l>Though I do know it is a deed of death</l>
                     <l>Condemn'd to torments in the other world,</l>
                     <l>Such tempting ſweetneſſe dwels in every limb,</l>
                     <l>That I muſt venter my eſſentiall parts</l>
                     <l>For the fruition of a moments luſt,</l>
                     <stage>Exit with a re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolve not to do it.</stage>
                     <l>A pleaſure dearly bought.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Aphe.</speaker>
                     <l>Alack poor maid,</l>
                     <l>Poor raviſht <hi>Philomel,</hi> thy lot was ill</l>
                     <l>To meet that violence in a Brother, which</l>
                     <l>I in a ſtranger doubt not; vet methinks</l>
                     <l>I am too confident, for I feel my heart</l>
                     <l>Burd'ned with ſomething ominous; theſe men</l>
                     <l>Are things of ſubtil nature, and their oaths</l>
                     <l>Unconſtant like themſelves. <hi>Clovis</hi> may prove unkind,</l>
                     <l>Alack why not? ſay he ſhould offer foul,</l>
                     <l>The evil counſel of a ſecret place,</l>
                     <l>And night his friend, might over-tempt his will;</l>
                     <l>I dare not ſtand the hazard; guide me light</l>
                     <l>To ſome untroden place, where poor I may</l>
                     <pb facs="tcp:98989:12"/>
                     <l> Wear out the night with ſighs till it be day.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <stage>Ent. Clota.</stage>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Clot.</speaker>
                     <l>I am reſolv'd, I will be bold and reſolute.</l>
                     <l>Hail beautious Damſell.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Aphe.</speaker>
                     <l>Ha, what man art thou</l>
                     <l>That haſt thy count'nance clouded with thy cloak,</l>
                     <l>And hid'ſt thy face from darkneſſe and the night?</l>
                     <l>If thy intents deſerve a Muſtler too,</l>
                     <l>Withdraw and act them not. What art thou, ſpeak?</l>
                     <l>And wherefore cam'ſt thou hither?</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Clot.</speaker>
                     <l>I came to find one beautiful as thou,</l>
                     <l>And am a man willing to pleaſe a woman.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Aphe.</speaker>
                     <p>I underſtand you not.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Clot.</speaker>
                     <l>But I muſt you, yea and the right way too,</l>
                     <l>Or my ſtrength ſhall fail me.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Aphe.</speaker>
                     <p>Help, help, help.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Clot.</speaker>
                     <l>Peace, none of your loud muſick Lady,</l>
                     <l>If you raiſe a note, or beat the air with clamor,</l>
                     <l>You ſee your death.</l>
                     <stage>Drawes his Dagger.</stage>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Aphe.</speaker>
                     <l>What violence is this? inhuman ſir,</l>
                     <stage>kneels.</stage>
                     <l>Why do you threaten war, fright my ſoft peace</l>
                     <l>With moſt ungentle ſteel? what have I done</l>
                     <l>Dangerous, or am like to do? why do you wrack me thus?</l>
                     <l>Mine armes are guilty of no crimes, do not torment'um:</l>
                     <l>Mine heart and they have been heav'd up together</l>
                     <l>For mankind that was holy, if in that act</l>
                     <l>They have not prai'd for you, mend and be good,</l>
                     <l>The fault is none of their's.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Clot.</speaker>
                     <l>Come, do not ſeem</l>
                     <l>More holy than you are, I know your heart.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Aphe.</speaker>
                     <l>Let your Dagger too; noble ſir, ſtrike home,</l>
                     <l>And ſacrifice a ſoul to chaſtitie,</l>
                     <l>As pure as is it ſelf, or innocence.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Clot.</speaker>
                     <p>This is not the way, —know you me beauty?</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Aph.</speaker>
                     <p>The Majeſtie of <hi>France!</hi>
                     </p>
                     <stage>diſcovers himſelf.</stage>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Clot.</speaker>
                     <p>Be not afraid.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Aphe.</speaker>
                     <l>I dare not fear, it's treaſon to ſuſpect</l>
                     <l>My King can harbour thoughts that tend to ill,</l>
                     <l>I know you'r godlike good, and have but tri'd</l>
                     <pb facs="tcp:98989:12"/>
                     <l> How far weak women durſt be vertuous.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Clot.</speaker>
                     <l>Cunning ſimplicity, thou art deceiv'd,</l>
                     <l>Thy wit as well as beauty wounds me, and thy tongue</l>
                     <l>In pleading for thee pleads againſt thy ſelf;</l>
                     <l>It is thy virtue moves me, and thy good</l>
                     <l>Tempts me to acts of evil; wert thou bad,</l>
                     <l>Or looſe in thy deſires, I could ſtand,</l>
                     <l>And onely gaze, not ſurfeit on thy beauty;</l>
                     <l>But as thou art, there's witchcraft in thy face,</l>
                     <l>I muſt injoy thee, or not thou thy life.</l>
                     <stage>Enter Clovis &amp; Charles.</stage>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Aphe</speaker>
                     <l>You are my King, and may command my life,</l>
                     <l>My will to ſin you cannot; you may force</l>
                     <l>Unhallowed deeds upon me, ſpot my fame,</l>
                     <l>And make my body ſuffer, not my mind;</l>
                     <l>When you have done this unreligious deed,</l>
                     <l>Conquer'd a poor weak maid, a trembling maid,</l>
                     <l>What trophie or what triumph will it bring</l>
                     <l>More than a living ſcorn upon your name?</l>
                     <l>The aſhes in your Urn ſhall ſuffer for't,</l>
                     <l>Virgins will ſow their curſes on your Grave,</l>
                     <l>Time blot your Kingly parentage, and call</l>
                     <l>Your birth in queſtion; do not think</l>
                     <l>This deed will lie conceal'd, the faults Kings do</l>
                     <l>Shine like the fiery Beacons on a hill</l>
                     <l>For all to ſee, and ſeeing tremble at:</l>
                     <l>It's not a ſingle ill which you commit;</l>
                     <l>What in the ſubject is a petty fault,</l>
                     <l>Monſters your actions, and's a foul offence;</l>
                     <l>You give your ſubjects licence to offend,</l>
                     <l>When you do teach them how.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Clot.</speaker>
                     <l>I will indure no longer, come along,</l>
                     <l>Or by the curious ſpinſtrie of thy head,</l>
                     <l>Which natures cunnin'ſt finger twiſted out,</l>
                     <l>I'l drag thee to my couch; tempt not my fury.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Clov.</speaker>
                     <l>Hold, hold my heart—can I indure this—</l>
                     <l>Unhand me <hi>Charles</hi> and render me my ſelf,</l>
                     <l>Leſt I forget my ſelf on thee.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Char.</speaker>
                     <l>Great ſir;</l>
                     <pb facs="tcp:98989:13"/>
                     <l> Remember 'tis your brother, and the King.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Clov.</speaker>
                     <l>O that I could forget it, and ſhake off</l>
                     <l>Duty at once and Conſanguinitie,</l>
                     <stage>Enter Eunuch.</stage>
                     <l>That like a whirlwind I might ruſh upon him,</l>
                     <l>And bear him to deſtruction. Monſter of men,</l>
                     <l>Thou King of darkneſſe down unto thy Hell,</l>
                     <l>I have a Spel wil lay thy honeſty,</l>
                     <l>And this abuſed goodneſſe: Is't not enough</l>
                     <l>That thou haſt wrong'd <hi>Crotilda,</hi> raviſh't a Maid,</l>
                     <l>A Virgin of that puritie of life</l>
                     <l>Might ſaint her here on earth; but thou wilt add</l>
                     <l>Unto the firſt a ſecond violence the Gods muſt not forgive:</l>
                     <l>Don't arm your face,</l>
                     <l>Nor wear acount'nance of horror, I can't fear</l>
                     <l>Bearing a boſome innocent and pure:</l>
                     <l>Is't even ſo, then guard thy ſelf Oh King,</l>
                     <l>For I am ſwift as thought that executes.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Char.</speaker>
                     <p>Hold, hold, my Lotd forbear.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Eu.</speaker>
                     <l>Beat down their ſwords, what do the Princes mean?</l>
                     <l>Ring out the larum Bell, call up the Court,</l>
                     <stage>Ring the Bell.</stage>
                     <l>The Princes here will murder one another.</l>
                     <l>For ſhame for ſhame forbear.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <stage>Enter the Queen, the Guard, and Attendants, Landrey at the other door.</stage>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Qu.</speaker>
                     <l>What means this ſudden outcry? oh my Sonnes,</l>
                     <l>Hold, hold; part 'um good Gentlemen.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Clot.</speaker>
                     <p>Brav'd by a ſubjects hand?</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Qu</speaker>
                     <l>Though nature by precedencie of birth</l>
                     <l>Made thee his King, it therefore follows not</l>
                     <l>His Murtherer: wherein is our <hi>Clotair</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>Greater than <hi>Clovis?</hi> the ſelf ſame blood</l>
                     <l>That ſpirits thee, makes him as valiant,</l>
                     <l>The difference lyes in <hi>Anno Domini.</hi>
                     </l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Eu.</speaker>
                     <p>Moſt acurat miſchief, moſt rare Crocadile!</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Qu.</speaker>
                     <l>I grant thou art his elder, by which law</l>
                     <l>Thou'rt born his ſubject, not his equal <hi>Clovis:</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>Know <hi>Clotair</hi>'s thy King, and ſubjects hands</l>
                     <pb facs="tcp:98989:13"/>
                     <l> Without the deep and dangerous traytors name,</l>
                     <l>May not advance againſt their ſovereignes head.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Clota.</speaker>
                     <l>Neither ſhall his without Correction</l>
                     <l>Upon him ſlaves.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Qu.</speaker>
                     <l>Hold, I command ye hold:</l>
                     <l>Oh <hi>Clotair</hi> thou art of a valiant ſoul,</l>
                     <l>And wilt thou baſely thus beſet thy Brother?</l>
                     <l>Fear argues ſpirits moſt degenerate,</l>
                     <l>And that thou fear'ſt, th'advantage argues it;</l>
                     <l>O ſet not on thy ſlaves, if he muſt die,</l>
                     <l>Let thy ſacrifice not butcher him.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Clota.</speaker>
                     <p>That argument ſounds harſh, does <hi>Clotair</hi> fear?</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Clo.</speaker>
                     <p>Sacrifice me? it is not in his power.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Eu.</speaker>
                     <p>Exquiſite Philter, how it operates!</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Qu.</speaker>
                     <l>We hope ſo <hi>Clovis;</hi> yet thy brother King</l>
                     <l>Is as an earthly God, his will his law,</l>
                     <l>His power uncircumſcrib'd, unlimited,</l>
                     <l>Whoſe Majeſty can look a ſubject dead.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Clo.</speaker>
                     <p>How? look me dead? I do not fear his frowns.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Qu.</speaker>
                     <l>I grant th'as great a Baſiliske as he,</l>
                     <l>As thou art meerly man; but as thy King</l>
                     <l>Divinity doth prop him, he ſtands firm</l>
                     <l>That builds on that foundation; yet I know</l>
                     <l>Thy ſword's as ſharp as his, and where it lights</l>
                     <l>Imprints as much of fate; thine arm's as ſtrong,</l>
                     <l>Thy ſpirit as daring, and thy will as prompt</l>
                     <l>To any action that may write man, Man.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Clot.</speaker>
                     <l>He is your darling, you do wel to praiſe him;</l>
                     <l>When I have ſlain him write his Epitaph.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Clo.</speaker>
                     <l>My Epitaph? this Pen of ſteel ſhall firſt</l>
                     <l>Write on thy heart thine end.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Eu.</speaker>
                     <l>Stil, ſtill better.</l>
                     <l>The venom'd poyſon of a womans tongue</l>
                     <l>Is more ſublim'd than Mercurie.</l>
                     <stage>they fight again.</stage>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Char.</speaker>
                     <l>Hold, hold.</l>
                     <l>O deareſt Maddam, your maternal breath</l>
                     <l>Bears a Mandamus in it, and like heaven</l>
                     <l>Will lay this tempeſt.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <pb facs="tcp:98989:14"/>
                     <speaker>Eu.</speaker>
                     <l>As the wind the Sea,</l>
                     <l>Which makes it rage the lowder,</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Clot.</speaker>
                     <l>Where's our guard</l>
                     <l>That lets a tray tor pull me by the berd?</l>
                     <l>Upon him ſlaves.</l>
                     <stage>The Guard fall on him and he falls.</stage>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Qu.</speaker>
                     <l>O they have ſlain my Son;</l>
                     <l>Bloody villain, thy hands have made theſe holes,</l>
                     <l>Hell take thee for't.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Clot.</speaker>
                     <l>Mother, riſe and depart,</l>
                     <l>For I am bent on miſchief.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Qu.</speaker>
                     <l>Do thy worſt</l>
                     <l>Thou murderous minded Prince, this blood is mine,</l>
                     <l>For in ſome ſort I bleed; out Paricide.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Eu.</speaker>
                     <l>How cunningly ſhe ſpits her poyſon forth!</l>
                     <l>I know her ſoul is light, ſhe's glad he's dead,</l>
                     <l>And joyes in the opportuntie to curſe the killer,</l>
                     <l>For which ſhe gaines the name of pious mother;</l>
                     <l>Here's pretty woman-villany and diſſimulation.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Aphe.</speaker>
                     <l>If they have ſlain him, wherefore do I live?</l>
                     <l>O my ſwoln heart.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Clot.</speaker>
                     <l>Remove the Corps, withall</l>
                     <l>Convey this Syren from our wandring eyes,</l>
                     <l>And howſe her in a Dungeon; let no light</l>
                     <l>Peep through a cranney on her; mask the day,</l>
                     <l>Put the all-ſearching eyes of Phaebus out;</l>
                     <l>Leſt accidentally he gazing here,</l>
                     <l>Here fix eternally, and ſo we may</l>
                     <l>Deſpair of night as once we did of day:</l>
                     <l>Bear her to priſon; reaſon not the cauſe,</l>
                     <l>A Kings prerogative's above his lawes.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Aphe.</speaker>
                     <l>Be mercifull and lead to earth, away,</l>
                     <l>Since he is gone it is to die to ſtay.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <stage>
                     <hi>Exeunt ſome with the</hi> King, <hi>others leading</hi> Aphelia, <hi>and bearing away the Corps.</hi>
                  </stage>
                  <stage>
                     <hi>Manent</hi> Eunuch, Queen, Landrey.</stage>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Qu.</speaker>
                     <l>Now we begin to flouriſh, this black night</l>
                     <l>Is onely lighted by our ſtars, which ſmile</l>
                     <l>Upon theſe actions, and rejoyce to ſee</l>
                     <l>Thee our ſole favorite ſo neer a Crown.</l>
                     <pb facs="tcp:98989:14"/>
                     <l> But tell me <hi>Landrey,</hi> how did I play the mother;</l>
                     <l>Did not I ſeem a <hi>Niobe</hi> in paſſion,</l>
                     <l>A deluge of ſalt tear?</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Land.</speaker>
                     <p>Moſt true, you wept.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Qu.</speaker>
                     <l>As a good Actor in a play would do,</l>
                     <l>Whoſe fancy works (as if he waking dreamt)</l>
                     <l>Too ſtrongly on the Object that it copes with,</l>
                     <l>Shaping realities from mockeries;</l>
                     <l>And ſo the Queen did weep: By this good night</l>
                     <l>I think I could become the Stage as well</l>
                     <l>As any ſhe that ſels her breath in publique;</l>
                     <l>Come ſhall we Act <hi>Landrey?</hi>
                     </l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Land.</speaker>
                     <p>Act Lady, what?</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Qu.</speaker>
                     <l>Nothing that's new, old Playes you know are beſt:</l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Eunuch</hi> is our bed ready?</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Eu.</speaker>
                     <p>Great Queen it is.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Qu.</speaker>
                     <l>Come then my joy to bed, where we will Act</l>
                     <l>The truth which others doubt, and in that ſport</l>
                     <l>We'l laugh at death which triumphs in the Court.</l>
                     <stage>Exeunt, Qu. &amp; Lan.</stage>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Eu.</speaker>
                     <l>Go ſleep your laſt; i'l ſtraight unto the King,</l>
                     <l>And he ſhall take them in the very act;</l>
                     <l>And then to cover my diſcoverie</l>
                     <l>I'l ſet on fire the Queens Bed-chamber,</l>
                     <l>That ſo I may diſturb them more ſecure,</l>
                     <l>And yet the plot not mine, i'l tell the King</l>
                     <l>Unleſſe he preſent help, his mother burns:</l>
                     <l>About it then, this is a happie night,</l>
                     <l>The more it works their woe more's my delight.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <stage>Exit.</stage>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div n="3" type="act">
               <div n="1" type="scene">
                  <head>Actus Tertius, Scena Prima.</head>
                  <stage>Enter <hi>King Clotair,</hi> and the <hi>Eunuch.</hi>
                  </stage>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Eu.</speaker>
                     <l>LOok how it fiames, I fear ſome treachrie,</l>
                     <stage>the bed<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chamb, on fire</stage>
                     <l>Beat at her Chamber door, cry it aloud,</l>
                     <l>And let your voice be thunder to this lightning;</l>
                     <pb facs="tcp:98989:15"/>
                     <l> Cry, fire, fire, fire, the Court is all a hot-houſe, fire, fire.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Clot.</speaker>
                     <l>Great Queen, royall mother, open your door</l>
                     <l>Leſt you do ſleep for ever; mother awake.</l>
                     <l>The God of ſleep lies heavie on her eyes;</l>
                     <l>Force up the door; fire, fire, fire.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Eu.</speaker>
                     <p>It's fortifi'd 'gainſt ſtrength, you muſt call louder.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Clot.</speaker>
                     <l>Mother, Queen, Mother, awake awake,</l>
                     <l>Your ſleep was never more like death than now;</l>
                     <l>Lady, Great Princeſs; fire, fire, fire.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <stage>
                     <hi>Enter</hi> Queen <hi>above in night attire,</hi> Landrey.</stage>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Qu.</speaker>
                     <l>What ſaucie Groom</l>
                     <l>Beats our offendleſs doores thus daringly?</l>
                     <l>H'had better rows'd a ſleeping Lyoneſs</l>
                     <l>Than thus t'have broke our ſlumbers; what art thou?</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Clot.</speaker>
                     <l>Look,</l>
                     <l>The fire will give you light, 'tis I your Son,</l>
                     <l>Flie from your Chamber elſe you are but dead,</l>
                     <l>Your Court is all a Bonſire.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Qu.</speaker>
                     <l>Let it burn, I have loſt my credit everlaſtingly,</l>
                     <l>I will not move afoot.</l>
                     <stage>aſide.</stage>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Clot.</speaker>
                     <p>You muſt be forced then.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <stage>Exit Eunuch <hi>buſie to quench the fire.</hi>
                  </stage>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Land.</speaker>
                     <l>Ladie,</l>
                     <l>Where is your wit now in neceſſitie?</l>
                     <l>Whe ſhall be taken, and you ſham'd for ever.</l>
                     <l>Bethink, bethink your ſelf, what ſhall we do.</l>
                     <stage>aſide.</stage>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Qu.</speaker>
                     <l>I have't, it ſhall be ſo; there, put on that,</l>
                     <l>And as the door flies open meet him full</l>
                     <l>Appearing in his Brothers warlike form,</l>
                     <l>Thou wilt amaze and ſo paſſe by him ſafely.</l>
                     <l>Do not appear to me, I did not wound thee,</l>
                     <stage>aloud this.</stage>
                     <l>Seek out the beds of thoſe that caus'd thy death,</l>
                     <l>And howl to them thy pittious complaints;</l>
                     <l>O do not look on me, be gone, be gone.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Clot.</speaker>
                     <l>Whom d'ee hold diſcourſe with, with the air?</l>
                     <l>Bethink your ſelf, this is no time to dallie.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Qu</speaker>
                     <l>O my Son, ſuch horrid apparitions full of dread</l>
                     <l>Have I beheld, have quite unwitted me;</l>
                     <pb facs="tcp:98989:15"/>
                     <l> Thy brothers Ghoſt, young <hi>Clovis</hi> Ghoſt in armes</l>
                     <l>Has thrice appear'd to me this diſmall night,</l>
                     <l>You heard me ſpeak too't.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Clot.</speaker>
                     <l>True, I heard you ſpeak,</l>
                     <l>But what of that?</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Qu.</speaker>
                     <l>Calls for <hi>Aphelia</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>To bear him company i'th'other world,</l>
                     <l>Or elſe hee'l nightly haunt us in our ſleep.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <stage>
                     <hi>Enter</hi> Landrey, <hi>as in the Princes Armour.</hi>
                  </stage>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Clot.</speaker>
                     <p>O ſee, it comes!</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Qu.</speaker>
                     <p>Fear it not, Son.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Clot.</speaker>
                     <l>What art thou that uſurp'ſt this dead of night,</l>
                     <l>In metal like the age? why art thou ſent</l>
                     <l>To caſt a horror on me? If thy ſoul</l>
                     <l>Walks unreveng'd, and the grim Ferriman</l>
                     <l>Deny thy paſſage, i'l perform thy rights.</l>
                     <stage>the Ghoſt points to his wounds.</stage>
                     <l>O do not wound me with ſuch piteous ſigns,</l>
                     <l>Leſt I diſſolve to air, and like thy ſelf</l>
                     <l>Affright fool mortals: If that thou deſir'ſt</l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Aphelia's</hi> death t'appeaſe thy troubled ſoul,</l>
                     <l>Make ſome conſenting ſign, and ſo depart.</l>
                     <l>Thy ſight afflicts my ſoul.</l>
                     <stage>Enter Queen.</stage>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Qu.</speaker>
                     <p>How fares our Son?</p>
                     <stage>
                        <hi>He bends and ſo goes off; then at the other door enter</hi> Eunuch.</stage>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Clos.</speaker>
                     <p>It was my brothers ſpirit; nothing but <hi>Aphelia?</hi>
                     </p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Qu.</speaker>
                     <p>She muſt die, you ſee it's requiſite.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Clot.</speaker>
                     <p>Would he had askt my life firſt.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Qu.</speaker>
                     <p>Why ſhould you be ſo fond upon a woman?</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Clot.</speaker>
                     <p>Woman's the leaſt part of her, ſhee's all Goddeſſe.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Qu.</speaker>
                     <p>'Twas your offer;</p>
                     <l>Remember there's no jeſting with the Gods.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Eu.</speaker>
                     <p>What might this mean? ha, where are my brains?</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Clot.</speaker>
                     <l>I had forgot my ſelf, your pardon Mother;</l>
                     <l>Bear her from me this Jewel, I eſteem</l>
                     <l>Equall with life; it was my brothers picture;</l>
                     <l>And with it, this, that ſhe prepare to die;</l>
                     <l>Pray her to take it; and in death, but kiſſe</l>
                     <pb facs="tcp:98989:16"/>
                     <l> This ſad remembrance for the ſenders ſake,</l>
                     <l>Although for his whoſe form it repreſents,</l>
                     <l>And I ſhall take it for the greateſt grace</l>
                     <l>That ſhe can give, or I ought to deſire.</l>
                     <l>Tell her, and if you can be mov'd to ſorrow</l>
                     <l>Expreſs it in you tears, it is not I</l>
                     <l>Pronounce this fatall ſentence 'gainſt her life</l>
                     <l>Which needs muſt ruine mine, but the hid will</l>
                     <l>And providence of heaven, 'gainſt which to rage</l>
                     <l>It were as impious as not obey.</l>
                     <l>My brothers funerall is her dying day.</l>
                     <l>Tell her, though reaſon and my will do jarr,</l>
                     <l>My ſoul'ſpeaks peace, although my ſentence war.</l>
                     <l>Say I love, and pray her to forgive me.</l>
                     <stage>Exit Queen.</stage>
                     <l>Go, all attend my Mother; my eſtate</l>
                     <l>Delights not in Court Ceremony; ſtay,</l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Caſtrato</hi> ſtay,</l>
                     <stage>
                        <hi>Eut. all but the</hi> Eunuch <hi>&amp;</hi> Clota.</stage>
                     <l>And with thy Counſell cure thy dying Prince;</l>
                     <l>Thou art my boſome, <hi>Eunuch,</hi> and to thee</l>
                     <l>I dare unclaſp my ſoul; what's to be done?</l>
                     <l>This is a damned ſpirit I have ſeen,</l>
                     <l>And comes to work my ruine.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Eu.</speaker>
                     <p>What ſpirit?</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Clot.</speaker>
                     <l>My Brothers ſpirit in Arms, I ſwear it came forth here</l>
                     <l>Out of my Mothers Chamber as I knockt.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Eu.</speaker>
                     <l>Was it in Armor ſaid you?</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Clot.</speaker>
                     <l>Yes, in that Armor he was us'd to wear</l>
                     <l>When we have run at Tilt, till our cleft Spaeres</l>
                     <l>Have with their ſplinters ſcar'd the Element.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Eu.</speaker>
                     <l>That Armor as I well remember, I did leave</l>
                     <l>In the Queens Bed-chamber as yeſterday,</l>
                     <l>After the Trlumphs and the Tournaments,</l>
                     <l>Having unbrac'd the Prince; 'tis even ſo,</l>
                     <l>Ha, ha, ha.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Clot.</speaker>
                     <l>Why this ridiculous paſſion?</l>
                     <l>My ſtate requires thy tears, and not thy mirth.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Eu.</speaker>
                     <l>The Devill came from your Mothers Chamber ſir',</l>
                     <l>She has a circle that can raiſe a Spirit;</l>
                     <pb facs="tcp:98989:16"/>
                     <l> A <hi>Mars</hi> in armor too, ſhe is a <hi>Venus,</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>And through your licence <hi>Landrey</hi> is no Eunuch.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Clot.</speaker>
                     <l>What killing ſenſe thou utter'ſt?</l>
                     <l>There's ſometing in it I would underſtand,</l>
                     <l>And yet I dare not; <hi>Landrey?</hi> How know'ſt thou this?</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Eu.</speaker>
                     <l>Since I have gone ſo far, i'l tell you;</l>
                     <l>I looked in at th'Key-hole, and I ſaw</l>
                     <l>Him in your Mothers arms upon the bed,</l>
                     <l>As ſportingly as e'r I ſaw your Father.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Clot.</speaker>
                     <l>Thou ly'ſt, take that; ſuſpition double ſees,</l>
                     <stage>ſtrikes. him, &amp; offers to go out.</stage>
                     <l>Jealous informers no'r meet better fees.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Eu.</speaker>
                     <l>King, thou hadſt better far have ſtrook thy Father,</l>
                     <l>Dig'd up his bones and plaid at logats with them.</l>
                     <l>Stroken?</l>
                     <stage>the King returns calmly.</stage>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Clot.</speaker>
                     <l>I know not,</l>
                     <l>My Mother alwaies had a ſeanted fame;</l>
                     <l>His thoughts too have been mine; I was to blame,</l>
                     <l>Prethee forgive me; my paſſions but like lightning,</l>
                     <l>Flaſh and away, dead e'r we ſay it is;</l>
                     <l>I am not alwaies angry, let that aſſure:</l>
                     <l>My Mother may befalſe, ſhe is a woman.</l>
                     <stage>gives him his Purſe.</stage>
                     <l>Prethee deliver, come I will believe thee</l>
                     <l>Even to the utmoſt ſyllable.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Eu.</speaker>
                     <p>Then, ſhe is falſe.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Clot.</speaker>
                     <p>And didſt thou ſee him mount my Mother bed?</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Eu.</speaker>
                     <p>Elſe pull theſe out.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Clot.</speaker>
                     <l>Thou haſt ſhot poyſon through me;</l>
                     <l>Falſe with <hi>Landrey,</hi> her ſometime Page?</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Eu.</speaker>
                     <p>Even with the ſame.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Clot.</speaker>
                     <l>But wherefore would they have <hi>Aphelia</hi> die?</l>
                     <l>There lies the myſtery.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Eu.</speaker>
                     <l>They fear you will accept her as the Queen,</l>
                     <l>Of whom you may beget a hopeful iſſue</l>
                     <l>And fruſtrate their intents, who but expect</l>
                     <l>Your hop'd-for death, and perhaps plotted too,</l>
                     <l>That ſo they might become, what now you croſſe,</l>
                     <l>Lawfully man and wife, and govern in your ſeat.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Clot.</speaker>
                     <l>This carries ſhew of truth, or is't a lie</l>
                     <pb facs="tcp:98989:17"/>
                     <l> Well ſahdowed by the ſlave? I cannot tell:</l>
                     <l>My mother certainly is not ſo bad,</l>
                     <l>It is a ſin to think it; hence and avoid my ſight</l>
                     <l>Thou ſower of debate, thy ſeeds are ſtrow'd</l>
                     <l>On ſteril groun; and therefore ill beſtow'd.</l>
                     <stage>Exit.</stage>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Eu.</speaker>
                     <l>Is't even ſo, work and about my brain,</l>
                     <l>I'm loſt for ever if not cloſe again.</l>
                     <stage>Exit.</stage>
                  </sp>
               </div>
               <div n="2" type="scene">
                  <head>SCEN. II.</head>
                  <stage>
                     <hi>Enter Dumain, Martells, Bourbon,</hi> Lanove.</stage>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Lano.</speaker>
                     <l>Are all your Troops well furniſh'd 'gainſt reſiſtance?</l>
                     <l>Are your men bold and daring, reſolute</l>
                     <l>To run your hazard, indifferent rich, not poor,</l>
                     <l>That onely fight for bread? ſuch oft betray</l>
                     <l>The ſinews of a well knit plot for gain,</l>
                     <l>When theſe as well fight to defend as win.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Dum.</speaker>
                     <l>Noble <hi>Lanove,</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>Mine know, nor fear no death, ſouls of that fire,</l>
                     <l>They'l catch the bullet flying, ſcale a wall</l>
                     <l>Battled with Enemy, ſtand breaches, laugh</l>
                     <l>The thunder of a Canon, call it muſick</l>
                     <l>Fitter a Ladies Chamber than the field;</l>
                     <l>When o'r their heads the Element is ſeel'd,</l>
                     <l>Darkned with Darts, they'l fight under the ſhade,</l>
                     <l>And ask no other roofs to hid their heads in;</l>
                     <l>They fear not <hi>Jove,</hi> and had the Giants been</l>
                     <l>But half ſo ſpirited, they had diſthron'd him:</l>
                     <l>Kill, till they'r kill'd with killing, and oftner die</l>
                     <l>Wearied than wounded, being more oppreſt</l>
                     <l>With giving wounds than taking; when they fall,</l>
                     <l>They fall not vaquiſh'd, but by fate betraid;</l>
                     <l>Such are the men I lead.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Mart.</speaker>
                     <l>They'r Souldiers fit to ſack a Kingdom then,</l>
                     <l>And ſhare the ſpoil between them.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Bourb.</speaker>
                     <p>Were it come to that ſport once.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Dum.</speaker>
                     <p>
                        <hi>Bourbon,</hi> it muſt, or ſome of us muſt fall.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Mart.</speaker>
                     <p>Where ſhall we firſt attempt?</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <pb facs="tcp:98989:17"/>
                     <speaker>Dum.</speaker>
                     <p>The Citadel.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Lanove.</speaker>
                     <p>I ſay no, it's dangerous.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Dum.</speaker>
                     <p>It is the ſafeſt courſe.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Mart.</speaker>
                     <p>Believe it not, it's full of hazard.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Dum.</speaker>
                     <p>So is the generall enterpriſe in hand.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Lano.</speaker>
                     <p>But this of certain ruine.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Mart.</speaker>
                     <l>Give me a reaſon, why you would invade</l>
                     <l>The Palace firſt, and I am ſatisfi'd?</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Dum.</speaker>
                     <l>Then underſtand, <hi>Lamot</hi> lives ſtill at Court.</l>
                     <l>Diſguiſed like a formal Surgion,</l>
                     <l>To whom the Prince being delivered</l>
                     <l>To be embalm'd and boweld, finding life</l>
                     <l>Yet in his Corps, which way he's very skilful,</l>
                     <l>H'as balſomed all his wounds and cur'd him.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Lano.</speaker>
                     <p>And what of all this!</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Dum.</speaker>
                     <l>Have temperance, and hear the reſt:</l>
                     <l>For this the Prince h'as promis'd him the place,</l>
                     <l>The grand Commander of the Citadel,</l>
                     <l>Whoſe aid can ſtead us infinitely.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Lano.</speaker>
                     <p>Is it certain?</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Dum.</speaker>
                     <l>I did but even now receive this Letter,</l>
                     <stage>ſhews the Letter.</stage>
                     <l>Which conſtantly affirms it from himſelf;</l>
                     <l>He ſaies it is not known in Court yet, that the Prince lives,</l>
                     <l>For divers reaſons beſt known to themſelves;</l>
                     <l>And herein doth require our ſecrecie,</l>
                     <l>Therefore dear friends be warie to divulge it.</l>
                     <l>Beſides he ſaies here,</l>
                     <l>That the great Monſeiur's ſuppos'd funeral</l>
                     <l>This day's ſolemnized with greateſt pomp;</l>
                     <l>And how <hi>Aphelia</hi> dies a ſacrifice</l>
                     <l>That hour he is buried on his Herſe:</l>
                     <l>What if we made attempt to ſave the Virgin?</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Lano.</speaker>
                     <l>It may not be, better ſhe fall alone,</l>
                     <l>Than all of us together. And now beſt friends</l>
                     <l>Let us behave us bravely, it's no baſe act</l>
                     <l>We undertake, but our whole Countries freedom</l>
                     <l>From ſlaverie and bondage; men of worth ſtand bare</l>
                     <l>To pages and gilt Butterflies? beſides the Queen</l>
                     <pb facs="tcp:98989:18"/>
                     <l> Will grave us all rather than want ſport</l>
                     <l>In ſpilling human blood; come, let's withdraw,</l>
                     <l>And laie the plat-form of this mighty work;</l>
                     <l>My ſoul ſits ſmiling in me, I divine</l>
                     <l>Though now it lows, I ſhall ſee Sun will ſhine.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <stage>Exeunt.</stage>
                  <stage>
                     <hi>Enter</hi> Clovis <hi>and</hi> Lamot <hi>both diſguiſed.</hi>
                  </stage>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Clo.</speaker>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Strephon,</hi> for ſo thou nam'ſt thy ſelf, thou'ſt made</l>
                     <l>Thy Prince thy ſubject by thy timely cure;</l>
                     <l>This is the hour I muſt be buried living;</l>
                     <l>And this the hour the fair <hi>Aphelia</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>Dyes on my Herſe t'appeaſe my wandring Ghoſt;</l>
                     <l>Say <hi>Strephon,</hi> is it ſo?</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Lam.</speaker>
                     <p>Nay this the very minute: hark, I hear them Comming.</p>
                     <stage>ſad ſolemn muſick.</stage>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Clov.</speaker>
                     <p>Stand cloſe here, wee'l obſerve the Mourners.</p>
                     <stage>
                        <hi>Enter ſix of the Guard, their Halberds reverſt, then a Cardinal,</hi> Landrey, Old Briſſac; <hi>then the Herſe born by ſix young men, then</hi> King, Queen, Eunuch <hi>holding up her train, two or three Ladies, theſe in morning: at the other door, a</hi> Headſman, <hi>two Nuns in white ſinging,</hi> Aphelia <hi>with a Garland on her head, led by two little boyes in white; after theſe, more Virgins ador<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned liked the reſt; both Troops paſſe by each other; the ſong ended, the Herſe is ſet down between both companies,</hi> Aphelia <hi>mourning as one end, and the</hi> King <hi>at the other, who after a little pauſe ſpeaks.</hi>
                     </stage>
                     <lg>
                        <head>The Song by Nuns.</head>
                        <l>
                           <hi>Come bleſt Virgins come and bring</hi>
                        </l>
                        <l>
                           <hi>To this Goddeſs offering,</hi>
                        </l>
                        <l>
                           <hi>Offer to her kiſſes, ſuch</hi>
                        </l>
                        <l>
                           <hi>As make good better by the touch;</hi>
                        </l>
                        <l>
                           <hi>Where her eyes let fall a tear,</hi>
                        </l>
                        <l>
                           <hi>Another Paradice ſprings there;</hi>
                        </l>
                        <l>
                           <hi>It's prepoſtrons crueltie</hi>
                        </l>
                        <l>
                           <hi>To ſaerifice a Deitie;</hi>
                        </l>
                        <l>
                           <hi>If a true path ſhould be trod,</hi>
                        </l>
                        <l>
                           <hi>To her ſacrifice a God.</hi>
                        </l>
                     </lg>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <pb facs="tcp:98989:18"/>
                     <speaker>Clot.</speaker>
                     <l>Set down, ſet down your honourable load,</l>
                     <l>Fitting an <hi>Atlas</hi> ſhoulder; burden of grace</l>
                     <l>And majeſtie immenſe, whoſe weight doth load</l>
                     <l>Heavens ſtooping Porter, under which he groans</l>
                     <l>More than the Spaeres, and ſweats thy weight not theirs;</l>
                     <l>Let me bedew thy Herſe with pious tears,</l>
                     <l>Balm to wounds, repenting ones; look down</l>
                     <l>From heaven empireall and behold me ſtand</l>
                     <l>All flood in ſorrow, drown'd in mine own tears;</l>
                     <l>Behold this ſpotleſſe ſacrifice, a Virgin</l>
                     <l>As pure in thought as Veſture, an Oblation</l>
                     <l>To ranſome <hi>Jove</hi> and Heaven had he been taken,</l>
                     <l>And ſo we yeeld her up.</l>
                     <stage>Delivers her to the Headſman.</stage>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Briſ.</speaker>
                     <l>O my good Lord,</l>
                     <l>This is conſpiracie 'gainſt an old mans life;</l>
                     <l>Have you no other way to murther me,</l>
                     <l>But to begin wit her? are theſe your plots?</l>
                     <l>You'r weary of my counſell? and my place</l>
                     <l>May better be ſuppli'd by greener heads?</l>
                     <l>Pray cut off mine, do, do, a weak old man,</l>
                     <l>My abſence were material, ſince your ſtate</l>
                     <l>Requires Paricides about you,</l>
                     <l>Alas I may be ſpar'd; why muſt ſhe die?</l>
                     <l>Becauſe ſhe's fair? or that a Prince</l>
                     <l>Once thought her ſo? the fault is none of hers,</l>
                     <l>Let nature ſuffer for't; if it prove Art,</l>
                     <l>Or that with plaiſtred cunning ſhe did catch</l>
                     <l>Your Brothers love with an adulterate form,</l>
                     <l>I yeeld her up as not aly'd to me;</l>
                     <l>If not, why ſhould ſhe ſuffer?</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Clot.</speaker>
                     <p>
                        <hi>Briſſac,</hi> peace.</p>
                     <stage>The King takes the ſword from the Exe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cutioner.</stage>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Clov.</speaker>
                     <p>What pageant's this?</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Clot.</speaker>
                     <l>Be it no wonder Lords</l>
                     <l>To ſee a Prince an Executioner;</l>
                     <l>Far be it from the dignitie of <hi>France</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>To let a ſoul forth ſo refin'd as her's</l>
                     <l>With mercinary hands.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Lam.</speaker>
                     <l>Contain your ſelf,</l>
                     <pb facs="tcp:98989:19"/>
                     <l> You may prevent the danger when you pleaſe.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Clot.</speaker>
                     <l>Behold the conqueſt of thine eies <hi>Aphelia,</hi>
                     </l>
                     <stage>the King kneels, and laies the ſword at Aphelia's foot.</stage>
                     <l>
                        <hi>France</hi> at thy foot, tread on his Royaltie;</l>
                     <l>Or if thy nature knows not to forgive,</l>
                     <l>which to believe were impious, take this ſword</l>
                     <l>And ſearch my heart, ſend me a ſacrifice</l>
                     <l>T'appeaſe the troubled ſpirit of thy love.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Qu.</speaker>
                     <p>O <hi>Eunuch,</hi> that ſhee'd take him at his word.</p>
                     <stage>aſide.</stage>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Clot.</speaker>
                     <l>I find a ſpeaking pitty in thine eyes,</l>
                     <l>Which thence will drop upon thy gentle tongue,</l>
                     <l>And cry in peace, Long live my Soveraign.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Aphe.</speaker>
                     <p>Long live <hi>Clotair,</hi> long live my Soveraign.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Clot.</speaker>
                     <l>The motions of the Sphaeres move in that tongue.</l>
                     <l>Turn all your ſables to the Tyrian dye,</l>
                     <l>Your dirges into ſprightful wedding airs.</l>
                     <l>Why looks our Court ſo ſad? is this a time</l>
                     <l>To anckor your aſpects unto the earth?</l>
                     <l>By my bleſt ſelf, he's traytor to the height,</l>
                     <l>That do's not ſtraight ſalute her as his Queen.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Omner.</speaker>
                     <p>Long live <hi>Aphelia</hi> Queen of <hi>France</hi> and us.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Lamot.</speaker>
                     <l>Do you hear this? what are you planet-ſtroken?</l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Clovis,</hi> Prince, Monſiure?</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Qu.</speaker>
                     <p>What will <hi>Clotair</hi> do?</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Clot.</speaker>
                     <p>What heaven ha's pointed for him, Marrie her.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Qu.</speaker>
                     <p>Thy Grave, thy Grave firſt <hi>Clotair.</hi>
                     </p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Clot.</speaker>
                     <p>Cardinal.</p>
                     <stage>The Cardinal and the King whiſper.</stage>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Qu.</speaker>
                     <l>What evill ſpirit's crept into my Son?</l>
                     <l>Venom'd his noble nature, ſickned all</l>
                     <l>His wholſome faculties, ſlain's divinitie?</l>
                     <l>Are theſe your vowes? or canſt thou couzen heaven?</l>
                     <l>Neceſſity of fate depends on it,</l>
                     <l>Your know ſhe muſt to earth.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Clot.</speaker>
                     <l>I, but not yet:</l>
                     <l>Since ſhe ha's conquer'd me, that could do fate,</l>
                     <l>Had ſhe joyn'd with me, the aw'd deſtinies</l>
                     <l>Spin her decrees, and what ſhe wills they act;</l>
                     <l>Sith then what muſt be muſt be, joyn our hands.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <pb facs="tcp:98989:19"/>
                     <speaker>Lam.</speaker>
                     <l>Now, now, prevent them yet, O ſtatue Prince</l>
                     <l>Thou art undone for ever.</l>
                     <stage>The Monſiure ſtands amaz'd.</stage>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Clov.</speaker>
                     <l>Where am I?</l>
                     <l>Awake? for ever rather let me ſleep.</l>
                     <l>Is this a funerall, O that I were a Herſe,</l>
                     <l>And not the mock of what is pagented.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Clot.</speaker>
                     <p>Amazement quite confounds me, <hi>Clovis</hi> alive!</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Lam.</speaker>
                     <l>Yes ſir, by my Art he lives, though his deſire</l>
                     <l>Was not to have it known; this Cheſt contains</l>
                     <l>Nothing but ſpices ſweetly oderiferous.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Clot.</speaker>
                     <l>Into my ſoul I welcome thee dear brother;</l>
                     <l>This ſecond birth of thine brings me more joy,</l>
                     <l>Than had <hi>Aphelia</hi> brought me forth an Heir,</l>
                     <l>Whom now you muſt remember as a Siſter.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Clo.</speaker>
                     <l>O that in nature there was left an Art,</l>
                     <l>Could teach me to forget I ever lov'd</l>
                     <l>This her great Maſterplece; O well built frame,</l>
                     <l>Why doſt thou harbour ſuch unhallow'd gueſts</l>
                     <l>To houſe within thy boſome perjurie?</l>
                     <l>If that our vowes are regiſtred in heaven,</l>
                     <l>Why are they broke on earth—? <hi>Aphelia,</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>This was a haſtie match, the ſubtill air</l>
                     <l>Ha's not yet cool'd the breath, with which thou ſwor'ſt</l>
                     <l>Thy ſelf into my ſoul; and on thy cheeks,</l>
                     <l>The print and path-way of thoſe tears remain</l>
                     <l>That woo'd me to believe ſo: flie me not,</l>
                     <stage>ſhe gives back.</stage>
                     <l>I am no ſpirit; taſt my active pulſe,</l>
                     <l>And you ſhall find it make ſuch harmony.</l>
                     <l>As youth and health enjoy.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Eu,</speaker>
                     <p>The Queen ſhe faints.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Clov.</speaker>
                     <l>Is there a God left ſo propitious</l>
                     <l>To rid me of my fears; ſtill let her ſleep,</l>
                     <l>For if ſhe wake (O King) ſhe will appear</l>
                     <l>Too monſtrous a ſpectre for frail eyes</l>
                     <l>To ſee and keep their ſenſes.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Lam.</speaker>
                     <p>Are you mad?</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Clo.</speaker>
                     <l>Nothing ſo happy <hi>Strephon,</hi> would I were;</l>
                     <l>In times firſt progreſs I diſpair the hour,</l>
                     <pb facs="tcp:98989:20"/>
                     <l> That brings ſuch fortune with it; I ſhould then</l>
                     <l>Forget that ſhe was ever pleaſing to me;</l>
                     <l>I ſhould no more remember ſhe would ſit</l>
                     <l>And ſing me into dreams of Paradice;</l>
                     <l>Never more hang about her Ivory neck</l>
                     <l>Believing ſuch a one <hi>Diana's</hi> war,</l>
                     <l>Never more dote ſhe breaths Arabia,</l>
                     <l>Or kiſs her Corrall lip into a paleneſs.</l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Streph</hi> See, ſhe's return'd, an with majeſtique gaze,</l>
                     <l>In pity rather than contempt, beholds you.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Clov.</speaker>
                     <l>Convey me hence ſome charitable man,</l>
                     <stage>admiringly.</stage>
                     <l>Leſt this ſame Creature looking like a Saint,</l>
                     <l>Hurry my ſoul to Hell; ſhe is a fiend</l>
                     <l>Apparel'd like a woman, ſent on earth</l>
                     <l>For man's deſtruction.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Clot.</speaker>
                     <l>Rule your diſordea'd tongue;</l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Clovis,</hi> what's paſt we are content to think,</l>
                     <l>It was our brother ſpoke, and not our ſubject.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Clov.</speaker>
                     <l>I had forgot my ſelf, yet well remember.</l>
                     <l>Yon Gorgon ha's transfrom'd me into ſtone;</l>
                     <l>And ſince that time my language ha's been harſh,</l>
                     <l>My words too heavie for my tongue, to earthly;</l>
                     <l>I was not born ſo, truſt me <hi>Apbelia:</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>Before I was poſſeſt with theſe black thoughts,</l>
                     <l>I could ſit by thy ſide, and reſt my head</l>
                     <l>Upon the riſing pillows of thy breaſt,</l>
                     <l>Whoſe naturall ſweetneſſe would invite mine eies</l>
                     <l>To ſinck in pleaſing ſlumbers, wake, and kiſſe</l>
                     <l>The Roſe beds that afforded me ſuch bliſs;</l>
                     <l>But thou art now a generall diſeaſe</l>
                     <l>That eat'ſt into my Marrow, turn'ſt my blood,</l>
                     <l>And mak'ſt my veines run poyſon, that each ſenſe</l>
                     <l>Groans at the alteration: am I Monſiure?</l>
                     <l>Do's <hi>Clovis</hi> talk his ſorrows. and not act?</l>
                     <l>O man bewomaniz'd; wert thou not mine,</l>
                     <l>How comes it thou art his?</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Clot.</speaker>
                     <l>You have done ill,</l>
                     <l>And muſt be taught ſo; you Capitulate</l>
                     <l>Not with your equall <hi>Clovis,</hi> ſhe's thy Queen.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <pb facs="tcp:98989:20"/>
                     <speaker>Clov.</speaker>
                     <l>Upon my knees I do acknowledge her,</l>
                     <stage>he kneels.</stage>
                     <l>Queen of my thoughts and my affections.</l>
                     <l>O pardon me, if my ill-tutor'd tongue</l>
                     <l>Ha's forfeited my head; if not, behold</l>
                     <l>Before the ſacred altar of thy ſeet,</l>
                     <l>I lie a willing ſacrifie.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Aphe.</speaker>
                     <l>Ariſe:</l>
                     <l>And henceforth <hi>Clovis</hi> thus inſtruct thy ſoul;</l>
                     <l>There lies a depth in fate, which earthly eies</l>
                     <l>May faintly look into, but cannot fathom;</l>
                     <l>You had my vow till death to be your wiſe,</l>
                     <l>You being dead my vowes were cancelled,</l>
                     <l>And I as thus you ſee beſtow'd.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Clov.</speaker>
                     <l>Farewell;</l>
                     <l>I will no more offend you: would to God</l>
                     <l>Thoſe cruell hands not enough barbarous,</l>
                     <l>That made theſe bleeding witneſſes of love,</l>
                     <l>Had ſet an endleſs period to my life too.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Clot.</speaker>
                     <l>Where there's no help it's boothleſs to complain;</l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Clovis</hi> ſhe's mine; let not your ſpirit war</l>
                     <l>Or mutiny within you, becauſe I ſay't;</l>
                     <l>Nor let thy tongue from henceforth dare preſume,</l>
                     <l>To ſay ſhe might, or ever ſhould be thine;</l>
                     <l>What's paſt once more I pardon, 'tis our wedding day.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Clo.</speaker>
                     <l>A long farewel to love, thus do I break</l>
                     <stage>he breaks the King.</stage>
                     <l>Your broken pledge of faith; and with this kiſs,</l>
                     <l>The laſt that ever <hi>Clovis</hi> muſt print here:</l>
                     <l>Unkiſs the kiſs that feal'd it on thy lips.</l>
                     <l>Ye powers ye are unjuſt, for her wild breath</l>
                     <l>That ha's the ſacred tie of contract broken,</l>
                     <l>Is ſtill the ſame Arabia that it was:</l>
                     <stage>the King Clotain pulls him.</stage>
                     <l>Nay I have done; beware of jealouſie,</l>
                     <l>I would not have you nouriſh jealous thoughts;</l>
                     <l>Though ſhe ha's broke her faith to me, to you</l>
                     <l>Againſt her reputation ſhee'l be true:</l>
                     <l>Farewel my firſt love loſt, i'l chuſe to have</l>
                     <l>No wife, till death ſhall wed me to my Grave.</l>
                     <l>Come <hi>Strephon,</hi> come and teach me how to die,</l>
                     <l>That gav'ſt me life ſo unadviſedly.</l>
                     <stage>Ex. Clovis &amp; Streph.</stage>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <pb facs="tcp:98989:21"/>
                     <speaker>Clot.</speaker>
                     <l>Let <hi>Clovis</hi> that way go, this way will we,</l>
                     <l>He's great with grief, we with felicity,</l>
                     <stage>Exe, all with Glotair.</stage>
                  </sp>
                  <stage>Manent Queen and Eunuch.</stage>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Qu.</speaker>
                     <l>Miſchief grows lean <hi>Coſtrato,</hi> all our plots</l>
                     <l>Turn head upon themſelves, my brains grow weak;</l>
                     <l>And in this Globe the policie's not left</l>
                     <l>To kill a worm unſeen; I am undone,</l>
                     <l>And all my plots diſcover'd.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Eu.</speaker>
                     <l>This is ſtrange,</l>
                     <l>Some comick Devil croſſes our deſignes;</l>
                     <l>How elſe ſhould he revive, or yea prepar'd,</l>
                     <l>Nay in the arms <hi>Landrey,</hi> when deſire</l>
                     <l>Had made you all a Venus, meet events</l>
                     <l>So barren in their expectations?</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Qu.</speaker>
                     <l>Their lies the grief <hi>Coſtrate;</hi> Had the Court,</l>
                     <l>So I had quencht theſe burnings flames within,</l>
                     <l>Been buri'd her cinders, I had car'd not.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Eu.</speaker>
                     <l>But yet <hi>Landreis</hi> eſcape doth qualifie</l>
                     <l>The non-performance.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Qu.</speaker>
                     <l>That ſits ſmiling here,</l>
                     <l>It ſet my brains upon the tentors <hi>Eunuch;</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>Was't not a rare device?</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Eu.</speaker>
                     <l>And was not I</l>
                     <l>As fortunate to leave that Armour there;</l>
                     <l>But now what's to be done?</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Qu.</speaker>
                     <l>My dul Aethlope,</l>
                     <l>I will inſtruct thy blackneſſe; learn to know</l>
                     <l>My reputation's ſichned, and my fame</l>
                     <l>Is look'd into with narrow eyes at Court;</l>
                     <l>Therefore it's thus decreed, I will remove,</l>
                     <l>And ſequeſter my ſelf from company.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Eu.</speaker>
                     <p>Good!</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Qu.</speaker>
                     <l>Thou know'ſt where <hi>Childrick</hi> keep his Concubine</l>
                     <l>To none diſcover'd by thy ſelf and me,</l>
                     <l>For which ſhe is no more.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Eu.</speaker>
                     <p>Right.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Qu.</speaker>
                     <l>There will I</l>
                     <l>And my <hi>Landrey</hi> ſecurely ſpend our time,</l>
                     <pb facs="tcp:98989:21"/>
                     <l> Revil, imbrace, and what not my <hi>Eunuch:</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>The Cave that leads unto the poſtern Gate,</l>
                     <l>Which <hi>Childrick</hi> made, will give him entrance:</l>
                     <l>No ele acquainted, being thus retir'd.</l>
                     <l>What luſt inflam'd muſt be by luſt unfir'd.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Eu.</speaker>
                     <p>Excellent miſtris, I applaud your brain.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Qu.</speaker>
                     <l>I will away to night, I cannot brook</l>
                     <l>Theſe loathed Nuptials, they have undone</l>
                     <l>My hopes on earth for ever, therefore my <hi>Eunuch,</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>Acquaint <hi>Landrey</hi> with theſe deſignes.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Eu.</speaker>
                     <p>What elſe?</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Qu.</speaker>
                     <l>If by the engine of thy ſtronger brain,</l>
                     <l>Thou couldſt remove—</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Eu.</speaker>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Aphelia</hi> or the King,</l>
                     <l>Monſiure, or all; it is not ſo my Queen?</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Qu.</speaker>
                     <l>Thou haſt a brain which doth ingender thoughts</l>
                     <l>As regall as our own, which do beget</l>
                     <l>A race of rare events; what pitty 'tis</l>
                     <l>Thy body ſhould be ſterril, ſince thy mind</l>
                     <l>Is of ſo pregnant and a fruitful kind;</l>
                     <l>Farewell, remember me.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <stage>Exit Queen.</stage>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Eu.</speaker>
                     <l>Remember you?</l>
                     <l>Your Gibſhip ſhall be thought on fear it not;</l>
                     <l>And now bethink thee <hi>Eunuch,</hi> all thy plots</l>
                     <l>Find fruitleſſe iſſues, onely in the King,</l>
                     <l>His worſhip walkt into the other world,</l>
                     <l>Like a tame ſuckling Pig that dy'd o'th pipp;</l>
                     <l>The trouble is behind, my hate extends</l>
                     <l>To the whole family, I muſt root them up,</l>
                     <l>And beldam firſt with you: but how? but how?</l>
                     <l>If (in her proud deſire) I do prevent</l>
                     <l>Her luſt this ſecond time, before the third</l>
                     <l>She may repent and ſave her loathed ſoul,</l>
                     <l>Which my revenge would damn; yet were ſhe croſt,</l>
                     <l>Her luſt being now at full flood in her,</l>
                     <l>And no way left to quench her burning flame,</l>
                     <l>Her dryer bones would make a bonfire,</l>
                     <l>Fit forthe Devill to warm his hands by:</l>
                     <pb facs="tcp:98989:22"/>
                     <l> Stay, ſtay, <hi>Castrato;</hi> no, this muſt not be,</l>
                     <l>Nor Muſt the high and mighty Queen <hi>Aphelia</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>This night enjoy her Bridegroom, I muſt ſet</l>
                     <l>Some miſchief inſtantly on foot to ſtop it;</l>
                     <l>If I miſcarry in it ſtory ſhall tell,</l>
                     <l>I did attempt it bravely though I fell.</l>
                     <stage>Enter Lamot and Clovis.</stage>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Clov</speaker>
                     <l>Diſſwade me not, <hi>Caſtrato</hi> I have ſought thee</l>
                     <l>Through every angle of this ſpatious Court,</l>
                     <l>I've buſineſſe to impart.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Eu.</speaker>
                     <p>And ſo have I.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Clo.</speaker>
                     <l>Mine is of honourable conſequence,</l>
                     <l>And doth require thine aid.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Eu.</speaker>
                     <p>So doth mine yours.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Clo.</speaker>
                     <p>
                        <hi>Aphelia</hi> is—</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Eu.</speaker>
                     <l>Your Brother Wife. and you</l>
                     <l>Would fain injoy her too: why ſir you may,</l>
                     <l>But time muſt work her.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Clo.</speaker>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Eunuch,</hi> thou art wide;</l>
                     <l>Thoſe vaneties of love are quite extinct,</l>
                     <l>Revenge doth ſwell the Monſiure, and his thought</l>
                     <l>Which burn within him muſt be quencht with blood;</l>
                     <l>I have incenſt the King with yellowneſs,</l>
                     <l>With doubtfull phraſes on <hi>Aphelia's</hi> fame;</l>
                     <l>See'ſt thou this Letter, 'tis a ſcript I feign'd,</l>
                     <stage>ſhew a Paper.</stage>
                     <l>For I can counterfeit <hi>Aphelia's</hi> hand;</l>
                     <l>The King ha's baniſh'd <hi>Landrey</hi> from the Court,</l>
                     <l>Becauſe he wore the Jewel which he ſent</l>
                     <l>To his <hi>Aphelia:</hi> light ſuſpitions,</l>
                     <l>But this ſhall aggravte; find thou the King,</l>
                     <l>Shew him his Note, it doth expreſſe great love</l>
                     <l>To <hi>Landrey</hi> from <hi>Aphelia;</hi> and withall,</l>
                     <l>It mentioneth the Jewel as a Gift</l>
                     <l>To gratifie her ſervant; this to the reſt</l>
                     <l>Of poyſon he ha's ſuck'd already in,</l>
                     <l>Will ſo inflame him, that the Court ſhall burn</l>
                     <l>Too hot for his <hi>Aphelia.</hi>
                     </l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Eu.</speaker>
                     <l>Think it done;</l>
                     <l>But now your aid, ſince that your mind is bent</l>
                     <pb facs="tcp:98989:22"/>
                     <l> On honourable ends, here's one will trie you.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Clo.</speaker>
                     <l>Thou'dſt have me joyn my ſelf unto the Rebels,</l>
                     <l>And with my perſon grace their cauſe, perhaps</l>
                     <l>That is not now to plot.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Eu.</speaker>
                     <l>I find you high,</l>
                     <l>Worthy the name of Monſieure; yet your thoughts</l>
                     <l>Hit not my purpoſe, it is ſuch that made</l>
                     <l>Your Brother quake to hear.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Clo.</speaker>
                     <l>What is it <hi>Eunuch?</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>If that if bear an honourable ſound,</l>
                     <l>Though death ſtood gaping wide to ſwallow me,</l>
                     <l>I would not ſhrink nor fear.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Eu.</speaker>
                     <l>Noble; hear it then,</l>
                     <l>Your Mother's looſe, and this night renders up</l>
                     <l>Her body unto luſt, if not prevented;</l>
                     <l>I can direct you where and when, with whom.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Clo.</speaker>
                     <p>My ſoul finds the man, is't not <hi>Landrey?</hi>
                     </p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Eu.</speaker>
                     <p>The ſame</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Clov.</speaker>
                     <l>I'l tear him all to pieces then,</l>
                     <l>Whore my Mother; <hi>Eunuch</hi> lead the way,</l>
                     <l>In what thou ſhalt preſcribe we will obey.</l>
                     <stage>Exeunt omnes.</stage>
                  </sp>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div n="4" type="act">
               <div n="1" type="scene">
                  <head>Actus Quartus, Scena Prima.</head>
                  <stage>
                     <hi>Enter</hi> Clotair, <hi>Solus,</hi>
                  </stage>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Clot.</speaker>
                     <l>WHat vulture gripes me here, ha, what art thou?</l>
                     <l>If thou beeſt jealouſie mount and be gone;</l>
                     <l>Fly to the vulgar boſome, whoſe cheap thoughts</l>
                     <l>Deſpair their own performance; in a Prince</l>
                     <l>Thou ſhew'ſt a nature retrograde to honour.</l>
                     <l>Suppoſe ſhe gave the Jewels, muſt it follow</l>
                     <l>She therefore is diſloyal? poor conſequence,</l>
                     <l>A Bable for a boy to play withall;</l>
                     <l>I am reſolv'd, hark, I hear her comming;</l>
                     <l>O <hi>Juno,</hi> what a look and gate is there!</l>
                  </sp>
                  <stage>
                     <pb facs="tcp:98989:23"/> 
                     <hi>Enter</hi> Aphelia <hi>as going to bed, two or three Ladyes with Light.</hi>
                  </stage>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Aphe.</speaker>
                     <l>Mock me not Ladyes with this Ceremony,</l>
                     <l>For I am fitter to attend on you;</l>
                     <l>I am become a ſervant and a ſlave</l>
                     <l>To every moodle paſſion of my Lord.</l>
                     <l>All that's behind I can perform my ſelf,</l>
                     <l>Without this complement.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>1 <hi>Lady</hi>
                     </speaker>
                     <l>Sweet Lady,</l>
                     <l>You muſt not weigh theſe things ſo deeply,</l>
                     <l>Your Lord is of a noble ſpirit;</l>
                     <l>And you ſhall ſee how calm he will return,</l>
                     <l>Bleſſing your Bridall bed with fruitfull iſſue.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Aphe.</speaker>
                     <l>No, no;</l>
                     <l>The Safforn-coated Hymen frowns upon us,</l>
                     <l>Theſe Tapers here wre lighted at a pile,</l>
                     <l>As ſit Attendance on the Grave, not Bed;</l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Juno</hi> denyes her preſence at this match,</l>
                     <l>And all the ill preſaging birds of night</l>
                     <l>Sing fatall Requiems for a Bridall Song;</l>
                     <l>O Ladyes, is not this ominous?</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Clot.</speaker>
                     <l>Yes my <hi>Aphelia,</hi> if that ragged fate</l>
                     <l>Lie in a kiſs, then it is ominous.</l>
                     <l>Let me dwell here; I am raviſht,</l>
                     <l>Am I on earth? no, heaven is here,</l>
                     <l>And all th'unimitable joyes, that Poets feign,</l>
                     <l>Are better'd in thy goodneſſe.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Aphe.</speaker>
                     <l>I hope your fears are ſatisfied now,</l>
                     <l>You bear a brow ſo ſweetly pleaſant.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Clot.</speaker>
                     <l>What pretty foolery is this <hi>Aphelia?</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>I am not jealous, for by all that good</l>
                     <l>I cannot think thee evill; kiſs me ſweet,</l>
                     <stage>kiſſes her.</stage>
                     <l>There's no deceit lies here; again, agen:</l>
                     <stage>again kiſſes.</stage>
                     <l>Her kiſſes melt upon my lip, if ſin</l>
                     <l>Have ſo much heaven in't, i'l be a ſinner;</l>
                     <l>Prethee forgive my folly that could be wrought</l>
                     <l>To ſuch a ſenſeleſſe paſſion, come let's in</l>
                     <l>And ſhake this off as it never been.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <pb facs="tcp:98989:23"/>
                     <speaker>1 <hi>Lady.</hi>
                     </speaker>
                     <l>We muſt a while my Lord intreat your abſence,</l>
                     <l>We have ſome certain Notions to deliver,</l>
                     <l>Some pillow counſels; i'l aſſure your highneſs</l>
                     <l>It ſhall be no wayes prejudiciall to you.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>2 <hi>Lady.</hi>
                     </speaker>
                     <l>You ſee ſhe's not prepar'd, till that's perform'd</l>
                     <l>She's ours; that done, we yeeld her up</l>
                     <l>To the dark night, and mercy of your Lordſhip.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Clot.</speaker>
                     <l>Go then unharnis your Lady for theſe wars,</l>
                     <l>For we are of the <hi>Camilli,</hi> and fight naked.</l>
                     <stage>Exe. Ladies &amp; Aphe.</stage>
                     <l>Ye powers that favour Lovers, infuſe apt ſtrength</l>
                     <l>Through every nerve and ſinew of this frame;</l>
                     <l>Make me all pleaſure; and unto the bride</l>
                     <l>Add every vein a <hi>Venus;</hi> guid me light,</l>
                     <l>Wherein on bed lies all the worlds delight.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <stage>
                     <hi>Offers to go out and meets the</hi> Eunuch.</stage>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Eu.</speaker>
                     <l>Not yet in bed! O happy, happy minute,</l>
                     <l>Untill this hour I ne'r was fortunate;</l>
                     <l>I have preſerv'd my King, my Prince, my Patron,</l>
                     <l>From the looſe ardor of a Strumphts bed.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Clot.</speaker>
                     <p>What's this?</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Eu.</speaker>
                     <l>Be not this ſecond time incredulous,</l>
                     <l>And ſcorn my honeſt heart; or grant you were,</l>
                     <l>Diſhoneſts as the Suburbs, I am loath</l>
                     <l>To nominate her whore though it betrue.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Clot.</speaker>
                     <p>True? ha!</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Eu.</speaker>
                     <l>Leave this Lethargiz'd paſſion which benumns</l>
                     <l>Your nobler nature; turn your eies on this;</l>
                     <stage>ſhews a Letter.</stage>
                     <l>Whoſe Character is this?</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Clot.</speaker>
                     <l>It is <hi>Aphelia's</hi> hand, the very ſame</l>
                     <l>Which I have often ſeen <hi>Clovis</hi> peruſe</l>
                     <stage>
                        <hi>The bed thruſt forth with</hi> Aphe. aſleep.</stage>
                     <l>In his loves amorous purſute.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Eu.</speaker>
                     <p>Read the Contents.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Clot.</speaker>
                     <l>A Letter that ſhee loves <hi>Landrey,</hi> with thanks</l>
                     <l>For his ſo freequent viſits, which ſhe repaies</l>
                     <l>With the rich Jewel ſent her by the King,</l>
                     <l>Wiſhing a perpetuitie of imbracements.</l>
                     <l>Ten thouſand Ravens crook is this black paper.</l>
                     <pb facs="tcp:98989:24"/>
                     <l> How came you by it.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Eu.</speaker>
                     <l>I ſaw it drop from <hi>Landrey,</hi> but ne'r thought</l>
                     <l>'Fore I perus'd it what it did contain;</l>
                     <l>Which finding, in my duty I was bound</l>
                     <l>To ſave my Prince from ruine.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Clot.</speaker>
                     <l>Hold my heart,</l>
                     <l>Oh what ſhall <hi>Clotair</hi> do?—it cannot be;</l>
                     <l>Do but behold her face, and thou ſhalt read</l>
                     <l>What we call vertue there, and modeſty;</l>
                     <l>Here is a look would perſwade cruelty</l>
                     <l>To ſigh and ſhed a tear, bride <hi>Nemeſis</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>To knot her ſteely ſcourge with Plume of Down,</l>
                     <l>And <hi>Jove</hi> himſelf to call her vice a virtue,</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Eu.</speaker>
                     <l>A book of Devils may have the Cover gilt;</l>
                     <l>Treaſon lyes Cabin'd in the ſmootheſt brow;</l>
                     <l>The Devil can aſſume an Angles form;</l>
                     <l>Your wife is fair, but fair to do you harm.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Clot.</speaker>
                     <l>Oh ſay not ſo, ſhe is the neateſt cut</l>
                     <l>As <hi>e'r</hi> was printed by the hand of heaven;</l>
                     <l>Here is a volum of Divinity,</l>
                     <l>Compos'd ſo rarely, that to add to this,</l>
                     <l>Or take away from hence, were ſuch a ſin</l>
                     <l>Repentance could not expiate; i'l not touch</l>
                     <l>With hands unhallowrd ſuch a puritie,</l>
                     <l>Could it change all my thoughts to peace and ſilence.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Eu.</speaker>
                     <p>My Lord —</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Clot.</speaker>
                     <l>Peace ſlave,</l>
                     <l>Thou that infects all peace.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Eu.</speaker>
                     <l>Why are you thus diſtemper'd? let not truth</l>
                     <l>Make you ſo wild a tempeſt; were it falſe,</l>
                     <l>Or that I ſought the ruine of your houſe,</l>
                     <l>Your youth and honour, then it were a time</l>
                     <l>To ſwell beyond all charming down, but being truth-</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Clot.</speaker>
                     <l>Truth! hence and avoid my ſight, fly where the world</l>
                     <l>Promiſcuouſly combines without diſtinction;</l>
                     <l>Where every man is every womans husband,</l>
                     <l>Or where it's thought a curteſie to have</l>
                     <l>A fellow labourer in the marriage bed.</l>
                     <pb facs="tcp:98989:24"/>
                     <l> Theſe were a people that might bear with thee,</l>
                     <l>And fit for thee to dwell with; hence away,</l>
                     <l>And if thou lov'ſt thy life, acquaint thy feet</l>
                     <l>With ſuch by paths that we may never meet.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <stage>Exit.</stage>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Eu.</speaker>
                     <l>This Prince is of a nature mild and genlte,</l>
                     <l>His mothers milk's too fluent in his eies,</l>
                     <l>And much I fear his reſolution:</l>
                     <l>Yet I will work him forward; ſhe awakes</l>
                     <stage>Aphelia ſtirs in the bed.</stage>
                     <l>I'l after him and fetch him back; if then</l>
                     <l>She ſcape his hate, Hell has no power with men.</l>
                     <stage>Ex. Ex.</stage>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Aphe.</speaker>
                     <l>Oh, oh, oh, help, help my Lord and husband;</l>
                     <l>O my Father, my Lord and husband; help, help.</l>
                     <l>Bleſs me Divinity, is it but a Dream! ha the light</l>
                     <l>Gone; who waits there? <hi>Iſabel, Julia.</hi>
                     </l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Iſa.</speaker>
                     <l>It was my Ladies voice, do's ſhe call for help?</l>
                     <stage>Ent. Iſabel with a light.</stage>
                     <l>I cannot blame her; were I in her place I ſhould</l>
                     <l>Do ſo too, the Prince looks like a bungler.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Aphe.</speaker>
                     <p>Who's there? <hi>Iſabel?</hi>
                     </p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Iſab.</speaker>
                     <p>Did you call Maddam?</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Aphe.</speaker>
                     <p>Saw'ſt thou nothing? where is my Lord?</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Iſab.</speaker>
                     <l>Is he abſent? I cannot blame her then to cry for help,</l>
                     <l>I ſhould do it my ſelf; a Prince, a Puppit would have</l>
                     <l>Been more manly: how do you Maddam?</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Aphe.</speaker>
                     <p>All ſtands not well.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Iſab.</speaker>
                     <p>I believe that faithfully.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Aph.</speaker>
                     <l>O Girl I've paſt the diſmal'ſt part of night,</l>
                     <l>As ever tortur'd fancy with extremes.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Iſab.</speaker>
                     <p>If all Brides ſhould be ſo tortur'd, i'd for ſwear Marriage.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Aphe.</speaker>
                     <l>Methoughts I ſaw my Father in a Vault,</l>
                     <l>His ſilver hair made crimſon with his blood;</l>
                     <l>My brother at his Herſe upon his knees,</l>
                     <l>Taking a ſolemn oath for his revenge;</l>
                     <l>Yet all this while fancy ſo fool'd my ſenſe,</l>
                     <l>Methought that I was here; where on the inſtant,</l>
                     <l>My Lord in preparation for my bed,</l>
                     <l>Was by an uglyfiend raviſht from hence</l>
                     <l>And hurried to deſtruction; here I awak'd,</l>
                     <pb facs="tcp:98989:25"/>
                     <l> And they ready—</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Clo.</speaker>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Landrey,</hi> blood doth ſwell</l>
                     <l>The Monſiur's thoughts, to ſend thy ſoul to Hell.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <stage>Exeunt omnes.</stage>
               </div>
               <div n="3" type="scene">
                  <head>SCEN. III.</head>
                  <stage>
                     <hi>Enter</hi> Landrey, <hi>muſick above, and this Song.</hi>
                  </stage>
                  <lg>
                     <head>The Song.</head>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Wiſdome bids ui ſhun the Court,</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>What great ones do, fame will report;</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Here we may enjoy each other,</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>And no eye our loves diſcover.</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>I will make thee choice of poſet,</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Beds of Caſtia mixt with Roſes;</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Where wee'l toy, and kiſſe, and varie</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Pleaſures till the mores diſoloſes</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>All our ſecrets, if thou's tarry.</hi>
                     </l>
                  </lg>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Lan</speaker>
                     <l>If I will tarry, let me wither here,</l>
                     <l>Within theſe ſacred walls let me expire,</l>
                     <l>And ſpend the remnant of my life that's left,</l>
                     <l>In ſervice of the Deitie lives here,</l>
                     <l>The air's perfum'd each room thorugh which I walk,</l>
                     <l>Banquets the ſenſes, courts the appetice</l>
                     <l>Of every facultie that makes up man,</l>
                     <l>To complement it into paradice.</l>
                     <l>If then Elyſium's here; where are thoſe ſhades,</l>
                     <l>Thoſe bleſſed apparitions Poets feign?</l>
                     <l>Appear my Goddeſs and out ſing the Poets:</l>
                     <stage>Enter Queen.</stage>
                     <l>Realty of fancy that excell'ſt</l>
                     <l>The faint expreſſions of a lazie tongue,</l>
                     <l>Whoſe houſe is roof'd with fleſh; to tell thy worth,</l>
                     <l>Tongues tip'd with imortality would faint in't.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Qu.</speaker>
                     <l>Excellent ſervant, what houſe do you write too?</l>
                     <l>Poet and Actor both? why, this ſudden gaze,</l>
                     <l>Your caſes are too narrow for your eies?</l>
                     <l>Pray ſpare your Optiques ſir for <hi>Venus</hi> ſervice.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Lan.</speaker>
                     <l>No,</l>
                     <l>I'l play the prodigal with my precious ſight,</l>
                     <pb facs="tcp:98989:25"/>
                     <l> And ſpend it all on you; to view your ſecond</l>
                     <l>Were ſuch a happineſs, after the which</l>
                     <l>It were a ſin to ſee more.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Qu.</speaker>
                     <l>bleſs me <hi>Rahlais,</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>And all ye foſter phanſies of the <hi>French;</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>What ails the man? my <hi>Landrey</hi> Laureat.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Lin.</speaker>
                     <l>It is my <hi>Queen</hi> that's Laureat, whoſe bleſt ſight</l>
                     <l>Creates a Poet; this divine feature</l>
                     <l>Heaven onely made to make man ingenious.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Qu.</speaker>
                     <l>Is this <hi>Extempare,</hi> or have you hir'd</l>
                     <l>Some hackney Muſe acquainted with the road</l>
                     <l>Of vulgar exoricſms to charm cheap beauties;</l>
                     <l>Take up, at this ſpeed elſe your Muſe will founder.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Land.</speaker>
                     <l>Founder, and have her founders by? with patience</l>
                     <l>Here but theſe poor expreſſions of your worth,</l>
                     <l>Which faintly paint forth your perfections,</l>
                     <l>And you ſhall bleſſe my Muſe.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Qu.</speaker>
                     <l>Wee'l hear your jigg,</l>
                     <l>How is your Ballad titl'd? come pronounce.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <stage>Landrey Reads.</stage>
                     <lg>
                        <l>
                           <hi>From head to foot,</hi> Fredigond <hi>been</hi>
                        </l>
                        <l>
                           <hi>Far excelling beauties Queen;</hi>
                        </l>
                        <l>
                           <hi>Had</hi> Jaſon <hi>but beheld her hair,</hi>
                        </l>
                        <l>
                           <hi>The golden Fleece had ne'r ſeem'd fair;</hi>
                        </l>
                        <l>
                           <hi>Thoſe ſtars which mortals ſuppoſe eyes,</hi>
                        </l>
                        <l>
                           <hi>Were aſcendant in the skies,</hi>
                        </l>
                        <l>
                           <hi>When it fell to</hi> Venus <hi>lot</hi>
                        </l>
                        <l>
                           <hi>That little</hi> Cupid <hi>was begot.</hi>
                        </l>
                        <l>
                           <hi>Her tongue in which the Sphares do move,</hi>
                        </l>
                        <l>
                           <hi>Organ of divineſt love,</hi>
                        </l>
                        <l>
                           <hi>Was by</hi> Apollo <hi>fram'd, that be</hi>
                        </l>
                        <l>
                           <hi>From hence might learn more harmonies;</hi>
                        </l>
                        <l>
                           <hi>Who neats her teeth, and lips diſcloſes,</hi>
                        </l>
                        <l>
                           <hi>VValls of Pearl, and gates of Roſes;</hi>
                        </l>
                        <l>
                           <hi>Two leaved doores that lead the way</hi>
                        </l>
                        <l>
                           <hi>Through her breath t'</hi> Arabia,</l>
                        <l>
                           <hi>To which would</hi> Cupid <hi>grant that bliſs,</hi>
                        </l>
                        <l>
                           <hi>I'd go a pilgrimage to kiſs:</hi>
                        </l>
                        <l>
                           <hi>Thoſe bills of ſnow which on her breaſt.</hi>
                        </l>
                        <pb facs="tcp:98989:26"/>
                        <l> 
                           <hi>Riſe ſwelling with their double creſt,</hi>
                        </l>
                        <l>
                           <hi>Mate</hi> Parnaſſus <hi>mountain, whence</hi>
                        </l>
                        <l>
                           <hi>The Muſes ſuck their eloquence;</hi>
                        </l>
                        <l>
                           <hi>Whoſe parts which we will not diſcover</hi>
                        </l>
                        <l>
                           <hi>Hee'l imagine that's a lover.</hi>
                        </l>
                     </lg>
                     <lg>
                        <l>
                           <hi>Like</hi> Juno <hi>ſhe doth go,</hi>
                        </l>
                        <l>
                           <hi>Like</hi> Pallas <hi>talk and ſow,</hi>
                        </l>
                        <l>
                           <hi>Like</hi> Venus <hi>in her bliſs,</hi>
                        </l>
                        <l>
                           <hi>Each kiſſe a</hi> Cupid <hi>is,</hi>
                        </l>
                     </lg>
                     <lg>
                        <l>
                           <hi>And her hands as white as ſnow.</hi>
                        </l>
                        <l>
                           <hi>From head to foot my Miſtriſs been</hi>
                        </l>
                        <l>
                           <hi>Far excelling beauties Queen.</hi>
                        </l>
                     </lg>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Qu.</speaker>
                     <l>Leave theſe ariall Viands, taſt of that</l>
                     <l>Is here ſubſtantiall; how like you the fruit?</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Land.</speaker>
                     <p>Let me for ever dwell upon theſe lips.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Qu.</speaker>
                     <l>You are too greedy of theſe rarities,</l>
                     <l>And muſt be dyeted, leſt ſurfeiting</l>
                     <l>Your appetite ſhould ſicken and ſo die.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Lan.</speaker>
                     <l>Die on yuur lips, O death-bed for a <hi>Jove,</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>Who's buried here, his Grave's immortall love;</l>
                     <l>Here will I dwell, and know no age nor ſorrow.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Q.</speaker>
                     <p>Yet <hi>Childrick</hi> knew them both.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Lan.</speaker>
                     <l>A froſty Prince</l>
                     <l>Begot on <hi>January</hi> by a <hi>Dutch man.</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>And worthy of thſe flames he now indures.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <stage>
                     <hi>Enter</hi> Clovis <hi>from under the Stage with his Fathers Grown and Robes on.</hi>
                  </stage>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Qu.</speaker>
                     <p>What noiſe is this? guard me divinitie.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Clov.</speaker>
                     <l>What has my harſhnes done? ſhe is my Mother;</l>
                     <l>My conſcience tells me I was much to blame</l>
                     <l>Thus to delude her fancy; ſhe returns.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Qu.</speaker>
                     <l>O <hi>Childrick</hi> I confeſſe 'twas I that kill'd thee,</l>
                     <l>Theſe hands adminiſtred the fatal draught</l>
                     <l>That ſet thy ſoul on wing.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Clov.</speaker>
                     <p>What do I hear?</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Qu.</speaker>
                     <l>Oh do not ſnatch my ſoul from out this world,</l>
                     <l>Till I have bath'd it in repentant tears,</l>
                     <l>And made it fit for heaven.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <pb facs="tcp:98989:26"/>
                     <speaker>Clov.</speaker>
                     <l>She faints again;</l>
                     <stage>he puts off his robes.</stage>
                     <l>Who waits within? come forth and lend your aid;</l>
                     <stage>Enter Lamot at the Trap door.</stage>
                     <l>O welcome <hi>Strephon;</hi> uſe thy beſt of skill</l>
                     <l>That maſters nature, and doth life reſtore,</l>
                     <l>Beyond the Art of <hi>Aeſculapius;</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>Apply thy gentleſt med'cines.</l>
                     <stage>Enter Muſicians.</stage>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Lam.</speaker>
                     <l>Let us withdraw;</l>
                     <l>My life ſir anſwer hers if ſhe miſcarry.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Clov.</speaker>
                     <p>What are ye?</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Muſi.</speaker>
                     <l>Muſicianes, whoſe obedience</l>
                     <l>Doth here attend the Queen.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Clov.</speaker>
                     <l>Bawds, arrant-bawds;</l>
                     <l>I'l talk with you anon; in, in.</l>
                     <stage>Exeunt omnes.</stage>
                  </sp>
                  <stage>Enter the Guard.</stage>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>1 <hi>Gua.</hi>
                     </speaker>
                     <p>Stand cloſe, ſtand cloſe, I heard a buſling within here while.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>2 <hi>Gua</hi>
                     </speaker>
                     <p>Buſling, and they come this way here's that ſhall buſlle them.</p>
                     <stage>Enter Landrey.</stage>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>3 <hi>Gua.</hi>
                     </speaker>
                     <p>Fly upon him, hee's drunk, and will betray us all.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Land.</speaker>
                     <l>I am betraid, tht Monſiure ſeeks my life,</l>
                     <l>All waies 'gainſt m'eſcape are fortifi'd;</l>
                     <l>O cruel fortune bawd to time and fate,</l>
                     <l>That ſooth'ſt us up to make us ruinate:</l>
                     <l>For now thou know'ſt no tears, anon no glee,</l>
                     <l>But onely conſtant in inconſtancic.</l>
                     <stage>finds the Robes.</stage>
                     <l>Ha! what is here? great Goddeſs pardon me,</l>
                     <l>I have offended 'gainſt thy Deitie.</l>
                     <l>This ſhall delude the Watch; thrice bleſſed hap</l>
                     <l>That thus deliver'ſt whom they would intrap.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>2 <hi>Guard.</hi>
                     </speaker>
                     <l>I will not ſtand, nor I cannot ſtand; d'ee think</l>
                     <l>I'm drunk, what's that?</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Om. Gua.</speaker>
                     <p>Bleſſe us, Obleſſe us; Diabolo, Diabolo.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>2 <hi>Gua.</hi>
                     </speaker>
                     <l>The Devil, what a Devil care I, keep off Devil,</l>
                     <l>I ſay keep off, I do not fear thee; are you</l>
                     <l>Sneaking back, you cowardly Rogue, d'ee budge;</l>
                     <l>I hate a cowardly rogue, as I hate, as I hate the</l>
                     <l>Devil; take that.</l>
                     <stage>knocks him down.</stage>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <pb facs="tcp:98989:27"/>
                     <speaker>Land.</speaker>
                     <p>Oh, oh, oh.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>2 <hi>Guar.</hi>
                     </speaker>
                     <l>Oh, oh, oh, i'l make you cry oh;</l>
                     <l>What Devil made you in my way?</l>
                     <l>I'l now ſee what money he carries about him;</l>
                     <l>Men ſay the Prince of darkneſſe is a Gentleman,</l>
                     <l>By'rladie he ha's good clothes; but yet for all that</l>
                     <l>He may have no money.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <stage>Enter Queen, Clovis, Lamot undiſguiſed, Muſicians.</stage>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Qu.</speaker>
                     <l>I know not were he is, or if <hi>I</hi> did,</l>
                     <l>Before i'd yeeld him up to thy revenge,</l>
                     <l>I'l die the thouſand deaths.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Clov.</speaker>
                     <l>Thou glorious light, that in thy naturall Orb</l>
                     <l>Didſt comfortably ſhine upon this Kingdome;</l>
                     <l>How is thy worth ecclips'd, what a dull darkneſs</l>
                     <l>Hangs round about thy fame? in all this piece,</l>
                     <l>To every limb whereof I once ow'd dutie,</l>
                     <l>I know not where now to find out my mother.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Qu.</speaker>
                     <p>The Devil and diſobedience blinds your eyes;</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Clov.</speaker>
                     <l>O that I had no eyes, ſo you no ſhame;</l>
                     <l>Murther your Husband to arrive at luſt,</l>
                     <l>And then to lay the blame on innocents?</l>
                     <l>Bluſh, bluſh, thou worſe than woman.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Qu.</speaker>
                     <p>Ha, ha, ha.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Clov.</speaker>
                     <l>Hold my heart,</l>
                     <l>You'r impudent in ſin; has your proud page</l>
                     <l>Made you thus valiant? tell me, where he is;</l>
                     <l>For if you dally with me, know this hand</l>
                     <l>Shall rip him from thy heart, though Cabin'd there.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Qu.</speaker>
                     <l>How dar'ſt thou cloth thy ſpeech in ſuch a phraſe</l>
                     <l>To me thy naturall Mother?</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Clov.</speaker>
                     <l>My Mother!</l>
                     <l>Adulterate woman, ſhame of Royal tie,</l>
                     <l>I bluſh to call thee mother; thy foul luſts</l>
                     <l>Have taught me words of that harſh conſequence</l>
                     <l>That Stigmatize obedience, and do brand</l>
                     <l>With miſ-becoming accents ſiliall duty:</l>
                     <l>Deliver quickly where this leacher is;</l>
                     <l>Here hous'd he muſt be, for he cannot ſcape,</l>
                     <l>Leſt wildneſs conquering my foſter ſenſe,</l>
                     <pb facs="tcp:98989:27"/>
                     <l> Thruſt forth my hand into an act of horror,</l>
                     <l>And leave you breathleſſe here.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Q.</speaker>
                     <l>What <hi>French</hi> Neronian ſpirit have we here?</l>
                     <l>
                        <gap reason="illegible: missing" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>nſolent boy, wilt thou turn Paricide?</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Clov.</speaker>
                     <l>The juſtneſs of my cauſe would excuſe me</l>
                     <l>If I ſhould execute; ſpeak murthereſs,</l>
                     <l>Where have you mew'd your Monſter?</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Qu.</speaker>
                     <l>Here lies the Monſter, oh rare Monſter; two Berds,</l>
                     <l>This is a comick Monſter; a Periwick too, this is a Court Moniſter;</l>
                     <l>D'ee gape, what in the Devils name would you beg now?</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Lam.</speaker>
                     <l>Behold my Lord, the Woodcock's in the Gin,</l>
                     <l>Here lies the great <hi>Landrey.</hi>
                     </l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Qu.</speaker>
                     <p>O horrid ſin.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Clov.</speaker>
                     <l>This habit might have ruin'd all <hi>Lamot.</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>But Goblin now you are caught; what is he dead?</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Lam.</speaker>
                     <p>Scarce hurt my Lord; how is't? look up.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Eu.</speaker>
                     <p>Where is the Queen?</p>
                     <stage>Enter Eunuch.</stage>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Qu.</speaker>
                     <p>Here <hi>Eunuch,</hi> as thou fee'ſt, in miſery.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Eu.</speaker>
                     <p>O my heart, how came the Monſiur hither? <hi>Lamot</hi> too?</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Qu.</speaker>
                     <p>All that I know is that we are betraid.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Eu.</speaker>
                     <p>I'l ſet them packing, fear not, —my good Lord.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Clov.</speaker>
                     <p>Thou art a faithful ſervant.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Eu</speaker>
                     <p>Sir, the Rebels—</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Clov.</speaker>
                     <l>Give' hem a nobler Title, by my life</l>
                     <l>I do applaud their courage; come they on?</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Eu.</speaker>
                     <p>Yes, and <hi>Briſſac</hi> is made their Generall.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Clov.</speaker>
                     <l>A hopeful youth, fraught with Nobility,</l>
                     <l>And all the graceful qualities that write</l>
                     <l>Man truly honourable; my injuries</l>
                     <l>Have ſwell'd me up to this.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Eu.</speaker>
                     <p>His Father's dead.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Clov.</speaker>
                     <l>Truſt me i'm ſorry, grief has broke his heart,</l>
                     <l>And mine <hi>Castrato</hi> too; canſt thou imagine</l>
                     <l>Who was the Author of our Fathers death?</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Eu.</speaker>
                     <l>Am I betraid? then lend me impudence,</l>
                     <l>I'm ſure I cannot bluſh: Royal ſir, whom?</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Clov.</speaker>
                     <l>Our Mother with <hi>Landrey,</hi> and this <hi>Lamot,</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>They ment ſhould bear the blame; this was <hi>Strephon.</hi>
                     </l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <pb facs="tcp:98989:28"/>
                     <speaker>Eu.</speaker>
                     <p>Indeed?—would I were fairly off.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Clov.</speaker>
                     <p>But what news with <hi>Aphelia</hi> and her Bridegroom?</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Eu.</speaker>
                     <l>As you could wiſh, hees lull of jealouſie,</l>
                     <l>No <hi>Frenchman</hi> e'r was more <hi>Italian;</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>I've wrought him bravely on, your Phyſick works,</l>
                     <l>Hither i've brough <hi>Aphelia;</hi> to morrow</l>
                     <l>You ſhall hear further ſport i'l warrant you;</l>
                     <l>In the mean while, what will you do with theſe?</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Clov.</speaker>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Caſtrato</hi> thus;</l>
                     <l>Nature forbids me ſpill my Mothers blood,</l>
                     <l>And <hi>Landrey</hi> is unfit for my revenge;</l>
                     <l>For I muſt ſtudy torments for the ſlave,</l>
                     <l>Therefore I give them up to your tuition,</l>
                     <l>Until I ſhall return victorious.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Qu.</speaker>
                     <p>Obſerv'd you that? there is ſome comfort yet.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Clov.</speaker>
                     <l>Then wee'l determine of them, if we fall</l>
                     <l>Let <hi>Clotair</hi> point them out a funerall:</l>
                     <l>Reward theſe with the whip, theſe with my purſe,</l>
                     <l>His merit is two hundred Crowns, perform it</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>2. <hi>Guard.</hi>
                     </speaker>
                     <l>Drink, I adore thee drink; good fellows all,</l>
                     <l>Sometimes we riſe by drink, but oftner fall.</l>
                     <stage>
                        <hi>Ex.</hi> 2 <hi>Guard.</hi>
                     </stage>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Clov.</speaker>
                     <l>A moral drunkard, go away with them;</l>
                     <stage>Ex. Eunuch, Muſicians, Landry &amp; Queen.</stage>
                     <l>And on your life let them not ſtir from hence.</l>
                     <l>Now my revenge grows to maturity,</l>
                     <l>Wee'l to <hi>Dumain (Lamot)</hi> and joyn with him;</l>
                     <l>Now <hi>France</hi> thou lieſt a bleeding, thou ſhalt prove</l>
                     <l>What 'tis to croſs the Monſiur in his love.</l>
                     <stage>Exeunt omnes.</stage>
                  </sp>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div n="5" type="act">
               <div n="1" type="scene">
                  <head>Actus Quintus.</head>
                  <stage>Enter Briſſac, Dumain, Bourbon, Lanove, Martel.</stage>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Dum.</speaker>
                     <p>FOr certain then the Princes are at odds.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Briſ.</speaker>
                     <p>Yes, and the ground the marriage of my ſiſter.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Bourb.</speaker>
                     <p>The Ulcerous ſtate is ripe, and we muſt launce it.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Briſ.</speaker>
                     <l>The King doth Whore my ſiſter; ſhe's not his,</l>
                     <pb facs="tcp:98989:28"/>
                     <l> But true and lawfully the Monſiur's wife.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Dum.</speaker>
                     <p>Did not one <hi>Strephon</hi> wait upon the Monſiure?</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Briſ.</speaker>
                     <p>What's his condition?</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Dum.</speaker>
                     <p>A Surgion, and famous for the cure o'ch' Prince.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Briſ.</speaker>
                     <p>Yes, ſuch there was; but litle nois'd at Court.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Dum.</speaker>
                     <p>That was <hi>Lamot</hi> our faſt and noble friend.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Mars.</speaker>
                     <l>There's ſome deſign on foot that hinders him,</l>
                     <l>He would not elſe neglect us.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <stage>VVithin, the Monſiure, the Monſiure, ho, ho, ho.</stage>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Briſ.</speaker>
                     <p>What noiſe is that <hi>Lanove,</hi> ſtep forth and ſee.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Du.</speaker>
                     <l>O death we are ſuppris'd, the Monſiure, ſuddenly</l>
                     <stage>again</stage>
                     <l>Snared, let each man to his charge.</l>
                     <stage>again.</stage>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Bourb.</speaker>
                     <p>Hark, ſtill the noiſe increaſeth.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Briſ.</speaker>
                     <l>By the ſound, this is a ſhout of joy and not of dread;</l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Lanove</hi> the news?</l>
                     <stage>En. Lanove, the Monſiure, Lamot &amp; others.</stage>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Monſi. Briſſac, Dumain, Martel,</speaker>
                     <l>and you the reſt,</l>
                     <l>Think not I come a Traytor to your Camp;</l>
                     <l>I cannot gild my ſpeech with eloquence,</l>
                     <l>If this will ſerve you ſir, I am a friend.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Briſ.</speaker>
                     <l>The Monſiur's welcome, and his worth will grace</l>
                     <l>The dignity of this dayes work in hand.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Monſi.</speaker>
                     <l>My almoſt Brother once, ſuffice I thank you,</l>
                     <l>And fairly greet this brave aſſembly,</l>
                     <l>Whoſe ſouls do look for ſtirring oppoſites,</l>
                     <l>When your reſiſtance I fear will be ſlender;</l>
                     <l>But were they centupul'd, i'l fight your cauſe,</l>
                     <l>Kings arm their ſubjects when they break their laws.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Omnes.</speaker>
                     <p>Long live the Monſiure.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Monſi.</speaker>
                     <p>Lead on, away.</p>
                     <stage>Exeunt omnes.</stage>
                  </sp>
               </div>
               <div n="2" type="scene">
                  <head>SCEN. II.</head>
                  <stage>
                     <hi>Enter the</hi> Eunuch, <hi>Whilſt the waits play ſoſily, and ſolemn'y drawes the Canopie, where the</hi> Queen <hi>ſits at one end bound with</hi> Landrey <hi>at the other, both as a ſleep.</hi>
                  </stage>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Eu.</speaker>
                     <l>Here ſits our Beldam dieted for Venerie,</l>
                     <l>And by her, her <hi>Landrey</hi> not ſur feited;</l>
                     <l>Her Ladyſhip's allou'd a mouldie cruſt,</l>
                     <pb facs="tcp:98989:29"/>
                     <l> He ſtinking water to peece out his life,</l>
                     <l>Between them both they banquet like one ſlave,</l>
                     <l>Condemn'd perpetually to the Burdello;</l>
                     <l>They think I know not that they thus are us'd,</l>
                     <l>When it is ouely I that uſe them thus.</l>
                     <l>How wickedly they look, oh I could laugh</l>
                     <l>To hear them rail at others miſery;</l>
                     <l>He curſes her, and ſhe ſooth curſes him,</l>
                     <l>And both each other damn for their offences.</l>
                     <l>Learn ye that pamper up your fleſh for luſt,</l>
                     <l>The <hi>Eunuch</hi> in his wickedneſs is juſt. Play louder, they ſleep too long.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Qu.</speaker>
                     <l>A miſchief take thee keeper, hardned dog,</l>
                     <l>Whom no diſtreſs can melt or mollifie;</l>
                     <l>The cruell King doth not deny us ſleep,</l>
                     <l>Although the Nurſers of it, food and eaſe.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Eu.</speaker>
                     <l>Peace, peace, ye villains ceaſe that ruder noiſe</l>
                     <l>That breaks your ſofter ſlumbers; gentle Queen,</l>
                     <l>I am not guilty of theſe harſh-voic'd words</l>
                     <l>Your wilder ſence hurls at me; you miſtake,</l>
                     <l>I am your <hi>Eunuch,</hi> one that weeps for you.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Qu.</speaker>
                     <l>Oh <hi>Caſtrato,</hi> waſt not thoſe tears in vain,</l>
                     <l>Come hither and i'l catch thoſe falling drops</l>
                     <l>Which prodigally over-flow their banks;</l>
                     <l>There's Nectar in thine eye, oh let me drink it;</l>
                     <l>Theſe aged Ceſterns are grown drie, and yeeld</l>
                     <l>Not one relenting drop to eaſe my thirſt.</l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Caſtrato</hi> pitty me, my veins are parcht,</l>
                     <l>And this ſame fleſh which walls about my ſoul,</l>
                     <l>Chops with exceſſive heat; a little water</l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Caſtrato,</hi> but a little, though it hath been</l>
                     <l>The birth of Toads, or what the leapers bath'd in;</l>
                     <l>O ſhew thy love but in a little water,</l>
                     <l>What can a Queen ask leſſe, or ſubject grant her?</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Eu</speaker>
                     <p>Though I be tortur'd, for it yet i'l do it.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <stage>Ex, <hi>Ennuch.</hi>
                  </stage>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Qu.</speaker>
                     <p>It hath quencht half my thirſt to find ſome pitty.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Land.</speaker>
                     <l>I cannot bite mine arm, their tyrannie</l>
                     <l>Denyes me what's mine own to feed upon,</l>
                     <pb facs="tcp:98989:29"/>
                     <l> One mouthfull would ſuffice; I cannot get it,</l>
                     <l>Poor unfed ſides that paſſe along the ſtreet,</l>
                     <l>I now am ſenſible of what ye want;</l>
                     <l>Did I e'r think to die for want of food,</l>
                     <l>Whoſe Table was the world, from whence I cull'd</l>
                     <l>The rarities of nature to delight me,</l>
                     <l>And more to feed my luſt than Appetite?</l>
                     <l>One bit of bread, though it were gray with age,</l>
                     <l>Hoary and cruſted with a ſecond bark,</l>
                     <l>Whoſe loathed outſide would not court a Dog</l>
                     <l>Arm'd with the edge of appetite, would ſeem</l>
                     <l>A rare rich banquet to my emptie gorge;</l>
                     <l>Oh I am worn to nothing with this want,</l>
                     <l>Such emptineſs ha's hunger made of me</l>
                     <l>That you may draw me on another man.</l>
                     <l>Some bread, ſome bread.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <stage>
                     <hi>Enter</hi> Eunuch <hi>with Wine and Meat, he congees with great reverence and ceremony to the</hi> Queen.</stage>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Qu.</speaker>
                     <l>Oh thou art welcome,</l>
                     <l>Quick, dear <hi>Eunuch</hi> quick; what needs this delay?</l>
                     <l>A way with form and ceremonious duty,</l>
                     <l>Reſpect in this is too reſpectleſs.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Eu.</speaker>
                     <l>O give me leave, I will begin a heald;</l>
                     <l>It's very good, exceeding pleaſant Wine.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Qu.</speaker>
                     <l>Doſt thou deride my ſufferance?</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Eu.</speaker>
                     <p>No, no, not I.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Qu.</speaker>
                     <p>Give me the drink then, i'm all flame and fire.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Eu.</speaker>
                     <l>Say you ſo, ſay you ſo? then you muſt pardon me,</l>
                     <l>I love your ſafety, and it's dangerous</l>
                     <l>To drink while you are hot, pray cool and tarry:</l>
                     <l>In the mean while I will begin to you;</l>
                     <l>How tart and pleaſing this is to the Palate,</l>
                     <l>A ſweeter Pheaſant Chriſtendom affords not.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Land.</speaker>
                     <p>I thank thee <hi>Eunuch</hi> prethee give it me.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Eu.</speaker>
                     <l>You'l let me taſt it for you, will you not?</l>
                     <l>Are you ſo ſharply ſet? fie, this ſauce is naught.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Land.</speaker>
                     <p>Prethee make haſt, hunger digeſt's no taſters.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <pb facs="tcp:98989:30"/>
                     <speaker>Eu.</speaker>
                     <l>Come ſir, I muſt feed you, oh, oh, not ſo faſt,</l>
                     <l>Be not ſo haſty; here, ſtill you are too haſty;</l>
                     <stage>he puts it to his mouth, &amp; puls it away again.</stage>
                     <l>Gentle ſir it will digeſt the better.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Land.</speaker>
                     <p>More, more, oh it is excellent.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Eu.</speaker>
                     <p>Madam, here's for you now.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Qu</speaker>
                     <p>May heaven reward thee for't, oh it's rare.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Eu.</speaker>
                     <p>How do you like your banquet great <hi>Landrey?</hi>
                     </p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Land.</speaker>
                     <p>Beyond compare.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Eu.</speaker>
                     <p>And you your drink?</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Qu.</speaker>
                     <p>The Gods taſt not the like.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Eu.</speaker>
                     <p>Ha, ha, ha, y'have both eat and drunk abominable poyſon.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Qu.</speaker>
                     <p>Ha!</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Land.</speaker>
                     <p>How!</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Eu</speaker>
                     <l>'Tis true, I tell your Oracle;</l>
                     <l>There's not an hours life between ye both;</l>
                     <l>The poyſon's ſure, I did prepare it for ye,</l>
                     <l>And have my ſelf taken an Antidote:</l>
                     <l>What ſay'now to th'other bout with <hi>Landrey,</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>I can procure a ſecond meeting for you,</l>
                     <l>Indeed I can; think you not whoredome ſweet</l>
                     <l>Now you are a dying? is not you ſoul at eaſe,</l>
                     <l>The murther of your Husband but a toy,</l>
                     <l>A flea-biting? alack you feel it not.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Qu.</speaker>
                     <p>Inhumane ſlave, treacherous Raſcal.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Eu.</speaker>
                     <p>Good words, Lady whore, good words: what are you looſe?</p>
                     <stage>Landrey gets looſe.</stage>
                     <l>Miraculous famine, ha's your empty guts</l>
                     <l>Perſwaded you to valour? will it ſcratch or bite?</l>
                     <l>I'm ſure't has no weapon, Monſiure diſarm it.</l>
                     <stage>ſhews a keen knife which he pulls out of his ſleeve, staggers with faintneſs.</stage>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Lan.</hi> He did ſo Raſcal, yet your curious ſearch</l>
                     <l>Ne'r pri'd into this ſheath; do you ſee this:</l>
                     <l>With mine own hands it had let forth mine own life,</l>
                     <l>Had the proud Monſiure truſted us to any,</l>
                     <l>Thy ſelf excepted, whom I now perceive</l>
                     <l>The onely Author of our miſery.</l>
                     <stage>The Eunuch tript up his heels in ſcuffle and ſits on him.</stage>
                     <l>You'r very nimble Hell-hound.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Eu.</speaker>
                     <l>O Lord ſir, you know the cauſe,</l>
                     <pb facs="tcp:98989:30"/>
                     <l> I'm lighter by a ſtone or two than you,</l>
                     <l>Yet I am weight enough to keep you down;</l>
                     <l>Stir and thou dy'ſt—now ſir, what ſay you to me?</l>
                     <l>How did you like your old Queen? was ſhe gameſome?</l>
                     <l>Did ſhe apply her ſelf like an apt whore</l>
                     <l>Unto your looſe imbraces?</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Land.</speaker>
                     <p>Dog, let me reſt.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Eu.</speaker>
                     <l>Good my Lord pardon me,</l>
                     <l>Under your Graces favour be it ſpoken,</l>
                     <l>You are our cuſhion, and i'l ſit on you.</l>
                     <l>I am not very heavie, and I ſir?</l>
                     <stage>joults upon him.</stage>
                     <l>I do not altogether weigh a man.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Qu.</speaker>
                     <l>Villanous Traytor,</l>
                     <l>O let him riſe, and wreck thy ſpite on me.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Eu.</speaker>
                     <p>You cog now, you'd rather I ſhould kill.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Qu.</speaker>
                     <l>O ſpare him, ſpare him; <hi>Eunuch</hi> ſave my ſervant,</l>
                     <l>And i'l forgive thee all thy ſinnes againſt me;</l>
                     <l>There's not an injurie thou doſt to him,</l>
                     <l>But wounds me to the ſoul.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Eu.</speaker>
                     <l>Pray then look here,</l>
                     <l>How eaſily this Skean is ſheath'd in him;</l>
                     <l>An Engine of his own preparing Ladie,</l>
                     <l>And pittie't were ſo brave a Gentleman,</l>
                     <l>Such a neat hopeful whore-maſter as he,</l>
                     <l>Should die by any weapon but his own.</l>
                     <l>So periſh all that love Adulterie.</l>
                     <l>There, ſit you there again: once more to you,</l>
                     <stage>he ſets him in his Chair.</stage>
                     <l>Who if your poyſon do not work too faſt,</l>
                     <l>Shall ſee more ſights like theſe before you die;</l>
                     <l>But leſt you ſhould prevent us with your tongue,</l>
                     <l>I will be bold to gag your Ladyſhip;</l>
                     <l>I'l leave a peeping hole through which you ſhall</l>
                     <l>See ſights, ſhall kill thee faſter than thy poyſon;</l>
                     <stage>draws the Curtain again.</stage>
                     <l>I am prepar'd now for <hi>Aphelia's</hi> death.</l>
                     <l>All things are ready, and behold the King.</l>
                     <l>Now for my part.</l>
                     <stage>
                        <hi>Ent.</hi> Clotair <hi>melancholly.</hi>
                     </stage>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Clot.</speaker>
                     <l>I am too pittiful, a watrie flux,</l>
                     <l>Which ſoft and tender hearted men call tears,</l>
                     <pb facs="tcp:98989:31"/>
                     <l> Stand on mine eies, and do's expreſs a nature</l>
                     <l>Too like my Bearer; it is now with me</l>
                     <l>Full tide in ſorrow, my <hi>Cynthia</hi> governs ſtrongly.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Eu.</speaker>
                     <p>How fares the great <hi>Clotair?</hi>
                     </p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Clot.</speaker>
                     <l>What do the wiſe,</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Caſtrato,</hi> call the moiſture which preſumes</l>
                     <l>To meditate betwixt my wrath and me?</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Eu.</speaker>
                     <l>Expreſſions of a weak and ſilly nature,</l>
                     <l>Paſſion of fools and women: are you a man</l>
                     <l>And bear ſo tame a ſoul, ſuch a ſmock ſpirit?</l>
                     <l>The Diſtaff owns more ſpleen, more noble anger;</l>
                     <l>Pray let her live untill the Pages write,</l>
                     <l>An hopping balladry verſe rime upon you,</l>
                     <l>Great <hi>Clotair</hi> had a wife and ſhe was fair,</l>
                     <l>Yea fairer than the flowerie meads in May;</l>
                     <stage>ſcoffingly.</stage>
                     <l>Oh ſhe was fair, yet foul; moſt ridling ſence,</l>
                     <l>Oh it is horrid; then to conclude</l>
                     <l>In what a high ſtreign you did take revenge,</l>
                     <l>How like your houſe and honour, hark, how ſhe dies,</l>
                     <l>Strangled in tears fall'n from the Cuckolds eies;</l>
                     <l>You are her husband ſir, and now muſt own</l>
                     <l>Her doubtfull iſſue, and her lawleſſe luſt;</l>
                     <l>Although a Bull ſhould leap her, you muſt father,</l>
                     <l>And have a drove of forked Animals,</l>
                     <l>Shall have their horns born with them to the ſound,</l>
                     <l>'Twill ſave their prodigall wives the reacky labour.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Clot.</speaker>
                     <p>Marry a Whore? father a baſtard iſſue?</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Eu.</speaker>
                     <p>I tell you truth, there's no avoiding it.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Clot.</speaker>
                     <p>Come bring her forth.</p>
                     <stage>Ent. Aphelia drag'd by two Ruffins in her petticoat &amp; hair.</stage>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Aphe.</speaker>
                     <l>Uſe not ſuch violence good Gentlemen,</l>
                     <l>I'l walk a lamb to ſlaughter, not repine</l>
                     <l>At any torments you ſhall put me too,</l>
                     <l>Onely be modeſt: commend me to my Lord,</l>
                     <l>I doubt I never ſhall behold him more;</l>
                     <l>For by the calculation of your looks</l>
                     <l>I have not long to live.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Clot.</speaker>
                     <l>True <hi>Aphelia,</hi> confeſs &amp; turn thy fate; give me to know</l>
                     <l>With what foul Monſter thou haſt wrong'd thy ſoul,</l>
                     <pb facs="tcp:98989:31"/>
                     <l> Seam-rent that holy weed, Virginitie;</l>
                     <l>And caſe me of a load that bears more weight</l>
                     <l>Than what my youthful ſins have heap'd upon me.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Aphe.</speaker>
                     <p>If e'r my Lord—</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Clot.</speaker>
                     <l>No more of that, it tends to madneſs;</l>
                     <l>I'l force it from thee; bring forth the tortures there;</l>
                     <l>I'l trie if in theſe fiery inſtruments</l>
                     <stage>Ent. man with pan and irons.</stage>
                     <l>There lie a tongue, which better can perſwade</l>
                     <l>Confeſſion from thee; theſe red hot applied</l>
                     <l>Unto thy breaſt adulterate, ſhall extract</l>
                     <l>All future hope to ſuckle lawleſs iſſue;</l>
                     <l>The poyſonous ſprings which from theſe hills ariſe,</l>
                     <l>Shall have their fountain head dam'd up by theſe.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Aphe.</speaker>
                     <l>I've heard you ſwear, that you were poor in words,</l>
                     <l>And knew not to expreſs the happineſs</l>
                     <l>Which you conceiv'd was habitable here.</l>
                     <l>How much my Lord is altred from himſelf</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Clot.</speaker>
                     <l>'Tis thou art altred; true <hi>Aphelia,</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>That whilſt thy purer thoughts did awe thy will,</l>
                     <l>I lov'd like an Idolater: I was poſſeſt</l>
                     <l>That theſe two twins, theſe Globes of fleſh, contain'd</l>
                     <l>All that was happy both in earth and heaven;</l>
                     <l>In this I could deſcrie the Milkey way,</l>
                     <l>The maiden Zone that girds the waſte of heaven;</l>
                     <l>In this the ſeat of Paradice, and how</l>
                     <l>The wanton Rivelets plai'd about the Iſle</l>
                     <l>Which puzzel yet Geographie: all this I could,</l>
                     <l>I could in thee my ſometime chaſt <hi>Aphelia</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>Find and rejoyce in; but thou art now</l>
                     <l>An undreſt wilderneſs wherein I walk,</l>
                     <l>Loſing my ſelf 'mongſt multitude of beaſts;</l>
                     <l>O ſavage actions! Come diſpatch.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Aphe.</speaker>
                     <p>Sir—?</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Clot.</speaker>
                     <p>I'I hear no more.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Aphe.</speaker>
                     <l>Heaven will then;</l>
                     <l>And though it bear an ear far diſtant hence,</l>
                     <l>Both hear and pitty me. O my lov'd Lord,</l>
                     <l>Should but a dream work on my fancy,</l>
                     <pb facs="tcp:98989:32"/>
                     <l> That you were thus to ſuffer as I am,</l>
                     <l>It would conſpire to kill me with more ſpeed</l>
                     <l>Than theſe your threatning Miniſters; alas,</l>
                     <l>I'l force a gentler nature in the ſteel,</l>
                     <l>And with my rainy eies weep out their heat;</l>
                     <l>Which as it dies ſhould hiſs it ſelf to ſcorn,</l>
                     <l>For offering to contain but fire to hurt you;</l>
                     <l>And will you then a bold ſpectator ſtand,</l>
                     <l>Smiling at what I ſuffer? ſhed but one tear,</l>
                     <l>Or counterfeit a ſorrow for my ſake,</l>
                     <l>A little ſeeming woe, and I ſhall die</l>
                     <l>Sick of your kindneſſe, not your crueltie.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Clot.</speaker>
                     <l>O my ſoft temper, her ſweet harmonic</l>
                     <l>Will melt me into fool; to hear theſe words,</l>
                     <l>The Mother is to buſie in mine eies;</l>
                     <l>What ſhall I do?</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Eu.</speaker>
                     <l>Make a new Hell,</l>
                     <l>And if thou canſt, create more Devils, do,</l>
                     <l>And they will find imployment all on her;</l>
                     <l>For ſince the generall Creation,</l>
                     <l>Time never did produce a fowler ſinner,</l>
                     <l>Or one more begger'd hell in puniſhing.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Clot.</speaker>
                     <l>Thou haſt awak'd me; Whore will you confeſſe?</l>
                     <l>Do not inforce your death through wilfulneſs;</l>
                     <stage>drags her by the hair.</stage>
                     <l>Speak ſtubborn ſilence, or i'l break thy heart.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Aphe.</speaker>
                     <l>My Lord and Husband, oh my Lord and husband,</l>
                     <l>Regard my miſerie and pittie me.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Clot.</speaker>
                     <l>Thou'rt cruel to thy ſelf, I wrong thee not;</l>
                     <l>It is not I that tear this precious Fleece,</l>
                     <stage>again.</stage>
                     <l>This glorious excrement, in validitie,</l>
                     <l>Another <hi>Cholcos</hi> better ſeeming <hi>Jaſon.</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>I pull not off theſe curious ſporting Treſſes,</l>
                     <stage>again.</stage>
                     <l>Fit braids to Captive Kings hadſt thou been honeſt.</l>
                     <l>I wound thee not, confeſſe, and live as free</l>
                     <l>As mountain air, I will not injure thee.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Aphe.</speaker>
                     <l>My gracious Prince, I dare not call you husband,</l>
                     <l>Your actions do forbid, which write me ſlave</l>
                     <l>And not your equall; if to be your wife</l>
                     <pb facs="tcp:98989:32"/>
                     <l> Has pluckt this miſery upon my head,</l>
                     <l>Or caus'd in you this phrenſie, put me off,</l>
                     <l>I will indure it patiently; but if e'r—</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Clot.</speaker>
                     <p>The old tune this, come, come, the Irons there.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Aph.</speaker>
                     <l>Oh, oh, oh, cruel my Lord, unmanly;</l>
                     <stage>
                        <hi>they bind her to the Chair, the</hi> Eu. <hi>much ſears her breaſt.</hi>
                     </stage>
                     <l>I will not curſe yet heaven, no nor blaſpheme,</l>
                     <l>Although mine injuries would half perſwade,</l>
                     <l>Gods are not, or are deaf to innocents.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Sould.</speaker>
                     <l>Arm, arm, my Lord, the Caſtle's wall'd about</l>
                     <stage>Enter a Souldier haſtily with his ſword drawn.</stage>
                     <l>With living Clay, three times ten thouſand men,</l>
                     <l>Approved Warrlers, ſouls of blood and fire,</l>
                     <l>That onely known to do, and not to ſuffer,</l>
                     <l>Make head againſt you; believe me ſir,</l>
                     <l>A braver Troop, and ſpirits more reſolv'd,</l>
                     <l>Life never put in action: young <hi>Briſſac</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>Now old enough to quit his Fathers death,</l>
                     <l>Together with the ruine of his Siſter,</l>
                     <l>H'as vow'd deſtruction to your name and aſhes.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Clot.</speaker>
                     <l>Let them come on, wee'l dare them do their worſt;</l>
                     <l>This Caſtle will indure a fortnights ſiege,</l>
                     <l>Before the expiration of which time,</l>
                     <l>My Brother with his fellow Peers of <hi>France,</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>Shall whip theſe Rebels for their inſolence.</l>
                     <l>Know'ſt thou ought elſe; why doſt thou ſhake thy head?</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>2 <hi>Sould.</hi>
                     </speaker>
                     <p>Fly, fly, my Lord.</p>
                     <stage>Enter another Souldier.</stage>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Clot.</speaker>
                     <p>Villain, it is no language for a Prince.</p>
                     <stage>ſtrikes him.</stage>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>2 <hi>Sould.</hi>
                     </speaker>
                     <l>Then ſtand upon your guard; yet that's as bad,</l>
                     <l>The Caſtle's wall'd about with walking ſteel,</l>
                     <l>And you but tempt your death in your eſcape,</l>
                     <l>If you ſtay here, provoke it.</l>
                     <l>The Monſiur, like the God of war, beſtrides</l>
                     <l>A bounding Courſer, who is therefore proud</l>
                     <l>To be ſo back'd, as knowing whom he bears:</l>
                     <l>So Centaur-like he's anckor'd to his ſeat,</l>
                     <l>As he had twind with the proud ſteed he rides on;</l>
                     <l>He grows unto his ſaddle all one piece,</l>
                     <l>And that unto his Horſe; who thus unmov'd,</l>
                     <l>Sits like a <hi>Perſons</hi> on his <hi>Pegaſus,</hi>
                     </l>
                     <pb facs="tcp:98989:33"/>
                     <l> Stable and fleet. Who at head of all his Troops,</l>
                     <l>With words inflames 'em that did burn before,</l>
                     <l>But now appear much brighter; their gliſtering arms</l>
                     <l>Reflecting 'gainſt the Sun, doth lightning mock;</l>
                     <l>Unto which blaze, their Drums and Horſes hoofs</l>
                     <l>Do not want much of Thunder: ſuch is the ſhow,</l>
                     <l>As if great <hi>Mars,</hi> angry with humane race,</l>
                     <l>Did lead the Gods to battel 'gainſt the Earth.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Eu.</speaker>
                     <p>How does your Grace? how fares your Majeſtie?</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Clot.</speaker>
                     <p>The Monſiur? did he not name the Monſiur?</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>2 <hi>Sould.</hi>
                     </speaker>
                     <p>I did my Lord.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Clot.</speaker>
                     <l>Is he joyned with them too?</l>
                     <l>Then Dooms-day is at hand, I ſee my ruine.</l>
                     <l>Go to the Caſtle walls to ſummon them</l>
                     <l>To render an accompt of their intents.</l>
                     <l>Ask the proud Monſiur (though I know the cauſe)</l>
                     <stage>Looks on Aphelia.</stage>
                     <l>Why his preſumptious and ambitious feet,</l>
                     <l>Have on the boſome of his mother earth,</l>
                     <l>Made a broad road of treaſon; go, begone.</l>
                     <stage>Exe. Souldiers.</stage>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Caſtrato</hi> thou doſt love me, i'm ſure thou doſt;</l>
                     <l>I have ſuch proofs of thy true hearted-love,</l>
                     <l>That I muſt put my life into thy hands.</l>
                     <l>Thou ſee'ſt how all things ſtand, my wife ſhe's falſe,</l>
                     <l>Her brother ſeeks my life, the Monſiur's thoughts</l>
                     <l>(Back'd with the ever factious ſouls of <hi>France</hi>)</l>
                     <l>Aim at the Gallick Crown and dignitie,</l>
                     <l>Whil'ſt I a catiff and neglected Prince</l>
                     <l>Muſt fall by traytors hands.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Eu.</speaker>
                     <p>What mean you ſir?</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Clot.</speaker>
                     <l>Look here's a Piſtoll in whoſe womb lies death,</l>
                     <l>A heavie leaden ſleep.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Eu.</speaker>
                     <l>Would you I ſhould</l>
                     <l>Trie the concluſion here? make her confeſſe</l>
                     <l>By other inſtruments her horrid guilt,</l>
                     <l>In this there's too much mercy.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Clot.</speaker>
                     <l>Hear me ſpeak,</l>
                     <l>I'l trouble her no further; let her ſin</l>
                     <l>Be puniſh'd from above, i'l wait heavens leiſure.</l>
                     <pb facs="tcp:98989:33"/>
                     <l> Here <hi>Eunuch</hi> take thou this, it was prepar'd</l>
                     <l>For the adulterate <hi>Landrey;</hi> here, receive it,</l>
                     <l>And if thou lov'ſt me uſe it upon me:</l>
                     <l>Come ſhoot me through, I know I ſhall be ſlain,</l>
                     <l>(If not by thee, yet by the enemie)</l>
                     <l>And therefore to prevent the bitter ſcorn</l>
                     <l>Of the inſulting foe (which is a death</l>
                     <l>So full of horror to the conquer'd,</l>
                     <l>No Tyranny is like it) uſe this handfull,</l>
                     <l>The handſom'ſt weed that nature can produce</l>
                     <l>In the large Storehouſe of her providence,</l>
                     <l>Can ſhew no ſimple like it; for this cures</l>
                     <l>At once, the ſickneſſe of the mind and body.</l>
                     <l>Thou ſhalt, I know thou wilt, I prethee take it;</l>
                     <l>It is not murder, tender-hearted fool</l>
                     <l>Which thou commits, rather a ſacrifice,</l>
                     <l>For which heaven will reward thee.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Eu.</speaker>
                     <l>I do not know the nature of your Gods,</l>
                     <l>Yet on your words i'l trie their kindneſſe.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Clot.</speaker>
                     <p>Nobly reſoly'd, come ſhoot me quickly then.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Eu.</speaker>
                     <l>I never was liker t'expreſs my ſelfe</l>
                     <l>Than at this minute; do not betray me tears,</l>
                     <stage>aſide.</stage>
                     <l>The <hi>Eunuchs</hi> nature muſt be harſh and cruell.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Aphe.</speaker>
                     <l>O ſpare him <hi>Eunuch,</hi> ſpare him, ſave my Lord,</l>
                     <l>And i'l forgive thee all thy ſins 'gainſt me.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Eu.</speaker>
                     <l>Peace foollſh woman, 'tis thou that kill'ſt thy Lord,</l>
                     <l>Were't not for thee he might live long and happy;</l>
                     <l>Pray let me kiſſe your hand, and take my leave</l>
                     <l>Of my beſt beſt Maſter.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Clot.</speaker>
                     <p>Do't and be ſudden then: ah what means this?</p>
                     <stage>as he kiſſes his hand, he ſnatches out his ſword.</stage>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Eu.</speaker>
                     <l>Marry ſir this it means,</l>
                     <l>That if this fail, this ſhall perform the deed;</l>
                     <l>Think not but I will kill you, do not fear,</l>
                     <l>I am the excellent'ſt he alive at theſe ſame toyes,</l>
                     <l>Look here my coufin'd fool I do not bungle.</l>
                     <stage>ſhews Landrey and the Queen.</stage>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Clot.</speaker>
                     <p>Are theſe dead then?</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Eu.</speaker>
                     <p>As ſure as you live, pray ask them elſe;</p>
                     <l>Unleſſe this Ewes fleſh too intenſe in heat</l>
                     <pb facs="tcp:98989:34"/>
                     <l> Be lingring yet behind; ſhe's ſcarcely dead,</l>
                     <l>But in her dying ears i'l howl this noiſe;</l>
                     <l>Look Queen, here's the top-branch of all thy Family,</l>
                     <l>Mark but how kindly for thy ſake'i'l uſe him.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Clot.</speaker>
                     <l>Then I perceive I have been much abus'd,</l>
                     <l>So ha's my chaſter Queen; oh my curſt fate!</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Eu.</speaker>
                     <p>Oh, do you ſo, do you ſo.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Qu.</speaker>
                     <p>Oh, oh, oh.</p>
                     <stage>Queen dyes.</stage>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Eu.</speaker>
                     <l>There broke a Strumpets heart; hear me King,</l>
                     <l>Thy Mother was a foul adultereſs,</l>
                     <l>A cruel butcherer of innocents;</l>
                     <l>Witneſſe thy brother, that thy Mother's falſe,</l>
                     <l>Witneſſe thine own eyes that beheld the fall</l>
                     <l>And ruine of the <hi>Dumain!</hi> amily.</l>
                     <l>Thy Mother's deep in blood, for which ſhe's damn'd:</l>
                     <l>You raviſht fair <hi>Chrotilda; Clodimir</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>Your valiant Uncle, brother to this Queen,</l>
                     <l>Was for the foul fact ſlain; for which miſtake,</l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Dumain, Lamot, Maria, Iſabel,</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>And the abus'd <hi>Chrotilda,</hi> if by flight</l>
                     <l>She had not ſav'd her life, had fall'n with them.</l>
                     <l>I knowing this, and ever pittying</l>
                     <l>The wrongs that they indur'd,</l>
                     <l>Have found it time thus to revenge them.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Clot.</speaker>
                     <p>What were their wrongs to thee?</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Eu.</speaker>
                     <l>I'l not Capitulate mine injuries,</l>
                     <stage>hear a March ſoftly within.</stage>
                     <l>I hear my time is ſhort.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Clot.</speaker>
                     <p>How fain would I preſerve my life from death,</p>
                     <l>Since my <hi>Aphelia</hi>'s chaſt; to think her falſe,</l>
                     <l>(Not that I fear the foe) made me diſpair</l>
                     <l>Of future comfort. <hi>Eunuch,</hi> ſpare my life,</l>
                     <l>I will forgive thee, and reward thee too;</l>
                     <l>Remember who it is that ſues to thee.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Eu.</speaker>
                     <l>In that remembrance I have loſt my ſelf,</l>
                     <l>I cannot ſtrike him, my relenting heart</l>
                     <l>Yerns on his Princely perſon: take your ſword,</l>
                     <l>But on condition <hi>Clotair,</hi> thou ſhalt ſwear</l>
                     <l>By thy deſcent, thy princely parentage,</l>
                     <pb facs="tcp:98989:34"/>
                     <l> By the wrong'd ſouls of all thoſe innocents</l>
                     <l>To thy luſt ſatisfi'd, by <hi>Aphelia's</hi> ſelf,</l>
                     <l>Or any thing thy ſoul ſhall hold more dear,</l>
                     <l>Upon receipt, to guide the fatal point.</l>
                     <l>Directly to thy heart.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Clot.</speaker>
                     <p>Why would'ſt thou ſo?</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Eu.</speaker>
                     <l>Piſh, I'l teach thee to be ſpeedy in the fact;</l>
                     <l>Remember how thy Royall Father fell;</l>
                     <l>Behold thy Mother murther'd by this hand;</l>
                     <l>Into thy boſome caſt thine inward eyes.</l>
                     <l>And view the ſorrows I have heaped on thee:</l>
                     <l>Look on <hi>Aphelia,</hi> and let her wrongs</l>
                     <l>Prompt thy ſlow hand to this moſt timely flaughter;</l>
                     <l>I cannot brook delay, or do, or ſuffer.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Clot.</speaker>
                     <p>A Heathen, and a Traytor die with thee.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Eu.</speaker>
                     <l>A Chriſtian Heathen <hi>Clotair</hi> if thou wilt,</l>
                     <l>Made ſo by thee; read that and break thy heart.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <stage>
                     <hi>Enter the</hi> Monſieur <hi>and his Comp.</hi>
                  </stage>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Mo.</speaker>
                     <l>Force ope the door, ſeiz on his Royal perſon:now <hi>Clotair</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>Thou are the Monſieur's pris'ner; Tyrant ſay,</l>
                     <l>Where is <hi>Aphelia</hi> your Adultereſ!</l>
                     <stage>stands amaz'd</stage>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Clot.</speaker>
                     <p>It makes no matter where.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Briſ.</speaker>
                     <p>O my dear Siſter, O my deareſt life.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Dum.</speaker>
                     <l>See Noble Lords,</l>
                     <l>Here lies that Hel-hound <hi>Eunuch;</hi> villain up,</l>
                     <l>And tell us who ha's done theſe fatall deeds.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Eu.</speaker>
                     <l>They'r ne'r ali'd to thee that did theſe Acts,</l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Chrotilda</hi> and a woman.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Dum.</speaker>
                     <l>Villain thou li'ſt, my ſiſter's gone a weary pilgrimage,</l>
                     <l>And for this many years with grief I ſpeak it,</l>
                     <l>Been travel'd none knows where.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Clot.</speaker>
                     <l>What am I?</l>
                     <l>What ſtrange and uncouth thing?</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Eu.</speaker>
                     <l>A raviſher,</l>
                     <l>And better to inſtruct thee in thy ſelf;</l>
                     <l>Had not <hi>Chrotilda</hi> been, inceſtuous.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Omnes.</speaker>
                     <p>Hold, hold your Royal hand; what will you do?</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Clot.</speaker>
                     <l>What elſe but follow her; ſhall <hi>Clotair</hi> live</l>
                     <pb facs="tcp:98989:35"/>
                     <l> A Captive to his Brother, ſlav'd to ſin,</l>
                     <l>Inthral's in wedlock that's inceſtuous,</l>
                     <l>O raviſher and murtherer of his friend,</l>
                     <l>There's no way left to rid me but my ſword,</l>
                     <l>Of all theſe ills at once, Oh wrong'd <hi>Chrotilda / </hi>
                     </l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Dum.</speaker>
                     <p>My ſiſter</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Clot,</speaker>
                     <l>I <hi>Dumain,</hi> no <hi>Eunuch</hi> ſhe;</l>
                     <l>No ſun-burnt vagabond of Aethiope,</l>
                     <l>Though entertain'd for ſuch by <hi>Fredigond.</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>I ſay here lies thy raviſht ſiſter ſlain</l>
                     <l>By me the raviſher.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Dum.</speaker>
                     <p>Hold, hold, my heart.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Eu.</speaker>
                     <p>Lend me thy hand <hi>Clotair,</hi> have I thy hand?</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Clot.</speaker>
                     <p>Thou moſt abus'd of womenkind, thou haſt.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Eu.</speaker>
                     <l>I ſhould have kill'd thee King, and had put on</l>
                     <l>A maſculine ſpirit to perform the deed;</l>
                     <l>Alas how frail our reſolutions are!</l>
                     <l>A womans weakneſs conquer'd my revenge:</l>
                     <l>I'd ſpirit enough to quit my Fathers wrongs;</l>
                     <l>And they which ſhould have ſeen me act that part,</l>
                     <l>Would not believe I ſhould ſo ſoon prove haggard:</l>
                     <l>But there is ſomething dwels upon thy brow</l>
                     <l>Which did perfwade me to humanitie;</l>
                     <l>Thou injur'dſt me, and yet I ſpar'd thy life;</l>
                     <l>Thou injurd'ſt me, yet I would fall by thee;</l>
                     <l>And like to my ſoft ſex, I fall and periſh.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Clot.</speaker>
                     <p>Speak, for ever ſpeak: <hi>Chrotilda, Chrotilda.</hi>
                     </p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Dum.</speaker>
                     <l>My Siſter's in mine eies, this brave revenge</l>
                     <l>Should have been mine, and not thy act <hi>Chrotilda;</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>Away ſalt rhume, <hi>Chrotilda</hi> laughs at thee,</l>
                     <l>Her ſpirit is more manly.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Aphe.</speaker>
                     <l>I muſt weep too,</l>
                     <l>Mine injuries and hers are ſo near kin,</l>
                     <l>That they muſt bear each other company</l>
                     <l>In tears of blood and death;</l>
                     <l>For my griev'd heart too long with earth,</l>
                     <l>Would gladly ſeek a way to find out reſt.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Clot.</speaker>
                     <l>Art thou joyn'd with her too againſt thy ſelf?</l>
                     <pb facs="tcp:98989:35"/>
                     <l> Will my <hi>Aphelia</hi> leave me? pardon ſweet,</l>
                     <l>My love is fatall, and too well thou know'ſt</l>
                     <l>The deadly proof in fair <hi>Chrotilda</hi> death;</l>
                     <l>Yet leave me not though I refrain thy bed,</l>
                     <l>And muſt abandon all thoſe thoughts of love</l>
                     <l>Which married couples uſe; yet we may ſit</l>
                     <l>And gaze upon each other, tell ſad tales</l>
                     <l>Of ruin'd Princes, wrong'd Virginitie;</l>
                     <l>And when our utterance is tyr'd by ſpeech,</l>
                     <l>Wee'l ſit and ſigh a ſad parentheſis,</l>
                     <l>And then proceed again, then ſigh again</l>
                     <l>A ſilent <hi>Chorus</hi> to our Hiſtory;</l>
                     <l>Our tears ſhall keep our ſorrows ever green,</l>
                     <l>Still ſpringing, never ripe: ſhall we do thus</l>
                     <l>To lengthen out our grief?</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Aphe.</speaker>
                     <l>For ever King,</l>
                     <l>The hand of heaven lies on me; for I feel</l>
                     <l>My in ward and externall injuries</l>
                     <l>Wreſtle with life, in which condition</l>
                     <l>My ſoul is woried by that Tyrant death.</l>
                     <l>I muſt forſake thee <hi>Clotair</hi>
                     </l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Clot.</speaker>
                     <l>Stay awhile, it is unkindly done to leave me thus:</l>
                     <l>O ſhe is gone, for ever, ever gone;</l>
                     <l>And I ſtand prating here between them both,</l>
                     <l>The fatall cauſe of death unto them both.</l>
                     <l>Wilt thou not break proud heart, I prethee break,</l>
                     <l>Prove not a Rebell to thy Prince like theſe;</l>
                     <l>It's well there is ſome loyaltie in thee yet;</l>
                     <l>Thou art commanded by me —</l>
                     <stage>the King faints.</stage>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Briſ.</speaker>
                     <p>Gracious my Liege.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Clot.</speaker>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Charles</hi> I have injur'd thee, and thee <hi>Dumain;</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>Can ye forgive me?</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Briſ.</speaker>
                     <l>Good your Grace</l>
                     <l>Call back your ſpirits, think what's to be done.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Clot.</speaker>
                     <l>I conſider well, and the now King,</l>
                     <l>The quondam Mounſieur ſhall not denie me this;</l>
                     <l>Half of the honours of the deal <hi>Landrey</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>We do confer on thee, the other half</l>
                     <pb facs="tcp:98989:36"/>
                     <l> Be thine <hi>Dumain; Charles</hi> ſhall be Duke of <hi>France,</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>Thou of the Palace Major: this is our will.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Dum.</speaker>
                     <l>Great King, you are not yet ſo neer your end,</l>
                     <l>Forſend it heaven.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Briſ.</speaker>
                     <p>Look up my Gracious Lord.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Monſi.</speaker>
                     <p>My Royall Brother?</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Clot.</speaker>
                     <l>I begin to faint,</l>
                     <l>A darkneſſe like to death hangs on mine eies;</l>
                     <l>Lend me thine hand <hi>Briſſac,</hi> and thine <hi>Dumain.</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>Good gentle ſouls when ye ſhal mention me,</l>
                     <l>And elder time ſhall rip theſe ſtories up,</l>
                     <l>Diffected and Anatomiz'd by you;</l>
                     <l>Touch ſparingly this ſtory, do not read</l>
                     <l>Too harſh a comment on this loathed deed,</l>
                     <l>Left you inforce poſterity to blaſt</l>
                     <l>My name and Memory with endleſſe curſes;</l>
                     <l>Call me an honouralbe murtherer,</l>
                     <l>And finiſh there as I do.</l>
                     <stage>He dyes.</stage>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Dum.</speaker>
                     <l>O Noble Lord,</l>
                     <l>Whoſe fame was very eſſence to his ſouls.</l>
                     <l>That gone, the other fled, chooſing to die,</l>
                     <l>Rather then live a King in infamy.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Monſi.</speaker>
                     <l>A heavie ſpectacle of grief and woe</l>
                     <l>Have beheld ſince our arivall here;</l>
                     <l>Take up the body of the King, and theſe</l>
                     <l>That for his love on either hand lie ſlain,</l>
                     <l>They ſhall lie buried in one Monument:</l>
                     <l>And take up theſe; this was Royall Queen</l>
                     <l>When virtue ſteer'd her thoughts; but we may ſee,</l>
                     <l>When we turn foes to good, to vice a friend,</l>
                     <l>We fall like theſe, and like theſe thus we end.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <stage>A dead March within.</stage>
                  <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
               </div>
            </div>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
