<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>The loyal lovers a tragi-comedy / written by Major Cosmo Manuche.</title>
            <author>Manuche, Cosmo, fl. 1650-1652.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1652</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 193 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 30 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-12">2011-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A51870</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing M550</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R6308</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">12987357</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 12987357</idno>
            <idno type="VID">96238</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A51870)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 96238)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 390:2)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>The loyal lovers a tragi-comedy / written by Major Cosmo Manuche.</title>
                  <author>Manuche, Cosmo, fl. 1650-1652.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[4], 48 [i.e. 56], [1] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed for Thomas Eglesfield ...,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1652.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Title page vignette.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in Huntington Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2010-02</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-03</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-05</date>
            <label>Pip Willcox</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-05</date>
            <label>Pip Willcox</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-06</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:96238:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:96238:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>THE LOYAL LOVERS: A Tragi-Comedy. Written by Major COSMO MANUCHE.</p>
            <figure>
               <figDesc>printer's or publisher's device</figDesc>
            </figure>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON,</hi> Printed for <hi>Thomas Eglesfield</hi> at the Brazen Serpent in S<hi rend="sup">t</hi> 
               <hi>Paul</hi>'s Church-yard. 1652.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="dramatis_personae">
            <pb facs="tcp:96238:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:96238:2"/>
            <head>The Names of the Perſons preſented.</head>
            <list>
               <item>
                  <label>Corianus,</label> A noble perſon betrothed to <hi>Apfia.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <label>Adraſtus,</label> Loyall Comrades.</item>
               <item>
                  <label>Albinus,</label> Loyall Comrades.</item>
               <item>
                  <label>Symphronio,</label> Loyall Comrades.</item>
               <item>
                  <label>Gripe-man,</label> A Committee-man.</item>
               <item>
                  <label>Sent-well,</label> A creature of <hi>Gripe-man</hi>'s, an Informer.</item>
               <item>
                  <label>Sodome,</label> One of the Synod.</item>
               <item>
                  <label>Atheos,</label> Governour of a Sea-town.</item>
               <item>
                  <label>Rogaſtus,</label> A Lievtenant under <hi>Atheos.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <label>Mettle,</label> Servant to <hi>Adraſtus.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <label>Perjurus,</label> Servant, and Clark to <hi>Gripe-man.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <label>Leteſia,</label> Daughter to <hi>Gripe-man.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <label>Apfia,</label> Servant to <hi>Leteſia,</hi> diſguiſed, and call'd <hi>Clarathea.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <label>Riggle,</label> A common ſtrumpet.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Souldiers.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>A Book-cryer.</hi>
               </item>
            </list>
            <p>The SCENE <hi>Amſterdam.</hi>
            </p>
         </div>
         <div type="author_to_friends">
            <pb facs="tcp:96238:3"/>
            <head>The <hi>Author</hi> to his Honorable Friends.</head>
            <l>THink mee not proud as poor, when you ſhall ſee</l>
            <l>I borrow not in my neceſsity.</l>
            <l>And ſhould I ſteal, (though common in this age)</l>
            <l>I ſhould (by ſome) be trap't in every page.</l>
            <l>Then hue and cry comes forth, ſwiftly purſu'd</l>
            <l>At length I'me taken, guiltie found, and mew'd.</l>
            <l>Now, as for Juſtice, (faith) I'me like to finde</l>
            <l>Her, like Fortune muſfled, if not ſtark blinde.</l>
            <l>All Deprecations then, when deprehended,</l>
            <l>Little availe mee; The Judge aſcended</l>
            <l>Appears two Critick would bees, point blank ſwears</l>
            <l>That all the wit they found about mee's theirs.</l>
            <l>Which grant it were, let it be prais'd by ſence,</l>
            <l>And 'twill be found not worth 'bove thirteen pence,</l>
            <l>Which wants of halter proof. Now 'twere ill done</l>
            <l>To hang a man ne're rob'd 'twixt ſun and ſun.</l>
            <l>Nor have I ſtoln by night, (as I can think)</l>
            <l>Unleſſe 'twere home to bed full fraight with drink.</l>
            <l>But ſuch, as wanted virtue to infuſe</l>
            <l>The Heliconian fire into my Muſe.</l>
            <l>I know you'l gueſs what beer and ale can do,</l>
            <l>Where daily care's had to procure that too.</l>
            <l>My Jury now (might I but chooſe) ſhould be</l>
            <l>Such as hath liv'd high, and know miſerie.</l>
            <l>And if ſuch quit mee not, I'm ſure they'l ſay,</l>
            <l>'Twas (partly) want of money ſpoyl'd my play.</l>
            <l>Since Ile not ſteal, nor borrow, give mee wit;</l>
            <l>'Tis in your power to make mee purchaſe it.</l>
            <l>I cannot bluſh to own what comes from friends,</l>
            <l>Give, and forgive, I have obtein'd my Ends.</l>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="play">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:96238:3"/>
            <head>THE LOYALL LOVERS: A Tragi-Comedy.</head>
            <div n="1" type="act">
               <head>ACT I.</head>
               <div n="1" type="scene">
                  <head>SCENE I.</head>
                  <stage>Enter <hi>Adraſtus,</hi> looking on his watch.</stage>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Adraſtus.</speaker>
                     <l>MY Youths have forfeited their pottle;</l>
                     <l>'Tis almoſt ten of clock.—</l>
                     <stage>Enter <hi>Book-cryer.</hi>
                     </stage>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Book.</speaker>
                     <l>Come new new new new</l>
                     <l>Who buyes my new books here?</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Adraſt.</speaker>
                     <p>What books have you got there, Sirrah?</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Book.</speaker>
                     <l>Newly come forth, and newly printed.</l>
                     <l>Why (Sir!) here is, how conſpicuouſly the Hogans are conculcated by their own Adulation.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Adraſt.</speaker>
                     <p>Thoſe are hard words, Sirrah.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Book.</speaker>
                     <p>But altogether in faſhion, I can aſſure you, Sir.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Adraſt.</speaker>
                     <p>Not with thoſe that underſtand them not.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Book.</speaker>
                     <p>Sir, you do moſt prodigiouſly miſtake; there being an order they ſhould paſſe without exception where there is the ſpirit of pronunciation.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Adraſt.</speaker>
                     <p>Pray let me have more facetious language, and leſſe of your ſpirit.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Book.</speaker>
                     <p>Sir, I know your minde, And ſhall endeavour to pleaſure you preſently. Let mee ſee, here is A true, perfect, and exact account of Juſtice <hi>Dapper,</hi> and his Clark's Sodomitical revenue, to the great diſabling, and impoveriſhing the Active, and well-affected Females.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Adraſt.</speaker>
                     <p>Come give mee that, what others have you?</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Book.</speaker>
                     <p>Why here is another, of a famous Doctor's miraculous obteining the Philoſophers ſtone.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Adraſt.</speaker>
                     <p>Doth your book ſpeak how?</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Book.</speaker>
                     <p>Yes Sir, that either the Stone, or a perfect receit to obtein it, was preſerved in a wrack, and caſt on this ſhore; which hee hath purchaſed, to the unſpeakable content of all his beleevers.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Adraſt.</speaker>
                     <p>What is the price of them both?</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Book.</speaker>
                     <p>A groat Sir, I can aſſure you.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Adraſt.</speaker>
                     <p>Sirrah, that's too much, here's three pence for you.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Book.</speaker>
                     <p>Why Sir? Juſtice <hi>Dapper,</hi> and his Clerk's revenue is worth three pence; And do you think the Philoſophers Stone coſt mee nothing.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Adraſt.</speaker>
                     <l>Here Crackrope, here's your money.</l>
                     <pb n="2" facs="tcp:96238:4"/>
                     <l>You make a brave trade of this, Sirrah.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Book.</speaker>
                     <l>In troth Sir, but a bare livelyhood; (or where I get</l>
                     <l>A penny by the Philoſophers ſtone, there's <hi>Dapper</hi> and his Clark</l>
                     <l>Gets ten pounds by the well-affected female.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Adraſt.</speaker>
                     <l>'Tis very probable; for they often for a touch</l>
                     <l>Change Droſſe into Gold. Farwell Sirrah.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Book.</speaker>
                     <l>Thank you good Maſter, I hope to have rare news for you next week.</l>
                     <l>Come new new. who buyes my choiſe new new here?</l>
                     <l>Pox on't. Here's a diſpenſation for oaths neceſſarie, ſticks damnably on my hands;</l>
                     <l>The people refuſing to buy, as if they had it all by Rote.—</l>
                  </sp>
                  <stage>Exit Book.</stage>
                  <stage>Enter to <hi>Adraſt. Albinus, Symphronio.</hi>
                  </stage>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Albin.</speaker>
                     <p>
                        <hi>Adraſtus,</hi> good day to you: what, at your ſtudy thus early?</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Adraſt.</speaker>
                     <p>A ſtudy your neglect invited mee to ſpend my idle time.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Albin.</speaker>
                     <l>Tearm not that neglect (Dear friend) which wee'l confeſſe</l>
                     <l>A fault of Drowſineſſe.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Adraſt.</speaker>
                     <l>Come, come, you are ſluggards both. I hope you will confeſſe</l>
                     <l>You have forfeited your pottle.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Symph.</speaker>
                     <l>VVee have. And when you pleaſe demand it;</l>
                     <l>You'l finde us ready pay-maſters.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Albin.</speaker>
                     <p>But what books were you ſo ſeriouſly meditating on?</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Adraſt.</speaker>
                     <l>Strange books, which wee'l peruſe</l>
                     <l>VVhen you ſhall pay your forfeits.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Symph.</speaker>
                     <p>It wants not much of noon, what think you of it now?</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Albin.</speaker>
                     <p>I, I, let's march.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Adraſt.</speaker>
                     <p>'Tis ſure too ſoon.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Albin.</speaker>
                     <p>Not to be merry, wee have been ſad too long.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Adraſt.</speaker>
                     <p>Then lead the way.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Albin.</speaker>
                     <p>Come let us walk <hi>Symphronio,</hi> 'tis wee muſt pay:</p>
                  </sp>
                  <stage>Exeunt Omnes.</stage>
                  <stage>Enter <hi>Gripeman</hi> and <hi>Sent-well.</hi>
                  </stage>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Gripe.</speaker>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Sent-well,</hi> mee thinks thou art not half ſo active as thou wer't wont.</l>
                     <l>Sure thou art grown rich of late.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Sent.</speaker>
                     <p>'Tis (as you ſay) of late, if I be rich.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Gripe.</speaker>
                     <l>'Tis thy own fault thou art not. Thou art young,</l>
                     <l>VVhen I was at thy years, I would have ſtirr'd my ſelf i-faith,</l>
                     <l>Such getting times as theſe.</l>
                     <l>VVhy there is old <hi>Firmstand</hi> would make half a dozen of us.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Sent.</speaker>
                     <l>Yes, a weary with running up and down after him</l>
                     <l>As I have done. I have followed him, like his ſhadow,</l>
                     <l>Dayly this half year, and to no purpoſe.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Gripe.</speaker>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Sentwell,</hi> you give mee no account of the five pounds</l>
                     <l>You had of mee to furniſh your Comrades</l>
                     <l>That undertook to trap him.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Sent.</speaker>
                     <l>Had it been more 't had gone; I am out of purſe an Angel</l>
                     <l>About that buſineſſe. You reckon ſtill what you are out of purſe,</l>
                     <l>But do forget what I have brought you in.</l>
                     <l>(I will not ſay by my juſt information)</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Gripe.</speaker>
                     <l>I do remember, I do remember, <hi>Sent-well,</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>But could wee trap old <hi>Firmſtand,</hi>
                     </l>
                     <pb n="3" facs="tcp:96238:4"/>
                     <l>VVee might lye ſtill and reſt a moneth.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Sent.</speaker>
                     <l>Sir, I have tryed all wayes man could invent to undo him:</l>
                     <l>Intruded into his company, not only once or twice,</l>
                     <l>But times innumerable; And <hi>Proteus</hi>-like, varied my ſhape,</l>
                     <l>And fac't him down that I was not my ſelf.</l>
                     <l>Yet hee, ſo cautious (ſtill) in drink, or other waies,</l>
                     <l>That not a ſyllable, tending to th' States abuſe,</l>
                     <l>I e're could hear him utter.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Gripe.</speaker>
                     <l>VVhy then wee muſt another way to work before hee leaves the town:</l>
                     <l>Hee never (yet) ſaw <hi>Perjurus</hi> my Clark.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Sent.</speaker>
                     <p>Never, to my beſt of knowledge.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Gripe.</speaker>
                     <l>It muſt be ſo, <hi>Sent-well: Perjurus</hi> and you ſhall to his</l>
                     <l>Lodging go; And under ſome pretence of buſineſſe</l>
                     <l>That <hi>Perjurus</hi> ſhall ſeem to have with him,</l>
                     <l>Fall in diſcourſe ot'h State.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Sent.</speaker>
                     <l>VVhich hee will hardly do, or if hee ſhould, hee'l cautious be</l>
                     <l>VVhat language hee delivers.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Gripe.</speaker>
                     <p>No matter, if that will not do, <hi>Perjurus</hi> and you ſhall ſwear.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Sent.</speaker>
                     <p>VVee heard him ſpeak treaſon 'gainſt the State.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Gripe.</speaker>
                     <p>Right, very right.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Sent.</speaker>
                     <l>Not ſo very right neither. Sir, you know mee to be your creature,</l>
                     <l>But you have ſo ſlenderly rewarded mee for ſuch like actions,</l>
                     <l>I know not what to think on't.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Gripe.</speaker>
                     <l>No more, no more, all ſhall be well. I muſt away to ſee</l>
                     <l>There's no injuſtice done about ſharing the VViddows goods</l>
                     <l>VVee caus'd to be plundered. <hi>Sent-well,</hi> let mee alone</l>
                     <l>'Bout eight of clock this evening to plot your buſineſſe</l>
                     <l>For old <hi>Firmſtand;</hi> and for thy part,</l>
                     <l>Thou ſhalt have trebble ſhare.—</l>
                  </sp>
                  <stage>Exit Gripe.</stage>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Sent.</speaker>
                     <p>I think ſo too. The trebble Gallowes, if wee had our due.—</p>
                  </sp>
                  <stage>Exit Sent.</stage>
                  <stage>Enter <hi>Leteſia, Clarathea,</hi> and <hi>Perjurus.</hi>
                  </stage>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Clarath.</speaker>
                     <p>Miſtreſſe, have you any acquaintance in the Change?</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Leteſ.</speaker>
                     <p>Not I, <hi>Clarathea:</hi> Haſt Thou?</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Clarath.</speaker>
                     <l>Not I truely; but it matters not much, for I have often</l>
                     <l>Found ſtrangers to part with their Commodities</l>
                     <l>At cheaper rates then thoſe that would be thought our friends.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <stage>Enter <hi>Adraſt. Symph.</hi>
                  </stage>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Leteſ.</speaker>
                     <p>You wagg, ſpeak ſoftly, or you'l be heard.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Adraſt.</speaker>
                     <l>Now by the Gods I have not ſeen a rarer piece.</l>
                     <l>In all my travells.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Symph.</speaker>
                     <l>Beſhrew mee but ſhee is handſom.</l>
                     <l>Let's walk and obſerve her.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Adraſt.</speaker>
                     <l>Dear <hi>Symphronio,</hi> wait an opportunity to accoſt her maid, and know</l>
                     <l>Her name and being.—</l>
                  </sp>
                  <stage>
                     <hi>Exit Leteſ. Clarath.</hi> and <hi>Perjurus.</hi>
                  </stage>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Symph.</speaker>
                     <l>So quick, ſhee's gone, I'le follow her, and it ſhall go hard but I'le be</l>
                     <l>Able to give you punctuall ſatisfaction.—</l>
                     <stage>Exit Symph, and enters immediately.</stage>
                     <l>But do you hear, you'l not be ſcrupulous to pay</l>
                     <pb n="4" facs="tcp:96238:5"/>
                     <l>this debt, and pimp when fleſh invites.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Adraſt.</speaker>
                     <p>No, no, my friendſhip ſtand engaged.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Symph.</speaker>
                     <p>I'le take't, farewell.—</p>
                  </sp>
                  <stage>Exit Symph.</stage>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Adraſt.</speaker>
                     <l>I feel an unaccuſtomed qualm, I hope I am not caught.</l>
                     <l>If I miſtake not, ſhe more then ordinarily eyed mee.</l>
                     <l>VVhy how now <hi>Adraſtus?</hi> have I ſtood the ſhock of ſo many ſparkling eyes, to ſhrink now in thy prime of judgment? but
'twill away again I hope.</l>
                     <l>Yet why may not ſhee deſerve my love? I have made no vow that I have broke, nor ere prophan'd at <hi>Cupid</hi>'s Altar: <hi>Venus</hi> aſſiſt me then, and let it work.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <stage>Enter <hi>Albinus.</hi>
                  </stage>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Albin.</speaker>
                     <p>Noble <hi>Adraſtus,</hi> what all alone? where's <hi>Symphronio?</hi>
                     </p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Adraſt.</speaker>
                     <p>Faith I have imployed him in a buſineſſe, hee'l not be ſcrupulous in telling thee.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <stage>Enter <hi>Symphronio.</hi>
                  </stage>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Albin.</speaker>
                     <p>See here hee is come. Sure 'twas ſome merry buſineſſe hee looks ſo pleaſant 'bout the mouth. <hi>Symphronio</hi> prethee make us partakers of your mirth.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Symph.</speaker>
                     <l>That you ſhall, juſt at the turning out ot'h change</l>
                     <l>I gave the Maid a pull by the coat.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Albin.</speaker>
                     <p>VVhat Maid, in the name of <hi>Cupid?</hi>
                     </p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Symphr.</speaker>
                     <l>Thou man of ignorance, be ſilent, and give ear.</l>
                     <l>Shee turn'd about, and with a ſmiling countenance</l>
                     <l>Told mee I was miſtaken, they were not for my turn.</l>
                     <l>Her Miſtreſſe hearing her, look't back, and bluſh't,</l>
                     <l>Then caus'd her man go forward.</l>
                     <l>I, reſolv'd not to return unſatisfied, fell on again,</l>
                     <l>And with a civil Confidence told her I had a reaſonable</l>
                     <l>Requeſt, ſhee, in two or three words could ſatisfie.</l>
                     <l>At which ſhe made a ſtand, and gave mee leave to ask her Miſtreſſe</l>
                     <l>Name, and dwelling. Shee readily anſwered,</l>
                     <l>'Twas more then ſhee had Commiſſion for to do.</l>
                     <l>Yet for that I look't like an honeſt Gentleman,</l>
                     <l>(That could not harbor a diſhonorable thought) ſhe would.—</l>
                     <stage>Albin. hums by.</stage>
                     <l>Shee told mee her father, —And there ſhee ſtopt, and ſigth'd,</l>
                     <l>As if ſhe thought him unworthy ſo heavenly a childe.</l>
                     <l>At laſt ſhee brought it out, telling mee, her Maſter</l>
                     <l>(Father to that Gentlewoman) was call'd <hi>Gripe-man;</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>His dwelling in the High-ſtreet; And this his Daughter</l>
                     <l>And onely childe, was named <hi>Leteſia.</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>I courteouſly thank't her, and ſo departed.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Albin.</speaker>
                     <l>Hey day, what ſtuffe's here? all this ceremony for a wench?</l>
                     <l>You might have courted (with leſſe ado) the holieſt</l>
                     <l>Siſter in the City, and have ſped too.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Adraſt.</speaker>
                     <l>Peace, peace you wag; upon my ſoul ſhee is</l>
                     <l>A virtuous creature.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Albin.</speaker>
                     <p>Prethe ingage not thy ſoul for the female ſex, they are brittle ware.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Adraſt.</speaker>
                     <l>Thou wouldſt adore her ſex during life,</l>
                     <l>Did'ſt thou but ſee her face.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <pb n="5" facs="tcp:96238:5"/>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Albin.</speaker>
                     <l>Is it a friend of yours that hath the letting of her out,</l>
                     <l>You ſo extoll her?</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Adraſt.</speaker>
                     <l>Leave jeſting; By <hi>Jupiter</hi> I dare ſwear ſhee is virtuous;</l>
                     <l>Would I had never ſeen her face.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Albin.</speaker>
                     <l>By <hi>Cupid</hi> hee is ſerious; nay if the winde blow there,</l>
                     <l>Come, come, let's pack.</l>
                     <l>No cure for love like a good cup of ſack.—</l>
                  </sp>
                  <stage>Ex. Om.</stage>
                  <stage>Enter <hi>Leteſia Clarathea.</hi>
                  </stage>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Leteſ.</speaker>
                     <p>How now <hi>Clarathea,</hi> what taken up i'th ſtreets by Gallants?</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Clarath.</speaker>
                     <l>Not by Gallants, Miſtreſſe; And for taking up the place</l>
                     <l>Was not convenient; which had it been</l>
                     <l>I ſhould have ſaved him that labor,</l>
                     <l>And have taken up for him.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Leteſ.</speaker>
                     <p>You ſhould.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Clarath.</speaker>
                     <p>Faith like enough, had wee been both agreed.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Leteſ.</speaker>
                     <l>Thou art a mad ſoul, but faith deal truly with mee,</l>
                     <l>What his buſineſſe was.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Clarath.</speaker>
                     <p>Cannot you gueſs?</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Leteſ.</speaker>
                     <l>'Twere ſtrange I ſhould;</l>
                     <l>Do'ſt take mee for a Witch?</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Clarath.</speaker>
                     <l>No I'le beſworn, nor I beleeve hee neither; for if hee had,</l>
                     <l>Hee would not have ſo earneſtly enquired after you.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Leteſ.</speaker>
                     <p>After mee?</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Clarath.</speaker>
                     <p>Even ſo; his buſineſſe was to know your name and habitation.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Leteſ.</speaker>
                     <p>Prethee wench be ſerious.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Clarath.</speaker>
                     <p>By my maiden-head 'tis truth.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Leteſ.</speaker>
                     <p>That's but a tickliſh oath, may I beleeve it?</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Clarath.</speaker>
                     <p>Seriouſly, moſt true.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Leteſ.</speaker>
                     <p>And didſt thou tell him?</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Clarath.</speaker>
                     <p>I did indeed.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Leteſ.</speaker>
                     <p>Urg'd hee to know no more?</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Clarath.</speaker>
                     <p>But onely ſo. 'Tis your father calls, Away.—</p>
                  </sp>
                  <stage>Ex. Omnes.</stage>
                  <stage>Enter <hi>Riggle, Sodome</hi> following her, and <hi>Mettle</hi> following him.</stage>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Sod.</speaker>
                     <l>That Lady ſhould be right by her ſwimming gate.</l>
                     <l>I am provok't, and muſt have eaſe.
<stage>—<hi>calls.</hi>
                        </stage>
                     </l>
                     <l>Siſter, ſiſter, his't, his't, why ſiſter.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Rigg.</speaker>
                     <p>Would you ought with mee, Sir?</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Sod.</speaker>
                     <p>Lady, 'tis dark.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Rigg.</speaker>
                     <p>'Tis very true. Sir! Can you make it lighter?</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Mett.</speaker>
                     <l>You may with ſtanding on your head;</l>
                     <l>For there's no doubt you burn below.
<stage>—<hi>aſide.</hi>
                        </stage>
                     </l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Sod.</speaker>
                     <l>My directions (Fair Lady!) will be</l>
                     <l>No ſtumbling block to you.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Mett.</speaker>
                     <l>No, I dare ſwear, ſhee will by them finde</l>
                     <l>A very even way to hell.</l>
                     <l>This is ſome zealous brother troubled with rebellious fleſh.</l>
                     <l>I will obſerve them further.
<stage>—<hi>aſide.</hi>
                        </stage>
                     </l>
                  </sp>
                  <pb facs="tcp:96238:6"/>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Sod.</speaker>
                     <l>If my heartily profered ſervice appear not troubleſom,</l>
                     <l>I ſhall perform the duty of a ſervant,</l>
                     <l>And wait upon you home.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Rigg.</speaker>
                     <l>Sir, I thank you. But mee thinks your habit</l>
                     <l>And your language are not well match't.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Sod.</speaker>
                     <p>However match't, they ſhall agree to do you ſervice.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Mett.</speaker>
                     <p>This is no Rogue.
<stage>aſide.</stage>
                     </p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Rigg.</speaker>
                     <l>Sir, to give you anſwer. I am this night to encounter</l>
                     <l>With a friend about ſome buſineſſe</l>
                     <l>That much concerns my livelyhood.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Mett.</speaker>
                     <l>I beleeve ſo; And may concern his death</l>
                     <l>If hee procure not the better Chirurgion.
<stage>aſide.</stage>
                     </l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Sod.</speaker>
                     <l>Lady, ſhall I requeſt you make mee then ſo happy</l>
                     <l>As let mee know where I may wait on you to morrow?</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Rigg.</speaker>
                     <p>So it be in the evening, where you pleaſe.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Sod.</speaker>
                     <l>Pray name the place moſt convenient for you,</l>
                     <l>And I'le not faile to attend you.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Rigg.</speaker>
                     <p>What think you of the Naked-boy in Fleſh lane?</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Sod.</speaker>
                     <p>The hour now, and I'le not fail you, Lady.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Rigg.</speaker>
                     <p>'Tween four and fiveith' evening,</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Sod.</speaker>
                     <l>Till when, your faithfull ſervant.</l>
                     <l>Lady, all happineſſe attend you.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <stage>Ex. Sodome.</stage>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Mett.</speaker>
                     <l>O here is rare ſport for Mounſieur <hi>Albinus,</hi>
                     </l>
                     <stage>Ex. Rigg.</stage>
                     <l>My maſters friend.</l>
                     <l>Well, Brother Zealot, if my wits not fail,</l>
                     <l>I'le have an excellent Cure to cool your tail.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <stage>Ex. Mettle.</stage>
                  <stage>Enter <hi>Adraſtus, Albinus, Symphronio,</hi> and <hi>Drawer,</hi> as in a Tavern.</stage>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Albin.</speaker>
                     <p>
                        <hi>Drawer,</hi> be ſure you let's have that that's right.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Draw.</speaker>
                     <l>Sir, I'le play with any Vintner (confin'd within the circuit</l>
                     <l>Of a hundred mile) Canarie 'gainſt Canarie.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Albin.</speaker>
                     <l>Well Sirrah, let your wine be rich as your words,</l>
                     <l>And I'le bet on your ſide.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Draw.</speaker>
                     <p>I'le warrant you Sir.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <stage>Ex. Drawer.</stage>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Albin.</speaker>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Mettle,</hi> welcom to town.</l>
                     <stage>Enter <hi>Mettle.</hi>
                     </stage>
                     <l>How do our friends ith' countrey?</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Mett.</speaker>
                     <p>All well, Sir. Sir, here are letters for you.
<stage>gives Adraſtus letters.</stage>
                     </p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Adraſt.</speaker>
                     <p>Sirrah, I look't for you two dayes ago.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Mett.</speaker>
                     <p>Sir, your letters ſpeak my occaſion of ſtay.
<stage>Adraſt. reads to himſelf.</stage>
                     </p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Symph.</speaker>
                     <p>And how? And how honeſt <hi>Mettle?</hi>
                     </p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Mett.</speaker>
                     <l>Your faithfull ſervant, Sir.</l>
                     <l>I have rare ſport in chaſe for you.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Albin.</speaker>
                     <p>For mee, <hi>Mettle?</hi>
                     </p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Mett.</speaker>
                     <p>For you Sir, if you pleaſe purſue it.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Symph.</speaker>
                     <p>Here is a cup of Sack to your welcom to town, <hi>Mettle.</hi>
                     </p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Mett.</speaker>
                     <p>I thank you, Sir.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Albin.</speaker>
                     <p>Nay give him t'other cup. What newes <hi>Adrastus?</hi>
                     </p>
                  </sp>
                  <pb n="7" facs="tcp:96238:6"/>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Adraſt.</speaker>
                     <p>The newes is, they write to mee for newes.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Albin.</speaker>
                     <p>
                        <hi>Adraſtus,</hi> Lore your top ſail: Vive la Roy.
<stage>—<hi>Albinus drinks.</hi>
                        </stage>
                     </p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Adraſt.</speaker>
                     <p>Come, away with it; <hi>Symphronio,</hi> to you.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Symph.</speaker>
                     <p>Thanks good <hi>Adraſtus.</hi>
                     </p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Albin.</speaker>
                     <p>Come <hi>Mettle,</hi> the rare ſport you talk off, what is't?</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Mett.</speaker>
                     <l>Why Sir? ſome hour ſince, making enquiry for my maſter,</l>
                     <l>(Though ſomewhat dark) I could diſcover a zealous Brother</l>
                     <l>In hot purſuit of a wench; hee followed her,</l>
                     <l>I followed him: at length with complementall language</l>
                     <l>Hee aſſaulted her, who ſeemed ſomewhat ſhy at firſt;</l>
                     <l>At laſt, pretending earneſt occaſions for her excuſe this night,</l>
                     <l>Shee engaged to morrow evening to meet him, 'twixt four and five.</l>
                     <l>The bargain driven thus, they parted ſeverall waies.</l>
                     <l>I followed the wench, and pretending my ſelf to be his man,</l>
                     <l>Told her, my maſter had conſidered, and would requeſt her</l>
                     <l>The meeting might be by three ith' afternoon.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Albin.</speaker>
                     <p>What deſign hadſt thou in that?</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Mett.</speaker>
                     <l>Sir, as thus: That if in caſe you and my maſter</l>
                     <l>Fancy a ſcene of mirth, l'le bring you to the place</l>
                     <l>By three oth' clock, where (without doubt)</l>
                     <l>You'l finde her. Then you have time enough before hee comes,</l>
                     <l>For to contrive (which without doubt ſhee will conſent to)</l>
                     <l>Some puniſhment fits your mirth, and worthy ſo baſe an abuſer</l>
                     <l>Of the Common-wealth.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Albin.</speaker>
                     <p>Excellent <hi>Mettle!</hi> Here drink this for mee.
<stage>—<hi>gives him money.</hi>
                        </stage>
                     </p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Mett.</speaker>
                     <p>You binde mee to you, Sir.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Albin.</speaker>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Adrastus,</hi> Pox of your melancholy, there's no denyall,</l>
                     <l>You muſt (in this deſign) along with us to morrow.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Adraſt.</speaker>
                     <p>I ſhall conſider of it.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Albin.</speaker>
                     <p>Conſider mee no conſiders, you muſt go with us.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Symph.</speaker>
                     <p>Hee muſt, hee muſt.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Adraſt.</speaker>
                     <p>
                        <hi>Mettle,</hi> come hither.
<stage>—<hi>Adraſt. &amp; Mettle whiſper. Mett. goes of.</hi>
                        </stage>
                     </p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Albin.</speaker>
                     <l>Prethee <hi>Adraſtus,</hi> ingeniouſly tell mee,</l>
                     <l>Doth not this wench, this ſhee fayrie-female trouble thee?</l>
                     <l>Thou wer't not wont to be thus off the hooks.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Adraſt.</speaker>
                     <p>Wilt thou not laugh at mee, if I ſhould confeſſe?</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Albin.</speaker>
                     <l>Faith no: I ever could diſtinguiſh between a friend</l>
                     <l>Seriouſly deſerving pitie, and objects fit for laughter.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Adraſt.</speaker>
                     <l>I know not what you call being in love,</l>
                     <l>But if I not enjoy her, I muſt forget</l>
                     <l>There can be joy on earth.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Albin.</speaker>
                     <l>Injoy? Do'ſt know what 'tis thou would'ſt injoy?</l>
                     <l>Shee may be (for ought I can perceive) thou know'ſt</l>
                     <l>Not worthy thy affection.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Adraſt.</speaker>
                     <l>Can there be ſo much beauty</l>
                     <l>Without a world of virtue and deſert?</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Albin.</speaker>
                     <p>
                        <hi>Symphromo,</hi> you know her fathers houſe.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Symph.</speaker>
                     <p>If what lier maid delivered to mee be true, I do.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <pb n="8" facs="tcp:96238:7"/>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Albin.</speaker>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Adraſtus,</hi> few hours will make known if ſhe worthlly deſerve,</l>
                     <l>Which when diſcovered, and that I finde her worthy thy affection,</l>
                     <l>Imploy Thy <hi>Albinus:</hi> And if I faile to ſerve Thee, to my laſt drop of blood,</l>
                     <l>May miſerie enforce mee take up arms againſt</l>
                     <l>My naturall Prince.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Symph.</speaker>
                     <p>The ſame wiſh I; And I know nothing worſe.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Adraſt.</speaker>
                     <l>My noble friends, I thank you, and cordially beleeve you,</l>
                     <l>What e're (through weakneſſe) I deſerve.</l>
                     <l>Now for contrivance, how to obtein that happy houre</l>
                     <l>Wherein I may reveal my thoughts to her, (none elſe being by)</l>
                     <l>To mee appeares miraculous.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Albin.</speaker>
                     <p>That, I'le engage my life, you ſpeedily ſhall do.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Adraſt.</speaker>
                     <l>It is impoſſible, how can'ſt thou contrive it?</l>
                     <l>It were a happineſſe I dare not hope for.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Albin.</speaker>
                     <l>Be not too incredulous, this I'le perform,</l>
                     <l>Or ne're draw ſword again.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Symph.</speaker>
                     <l>My life for't, what hee undertakes, hee'l confidently</l>
                     <l>Go through with.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Adraſt.</speaker>
                     <p>O <hi>Symphronio,</hi> I know his will, would hee had power equall!</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Albin.</speaker>
                     <l>I hope on the condition I do your buſineſſe, you will</l>
                     <l>Accompany us to morrow to <hi>Mettle</hi>'s Wench and holy Brother.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Adraſt.</speaker>
                     <l>I will, and what lies in mee to encreaſe your mirth</l>
                     <l>I really ſhall act.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Albin.</speaker>
                     <l>Why that's well ſaid. Now for your buſineſſe.</l>
                     <l>Some time this night will I procure a ſuit of clothes, with which</l>
                     <l>(My periwick left off) I well may paſſe for round amongſt the Synod.</l>
                     <l>The iſſue of my buſineſſe expect to hear to morrow.</l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Drawer, Drawer,</hi> to pay?—</l>
                     <stage>Enter <hi>Drawer.</hi>
                     </stage>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Draw.</speaker>
                     <p>Sir, you ſhall know preſently.—</p>
                  </sp>
                  <stage>Exit Drawer.</stage>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Adraſt.</speaker>
                     <l>Name but your hour of return,</l>
                     <l>And wee'l expect you here.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Albin.</speaker>
                     <l>There's no place better; by nine or ten ith' morning</l>
                     <l>I will be with you.</l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Symphronio,</hi> give mee a note of the old mans houſe and name.—</l>
                     <stage>Enter <hi>Drawer:</hi>
                     </stage>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Symph.</speaker>
                     <l>That at our lodging you ſhall have.</l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Drawer,</hi> what's to pay?</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Draw.</speaker>
                     <p>Four ſhillings and a penny.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Symph.</speaker>
                     <l>Eighteen pence club will do it.</l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Drawer,</hi> the reſt take for your pains.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Draw.</speaker>
                     <l>Thank you Gentlemen, you are very kindly welcom.</l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Peerce,</hi> ſhow a light down ſtairs.</l>
                     <l>'Tis all paid ith'Kings-head,—</l>
                     <stage>Ex. Om.</stage>
                     <stage>Enter <hi>Leteſia ſol.</hi>
                     </stage>
                     <l>How have I loſt my liberty? Was ever Maid betrayed</l>
                     <l>By her eyes as I have been?</l>
                     <l>Dote on I know not what, or whom?</l>
                     <l>Muſt I languiſh for what I know's impoſſible to obtain?</l>
                     <l>Thy hopes, <hi>Leteſia,</hi> at beſt, are but that hee is noble, and a ſingle man.</l>
                     <pb n="9" facs="tcp:96238:7"/>
                     <l>Suppoſe this be, where ſhall I finde him, or of whom enquire</l>
                     <l>To eaſe my troubled ſoul?</l>
                     <l>I may aſwell ſearch for a Diamond in the main Ocean loſt,</l>
                     <l>And hope (alike) to finde it.</l>
                     <l>And yet, how much deſirous is my troubled heart</l>
                     <l>To entertain ſomething like hope?</l>
                     <l>Why ſhould his friend (for ſure hee muſt be ſo)</l>
                     <l>Enquire after mee? give my Maid money for diſcovering</l>
                     <l>My name and dwelling? All this is nothing,</l>
                     <l>And yet it may be ſomething: No it cannot neither;</l>
                     <l>For 'twas his friend enquired, and ſure his buſineſſe</l>
                     <l>Only concern'd himſelf.</l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Leteſia,</hi> Thy little hopes is daſh't. But if his friend</l>
                     <l>Come in his own behalf, I may enquire of him.</l>
                     <l>And that will breed a jealouſie, and may, ſuſpecting</l>
                     <l>Him his rivall, kill him, (which heaven forbid)</l>
                     <l>That muſt not be.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <stage>Enter <hi>Clarathea.</hi>
                  </stage>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Clarath.</speaker>
                     <l>This is the third time</l>
                     <l>I have taken you alone in melancholy poſtures.</l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Venus</hi> grant you are not in love.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Leteſ.</speaker>
                     <p>In love, with what?</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Clarath.</speaker>
                     <l>That (if you pleaſe) lyes in your breaſt to reſolve mee.</l>
                     <l>There is one of the pitifull'ſt holy brethren within</l>
                     <l>To ſpeak with your father, that ever eyes beheld.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Leteſ.</speaker>
                     <p>Know'ſt thou his buſineſſe?</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Clarath.</speaker>
                     <l>Not I, but ſomething hee pretends to have with him</l>
                     <l>Of much concernment.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Leteſ.</speaker>
                     <p>Know's my father of his being here?</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Clarath.</speaker>
                     <p>Not yet.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Leteſ.</speaker>
                     <p>I'le then go call him.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Clarath.</speaker>
                     <p>See, ſee, they are here.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <stage>Enter <hi>Gripe-man,</hi> and <hi>Albinus</hi> diſguiſed.</stage>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Albin.</speaker>
                     <p>Good morrow to you, fair Miſtris.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Leteſ.</speaker>
                     <p>The like to you, Sir.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Gripe.</speaker>
                     <p>
                        <hi>Leteſia</hi> leave us till I call you.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Leteſ.</speaker>
                     <p>I ſhall Sir.—</p>
                  </sp>
                  <stage>
                     <hi>Ex. Leteſia</hi> and <hi>Clarathea.</hi>
                  </stage>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Gripe.</speaker>
                     <p>Now when you pleaſe, begin your buſineſſe.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Albin.</speaker>
                     <l>Sir, the common report of your juſt carriage in the holy cauſe</l>
                     <l>You undertake, hath encouraged mee to make my caſe known</l>
                     <l>To you, the well handling of which (I doubt not) but will</l>
                     <l>Be very advantagious to us both.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Gripe.</speaker>
                     <l>You ſay wonderfull well, and to the purpoſe.</l>
                     <l>Pray proceed.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Albin.</speaker>
                     <l>A repetition of ſuch truths as I could juſtly deliver</l>
                     <l>To your ample ſatisfaction, how laboriouſly active</l>
                     <l>I have been in the advancing this great cauſe,</l>
                     <l>Would be too tedious for you to undergo the hearing of;</l>
                     <pb n="10" facs="tcp:96238:8"/>
                     <l>Though my preſent condition muſt invite you to beleeve,
<stage>—<hi>looks on himſelf.</hi>
                        </stage>
                     </l>
                     <l>I have been rather not rewarded at all, then meanly.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Gripe.</speaker>
                     <l>Sir, it is beleeved. Pray proceed to your preſent buſineſſe</l>
                     <l>Now in hand.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Albin.</speaker>
                     <l>I ſhall. And, to be ſhort, thus ſtands the caſe.</l>
                     <l>There is (and not far hence) a wanting Gentleman</l>
                     <l>Whoſe former rate of living being high, will eaſily be wrought</l>
                     <l>The only inſtrument to work our ends, his acquaintance</l>
                     <l>Being great with a young Gentleman hath long born</l>
                     <l>Armes againſt us; And one that onely truſts this</l>
                     <l>Gentleman with his abſconded living.</l>
                     <l>Now your promiſe that hee ſhall ſhare (of what your</l>
                     <l>Known Authoritie may eaſily wrack from him)</l>
                     <l>I'le ſtand engaged, makes him your creature.</l>
                     <l>A brace or two of thouſands will not be hurtfull,</l>
                     <l>And may be ſpared from twenty, which this my friend</l>
                     <l>Will make appear, not only that hee is worth,</l>
                     <l>But where it is.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Gripe.</speaker>
                     <l>Honeſtly ſpoken, very honeſtly ſpoken, and to he purpoſe,</l>
                     <l>Home to the purpoſe. And let mee tell you, you need</l>
                     <l>Not doubt, but that your care, and wiſely managing a buſineſſe</l>
                     <l>So much concernes the generall Good, ſhall largely be</l>
                     <l>Rewarded beyond your expectation;</l>
                     <l>Beleeve it honeſt Gentleman it ſhall.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Albin.</speaker>
                     <l>Sir, I doubt it not. But for my friend, when hee hath</l>
                     <l>Diſcovered what wee can wiſh to know,</l>
                     <l>Wee'l hold him to't.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Gripe.</speaker>
                     <p>Right, right, our ſhares will mount the higher.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Albin.</speaker>
                     <l>The reſt I have to ſay, is, That I could wiſh,</l>
                     <l>And heartily, you would delay no time in being known</l>
                     <l>To this ſame Gentleman. Your ſummons ſhall procure</l>
                     <l>His preſence here, or where elſe you pleaſe, at two</l>
                     <l>Houres warning. Though (if my poor advice may ſtand)</l>
                     <l>I think your houſe the only place.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Gripe.</speaker>
                     <l>By any means my houſe, Sir. And let mee intreat you</l>
                     <l>Make it yours, and your friends. Faith, what think you</l>
                     <l>Of a piece of Beef, and bring your friend?</l>
                     <l>Come, come, you ſhall dine with mee to day. <hi>Clarathea, Clarathea,</hi>
                        <stage>—<hi>hee calls.</hi>
                        </stage>
                     </l>
                     <l>Fetch mee a pinte of ſack, and call <hi>Leteſia</hi> in.—</l>
                     <stage>Enter <hi>Clarathea.</hi>
                     </stage>
                     <l>That baggage will have the green ſickneſſe,</l>
                     <l>Shee's ſpoil'd for want of exerciſe.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Clarath.</speaker>
                     <p>Sir, will you have a whole pinte?</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Gripe.</speaker>
                     <p>No words be gone, I ſay a whole pinte.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Clarath.</speaker>
                     <p>Miraculous! hee is not long lived ſure.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <stage>Ex. Clarath.</stage>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Albin.</speaker>
                     <l>Well Sir, ſince you will have it ſo, I have conſidered,</l>
                     <l>Wee'l be your gueſt.—</l>
                     <stage>Enter <hi>Leteſia.</hi>
                     </stage>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Gripe.</speaker>
                     <l>And welcom, heartily welcom honeſt Gentleman.</l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Leteſia,</hi> take ſpecial notice of this Gentleman and his friend, that when they come,</l>
                     <pb n="11" facs="tcp:96238:8"/>
                     <l>You bid them welcom, as my poor houſe can make them,</l>
                     <l>They will deſerve your acquaintance and reſpect.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Leteſ.</speaker>
                     <l>Sir, your commands, and their deſert will merit much more</l>
                     <l>Then I can be ſerviceable in. But, to my power, I'le labour to deſerve</l>
                     <l>From both forgiveneſſe.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Albin.</speaker>
                     <l>Such Angels of light, are onely capable of forgiving</l>
                     <l>What wee poor mortals treſpaſs.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Gripe.</speaker>
                     <p>No more, no more: Beſhrow mee Sir, this ſavours of the Court.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Albin.</speaker>
                     <l>Pray Sir, let your charitie extend ſo far, to credit mee,</l>
                     <l>I hated much that Idol.—</l>
                     <stage>Enter <hi>Clarathea with wine.</hi>
                     </stage>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Gripe.</speaker>
                     <l>Well ſaid wench, Fill, fill.</l>
                     <l>Sir, here's to you, and your noble friend.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Albin.</speaker>
                     <l>Thank you, worthy Sir.</l>
                     <l>Health to you. Faireſt Miſtris.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Leteſ.</speaker>
                     <p>Your ſervant, Sir.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Albin.</speaker>
                     <p>Lady, you cannot drink.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Gripe.</speaker>
                     <l>Shee is a very pingler, a very pingler.</l>
                     <l>Come Sir, t'other cup to you.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Albin.</speaker>
                     <l>Thank you Generous Sir.
<stage>—<hi>Drinks.</hi>
                        </stage>
                     </l>
                     <l>Verily it is more of the creature, then I have</l>
                     <l>So liberally taſted (in a fore-noon)</l>
                     <l>This ſanctified ten years.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Gripe.</speaker>
                     <l>Sir, time (at preſent) is pretious with mee, having a very</l>
                     <l>Great influence on the affairs of this Country,</l>
                     <l>And muſt take leave, but ſhall not fail you at the hour of twelve.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Albin.</speaker>
                     <l>Till when, I humbly take my leave.</l>
                     <l>Fair Miſtris, your faithfull ſervant.—</l>
                  </sp>
                  <stage>Ex. Albin.</stage>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Gripe.</speaker>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Leteſia.</hi> I have invited this Gentleman and his friend</l>
                     <l>To dine with mee to day, let us have ſome things extraordinarie,</l>
                     <l>'Twill not be loſt: ſo good morrow, Girle.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <stage>Ex. Gripe.</stage>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Leteſ.</speaker>
                     <l>I do beleeve ſo: you ſeldom do invite thoſe you looſe by.</l>
                     <l>You Powers above! lay not your heavy judgments on a feeble</l>
                     <l>Maid for het fathers ſins; For I much ſear the crooked</l>
                     <l>Paths hee treads, portend our houſe no good.</l>
                     <l>Juſt Powers! protect the innocent.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <stage>Exit Leteſia.</stage>
                  <stage>Enter <hi>Adraſtus, Symphronio, Mettle, Drawer,</hi> as in a Tavern.</stage>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Draw.</speaker>
                     <p>What wine is it, Gentlemen?</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Symph.</speaker>
                     <p>Your beſt Canarie.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Draw.</speaker>
                     <p>I'le draw you a pinte of the beſt ith' town, Sir</p>
                  </sp>
                  <stage>Ex. Drawer.</stage>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Symph.</speaker>
                     <p>
                        <hi>Adraſtus,</hi> what is't a clock by your watch?</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Adraſt.</speaker>
                     <l>'Tis ſomewhat more then nine.
<stage>—<hi>looks in his watch.</hi>
                        </stage>
                     </l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Albinus</hi> promiſed to be here before noon.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Symph.</speaker>
                     <l>My life on't, that hee'l perform. And were you not</l>
                     <l>Acquainted with his change of habit, I am confident</l>
                     <l>You would not know him.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Adraſt.</speaker>
                     <p>Is hee ſo metamorphoſed?</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Symph.</speaker>
                     <l>As e're man was: Hee looks ſo like a factious Brother,</l>
                     <pb n="12" facs="tcp:96238:9"/>
                     <l>That the Synod, though utterly againſt any enjoying</l>
                     <l>Pluralities but themſelves, could not leſſe beſtow upon him</l>
                     <l>Then three Benefices.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Adrast.</speaker>
                     <p>'Twere rare ſport to be a ſpectator how hee behaves himſelf.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Symph.</speaker>
                     <p>Wee ſhall have that at large when he returns.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <stage>Enter <hi>Drawer</hi> with wine.</stage>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Draw.</speaker>
                     <p>Sir, there is one below deſires to ſpeak with you.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Adraſt.</speaker>
                     <p>Why didſt not bid him come up?</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Draw.</speaker>
                     <l>Faith (Sir!) hee looks ſo like a factious Brother,</l>
                     <l>I thought you'd be offended.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Adraſt.</speaker>
                     <p>Go, prethee bid him come up.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <stage>Exit Drawer.</stage>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Symph.</speaker>
                     <l>'Tis hee; wee muſt take no notice who hee is</l>
                     <l>Before the <hi>Drawer.</hi>
                     </l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Adraſt.</speaker>
                     <p>By no means.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <stage>Enter <hi>Albinus</hi> and <hi>Drawer.</hi>
                  </stage>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Albin.</speaker>
                     <p>Save you, Gentlemen.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Adraſt.</speaker>
                     <l>You are welcom, Sir! I am glad to ſee you well.</l>
                     <l>Pray ſit down. <hi>Drawer,</hi> reach a chair.</l>
                     <l>And how doth our noble friend?
<stage>Drawer is call'd without.</stage>
                     </l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Draw.</speaker>
                     <p>I come, I come; Anon, anon, Sir.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <stage>Ex. Drawer.</stage>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Albin.</speaker>
                     <l>In perfect health; And how, and how, Gentlemen?</l>
                     <l>Faith, how do you like my ſhape?</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Adraſt.</speaker>
                     <p>I hardly can beleeve that thou can'ſt be <hi>Albinus.</hi>
                     </p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Albin.</speaker>
                     <l>Very likely; nor that you are (this day) to dine with <hi>Leteſia</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>Your fair Miſtris.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Adraſt.</speaker>
                     <p>Yes; that I ſhall be to dine with her I doubt not.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Albin.</speaker>
                     <l>Thou man of little faith.</l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Mettle,</hi> fill mee a glaſſe of ſack.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Mett.</speaker>
                     <p>Here (Sir!) here's wine.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Albin.</speaker>
                     <l>Here <hi>Symphronio,</hi> here's to <hi>Hollands</hi> Maſter-piece.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Adraſt.</speaker>
                     <p>You are very merry <hi>Albinus.</hi>
                     </p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Albin.</speaker>
                     <l>And ſo may you be if you pleaſe,</l>
                     <l>I am ſure you have cauſe enough.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Adraſt.</speaker>
                     <p>Prethee Mad-cap be ſerious, Didſt thou ſee her?</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Albin.</speaker>
                     <l>Yes, by this fleſh and blood did I, and feel her too;</l>
                     <l>Had I not loved thee well, I had become my own petitioner</l>
                     <l>And deceived thy truſt.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Adraſt.</speaker>
                     <l>Dear <hi>Albinus,</hi> be ſerious; And let mee know</l>
                     <l>The event of thy proceedings.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Albin.</speaker>
                     <l>Mark then, and rejoice, for by our friendſhip</l>
                     <l>I'le utter nought but truth.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Adraſt.</speaker>
                     <p>Then I beleeve thee; Prethee proceed.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Albin.</speaker>
                     <l>Then thus: This morning early (as well <hi>Symphrenio</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>Can witneſſe) I parted with him. And as hee directed,</l>
                     <l>Towards <hi>Gripe-mans</hi> houſe I ſteered my courſe.</l>
                     <l>Where when arrived, and knocking at the door,</l>
                     <l>There comes a wench, demanding what my buſineſſe was.</l>
                     <l>I, in a zealous tone (as if I had worn my own clothes)</l>
                     <pb n="13" facs="tcp:96238:9"/>
                     <l>Told her, I deſired to ſpeak with her Maſter; (whoſe condition,</l>
                     <l>I had ever a pinte of wine with a poor botcher, his neer</l>
                     <l>Neighbour, ſufficiently enquired) ſhe intreated mee come in,</l>
                     <l>Telling mee, her Maſter (ſhee thought) was ready, but not</l>
                     <l>Come down. Away ſhee went, and no ſooner gone,</l>
                     <l>But down comes a bad father (for ſo I am given to underſtand)</l>
                     <l>To a moſt virtuous childe. I told him I had a buſineſſe</l>
                     <l>To impart that much concerned him. Hee immediately</l>
                     <l>Had mee into a handſom parlor, where I was bleſt</l>
                     <l>With a ſight of (I muſt confeſſe) your beauteous Miſtris;</l>
                     <l>(If e're my eyes beheld one) her father commanded his</l>
                     <l>Daughter and Maid-ſervant forth the room, which they</l>
                     <l>Obediently obeying, I began my ſtory, which as wee go</l>
                     <l>I'le tell you; for dine with him this day, I have engaged my ſelf you ſhall.</l>
                     <l>And this, dear friend, is truth.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Adraſt.</speaker>
                     <l>I know not how to husband this poor life I hold</l>
                     <l>To make thee ſatisfaction.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Albin.</speaker>
                     <p>Nay, if you complement, I'le diſ-engage my ſelf again.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Adraſt.</speaker>
                     <l>Thou know'ſt with thee I cannot.</l>
                     <l>Come, wee'l knock off, and all go to my chamber.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Albin.</speaker>
                     <l>Where you muſt ſmug your ſelf up for your encounter.</l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Mettle,</hi> wee muſt not forget three of clock this afternoon,</l>
                     <l>The whore muſt be remembred.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Mett.</speaker>
                     <p>And the rogue too, or I am much miſtaken.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Adrast.</speaker>
                     <p>
                        <hi>Mettle,</hi> pay you the reckoning; Come, let's go.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Mett.</speaker>
                     <p>I ſhall Sir. —</p>
                  </sp>
                  <stage>Ex. Omnes.</stage>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div n="2" type="act">
               <head>ACT II.</head>
               <div n="1" type="scene">
                  <head>SCENE I.</head>
                  <stage>Enter <hi>Gripe-man, Adraſtus, Albinus,</hi> and <hi>Leteſia,</hi> as from dinner.</stage>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Adraſt.</speaker>
                     <l>SIr, wee thank you for your noble entertainment, and ſhall as men</l>
                     <l>You highly have obliged (to the uttermoſt of our poor power)</l>
                     <l>Faithfully ſerve you.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Gripe.</speaker>
                     <l>Gentlemen, you are heartily welcom to ſuch poor fare you have found.</l>
                     <l>And what was amiſſe to day, <hi>Leteſia,</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>Pray let it be your care next time to mend.</l>
                     <l>For (Gentlemen!) I ſhall expect you'l be my daily Gueſts.</l>
                     <l>Sir, pray a word with you. —</l>
                     <stage>Gripe. Albin. whiſper aſide<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
                     </stage>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Adrast.</speaker>
                     <l>Sir, wee humbly thank you, and reſt your gratefull ſervants.</l>
                     <l>Lady, content; wait on your fair ſoul.</l>
                     <l>May I deſerve the honoured title of your ſervant.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Leteſ.</speaker>
                     <l>Sir, I want a judgment to pay deſert, yet never hated</l>
                     <l>Where I ne're found any.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Albin.</speaker>
                     <l>Sir, be confident I ſhall not fail (ſpeedily)</l>
                     <l>To put it in execution.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Gripe.</speaker>
                     <p>I doubt it not.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <pb n="14" facs="tcp:96238:10"/>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Adraſt.</speaker>
                     <l>Lady, the gratefull'ſt of your poor ſervants kiſſes your hand,</l>
                     <l>And humbly takes his leave.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Leteſ.</speaker>
                     <l>Your ſervant, Sir. —</l>
                     <stage>Ex. Gripe. Adraſt. Alb.</stage>
                     <l>'Tis hee: You juſt Powers! that have vouchſafe't</l>
                     <l>To hear the poor petitions of a diſtreſſed Virgin,</l>
                     <l>Be ſtill aſſiſting the humbleſt of your hand-maids.</l>
                     <l>What ſhould his buſineſſe with my father be?</l>
                     <l>There muſt be ſtrange pretences of large profit in it,</l>
                     <l>They hardly elſe ſhould be invited here.</l>
                     <l>My youth, and unexperience I have in <hi>Cupid</hi>'s ſchool,</l>
                     <l>Puts me in doubt of what I fane would credit.</l>
                     <l>I do confeſſe (I bluſh to ſpeak the reſt) I eyed him more then</l>
                     <l>Became my modeſty to do; (I hope hee thought not ſo)</l>
                     <l>And if I not miſtake, his looks betrayed much more of love</l>
                     <l>Then buſineſſe with my father. Yes, yes, it muſt be ſo,</l>
                     <l>And yet it may be otherwaies. Suppoſe (which <hi>Venus</hi> grant hee may)</l>
                     <l>Hee love mee (if it be poſſible) as well as I love him,</l>
                     <l>The hopes I have to enjoy him with conſent of my father, is ſo little,</l>
                     <l>Deſpair awaits that thought.</l>
                     <l>His looks ſpeaks too much of honeſty to be rich enough, (as times go now)</l>
                     <l>For his conſent, No, no, <hi>Loteſia,</hi> it muſt be one dares lift his hand</l>
                     <l>Againſt his ſacred Prince, (which ſure hee dares not do)</l>
                     <l>And by ſiniſter waies hoard up unlawfull Wealth,</l>
                     <l>Muſt (by my fathers choice) be made my Bridegroom.</l>
                     <l>But I'le aſſoon imbrace a Leper,</l>
                     <l>As tye my ſelf to what my ſoul abhorres.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <stage>Enter <hi>Clarathea.</hi>
                  </stage>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Clarath.</speaker>
                     <l>What meditating, Miſtris, who your noble Gueſt ſhould be,</l>
                     <l>You din'd with all to day?</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Leteſ.</speaker>
                     <l>That requires but ſmall ſtudy;</l>
                     <l>They are men that come 'bout buſineſſe to my father.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Clarath.</speaker>
                     <p>My maiden-head upon it, you will not finde it ſo.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Leteſ.</speaker>
                     <p>Why do'ſt thou laugh?</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Clarath.</speaker>
                     <p>To think how you miſtake.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Leteſ.</speaker>
                     <p>Prethee, unfold thy riddles, and let mee know thy thoughts.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Clarath.</speaker>
                     <l>Cannot you call to minde, you e're did ſee one</l>
                     <l>Or both of them before?</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Leteſ.</speaker>
                     <p>Never to my beſt of knowledge.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Clarath.</speaker>
                     <l>Why then I can aſſure you theſe are the very Gentlemen</l>
                     <l>Wee ſawith' Change the one of which enquired of mee</l>
                     <l>Your name and dwelling.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Leteſ.</speaker>
                     <p>That cannot be, they were all Gentlemen.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Clarath.</speaker>
                     <l>If you examine ſtrictly, ſo you'l finde theſe to be.</l>
                     <l>For know, hee that wee took to be the pitifull holy brother,</l>
                     <l>Is, in diſguiſe, the Gentleman enquired of mee for you.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Leteſ.</speaker>
                     <p>It is impoſſible.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Clarath.</speaker>
                     <p>'Tis ſo; That I ſhould be miſtaken.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Leteſ.</speaker>
                     <p>What ſhould this mean, <hi>Clarathea?</hi> Canſt thou gueſſe?</p>
                  </sp>
                  <pb n="15" facs="tcp:96238:10"/>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Clarath.</speaker>
                     <l>Yes, that one (for both I cannot think)</l>
                     <l>Would fain make love to you.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Leteſ.</speaker>
                     <l>What e're it be (dear wench!) keep ſecret,</l>
                     <l>Till time reveal the event.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Clarath.</speaker>
                     <l>Be confident of mee; for when <hi>Clarathea</hi> ſhall betray</l>
                     <l>Your truſt, may ſhee live neglected,</l>
                     <l>And dye forgotten. —</l>
                  </sp>
                  <stage>Ex. Leteſ. Clarath.</stage>
                  <stage>Enter <hi>Adraſt. Symphr.</hi> as in a Tavern.</stage>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Adraſt.</speaker>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Symphronio,</hi> Your haſte hath brought us hither an hour</l>
                     <l>Before our time, and 'tis too ſoon to drink</l>
                     <l>After ſo full a meal.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Symph.</speaker>
                     <l>'Twas well conſidered; Let mee alone to drive away ſome</l>
                     <l>Time without the help of Sack.</l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Mettle</hi> hath perfectly got the part I gave him (if the</l>
                     <l>Bulls pizill put him not out)</l>
                     <l>And I have mine <hi>ex tempore.</hi>
                     </l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Adrast.</speaker>
                     <p>Doth the Rogue know hee ſhall be baſted?</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Symph.</speaker>
                     <l>Gently, hee doe's: But I am reſolved to try his utmoſt</l>
                     <l>Patience; ſee here, they are come. —</l>
                  </sp>
                  <stage>Enter <hi>Albin. and Mettle.</hi>
                  </stage>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Albinus,</speaker>
                     <l>wee are reſolved</l>
                     <l>(Not knowing how wee may be encountred</l>
                     <l>When our expected company arrives) to paſs by drinking</l>
                     <l>For half an hour. <hi>Mettle,</hi> you are perfect in the part I gave you:</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Mett.</speaker>
                     <l>Sir, I have not con'd this three dayes, yet</l>
                     <l>Dare prefume I am perfect.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Symph.</speaker>
                     <p>Well, look to't, you know your forfeit, if you but miſs a word.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Mett.</speaker>
                     <p>If you are ready, come what will, I'le run the hazzard.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Albin.</speaker>
                     <p>But where are your properties?</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Mett.</speaker>
                     <p>For thoſe, I ſhall furniſh my ſelf below. —</p>
                  </sp>
                  <stage>Ex. Mettle.</stage>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Albin.</speaker>
                     <l>Pox on't, I ſhall ne're hold out without ſome drink.</l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Drawer!</hi>
                     </l>
                  </sp>
                  <stage>Enter <hi>Drawer.</hi>
                  </stage>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Draw.</speaker>
                     <p>Here, Sir.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Albin.</speaker>
                     <p>Sirrah, fetch us a quart of ſack. —</p>
                  </sp>
                  <stage>Enter <hi>Mettle with a black gown, and pen, ink, paper, and books.</hi>
                  </stage>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Adraſt.</speaker>
                     <l>Here's <hi>Mettle.</hi> Prethee <hi>Albinus</hi> forbear your ſack,</l>
                     <l>They'l ſoon diſpatch the Scene.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Albin.</speaker>
                     <p>Well ſirrah, let the ſack alone till wee call.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Draw.</speaker>
                     <p>I ſhall, Sir.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <stage>Ex. Drawer.</stage>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Albin.</speaker>
                     <p>Come, come to your ſport, prepare, prepare.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <stage>Aldraſt. Albin. ſeat themſelves. Mettle in an old black gown ſeats himſelf behinde a curtain, with ſome books, pen, ink, and paper before him, perſonating Phanaticus a Prieſt. Symphronio ſtanding behinde the hangings till his cue to Enter, perſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nating Fly-blow a Butcher. Mettle drawes the curtain, and turnes over ſome accounts.</stage>
                  <pb n="16" facs="tcp:96238:11"/>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Phanat.</speaker>
                     <l>Let mee ſee, let mee it, gotten this week by incomes</l>
                     <l>From Miſtris <hi>Dunce</hi> a Common-Council mans wife, — Three pounds, a gold Ring two ſilver ſpoons worth thirty ſeven ſhillings.</l>
                     <l>From Miſtris <hi>Zeal</hi> widdow, — forty ſhillings.</l>
                     <l>From Miſtris <hi>Tartwit</hi> a Cooks wife, — three pounds.</l>
                     <l>From Miſtris <hi>Fat</hi> a Tanners wife, — fifty ſhillings.</l>
                     <l>From Miſtris <hi>Phime</hi> Feather-woman and widdow, — one pound ten.</l>
                     <l>From Miſtris <hi>Greaſe</hi> a Tallow-chandlers wife, — one pound two.</l>
                     <l>From Miſtris <hi>Error</hi> widdow, — forty ſhillings.</l>
                     <l>From Miſtris <hi>Extortion</hi> a Broakers wife, — Taſtetie to line a cloak.</l>
                     <l>From Goodwife <hi>Shuttle</hi> a gifted Weavers wife, — two fat Geeſe.</l>
                     <l>From Miſtris <hi>Fly-blow</hi> a Butchers wife— a filver bowle worth three pounds.</l>
                     <l>Why here is nineteen pound, nineteen ſhillings got with much eaſe.</l>
                     <l>How willing theſe poor ſoules, in body, and in purſe,</l>
                     <l>Are to contribute to the Elect!</l>
                     <l>For (to ſay truth) wee are choſen, but 'tis to cozen them.</l>
                     <l>I muſt abſcond: My ſpiritual exerciſe grows too laborious.</l>
                     <l>O for a Corniſh Curate from beyond ſea, to officiate in my</l>
                     <l>Abſence but for one moneth!</l>
                     <l>Would they forbear mee on the ſeventh day, I ſhould rub out</l>
                     <l>Much longer, and pleaſe much higher on the week dayes.</l>
                     <l>But to ſtand two hours ſpending (to no purpoſe) is too much.</l>
                     <stage>Symphronio perſonating Fly-blow, knocks at Phanatious his door.</stage>
                     <l>Who's there? Upon my life another client.</l>
                     <l>A Greek or Hebrew book diſplayed doe's well.
<stage>ſpreads open ſome books.</stage>
                     </l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Fly.</speaker>
                     <p>Here's one deſires admittance to you.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Phanat.</speaker>
                     <p>Who would you ſpeak withall?</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Fly.</speaker>
                     <p>With your reverend ſelf, divine Sir.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Phanat.</speaker>
                     <l>O hee is right, hoe is right.
<stage>—<hi>opens the door, Fly blow enters.</hi>
                        </stage>
                     </l>
                     <l>Come in, Friend.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Fly.</speaker>
                     <p>Save you, holy man.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Phanat.</speaker>
                     <p>You alſo: What may your buſineſſe be?</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Fly.</speaker>
                     <p>A ſcruple Sir of conſcience, I fain would be deſolved in.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Phanat.</speaker>
                     <p>Reſolved, you would ſay, friend.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Fly.</speaker>
                     <p>'Tis very right, reſolved I fain would be.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Phanat.</speaker>
                     <l>Time with the Elect is pretious, but to ſuch good works</l>
                     <l>As theſe wee are called; Friend, open your caſe.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Fly.</speaker>
                     <l>Sir, I am poor but however have brought that with mee,</l>
                     <l>That ſhall ſhow I am willing (to my utmoſt ſtrength,</l>
                     <l>And abilitie) to give you ſatisfaction for your pains.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Phanat.</speaker>
                     <l>Honeſtly ſpoken, very honeſtly ſpoken,</l>
                     <l>And conſcientiouſly; pray begin.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Fly.</speaker>
                     <l>Then thus I ſhall diſcover my ſecrets to you.</l>
                     <l>I finde my ſelf (of late) much given to rebellion,</l>
                     <l>Towards a poor woman, yet, young and luſtie.</l>
                     <l>A neighbours wiſe of mine, who (I fear) if I enjoy,</l>
                     <l>Will lye very heavy on mee.</l>
                     <pb n="17" facs="tcp:96238:11"/>
                     <l>Now, Sir, I have endeavoured to become a true</l>
                     <l>Subject to my ſelf, but finding my endeavours no way prevalent,</l>
                     <l>I ſhall deſire to be reſolved, how farre</l>
                     <l>Your diſpenſation (ſhee being none of the Elect)</l>
                     <l>Will extend towards the ſatisfying our venial deſires,</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Phanat.</speaker>
                     <p>How far inclinable to your deſires finde you our Siſter?</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Fly.</speaker>
                     <p>Verily Sir, comfortably enclining.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Phanat.</speaker>
                     <p>Is her husband of able body for the procreation of the Elect?</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Fly.</speaker>
                     <l>That caſe is doubtfull, and much to be fear'd,</l>
                     <l>Hee having known her this two year and upward</l>
                     <l>Without fruit thereof;</l>
                     <l>The woman having ever been laboriouſly endeavouring.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Phanat.</speaker>
                     <l>Brother, enough, enough, I ſay.</l>
                     <l>I have with attention heard you; and ſhall (as conſidering</l>
                     <l>It my own caſe) inſtruct you for your beſt advantage</l>
                     <l>Both of ſoul and body.</l>
                     <l>As for your rebellion, if your cauſe be wholeſomly</l>
                     <l>Advantagious to your profit, you may rebell,</l>
                     <l>As many others, and my ſelf (at preſent) do.</l>
                     <l>But ſo to rebell, as of neceſſitie muſt be prejudiciall to you</l>
                     <l>(Our ſiſter being impoveriſh't) I ſhall adviſe you to take</l>
                     <l>This comfortable admonition from mee, which is,</l>
                     <l>That you put on the Armour of Providence,</l>
                     <l>And cleave to a more beneficiall ſiſter.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Fly.</speaker>
                     <l>Divine Sir, I thank you; and do begin to finde your</l>
                     <l>Wholſom and comfortable admonition effectually to operate.</l>
                     <l>And that you may perceive, I came not altogether unfurniſh't</l>
                     <l>With what, I hope, ſhall (in ſome reaſonable meaſure)</l>
                     <l>Satisfie you.
<stage>—<hi>Fly. layes off his cloak and diſcovers a Bulls pizil.</hi>
                        </stage>
                     </l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Phanat.</speaker>
                     <p>Good Sir, I doubt it not.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Fly.</speaker>
                     <l>You ſhall not need; Behold this ell of mettle,
<stage>—<hi>advanoeth his pizil.</hi>
                        </stage>
                     </l>
                     <l>'Tis a good one: the Bull it once belong'd to</l>
                     <l>Coſt mee eight pounds.</l>
                     <l>Marry, I ſhall give nine for yours, if you waſte it not</l>
                     <l>Too much in the ſervice of the Elect.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Phanat.</speaker>
                     <p>Sir, what's your meaning?</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Fly.</speaker>
                     <l>That you ſhall ſoon diſcover.</l>
                     <l>Now hear mee with attention:</l>
                     <l>Thou Metropolitan Imp of Satan, Monſter of mankinde,</l>
                     <l>Thou compound of Fornication and Adultery.</l>
                     <l>Nay, nay, ſtir not, nor let nothing of noiſe come from</l>
                     <l>Thy perjur'd tongue, which know can mollifie as much as tears can rocks.</l>
                     <l>Now, in a ſoftly tone, anſwer mee (if it be poſſible) nothing but truth</l>
                     <l>(A thing by thee rarely uttered) to what I ſhall demand.</l>
                     <l>You know one <hi>Fly-blow</hi> a Butchers wife.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Phanat.</speaker>
                     <p>
                        <hi>Fly-blow,</hi> Sir?</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Fly.</speaker>
                     <l>Yes, <hi>Fly-blow</hi> Sir. Know, wretched miſcreant, ſhee hath diſcovered</l>
                     <l>Thy black ſoul to mee; and ſhould'ſt thou but utter one</l>
                     <pb n="18" facs="tcp:96238:12"/>
                     <l>Falſe ſyllable to thoſe known truths I ſhall ask from thee,</l>
                     <l>By all the Gods, I'le adde to my intended fury, and geld thee.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Phanat.</speaker>
                     <l>Forbid, you Powers, geld mee; I am undone then.</l>
                     <l>Sir, I ſhall confeſſe any I know, you pleaſe to ask mee.</l>
                     <l>Good Sir, be merciful. Geld mee.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Fly.</speaker>
                     <l>If truth ſo long forgotten by thee can be again remembred,</l>
                     <l>You may be mercifull to your ſelf, and ſave your Dowcets.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Phanat.</speaker>
                     <l>Thank you, good Sir; and be confident, what you ſhall</l>
                     <l>Pleaſe demand within the power of my utmoſt knowledg,</l>
                     <l>You fully ſhall be ſatisfied.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Fly.</speaker>
                     <l>Then to the purpoſe: How long have you been acquainted</l>
                     <l>With Miſtris <hi>Flye-blow?</hi>
                     </l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Phanat.</speaker>
                     <p>Verily, I ſhall moſt punctually reſolve you.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Fly.</speaker>
                     <l>Sirrah, anſwer me not in that ſniv'ling tone</l>
                     <l>You cheat the world with.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Phanat.</speaker>
                     <l>Why, Sir, it is ſome eight weeks and odd dayes</l>
                     <l>Since firſt I did enjoy her.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Fly.</speaker>
                     <p>Villain, did you enjoy her then?</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Phanat.</speaker>
                     <l>Pardon mee Sir, I mean no otherwaies then</l>
                     <l>The ſanctified company of a zealous ſiſter.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Fly.</speaker>
                     <l>Alter that tone (I ſay) or I ſhall whet
<stage>—<hi>pulls out his knife, and offers to whet it at his ſteel hangs by his ſide.</hi>
                        </stage>
                     </l>
                     <l>You underſtand the reſt.</l>
                     <l>Sirrah, be ſhort; what money, and monies worth have you had</l>
                     <l>Of her? For Villain, know, that miſled</l>
                     <l>Woman is my wife.
<stage>Phanaticus ſtarts.</stage>
                     </l>
                     <l>What do you ſtart? (I muſt confeſſe, I bluſh to own her)</l>
                     <l>Come, be brief, and to a penny ſatisfie my demand,</l>
                     <l>Or you grow fat, and ſing well.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Phanat.</speaker>
                     <l>I underſtand you, Sir, and ſhall caſt it up to a penny.</l>
                     <l>Let mee ſee, my book will tell mee; let mee ſee,
<stage>—<hi>turns over his book of accounts.</hi>
                        </stage>
                     </l>
                     <l>The eleventh of Auguſt laſt, —twenty ſhillings.</l>
                     <l>Auguſt the eighteenth, —ten ſhillings.</l>
                     <l>The ſecond of September, —forty ſhillings.</l>
                     <l>The fourteenth of the ſame Moneth,— twenty ſhillings.</l>
                     <l>The firſt of October, —A ſilver bowle, to the value of three pounds.</l>
                     <l>This is to a penny, what ſhee hath been pleaſed to beſtow.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Fly.</speaker>
                     <p>And upon what tearmes did you receive it?</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Phanat.</speaker>
                     <l>Meerly her charitie, for good</l>
                     <l>And wholeſom admonition.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Fly.</speaker>
                     <l>Indeed ſuch admonition requires conſideration,</l>
                     <l>Which you ſhall have. Come, come, depoſit</l>
                     <l>What with your Mountebanck tricks</l>
                     <l>You have juggled from her.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Phanat.</speaker>
                     <l>No conſideration, Sir, for the paines</l>
                     <l>I have taken with your wife.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Fly.</speaker>
                     <l>For that, let me conſider—yes, I have thought</l>
                     <l>Of ſome valuable conſideration, worthy your care and paines,</l>
                     <pb n="19" facs="tcp:96238:12"/>
                     <l>But you muſt ſtand to my courteſie,</l>
                     <l>The bowle and money being tendered mee.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Phanat.</speaker>
                     <p>I thank you, Sir, moſt kindely.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Fly.</speaker>
                     <l>Nay, nay, for that, let it alone,</l>
                     <l>Till you ſee what I ſhall deſerve.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Phanat.</speaker>
                     <p>Here is to a penny, Sir, what I have received of her.
<stage>—<hi>Phanat. takes out of a desk the bowle and money.</hi>
                        </stage>
                     </p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Fly.</speaker>
                     <l>Now, Sir, how ever you have plaid the knave</l>
                     <l>By deluding my wife, you ſhall be ſure</l>
                     <l>To finde mee a man of my word.
<stage>—<hi>Fly-blow beats the Prieſt egregiouſly with a Bulls pizil.</hi>
                        </stage>
                     </l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Phanat.</speaker>
                     <l>Hold Sir, if you be a man, conſider, and be mercifull;</l>
                     <l>Good Sir, conſider my Coat.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Fly.</speaker>
                     <l>'Twas well remembred; I ſhall, I ſhall, and lay it on ſo much</l>
                     <l>The harder, you may feel the better through it.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Phanat.</speaker>
                     <l>O Sir! draw in your pizil, (if you be a man) and ſpare mee</l>
                     <l>Till the next Lords day is paſt, or I ſhall be unable</l>
                     <l>To ſcatter the ſanctified ſeed of Reformation into the bowels</l>
                     <l>Of our dear Siſter-hood.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Fly.</speaker>
                     <l>Their reverent hearing, and your inſtructions</l>
                     <l>Claimes good places in hell.</l>
                     <l>Sirrah, give thanks I am out of breath; Farwell.</l>
                     <l>Cheat mee once more, I'le ſend thee home to hell—.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <stage>Ex. Fly-blow.</stage>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Phanat.</speaker>
                     <l>I do beleeve you; A plague go with you, and your pizil.</l>
                     <l>The Rogue hath made jelly of mee.</l>
                     <l>Complain of this, I dare not for my credit, which, I muſt more</l>
                     <l>For my profit, then my conſcience value.</l>
                     <l>This muſt not unreveng'd go thus,</l>
                     <l>The ſlave is honeſt, that claws enough for mee</l>
                     <l>To ruine him, and his whole family.
<stage>—<hi>Mettle pulls off his gown in great fury.</hi>
                        </stage>
                     </l>
                  </sp>
                  <stage>Enter <hi>Symphronto.</hi>
                  </stage>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Albin.</speaker>
                     <l>How now, <hi>Mettle?</hi> This was but a rehearſal,</l>
                     <l>When is your reall day of performance.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Mett.</speaker>
                     <l>Zwounds, I know not what jeſt there was on my ſide,</l>
                     <l>But I have all the reaſon in the world to beleeve</l>
                     <l>Hee was in earneſt.</l>
                     <l>You ſhall excuſe mee for acting the ſinner again in jeſt.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Symph.</speaker>
                     <l>Indeed thy naturall doing of it is in earneſt,</l>
                     <l>Though wee applaud thy ſufferings in jeſt.</l>
                     <l>But how? but how, i-faith <hi>Mettle?</hi> was it not ſmartly perform'd?</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Mett.</speaker>
                     <l>Yes, on my ſide, I'le beſworn.</l>
                     <l>A plague on't, my gown had no lining in't neither,</l>
                     <l>Which you ne're conſidered.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Symph.</speaker>
                     <p>Pox of a bad memory, I had ſpar'd thee elſe—.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <stage>Enter <hi>Drawer.</hi>
                  </stage>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Draw.</speaker>
                     <p>There is a Gentlewoman below enquires for you, <hi>Mettle.</hi>
                     </p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Mett.</speaker>
                     <p>Tell her I'le wait upon her ſtraight.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Albin.</speaker>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Drawer,</hi> bring up ſome of your beſt ſack.</l>
                     <l>Another Scene as long as this had choak't mee.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <pb n="20" facs="tcp:96238:13"/>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Draw.</speaker>
                     <p>I ſhall Sir. —</p>
                  </sp>
                  <stage>Exit Drawer.</stage>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Adraſt.</speaker>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Mettle,</hi> take your Lady into the next room,</l>
                     <l>And as you finde her tractable to your defignes, acquaint us.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Mett.</speaker>
                     <p>I ſhall Sir.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Symph.</speaker>
                     <l>Shee muſt have my aſſiſtance to perſwade her to it.</l>
                     <l>Come <hi>Mettle</hi> let's to her.—</l>
                  </sp>
                  <stage>Ex. Symph. and Mett.</stage>
                  <stage>Enter <hi>Drawer with wine.</hi>
                  </stage>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Albin.</speaker>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Drawer,</hi> fill mee a brimmer.</l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Adraſtus,</hi> here's to the fair <hi>Leteſin,</hi> earths richeſt Jewell.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Adraſt.</speaker>
                     <p>Too rich (I fear) for Mortals to enjoy.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Albin.</speaker>
                     <l>Such another deſperate word, and, by all the Gods, I'le court</l>
                     <l>Her for my ſelf, and hope to enjoy her too. And, I think, I look</l>
                     <l>As like a Mortal (in this ſhape) as any brother in town.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <stage>Enter <hi>Symph. Riggle,</hi> and <hi>Mettle.</hi>
                  </stage>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Symph.</speaker>
                     <p>Save you, Gallants. Pray bid this Lady welcom.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Albin.</speaker>
                     <l>I hope you ſpeak not in the plural number.</l>
                     <l>What think you, Lady, do I appear a Gallant?
<stage>—<hi>ſhowes his cloaths.</hi>
                        </stage>
                     </l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Rigg.</speaker>
                     <l>Sir, though it be a thing much given to people of my profeſſion</l>
                     <l>To pry into the habit of a man, I look into the minde</l>
                     <l>And nobler part, and where I finde moſt worth,</l>
                     <l>I there moſt honour.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Albin.</speaker>
                     <l>Spoke like the Queen of Amazons;</l>
                     <l>I muſt ſalute your judgment.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Rigg.</speaker>
                     <p>Sir, you miſtake, thoſe were my lips you kiſs't.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Albin.</speaker>
                     <l>Lady, my ambition was to come as neer</l>
                     <l>Your judgment as I could.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Adraſt.</speaker>
                     <l>Lady, your ſervant.
<stage>—<hi>ſalutes her.</hi>
                        </stage>
                     </l>
                     <l>Nay, pray ſit down.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Symphronio,</speaker>
                     <l>'twas well this</l>
                     <l>Gentlewoman had vertue enough to guard her,</l>
                     <l>I ſhould ſuſpect her being with you alone elſe.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Symph.</speaker>
                     <l>Make you no body of <hi>Mettle?</hi> Or do you think,</l>
                     <l>Becauſe hee pleaſures you ſometimes,</l>
                     <l>Hee'l pimp for all your friends?</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Adraſt.</speaker>
                     <p>What ſay you to this, <hi>Mettle?</hi>
                     </p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Mett.</speaker>
                     <p>I ſay, Sir, 'tis an office I never underſtood.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Rigg.</speaker>
                     <p>That's very ſtrange, truly.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Mett.</speaker>
                     <l>To you, I do beleeve it is; I think I had beſt take up</l>
                     <l>The next room againſt our Brother comes;</l>
                     <l>Hee muſt not know ſhee is in our company.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Albin.</speaker>
                     <l>By no means. Carry a pinte of wine into it,</l>
                     <l>As if ſhee call'd for it.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Mett.</speaker>
                     <p>I ſhall, Sir.—</p>
                  </sp>
                  <stage>Exit Mettle.</stage>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Rigg.</speaker>
                     <p>'Tis a pretious youth.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Albin.</speaker>
                     <p>Lady, Health to your deareſt ſervant.
<stage>—<hi>Drinks</hi>
                        </stage>
                     </p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Rigg.</speaker>
                     <p>Thank you, noble Sir. —</p>
                  </sp>
                  <stage>Enter <hi>Mettle.</hi>
                  </stage>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Mett.</speaker>
                     <p>I muſt have this pinte pot, hee is below already.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Symph.</speaker>
                     <l>Miſtris, pray go into the next room,</l>
                     <l>And act your part toth' life.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Rigg.</speaker>
                     <l>Let mee alone; hee is not the firſt knave</l>
                     <pb n="21" facs="tcp:96238:13"/>
                     <l>That I have made a fool of.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <stage>Ex. Rigg.</stage>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Albin.</speaker>
                     <l>Not by a brace of thouſands. Now will ſhee pick his pocket,</l>
                     <l>And hee lay fellony to our charge,</l>
                     <l>Then where lyes our ſcene of Mirth?</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Adraſt.</speaker>
                     <l>Faith, under the laſh. <hi>Symphronio,</hi> how do you</l>
                     <l>Like the Vermin you have had conference?</l>
                  </sp>
                  <stage>Enter <hi>Mettle.</hi>
                  </stage>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Mett.</speaker>
                     <l>They are together, the Rogue kiſs't,</l>
                     <l>You might have heard him hither.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Adraſt.</speaker>
                     <l>Gentlemen! what's your plot? as yet</l>
                     <l>I am a ſtranger to your deſign.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Symph.</speaker>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Mettle,</hi> and I have ſtudied that.</l>
                     <l>What 'tis, the event ſhall ſhow. But now you talk of plots,</l>
                     <l>How goes your buſineſſe forward?</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Albin.</speaker>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Adraſtus,</hi> art thou not a hungry?</l>
                     <l>Thou feed'ſt (to day) on nothing but thy Miſtris eyes,</l>
                     <l>And thoſe you fell upon without any grace.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Adraſt.</speaker>
                     <l>I do confeſſe</l>
                     <l>I hardly know what other food wee had; but as for grace,</l>
                     <l>The Gods ſend thee but half as much.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Albin.</speaker>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Symphronio,</hi> hee is now admitted.</l>
                     <l>Hee has got the Old mans good will.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Symph.</speaker>
                     <p>VVhat, to marry his Daughter?</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Albin.</speaker>
                     <l>Soft, and fair; there's ſomewhat more goes to getting his good will.</l>
                     <l>Hee hath free admittance to viſit his fair</l>
                     <l>Miſtris when hee pleaſes,</l>
                     <l>Marry, I beleeve, you might have had</l>
                     <l>Fathers, Mothers, and all the Kinns</l>
                     <l>Conſent beſides, (in a leſſe time) to have match't with your Lady</l>
                     <l>You parted with but now.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Symph.</speaker>
                     <l>Thou look'ſt like one that would</l>
                     <l>Have married us, had wee been both agreed.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <stage>Enter <hi>Mettle</hi> from peeping.</stage>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Mett.</speaker>
                     <l>The Rogue drinks like a fiſh, and ſhee plyes</l>
                     <l>Him with half pinte draughts; ſhee hath much ado</l>
                     <l>To keep his hands above board: the other cup will ripen him for your company,</l>
                     <l>Then 'tis my cue to Enter.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Adraſt.</speaker>
                     <p>VVill not the rogue be troubleſom?</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Albin.</speaker>
                     <l>Not long, if hee drink ſo faſt. And it</l>
                     <l>Shall be my care that hee ſhall want none here.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Adraſt.</speaker>
                     <p>
                        <hi>Mettle,</hi> how doth ſhee bear her drink?</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Mett.</speaker>
                     <l>Hang her, ſhee'l bear any thing is laid upon her.</l>
                     <l>Now will I enter.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <stage>Ex. Mettle.</stage>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Albin,</speaker>
                     <l>And wee prepare to entertain the ſlave with gravitie.</l>
                     <l>Is all contrived, <hi>Symphronio?</hi> VVhat puniſhment wee</l>
                     <l>Lay upon the Rogue? for ſomething wee muſt do worth his</l>
                     <l>Remembrance.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <stage>Enter <hi>Mettle.</hi>
                  </stage>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Symph.</speaker>
                     <p>It is, it is; all is contrived.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <pb n="22" facs="tcp:96238:14"/>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Mett.</speaker>
                     <l>She hath prevail'd upon the Babe of Grace.</l>
                     <l>And hee prepared to enter.—</l>
                  </sp>
                  <stage>Enter <hi>Sod. drunk: and Riggle.</hi>
                  </stage>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Rigg.</speaker>
                     <l>Come near, come near, good Coſin.</l>
                     <l>Here's none but are my ſpecial friends,</l>
                     <l>I can aſſure you.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Sod.</speaker>
                     <p>Save you, Gentlemen.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Albin.</speaker>
                     <l>You are moſt nobly welcom. <hi>Mettle,</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>A chair there for the Gentleman. Miſtris, pray ſit here.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Rigg.</speaker>
                     <l>Thank you, good friend: why, I had thought I had loſt you all.</l>
                     <l>I think I have not ſeen you, nor your friends here, theſe eight or nine dayes.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Mett.</speaker>
                     <p>This whore is got half drunk, and ſhee will do it rarely.
<stage>aſide.</stage>
                     </p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Symph.</speaker>
                     <l>Lady, 'tis true; but blame not us, but our occaſions, that enforc't us</l>
                     <l>To it: our buſineſſe now being over, wee'l be your daily viſitants.</l>
                     <l>Sir, a health to the greateſt honourer of this fair Ladies</l>
                     <l>Virtues.
<stage>—<hi>drinks to Sodom.</hi>
                        </stage>
                     </l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Rigg.</speaker>
                     <p>Coſin, the Gentleman drinks to you.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Sod.</speaker>
                     <p>Thank you, noble Sir.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Symph.</speaker>
                     <p>Help the Gentleman to ſome wine.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Mett.</speaker>
                     <p>Here Sir, pleaſe you drink.
<stage>gives Sodom wine.</stage>
                     </p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Sod.</speaker>
                     <p>Thank you, Sir; Lady, here's to you.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Albin.</speaker>
                     <p>Sir, ſhee ſhould have it laſt.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Sod.</speaker>
                     <l>Say you ſo? Then here's to you, Sir,</l>
                     <l>This fair Ladies ſervant.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Albin.</speaker>
                     <p>Thank you, Sir; <hi>Mettle,</hi> help the Gentleman.
<stage>Sodom drinks and falls down, they help him up, and laugh.</stage>
                     </p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Mett.</speaker>
                     <p>Help, help, the Gentleman is troubled with the falling ſickneſſe.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Adraſt.</speaker>
                     <p>How is it, Sir? chear up, all's well again.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Rigg,</speaker>
                     <l>How is it, Coſin? what, not well, ſweet heart?</l>
                     <l>Pray fetch him ſome ſtrong water.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Albin.</speaker>
                     <p>A pinte at leaſt. Courage, noble Sir; how is't?</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Sod.</speaker>
                     <p>Very well. Sir,—but that I have got the hey-cot.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Albin.</speaker>
                     <p>Your Coſin, Miſtris, is drunk.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Rigg.</speaker>
                     <p>I hope not ſo.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Sod.</speaker>
                     <l>Verily not drunk—I am—not drunk—I muſt</l>
                     <l>Confeſſe I—I—I have taſted liberally of the creature,</l>
                     <l>But you ſhall ſee—I am not drunk;</l>
                     <l>Here's to our Prince.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Adraſt.</speaker>
                     <p>How dares hee drink that health?</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Albin.</speaker>
                     <l>I thank you, Sir.</l>
                     <l>Hee dares (now) drink his health, hee dares not name</l>
                     <l>But to revile, when hee's ſober.</l>
                     <l>That's bravely done.
<stage>Sodom drinks.</stage>
                     </l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Sod.</speaker>
                     <p>You'l pledge mee, Sir?</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Albin.</speaker>
                     <l>That I will.</l>
                     <l>Here, Lady, here's to you.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Rigg.</speaker>
                     <p>Thanks, noble Sir.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <pb n="23" facs="tcp:96238:14"/>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Mett.</speaker>
                     <l>The beaſt ſleeps, the wine works rarely.</l>
                     <l>Shall I produce? The engine is in the next room.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Symph.</speaker>
                     <l>Come, bring't in, bring't in,</l>
                     <stage>Exit Mettle.</stage>
                     <l>'Twill cleanſe him better then a purge.</l>
                     <l>Sir, do you hear? do you hear?
<stage>joggs Sod.</stage>
                     </l>
                     <l>Come, come, hee is faſt.</l>
                     <stage>Enter <hi>Mettle with a blanket.</hi>
                     </stage>
                     <l>Gentlemen, wee muſt have all your hands.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Adrast.</speaker>
                     <p>With all our hearts.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Rigg.</speaker>
                     <p>Do you want my help?</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Albin.</speaker>
                     <l>No, Miſtris, you have acted your part already.</l>
                     <l>Wee four make the compleat number.</l>
                     <l>Lady, pray ſhut the door.</l>
                     <l>Come, in with him, in with him, in with him.
<stage>—<hi>they put him in a blanket and toſse him.</hi>
                        </stage>
                     </l>
                     <l>So, ſo, 'tis pretty well for the firſt heat.</l>
                     <l>Something hee would have ſaid, could hee have ſpoke;</l>
                     <l>Hee grumbled vilely.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Rigg.</speaker>
                     <l>Incomparable ſport! Fie, fie, you let him breathe</l>
                     <l>Too much. So, ſo, to work again.
<stage>they toſs him as before.</stage>
                     </l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Adraſt.</speaker>
                     <l>Prethee, let him down, it has wrought;</l>
                     <l>The Rogue ſtinks like a pole-cat.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Rigg.</speaker>
                     <p>How rank a Traytor ſmells.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Albin.</speaker>
                     <l>Very true; eſpecially, in the noſtrils of the righteous.</l>
                     <l>The Rogue hath tir'd mee; hee looks white,</l>
                     <l>I fear wee have kill'd him.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Symph.</speaker>
                     <p>No, no, hee breathes.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Albin.</speaker>
                     <p>How, do you like this ſport, Lady?</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Rigg.</speaker>
                     <p>So well, I fain would have ſome more of it.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Adraſt.</speaker>
                     <p>The ſlave hath put my ſhoulders out of joint.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Mett.</speaker>
                     <p>What, ſhall wee leave him ſo?</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Albin.</speaker>
                     <p>Wee muſt <hi>per</hi> force, till wee have breath'd our ſelves.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Rigg.</speaker>
                     <l>Hee that is weari'ſt I'le ſupply his place.</l>
                     <l>I fain would help to give him t'other ſtool.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Symph.</speaker>
                     <l>Let him recover firſt, and then for t'other bout.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Mettle,</speaker>
                     <l>Fill me a glaſſe of ſack.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Adrastus</speaker>
                     <l>here's to the diſh you feaſted on to day.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Adraſt.</speaker>
                     <l>Thanks, dear Friend, this Vlllain hath almoſt</l>
                     <l>Broke my winde. Lady to you.
<stage>—<hi>drinks to Riggle.</hi>
                        </stage>
                     </l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Rigg.</speaker>
                     <p>Your poor ſervant thanks you, Sir.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Adraſt.</speaker>
                     <p>
                        <hi>Mettle,</hi> fill ſome wine; Come, now for t'other bout.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Symph.</speaker>
                     <p>A match, come Gentlemen, four corners and a fool.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Albin.</speaker>
                     <l>A knave, I am ſure; come, ho-vaſt.
<stage>they toſs him as formerly.</stage>
                     </l>
                     <l>So, ſo, ſo; 'tis well, 'tis very well; Gently, gently, down with him; hee grumbles.</l>
                     <l>Hee is not drunk, but hee hath taſted ſo liberally of the creature.</l>
                     <l>All this will not bring him to his ſenſes.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Mett.</speaker>
                     <p>Here's money fallen out of his pocket.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Adrast.</speaker>
                     <l>Sirrah. diminiſh not a penny of his ill-got coin,</l>
                     <l>But put it in his pocket.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <pb n="24" facs="tcp:96238:15"/>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Mett.</speaker>
                     <p>I ſhall, Sir.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Symph.</speaker>
                     <p>
                        <hi>Mettle,</hi> help mee to a Butchers prick or two.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Mett.</speaker>
                     <p>Here's a brace of great pins, if they will do.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Symph.</speaker>
                     <p>Yes, yes, they'l ſerve; give them them,
<stage>—<hi>Symph. pins the blan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ket about Sodome.</hi>
                        </stage>
                     </p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Rigg.</speaker>
                     <l>I'le ſwear you have performed it rarely.</l>
                     <l>What follows now? —</l>
                  </sp>
                  <stage>Enter <hi>Drawer.</hi>
                  </stage>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Symph.</speaker>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Drawer,</hi> take you a care of this beaſt in mans cloaths,</l>
                     <l>Here let him lye (without diſturbance) till hee wakes.</l>
                     <l>Take charge of what hee hath,</l>
                     <l>That nothing be diminiſhed.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Draw.</speaker>
                     <p>Sir, be confident, none ſhall come neer him but my ſelf.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Albin.</speaker>
                     <l>Sirrah, make him pay the reckoning, and if hee enquire</l>
                     <l>(As queſtionleſſe hee will) tell him wee are all ſtrangers;</l>
                     <l>If hee refuſe to pay, wee will.</l>
                     <l>Here's for your paines.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Draw.</speaker>
                     <p>Sir, I thank you, and carefully will perform your will.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Mett.</speaker>
                     <l>Good holy Brother, I muſt make bold to pin</l>
                     <l>This paper on your breaſt.
<stage>—<hi>pins a paper on Sodome's breast.</hi>
                        </stage>
                     </l>
                     <l>Farwell, my fleſhly Saint.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Symph.</speaker>
                     <l>Wee are all indebted to this Lady for our Scene of mirth,</l>
                     <l>Without whoſe help wee had done nothing.</l>
                     <l>Lady, here's half a peece to keep you honeſt.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Rigg.</speaker>
                     <l>Thank you, courteous Sir, I ſhall endeavour to practiſe,</l>
                     <l>And what in my power lyes, I ſhall be glad to ſerve you in.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Adraſt.</speaker>
                     <l>Your ſervant, Lady.</l>
                     <l>Come, let's go, the ſport will be his wonder,</l>
                     <l>When hee wakes, which (by the <hi>Drawer</hi>)</l>
                     <l>Wee ſhall know at full. —</l>
                  </sp>
                  <stage>Ex. Om. but Sodom.</stage>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div n="3" type="act">
               <head>ACT III.</head>
               <div n="1" type="scene">
                  <head>SCENE I.</head>
                  <stage>Enter <hi>Sodome</hi> pin'd in a blanket.</stage>
                  <l>VVHere have I been? Was ever man in ſuch a plight as I?</l>
                  <l>Sure I have been caſt into a ſleep, and hung in ſome painted</l>
                  <l>Cloth, to perſonate the prodigall.</l>
                  <l>What's here? a paper pin'd upon my breaſt?</l>
                  <l>Perhaps I am in <hi>Turkey,</hi> and this my price of ſale.</l>
                  <l>I muſt make bold to ſee how I am valued.
<stage>—<hi>pulls the paper off from his breaſt, and reads.</hi>
                     </stage>
                  </l>
                  <l>Here lies a fleſhly ſaint did lately prank it,</l>
                  <l>Inſtead of ſheet, doe's pennance in a blanket.</l>
                  <l>This may be all true, And I beleeve the Author might have writ</l>
                  <l>To'ſt too. Yes, yes, it muſt be ſo, for I am pocky ſore.</l>
                  <l>They have given mee purging comfits too, for I'me</l>
                  <l>Damnable moiſt behinde; What company was I in?</l>
                  <l>I remember nothing but a whore, and that ſhee would</l>
                  <pb n="25" facs="tcp:96238:15"/>
                  <l>Needs carry mee to ſome friends of hers, and they have us'd mee thus.</l>
                  <l>No hat, nor cloake,
<stage>—<hi>feels in his pocket, and pulls out his money.</hi>
                     </stage>
                  </l>
                  <l>'Tis ſtrange, they ſhould not be theeves,</l>
                  <l>And ſtranger that any other ſhould uſe mee thus.</l>
                  <l>Here's all my money to a penny.</l>
                  <l>I ſhall unfold this myſterie in time.</l>
                  <l>I hear by a-non, a-non, Sir, this is a tavern.</l>
                  <l>The door is lock't, and I muſt knock,</l>
                  <l>Though to my ſhame, I do't.
<stage>hee knocks.</stage>
                  </l>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Draw.</speaker>
                     <p>A-non, a-non, Sir.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <stage>Enter <hi>Drawer.</hi>
                  </stage>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Sod.</speaker>
                     <l>Who ever us'd mee thus, ſure they dare not</l>
                     <l>Speak of it, for fear I come to know it, and puniſh them.</l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Drawer,</hi> how came I in this pickle?</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Draw.</speaker>
                     <p>Do you not know, Sir?</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Sod.</speaker>
                     <l>Not I; prethee, honeſt <hi>Drawer,</hi> tell mee, and</l>
                     <l>I'le be thankfull to thee.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Draw.</speaker>
                     <p>Sir, I cannot tell, I do aſſure you.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Sod.</speaker>
                     <p>Who was in my company? Did you tend this rome?</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Draw.</speaker>
                     <l>I did, and if I not miſtake, there was three or four Gentlemen</l>
                     <l>And a Gentlewoman.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Sod.</speaker>
                     <p>Know'ſt thou any of their names?</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Draw.</speaker>
                     <p>Not I, nor can remember I e're ſaw any of them before.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Sod.</speaker>
                     <p>Where is my hat and cloak?</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Draw.</speaker>
                     <p>I have them ſafe below.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Sod.</speaker>
                     <p>That's ſome comfort yet; how long ſtayed the company here?</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Draw.</speaker>
                     <p>Four or five hours.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Sod.</speaker>
                     <p>Is the reckoning paid?</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Draw.</speaker>
                     <p>Not a penny.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Sod.</speaker>
                     <p>Why did you let them go?</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Draw.</speaker>
                     <l>What Authoritie had I to ſtay them?</l>
                     <l>They gave mee charge of your hat and cloak, and ſaid you loſt the reckoning,</l>
                     <l>Which you not being in a condition to deny,</l>
                     <l>They gave mee charge of you, and went their way.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Sod.</speaker>
                     <p>What is to pay?</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Draw.</speaker>
                     <p>A mark, within a penny.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Sod.</speaker>
                     <p>Fetch mee my hat and cloak, and here's your money.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Draw.</speaker>
                     <p>I ſhall, Sir.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <stage>Ex. Drawer.</stage>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Sod.</speaker>
                     <p>This <hi>Drawer</hi> is a rogue, and privy to my ſufferings,</p>
                     <p>But I muſt hold my tongue,</p>
                  </sp>
                  <stage>Enter <hi>Drawer.</hi>
                  </stage>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Draw.</speaker>
                     <p>Sir, here is your cloak and hat.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Sod.</speaker>
                     <p>And here's your money.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Draw.</speaker>
                     <p>I hope, Sir, you will remember the <hi>Drawer.</hi>
                     </p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Sod.</speaker>
                     <l>I would I had as much reaſon to remember you</l>
                     <l>As you have mee,</l>
                     <l>I made you rare ſport, without all doubt.</l>
                     <l>Here take your blanket, are not the corners ſtretch't?</l>
                     <l>A very pretty wholeſom way of purge,</l>
                     <l>A plague of ſuch Phyſitians.</l>
                     <pb n="26" facs="tcp:96238:16"/>
                     <l>This is the fruits of wenching: ſhew mee the ſtairs;</l>
                     <l>I'le cautions be, how I come in ſuch ſnares. —</l>
                     <stage>Ex. Om.</stage>
                     <stage>Enter <hi>Leteſia Sol.</hi>
                     </stage>
                     <l>What ſhould this buſineſſe be, my father laid, ſo ſtrickt</l>
                     <l>A charge on mee to uſe them with reſpect?</l>
                     <l>'Tis out of ſome ſtrange hopes of profit they aſſure him.</l>
                     <l>How I ſhould learne it out? I know not.—</l>
                     <stage>Enter Clarathea:</stage>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Clarath.</speaker>
                     <l>Miſtris, the Gentleman that din'd here is at doore.</l>
                     <l>Enquiring for your father; ſhall I admit him in?</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Leteſ.</speaker>
                     <p>Why, thou know'ſt my father is not within.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Clarath.</speaker>
                     <l>All's one for that, I beleeve you can doe his buſineſſe better;</l>
                     <l>I'le call him in—</l>
                     <stage>Ex. Clar.</stage>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Leteſ.</speaker>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Clarathea, Clarathea: —</hi>
                        <stage>ſhee calls.</stage>
                     </l>
                     <l>This wench, will ſhame mee.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <stage>
                     <hi>Enter Clarathea</hi> and <hi>Adraſtus.</hi>
                  </stage>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Clarath.</speaker>
                     <l>Sir, my Maſter is not within.</l>
                     <l>Here's my young Miſtris, pleaſe you to impart</l>
                     <l>Your mind to her.</l>
                     <l>I thinke I have given him hint enough,</l>
                     <l>His lookes ſpeake him not faint hearted.</l>
                     <l>I'le leave you both to vent, or burſt.
<stage>—<hi>aſide.</hi>
                        </stage>
                     </l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Adraſt.</speaker>
                     <l>Fairſt Miſtris, I have ſomething of importance</l>
                     <stage>Ex. Clarathea.</stage>
                     <l>To impart to your father.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Leteſ.</speaker>
                     <l>Truely, Sir, hee is abroad, but if you pleaſe to expoſe ſome</l>
                     <l>Litle time to the hazzard of his comming home,</l>
                     <l>You are moſt kindly welcome.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Adraſt.</speaker>
                     <l>Virtuous fair, One I thanke you. And ſince your</l>
                     <l>Noble ſoule hath deny'd to honour mee with this your</l>
                     <l>Courtous invitation, Pardon mee, ſweeteſt, if I endeavour</l>
                     <l>Not to let ſlip theſe happy minuts, the Gods (for ought I know)</l>
                     <l>Hath lent us to enjoy for our unmatchleſs happineſſe.
<stage>—<hi>Shee ſtarts.</hi>
                        </stage>
                     </l>
                     <l>Nay ſtart not, ſweeteſt fair One, I have no frightful</l>
                     <l>Story to relate; I have forgot all things of horror</l>
                     <l>Since I became unable (more) to ſerve</l>
                     <l>My too much injur'd Prince.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Leteſ.</speaker>
                     <p>You have been then in theſe unhappy wars?</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Adraſt.</speaker>
                     <l>Pittie it had been, I ſhould have lived to ſee my Prince</l>
                     <l>Engaged, And I in debt to nature for my health</l>
                     <l>And limbs, and been a looker on.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Leteſ.</speaker>
                     <l>You ſpeak like one our Prince may juſtly call his</l>
                     <l>Loyall ſubject; it had been happy wee had all been ſuch.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Adraſt.</speaker>
                     <l>Lady, ſo intirely I lov'd and honour'd you,</l>
                     <l>(E're you delivered this your Loyall ſoule.)</l>
                     <l>That were it (in nature poſſible) this might have added.</l>
                     <l>Know then, I have eſcap't theſe wars, to be (by your virtuous ſelfe)</l>
                     <l>Adjudg'd to live or dye.</l>
                     <l>Can you love? love mee ſo, to make mee yours.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Leteſ.</speaker>
                     <l>Sir, 'tis a queſtion, requires much more deliberation, then</l>
                     <l>A ſuddaine anſwer. I muſt confeſs, it were a meanes</l>
                     <pb n="27" facs="tcp:96238:16"/>
                     <l>To quench thoſe flames (you do pretend to burn in) ſhould I,</l>
                     <l>And to a ſtranger to, ſo eaſie part, with what (ſo much)</l>
                     <l>Concerns my life and honour?</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Adraſt.</speaker>
                     <l>Miſtake mee not, ſweet ſaint, 'tis but a hope I beg,</l>
                     <l>Which a ſmall encouragement (from you) will make mee proud of.</l>
                     <l>Nor can I poſſibly urge, or dare expect that ſatisfaction from you,</l>
                     <l>That may impair your honour; let mee but hope,</l>
                     <l>And it ſhall be a happy prologue to my enſuing ſtory.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Leteſ.</speaker>
                     <l>Sir, The hope you can expect from mee, and <hi>I</hi> in honour give,</l>
                     <l>Is this; I nothing ſee, but that your perſon, and your noble minde,</l>
                     <l>Deſerves a far more worthy wife then I can be.</l>
                     <l>But, Sir, I have a father, whoſe choice I muſt prefer (in duty)</l>
                     <l>If hee gives conſent, 'tis probable I may not repent it.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Adraſt.</speaker>
                     <l>You have with joy unſpeakable tranſported mee</l>
                     <l>Above the clouds, there let mee drop, my fall might be the greater.</l>
                     <l>O! unſay that again; that very name of father hath chill'd my bloud,</l>
                     <l>And ſounds deſpair to my beguiling hopes.</l>
                     <l>Too well, I know what choice your father aims at;</l>
                     <l>Nor is fit you ſhould obey him, where the choice hee makes</l>
                     <l>Tends to your ruine.</l>
                     <l>Can the Woolf and Lamb imbrace? Or can there be</l>
                     <l>A ſympathy, where nature hath made antipathy?</l>
                     <l>Nor are you oblieged (by duty) to obey him in what's unjuſt.</l>
                     <l>You know his ſoul is black with ſin, Forgive mee, Deareſt,</l>
                     <l>That I am forc't to put you in minde, of what, I know,</l>
                     <l>You gladly would forget. Can you expect to enjoy one happy hour</l>
                     <l>With him, whoſe ſole delight muſt be to hoard up wealth,</l>
                     <l>Gotten by baſe ſiniſter meanes.</l>
                     <l>Beſides the daily curſes (for his ſake) you'l have.</l>
                     <l>Your door waſh't too, with tears of Orphans, and ſuch</l>
                     <l>Oppreſſed poor, as hee ſhall hourly boaſt hee hath undone.</l>
                     <l>For know, ſweet Creature, the free acceſſe wee at this preſent have,</l>
                     <l>To your fair ſelf, is onely that wee will aſſiſt him</l>
                     <l>In the ruine of a young Gentleman (for ought I know)</l>
                     <l>Unborn; but as wee do pretend, knowing his griping way of gain,</l>
                     <l>That I thereby might have the happy means</l>
                     <l>To make my love known to you.</l>
                     <l>I am a Gentleman, though (I muſt confeſſe) a husband</l>
                     <l>Far unworthy ſo Angelical a Beauty.</l>
                     <l>Nor have I to my wiſh (for your virtuous ſake) means</l>
                     <l>Worthy your acceptance. But what I have, (though not ſo poor to want)</l>
                     <l>Shall be enjoyed by mee, onely to do you ſervice.</l>
                     <l>And as you are known to be your fathers Heir,</l>
                     <l>You may ſuppoſe his wealth, more then your virtue, is what I aim at,</l>
                     <l>Make mee but happy in your ſelf,</l>
                     <l>Let him enjoy his pelf; which, when I covet,</l>
                     <l>May I live long forgotten of my friends, and looſe you love,</l>
                     <l>Which (with my life) muſt in one grave be buried.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <pb n="28" facs="tcp:96238:17"/>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Leteſ.</speaker>
                     <l>Sir, what you have ſaid touching my fathers life,</l>
                     <l>I could with tears wiſh were not true.</l>
                     <l>And for your love to mee, I thank you, which</l>
                     <l>(To my poor power) I'le labor to requite.</l>
                     <l>Pray take this for preſent anſwer.</l>
                     <l>Indeed, I am not well, and muſt retire; onely</l>
                     <l>This, your language, I ſhall ſeriouſly weigh, and at our</l>
                     <l>Next meeting reſolve you more at large.</l>
                     <l>So heavens preſerve you. —</l>
                  </sp>
                  <stage>Ex. Leteſia,</stage>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Adraſt.</speaker>
                     <p>Angels protect thee, ſweeteſt of thy Sex. —</p>
                  </sp>
                  <stage>Ex. Adraſt.</stage>
                  <stage>Enter <hi>Gripe-man, Sent-well,</hi> and <hi>Clarathea.</hi>
                  </stage>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Sent.</speaker>
                     <l>Wee have been at Old <hi>Firmſtand</hi>'s Lodging, but to no purpoſe.</l>
                     <l>Hee left the town three dayes ſince, but will return for certain</l>
                     <l>Two dayes hence at furtheſt.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Gripe.</speaker>
                     <l>It was ill luck you miſt him, but ſince his ſtay from town</l>
                     <l>Will be ſo ſhort, the matter is the leſſe.</l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Sent-well,</hi> here's money for your preſent wants,</l>
                     <l>You muſt about a buſineſſe preſently for mee,</l>
                     <l>You know the Golden-head.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Sent.</speaker>
                     <p>Very well, Sir.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Gripe.</speaker>
                     <l>There lyes a Gentleman, his name <hi>Adraſtus,</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>I think you have ſeen him.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Sent.</speaker>
                     <p>Marry have I, Sir.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Gripe.</speaker>
                     <l>So much the better: Be ſure you dog him</l>
                     <l>Forth his Lodging, and if you houſe him in a tavern (as ten to one you will)</l>
                     <l>Uſe all the ſlights you can to Riggle into his company,</l>
                     <l>VVhich, if you cannot do, be ſure you take a rome, or wait ſo neer him,</l>
                     <l>You may diſcover what their diſcourſe is.</l>
                     <l>And let mee know what you can gather this night;</l>
                     <l>And if their plot (contrived) ſtand right, 'tis rare.</l>
                     <l>I'le firk my youngſters when they come to ſhare.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Sent.</speaker>
                     <p>Sir, I'le do my beſt, and doubt not to perform your will.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Gripe.</speaker>
                     <l>Go, go about it ſtraight, make haſte. —</l>
                     <stage>Ex. Sent.</stage>
                     <l>Yes, yes, it muſt be ſo;
<stage>Gripe. pulls out a letter. and reads it to himſelf.</stage>
                     </l>
                     <l>There's danger in delayes: The Girle</l>
                     <l>Muſt from temptation, or ſhee's loſt.</l>
                     <l>Some few moneths more ſhee will be head-ſtrong,</l>
                     <l>And carve her own bits, which I'le in time prevent.
<stage>— <hi>hee calls</hi>
                        </stage> 
                        <hi>Leteſia. Leteſia.</hi>
                     </l>
                     <stage>Enter <hi>Leteſia.</hi>
                     </stage>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Leteſia,</hi> here's newes for you.</l>
                     <l>Your unkle <hi>Miſer,</hi> writes old <hi>Avaritia,</hi> likes well of</l>
                     <l>The match between his ſon and you.</l>
                     <l>And that becauſe hee would have you neer one another,</l>
                     <l>Hee thinks it fit you ſhould be at his houſe,</l>
                     <l>And ſojorn there a while, till things between us</l>
                     <l>Fully are agreed on.</l>
                     <l>You ſee, Girle, what a care I have of your well doing;</l>
                     <pb n="29" facs="tcp:96238:17"/>
                     <l>My thoughts are often hammering about your good,</l>
                     <l>When you full ſoundly ſleep; young <hi>Avaritia</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>Will make a wealthy husband for thee.</l>
                     <l>Up with your trinkets, and prepare to go:</l>
                     <l>Nay, no ſtudy, I have ſaid it, and it muſt be ſo. —</l>
                  </sp>
                  <stage>Ex. Gripe.</stage>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Leteſ.</speaker>
                     <l>Indeed it muſt not. Good <hi>Avaritia,</hi> match in your own</l>
                     <l>Dunghill, it will avoid a baſtard breed.</l>
                     <l>Money makes men ador'd, faith not by mee;</l>
                     <l>Virtue and honour crowns felicitie.</l>
                     <stage>Enter <hi>Clarathea.</hi>
                     </stage>
                     <l>How now, <hi>Clarathea?</hi> Ar't ſure <hi>Sent-well</hi> is imployed</l>
                     <l>To pry into his actions?</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Clarath.</speaker>
                     <l>Am I ſure I live? I ſtood by when your father gave the charge,</l>
                     <l>And the Villain undertook it greedily.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Leteſ.</speaker>
                     <l>How ſhall wee do to give <hi>Adraſtus</hi> notice of it?</l>
                     <l>This ſlave will diſcover elſe, they do delude my father,</l>
                     <l>And then wee are all undone.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Clarath.</speaker>
                     <l>Why, faith, for once, (to do you ſervice) I'le to</l>
                     <l>His Lodging my ſelf. I heard what directions my Maſter</l>
                     <l>Gave him. Let mee alone to acquaint him with the plot;</l>
                     <l>But now I think on't too, I'le not go neither.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Leteſ.</speaker>
                     <p>Dear wench, why not?</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Clarath.</speaker>
                     <p>Why Faith, cauſe you'l be jealous.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Leteſ.</speaker>
                     <l>Prethee, leave thy jeſting, by my life not I.</l>
                     <l>Tis more then time thou wer't gone.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Clarath.</speaker>
                     <l>You have prevailed; and I reſolved to venture. —</l>
                     <stage>Ex. Amb.</stage>
                     <stage>Enter <hi>Atheos,</hi> richly clad, admiring himſelf.</stage>
                     <l>Marry, Sir, this is ſomething like.</l>
                     <l>I ſee my Taylor can fit mee without taking meaſure of my conſcience.</l>
                     <l>The ſame quantitie ſerves, how large ſo ever,</l>
                     <l>Fools report 'tis ſtreach't.</l>
                     <l>What a handſom bug-bear it is, to 'fright men out of a happineſſe,</l>
                     <l>Their reaſon (wer't not enſlaved, by doting on a world ith' moon,</l>
                     <l>To recompence their pining Miſerie) muſt prompt them to enjoy.
<stage>—<hi>puts off his hat.</hi>
                        </stage>
                     </l>
                     <l>Perſiſt in beggary, do, and let your admired conſcience</l>
                     <l>(Uſhered in with rags, and meagre chops)</l>
                     <l>Attend you to your graves; Where (if your duſt</l>
                     <l>More brighter ſhine then mine)</l>
                     <l>Be thankfull to the Glow-worm</l>
                     <l>Let mee imbrace this world, till I forbear</l>
                     <l>(For conſcience ſake) to enjoy, with full delights</l>
                     <l>What luſt unſatisfied deſires.</l>
                     <l>This dumb God I'le adore, Money, to thee</l>
                     <l>I'le ſacrifice, thou art my Deitie.</l>
                     <l>How now, <hi>Rogaſtos?</hi>
                     </l>
                     <stage>Enter <hi>Rogaſtos.</hi>
                     </stage>
                     <l>How drawes the lungs of our new Government,</l>
                     <pb n="30" facs="tcp:96238:18"/>
                     <l>The air of profit, (ſweeter then are the Arabian winds)</l>
                     <l>Into our garriſon?</l>
                     <l>Doth conſcience (ſtill) part freely with her outward</l>
                     <l>Garments, truſting the ſoul for to re-cloath the body?</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Rogast.</speaker>
                     <l>As yet they gallop to their ſufferings, as wee can wiſh;</l>
                     <l>Only the Lady that wee raviſhed,</l>
                     <l>Hangs ſtill an arſe.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Athe.</speaker>
                     <l>Shee ſtill continues firm in belief,</l>
                     <l>It was the private Souldier.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Rogaſt.</speaker>
                     <l>Shee doe's; but wonders much there's no ſeverer ſearch</l>
                     <l>To apprehend what (fooliſhly) ſhee tearmes her foes.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Athe.</speaker>
                     <l>For that wee ſhall (with fair pretences) gild</l>
                     <l>Much thicker then her eyes can pierce.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Rogaſt.</speaker>
                     <l>As thus; the wrack ſhall force a guiltleſſe priſoner</l>
                     <l>To confeſſe the fact, which done before ſuch</l>
                     <l>Witneſſes as ſoon ſhall publiſh it,</l>
                     <l>Wee may (with ſafety) murder him,</l>
                     <l>And it cryed up for Juſtice.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Athe.</speaker>
                     <l>Securely contrived, (my better Genius) and politickly;</l>
                     <l>But wee'l forbear a while, to try what gentler</l>
                     <l>Means may work upon her (eaſily) beguil'd faith,</l>
                     <l>Which I ſhall make my ſtudy.</l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Rogaſtos<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
                        </hi> haſte, and give order the Foot</l>
                     <l>Be all drawn out.</l>
                     <l>That part oth' ſpoil wee ſeiz'd on laſt, I intend</l>
                     <l>For to diſtribute to all an equal ſhare,</l>
                     <l>As well to thoſe remained in garriſon,</l>
                     <l>As the party march't to take it.</l>
                     <l>It will unanimouſly beget a will to Act</l>
                     <l>What ever I preſcribe.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Rogaſt.</speaker>
                     <l>Your judgment's deep and noble.</l>
                     <l>What you command, I'le ſee (with carefull ſpeed)</l>
                     <l>Shall be performed. —</l>
                  </sp>
                  <stage>Ex. Rogaſt.</stage>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Athe.</speaker>
                     <l>Well, go thy waies, Conſcience is mercifull,</l>
                     <l>And troubles not thee.</l>
                     <l>Why, here's a Proſelyte newly converted to our ſide,</l>
                     <l>Out-doe's us all in miſchief.</l>
                     <l>I can diſpence to trot, in what ſome in the world</l>
                     <l>Call ſin, but love not to run off my legs too ſoon.</l>
                     <l>Humanity commands mee hate the violence</l>
                     <l>Of his tyranny, which (for our own ends)</l>
                     <l>Wee muſt privately imbrace, how e're intend</l>
                     <l>For to depreſſe his fury.</l>
                     <l>'Tis policie makes us conſpicuous to the world,</l>
                     <l>Which wee, with ſly hypocriſie muſt</l>
                     <l>Endeavour to conſociate, and then this little.</l>
                     <l>World's our own. —</l>
                  </sp>
                  <stage>Ex. Atheos.</stage>
                  <pb n="31" facs="tcp:96238:18"/>
                  <stage>Enter <hi>Adraſtus, Albinus, Symphronio,</hi> and <hi>Mettle.</hi>
                  </stage>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Adraſt.</speaker>
                     <l>How am I obliged to fair <hi>Leteſia</hi> for this diſcovery?</l>
                     <l>Her virtue will redeem her fathers ſoul.</l>
                     <l>Devoted pilgrims with their tears,</l>
                     <l>Could not have cleans'd by prayer.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Albin.</speaker>
                     <l>Shee's thy own, Boy; this very act of her's</l>
                     <l>Confirms it.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Symph.</speaker>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Adraſtus,</hi> wee muſt have gloves; and for her</l>
                     <l>Garters, let <hi>Albinus</hi> and I alone.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Adraſt.</speaker>
                     <p>Would it were come to that.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Albin.</speaker>
                     <l>Nay, if you cannot ſtay, <hi>Mettle</hi> knows where</l>
                     <l>To help you to a cooler.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Mett.</speaker>
                     <l>Would I had one for you, as hot as I could wiſh.</l>
                     <l>Why, Sir, do you think my Maſter wants a pimp?</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Albin.</speaker>
                     <p>No, I'le beſworn, as long as thou ſerv'ſt him.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Adraſt.</speaker>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Mettle,</hi> hee doe's abuſe thee. Go ſee if thou</l>
                     <l>Can'ſt diſcover ſuch a perſon ſneaking here about, <hi>Leteſia</hi>'s</l>
                     <l>Maid deſcrib'd, and bring mee word.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Mett.</speaker>
                     <p>I ſhall, Sir. —</p>
                  </sp>
                  <stage>Ex. Mettle.</stage>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Albin.</speaker>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Leteſia</hi> goes contrary to the rules at court.</l>
                     <l>They chuſe to entertain, ſuch as may ſtand for foils to beauty.</l>
                     <l>Were but that wench (ſhee keeps) trick't up like them,</l>
                     <l>Shee would out-ſhine them all.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Adraſt.</speaker>
                     <l>Mee thought ſhee did deliver her meſſage to mee,</l>
                     <l>Not like one bred to ſerve.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Albin.</speaker>
                     <l>What puniſhment ſhall wee invent, to inflict upon</l>
                     <l>This Rogue, hath undertook to pry into our actions?</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Adraſt.</speaker>
                     <l>That muſt be thought on.</l>
                     <l>VVhere ſhall wee dine to day?</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Symph.</speaker>
                     <l>Faith at ſome tavern, if but to ſee what</l>
                     <l>This ſame Rogue dares do.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Albin.</speaker>
                     <p>Agreed,</p>
                  </sp>
                  <stage>Enter <hi>Mettle.</hi>
                  </stage>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Adraſt.</speaker>
                     <p>What haſt thou diſcovered?</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Mett.</speaker>
                     <l>I have, Sir, a Rogue, mark't out for ſuch deſignes,</l>
                     <l>Ha's walk't ſome half a dozen turns about the door.</l>
                     <l>You may eaſily know him, A ſhort ſquat Villain,</l>
                     <l>Crop't cloſe to a large ear pendent, with a broad blew liſt,</l>
                     <l>Crook't back't, ſplay feet,</l>
                     <l>And a ſeared Conſcience, Sables.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Albin.</speaker>
                     <p>Herald-like ſpoken, but that hee left out his Arms.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Mett.</speaker>
                     <l>Give mee but leave, and I'le engage</l>
                     <l>To torture his black ſoul to death.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Adraſt.</speaker>
                     <p>Pray try your art, and take your own freedom.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Albin.</speaker>
                     <p>But, <hi>Mettle,</hi> Muſt not wee ſhare ith' laughter of his ſufferings?</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Mett.</speaker>
                     <p>You ſhall, Sir, and be an Actor too.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Adraſt.</speaker>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Mettle,</hi> go you before: Beſpeak a diſh or two of meat</l>
                     <l>Where wee laſt night ſup't.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Mett.</speaker>
                     <p>I ſhall, Sir.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <pb n="32" facs="tcp:96238:19"/>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Adraſt.</speaker>
                     <p>You two ſhall go the back way, and I'le take this.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Symph.</speaker>
                     <p>Come, <hi>Albinus,</hi> then wee'l take this. —</p>
                  </sp>
                  <stage>Ex. Om.</stage>
                  <stage>Enter <hi>Leteſia, Clarathea.</hi>
                  </stage>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Clarath.</speaker>
                     <l>I dare ſay hee loves you; for when I had delivered</l>
                     <l>My meſſage to him (poor Gentleman!) o're-joyed,</l>
                     <l>Hee knew not what to ſay. Till anon, collecting his ſcattered</l>
                     <l>Spirits (aſhamed I ſhould take notice of his paſſion)</l>
                     <l>Hee made mee this anſwer; Sweet heart!</l>
                     <l>Pray (from mee) thank your fair Miſtris for this</l>
                     <l>Noble Courteſie: And let her know, the life I hold</l>
                     <l>(Too poor a thing to part with in recompence of this great favour)</l>
                     <l>Is onely by mee valued, but as 'tis her's to diſpoſe of,</l>
                     <l>I took my leave of him,</l>
                     <l>And what I could to avoid it, hee forc't mee</l>
                     <l>Take a peece, and bid mee tell you,</l>
                     <l>Sometime this afternoon, hee would</l>
                     <l>Not faile to wait on you.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Leteſ.</speaker>
                     <p>But art thou ſure hee'l come?</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Clarath.</speaker>
                     <l>Are you ſure that you would have him come?</l>
                     <l>So ſure am I hee'l come.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Leteſ.</speaker>
                     <l>Dear wench! what (in this ſtraight of trouble) ſhall I do?</l>
                     <l>My father hath plotted with his brother <hi>Miſer,</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>That I muſt into countrey, there to be made ſure</l>
                     <l>To that moſt ſordid wretch, young <hi>Avaritia.</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>This muſt I be forc't to do, or ſtudy quick prevention.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Clarath.</speaker>
                     <l>Study? I underſtand nothing of ſtudy in it.</l>
                     <l>Too well you know your fathers temper,</l>
                     <l>Whoſe reſolutions are unalterable.</l>
                     <l>What then can you reſolve, but bag and baggage (with <hi>Adrastus</hi>)</l>
                     <l>To be gone to ſome ſecure place of ſafety?</l>
                     <l>And you do not know, things being paſt his reach to compaſſe, how the</l>
                     <l>Gods may work his alteration.
<stage>—<hi>Leteſ pauſes.</hi>
                        </stage>
                     </l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Leteſ.</speaker>
                     <l>I have thought on't; And muſt conclude it ſo.</l>
                     <l>I had rather marry an Ethiope, then one</l>
                     <l>I ſhall be ſham'd to own. You Gods above, forgive</l>
                     <l>My diſobedience to my father, which you well know,</l>
                     <l>Virtue and honour both enjoin mee ſo. —</l>
                  </sp>
                  <stage>Ex. Om.</stage>
                  <stage>Enter at ſeveral doors <hi>Sent-well</hi> and <hi>Mettle; Mettle</hi> falls down as in a trance, <hi>Sent-well</hi> takes up <hi>Mettle</hi> who looks diſtractedly.</stage>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Sent.</speaker>
                     <l>How now friend, are you uſed to theſe ſame fits?</l>
                     <l>Now (by my life) it was a ſhrewd one.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Mett.</speaker>
                     <p>'Tis gone; have you no harm, Sir?</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Sent.</speaker>
                     <p>What harm? I underſtand you not,</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Mett.</speaker>
                     <p>Did you not ſee it then?</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Sent.</speaker>
                     <l>What do'ſt thou mean?</l>
                     <l>What ſhould I ſee?</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Mett.</speaker>
                     <p>The Gods protect mee from ſuch another ſight of horror;</p>
                     <pb n="33" facs="tcp:96238:19"/>
                     <l>Sure it has hurt your ſhoulders.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Sent.</speaker>
                     <l>What thing? what hurt? what, or whoſe</l>
                     <l>Shoulders? Art thou not mad?</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Mett.</speaker>
                     <l>Not yet; I do not know what ſuch</l>
                     <l>Another ſight may do; For ſure in a more horrid ſhape</l>
                     <l>The Divel ne're appear'd.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Sent.</speaker>
                     <p>Do'ſt take mee for a Divel?</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Mett.</speaker>
                     <l>You were not farre from one but now,</l>
                     <l>When hee ſat upon your ſhoulders.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Sent.</speaker>
                     <p>Upon my ſhoulders?</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Mett.</speaker>
                     <l>I am glad (for your own ſake) you neither ſaw</l>
                     <l>Nor felt it: I am afraid there is ſome fearfull ſin</l>
                     <l>Sits black upon thy ſoul, that's unrepented of.</l>
                     <l>You Powers, protect mee from ſuch encounters! Farwell. —</l>
                  </sp>
                  <stage>Ex. Mettle.</stage>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Sent.</speaker>
                     <l>What ſhould this mean? mee thought hee did appear</l>
                     <l>Too truely 'frighted to abuſe mee; His action could not be</l>
                     <l>Counterfeit; his colour went and came:</l>
                     <l>I am a Villain, that's certain.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <stage>Enter <hi>Albinus,</hi> hee ſtarts back, throwes of his hat and cloak, drawes his ſword, looking diſtractedly.</stage>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Albin.</speaker>
                     <l>Heavens, protect the man. What art thou?</l>
                     <l>I do conjure thee in the names of all the Gods, ſpeak,</l>
                     <l>Why in that hideous ſhape do'ſt hang on that man's ſhoulders?</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Sent.</speaker>
                     <p>Who, mine, Sir, do you mean?</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Albin.</speaker>
                     <l>VVhy do'ſt not ſpeak to it? See, ſee, 'tis down and beckons thee.</l>
                     <l>As if the buſineſſe it had on earth, concern'd thee onely.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Sent.</speaker>
                     <p>Heavens bleſſe mee, Sir, I ſee nothing.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Albin.</speaker>
                     <l>Look, look, there it walks; ſpeak to it (I ſay)</l>
                     <l>It beckons thee to follow it: So, ſo, now 'tis gone,</l>
                     <l>Juſt there it vaniſh't.</l>
                     <l>Into what a cold clammy ſweat 't has put mee?</l>
                     <l>The Gods guard mee from ſuch foul fiends.</l>
                     <l>How do'ſt thou feel thy ſelf?</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Sent.</speaker>
                     <l>Sir, truely, not well. I am ſomewhat 'frighted</l>
                     <l>At what, you ſay, you ſaw.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Albin.</speaker>
                     <p>It is impoſſible; Did'ſt thou not ſee, nor feel it.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Sent.</speaker>
                     <p>Not I, Sir, truly.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Albin.</speaker>
                     <l>'Tis wondrous ſtrange.</l>
                     <l>Friend, look into thy conſcience, and</l>
                     <l>There ſearch if unrevenged blood</l>
                     <l>Cry not for juſtice.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Sent.</speaker>
                     <l>Truly, Sir, I never had a hand in murdering any body.</l>
                     <l>I muſt confeſſe, many a poor ſoul I have undone.
<stage>aſide.</stage>
                     </l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Albin.</speaker>
                     <l>Thy conſcience be thy judge, which well examine,</l>
                     <l>And I am confident you'l finde it clogg'd</l>
                     <l>VVith fearfull crying ſins. —</l>
                  </sp>
                  <stage>Ex. Albin.</stage>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Sent.</speaker>
                     <l>'Tis true, 'tis true, they are crying ſins indeed.</l>
                     <l>Theſe are no idle fancies; this Gentleman is a ſtranger too,</l>
                     <pb n="34" facs="tcp:96238:20"/>
                     <l>And did but confirm what the former ſaw.</l>
                     <l>Mee thinks my ſins circle mee round, and in a ring</l>
                     <l>Unmask't, appear each in their horrid ſhape.</l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Gripe-man,</hi> (thou Author of my ruine)</l>
                     <l>Thou now appear'ſt a monſter. 'Curſe on the time,</l>
                     <l>I ever ſaw thy face.</l>
                     <l>You Gods (above) forgive mee. 'Tis time well ſpent,</l>
                     <l>My eyes being open (now) for to repent.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <stage>Exit.</stage>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div n="4" type="act">
               <head>ACT IV.</head>
               <div n="1" type="scene">
                  <head>SCENE I.</head>
                  <stage>Enter <hi>Adraſtus, Albinus, Symphronio,</hi> and <hi>Mettle.</hi>
                  </stage>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Adraſt.</speaker>
                     <p>COuld you perceive it wrought at all upon the ſlave?</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Albin.</speaker>
                     <l>Rarely; the Rogues bones made muſick in his skin.</l>
                     <l>I ſtrongly do beleeve (if the ſlave be not quite given o're)</l>
                     <l>It will convert him.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Symph.</speaker>
                     <p>Hang him, flint hearted ſlave, hee's unrecoverably ſpent.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Mett.</speaker>
                     <l>Hee vaniſh't like our Divel, hee has</l>
                     <l>Quit his imployment upon it.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Albin.</speaker>
                     <p>I tell you, hee is converted.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Adraſt.</speaker>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Symphronio,</hi> prethee tell mee, Were it</l>
                     <l>Not ſtrange <hi>Albinus</hi> ſhould turn converter</l>
                     <l>Of the wicked?</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Smph.</speaker>
                     <p>Strange as a froſt in Auguſt.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Albin.</speaker>
                     <l>Yet you had hang'd your ſelfe, had I not wrought you meanes</l>
                     <l>To court your fair <hi>Leteſia</hi> and what had then (think you)</l>
                     <l>Been of your ſoul become?</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Symph.</speaker>
                     <p>
                        <hi>Adraſtus,</hi> What can you ſay to that?</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Adraſt.</speaker>
                     <l>I grant hee did a pretty handſome cure (indeed)</l>
                     <l>His Maſter-piece.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Albin.</speaker>
                     <p>Indeed, your Miſtreſſes.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Adraſt.</speaker>
                     <l>Time calls away to viſit her.</l>
                     <l>Gallants, where ſhall I ſee you ſome two hours hence.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Symph.</speaker>
                     <p>Wee'l wait you at our Lodging.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Adraſt.</speaker>
                     <p>Agreed.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Albin.</speaker>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Adraſtus,</hi> My ſervice to the fair ſervant</l>
                     <l>Of your fairer Miſtris.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Adraſt.</speaker>
                     <p>Hangs your mouth that way?</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Albin.</speaker>
                     <l>No, you miſtake, all that I have ſtands</l>
                     <l>That way.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Adraſt.</speaker>
                     <p>That may be doubtfull. Farwell.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Albin.</speaker>
                     <l>May all thy undertakings proſper,</l>
                     <l>To thy noble ſouls deſire. —</l>
                  </sp>
                  <stage>Ex. Omnes.</stage>
                  <stage>Enter <hi>Leteſia, Clarathea.</hi>
                  </stage>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Leteſ.</speaker>
                     <l>Sure, wench, thou did'ſt miſtake; Art ſure hee promiſed to be here?</l>
                     <l>'Tis more then two of clock.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Clarath.</speaker>
                     <l>By none but Lovers clocks; I know it wants of two.
<stage>—<hi>Knocks as door.</hi>
                        </stage>
                     </l>
                     <pb n="35" facs="tcp:96238:20"/>
                     <l>Now, what ſay you? Am I miſtaken?</l>
                     <l>Upon my life 'tis hee. —</l>
                  </sp>
                  <stage>Ex. Clarath.</stage>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Leteſ.</speaker>
                     <l>My modeſtie will not give mee leave to acquaint him</l>
                     <l>With what (more then the world beſides) my heart deſires.</l>
                     <l>You Gods, I hope hee'l move it firſt,</l>
                     <l>That wee eſcape together, for I ſhall never do it.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <stage>Enter <hi>Adraſtus, Clarathea.</hi>
                  </stage>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Adraſt.</speaker>
                     <l>The joyes the Gods delight in moſt,</l>
                     <l>Still wait upon you, fair One.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Leteſ.</speaker>
                     <p>I ſhould ungratefull bee, ſhould I not wiſh you ſhare in them.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Adraſt.</speaker>
                     <l>Preſerver of my life, ſo much have you engaged your creature,</l>
                     <l>It were a ſtudy too preſumptuous for mortals to requite.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Leteſ.</speaker>
                     <p>If I have done you any, truly, I am glad. But
<stage>—<hi>Shee pauſes.</hi>
                        </stage>
                     </p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Adraſt.</speaker>
                     <p>But what, bleſt Saint?</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Leteſ.</speaker>
                     <l>But I much fear, it will not lye within the</l>
                     <l>Compaſſe of my weak power to do you more.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Adraſt.</speaker>
                     <l>Rob mee not of a joy, the hopes of</l>
                     <l>Hath tranſported mee.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Leteſ.</speaker>
                     <l>I am, by the expreſs command of my father, charg'd into the</l>
                     <l>Countrey, and there to try how I can like a ſuiter of his chooſing.</l>
                     <l>And one (hee is reſolved) whether I like, or not, muſt be my husband.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Adraſt.</speaker>
                     <l>'Tis an unjuſt reſolve; (I do perceive, your Maid</l>
                     <l>Is no ſtranger to your counſels, Lady.)</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Leteſ.</speaker>
                     <l>I ſhould ill reward the ſervice ſhee hath done mee,</l>
                     <l>Should I requite it with diſtruſt.</l>
                     <l>There's nothing (I dare think) I dare not truſt her with.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Adraſt.</speaker>
                     <l>It is a noble performance, to be faithful,</l>
                     <l>And deſerves high reward.</l>
                     <l>Now ſince you are pleas'd to acquaint your poor Creature</l>
                     <l>With what ſo neer concerns you,</l>
                     <l>I humbly ſhall requeſt what you reſolve to do in't.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Leteſ.</speaker>
                     <l>Sir, you urge to know what lies not in my power</l>
                     <l>To ſatisfie.</l>
                     <l>I gladly would be aſſiſted (by ſome</l>
                     <l>Judicious friend) what I ſhould do</l>
                     <l>In ſuch a weighty buſineſſe as this is.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Adrast.</speaker>
                     <l>Then 'tis no time to dally.</l>
                     <l>Do you love mee ſo, to make mee Maſter of your ſelf?</l>
                     <l>A happineſſe (by all the Gods) I would not change</l>
                     <l>For what (beſides) this world affords—</l>
                     <stage>Leteſ. pauſes.</stage>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Clarath.</speaker>
                     <l>Pray Miſtris ſpeak — no —Sir, ſhee doe's.</l>
                     <l>Be confident (I know) ſhee doe's.</l>
                     <l>Is this a time to nouriſh baſhfullneſſe?</l>
                     <l>Sir, pray think what's to be done,</l>
                     <l>And for the reſt,</l>
                     <l>Take poor <hi>Clarathea</hi>'s word.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Leteſ.</speaker>
                     <p>Thou art not mad.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Clarath.</speaker>
                     <l>No, nor would have you ſo tame, to fool your ſelf</l>
                     <pb n="36" facs="tcp:96238:21"/>
                     <l>Out of the joyes you aim at, next to heaven.</l>
                     <l>Pardon mee, Sir (I pray) if I appear too ſaucy.</l>
                     <l>'Twould make one mad to know as much as I.</l>
                     <l>And ſee how doubtfully ſhee would appear, in what</l>
                     <l>(I know) is in her heart confirm'd.</l>
                     <l>Sir, ſhee is yours. Will you confeſſe it Miſtris?</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Leteſ.</speaker>
                     <l>It is a truth, my breaſt (ſpight of reſiſtance)</l>
                     <l>Will it ſelf diſcover.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Adraſt.</speaker>
                     <l>May I enjoy this bleſſing without envy from above?</l>
                     <l>No enamored God deſcending to forbid the banes.
<stage>takes her by the hand.</stage>
                     </l>
                     <l>Religious fires, without paſſion kindled,</l>
                     <l>Temperately burn, and laſt to out-live the envious world,</l>
                     <l>Whoſe narrow breaſts wee'l give leave to ſuſpect,</l>
                     <l>Not comprehend our joyes.
<stage>—<hi>kiſſes her.</hi>
                        </stage>
                     </l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Clarath.</speaker>
                     <l>Why this is as it ſhould be. Come fondlings,</l>
                     <l>Now wee ſhall have you as bad as t'other ſide.</l>
                     <l>Leave billing, and reſolve what's to be done.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Adraſt.</speaker>
                     <l>Thanks, good <hi>Clarathea,</hi> for thy remembrance;</l>
                     <l>For I had almoſt loſt my ſelf in joyes unſpeakable.</l>
                     <l>My dear <hi>Leteſia,</hi> (ſo I dare call the now)</l>
                     <l>Haſt thou made choice of any courſe to ſteer in this</l>
                     <l>Same ſea of trouble, mixt with joy?</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Leteſ.</speaker>
                     <l>Truly, not any I; My ſhallow judgment is too weak</l>
                     <l>To comprehend what's to be done in things of this high nature.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Clarath.</speaker>
                     <l>Sir, That's your part to act.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Adraſt.</speaker>
                     <l>Which I, with all reſpectfull care will labour to perform to our</l>
                     <l>Souls comfort. And to our great aſſiſtance, I have two noble Friends I dare</l>
                     <l>Call truſtie, as thou thy beſt <hi>Clarathea.</hi>
                     </l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Clarath.</speaker>
                     <l>Sir, be confident, that little life I have, ſhall willingly (in toil)</l>
                     <l>Be ſpent to ſee your joyes compleated.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Adraſt.</speaker>
                     <l>It is beleeved, <hi>Clarathea,</hi> and it ſhall be my carefull ſtudy to finde</l>
                     <l>Out ſome noble way of requital. My <hi>Leteſia,</hi> I now muſt leave thee</l>
                     <l>Till my next return, which ſhall be ſpeedy, as our ſafety ſhall permit.</l>
                     <l>My truſty Friends (I muſt impart my ſecrets to) expect</l>
                     <l>My coming; whoſe help I muſt make uſe of in our ſpeedy flight.</l>
                     <l>This kiſs, and ſo wee part.
<stage>kiſſes her.</stage>
                     </l>
                     <l>My perſon moves, with thee remaines my heart.</l>
                     <l>Farwell, thou faithfull ſervant.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <stage>Ex. Adraſt.</stage>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Clarath.</speaker>
                     <p>The Gods protect you, Sir.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Leteſ.</speaker>
                     <l>Amen to that. <hi>Clarathea,</hi> thou haſt plaid the wagg</l>
                     <l>Sufficiently to day, and yet I do forgive thee.</l>
                     <l>For, I confeſſe, I am glad 'tis out; I would not have it to do</l>
                     <l>Again, for half my fathers ill-got coyn.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Clarath.</speaker>
                     <l>And now you talk on't,</l>
                     <l>You ſhould do well for to provide good ſtore of it.</l>
                     <l>You know not what may happen.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Leteſ.</speaker>
                     <l>Happen what will or can, I'le not diminiſh one penny</l>
                     <l>Of his wealth, ſo many curſes goes along with.</l>
                     <pb n="37" facs="tcp:96238:21"/>
                     <l>No <hi>Clarathea,</hi> he ſhall not ſay I rob'd him.</l>
                     <l>What money, and jewels of my own</l>
                     <l>I have, il'e carry with me, the reſt let him enjoy.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Clarath:</speaker>
                     <p>I think I hear him Cough<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>, come let's away.—</p>
                  </sp>
                  <stage>Ex: Om:</stage>
                  <stage>Ent: <hi>Adrastus, Albinus, Symphrenio.</hi>
                  </stage>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Albin:</speaker>
                     <p>Did not I tell thee <hi>Adraſtus,</hi> that her Maids meſſuage was a prologue of confirmation to your late ſcald bliſs. Well the Gods give the joy, thou haſt the mine of vertue, her Maid's, a handſome ſcab, and well qualified. I read it in her face.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Adraſt:</speaker>
                     <p>
                        <hi>Albinus:</hi> Thou doſt not know the worth that's in that Virgin thou talks't of, by all the Gods (ſetting <hi>Leteſia</hi> aſide) I know not where to match her, beleeve it, ſhe is not what ſhe ſeems to be, (I mean) not born in ſo low a condition, but by ſome misfortune fallen to it.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Symph:</speaker>
                     <p>I muſt confeſſe, her language, ſhape, and carriage ſpeaks her of better breeding, then her preſents ſtate makes known. But what courſe <hi>(Adraſtus)</hi> do you intend to take, you cannot hope to have her Fathers will to this.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Adraſt:</speaker>
                     <p>Tis true; And therefore would adviſe with you, what's to be done her Father being reſolved (ſpeedily) to ſend her out of Town.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Albin:</speaker>
                     <p>Let him do ſo, then ſeate her on the way, and bear her to ſome place of ſafety, in which we'l both aſſiſt you with our lives and fortunes.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Adraſt:</speaker>
                     <p>Noble friends, I thank you. But that muſt not be the way, for firſt, her Father will not ſend her with a leſſe guard then two, from whom, we cannot take her (with our ſecurity) without we take their lives (which all the Gods forbid) but they'le purſue us ſtrictly. No, no, I have contrived a way much ſafer. You <hi>Albinus,</hi> (ſince you have pleaſed to proffer me (ſo fairly) your aſſiſtance.) I ſhall requeſt to viſit the old man in your accuſtomed diſguiſe, t'will cleer me from ſuſpect. You ſhall enjoy <hi>Symphronio</hi> here in Town; And fair <hi>Clarathea:</hi> who I intend to leave, to give me conſtant notice how her Maſter takes his Daughters flight, as alſo which way his genious drives in ſearch of her, while fair <hi>Leteſia,</hi> and I, ſteer to <hi>Geetrudenberghe,</hi> where (by <hi>Mettle</hi>) you ſhall have timely notice what's further to be done. How like you this contrivance?</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Symph:</speaker>
                     <p>Why very well, as can be wiſh't.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Albin:</speaker>
                     <p>It ſtands for me, on goes my mouldy Cloaths again, il'e once more be a brother. And when I know my part, let me alone to act.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Adraſt:</speaker>
                     <p>The next is, that you prepare all things in ſuch a readineſſe.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <gap reason="missing" extent="2 pages">
                     <desc>〈2 pages missing〉</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <pb n="40" facs="tcp:96238:22"/>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Leteſi:</speaker>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Clarathea,</hi> here is ſomewhat in this Letter</l>
                     <l>I fear me will diſpleaſe thee.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Clarath;</speaker>
                     <p>That is impoſſible, if it may tend to do you ſervice,
<stage>—<hi>Leteſia reads Adraſt. Letter.</hi>
                        </stage>
                     </p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Leteſi:</speaker>
                     <floatingText type="letter" xml:lang="eng">
                        <body>
                           <p>Vertuous fair one, I have ſince my departure from thee (with the aſſiſtance of my faithfull Friends) concluded of our remove, which will be ſo ſudden, that I muſt requeſt thee to prepare thoſe neceſſaries you take with you, to be in a readineſſe at a minutes warning. Remember me to thy faithfull Servant, who, I muſt requeſt to ſtay behind (ſome ſmall time) to obſerve her Maſters actions. My noble Friends (I leave behind) will upon the receit of a Letter from me, accompany her to <hi>Geetrudenberghe</hi> where we ſhall ſtay their coming. Fail not to burn this Letter.</p>
                           <closer>
                              <signed>Thine to Eternity, <hi>Adraſtus.</hi>
                              </signed>
                           </closer>
                        </body>
                     </floatingText>
                     <p>What ſaies my Deer Companion, i'ſt not too great a trouble to inflict upon thy patience, to ſtand the ſhock of my Fathers fury, when he ſhall know I am gone? </p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Clarath:</speaker>
                     <p>Not any, I am better acquainted with his temper, (let him but hold his hands) then to be troubled, at what his tongue can utter.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Leteſi:</speaker>
                     <p>Come then my beſt <hi>Clarathea,</hi> for till it be thy will to alter it, I ſtill ſhall call thee ſo, we muſt go pack up for our remove, for tis to me unknown, how ſoon we ſhall be ſummond.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Clarath:</speaker>
                     <p>What you command, I ever ſhall with joy obey. —</p>
                  </sp>
                  <stage>Ex: Om:</stage>
                  <stage>Ent: <hi>Atheos: Rogaſtus.</hi>
                  </stage>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Athe:</speaker>
                     <p>
                        <hi>Rogastus,</hi> the orders from our Generall ſpeak, we muſt be carefull both by Sea, and Land, what ſtrangers we admit into our Garriſon. Pray let it be your care to ſee the word be given, that no<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap> an Officer of mine may plead ignorance for his neglect. Something there is in it that much concerns the State: And as I gueſs, they fain would make a ſtop, of ſome that would deſert this Land, which we muſt look too.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Rogaſt:</speaker>
                     <p>Sir, can you gueſs what Perſons they ſhould be they aim at.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Athe:</speaker>
                     <p>Faith not, my Major will return this Night, of whom I do expect ſome Letters of import.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Rogaſt:</speaker>
                     <p>Sir, tis ſtrange to me, the ſword being in our hands, we ſhould from time, to time be put of thus, and not receive our pay.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Athe:</speaker>
                     <p>Tis true, but a little patience payes us. For know, the time approaches neer for us to pay our ſelves, (a frugall way our Maſters have all had before us) and now our turn comes next, there being a powerfull At my raiſing to oppoſe us. The which, before we can encounter, the Country we muſt drive, as what concerns <pb n="41" facs="tcp:96238:22"/>us moſt. And <hi>Rogaſtus,</hi> he's a fool, ſence ruine we intend that in the act, can't get enough to ſpend.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Rogaſt:</speaker>
                     <p>Tis happy news, I long to be at the ſport. How I ſhall laugh to ſee the Bacon eating churles upon their knees for ſix pence in the hundred of their own coyn which il'e in State deny them.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Athe:</speaker>
                     <p>
                        <hi>Rogaſtus</hi> take order that your ſentinels, bawl not for relief, as they have us'd to do. Your Corporals uſe no juſtice, in their relief, but as affection guids them, which, let me but find out, Il'e lay them neck, and heels.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Rogaſt:</speaker>
                     <p>Sir, it ſhall be my care to ſee it remedied. —</p>
                  </sp>
                  <stage>Ex; Om:</stage>
                  <stage>Ent. <hi>Gripe-man, and Clarathea.</hi>
                  </stage>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Gripe:</speaker>
                     <p>Tell me when ſhe went, and where ſhe is, or by my vexed ſoul, il'e rip thy heare out, and find it there.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Clarath:</speaker>
                     <p>You may rip it out if you pleaſe, which when you have done, t'will but confirm your error. Pray Sir, Argue but reaſon, would it not ill become your ſervant to examine you, where you go, and what your buſineſs is abroad?</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Gripe.</speaker>
                     <p>Why tell me, Thou Witch, could ſhe conveigh her things forth of the houſe without your knowledge? Go, not a ſyllable of reply. Finde her me out or i'le invent tortures unheard of for thee.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Clarath.</speaker>
                     <p>Sir, The Witch you threaten, cannot conjure for your Daughter, I will aſſure you.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <stage>Ex: Clarath.</stage>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Gripe.</speaker>
                     <p>I am undone, betrayed, to my eternall ruine. Where ſhould this Whore be gon? ſome villain hath intic't her. I'le find her hants out, if the expence of my eſtate will do it.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <stage>Ent: <hi>Albinus diſguiſed as formerly.</hi>
                  </stage>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Albin.</speaker>
                     <p>Save you worthy Sir.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Gripe.</speaker>
                     <p>Not ſo worthy, as you conceive. I am not worthy my own Childs keeping, but I will turn the infide of this whole Land outward, but I will finde her.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Albin.</speaker>
                     <p>Good Sir do, and all honeſt men ſhall thank you, we then ſhall have it right again.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Gripe:</speaker>
                     <p>I tell you Sir, I have loſt my Child, my only Child, and I muſt find her out.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Albin.</speaker>
                     <p>If you find her out, ſhe muſt be above one and thirty, and then (I hope) ſhe is paſt crying. Sir you are not well, il'e viſit you ſo me other time.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Gripe:</speaker>
                     <p>I cry you mercy Sir, I am diſtracted, nor can you blame me much. My Child, my Daughter, my only Child is gone.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Albin</speaker>
                     <p>Pray Sir whither.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Gripe:</speaker>
                     <p>You do not mock me Sir.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <pb n="42" facs="tcp:96238:23"/>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Albin.</speaker>
                     <p>Not I can aſſure you.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Gripe.</speaker>
                     <p>Why then I tell you, ſhe is gone (for ought I know) to the Devill.—Ent: <hi>Sent-well. Sent-well:</hi> My joy, and comfort's gone.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Sent.</speaker>
                     <p>Your torments then are coming.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Gripe.</speaker>
                     <p>You are a comforter for the Devill.
<stage>—<hi>Sent: ſtarts back feighted, and looks behind him.</hi>
                        </stage>
                     </p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Sent.</speaker>
                     <p>Again, where, where, the Gods protect me; where, what Devill.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Gripe.</speaker>
                     <p>Art thou Mad too.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Sent.</speaker>
                     <p>Yes, and tis you have made me ſo, look back upon your ſins; That Devill you talk of els, will haunt you, as he hath done me.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Gripe.</speaker>
                     <p>Leave of thy idle talk, and ſend thy ſpirits abroad to find out my <hi>Leteſia.</hi>
                     </p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Sent.</speaker>
                     <p>If ſhe be loſt find her your ſelf, for ſo you ſhall for me, know (if ſhe be gone) tis a juſt plague the Gods have layed upon you for your curſed life. Ile be no more your Drudg, and inſtrument of wickedneſſe, you have undone my ſoul, and body. You now may liſt me down, amongſt thoſe wretched ſouls, made miſerable by your tyranny. The Catalogue of which is infinite: But ile unmaſque you; And to the world diſplay ſuch horrid truths, ſhall vex the Friends of hell to ſee themſelves (by you) out down in villanie.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Gripo.</speaker>
                     <p>I am amaz'd, the whole world's conſpired againſt me. This Villain is poſſeſt. O my brains, my brains. Great <hi>Lucifer,</hi> I do conjure thee ſummon <hi>Boniface, Mahomet, Copernicus, Matchiavil, Ecphantus,</hi> and all thy Learned Polliticians in thy black <hi>Caos</hi> to invent a torment (yet unheard of) to inflict upon this ſlave. For 'tis reſolved you dye. This Councel ſet, your torments (then) grow nigh —</p>
                  </sp>
                  <stage>Exit Gripe.</stage>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Albin.</speaker>
                     <p>I fear, he is diſtracted paſt cure, you touch't him to the quick.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Sent.</speaker>
                     <p>I ſpeak but truth Sir: And I wiſh it may do good on him, he hath long gone aſtray.—</p>
                  </sp>
                  <stage>Ex: Om.</stage>
                  <stage>Ent: <hi>Rogastus: Adrastus. Leteſia, and Mettle.</hi>
                  </stage>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Rogaſt.</speaker>
                     <p>Sir, you ſtir not a foot further without a Paſs.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Adrast:</speaker>
                     <p>Which I could eaſily have procured, had I ſuſpected any ſtrictneſſe in your Garriſon.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Rogaſt:</speaker>
                     <p>Sir, the favour will be great, pleaſe you to let me have a Lodging in the Town, which I ſhall pay for. to their full content. And for yovr cuteſie, I ſhall ſtudy ſome noble requitall, worthy your acceptance. <pb n="43" facs="tcp:96238:23"/>And that I preſs thus earneſtly is in the behalf of this young Gentlewoman unuſed to travell.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Rogaſt:</speaker>
                     <p>Pray be ſatisfied, we have no lodging, or if we had, we keep none in our Garriſon for Whores.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Adraſt.</speaker>
                     <p>Thou foul mouth'd Villain, take what thou deſerv'ſt.
<stage>— <hi>Adraſt: ſtrikes him, they both draw. Rogaſt fals.</hi>
                        </stage> 
                     </p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Leteſi:</speaker>
                     <p>The Gods be mercifull, and gurard my Love.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Rogaſt:</speaker>
                     <p>Villaine; Thou haſt ſlain me.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Adraſt:</speaker>
                     <p>Thou lys't, my ſword did but it's office, it was thy tongue that hurt thee.
<stage>—Ent. <hi>Souldiers.</hi>
                        </stage>
                     </p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>1 <hi>Sould:</hi>
                     </speaker>
                     <p>Kill the ſlave, has murdered our Lieutenant.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>2 <hi>Sould:</hi>
                     </speaker>
                     <l>Hold, let's carry him to our Governor.</l>
                     <l>Bear the Lieutenant to his Quarter, make haſte, and call our</l>
                     <l>Chirurgion, leaſt he bleed to Death
<stage>—<hi>Ex: Sould. bearing of thy Lieutenant.</hi>
                        </stage>
                     </l>
                     <l>Come Sir, you that dare kill our Officers in our</l>
                     <l>own Garriſon, you, and your Minion,</l>
                     <l>muſt along with us.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Adraſt.</speaker>
                     <l>Honeſt Souldiers, as you are men, procure in ſome good</l>
                     <l>Houſe, a Lodging for this Gentlewoman, for which,</l>
                     <l>I liberally will reward you.</l>
                     <l>What I have done, my life ſhall anſwer.</l>
                     <l>Lay not uncivill hands on her, ner'c harbored evil thought.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>1 <hi>Sould.</hi>
                     </speaker>
                     <l>Trouble not your ſelf. The Governor will provide</l>
                     <l>Lodging for you both, ſhall hold you
<stage>Leteſia faints away.</stage>
                     </l>
                     <l>Look to the Wench, ſhe faints.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Adraſt.</speaker>
                     <p>Angels protect thy Life, how it is ſweeteſt.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>2 <hi>Sould:</hi>
                     </speaker>
                     <p>She comes again unto her ſelfe. Miſtreſſe cheer up, (poor Gentlewoman) heres none ſhall hurt you.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Leteſi:</speaker>
                     <p>I can receive no harm, if he be well.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Adraſt.</speaker>
                     <l>Why I am well (my Dear.)</l>
                     <l>Souldier, your Language ſpeaks Chriſtianitie.</l>
                     <l>Pray drink this, your reward is ſtill behind
<stage>—<hi>Gives him mony</hi>
                        </stage>
                     </l>
                     <l>if you'l aſſiſt this poor diſtreſſed Maid.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>2 <hi>Sould:</hi>
                     </speaker>
                     <p>Sir I thank you, but can do nothing till our Governor hath diſpos'd of you. Then if we can do you, or her any ſervice, you ſhall command us.—</p>
                  </sp>
                  <stage>Ex: Om:</stage>
                  <stage>Ent: <hi>Albinus. Sympronio.</hi>
                  </stage>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Symph:</speaker>
                     <p>Was he ſo much inraged.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Albin:</speaker>
                     <l>By all the Gods, he will run mad, (I fear.)</l>
                     <l>And that ſame Rogve, that we poſeſt, the Devill haunted ſo,</l>
                     <l>is ſo far from jealous that we did abuſe him.</l>
                     <l>That he will ingage his ſoul (which now he doth intend</l>
                     <l>to Husband to his beſt advantage.)</l>
                     <l>The Devill really haunted him.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Symph.</speaker>
                     <p>Works it any good on the flint harted ſlave.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Albin:</speaker>
                     <p>The moſt reformed man alive; And preaches nothing</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Gripe-man:</speaker>
                     <p>but he's damn'd. And that he <pb n="44" facs="tcp:96238:24"/>thunders in his ears, to the great terrour of his guilty Conſcience.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Symph:</speaker>
                     <p>How takes <hi>Gripe-man</hi> ſuch language from his Mercury?</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Albin:</speaker>
                     <p>Why faith, but ſcurvily; And conjures up the Devils to invent unheard of torments to afflict him.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Symph:</speaker>
                     <l>I cannot gueſs, till he hath ſpent his fury.</l>
                     <l>I long to hear of <hi>Adraſtus</hi> his ſafe arrivall with his Miſtreſſe,</l>
                     <l>would one of us had gone along with him,</l>
                     <l>he was but weakly guarded, with his Man <hi>Mettle.</hi>
                     </l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Symph:</speaker>
                     <p>It was his own deſire.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Albin:</speaker>
                     <p>Tis true, his Letters, which I ſpeedily expect, will cleer our doubts.—</p>
                  </sp>
                  <stage>Ex: Am:</stage>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div n="5" type="act">
               <head>ACT V.</head>
               <div n="1" type="scene">
                  <head>SCENE I.</head>
                  <stage>Enter <hi>Gripe-man: Sol:</hi>
                  </stage>
                  <lg>
                     <l>BE mercifull you Gods; And let me ſee my Child</l>
                     <l>before my breath depart this totterd manſion.</l>
                     <l>But how dare I invoke the Gods that muſt be juſt</l>
                     <l>in puniſhing my unexampled life.</l>
                  </lg>
                  <lg>
                     <l>How gaſhly (now) the wounds in my black Conſcience</l>
                     <l>doth appear. So numberleſſe, and mighty are my horrid ſins.</l>
                     <l>The remnant of my life, only to think them or'e</l>
                     <l>would be too little, what time would they require</l>
                     <l>(then) to be ſorry for.</l>
                     <l>Firſt, let me (with advantage) make amends, thoſe many</l>
                     <l>ſouls by my unheard of Villainies, made miſerable,</l>
                     <l>whoſe Prayers, may as a Cordiall refreſh my far ſpent ſoul.</l>
                     <l>My horrid treaſon againſt my juſt, and ſacred Prince</l>
                     <l>for vengeance cal's aloud.</l>
                     <l>The ruine of my Country, which (to my beſt of power)</l>
                     <l>I have been actor in. The leaſt of which conſidered,</l>
                     <l>I am but gently ſcourg'd.</l>
                     <l>O my <hi>Leteſia,</hi> poor innocent Girle, thou haſt not fin'd</l>
                     <l>to be a ſufferer with they cruell Father. Twas I conſpir'd</l>
                     <l>thy ruine—it muſt be ſo, my covetouſneſſe</l>
                     <l>to match her to young <hi>Avaritia,</hi> hath forc't her to this flight.</l>
                     <l>You Gods above, reſtore me but my Child; And il'e become</l>
                     <l>your faithfull Penicent.</l>
                     <l>And what I have unjuſtly from poor ſouls detain'd,</l>
                     <l>I will reſtore, till all cry hold, they h've gaind.—</l>
                  </lg>
                  <stage>Ex</stage>
                  <stage>Enter <hi>three Souldiers.</hi>
                  </stage>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>1 <hi>Sould:</hi>
                     </speaker>
                     <p>Have you heard how the Councell of War hath diſpoſed of the young Gallant that wounded our Lieutenant, t'was a ſhrewd hurt, t'was ten to one he had not kild him.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>3 <hi>Sould:</hi>
                     </speaker>
                     <p>I hear he ſhall be hangd.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>2 <hi>Sould:</hi>
                     </speaker>
                     <l>You are miſtaken, for when he had his ſentence to be hang'd,</l>
                     <l>hating ſo baſe a Death, he prov'd he had been an Officer</l>
                     <pb n="45" facs="tcp:96238:24"/>
                     <l>In the late war againſt us. And muſt be ſhot to death.</l>
                     <l>Truſt me, I pity him, he ſeems a gallant perſon.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>1. <hi>Sould.</hi>
                     </speaker>
                     <l>Me thinks 'tis great injuſtice he ſhould die,</l>
                     <l>The Lieutenant (as the Chirurgion doth give in) being likely</l>
                     <l>To recover.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>2. <hi>Sould.</hi>
                     </speaker>
                     <l>'Tis true, but ſince it is their pleaſure he ſhall die</l>
                     <l>What cannot they pretend to take away his life.</l>
                     <l>They ſay he fell upon our Guard, and that (though not</l>
                     <l>Diſcovered) he had more aid which fled, though</l>
                     <l>I dare ſay, there's nothing of it true, could I but ſave his life</l>
                     <l>I willingly would venture a limbe.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>1. <hi>Sould.</hi>
                     </speaker>
                     <p>And he that ſhoots him, may his hands rot off for me.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>2. <hi>Sould.</hi>
                     </speaker>
                     <l>Amen, ſay I. Come let's to the Parade, where we</l>
                     <l>Shall know, what hour he dies, and who are</l>
                     <l>Choſe his marks men.—</l>
                     <stage>Ex. Om.</stage>
                     <stage>Enter <hi>Atheos, Sol.</hi>
                     </stage>
                     <l>My eyes have not beheld a more diviner ſhape.</l>
                     <l>Her beauty hath inflamed me to that height, I muſt</l>
                     <l>Injoy her, though I ſurvive no minutes after.</l>
                     <l>She dotes upon that ſlave that wounded my Lieutenant, for which</l>
                     <l>He dies, for when ſhe knows him dead, her love</l>
                     <l>Like the affections of moſt women, will die with him.</l>
                     <l>But ſhould ſhe continue obſtinate, and hate me, as having</l>
                     <l>Power to ſave his life, I then were further off obtaining</l>
                     <l>My deſiers. But I will court her high. Rich gifts are</l>
                     <l>Baits, that beauty often bites at. Laborious cunning,</l>
                     <l>With a weighty purſe, in time will do it.</l>
                     <l>If nothing will prevail, this follows next by courſe</l>
                     <l>What I not fairly can, Ile do by force.—</l>
                  </sp>
                  <stage>Ex.</stage>
                  <stage>Enter <hi>Albin. Symph.</hi>
                  </stage>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Albin.</speaker>
                     <l>I wounder much we hear not from <hi>Adraſtus:</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>I know no reaſon for it, I have been ſtrangely troubled</l>
                     <l>Since his departure, the Gods grant all be well.</l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Symphronio:</hi> you ſhall along with me to old <hi>Gripemans</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>To ſee if he continue in his Frantick fury.</l>
                     <l>Beſides we ſhall of <hi>Clarathea,</hi> underſtand what courſe</l>
                     <l>He hath taken in ſearch of his fair Daughter.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Symph.</speaker>
                     <p>God when you will I am for you. —</p>
                  </sp>
                  <stage>Enter <hi>Mettle.</hi>
                  </stage>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Albin.</speaker>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Mettle:</hi> I ſomewhat fear the goodneſs of thy news</l>
                     <l>Thy looks betray ſome ſad miſchance.
<stage>—<hi>Mett.</hi> weeps.</stage>
                     </l>
                     <l>Nay, if thou weep'ſt 'tis vain but to ſuſpect it.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Mett.</speaker>
                     <l>'Tis ſad indeed. For if you make not haſte, you'l never ſee</l>
                     <l>My Maſter more alive.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Symph.</speaker>
                     <p>Is he ſo dangerouſly ſick.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Mett.</speaker>
                     <l>No, Sir, he wants no health, this letter will take you off
<stage>—gives <hi>Albin.</hi> a Letter.</stage>
                     </l>
                     <l>From wondring at my language.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Albin.</speaker>
                     <l>He muſt not long out-live him, by whoſe means he falls.
<stage>—<hi>Alb.</hi> reads.</stage>
                     </l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Symphronio</speaker>
                     <l>peruſe thoſe ſad contents.
<stage>—<hi>Symph.</hi> reads.</stage>
                     </l>
                     <pb n="46" facs="tcp:96238:25"/>
                     <l>Come, come <hi>Symphronio:</hi> 't is no time to grieve;</l>
                     <l>But to reſolve, what 's to be done, where's fair <hi>Leteſia:</hi>
                     </l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Mett.</speaker>
                     <l>She is cloſe priſoner in the Governour's houſe,</l>
                     <l>And none but ſuch as he appoints, comes near her.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Albin.</speaker>
                     <l>Poor Gentlewoman, I will redeem thy <hi>Adraſtus</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>Or periſh in the attempt.</l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Symphronio:</hi> I ſhall intreat thee, ſtay (yet) a while</l>
                     <l>In Town, and viſit <hi>Gripeman</hi> as my Brother:</l>
                     <l>The reſt contrive thy ſelf, onely to ſee what courſe</l>
                     <l>He ſteeres to finde his Daughter.</l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Clarathea</hi> ſhall along with me, her preſent ſervice</l>
                     <l>May ſtand <hi>Leteſia:</hi> in ſome ſted.</l>
                     <l>And be confident, you ſhall (by Mettle) ſpeedily hear</l>
                     <l>From me, how all things ſtands.</l>
                     <l>For ſo it may fall out, that you may do great ſervis</l>
                     <l>For <hi>Adraſtus</hi> here.</l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Mettle:</hi> run to <hi>Clarathea:</hi> tell her, ſhe muſt provide</l>
                     <l>(Immediately) to go a long with me to her Miſtreſs.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Mett.</speaker>
                     <p>I ſhall Sir,</p>
                  </sp>
                  <stage>— <hi>Ex. Mett</hi>
                  </stage>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Symph.</speaker>
                     <l>Since you conceive my ſtay may be a furtherance to my</l>
                     <l>Diſtreſſed friend, I faithfully ſhall ſtudy (here) to act</l>
                     <l>Whatever your directions ſhall imploy me in,</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Albin.</speaker>
                     <l>Thanks noble <hi>Symphronio:</hi> Fare thee well</l>
                     <l>My brains are all on fire.</l>
                     <l>I long to act, what, I in heart deſire</l>
                  </sp>
                  <stage>— <hi>Ex. Am.</hi>
                  </stage>
                  <stage>Enter <hi>Atheos, Leteſia.</hi>
                  </stage>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Athe.</speaker>
                     <l>Lady, you do exceed in grief, you wrong your beauty</l>
                     <l>To lament for what's not in your power to remedy:</l>
                     <l>He is but a man you grieve for: And there are more</l>
                     <l>It'h World as handſomely active as he.</l>
                     <l>Clear thoſe fair eyes, and tell me, if my ſelf</l>
                     <l>(I muſt confeſs unworthy) may deſerve your love.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Leteſi.</speaker>
                     <p>Do you love me then.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Athe.</speaker>
                     <p>My actions (fair one,) ſhall ſatisfie that doubt.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Leteſi.</speaker>
                     <p>I take you at your word, then ſet my husband free.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Athe.</speaker>
                     <p>That's not within the compaſs of my power to do.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Leteſi.</speaker>
                     <l>You are a diſſembler, and prophane the name of Love.</l>
                     <l>This is not nobly done to triumph over a weak woman,</l>
                     <l>(Through her ill fate) your ſlave:</l>
                     <l>The conqueſt you will gain by't, may well be added</l>
                     <l>Amongſt the Trophies of your great victories</l>
                     <l>Achiev'd in this rebellion.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Athe.</speaker>
                     <l>Lady, the uſage you have found (and from a ſtranger too)</l>
                     <l>Deſerves more civil language. But i'le forget it.</l>
                     <l>And doubt not, this fooliſh paſſion over,</l>
                     <l>But you'l conſider, and be ſorry for it.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Leteſi.</speaker>
                     <l>Never. For know, lay it in thy power to make me empreſs</l>
                     <pb facs="tcp:96238:25"/>
                     <l>Of the World. I would not out-live my husband</l>
                     <l>Many hours to injoy it.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Athe.</speaker>
                     <l>Lady. I ſee this is no time to urge a ſerious anſwer from you.</l>
                     <l>But yet remember, you are in my power, and (if you pleaſe)</l>
                     <l>You may be happy. Think on it.</l>
                     <l>So fare you well.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <stage>— <hi>Ex. Atheos.</hi>
                  </stage>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Leteſia.</speaker>
                     <l>Where am I, or of whom can I expect relief.</l>
                     <l>Was ever wretched creature ſo miſerably unhappy as I am.</l>
                     <l>And ſhall <hi>Leteſia</hi> live, and my <hi>Adraſtus</hi> die,</l>
                     <l>And I his murderer?</l>
                     <l>Thou might'ſt have lived brave ſoul the patern (ſtill)</l>
                     <l>Of virtue. But I have robb'd the World of ſuch a juel</l>
                     <l>The Gods eſteem'd too rich, to bleſs this earth with.</l>
                     <l>I muſt (in juſtice) ſacrifice my life to him that I have ruin'd,</l>
                     <l>For on my knees (before the gods) I vow
<stage>—ſhe kneels:</stage>
                     </l>
                     <l>When I ſhall underſtand his death, cauſed by this</l>
                     <l>Act of mine, one hour not to out-live him.</l>
                     <l>There is no hope of mercy (on honourable tearms)</l>
                     <l>From ſuch a heap of ſin, as this.</l>
                     <l>Was ever woman courted (by a villain) to her diſhonour</l>
                     <l>Juſt in the act of murdering her husband?</l>
                     <l>And ſhall I not revenge thy death (brave ſoul)</l>
                     <l>It is decreed.</l>
                     <l>That hand that murders thee, that heart ſhall bleed.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <stage>—<hi>Ex. Leteſia.</hi>
                  </stage>
                  <stage>Enter <hi>Albinus,</hi> and <hi>Clarathea,</hi> both diſguiſed</stage>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Albin.</speaker>
                     <l>Could'ſt thou <hi>(Clarathea)</hi> readily finde the way to the</l>
                     <l>Houſe we came from.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Clarath.</speaker>
                     <p>Moſt undoubtedly I could.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Albin.</speaker>
                     <p>And give perfect directions to <hi>Leteſia.</hi>
                     </p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Clarath.</speaker>
                     <l>Such, as ſhe ſhall not miſs.</l>
                     <l>But Sir, are you confident, they will be honeſt, in what</l>
                     <l>(I muſt confeſs) they chearfully have undertook</l>
                     <l>to be moſt ſecret in?</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Albin!</speaker>
                     <l>O <hi>Clarathea.</hi> The woman was my Nurſe, whoſe milk</l>
                     <l>Innocent, as the Livory it wore, ſtill ſympathized</l>
                     <l>With Loyal bloud. She can betray nothing</l>
                     <l>But her own fear, how much ſhe wants to do.</l>
                     <l>Not ſuffer for her friends.</l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Adrastus</hi> and <hi>Leteſia's</hi> lives, thrown upon leſs aſſurance</l>
                     <l>Might (though in their ſafeties) juſtly</l>
                     <l>Have call'd me murderer.</l>
                     <l>Pre thee <hi>Clarathea:</hi> how do I look, May I not paſs

<stage>— <hi>turns him about,</hi>
                        </stage>
                     </l>
                     <l>For currant, without a ſuperſcription written</l>
                     <l>On my back, this is a Traitour?</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Clarath.</speaker>
                     <l>You may. But Sir, the danger's great you undertake.</l>
                     <l>Do'ſt thou conſider mine, and ſlight thy own.</l>
                     <l>Thou wonder of thy Sex. Thou mak'ſt me (bluſhing)</l>
                     <pb facs="tcp:96238:26"/>
                     <l>To confeſs, that when I have paid my debt to friendſhip</l>
                     <l>By laying down this inconſiderable life.</l>
                     <l>I have but initated thee, a woman.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Clarath.</speaker>
                     <l>Pardon me worthy Sir, I do confeſs, I may reſolve,</l>
                     <l>But yet, may ſtagger too, in the performance of ſuch a piece of friendſhip</l>
                     <l>Had I not a guide to light me, more ſtrange</l>
                     <l>Than is a blazing Star.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Albin.</speaker>
                     <l>It is too pitifully ſtrange (indeed) to finde true friendſhip.</l>
                     <l>Farewell (brave ſoul.) Be carefull of the hour
<stage>— <hi>takes her by the hand.</hi>
                        </stage>
                     </l>
                     <l>And directions of the way. For <hi>Leteſia's</hi> impatient Love,</l>
                     <l>Should ſhe but miſs <hi>Adraſtus:</hi> ſome few minutes,</l>
                     <l>Might be occaſion of their certain ruine.</l>
                     <l>This kiſs, ſo, farewell earth
<stage>— <hi>Kiſſes her.</hi>
                        </stage>
                     </l>
                     <l>Our meetings next in Heaven.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <stage>— <hi>Ex. Albinus.</hi>
                  </stage>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Clarath.</speaker>
                     <l>And may the noble example of thy friendſhip</l>
                     <l>Be as a Star to future ages</l>
                     <l>To light them unto virtue.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <stage>—<hi>Ex. Clarath.</hi>
                  </stage>
                  <stage>Enter <hi>Gripeman. Symphronio.</hi>
                  </stage>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Gripe.</speaker>
                     <l>Sir, if I not miſtake you are a ſtranger to me.</l>
                     <l>What may your buſineſs be.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Symph.</speaker>
                     <l>Sir, I am brother to a Gentleman (made happy in your</l>
                     <l>Acquaintance) his name <hi>Adraſtus.</hi>
                     </l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Gripe.</speaker>
                     <l>Away out of my ſight, I know your buſineſs well.</l>
                     <l>Sir, know, I have left thoſe curſed ways, that would have</l>
                     <l>Headlong hurried me to Hell. Be gone I ſay.</l>
                     <l>And if you be his brother, tell him I do adviſe him</l>
                     <l>To repent, and not betray his friends.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Symph.</speaker>
                     <l>This is ſtrange, he is converted.</l>
                     <l>I muſt another way to work.
<stage>— <hi>Aſide.</hi>
                        </stage>
                     </l>
                     <l>Sir, you do miſtake my buſineſs. My brother not being well,</l>
                     <l>And ſorry to think what he had undertaken, ſent me</l>
                     <l>To let you know his change of minde.</l>
                     <l>And bade me tell you, in any thing that's noble, and honeſt,</l>
                     <l>He faithfully would ſerve you.</l>
                     <l>But to betray a friend, or do an act unworthy,</l>
                     <l>He would not for the World.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Gripe.</speaker>
                     <l>'Tis honeſtly reſolved, you now are welcom.</l>
                     <l>I love your brother for it. Young man follow his ſteps.</l>
                     <l>And covet not by baſe ſiniſter ways to hoard up wealth,</l>
                     <l>Leaſt thou be Father but of one virtuous childe,
<stage>— <hi>He weeps.</hi>
                        </stage>
                     </l>
                     <l>And have that taken from thee.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Symph.</speaker>
                     <l>Sir, your tears hath eaſily gain'd credit in my belief</l>
                     <l>It hath been your ſad caſe.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Gripe.</speaker>
                     <l>Indeed it hath, and could I but injoy my Childe,</l>
                     <l>I would (with comfortable tears) labour to waſh</l>
                     <l>My too bad ſins away.</l>
                     <l>But 't was my fault, ſeeking to match her to a covetious</l>
                     <pb n="49" facs="tcp:96238:26"/>
                     <l>Wretch, ſhe thus deſerted me.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Symph.</speaker>
                     <l>Suppoſe, in this her time of abſence, ſhe ſhould beſtow</l>
                     <l>Her ſelf on a more noble choice, though not ſo rich,</l>
                     <l>Could you forgive her, and (with joy) receive</l>
                     <l>Your Childe again.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Gripe.</speaker>
                     <l>O worthy Sir, there's Muſick in your tongue, receive her,</l>
                     <l>Yes, next to the joys above, on earth, I know none like it.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Symph.</speaker>
                     <l>I am glad to hear you ſay ſo,</l>
                     <l>And though I am a ſtranger, to your Daughters flight</l>
                     <l>And place of being, keep your houſe, and I doubt not</l>
                     <l>But ere long to be the happy bringer of the joyfull news</l>
                     <l>Your Daughter's well, and ſhew you where ſhe is.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <stage>— <hi>Ex. Symph.</hi>
                  </stage>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Gripe.</speaker>
                     <l>Bleſſings go with thee, thou art my good Angel.</l>
                     <l>How gracious are the Gods (ſo ſoon) to hear my prayers.</l>
                     <l>The hope I have of what I would injoy,</l>
                     <l>Hath made me young again.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <stage>— <hi>Ex. Gripe.</hi>
                  </stage>
                  <stage>Enter <hi>Adraſtus, Albinus</hi> as in Priſon.</stage>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Adraſt.</speaker>
                     <l>Dear friend leave off to urge it.</l>
                     <l>Canſt thou believe <hi>Adraſtus,</hi> values his wretched life</l>
                     <l>At ſuch a rate to purchaſe it with the loſs of thine.</l>
                     <l>I ſhould be branded for a Coward upon record, ſhould I accept it.</l>
                     <l>No, no, Thou miracle of friendſhip, preſerve thy noble life,</l>
                     <l>To imploy it in thy Prince, and Countreys cauſe.</l>
                     <l>There wants ſuch guides to honour, and deſert.</l>
                     <l>Poor <hi>Leteſia:</hi> I call the Gods to witneſs, were't not to part</l>
                     <l>With thee, my death, would be as welcom as my ſleep.</l>
                     <l>But ſince it is the pleaſure of the Gods, we ſhall not here</l>
                     <l>(On earth) injoy. I freely do beſtow her on thee. <hi>Albinus,</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>Take her, and be confident, thou wilt finde her worthy</l>
                     <l>Thy acceptance. And may you live long, and happy</l>
                     <l>And once a year,</l>
                     <l>Water my ſad remembrance with a tear.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <l>Pardon me <hi>Adraſtus,</hi> for I muſt ſpeak my thoughts.</l>
                     <l>Your language, or religion, I am miſtaken in.</l>
                     <l>You would bequeath fair <hi>Leteſia</hi> to me, your ſelf</l>
                     <l>Reſolves to Murder. Hath ſhe ſo ill deſerved,</l>
                     <l>For her return of Love, and loſs of friends</l>
                     <l>(Onely for your ſake.) And will you requite her love</l>
                     <l>With taking away her life.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Adraſt.</speaker>
                     <p>Protect me innocence, I underſtand you not.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Albin.</speaker>
                     <l>You ſhall do then. For know, <hi>Leteſia</hi> hath ſworn</l>
                     <l>Not many hours to out-live you, which ſhee'l perform</l>
                     <l>Maugre, the Worlds reſiſtance.</l>
                     <l>Can you deny, to ſave that noble life, that hath engaged her</l>
                     <l>Own (ſo far) for yours, and make her own white hands</l>
                     <l>The inſtruments of her death. Be mercifull, if not for pitie,</l>
                     <l>For ſhame of th' World, which will cry out in Ballads</l>
                     <pb n="50" facs="tcp:96238:27"/>
                     <l>'Gainſt the Murder. <hi>Clarathea</hi> too (That faithful'lſt of</l>
                     <l>Servants) at the ſame time ſhift's cloaths with your <hi>Leteſia:</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>Who will not fail to meet you at the houſe appointed.</l>
                     <l>Where ſhould ſhe miſs you, her impatient Love might put</l>
                     <l>The whole frame of our great buſineſs out of joynt.</l>
                     <l>And, for that you do ſuppoſe, I looſe my ſafety in preſerving</l>
                     <l>Yours, you much miſtake, I have not gone ſo ſimply to work</l>
                     <l>But I have ſecured that.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Adraſt</speaker>
                     <l>Make me but happy in that aſſurance.</l>
                     <l>And il'e deſire to live, if but to call thee friend.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Albin.</speaker>
                     <l>Know then, I have brib'd, ſome of your guard</l>
                     <l>To aſſiſt me in my eſcape. Come, come, no words, withdraw,</l>
                     <l>And let us ſhift our cloaths. Be confident in your going out,</l>
                     <l>And no man can ſuſpect you.</l>
                     <l>Be ſure, keep freſh in your remembrance, the directions</l>
                     <l>To the houſe you meet at, as what moſt near concerns you.</l>
                     <l>I cannot hear, therefore make no reply,</l>
                     <l>No complements (dear friend) when death's ſo nigh.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <stage>—<hi>Ex. Om.</hi>
                  </stage>
                  <stage>Enter <hi>Atheos,</hi> and <hi>Souldiers.</hi>
                  </stage>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Athe.</speaker>
                     <p>Where ſtands the wind,</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>1. <hi>Sould.</hi>
                     </speaker>
                     <p>North Eaſt.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Athe.</speaker>
                     <l>Run to the Key, and give order, the long Boat be made</l>
                     <l>Ready, and mann'd with able men. I'le out to Sea anon,</l>
                     <l>Two, or three leagues. Saw you your Lieutenant lately.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>2. <hi>Sould.</hi>
                     </speaker>
                     <p>Sir, I did this morning, and found him pretty hearty.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Athe.</speaker>
                     <p>Where are your Serjeants.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>2. Sould.</speaker>
                     <p>Sir, I left them at their quarter but now.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Athe.</speaker>
                     <l>Go, and from me give them ſtrickt charge they ſpeedily</l>
                     <l>Draw out all thoſe commanded men I gave them order for.</l>
                     <l>Ile have the priſoner ſhot before I put to Sea.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <stage>—<hi>Ex. Athe.</hi>
                  </stage>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>3. <hi>Sould.</hi>
                     </speaker>
                     <l>Now what ſay you, you that were confident</l>
                     <l>He ſhould not die for this.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>2. <hi>Sould.</hi>
                     </speaker>
                     <l>Why, I ſay I am ſorry for it, and could almoſt die for him:</l>
                     <l>There is no Juſtice he ſhould ſuffer death for this;</l>
                     <l>For what he did he was provok't too by uncivill language.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>3. <hi>Sould.</hi>
                     </speaker>
                     <l>'Tis all the Juſtice (now) in faſhion, every man in office</l>
                     <l>Makes his will, his Law. Were all the Souldiers</l>
                     <l>In the Garriſon of my minde, he ſhould ſhoot him himſelf</l>
                     <l>And that (I think) he dares not do, and</l>
                     <l>Look him in the face, come let's go.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <stage>—<hi>Ex. Sould</hi>
                  </stage>
                  <stage>Enter <hi>Atheos</hi> and <hi>Clarathea</hi> in <hi>Leteſias</hi> habit.</stage>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Athe.</speaker>
                     <p>'Tis your beſt way to tell me where ſhe is gone.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Clarath.</speaker>
                     <l>It lies not in my power, or if it did, can you think</l>
                     <l>I, that have undertaken thus much for her, will now betray her.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Athe.</speaker>
                     <p>Art' not afraid of Torture.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Clarath.</speaker>
                     <l>Not I, I can aſſure you, I came to undergo</l>
                     <l>What you d are lay upon me.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <pb n="51" facs="tcp:96238:27"/>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Athe.</speaker>
                     <l>That's nobly ſpoken yet. Let me but this night enjoy thee</l>
                     <l>And ile not onely forgive thee all, and ſet thee free our</l>
                     <l>Garriſon; But generouſly reward thee.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Clarath.</speaker>
                     <l>Sir, I thank you for your courteous proffer, but ile not buy</l>
                     <l>My freedom at that rate, Had my Siſter ſtayed</l>
                     <l>(Perhaps) you might have had her conſent.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Athe.</speaker>
                     <l>She jeers me.
<stage>— aſide.</stage>
                     </l>
                     <l>I do believe I ſhould, was ſhe your Siſter then.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Clarath.</speaker>
                     <p>She was.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Athe.</speaker>
                     <p>And do you love her ſo well to die for her.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Clarath.</speaker>
                     <p>Indeed I do.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Athe.</speaker>
                     <l>Then ſpeedily prepare, your time is ſhort:</l>
                     <l>Or will you (yet) conſent, do but conſider, what it is to live,</l>
                     <l>Which weighed with what you fooliſhly deny,</l>
                     <l>And you muſt yield in reaſon.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Clarath.</speaker>
                     <l>Indeed I muſt not, and when I do to ſave this wretched life.</l>
                     <l>May all diſeaſes mankinde hateth moſt</l>
                     <l>Proclaim it on my fore-head.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <stage>Enter 1. <hi>Souldier.</hi>
                  </stage>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Athe.</speaker>
                     <p>So brave:</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>1. <hi>Sould.</hi>
                     </speaker>
                     <l>Sir, the priſoner wounded our Lieutenant is fled,</l>
                     <l>And another in his cloaths left in his room.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Athe.</speaker>
                     <l>Then (by the Gods) the Marſhall ſhall to Torture.</l>
                     <l>This is brave juggling. Lady, you know (now) who this</l>
                     <l>Valiant villain is, that dares die for his friend.</l>
                     <l>But you have Engines (I doubt not) now at work</l>
                     <l>For your eſcapes. But ile prevent them.</l>
                     <l>And ſince you are ſo valiant you dare die,</l>
                     <l>You ſhall have your deſire. <hi>Souldier,</hi> run to the Goal</l>
                     <l>And let the Gallant know, at five a clock this evening</l>
                     <l>He dies. For, by my Tortured Soul, at my return from Sea,</l>
                     <stage>Ex. Sould.</stage>
                     <l>(Without you do repent, and yield to my deſires)</l>
                     <l>You both ſhall ſuffer death.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Clarath.</speaker>
                     <l>You'l eaſe me of a pain, ther's nothing elſe</l>
                     <l>Can quit me from.</l>
                     <stage>—<hi>Ex. Om.</hi>
                     </stage>
                     <stage>Enter <hi>Adriſtus, Solus.</hi>
                     </stage>
                     <l>What are we men, we ſhould deſire to live in this frail</l>
                     <l>World, where there is nothing certain, but uncertainty</l>
                     <l>To day, with the riſing of the Sun, rais'd to the height</l>
                     <l>Of what our joys can aim at. And by his ſetting,</l>
                     <l>Ruined, and forgotten: A friend
<stage>—<hi>The Ecche,</hi>
                        </stage>
                     </l>
                     <l>Twas friend I ſaid.
<stage>— <hi>Anſwers friend.</hi>
                        </stage>
                     </l>
                     <l>Hark how theretorting Eccho (ſhrilly) through the grove
<stage>Eccho anſwers again.</stage>
                     </l>
                     <l>Conveighs the name of friend, and reſts its ſelf,</l>
                     <l>As weary in the Toyling ſearch</l>
                     <l>Of what deſerved that name.</l>
                     <l>And ſhall my friend, (the worthieſt of what deſerves</l>
                     <l>That Title) die to preſerve my life. No</l>
                     <l>Dear <hi>Leteſia:</hi> whom (by the Gods) I love, and value</l>
                     <pb n="52" facs="tcp:96238:28"/>
                     <l>Next my honour, thou muſt excuſe me.</l>
                     <l>Too well (I know) <hi>Albinus</hi> did but pretend the way</l>
                     <l>Of his own ſafety, to encourage me, in the ſecuring mine.</l>
                     <l>How ſoon that fatal ſentence of his death</l>
                     <l>May be pronounc'd, I know not.</l>
                     <l>Something I muſt pretend to fair <hi>Leteſia,</hi> of buſineſs</l>
                     <l>For ſome time, which will be difficulty obtain'd.</l>
                     <l>Forgive me (my <hi>Leteſia.</hi>) my honour is more than life</l>
                     <l>Juſtice, and friendſhip (now) parts man, and wife.</l>
                     <stage>—<hi>Exit.</hi>
                     </stage>
                     <stage>Enter <hi>Albinus</hi> in <hi>Adraſtus</hi> cloaths, and two Souldiers.</stage>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Sould.</speaker>
                     <l>Sir, it is the pleaſure of our Governour, that I ſhould let</l>
                     <l>You know, about five a clock this evening, you muſt prepare to die.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Albin.</speaker>
                     <l>Thanks honeſt Souldier, there's for thy news
<stage>— gives him money.</stage>
                     </l>
                     <l>He ſhall not take me unprovided?</l>
                     <l>Know'ſt thou what death, he is reſolved I ſuffer</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>1. <hi>Sould.</hi>
                     </speaker>
                     <p>Shot, I believe Sir, for there's no order to the contrary.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Albin.</speaker>
                     <p>It is a noble death, I thank him for.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>2. <hi>Sould.</hi>
                     </speaker>
                     <l>Would I could ſave your life.</l>
                     <l>'Tis pity ſuch true friendſhip ſhould be cut off.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Albin.</speaker>
                     <l>Thank thee, noble Souldier.
<stage>—A great ſhout without.</stage>
                     </l>
                     <l>What may this ſhout of joy proclaim.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>1. <hi>Sould.</hi>
                     </speaker>
                     <l>Truly, Sir I know not,</l>
                     <stage>— Enter <hi>Corporal.</hi>
                     </stage>
                     <l>How now Corporal, know you the reaſon of this ſhout.</l>
                     <l>Hark, the great Guns are fired too.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Corpor.</speaker>
                     <l>Yes, it is to welcom a Gentleman aſhore</l>
                     <l>That this day ſaved our Governour's life.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>2. <hi>Sould.</hi>
                     </speaker>
                     <p>By what ſtrange means, there was no ſtorm at Sea.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Corpor.</speaker>
                     <l>No, no, 't was thus. Our Governour, no ſooner had put out to Sea,</l>
                     <l>(Whether to take the air, or make himſelf Sea-ſick,</l>
                     <l>I know not) But a ſmall Boat of Pirats, well mann'd</l>
                     <l>With Musketeers, hid in a ſmall creek, whipt out,</l>
                     <l>And got between our ſhore and them. Who being far</l>
                     <l>Too nimble for our Boat, having more Oars,</l>
                     <l>Soon boarded them, who to ſave their lives were forc'd</l>
                     <l>To yield. When (to the amazement of our Governour,)</l>
                     <l>This Gentleman now landed, (and then their Captain)</l>
                     <l>Clap't in our Governour's hand, a good broad ſword,</l>
                     <l>Bidding our men (if ever) now fight for Liberty, and injoy it.</l>
                     <l>Himſelf giving a brave teſtimony to our doubtfull men</l>
                     <l>By the death of two, or three of the chief Pyrats, that he was in earneſt.</l>
                     <l>This done, they all fell to it. The Pyrats diſtracted at this</l>
                     <l>Surpriſal, not knowing what to think (and leſs to do)</l>
                     <l>The major part was ſoon cut off, the reſt brought priſoners in<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
                     </l>
                     <l>In this ſame skirmiſh, we had but two men hurt.</l>
                     <l>And this brave Gentleman (the preſerver of their lives)</l>
                     <l>Received two wounds i'th' ſhoulder.</l>
                     <pb n="45" facs="tcp:96238:28"/>
                     <l>Now you may judg, whether our Governor hath not juſt</l>
                     <l>cauſe (nobly) to entertain this ſtranger.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>2 <hi>Sould.</hi>
                     </speaker>
                     <l>Come let's go ſee him.</l>
                     <l>Sir, we wiſh it lay within the compaſs of our powers to ſerve you.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Albin.</speaker>
                     <p>I thank you honeſt Souldiers.</p>
                     <stage>—<hi>Ex: Om:</hi>
                     </stage>
                     <stage>Ent. <hi>Leteſia. Sol. diſguiſed.</hi>
                     </stage>
                     <l>I was a curſt to let him go, what buſineſſe can he have here</l>
                     <l>in a place he is a ſtranger to.</l>
                     <l>His noble ſoul will not endure to let <hi>Albinus</hi> ſuffer</l>
                     <l>in his cauſe. And this a plot (by him) contrived for to</l>
                     <l>procure my ſafety. You powers above, that looks with joy</l>
                     <l>on penitential tears.
<stage>— <hi>She weeps.</hi>
                        </stage>
                     </l>
                     <l>behold a poor beblubbered Maid on bended knees
<stage>— <hi>She kneels.</hi>
                        </stage>
                     </l>
                     <l>to implore your mercy.</l>
                     <l>Let not your vengeance fall upon the innocent, for the</l>
                     <l>Guilties ſake, ſpare my <hi>Adraſtus,</hi> and lay your load on me.
<stage>She riſeth.</stage>
                     </l>
                     <l>But if my cruell Fathers fins cannot be waſh't off, but with</l>
                     <l>our bloods, we'l make one ſacrifice.</l>
                     <l>And ſince our bodies are denied to enjoy,</l>
                     <l>our bloods ſhall mingle.</l>
                     <l>And drop out life together.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <stage>— <hi>Ex. Leteſi.</hi>
                  </stage>
                  <stage>Enter <hi>Atheos: The new arrived Strainger. And Souldiers.</hi>
                  </stage>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Athe.</speaker>
                     <l>Worthy Sir, you are welcome to your Garriſon,</l>
                     <l>for whils't you pleaſe to ſtay in it, it muſt be ſo.</l>
                     <l>My life, I hold of you, which when you pleaſe command</l>
                     <l>Il'e ſacrifice to ſerve you.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Straing.</speaker>
                     <p>Sir, your b re acknowledging me your ſervant, hath wip't off, what I have, or can be ſerviceable in, and made me (now) your Debtor, which I ſhall never be unable to confeſs, although not pay. It was my love to vertue, and my Country, commanded me to do no leſs, then to indeavour your ſafety (together with my own) from ſuch rude ſlaves as thoſe, for whom (I muſt confeſs I did, (but ſore againſt my will) ſome ſmall ſervice, having been late their Priſoner, which gain'd me that command, you ſaw I had amongſt them.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Athe.</speaker>
                     <p>Sir, you ſhall or'e come in this, and all things els. And be aſſured, what entertainment this Country can afford (within the bounds of my command) ſhall not be wanting to ſerve you.</p>
                     <p>I have a ſight to entertain you with, (tis probable) you have not often ſeen. Souldiers, are the marks men ready, I gave command (to day) ſhould be drawn out.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>1 <hi>Sould.</hi>
                     </speaker>
                     <p>They are Sir.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Athe.</speaker>
                     <p>Go, and give order to the Marſhall, he bring the Priſoners <pb n="46" facs="tcp:96238:29"/>forth to execution.
<stage>— <hi>Ex:</hi> 1 <hi>Sould.</hi>
                        </stage> Com: Sir, will it pleaſe you walk, where I ſhall ſhew you a handſome Creature, which will needs taſte death, for to preſerve her Siſters life. The like example of friendſhip in a Gentleman for his friend, one that I ne'r yet ſaw.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Straing.</speaker>
                     <p>Is ſuch examples of friendſhip common in theſe parts?</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Athe.</speaker>
                     <p>Theſe are the firſt, and rareſt (ſhould they hold out touch) I ever ſaw, or heard of. Wil't pleaſe you walk.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Straing.</speaker>
                     <p>Your ſervant waits you Sir.—</p>
                  </sp>
                  <stage>Ex: Om:</stage>
                  <stage>Enter <hi>As on the Parade,</hi> Albinus <hi>bound</hi> Clarathea <hi>in</hi> Leteſia's <hi>Habuit vaild.</hi> Adraſtus <hi>diſguiſed. A Guard of Souldiers.</hi>
                  </stage>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Albin.</speaker>
                     <p>Dares that Villain Tyrant (your Governor) hope to find mercy in the other world; That can commit ſuch horrid murder on a harmleſſe Virgin, that hates bad deeds as much as he doth Virtue? You Gods above, redeem an innocent Maid forth from the jaws of this Rebellious Woolf. The act appears ſo horrid, it will not let me dye in peace.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>2 <hi>Sould.</hi>
                     </speaker>
                     <p>Peace, here is our Governor.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <stage>Ent: <hi>Athe. and Strainger.</hi>
                  </stage>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Albin.</speaker>
                     <p>Yea, I will hold my peace. You Tyrant, Governor, Villain, Monſter of Men.
<stage>— <hi>Albin unvails her.</hi>
                        </stage> Look on this heavenly form, as innocently fair
<stage>— <hi>Straing: starts at ſight of Clarathea.</hi>
                        </stage> as thou ar't ſinfull ſoul. And tell me, if thy fleſh not tremble to be her murderer.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Straing:</speaker>
                     <p>You Powers (above) protect me, what viſion's this. I is ſome Angel, hath aſum'd that ſhape to make my wounds bleed freſh.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Athe.</speaker>
                     <p>Sir, are you not well.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Straing.</speaker>
                     <p>Somewhat there was, that I have ſeen, much like that face that troubles me. Good Sir, what may her Name be.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Athe.</speaker>
                     <p>Miſtreſſe, what may we call your Name.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Clarath.</speaker>
                     <p>Tell now, the unfortunate <hi>Clarathea.</hi>
                     </p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Albin.</speaker>
                     <p>Cheer up (brave Maid.) Thou art ſo far from acting what may beget a fear, Angels rejoice, they have beg'd thee from this world, to inrich their Throne, whilſt this admiring world gropes in the dark, as wanting vertues light.
<stage>—<hi>Clarath. ſpies the ſtranger.</hi>
                        </stage>
                     </p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Clarath.</speaker>
                     <p>Thou ſacred Spirit ſpeak. T'was kindly done to come and bear me company, to the other world
<stage>—<hi>Clarathea. faints away.</hi>
                        </stage>
                     </p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Albin.</speaker>
                     <p>Help, help, ſhe faints.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Straing.</speaker>
                     <p>Tis ſhe tis ſhe, you Gods, rob us not of our joy ſo ſoon, Gentlemen, for Heavens ſake help. —</p>
                     <stage>Enter <hi>Leteſia diſguiſed.</hi>
                     </stage>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Apfis</speaker>
                     <p>ſpeak one word of comfort, Ti's thy <hi>Corianus</hi> cals thee. So, ſo, ſhe breaths again. <pb n="47" facs="tcp:96238:29"/>Sir, If I have ought deſerved at your noble hands, (in what you may) aſſiſt this vertuous Maid, in whoſe well being, conſiſts my life.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Athe.</speaker>
                     <p>Souldiers (ſome of you) lay by your arms. And run for my Sedan, fly you Villains.
<stage>Ex: Sould</stage> Dear Lady, pardon your penitent ſervant, who only did intend to ſhew you Death in him to ſee how bravely you could bear it out.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Clarath,</speaker>
                     <p>Doth my <hi>Corianus</hi> live, or do I Dream.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Corian.</speaker>
                     <p>Thou comfort of my ſoul. Thy <hi>Corianus</hi> lives. Lives to enjoy, what the rich Oceans treaſure ſhould not buy for me. My beſt <hi>Apfia:</hi>
                        <stage>Imbraces her.</stage>
                     </p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Athe.</speaker>
                     <p>Sir, this paſſion tels me, ſhe ſhould be of ſome value to you. And I am gladly happy it ſo fals out, that I may ſerve you for the life I hold. Souldiers make ready, and fire at that ſtout Villain.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Adraſt.</speaker>
                     <p>Hold, hold I ſay. Thou foul mouth'd tyrant. There is more worth lodg'd in that noble breſt of his then would redeem (forth from the jaws of hell) thy ſoul deſign'd for Ruine.
<stage>— <hi>Fals on Albinus his Neck.</hi>
                        </stage> Let all the unreconciled world, that ſtands deriding at the Name of Friend, waſh their beſpattered ſouls; And here fall down, and worſhip. O <hi>Albinus,</hi> thou haſt out done ſtory, for where invention found not charity to purchaſe a beleef in thee, they may behold their error. Here you tyrant, take the blood you thirſt for,
<stage>— <hi>Tares open his Doubles, and puls of his Diſguiſe</hi>
                        </stage> I am the mark you aim at: T'was I that wounded your Lieutenant.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Apfia.</speaker>
                     <p>My Dear <hi>Corianus,</hi> if you have any power to prevail ſpeak for theſe worthieſt of Men; They will deſerve your love, as Perſons I have been preſerved by.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Corian.</speaker>
                     <p>Sir, Then I muſt begg (what it you pleaſe to grant) you everlaſtingly engage your Creature. That ſince your Lieutenant (unfortunately wounded by this Gentleman) is paſt Deaths preſent danger, that all may be forgot between your ſelf, and thoſe two Gentlemen (the unparalleld examples of true friendſhip) for whom, beſides what obligation, my <hi>Apfia</hi> charms me with, I am bound (upon my knees) to plead for. And will engage, they ſhall deſerve your love; And prove your Gratefull Servants.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Athe.</speaker>
                     <p>Sir I have given you the power, diſpoſe of them, and me as you pleaſe. Souldiers, unbind the Gentleman, he is no more your Priſoner. And now we ſtand all three your Debtors for the lives we hold.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Adraſt.</speaker>
                     <p>Worthy Sir, what you have (ſo liberall,) ingaged for us.
<stage>— <hi>Turns to Corianus.</hi>
                        </stage> ſhall be performed. My Life you have preſerved, which I ſhall husband to the beſt advantage <pb n="48" facs="tcp:96238:30"/>(in all obedience) to your commands.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Corian.</speaker>
                     <p>Sir, I muſt proclaim my ſelf a Traytor to my own reaſon, ſhould I no<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap> endeavour to preſerve thoſe lives, I muſt in mercy to my ſelf (if il'e ſeek honour) Imitate.
<stage>Leteſi, takes of her Diſguiſe.</stage>
                     </p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Leteſi.</speaker>
                     <p>And doth <hi>Leteſia</hi> live, to ſee her Dear <hi>Adraſtus</hi> free, worthieſt of Maids, I joy to ſee (as for my ſelf) thee lodgd in thoſe bleſt arms thou gaveſt for Dead. Thy vertue hath redeem'd us all.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Apfi.</speaker>
                     <p>I ne'r could do ſervice worthy your acceptation till this hour. And what (through weakneſſe) I may want to ſerve you. I know my <hi>Coranius</hi> (gladly) will perform.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Corian.</speaker>
                     <p>Lady <hi>Apfia's</hi> Friends, commands the Life I hold. Come my <hi>Apfia,</hi> I ſhall unfold thy Fathers plots, and charge he gave his ſervants to confirm me Dead, which (once) began to grow diſputable, through the feſtering of a wound he gave me.—</p>
                  </sp>
                  <stage>Ent; <hi>Symph, and Gripe man.</hi>
                  </stage>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Adraſt.</speaker>
                     <p>
                        <hi>Symphronio.</hi>
                     </p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Symph.</speaker>
                     <l>The very ſame I can aſſure you.</l>
                     <l>Sir, (if I miſtake not) this is your Vertuous Daughter.
<stage>—<hi>Turns to Leteſi, Leteſi. ſtarts back.</hi>
                        </stage>
                     </l>
                     <l>Ney, flinch not fair <hi>Leteſia.</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>I bring you none but friends.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Gripe.</speaker>
                     <p>And lives my <hi>Leteſia;</hi> My Child, my Daughter?
<stage>—<hi>Adraſt. and Leteſi. kneels.</hi>
                        </stage>
                     </p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Adraſt.</speaker>
                     <p>Yes, and <hi>Adrastus</hi> your Son to, I can aſſure you.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Gripe.</speaker>
                     <p>My bleſſing on you both; And with it, all I have.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Adraſt.</speaker>
                     <p>Worthy Sir, (my Father now)</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Gripe.</speaker>
                     <l>Come come, no words; All is forgot, all is forgot.</l>
                     <l>My joy is too great for me to contain.</l>
                     <l>This ſight, hath fild my veins with youthfull blood,</l>
                     <l>I hardly can beleeve I am mortall.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Athe.</speaker>
                     <p>This is a Day of joy, worthy remembrance. And Gentlemen; And Ladies, what I have done diſpleaſing to you. Pray forgive it. And if you pleaſe to ſolemnize your joyes in this poor Garriſon, what is, and the Country can afford, is yours.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Althe.</speaker>
                     <p>We humbly thank you Sir.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Gripe:</speaker>
                     <p>And ſhould accept this noble curtefie, did not my Houſe call home, which pray command as yours. Where I, with Feaſant, Cocke, Parteridg, and Plovers, will nobly feaſt you; And theſe <hi>Loyall Lovers.</hi>
                     </p>
                  </sp>
               </div>
            </div>
         </div>
         <div type="author_to_friends">
            <pb facs="tcp:96238:30"/>
            <head>THE AUTHOR To his Honorable Friends.</head>
            <lg>
               <l>WHat ſuch a weak foundation can ſupport,</l>
               <l>yo' have read, which well may ſerve the vulgar ſort,</l>
               <l>as a good Winters tale, where brown bowl ſence,</l>
               <l>may ſtagger the attentive Audience.</l>
               <l>At leaſt ſo highly pleaſe, that the whole pack</l>
               <l>ſhall ſwear, in Ale's more vertue then in Sack.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>But how amongſt your worthier Breſts, t'will take,</l>
               <l>or what impreſsion in your judgments make.</l>
               <l>Lo, I ſubmit too, yet dare hope no leſs,</l>
               <l>Then that your mercy'l ſave me from the Preſs;</l>
               <l>which if I am ſqueez'd to Death with, tis my fate,</l>
               <l>ſome Dye with too much, I for want of wait.</l>
            </lg>
         </div>
         <div type="to_the_author">
            <head>To his dear Friend the Author.</head>
            <l>In ſtead of Epilogue, il'e chide thy Wit,</l>
            <l>at leaſt thy judgment for ſuſpecting it.</l>
            <l>Has't thou ſo nobly taught Friends what to do,</l>
            <l>and fears't to ſuffer mongs't the Loyall crew,</l>
            <l>who let's thee looſe by this, plainly diſcovers,</l>
            <l>was ne'r (yet) truly Friend to Loyall Lovers.</l>
            <closer>
               <signed>Ed: Aſhen.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
