<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>The noble ingratitude a pastoral-tragi-comedy / by Sr. William Lower, Knight.</title>
            <title>Généreuse ingratitude. English</title>
            <author>Quinault, Philippe, 1635-1688.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1659</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 142 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 59 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-04">2011-04 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A56910</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing Q218</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R6083</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">11893679</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 11893679</idno>
            <idno type="VID">50497</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A56910)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 50497)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 507:17)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>The noble ingratitude a pastoral-tragi-comedy / by Sr. William Lower, Knight.</title>
                  <title>Généreuse ingratitude. English</title>
                  <author>Quinault, Philippe, 1635-1688.</author>
                  <author>Lower, William, Sir, 1600?-1662.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[9], 7-101, [2] p. : port.  </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Imprinted by John Ramzey,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>Hage :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1659.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Erraa [sic] on p. [2] at end.</note>
                  <note>First edition.</note>
                  <note>Translation of La généreuse ingratitude.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in Dyce Collection, Victoria and Albert Museum.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2009-12</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-01</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-03</date>
            <label>Pip Willcox</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-03</date>
            <label>Pip Willcox</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-04</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="frontispiece">
            <pb facs="tcp:50497:1"/>
            <p>
               <figure>
                  <q>AMICO ROSA INIMICO SPINA</q>
                  <figDesc>portrait, possibly of Sir William Lower</figDesc>
               </figure>
            </p>
         </div>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:50497:1"/>
            <p>THE NOBLE INGRATITUDE.</p>
            <p>A PASTORAL-TRAGI-COMEDY.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>By S<hi rend="sup">r</hi>. WILLIAM LOWER Knight.</hi>
            </p>
            <q>Amico Roſa, Inimico Spina.</q>
            <p>
               <hi>HAGE,</hi> Imprinted by <hi>Iohn Ramzey,</hi> 1659.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="dedication">
            <pb facs="tcp:50497:2" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:50497:2"/>
            <head>To her MAJESTY THE QUEEN OF BOHEMIA.</head>
            <opener>
               <salute>MADAM,</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>Were I not fully per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwaded that this Dramatick Piece in the
Original is one of the beſt <pb facs="tcp:50497:3"/>that hath been preſented upon the
French Stage, I ſhould not have preſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med to offer the Copy to the beſt
of Queens, and indeed the moſt Juditious of Women: If I have failed in my
judgment of the Authours work, I am indiſputably right in the Character of my
Patroneſs: Your Majeſties goodneſs in pardoning this preſum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ption, and
in approving the Plot and Language of the Play in my Verſion, <pb facs="tcp:50497:3"/>hath begotten this fu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture ambition in me, to publish it under the
fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vour of your Royall pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tection, which will ſecure it indubitably from the
malevolent cenſures of any ignorant, arrogant, or malignant perſon
what<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoever. If in the inter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vals of your high contem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plations your ſerious
thoughts shall deſcend to divert them a little, as before, ſo now after the
Dedication and Im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſion, <pb facs="tcp:50497:4"/>in reading thoſe Sceanes, I
muſt ever eſteem it an unparalel'd honour to me, who am,</p>
            <closer>
               <salute>MADAM,</salute> 
               <signed>
                  <hi>Your Majeſties moſt hum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble, moſt obedient, and
moſt faithfull Servant</hi> William Lower</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="prologue">
            <pb facs="tcp:50497:4"/>
            <head>PROLOGUE.</head>
            <l>BEfore I enter'd, I vvas tould vvhat novv</l>
            <l>I ſee decypher'd upon every brovv;</l>
            <l>A ſullen ſadnes, and cloſe murmurs ſay,</l>
            <l>"The Title is enough to damn the Play</l>
            <l>"The Bill condemns before the Action, Pox</l>
            <l>"Vpon the Poet vvith his Paradox,</l>
            <l>"Noble Ingratitude, o barbarous ſound!</l>
            <l>"Vertue vvill die to ſee that Monſter crovvn'd:</l>
            <l>Strange voices theſe, ſtrange cenſures from the vvits,</l>
            <l>For ſuch he take you, every one that ſits</l>
            <l>Sp<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ctat<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ur here
uſurps a priviledge,</l>
            <l>VVhich is unjuſt, before he hears, to judge,</l>
            <l>VViſe, and juſt Iuries, vvho in every cauſe</l>
            <l>Strictly obſerve the cuſtom of the Lavvs,</l>
            <l>The bottome ſound, and ne'r their verdicts bring</l>
            <l>Vpon the ſuperficies of a thing;</l>
            <l>They vveigh the ground of matters vvell, and ne'r</l>
            <l>Proceed to ſentence till they ſee all cleer;</l>
            <l>Have patience then a little, and ſuſpend</l>
            <l>Your judgments till you ſee us at the end</l>
            <l>Of the fifth Act; three hours vvill ſoon be paſs'd,</l>
            <l>In Sceans and Songs the minutes fly too faſt;</l>
            <l>Then if vve do'nt maintain our Paradox,</l>
            <l>Let me be sham'd, and ſit three hours i' th' ſtocks</l>
            <l>For punishing your patience; if the crime</l>
            <l>Deſerves more rigour, let a longer time</l>
            <l>Of penance be preſcrib'd me there; but I</l>
            <l>Hope from your judgments, juſtice, clemency,</l>
            <l>A nobler ſentence, and that you'll allovv</l>
            <l>Me next a Lavvrell vvreath to crovvn my brovv.</l>
         </div>
         <div type="dramatis_personae">
            <pb facs="tcp:50497:5"/>
            <head>ACTORS.</head>
            <list>
               <item>ZELINDA, Daughter to Lindarache, diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guiſed like a man
under the name of Ormin, in the habit of a Slave.</item>
               <item>ZEGRY, Maſter to Zelinda, and Lover of Fatima.</item>
               <item>ALABEZ, Second Slave to Zegry.</item>
               <item>CHARIFA, Woman-Slave to Fatima.</item>
               <item>FATIMA, Miſtreſſe to Zegry, and in Love with
Adibar.</item>
               <item>ABENCERAGE, under the name of Almanſor, Brother to
Zelinda.</item>
               <item>ZAIDA, Siſter to Zegry.</item>
               <item>MEDINA, Woman-Slave to Zaida.</item>
               <item>ADIBAR, Lover of Zaida.</item>
               <item>GAZVL, Slave to Abencerage.</item>
               <item>GOMELLA, Father to Fatima.</item>
               <item>LINDARACHE, Mother to Zelinda, and to Abencerage.</item>
            </list>
            <stage>The Scene is in the Forreſt of Argier.</stage>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="play">
            <pb n="7" facs="tcp:50497:5"/>
            <head>THE NOBLE INGRATITVDE. A Tragi-Comedy.</head>
            <div n="1" type="act">
               <head>ACT. I.</head>
               <div n="1" type="scene">
                  <head>SCENE I, ORMIN alone.</head>
                  <l>CHarming aboad, delightfull ſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>litude,</l>
                  <l>Fair places where I firſt receiv'd my life</l>
                  <l>And love, old trees, cleer brooks, whoſe ſhade and
murmur</l>
                  <l>Speak pity for my ſorrowfull adventure,</l>
                  <l>Sweet Zephirs, Eccho, nocks, and ſilent forreſts,</l>
                  <pb n="8" facs="tcp:50497:6"/>
                  <l>Be witneſſes all of my ſecret griefs:</l>
                  <l>I am no more now that <hi>Zelinda</hi> ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>time</l>
                  <l>Adored by the worthieſt Lovers of</l>
                  <l>The country round about; alas! I ſerve</l>
                  <l>Vnder the habit of a Slave, a traitor</l>
                  <l>With an unparraleld'd fidelity,</l>
                  <l>Traitor in Love, I meane, not otherwiſe,</l>
                  <l>A Hero, but ingratefull, one who ſlatters me</l>
                  <l>In my extream misfortune, yet would hate me,</l>
                  <l>If he knew that I Love him. Gentle trees,</l>
                  <l>Happy are you, although the rigourous Winter</l>
                  <l>Vſeth you hardly, for when the fair Spring</l>
                  <l>Maketh the cold to ceaſe, you ſuddenly</l>
                  <l>Reſume your anciet verdure, and at harveſt,</l>
                  <l>Vpon your branches wee ſee fruits, where formerly</l>
                  <l>Hung Iſicles: my fortune's not ſo good;</l>
                  <l>Each of the ſeaſons have 'twice chaung'd, ſince Love</l>
                  <l>Reſolved to afflict me, all which time</l>
                  <l>I've languished continually, and could not</l>
                  <l>Pretend to the repoſe my heart hath loſt:</l>
                  <l>He whom I love with ſo much conſtancy</l>
                  <l>Is falſe and fleeting; o Gods! here he comet.</l>
               </div>
               <div n="2" type="scene">
                  <head>SCENE. II.</head>
                  <stage>ZEGRY, ORMIN.</stage>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>ZEGRY.</speaker>
                     <p>
                        <hi>Ormin,</hi> I ſought thee.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <pb n="9" facs="tcp:50497:6"/>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>ORMIN.</speaker>
                     <p>Sir, I ſought you alſo.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>ZEGRY.</speaker>
                     <p>Know that to morrow we will depart hence.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>ORMIN.</speaker>
                     <l>What! will you leave ſo ſoon your native country,</l>
                     <l>Theſe cottages, theſe woods and theſe fair
meadows?</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>ZEGRY.</speaker>
                     <l>I have not hid from thee that in thoſe places</l>
                     <l>I love the ſweet <hi>Fatima,</hi> a rich
Maſter-peice</l>
                     <l>Of Heaven, and hop'd to ſee that Beauty here</l>
                     <l>So cherish'd and ador'd; but I have learn'd</l>
                     <l>That she is now at <hi>Tunis</hi> with her Father;</l>
                     <l>And though this happy reſidence may be ſaid</l>
                     <l>To be a ſecond Paradiſe, I cannot</l>
                     <l>See any fair thing here, ſince she is abſent.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>ORMIN.</speaker>
                     <l>How happy is <hi>Fatima,</hi> and how miſerable</l>
                     <l>Am I! — 
<stage>aſide.</stage>
                     </l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>ZEGRY.</speaker>
                     <l>How grievous is her abſence to</l>
                     <l>My amourous ſoul! to render me by her,</l>
                     <l>To morrow by the break of day we'll take</l>
                     <l>Our way for <hi>Tunis,</hi> I shall be too happy,</l>
                     <l>If I may ſee her, and I do believe</l>
                     <l>That she will bear ſome part too in my joy;</l>
                     <l>She had no little trouble, I perceiv'd,</l>
                     <pb n="8" facs="tcp:50497:7"/>
                     <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                        <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
                     </gap>
                     <pb n="9" facs="tcp:50497:7"/>
                     <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                        <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
                     </gap>
                     <pb n="10" facs="tcp:50497:8"/>
                     <l>For my departure laſt, and without doubt</l>
                     <l>I'm not indifferent to her.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>ORMIN.</speaker>
                     <l>Certainly</l>
                     <l>Her flame will not be quench'd.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>ZEGRY.</speaker>
                     <p>That's all my hope.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>ORMIN.</speaker>
                     <p>And that is all my feare — 
<stage>aſide.</stage>
                     </p>
                  </sp>
               </div>
               <div n="3" type="scene">
                  <head>SCENE III.</head>
                  <stage>ALABEZ, ZEGRY, ORMIN.</stage>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>ALABEZ.</speaker>
                     <l>Cheer up, cheer up,</l>
                     <l>Smother your ſighs, I have a counter poiſon</l>
                     <l>For all your ſorrows.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>ZEGRY.</speaker>
                     <l>Speak it then without</l>
                     <l>Holding us long in trouble.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>ALABEZ.</speaker>
                     <l>Give me leave.</l>
                     <l>Firſt, if you pleaſe, to take a little breath.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>ZEGRY.</speaker>
                     <p>Speak then?</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>ALABEZ.</speaker>
                     <p>I'm not diſpos'd yet.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>ZEGRY.</speaker>
                     <l>Oh thou mak'ſt me.</l>
                     <l>Suffer too much? tell it unto us quickly.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>ALABEZ.</speaker>
                     <p>You might die with it.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>ZEGRY.</speaker>
                     <l>Is't then ſome misfortune</l>
                     <l>Sent me by deſtiny?</l>
                  </sp>
                  <pb n="11" facs="tcp:50497:8"/>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>ALABEZ.</speaker>
                     <l>I ſay agiane.</l>
                     <l>You might die with it, but t'would be with joy;</l>
                     <l>Fatima yeſterday late in the evening</l>
                     <l>Arrived in theſe quarters.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>ZEGRY.</speaker>
                     <l>Is it poſſible,</l>
                     <l>Fatima?</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>ALABEZ.</speaker>
                     <p>Yes, aſſure you, I have ſeen her.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>ZEGRY.</speaker>
                     <p>Perhaps thou art deceiv'd.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>ALABEZ.</speaker>
                     <l>I am no aſſe.</l>
                     <l>I did obſerve her well, and knew her per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fectly.</l>
                     <l>Her Slave, who was my Miſtreſſe formerly,</l>
                     <l>Entered juſt now with her into that wood.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>ZEGRY.</speaker>
                     <p>Good Gods? do I not ſee her?</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>ALABEZ.</speaker>
                     <l>Yes, that's she</l>
                     <l>Which paſſeth by.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>ZEGRY.</speaker>
                     <l>What luſtre hath her eye,</l>
                     <l>What grace her gate?</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>ORMIN.</speaker>
                     <p>Alas?</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>ZEGRY.</speaker>
                     <p>I ſee a thouſand new charms there.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>ALABEZ.</speaker>
                     <p>Are you beſotted? wil you not ſalute her?</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>ZEGRY.</speaker>
                     <l>No, to perform that complement, I'le give her</l>
                     <pb n="12" facs="tcp:50497:9"/>
                     <l>A viſit, when I shall have without doubt</l>
                     <l>My ſoul leſſe in diſorder.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>ALABEZ.</speaker>
                     <l>For m<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>
part,</l>
                     <l>Who do not love ſo daintily, I will,</l>
                     <l>Without deferring it, make my addreſſe.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>ZEGRY.</speaker>
                     <l>Without diſcovering our ſelves, we may</l>
                     <l>From hence know by the uſage of the ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vant,</l>
                     <l>In what eſteem the Maſter is at preſent.</l>
                  </sp>
               </div>
               <div n="4" type="scene">
                  <head>SCENE IV.</head>
                  <stage>ALABEZ, CHARIFA, FATIMA, ZEGRY, ORMIN.</stage>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>ALABEZ.</speaker>
                     <p>SWeet Beauties welcome, from what quarters come you?</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>CHARIFA.</speaker>
                     <p>What means this inſolent? Go on your way</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>ALABEZ.</speaker>
                     <l>How's this? inſtead of kiſſes and embraces,</l>
                     <l>As I expected, I am quarrel<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>d with:</l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Charifa,</hi> whence this change?</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>CHARIFA.</speaker>
                     <p>Begone, and leave us.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <pb n="13" facs="tcp:50497:9"/>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>ALABEZ.</speaker>
                     <p>Thou acteſt well the ſcornfull.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>FATIMA.</speaker>
                     <l>What's that follow</l>
                     <l>Which followes us?</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>CHARIFA.</speaker>
                     <l>Tis an impertinent,</l>
                     <l>Whom I know not.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>ALABEZ.</speaker>
                     <l>I am much changed then</l>
                     <l>Since this laſt voyage; but thy ſoul is chag'd</l>
                     <l>And not my viſage, without doubt thy Miſtreſſe</l>
                     <l>Hath better eyes, and more wit; she will know</l>
                     <l>An old, and a familiar acquaintance.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>FATIMA.</speaker>
                     <p>who are you then?</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>ALABEZ.</speaker>
                     <p>My Maſters Slave.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>FATIMA.</speaker>
                     <p>What Maſter?</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>ALABEZ.</speaker>
                     <l>Should you not know him neither?</l>
                     <l>Is his name raz'd out of your memory?</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>FATIMA.</speaker>
                     <p>Aſſuredly, <hi>Charifa,</hi> this man's mad.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>ALABEZ.</speaker>
                     <l>How, Madam, is it poſſible you can</l>
                     <l>Forget the valiant <hi>Zegry?</hi>
                     </l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>FATIMA.</speaker>
                     <p>
                        <hi>Zegry?</hi>
                     </p>
                  </sp>
                  <pb n="14" facs="tcp:50497:10"/>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>ZEGRY.</speaker>
                     <l>Heaven?</l>
                     <l>What ſtrange inconſtancy is this? who e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver</l>
                     <l>Could have imagin'd it? — 
<stage>aſide.</stage>
                     </l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>ALABEZ.</speaker>
                     <l>That noble and illuſtrious ſucceſſour</l>
                     <l>Of thoſe brave warriers who even in Spain</l>
                     <l>Have gathered Lawrells, and brought home faire ſpoils,</l>
                     <l>Madam, your faithfull Lover, Zaida's bro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>FATIMA.</speaker>
                     <p>Oh! I remember him.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>ZEGRY.</speaker>
                     <p>Falſe, and Ingratefull!</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>ALABEZ.</speaker>
                     <p>You ask not how he doth.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>FATIMA.</speaker>
                     <l>What intereſt</l>
                     <l>Have I in his ſweet perſon? happily</l>
                     <l>He's dead.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>ALABEZ.</speaker>
                     <p>He is indeed.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>FATIMA.</speaker>
                     <l>We are all mortall;</l>
                     <l>The Prophet hath his ſoul.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>CHARIFA.</speaker>
                     <l>A faithfull ſervant</l>
                     <l>Would have accompanied his Maſter; why</l>
                     <l>Art thou not dead too?</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>ALABEZ.</speaker>
                     <l>Only to enrage thee.</l>
                     <pb n="15" facs="tcp:50497:10"/>
                     <l>Zegry diſcovering himſelf.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>ZEGRY.</speaker>
                     <l>The Prophet hath his ſoul, o falſe Fati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ma!</l>
                     <l>Is't thus you do expreſſe your goodneſs to me?</l>
                     <l>Deceitfull object, my return, I ſee,</l>
                     <l>Diſpleaſeth you, who would deſpiſe me dead,</l>
                     <l>Muſt hate me living, I diſturb with plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure</l>
                     <l>That faithleſs joy which the delightfull news</l>
                     <l>Of my feign'd death procur'd you: I live ſtill</l>
                     <l>Ingratefull, but I live no more for you:</l>
                     <l>My paſſion is transform'd all into fury:</l>
                     <l>As much as I lov'd you, I now deſpiſe you:</l>
                     <l>My heart shakes of ſo rigourous a yoak:</l>
                     <l>Love raiſeth no more ſighs, nor fires within me,</l>
                     <l>Only I ſigh that I us'd ſo much care</l>
                     <l>To pleaſe you, and if I burn yet, it is</l>
                     <l>With anger, not with love.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>ORMIN.</speaker>
                     <l>Oh this ſucceſſe</l>
                     <l>Anſwereth my wishes fully? — 
<stage>a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſide.</stage>
                     </l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>FATIMA.</speaker>
                     <l>This confeſſion</l>
                     <l>Surpriſeth, but no way afflicteth me;</l>
                     <pb n="16" facs="tcp:50497:11"/>
                     <l>My firſt diſcourſe should make you under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtand</l>
                     <l>That I'm not very tender hearted to you,</l>
                     <l>And, me thinks, after ſuch a cleer con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tempt</l>
                     <l>As was expreſſed there you might believe</l>
                     <l>Nothing should trouble me that comes from you,</l>
                     <l>Vnleſſ your amourous addreſſe: I have</l>
                     <l>A thouſand other Lovers braver far</l>
                     <l>Then you, and therefore I daign not to put you</l>
                     <l>In the rank of my conqueſts.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>ZEGRY.</speaker>
                     <l>Sure, your pride</l>
                     <l>Is greater then your beauty, the charm is</l>
                     <l>Diſſolv'd wherein I formerly was held;</l>
                     <l>Tis true, I ſometime thought you beauti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full;</l>
                     <l>But I was amourous, and therefore not</l>
                     <l>To be believed, having now my ſpirit</l>
                     <l>No more diſordered, you ceaſe to be fair</l>
                     <l>And I to be abuſed, whereas you</l>
                     <l>Pleaſed me formerly, it was becauſe</l>
                     <l>It is impoſſible for me, when I</l>
                     <l>Am lov'd, to be inſenſible.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>FATIMA.</speaker>
                     <l>I love you?</l>
                     <l>Heaven! what a ſtrange opinion is this?</l>
                     <pb n="17" facs="tcp:50497:11"/>
                     <l>I never had but ſtrong averſion for you.</l>
                     <l>All your indeavours ſerv'd but to diſpleaſe me;</l>
                     <l>But though I hated you, I lov'd your Si<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter,</l>
                     <l>And t<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> was for her ſake that I feign'd to have</l>
                     <l>Some pitty for your paſſions; her prayer</l>
                     <l>A hundred times reſtain'd my hate, you ſware</l>
                     <l>That your daies did depend upon my ſight,</l>
                     <l>And yeelding unto her deſites I did</l>
                     <l>Enforce mine eyes to ſmile, when my heart frown'd,</l>
                     <l>To the end not to be cauſe of your death.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>ZEGRY.</speaker>
                     <p>Your eyes have never made a mortall wound.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>FATIMA.</speaker>
                     <l>Take heed that your do not revive again,</l>
                     <l>One Only of my looks darted more gently,</l>
                     <l>Can change this violent anger into love;</l>
                     <l>But I am verie nice of ſuch a look,</l>
                     <l>It is too rich a price, Sir, for your conqueſt</l>
                     <l>I limit my deſires to ſee you never,</l>
                     <l>Adieu, become wiſe, and leave me in peace.</l>
                     <stage>— Exit <hi>Fatima.</hi>
                     </stage>
                  </sp>
               </div>
               <div n="5" type="scene">
                  <pb n="18" facs="tcp:50497:12"/>
                  <head>SCENE. V.</head>
                  <stage>ZEGRY, ALABEZ, ORMIN.</stage>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>ZEGRY.</speaker>
                     <l>YEs falſe Fatima, I will become wiſe,</l>
                     <l>Thy contempt is unjuſt, but mine is lawfull:</l>
                     <l>Since thou pretendeſt but to make thee hated,</l>
                     <l>I will obey thee, thy unworthy trophy,</l>
                     <l>My heart shal be no more, his charmes are broken,</l>
                     <l>His flames are quench'd; Alabez, follow her</l>
                     <l>Cloſe at the heels, even unto her houſe;</l>
                     <l>But have a care not to diſcover thee.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>ORMIN.</speaker>
                     <l>Her pride's unjuſt, and not to be endur'd;</l>
                     <l>Your change herein is but too equitable,</l>
                     <l>O how wel should you do to free your heart</l>
                     <l>From the imperious captivity</l>
                     <l>Of ſuch a cruel conquerour, you are</l>
                     <l>Born with too many fair advantages,</l>
                     <l>To obtain nothing but eternall wrongs;</l>
                     <l>There are Sir, other beauties in the world</l>
                     <l>VVhich would be glad to share their flame with yours,</l>
                     <l>To imitate your ſighs, and which would tell you</l>
                     <l>That the reſplendent honour of a crown</l>
                     <l>Is beneath that to be beloved of</l>
                     <l>An object that one loves Contempt in love</l>
                     <l>Deſerves to be repayed with contempt,</l>
                     <pb n="19" facs="tcp:50497:12"/>
                     <l>And who refuſeth, is not worthy of,</l>
                     <l>For the moſt part, the perſon that's refuſ'd.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>ZEGRY.</speaker>
                     <l>How great my griefs are, and how grievous is</l>
                     <l>This proud contempt? o light, and wave<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring Sex!</l>
                     <l>O black ingratitude! ſince love began</l>
                     <l>To trouble Lovers, was there ever torment</l>
                     <l>Equall to mine? I feel my heart infected</l>
                     <l>VVith all imaginary griefs.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>ORMIN,</speaker>
                     <l>Oh? Sir,</l>
                     <l>Believe me, I know ſome that are much more</l>
                     <l>To be lamented, and if what I know</l>
                     <l>VVere reveald to you, you should have great cauſe</l>
                     <l>Of comfort by it.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>ZEGRY.</speaker>
                     <l>Oh ſpeak, and divert</l>
                     <l>The grief which doth oppreſſe me. of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tentimes</l>
                     <l>A wretch is pleaſed in his miſery</l>
                     <l>VVhen he ſees that he ſuffers not alone.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>ORMIN.</speaker>
                     <l>O love, I pray thee make his heart grow tender</l>
                     <l>At the recitall of the evill which he</l>
                     <l>Hath cauſed me, oh make him Senſible</l>
                     <l>Of my ſad ſufferings? — 
<stage>a ſide.</stage>
                     </l>
                     <l>A young Beauty, Sir,</l>
                     <l>VVhoſe name and birth, if you pleaſe I'l conceal</l>
                     <l>Through decency, only thus much I'l tell you,</l>
                     <pb n="18" facs="tcp:50497:13"/>
                     <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                        <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
                     </gap>
                     <pb n="19" facs="tcp:50497:13"/>
                     <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                        <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
                     </gap>
                     <pb n="20" facs="tcp:50497:14"/>
                     <l>That she was neer to me and lov'd me deer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly,</l>
                     <l>Scarce yet attained to the fifteenth yeer,</l>
                     <l>When love and marriage was propoſed to her,</l>
                     <l>And she commanded to expect for huſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>band</l>
                     <l>A man too lovely, and to much belov'd;</l>
                     <l>And who for his part was ſo farre from being</l>
                     <l>Warm'd with a mutuall flame, that he un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lawfully</l>
                     <l>Took an affection for another object:</l>
                     <l>His faithfull Lover with grief underſtood it</l>
                     <l>But yet a worſe misfortune afterward</l>
                     <l>Surpriſed her, th' ingratefull brak th' ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cord</l>
                     <l>Of the approaching marriage, and departed</l>
                     <l>For a long voyage without ſeeing her;</l>
                     <l>I can aſſure you that her grief was quick,</l>
                     <l>And anger ardent after this affront;</l>
                     <l>But yet her anger was leſſe then her love:</l>
                     <l>Although, th' inconſtant left her, she re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain'd him</l>
                     <l>Still in her ſoul, and valuing not her ſex,</l>
                     <l>Nor fearing death, i<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> th' habit of a man</l>
                     <l>She followed his ſteps.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <stage>Zegry meditating</stage>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>ZEGRY.</speaker>
                     <l>O barbarous rigour!</l>
                     <l>O lamentable paſſion!</l>
                  </sp>
                  <pb n="21" facs="tcp:50497:14"/>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>ORMIN.</speaker>
                     <l>You wil be</l>
                     <l>More touch'd when you shall know the reſt: ſcarce was
she</l>
                     <l>Embarked on the ſea, when by a new,</l>
                     <l>And worſe misfortune certain infamous ro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vers</l>
                     <l>Surpriſ'd her veſſel, and not long time after</l>
                     <l>They ſould her unto that ingratefull man,</l>
                     <l>Who falſly and unworthly forſook her:</l>
                     <l>And ſo at laſt it hapened that Fortune</l>
                     <l>Aſwell as Love would put her into chains:</l>
                     <l>But she ſtill without changing heart, or habit,</l>
                     <l>Found ſweetnes in this double ſlavery;</l>
                     <l>Far from deſiring to be free, she follow'd</l>
                     <l>Her faithles friend into his native coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>try,</l>
                     <l>And fearing not to be diſcovered,</l>
                     <l>Serv'd this deceitfull Maſter without hope,</l>
                     <l>Indeavoured to pleaſe him, and therein</l>
                     <l>Proſper'd ſo well, that he eſteem'd her zeal,</l>
                     <l>And conceal'd nothing from her; but this kindnes</l>
                     <l>Was not a cure, but corſive to her grief,</l>
                     <l>Becauſe it made her privy to the happi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes</l>
                     <l>Her Rivall did enjoy in the affection</l>
                     <pb n="22" facs="tcp:50497:15"/>
                     <l>Of him she lov'd, who every day proteſted</l>
                     <l>Vnto her, that rather then loſe her love,</l>
                     <l>He'd loſe his life.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <stage>Zegry ſtill meditating.</stage>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>ZEGRY.</speaker>
                     <l>Vnparalel'd punishment!</l>
                     <l>Cruell injuſtice!</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>ORMIN.</speaker>
                     <l>Gods! he groweth tender,</l>
                     <l>Love be propitious to me, — 
<stage>aſide.</stage>
                     </l>
                     <l>Sir, what ſay you,</l>
                     <l>Is not ſhe more then you to be lamented?</l>
                     <l>Compared to her torments, your afflictions</l>
                     <l>Are ſweet. You anſwer not.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>ZEGRY.</speaker>
                     <l>Yes, yes, I grant it</l>
                     <l>I ought to hate her, but I've too much weaknes:</l>
                     <l>Oh fair Fatima!</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>ORMIN.</speaker>
                     <p>Oh my hard misfortune!</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>ZEGRY.</speaker>
                     <p>Ormin, what charms she hath?</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>ORMIN.</speaker>
                     <l>You anſwer nothing</l>
                     <l>To what I ſaid.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>ZEGRY.</speaker>
                     <p>What ſpak'ſt thou to me of?</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>ORMIN.</speaker>
                     <l>Of a young maid</l>
                     <l>Oppreſs'd and injured in love.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>ZEGRY.</speaker>
                     <l>My thoughts</l>
                     <l>Were otherwiſe imploy'd, and troubled,</l>
                     <pb n="23" facs="tcp:50497:15"/>
                     <l>I heard thee not, at leaſt I have forgotten.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>ORMIN.</speaker>
                     <l>You ſeemed to compaſſionate her grief,</l>
                     <l>And her misfortune very much.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>ZEGRY,</speaker>
                     <l>Alas!</l>
                     <l>I onely thought upon my proper grief.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>ORMIN,</speaker>
                     <l>What! shall th' ingratefull and cruel Fatima</l>
                     <l>Although she quits your heart thus, have the glory</l>
                     <l>To live ſtill in your memory? oh no,</l>
                     <l>Banish her thence; but if you'l think of her,</l>
                     <l>To eaſe your evills a little, imploy your thought</l>
                     <l>Onely to think of her defects; remember</l>
                     <l>That she's too proud, and fancy to your ſelf</l>
                     <l>That she's not fair enough, to hould ſo no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble</l>
                     <l>And ſuch a faithfull Lover as you are,</l>
                     <l>That there is nothing charming in her eyes,</l>
                     <l>Nor in her cheeks, that her proportion,</l>
                     <l>Her poſture, ſtature, gate, and carriage</l>
                     <l>Have nothing commendable, that her witt —</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>ZEGRY</speaker>
                     <l>Ormin, no more, I cannot ſuffer yet</l>
                     <l>She should be injur'd; that ingrateful Beauty,</l>
                     <l>Who laughs with ſcorn at my ſad languish<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment,</l>
                     <l>Hath no defect at all but her fierce rigour;</l>
                     <pb n="24" facs="tcp:50497:16"/>
                     <l>And I fear that in ſpight of this defect,</l>
                     <l>My violent love will triumph o'r mine an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>ORMIN.</speaker>
                     <l>What, shall <hi>Fatima</hi> be ſo proud, and you</l>
                     <l>So humble? shall she be compoſ'd of Ice,</l>
                     <l>And you of fire? muſt you perſiſt to love her,</l>
                     <l>When she deſpiſeth you? oh fall no more</l>
                     <l>Into that fatall errour. It belongs, Sir</l>
                     <l>But to low ſpirits to ſuffer without hate,</l>
                     <l>Such a contempt; to leave what flyeth us,</l>
                     <l>Is little trouble, and when hope is quench'd,</l>
                     <l>Love should be querched alſo.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>ZEGRI.</speaker>
                     <l>What thou ſayſt,</l>
                     <l>Ormin, is verie true, I should indeed</l>
                     <l>Follow <hi>Fatima</hi> in her lightnes to me,</l>
                     <l>I should in her unkindnes trace her ſteps,</l>
                     <l>I should be as inſenſible as she's</l>
                     <l>Severe and rigourous, my flam'es an er<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rour,</l>
                     <l>I doe confeſſe it, but I love this errour,</l>
                     <l>Thy faithfull counſels are not ſeaſonable,</l>
                     <l>Love hath not yet given place unto my rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon,</l>
                     <l>I'm born to languish, and to die for her;</l>
                     <l>Although she be ingratefull she is not</l>
                     <l>The leſſe faire for it.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>ORMIN.</speaker>
                     <l>The falſe hope that flatter'd me</l>
                     <l>Fled in a moment; miſerable Lover,</l>
                     <l>And too unjuſt! — 
<stage>a ſide</stage>
                     </l>
                  </sp>
               </div>
               <div n="6" type="scene">
                  <pb n="25" facs="tcp:50497:16"/>
                  <head>SCENE VI.</head>
                  <stage>ALMANSOR, ZEGRY, ORMIN.</stage>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>ALMANSOR.</speaker>
                     <l>FRiend, I am very joyfull</l>
                     <l>To meet thee.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>ZEGRY.</speaker>
                     <l>My content is ſtill compleat,</l>
                     <l>When I behold thy face, as in thy abſence,</l>
                     <l>Nothing ſeems ſweet unto me: Now I ſee</l>
                     <l>Th'art habited like us, this garment is</l>
                     <l>Well made.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>ALMANSOR.</speaker>
                     <l>I took it juſt now in th'apartment</l>
                     <l>I have in thy abode.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>ZEGRY.</speaker>
                     <l>This Shepheards habit</l>
                     <l>Becomes thee rarely; but for an <hi>Almanſor,</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>It is too much abaſement.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>ALMANSOR.</speaker>
                     <l>Sure the habit</l>
                     <l>Takes nothing from the luſtre of the merit,</l>
                     <l>In imitating thee, I cannot erre;</l>
                     <l>Thee, whoſe heart is as noble as thy race,</l>
                     <l>And unto whoſe aid in an eminent danger</l>
                     <l>I owe my life.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>ZEGRY.</speaker>
                     <l>The Shepheards of this wood</l>
                     <l>And fair Campania, are deſcended from</l>
                     <l>Thoſe Heros, who in time paſs'd conquer'd Spain</l>
                     <l>From thoſe renowned Moors, whoſe great ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ploits</l>
                     <l>Made the Kings of a hundred Chriſtian people</l>
                     <pb n="26" facs="tcp:50497:17"/>
                     <l>Tremble for fear, and who ſeeing <hi>Tunis</hi>
con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quer'd</l>
                     <l>By <hi>Charls the fifth,</hi> conſerve here in theſe
places</l>
                     <l>Their glory and their freedom, ſecretly</l>
                     <l>Diſpoſe the hearts of the moſt Zealous Kings</l>
                     <l>To drive the Chriſtias fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> this deſolate cou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>try,</l>
                     <l>And are in readines to joyn themſelves,</l>
                     <l>And to encreaſe the firſt fair levies which</l>
                     <l>Shall be imploy'd on ſuch an expedition.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>ALMANSOR.</speaker>
                     <l>I know that this fair deſert's like a Court:</l>
                     <l>But haſt thou heard yet that Gomella is</l>
                     <l>Return'd heer? ſuffer me at preſent, <hi>Zegry,</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>To leave thee, he is my familiar friend,</l>
                     <l>And I owe him a viſit.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>ZEGRY.</speaker>
                     <l>Then thou know'ſt</l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Fatima.</hi>
                     </l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>ALMANSOR.</speaker>
                     <l>Yes, that Beauty hath receiv'd</l>
                     <l>The light from brave <hi>Gomella;</hi> friend adiew,</l>
                     <l>I will return to thee with ſpeed, excuſe me</l>
                     <l>At preſent, I muſt ſpeak with him upon</l>
                     <l>A buſines of importance. — 
<stage>Exit <hi>Almanſor.</hi>
                        </stage>
                     </l>
                  </sp>
               </div>
               <div n="7" type="scene">
                  <head>SCENE VII.</head>
                  <stage>ZEGRY ORMIN.</stage>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>ZEGRY.</speaker>
                     <l>A buſines of importance? oh that word</l>
                     <l>Redoubleth my affliction; to marry</l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Fatima,</hi> without doubt, is his deſign:</l>
                     <l>Oh Heave? haſt thou ordain'd that, to make up</l>
                     <l>The full proportion of my miſery,</l>
                     <pb n="27" facs="tcp:50497:17"/>
                     <l>My deareſt frie<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d should rob me of my Miſtreſſe?</l>
                     <l>Alas! if this be true, grief, fure will kill me;</l>
                     <l>Dear <hi>Ormin,</hi> let us uſe our beſt indeavour</l>
                     <l>To hinder this misfortune; I expect</l>
                     <l>My only remedy from thy adviſe.</l>
                     <l>The moſt reſplendent wit yeildeth to thine</l>
                     <l>In point of knowledge, <hi>I</hi> have obſerv'd in
thee</l>
                     <l>Something thats great, and extraordinary;</l>
                     <l>Thy judgment charms me, and thy care ſur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>priſeth me.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>ORMIN.</speaker>
                     <p>Sir, <hi>I</hi>'m your Slave, and glory to be ſo.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>ZEGRY.</speaker>
                     <l>No, no, <hi>I</hi> make thee free, henceforth be thou</l>
                     <l>Thy Maſters friend.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>ORMIN.</speaker>
                     <l>The ſweeteſt liberty</l>
                     <l>Pleaſeth my fancy leſſe then the chains which</l>
                     <l>I bear for you.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>ZEGRY</speaker>
                     <l>This zeal ſo little common,</l>
                     <l>Makes me grow tender, and amazeth me.</l>
                     <l>Quit, quit thy fetters, <hi>Ormin, I</hi> commmand it,</l>
                     <l>Be free.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>ORMIN</speaker>
                     <l>Since tis your pleaſure, <hi>I</hi> obey;</l>
                     <l>Alas! what have <hi>I</hi> ſaid, Love, can <hi>I</hi>
be</l>
                     <l>At liberty, when my heart is not free?</l>
                  </sp>
               </div>
               <trailer>The end of the first Act.</trailer>
            </div>
            <div n="2" type="act">
               <pb n="28" facs="tcp:50497:18"/>
               <head>ACT II.</head>
               <div n="1" type="scene">
                  <head>SCENE I.</head>
                  <stage>FATIMA, ZAIDA, CHARIFA, MEDINA.</stage>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>FATIMA.</speaker>
                     <l>ENter again, ſweet Zaida, ceremony</l>
                     <l>Between us should be banish'd, wherefore will you</l>
                     <l>Trouble your ſelf unneceſſarily?</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>ZAIDA.</speaker>
                     <p>Since you will have it ſo, I'l go no further.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>FATIMA.</speaker>
                     <l>I may aſſure my ſelf then ere we part,</l>
                     <l>That <hi>Adibar</hi> shall have no free admittance</l>
                     <l>To your ſociety, I have already</l>
                     <l>Told you, that formerly he loved me;</l>
                     <l>But now I know that you give laws to him</l>
                     <l>And I have cauſe to hope that, if you ſcorn him,</l>
                     <l>He may return unto his firſt ſubjection.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>ZAIDA.</speaker>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Fatima,</hi> be aſſur'd that he shall be</l>
                     <l>Repuls'd, his love will be but troubleſome;</l>
                     <l>But if you love me, forget not to feign</l>
                     <l>Some kindnes for my brother; I beſeech you</l>
                     <l>For my ſake give him cauſe to hope a little.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>FATIMA.</speaker>
                     <l>Adieu, I promiſe you that at next meeting</l>
                     <l>I will receive him better. — 
<stage>Exit Fatima.</stage>
                     </l>
                  </sp>
               </div>
               <div n="2" type="scene">
                  <pb n="29" facs="tcp:50497:18"/>
                  <head>SCENE II.</head>
                  <stage>ZAIDA, MEDINA.</stage>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>ZAIDA.</speaker>
                     <l>WHat think'ſt thou</l>
                     <l>Of fair <hi>Fatima,</hi> and of her requeſt?</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>MEDINA.</speaker>
                     <l>I think that <hi>Adibar</hi> is not a perſon</l>
                     <l>To be deſpis'd.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>ZAIDA.</speaker>
                     <l>True, but I am too proud</l>
                     <l>T'accept a heart that hath been conquered</l>
                     <l>By any other, and would now be mine</l>
                     <l>Trough an inconſtancie, but if I durſt</l>
                     <l>To love —</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>MEDINA.</speaker>
                     <p>Why ſtop you, Madam?</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>ZAIDA.</speaker>
                     <l>Oh <hi>Medina!</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>I muſt not ſpeak the reſt.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>MEDINA.</speaker>
                     <l>But I divine it;</l>
                     <l>You are in love, and I have cauſe to judge</l>
                     <l>That it is with <hi>Almanſor,</hi> that fair
ſtranger</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>ZAIDA.</speaker>
                     <p>Who, I in love with him?</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>MEDINA.</speaker>
                     <l>Why not, I pray you,</l>
                     <l>Is that a crime?</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>ZAIDA.</speaker>
                     <l>Oh do not name that love,</l>
                     <l>Which is no other but a fair eſteem.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <pb n="30" facs="tcp:50497:19"/>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>MEDINA.</speaker>
                     <l>There is ſo little difference between</l>
                     <l>Eſteem and love, that often times we take then</l>
                     <l>One for the other, and are ſo deceiv'd.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>ZAIDA.</speaker>
                     <l>
                        <hi>I</hi> cannot but remember that my brother</l>
                     <l>In his laſt voyage did conclude my marriage</l>
                     <l>In <hi>Argier,</hi> that he who's deſign'd to be</l>
                     <l>My husband, is heer shortly to arrive,</l>
                     <l>And that my heart ought to reſerve it ſelf</l>
                     <l>Wholy for him. Beſides in thy opinion.</l>
                     <l>Would it not argue a great weaknes in me</l>
                     <l>To love this ſtranger, though my brothers friend.</l>
                     <l>Who hath not been above a moneth among u<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>
                     </l>
                     <l>And whoſe deſert as yet's unknown unto me</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>MEDINA.</speaker>
                     <l>Seeing this Stranger, who's not of the vulgate,</l>
                     <l>Deſerves to be careſſed of your brother,</l>
                     <l>There's reaſon to believe that he deſerves</l>
                     <l>To be your Lover, and <hi>I</hi> can't conceive</l>
                     <l>Why your mouth will conceal the flame which is</l>
                     <l>So cleerly for him in your eyes and counte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nance.</l>
                     <l>As often as he commeth with your brother</l>
                     <l>To viſit you, your looks ſeem to be fix'd</l>
                     <l>Wholy one him, and at the ſame time alſo</l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>I</hi> obſerv'd often that the ſtranger ey'd you</l>
                     <l>With the ſame ardour.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>ZAIDA.</speaker>
                     <l>Prethee, ſpeak in earneſt,</l>
                     <l>Did'ſt ſee him to behold me oftentimes?</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>MEDINA.</speaker>
                     <l>You ask it me with very much impreſſement:</l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>I</hi> do believe in leſſe time then an howr,</l>
                     <l>That you have queſtion'd me upon this point</l>
                     <pb n="31" facs="tcp:50497:19"/>
                     <l>More then a hundred times; your curioſity</l>
                     <l>Gives me a full aſſurance that his looks</l>
                     <l>Displeaſe you not, nor wound your modeſty</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>ZAIDA.</speaker>
                     <l>Alas! can one in juſtice be offended,</l>
                     <l>To be belov'd?</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>MEDINA.</speaker>
                     <l>If his love pleaſeth you, <hi>I</hi> think his
perſon</l>
                     <l>Will pleaſe you equally.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>ZAIDA.</speaker>
                     <l>
                        <hi>I</hi> conſider him</l>
                     <l>Without interpreter; but perhaps, he loves</l>
                     <l>Elſewhere, and <hi>I</hi> may be unpleaſing to him.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>MEDINA.</speaker>
                     <l>Madam, although you fain would cover it,</l>
                     <l>This fond ſuſpition publisheth your flame,</l>
                     <l>Iealouſy alwaies is daughter of love.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>ZAIDA.</speaker>
                     <l>vvould it pleaſ'd Heaven, that he were free, and that</l>
                     <l>He thought me fair, But <hi>I</hi> ſee him come forth</l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Gomella's</hi> houſe, <hi>I</hi>'l ſatisfy my
ſelf</l>
                     <l>In ſounding of his ſoul, upon this bank</l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>I</hi> will repoſe my ſelf, and feign to
ſleep.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>MEDINA.</speaker>
                     <p>VVhat's your deſign? <hi>I</hi> cannot comprehend it.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>ZAIDA.</speaker>
                     <p>VVithdraw, anon thou't underſtand it better.</p>
                  </sp>
               </div>
               <div n="3" type="scene">
                  <head>SCENE III.</head>
                  <stage>ALMANSOR ZAIDA.</stage>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>ALMANSOR.</speaker>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Gomella</hi> is expecting his return.</l>
                     <pb n="32" facs="tcp:50497:20"/>
                     <l>In viſit, heer I may conveniently</l>
                     <l>Dream of my new love: Heaven! do I not ſee</l>
                     <l>Vnder that flourishing shade the beautious ſubject</l>
                     <l>Of my ſad ſufferings? Love in this encounter</l>
                     <l>Seemeth to flatter me ſufficiently;</l>
                     <l>It is the lovely <hi>Zaida</hi> without doubt:</l>
                     <l>How ſweetly, and with what tranquility</l>
                     <l>Doth that fair one repoſe, whil'ſt wretched I</l>
                     <l>Languish with the diſeaſe which she procures me?</l>
                     <l>Surely she cannot hear me now, I may</l>
                     <l>Speak at this preſent unto her of love,</l>
                     <l>And not offend her; but alas! the rigour</l>
                     <l>Of my ſad deſtiny is great, when I</l>
                     <l>Preſume to ſpeak, I fear that she may hear me.</l>
                     <l>You that have taught me the true uſe of ſighs,</l>
                     <l>Dear object of my joy and of my griefs;</l>
                     <l>Suffer my amorous and ſilent ſoul.</l>
                     <l>T<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> expreſſe its ſecret paſſion before
you,</l>
                     <l>And to complain heer of a thouſand evills</l>
                     <l>Which you have made me ſuffer, yet unkrown</l>
                     <l>Vnto your ſelf: and you reſplendent ſources</l>
                     <l>Of all my fires, from whence I have deriv'd</l>
                     <l>Such violent heats, fair charming eyes, the au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thors</l>
                     <l>Of my captivity, enjoy the reſt,</l>
                     <l>Which your have taken from me: If I ſee</l>
                     <l>The poppies which shut up your lids, be not</l>
                     <l>Offended that you loſe your lights, the Sun</l>
                     <l>Is ſubject to the ſame eclipſe, and can</l>
                     <l>No more then you, diſpenſe himſelf thereof.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <stage>Zaida feigning her ſelf in a dream.</stage>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>ZAID.</speaker>
                     <p>
                        <hi>Almanſor.</hi>
                     </p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>ALM.</speaker>
                     <p>Sure, she dreams.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>ZAIDA.</speaker>
                     <l>Oh! rigourous torment!</l>
                     <pb n="33" facs="tcp:50497:20"/>
                     <l>To burn, to languish, and not dare to ſpeak it,</l>
                     <l>Alas!</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>ALMANSOR.</speaker>
                     <p>O Heaven! what heare I?</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>ZAIDA</speaker>
                     <l>We reſent</l>
                     <l>One and the ſame heat.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>ALMANSOR.</speaker>
                     <p>Oh! that it were true!</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>ZAIDA.</speaker>
                     <p>My modeſty, excuſe me.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>ALMANSOR.</speaker>
                     <p>O favourable ſleep!</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>ZAIDA.</speaker>
                     <l>Cruel conſtraints!</l>
                     <l>When shal we be content, when shal our plaints</l>
                     <l>Have end?</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>ALMANSOR.</speaker>
                     <l>In this great extaſie of joy,</l>
                     <l>All my reſpects are vain; to give her thanks.</l>
                     <l>I'l kiſſe her fair hands. — 
<stage>He kiſſeth her hands.</stage>
                     </l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>ZAIDA.</speaker>
                     <p>Hold, inſolent; whence doth proceed this bold<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes? —

<stage>feigning to awake,</stage>
                     </p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>ALMANSOR.</speaker>
                     <l>What have I done? — 
<stage>aſide.</stage>
                     </l>
                     <l>I came to give you thanks.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>ZAIDA.</speaker>
                     <p>For what?</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>ALMANSOR.</speaker>
                     <p>Tis for your goodnes.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>ZAIDA.</speaker>
                     <l>Now, <hi>I</hi> know not:</l>
                     <l>I'm ſure <hi>I</hi> never gave you any matter</l>
                     <l>For this acknowledgment, who ever will</l>
                     <pb n="34" facs="tcp:50497:21"/>
                     <l>Conſult th' apparence of the thing, shal find</l>
                     <l>That I have much indifference for you;</l>
                     <l>But though I had leſſe, was it fit to trouble</l>
                     <l>My reſt, in making your acknowledgement?</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>ALMANZOR.</speaker>
                     <l>Excuſe my tranſport, beautious Shepheardeſſe,</l>
                     <l>If I had leſſe lov'd, I had been leſſe guilty;</l>
                     <l>In this occaſion a Wary Lover</l>
                     <l>Would have expreſſed little love in shewing</l>
                     <l>Too much reſpect; and whatſoer my crime be,</l>
                     <l>It would be pardoned, if you ſlept ſtil;</l>
                     <l>But, alas! my good fortune is ſoon chang'd,</l>
                     <l>I find that you awake but to afflict me,</l>
                     <l>Your eyes in taking unto them again</l>
                     <l>Their grace and luſtre, take unto them alſo</l>
                     <l>At the ſame time their uſual cruelty.</l>
                     <l>And that moſt charming hope which I ſo little</l>
                     <l>Enjoyed, vanish'd with your ſleep.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>ZAIDA.</speaker>
                     <l>This is</l>
                     <l>An ill expreſſion of your ſelf, that word</l>
                     <l>Of hope gives me aſtonishment, I never</l>
                     <l>Gave it, nor took it yet from any perſon.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>ALMANZOR.</speaker>
                     <l>If I might dare to credit your diſcourſe,</l>
                     <l>At leaſt you had not an averſion for me,</l>
                     <l>Nothing would be equall to my good fortune,</l>
                     <l>You would not find my preſence trouble ſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>me,</l>
                     <l>I should be uſed better, I should be</l>
                     <l>Eſteem'd and poſſibly—</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>ZAIDA.</speaker>
                     <p>Proceed.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>ALMANZOR.</speaker>
                     <l>I might be</l>
                     <l>Belov'd.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <pb n="35" facs="tcp:50497:21"/>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>ZAIDA.</speaker>
                     <l>Belov'd! of whom; if you magine</l>
                     <l>Of me, you are miſtaken.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>ALMAZOR.</speaker>
                     <l>Notwithſtanding</l>
                     <l>You honored me ſo much to tell me ſo:</l>
                     <l>If I may but believe your voice, I have</l>
                     <l>Place in your heart, you are my witneſſe and</l>
                     <l>My judge both at one time; oh diſavow not</l>
                     <l>That favorable ſentence, that fair Oracle</l>
                     <l>Proceding from an adorable mouth,</l>
                     <l>Thoſe words ſo full of charms pronounc'd in ſleep,</l>
                     <l>Which promiſed me bleſſings ſoſoon vanish'd</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>ZAIDA.</speaker>
                     <l>I dreamt, <hi>Almanſor,</hi> and you are not ignorant</l>
                     <l>That a dream oftentimes is a deceiver,</l>
                     <l>And ſtil a lie.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>ALMANSOR.</speaker>
                     <l>True, a dream is my glory;</l>
                     <l>But I have paſſions which are real truths,</l>
                     <l>The flame with in mine eyes hath appear'd to you</l>
                     <l>Too cleer, to be concealed, and the coldnes</l>
                     <l>Which you expreſſe unto me, quencheth not</l>
                     <l>My love, altbough it ruineth my hope.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>ZAIDA.</speaker>
                     <l>This love comes very late, and really</l>
                     <l>I'm troubled at it, you know wel that I</l>
                     <l>Am otherwiſe engag'd.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>ALMANSOR.</speaker>
                     <l>Alas! I cannot</l>
                     <l>Deny but I have heard ſay that a Lover</l>
                     <l>Favoured of Heaven is to come shortly heer</l>
                     <l>To take you from mine eyes, I know you love him</l>
                     <pb n="36" facs="tcp:50497:22"/>
                     <l>Before you ſee him, therefore I'le not trouble</l>
                     <l>Your pleaſures, nor his joy: how great ſoever</l>
                     <l>His happines be, I do intend to ſuffer it</l>
                     <l>VVithout complaining of you, but withall</l>
                     <l>I doe intend to die. As ſoon as you</l>
                     <l>Shall depart hence upon the fatal voyage</l>
                     <l>Ordained, where your happy mariage</l>
                     <l>Muſt be accomplish'd, Know, at the ſame time,</l>
                     <l>That you shall ſee me in my griefs exceſſe</l>
                     <l>Depart to go unto the grave, where thoſe</l>
                     <l>Remains of fire which ſparkle in my boſom,</l>
                     <l>Atter my death shall ſtill yet warm my ashes.</l>
                     <l>ZAID; Fortune doth ow you, Sir, a happier lot</l>
                     <l>ALM: My good or evill lot depends on you.</l>
                     <l>All other favours would be troubleſome:</l>
                     <l>Laſtly I do adore you, and not fortune.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>ZAIDA.</speaker>
                     <l>What expect you from me in the condition</l>
                     <l>Wherein I am?</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>ALMANSOR.</speaker>
                     <l>Immortall heats and torments;</l>
                     <l>I ſtill muſt love without hope to be loved.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>ZAIDA.</speaker>
                     <p>Who loves much, may hope to be loved like<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>ALMANSOR.</speaker>
                     <p>What may I hope one day for better uſage?</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>ZAIDA.</speaker>
                     <l>Conſult with your fidelity upon it.</l>
                     <l>ALM: Your ſoul appeareth too inſenſible</l>
                     <l>To love.</l>
                     <l>ZAID: A conſtant Lover may do much;</l>
                     <l>The firſt refuſal ought not to aſtonish</l>
                     <l>Any one that hath love enough to give it.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>ALMANSOR.</speaker>
                     <p>Oh this is plain enough to my glad ſenſe!</p>
                  </sp>
                  <pb n="37" facs="tcp:50497:22"/>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>ZAIDA.</speaker>
                     <l>The blood ſtrikes up unto my brow; alas!</l>
                     <l>I've ſaid too much, and now I blush for shame on't.</l>
                     <l>ALM: This glorious confeſſion rendereth me</l>
                     <l>Too happy and content.</l>
                     <l>ZAID: Dreams ſometimes are not</l>
                     <l>VVithout effect; but the Sun hath already</l>
                     <l>Finished his career, let us go in</l>
                     <l>Yet further to diſcourſe upon this matter</l>
                     <l>I fear that troubleſome.</l>
                  </sp>
               </div>
               <div n="4" type="scene">
                  <head>SCENE IV.</head>
                  <stage>ADIBAR, ZAIDA, ALMANSOR,</stage>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>ADIBAR.</speaker>
                     <l>Without too much ambition may I hope</l>
                     <l>The honour to take you by the fair hand</l>
                     <l>The one is free, may I preſume to kiſſe it?</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>ZAIDA.</speaker>
                     <p>I have no need, Sir, of your ſervices.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>ADIBAR.</speaker>
                     <l>They may be worth a Strangers, notwith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding</l>
                     <l>Your ſcorn of me.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>ZAIDA.</speaker>
                     <l>In thinking to oblige me,</l>
                     <l>You may diſpleaſe me, by this odd expreſſion.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>ADIBAR.</speaker>
                     <l>The Prophet, who knows how I reverence you,</l>
                     <l>Knows alſo how far forth I fear your anger,</l>
                     <l>And the cares which I take, should well aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure you,</l>
                     <l>That I come heer but for to honour you:</l>
                     <pb n="36" facs="tcp:50497:23"/>
                     <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                        <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
                     </gap>
                     <pb n="37" facs="tcp:50497:23"/>
                     <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                        <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
                     </gap>
                     <pb n="38" facs="tcp:50497:24"/>
                     <l>May I aſide declare a ſecret to you?</l>
                     <l>Of ſome importance?</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>ZAIDA.</speaker>
                     <l>Nothing is ſo important</l>
                     <l>As decency, which in th' opinion</l>
                     <l>Of every one, allowes we not the Liberty</l>
                     <l>To hear the ſecrets of ſuch as you are.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>ADIBAR.</speaker>
                     <l>I deſire nothing of you what another</l>
                     <l>Doth not obtain.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>ZAIDA.</speaker>
                     <l>His diſcourſe pleaſeth me,</l>
                     <l>And yours I hate.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>ALMANSOR.</speaker>
                     <l>You take an unfit time</l>
                     <l>To tell your ſecrets, to the indiſcreet</l>
                     <l>Love ſeldome is propitious; th' incivility</l>
                     <l>Which your pride doth expreſſe, is an ill mea<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s</l>
                     <l>To gain eſteem.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>ADIBAR.</speaker>
                     <l>I am not heer to take</l>
                     <l>Leſſons from you.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>ALMANSOR.</speaker>
                     <l>I give them to your equals</l>
                     <l>To all intents and purpoſes.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>ADIBAR.</speaker>
                     <l>This paſſion.</l>
                     <l>Which carries you away, convicteth you,</l>
                     <l>And doth excuſe me of the incivility</l>
                     <l>Wherewith your errour charge me; a man</l>
                     <l>Better inſtructed, to avoid ſuſpition,</l>
                     <l>Would have retir'd himſelf out of reſpect;</l>
                     <l>You are too groſſe; but as you are a Stranger,</l>
                     <l>I ought to bear a little with your ignorance.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>ZAIDA.</speaker>
                     <l>You have the faults which you co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>demn in him;</l>
                     <pb n="39" facs="tcp:50497:24"/>
                     <l>This Stranger doth oblige me, and you trou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble me.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>ADIBAR.</speaker>
                     <p>Yet you should take away your hand from him — to
<hi>Zaida.</hi>
                     </p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>ALMANSOR.</speaker>
                     <p>If she should do it, you would be in danger.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>ADIBAR.</speaker>
                     <p>In quitting her, you might run to your death.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>ALMNASOR.</speaker>
                     <p>I reſpect <hi>Zaida,</hi> you I do deſpiſe.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>ADIBAR.</speaker>
                     <l>If by the ſame reſpect I were not ſtop'd,</l>
                     <l>In my revenge, your punishment should ſoon</l>
                     <l>Follow your inſolence.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <stage>Zaida quitting, Almanſors hand.</stage>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>ZAIDA.</speaker>
                     <l>Theſe haſty motions</l>
                     <l>Are ſorry paſſtimes for me; by this violence</l>
                     <l>I know that neither of you doth reſpect me,</l>
                     <l>But both offend me.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>ALMMANSOR.</speaker>
                     <l>Do you take</l>
                     <l>Your hand from me to anſwer his deſires?</l>
                     <l>My Rivall will become too proud at this:</l>
                     <l>Should you affro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t me wit deſign to pleaſe him?</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>ZAIDA.</speaker>
                     <l>By what right alſo am I bound to give</l>
                     <l>You ſatisfaction?</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>ADIBAR.</speaker>
                     <l>Madam, I beſeech you,</l>
                     <l>Vſe no conſtraint to your free inclination</l>
                     <l>In my behalf, I know which of us two</l>
                     <l>Pleaſeth you beſt, I yeild to him in fortune,</l>
                     <l>And perhaps too in merit, his diſcourſe</l>
                     <l>Is acceptable, mine is hatefull to you;</l>
                     <pb n="40" facs="tcp:50497:25"/>
                     <l>Of this truth I cannot be ignorant;</l>
                     <l>Therefore to th' end <hi>I</hi> may not trouble you,</l>
                     <l>I will retire me, my reſpect for you</l>
                     <l>Is ſtronger then the jealouſie, wherewith</l>
                     <l>My amourous ſoul is juſtly ſeiſed now,</l>
                     <l>And I will force all my reſentiments for you,</l>
                     <l>Yea eve<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> to hate my ſelf, if you should hate me.</l>
                     <l>Let here my happy Rivall without trouble</l>
                     <l>Diſcourſe with you, eſtablish, if you pleaſe,</l>
                     <l>His happines at the expenſe of mine;</l>
                     <l>But take this into your conſideration</l>
                     <l>That <hi>Adibar,</hi> who quits you with regret,</l>
                     <l>Though the leaſt lov'd, is not the leaſt diſcreet.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>ZAIDA.</speaker>
                     <p>VVhere go you <hi>Adibar?</hi> come back again.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>ADIBAR.</speaker>
                     <p>My abſence will oblige you.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>ZAIDA.</speaker>
                     <l>No, once more</l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>I</hi> ſay come back again; if you eſteem me,</l>
                     <l>You will return, to take away ſuſpitions</l>
                     <l>Oppoſed to my glory, lend me, pray you,</l>
                     <l>Your hand, and lead me back. — 
<stage>he gives her his hand.</stage>
                     </l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>ALMANSOR.</speaker>
                     <l>Oh! <hi>I</hi> cannot</l>
                     <l>Suffer this cruell injury.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>ZAIDA.</speaker>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Almanſor,</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>Stay <hi>I</hi> command you, on pain of my hate.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>ALMANZOR.</speaker>
                     <p>Hear me a word or two,</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>ZAIDA.</speaker>
                     <l>
                        <hi>I</hi> can't be mov'd.</l>
                     <l>Reaſon <hi>I</hi> hear, and duty is my guide.</l>
                     <stage>Exeunt Zaida and Adibar.</stage>
                  </sp>
               </div>
               <div n="5" type="scene">
                  <pb n="41" facs="tcp:50497:25"/>
                  <head>SCENE V.</head>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>ALMANZOR.</speaker>
                     <l>What unexpected cl<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="2 letters">
                           <desc>••</desc>
                        </gap> 
                        <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 word">
                           <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                        </gap> thunder's
this,</l>
                     <l>Which ruineth my joy thus with my ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pe?</l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Reaſon I hear, and duty is my guide;</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>My conſtancy, at theſe words giveth place</l>
                     <l>To my deſpair; <hi>and duty is my guide</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>No, cruell <hi>Zaida</hi> in following <hi>Adibar,</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>Tis Love that guides you: but what! I may be</l>
                     <l>Too rash in cenſuring her ſo; perhaps</l>
                     <l>She doth enforce herſelf in quitting me,</l>
                     <l>And doth prefer my Rivall here before me,</l>
                     <l>To take off all ſuſpition of our love.</l>
                     <l>She loves, she loves me; oh! what ſay <hi>I,</hi>
fool?</l>
                     <l>without doubt she hath left me through con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tempt.</l>
                     <l>Love, like to fickle Fortune is inconſtant,</l>
                     <l>His Empire, doth reſemble his who doth</l>
                     <l>Command the ſea, where nothing is ſecure,</l>
                     <l>To day a calm, to morrow a ſad ſtorm,</l>
                     <l>And every minute, the moſt fortunate</l>
                     <l>Vpon that element, may fear a change.</l>
                     <l>Even in the Port, We often ſuffer Shipwrack:</l>
                     <l>Theſe are ſad truths, whereof <hi>I</hi> need not
doubt:</l>
                     <l>But what maketh my Slave ſo haſtily</l>
                     <l>T'addreſſe his ſteps unto me?</l>
                  </sp>
               </div>
               <div n="6" type="scene">
                  <head>SCENE VI.</head>
                  <stage>ALMANSOR, GAZUL.</stage>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>ALMANZOR.</speaker>
                     <l>Haſt thou found</l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Gomella?</hi>
                     </l>
                  </sp>
                  <pb n="42" facs="tcp:50497:26"/>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>GAZVL.</speaker>
                     <l>Yes, Sir. and I think that he</l>
                     <l>Adva<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ceth heer with large ſteps to embrace yo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>
                        <g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
                     </l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>ALMANSOR.</speaker>
                     <p>Tis that which my care should prevent.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>GAZVL.</speaker>
                     <l>Muſt I</l>
                     <l>Withdraw whilſt you diſcourſe?</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>ALMANSOR.</speaker>
                     <l>Yes, and be ſure</l>
                     <l>Thou fail not to prepare for me a conſort</l>
                     <l>Of Muſick.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>GAZVL.</speaker>
                     <p>How a conſort, Sir, ſo late?</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>ALMANSOR.</speaker>
                     <p>Go quickly, and without reply.</p>
                  </sp>
               </div>
               <div n="7" type="scene">
                  <head>SCENE VII.</head>
                  <stage>GOMELLA, ALMANSOR.</stage>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>GOMELLA.</speaker>
                     <l>Oh! Sir,</l>
                     <l>How glad am I to ſee you heer again?</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>ALMANSOR.</speaker>
                     <l>My joy in ſeeing you is no leſſe great:</l>
                     <l>But ſpeak we of my mother.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>GOMELLA.</speaker>
                     <l>Stay her comming;</l>
                     <l>To morrow without fail she arrives here</l>
                     <l>Vnknown.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>ALMANSOR.</speaker>
                     <p>Vnknown! and why dares she not to be ſee<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>
                        <g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
                     </p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>GOMELLA.</speaker>
                     <p>The ſecret only you muſt know from her,</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>ALMANSOR.</speaker>
                     <p>Comes not my Siſter?</p>
                  </sp>
                  <pb n="43" facs="tcp:50497:26"/>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>GOMELLA.</speaker>
                     <p>You muſt not expect her.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>ALMANSOR.</speaker>
                     <p>Where is her reſidence?</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>GOMELLA.</speaker>
                     <p>I cannot tell you.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>ALMANSOR.</speaker>
                     <l>How's this, <hi>Gomella,</hi> what can I imagine</l>
                     <l>In the uncertainty wherein you leave me?</l>
                     <l>I am aſtonished at this proceeding;</l>
                     <l>Your obſcure language is a cleer preſage</l>
                     <l>Of a conceal'd misfortune: Oh! my Siſter</l>
                     <l>Is dead, <hi>I</hi> need not doubt it.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>GOMELLA.</speaker>
                     <l>Her death is not</l>
                     <l>The evill which should attriſt you.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>ALMANSOR.</speaker>
                     <l>What, is't then</l>
                     <l>Hapned vnto her?</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>GOMELLA.</speaker>
                     <p>No, but ſomething worſe.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>ALMANSOR.</speaker>
                     <l>That word is not ſufficient to cleer me:</l>
                     <l>Shall <hi>I</hi> not know why <hi>I</hi> receiv'd an
order</l>
                     <l>To depart from <hi>Tremiſsa</hi> where <hi>I</hi> was</l>
                     <l>Brought up, to come with al ſpeed to theſe quarters,</l>
                     <l>T'addreſſe my ſelf to you with confidence,</l>
                     <l>To change my true name of <hi>Abencerage</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>Into that of <hi>Almanſor,</hi> and to have</l>
                     <l>A care not to reveale my family?</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>GOMELLA</speaker>
                     <l>Vpon this point <hi>I</hi> muſt shut up my mouth;</l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>I</hi>'m not allowed to ſay more unto you.</l>
                     <l>It is you Mothers abſolute injunction,</l>
                     <l>And requeſt to me; have but patience</l>
                     <pb n="44" facs="tcp:50497:27"/>
                     <l>Vntill to morrow, when you shal be ſatisfied</l>
                     <l>From her own mouth; but the Sun, <hi>I</hi> perceive</l>
                     <l>Already groweth pale before the Moon.</l>
                     <l>Enter into my cot, and take with me</l>
                     <l>A poor repaſt.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>ALMANSOR.</speaker>
                     <l>
                        <hi>I</hi> doe deſire to be</l>
                     <l>Diſpens'd thereof now, if it pleaſeth you.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>GOMELLA.</speaker>
                     <p>VVhere will you go?</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>ALMANSOR.</speaker>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Zegry</hi> expecteth me</l>
                     <l>On my engagement at his houſe to night.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>GOMELLA.</speaker>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Zegry,</hi> what ſay you, what charm doth oblige
you</l>
                     <l>To anſwer ſo ill to <hi>Abencerage</hi> name,</l>
                     <l>To that debate, which for a thouſand reaſon</l>
                     <l>Is, between your two houſes, as it were,</l>
                     <l>Hereditary?</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>ALMANSOR.</speaker>
                     <l>
                        <hi>A</hi> far juſter duty</l>
                     <l>Inviteth me to love him: but for him,</l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>I</hi>'d loſt my life in <hi>Cairo,</hi> treacherous
enemies</l>
                     <l>Encompaſſed me round, and had he not</l>
                     <l>Succoured me ſpeedily, <hi>I</hi> had been murthered</l>
                     <l>His name, which I knew well without diſco<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vering</l>
                     <l>Mine own, diſturb'd my new born amity;</l>
                     <l>But his, goodnes for me, his cares, his kindnes<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>
                     </l>
                     <l>Soon diſſipated all thoſe old reſentements;</l>
                     <l>And ſo in order to the friendship which</l>
                     <l>Conjoined us, at laſt we came together</l>
                     <l>Into this country, where <hi>I</hi> was oblig'd</l>
                     <l>By the ſame frienship to lodge no where elſe</l>
                     <l>But at home with him.</l>
                     <pb n="45" facs="tcp:50497:27"/>
                     <l>
                        <hi>GOM:</hi> Oh Heaven! but proceed.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>ALMANSOR.</speaker>
                     <l>You know his Siſter: at firſt ſight of her,</l>
                     <l>I was her ſervant: by a powerfull charm</l>
                     <l>VVhoſe art she only knows, her fair eyes paid</l>
                     <l>But one look for the purchaſe of my heart;</l>
                     <l>And if the God of marriage. —</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>GOMELLA.</speaker>
                     <l>Soft, hold there.</l>
                     <l>Take heed you flatter not your ſelf with ſuch</l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>A</hi> fatall hope, deſtroy your paſſions,</l>
                     <l>Or you deſtroy your honour.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>ALMANSOR.</speaker>
                     <p>How, my honour?</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>GOMELLA.</speaker>
                     <l>Yes, Sir, your honour, what! doth this diſcourſe</l>
                     <l>Surpriſe and trouble you?</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>ALMANSOR.</speaker>
                     <l>
                        <hi>I</hi> fear the name</l>
                     <l>Of an ingratefull perſon.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>GOMELLA.</speaker>
                     <l>Fear that alſo</l>
                     <l>Of a low ſpirited one; theſe shamefull motion</l>
                     <l>Do wound your duty.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>ALMANSOR.</speaker>
                     <p>May <hi>I</hi> not know how?</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>GOMELLA.</speaker>
                     <l>To morrow, when you ſee your Mother here,</l>
                     <l>You shall be ſatisfied, in the mean time,</l>
                     <l>Hate both the Siſter, and the brother.</l>
                     <l>ALM: Hate them?</l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>I</hi> who have been ſo much oblig'd unto them?</l>
                     <l>No, no, <hi>I</hi> ſwear —</l>
                     <l>GOM: Swear not but let us enter;</l>
                     <l>Your mind will change, when you have heard th'adventure.</l>
                  </sp>
               </div>
               <trailer>The end of the Second Act.</trailer>
            </div>
            <div n="3" type="act">
               <pb n="46" facs="tcp:50497:28"/>
               <head>ACT III,</head>
               <div n="1" type="scene">
                  <head>SCENE I.</head>
                  <stage>ZEGRY, ORMIN.</stage>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>ZEGRY.</speaker>
                     <l>THe night approacheth, it is time to put</l>
                     <l>This letter with my hope into thy hands:</l>
                     <l>Work on her Slave, and act diſcreetly, that</l>
                     <l>She take this diamond from thee, afterward</l>
                     <l>Vſe all the skill thou haſt to know the ſecrets</l>
                     <l>Of her diſdainfull Miſtreſſe, and conſider</l>
                     <l>That I expect at thy return to hear</l>
                     <l>The ſentence of my life, or of my death.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>ORMIN.</speaker>
                     <l>Cruell commandment, whereunto I ſee</l>
                     <l>My ſelf reduc'd! — 
<stage>aſide.</stage>
                     </l>
                     <l>One word, Sir, ere I go.</l>
                     <l>Think well upon it yet, what hope have you?</l>
                     <l>Your importunities will increaſe her anger,</l>
                     <l>And you should do much better, If I durſt</l>
                     <l>To tell you ſo, henceforth to free your ſelf</l>
                     <l>Of this unworthy Empire; as love is</l>
                     <l>The price of love, ſo hate should alwaies be</l>
                     <l>The recompenſe of hate, and of contempt.</l>
                     <l>Your ſoul's are too ill ſuited to unite,</l>
                     <l>Love loſeth his power in Antipathies,</l>
                     <l>And tis an equall crime, Sir, in a contrary</l>
                     <l>Effect, to hate who Loves us, or to love</l>
                     <l>Who hates us.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>ZEGRY.</speaker>
                     <l>Oh! ſpeak no more on 't unto me:</l>
                     <l>My evill's invincible, and my ſoul feels</l>
                     <l>Too ſenſibly the charms which doe deſtroy me;</l>
                     <l>To overcome my griefs, which have no equals</l>
                     <pb n="47" facs="tcp:50497:28"/>
                     <l>I ſeek ſome gentle ſuccour, and not counſel,</l>
                     <l>My chain, alas! is too ſtrong, and my heart</l>
                     <l>Too weak, as not to yeild unto the torrent</l>
                     <l>which carries me away.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>ORMIN.</speaker>
                     <l>O rigorous Fate! — 
<stage>aſide.</stage>
                     </l>
                     <l>But if all your indeavours ate in vain,</l>
                     <l>If fierce <hi>Fatima</hi> ſtill perſiſt in her</l>
                     <l>Former diſdains —</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>ZEGRY.</speaker>
                     <l>what pleaſure doſt thou take</l>
                     <l>T'increaſe my troubles? hide her rigours to me</l>
                     <l>And ſpeak but of her charms: my heart is try'd</l>
                     <l>By torments great enough, it need not be</l>
                     <l>afflicted with an evill not yet arriv'd.</l>
                     <l>flatter my weaknes, though therein thou shew</l>
                     <l>Thy ſelf leſſe faithfull, if thou doſt deſire</l>
                     <l>To intereſt thy ſelf in my misfortunes.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>ORMIN.</speaker>
                     <l>Sir, if your eyes could penetrate into</l>
                     <l>The ſecrets of my heart, you would ſoon find</l>
                     <l>How great an intereſt I take in them,</l>
                     <l>And that if your lot lay within my power.</l>
                     <l>Your pleaſures should ſoon paſſe your hope, I
call</l>
                     <l>The <hi>Prophet,</hi> ſo much honoured amongſt us,</l>
                     <l>To witnes, that I feel the counterſtroaks</l>
                     <l>Of all your troubles, that <hi>I</hi>'m grieved for them</l>
                     <l>Aſmuch as you, and tremble in like manner,</l>
                     <l>Laſtly that you are dearer to me far</l>
                     <l>Then you imagine, that my happines</l>
                     <l>Depends on the ſucceſſe of your amours,</l>
                     <l>And that it is for you alone my heart</l>
                     <l>Makes its devotions.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>ZEGRY.</speaker>
                     <l>Grant it gracious Heaven</l>
                     <pb n="46" facs="tcp:50497:29"/>
                     <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                        <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
                     </gap>
                     <pb n="47" facs="tcp:50497:29"/>
                     <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                        <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
                     </gap>
                     <pb n="48" facs="tcp:50497:30"/>
                     <l>That thy zeal happily ſucceed in touching</l>
                     <l>In my behalf the ſoul of that ingratefull:</l>
                     <l>My ſiſter hath already been with her,</l>
                     <l>And <hi>I</hi> believe she hath not fail'd to ſpeak</l>
                     <l>To her for me, their friendship flatters me;</l>
                     <l>And gives me leave to hope that who eſteems</l>
                     <l>The ſiſter, may in time cherish the brother.</l>
                     <l>Adiew, perform thy duty, and return</l>
                     <l>With ſpeed to calm the tempeſts of my ſpirit.</l>
                     <stage>— <hi>Exit Zegry.</hi>
                     </stage>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>ORMIN.</speaker>
                     <l>
                        <hi>I</hi> will indeavour with permiſſion of</l>
                     <l>The holy Prophet, to hear ſuch ſucceſſe</l>
                     <l>As <hi>I</hi> deſire.</l>
                  </sp>
               </div>
               <div n="2" type="scene">
                  <head>SCENE II.</head>
                  <stage>ORMIM alone.</stage>
                  <l>WHereto shall <hi>I</hi> reſolve me in this ſad</l>
                  <l>Extremity? shall <hi>I</hi> ſollicit now</l>
                  <l>My Rivall gainſt my ſelf in the behalf</l>
                  <l>Of an ingratfull Maſter that doth wrong me?</l>
                  <l>And though he appeares blind to my diſad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vantage,</l>
                  <l>Shall I approve my ſelf ſo more then he?</l>
                  <l>What shall I preſſe th'effect of what I fear?</l>
                  <l>Shall I give him content at my ſad coſt,</l>
                  <l>By a conſtraint ſo cruell? and shall I</l>
                  <l>Become my ſelf the faithfull Miniſter</l>
                  <l>Of the injuſtices which he doth do me?</l>
                  <l>No, no, let us not ſerve with ſo much heat</l>
                  <l>To trouble us yet with a new misfortune,</l>
                  <l>A perſon who coſt me ſo many tears:</l>
                  <l>If I muſt die, at leaſt let me not give</l>
                  <pb n="49" facs="tcp:50497:30"/>
                  <l>Arms for to peirce my heart; o'th contrary,</l>
                  <l>Let me act ſo, that he may hope for nothing</l>
                  <l>From fair <hi>Fatima,</hi> let me without ſcruple</l>
                  <l>Betray this falſe one, and deprive him of</l>
                  <l>A good which would become ſo fa'tal to me.</l>
                  <l>I should ground all the hope thats left unto me</l>
                  <l>Vpon the loſſe of his. But how is this,</l>
                  <l>That at theſe words <hi>I</hi> tremble with affright?</l>
                  <l>I find my heart already riſeth up</l>
                  <l>Againſt me in behalf of this falſe Maſter.</l>
                  <l>Alas! how cruel and perfidious</l>
                  <l>Soer he be, I cannot fail of faith</l>
                  <l>To wards him, but muſt love, and ſerve him truly.</l>
                  <l>'Tis ſo reſolv'd, my anger muſt give place</l>
                  <l>Vnto the love that raigneth in my boſom:</l>
                  <l>An ill example never juſtiſies</l>
                  <l>A crime: let us deliberate no more;</l>
                  <l>But what's the noiſe I hear? it is <hi>Fatima</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>That paſſeth, and <hi>Charifa</hi> follows her.</l>
               </div>
               <div n="3" type="scene">
                  <head>SCENE III.</head>
                  <stage>FATIMA, CHARIFA, ORMIN</stage>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>FATIMA.</speaker>
                     <l>THis foul contemps which <hi>Zaida</hi> offers me</l>
                     <l>Provokes me highly, fo far was this falſe one</l>
                     <l>From hindering <hi>Adibar</hi> to viſit her,</l>
                     <l>(As she engag'd herſelf in promiſe to me)</l>
                     <l>That she accepted kindly of his hand,</l>
                     <l>To diſoblige me; tis an injury</l>
                     <l>Of ſuch a nature as requires reveng.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <pb n="50" facs="tcp:50497:31"/>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>CHARIFA.</speaker>
                     <l>The affront is known unto your ſelf, you ſaw it</l>
                     <l>With your own eyes, and to ſpeak truely Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dame,</l>
                     <l>The injuſtice is extream.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>FATIMA.</speaker>
                     <l>Know that my anget</l>
                     <l>Is ſo too; let us enter, it is late,</l>
                     <l>This night shall give us counſell.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>ORMIN.</speaker>
                     <l>I'l go one,</l>
                     <l>And ſtay no longer, las! I dare not open</l>
                     <l>My mouth, nor keep it shut. Love, I beſeech thee,</l>
                     <l>Mingle at leaſt ſome good in the great maſſe.</l>
                     <l>Of my misfortunes, graunt that in demanding</l>
                     <l>All things of her, she grant me nothing for</l>
                     <l>him. — 
<stage>aſide.</stage>
                     </l>
                     <l>Madame, shall I find ſo much goodnes from you</l>
                     <l>As to allow me the ſweet liberty</l>
                     <l>To leave this letter heer in your fair hands?</l>
                     <l>It commeth from a Louer the moſt paſſionate</l>
                     <l>Of all thoſe which the Luſtre of your eyes.</l>
                     <l>Hath made ſlaves; and who, not withſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding all</l>
                     <l>The love where with his ſoul is ſeis'd, hath gri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven
you</l>
                     <l>Some cauſe of plaint.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>FATIMA.</speaker>
                     <l>Of plaint liſt <hi>Adibar</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>That writes vnto me? <hi>Softly to Charifa.</hi>
                     </l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>CHARIFA.</speaker>
                     <l>Without doubt tis he,</l>
                     <l>My heart doth tell me ſo.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <pb n="51" facs="tcp:50497:31"/>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>FATIMA.</speaker>
                     <l>What would that falſe one</l>
                     <l>Deſire of me?</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>ORMIN.</speaker>
                     <l>How cruell is this ſweetnes</l>
                     <l>To me? — 
<stage>aſide.</stage>
                     </l>
                     <l>The end of his deſires is to</l>
                     <l>Appear before you, highly to deteſt</l>
                     <l>His inſole<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t crime, he would expreſſe the trouble</l>
                     <l>Wherewith his ſoul is preſs'd, to the Divinity</l>
                     <l>Iuſtly offended, and receive in making</l>
                     <l>His fault worthy to be forgot, a pardon.</l>
                     <l>Or death at your fair feet.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>FATIMA.</speaker>
                     <l>I deſire not</l>
                     <l>His death; but I would have him live and hope;</l>
                     <l>How late ſoever his repentance comes,</l>
                     <l>I love it, and 't is welcome. My heart is</l>
                     <l>Already pacified by thy diſcourſe.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>ORMIN.</speaker>
                     <p>I have for my misfortune, too well ſped. — 
<stage>aſide.</stage>
                     </p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>FATIMA.</speaker>
                     <l>Lets ſee with what, air, in this letter he</l>
                     <l>Vtters his thought, we will go in to read it,</l>
                     <l>And to give anſwer; ſince he is no longer</l>
                     <l>Obſtinate in his coldnes, I will ſend</l>
                     <l>His pardon ſign'd and ſeal'd.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>ORMIN.</speaker>
                     <l>How full of joy</l>
                     <l>Will <hi>Zegry</hi> be at my return?</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>FATIMA.</speaker>
                     <p>What ſay you? 
<stage>Zegry.</stage>
                     </p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>ORMIN.</speaker>
                     <l>Tis he that ſends me, he will kiſſe</l>
                     <l>The words where with y'ave flatter'd him.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <pb n="50" facs="tcp:50497:32"/>
                  <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                     <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <pb n="51" facs="tcp:50497:32"/>
                  <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                     <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <pb n="52" facs="tcp:50497:33"/>
                  <stage>Fatima tearing his letter.</stage>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>FATIMA.</speaker>
                     <l>This is</l>
                     <l>My anſwer, go, and carry it unto him. — 
<stage>Exit Fatima.</stage>
                     </l>
                  </sp>
               </div>
               <div n="4" type="scene">
                  <head>SCENE IV.</head>
                  <stage>ORMIN, CHARIFA.</stage>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>ORMIN.</speaker>
                     <l>THis in equality aſtonisheth</l>
                     <l>And puzleth me, — <hi>Charifa!</hi>
                     </l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>CHARIFA.</speaker>
                     <p>No, good night.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>ORMIN.</speaker>
                     <p>Hear me, I pray thee.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>CHARIFA.</speaker>
                     <l>I take no delight</l>
                     <l>To talk with fools</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>ORMIN.</speaker>
                     <p>Stay yet a little.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>CHARIFA.</speaker>
                     <l>I have not the leiſure.</l>
                     <l>Adieu, fair prater!</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>ORMIN.</speaker>
                     <l>Be not ſo ungentle.</l>
                     <l>My ha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d shall ſpeak gould, to ſupply my mouth</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>CHARIFA.</speaker>
                     <p>I do'nt believe thee.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>ORMIN.</speaker>
                     <l>Believe the event.</l>
                     <l>From <hi>Zegry</hi> take this diamond.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>CHARIFA.</speaker>
                     <l>To betraye,</l>
                     <l>And ſell my Miſtreſſe? God defend, I will not</l>
                     <l>Receive it.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <pb n="53" facs="tcp:50497:33"/>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>ORMIN.</speaker>
                     <p>Be not ſuch a ſimple creature.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>CHARIFA.</speaker>
                     <l>
                        <hi>I</hi> take it then to pleaſe thee, but accept it</l>
                     <l>Vnto a good intent: the ſtone's not falſe,</l>
                     <l>At leaſt I think ſo:</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>ORMIN.</speaker>
                     <l>Thou mayſt be aſſur'd on't,</l>
                     <l>Tis very fair, and perfect.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>CHARIFA.</speaker>
                     <l>Pardon me,</l>
                     <l>My words might ſeem t'imply a doubt, that <hi>I</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>Suſpected thee, but <hi>I</hi> am innocent.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>ORMIN.</speaker>
                     <l>Wilt thou not tell me by what fatall errour</l>
                     <l>Thy miſtreſſe humour chang'd ſo ſuddenly?</l>
                     <l>And how it came, that only at the name</l>
                     <l>Of <hi>Zegry</hi> her heart preſently grew cold,</l>
                     <l>Although enflam'd with my diſcourſe before?</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>CHARIFA.</speaker>
                     <l>I love thee but too well; and if thou wilt</l>
                     <l>Be ſecret, I'l diſcover unto thee</l>
                     <l>This ſecret of importance, this hid miſtery.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>ORMIN.</speaker>
                     <l>Thou wilt oblige me much, ſpeak, I'm diſcreet.</l>
                     <l>And will concea'lt as cloſely as thy ſelfe.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>CHARIFA.</speaker>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Fatima</hi> then loves <hi>Adibar</hi> aſmuch</l>
                     <l>As she doth hate thy Maſter; but for her,</l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Adibar</hi> by a pleaſant fair return</l>
                     <l>Hath no, leſſe coldnes then thy maſter love.</l>
                     <l>Thou knowſt that thou art not yet known of her,</l>
                     <l>And that love oftentimes troubleth the brain:</l>
                     <l>Hence was it, that at firſt she did believe</l>
                     <l>That <hi>Adibar</hi> ſent thee to ſpeak to her;</l>
                     <pb n="54" facs="tcp:50497:34"/>
                     <l>But ſince she knew her errour, she was mad;</l>
                     <l>I hear a noiſe, let us ſpeak ſoft I fear</l>
                     <l>We should be heard.</l>
                  </sp>
               </div>
               <div n="5" type="scene">
                  <head>SCENE. V.</head>
                  <stage>ALABEZ, ORMIN, CHARIFA.</stage>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>ALABEZ.</speaker>
                     <l>THe Devill! where thinks my Maſter</l>
                     <l>That I should meet with <hi>Ormin?</hi> it is night</l>
                     <l>And I can't find my way.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>CHARIFA.</speaker>
                     <p>Prethee be ſtill.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>ORMIN.</speaker>
                     <l>Let me alone, thy honour is not much</l>
                     <l>In danger with me.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>CHARIFA.</speaker>
                     <l>Foh! my diamond</l>
                     <l>Is fallen from my ſinger.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>ORMIN.</speaker>
                     <l>Without doubt</l>
                     <l>The graſſe conceals it from our ſight.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>CHARIFA.</speaker>
                     <l>We may</l>
                     <l>Seek it a good while ere we find it heer.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>ORMIN.</speaker>
                     <p>Yes in this manner, I'le go fetch a light, 
<stage>Exit Ormin.</stage>
                     </p>
                  </sp>
               </div>
               <div n="6" type="scene">
                  <head>SCENE VI.</head>
                  <stage>ALABEZ, CHARIFA.</stage>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>CHARIFA.</speaker>
                     <p>Return I've found it. — 
<stage>taking him for Ormin.</stage>
                     </p>
                  </sp>
                  <pb n="55" facs="tcp:50497:34"/>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>ALABEZ.</speaker>
                     <l>I should know that voice;</l>
                     <l>It is <hi>Charifa,</hi> ſtrange! what might she do</l>
                     <l>So late heer in theſe woods? I will approach</l>
                     <l>A little neerer. — 
<stage>aſide.</stage>
                     </l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>CHARIFA.</speaker>
                     <l>Thou but jeſts with me,</l>
                     <l>Kiſſe me no more, if thou doſt, <hi>I</hi>'l
retire.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>ALABEZ:</speaker>
                     <p>A rare piece this! <hi>I</hi> muſt hear all.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>CHARIFA.</speaker>
                     <l>Yes really,</l>
                     <l>Promiſe me to be quiet, or I'l leave thee.</l>
                     <l>This is a little too much liberty</l>
                     <l>At firſt, I am a maid that ſtands upon</l>
                     <l>My reputation, and fear evill tongues,</l>
                     <l>I hold my honour very precious to me.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>ALABEZ.</speaker>
                     <l>Thou ſeek'ſt to loſe it, and inviteſt him</l>
                     <l>To take it from thee. — 
<stage>aſide.</stage>
                     </l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>CHARIFA.</speaker>
                     <l>What thon ſpeakeſt not</l>
                     <l>A word unto me.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>ALABEZ.</speaker>
                     <p>Excellent adventure!</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>CHARIFA.</speaker>
                     <l>How doth thy heart ſigh, and thy cloſe mouth murmur?</l>
                     <l>Thoſe liberties, for all what I have ſaid,</l>
                     <l>May be excuſ'd, if thou will marry me;</l>
                     <l>Thou know'ſt that one muſt marry, to love well</l>
                     <l>And if I pleaſe thee. —</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>ALABEZ.</speaker>
                     <p>Oh? what impudence?</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>CHARIFA.</speaker>
                     <p>What ſay'ſt thou?</p>
                  </sp>
                  <pb n="56" facs="tcp:50497:35"/>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>ALABEZ.</speaker>
                     <p>I am much ſurpriſ'd, by Heaven.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>CHARIFA.</speaker>
                     <l>What! anſwereſt thou nothing? should this be</l>
                     <l>Through a contempt? I think that I'm not yet</l>
                     <l>So torn by time, as not to be thought worthy</l>
                     <l>To be conſidered; thou knoweſt well</l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Alabez,</hi> if I would have had that fellow.</l>
                     <l>My marriage with him had been already</l>
                     <l>Concluded, but that is a lowt, and hath not</l>
                     <l>The art to pleaſe me as thou haſt, his faults</l>
                     <l>Are more conſidered by me, then his ſervices.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>ALABEZ.</speaker>
                     <p>The impudent jeers at me to my face.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>CHARIFA.</speaker>
                     <l>That troubleſome never did any thing</l>
                     <l>Which pleaſed me, he hath a ſottish ſpirit,</l>
                     <l>And ſilly carriage; if the fool should marry me</l>
                     <l>I would not paſſe my word that he should not</l>
                     <l>Be one of thoſe which every one points at</l>
                     <l>With finger, which permit their neighbours to</l>
                     <l>Think their wives fair, a<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d which we commo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ly</l>
                     <l>Call cuckoulds.</l>
                  </sp>
               </div>
               <div n="7" type="scene">
                  <head>SCENE VII.</head>
                  <stage>ORMIN, CHARIFA, ALABEZ.</stage>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>ORMIN.</speaker>
                     <p>SEe heer, I have brought you <hi>light.</hi>
                     </p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>CHARIFA.</speaker>
                     <p>What have I done? this is a groſſe miſtake.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>ALABEZ.</speaker>
                     <p>What think'ſt thou; have not <hi>I</hi> much cauſe to
be</p>
                     <pb n="57" facs="tcp:50497:35"/>
                     <l>Well ſatisfied? I have done nothing then</l>
                     <l>That ever pleaſ'd thee, I've a ſottish ſpirit</l>
                     <l>And ſilly carriage. Thou shouldſt die with sha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>me.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>CHARIFA.</speaker>
                     <p>Why? prethee? I have utteted but a truth.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>ALABEZ.</speaker>
                     <l>But a truth, traitreſſe, o thou brazen face!</l>
                     <l>What! If I married thee, thou dangerous beaſt</l>
                     <l>I should be of the number of thoſe people</l>
                     <l>Which we call cuckoulds? thy impertinent tongue</l>
                     <l>Lied a hundred times, I'd rather chuſe</l>
                     <l>A rope then ſuch a bed fellow:</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>ORMIN.</speaker>
                     <l>Whence ſprings</l>
                     <l>Your quarrel?</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>ALABEZ.</speaker>
                     <l>Peace a while, I shall in good time</l>
                     <l>Talk with you, friend, companion of ill luck</l>
                  </sp>
                  <stage>Ormin putting out the candle.</stage>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>ORMIN.</speaker>
                     <l>We muſt be gone, there's nothing to be gotten</l>
                     <l>But blows heer by a fool. — 
<stage>Exeunt Ormin and Charifa.</stage>
                     </l>
                  </sp>
               </div>
               <div n="8" type="scene">
                  <head>SCENE VIII.</head>
                  <stage>ALMANSOR, GASVL, ALABEZ, ADIBAR.</stage>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>ALMANSOR.</speaker>
                     <l>GOe ſee whence comes this noiſe.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>ALABEZ.</speaker>
                     <l>Oh have <hi>I</hi> met thee, — 
<stage>giving Gaſul a buffett.</stage>
                     </l>
                     <l>precious Apoſtle?</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>GASVL.</speaker>
                     <p>How baſe traitor!</p>
                  </sp>
                  <pb n="58" facs="tcp:50497:36"/>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>ALABEZ.</speaker>
                     <l>Pardon me,</l>
                     <l>I took thee for another, in good faith:</l>
                     <l>I ſought a ras kal that eſcaped me,</l>
                     <l>To whom <hi>I</hi> did intend that injury</l>
                     <l>But I shall ſoon o'r take him without running.</l>
                     <stage>Exit Alabe.</stage>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>ALMANSOR.</speaker>
                     <p>Haſt learnt the cauſe of thoſe co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>fuſed rumours?</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>GASVL.</speaker>
                     <l>No, but <hi>I</hi> have beene beaten by a perſon,</l>
                     <l>Who afterward made me excuſes for't.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>ALMANSOR.</speaker>
                     <l>The houſe is not far of, give order to</l>
                     <l>The voices to advance, and bid them ſing</l>
                     <l>Neer to that Little wood.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <stage>Adibar appearing on the other ſide:</stage>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>ADIAAR.</speaker>
                     <l>See, friends, the place</l>
                     <l>Where <hi>Zasda</hi> dwels, if you are ready now.</l>
                     <l>Begin immediately.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <lg>
                     <head>The firſt ſong.</head>
                     <l>
                        <hi>YE deſerts, and dark cells</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Where night and ſilence dwells</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>You whom I truſt with my ſad cares.</hi>
                     </l>
                  </lg>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>GASVL.</speaker>
                     <p>This voice belongs not to our company.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>ALMANSOR,</speaker>
                     <l>This Stanza finish'd, let us be prepar'd</l>
                     <l>To ſing forthwith the ayr which I compoſ'd.</l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Ye deſerts and dark cells,</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Where night and ſilence dwells,</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>You whom I trust with my ſad cares,</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>With all my deaths, and my deſpairs,</hi>
                     </l>
                     <pb n="59" facs="tcp:50497:36"/>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Rocks, forreſts, and thick Shades,</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Which the Sun ne'r invades,</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>You in whoſe boſomes</hi> I <hi>encloſe</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>My love, my ſighs, my plaints, and wees:</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Alas! when will you be</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Keepers of my felicity?</hi>
                     </l>
                  </sp>
                  <lg>
                     <head>Second Song.</head>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Ye brooks, and Zephirs ſweet,</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Which heer in Spring-time meet</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>To water and perfume theſe plains</hi>
                     </l>
                  </lg>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>ADIBAR.</speaker>
                     <l>What inſole<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t voice troubles our confort heer.?</l>
                     <l>Th'affront shal not paſſe without punishment</l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Ye Brooks, and Zephirs ſweet,</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Which heer in Spring-time meet</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>To water and perfume theſe plains</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Frequented by the amorous Swains</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Favour me not to flovv</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Oblige me not to blow,</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Vntill my tears their courſe have ſpent,</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>And my ſighs given my greeſs fult vent,</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Then in your Channells glide,</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>And winds breathe, as before, in pride.</hi>
                     </l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>ADIBAR.</speaker>
                     <p>Who art thou that dar'ſt heer to trouble me?</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>ALMANSOR.</speaker>
                     <l>My name is too well known to be conce<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>l'd.</l>
                     <l>I'm call'd <hi>Almanſor.</hi>
                     </l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>ADIBAR.</speaker>
                     <l>Fear, fear then mine anger.</l>
                     <l>I'm <hi>Adibar,</hi> thy greateſt Enemy</l>
                     <l>Who to meet thee, have made ſome weary ſteps</l>
                     <l>Vnto no purpoſe; now when leaſt ſought
<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 span">
                           <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                        </gap>
                     </l>
                     <l>I've found thee; tell me, how comes it
<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 word">
                           <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                        </gap>
                     </l>
                     <pb n="60" facs="tcp:50497:37"/>
                     <l>Takeſt a licence to beſiege my Miſtreſſe</l>
                     <l>With ſo much inſolence? doſt viſit her,</l>
                     <l>As friend unto her brother, or as Lover</l>
                     <l>And ſervant unto her?</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>ALMANSOR,</speaker>
                     <l>Content thy ſelf</l>
                     <l>To underſtand that as the brothers friend,</l>
                     <l>The Siſter doth accept my ſetvices,</l>
                     <l>And that I reverence her: aſſure thy ſelf</l>
                     <l>That if I were ſo happy as to be</l>
                     <l>Her Lover, I should be diſcret enough,</l>
                     <l>Not to acquaint thee with it.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>ADIBAR.</speaker>
                     <l>Theſe refinings,</l>
                     <l>And juglings which thou uſeſt to defend thee,</l>
                     <l>Cannot withdraw thee from my juſt revenge,</l>
                     <l>Thou shalt die.— 
<stage>Drawes</stage>
                     </l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>ALMANSOR.</speaker>
                     <l>Rather fear that my ſword heer — 
<stage>drawes.</stage>
                     </l>
                     <l>Peircing thy heart, que<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ch thy love in thy blood.</l>
                  </sp>
               </div>
               <div n="9" type="scene">
                  <head>SCENE IX.</head>
                  <stage>ZEGRY, ADIBAR, ALMANSOR.</stage>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>ZEGRY.</speaker>
                     <l>FOr bear, and moderate this barbarous fury,</l>
                     <l>What means this, friends?</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>ADIBAR.</speaker>
                     <p>Nothing, ſince we are parted.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>ZEGRY.</speaker>
                     <p>Oh, iſt you <hi>Adibar?</hi>
                     </p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>ALMANSOR.</speaker>
                     <l>This is not the Song</l>
                     <l>Which I deſire.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <pb n="61" facs="tcp:50497:37"/>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>ADIBAR.</speaker>
                     <p>
                        <hi>Zegry,</hi> thou doſt me wrong.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>ZEGRY.</speaker>
                     <l>What cauſe, dear friend, could animate thee ſo?</l>
                     <l>Permit me, I beſeech you having parted you,</l>
                     <l>To reconcile you too at the ſame time:</l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>I</hi> take an intereſt in your debats:</l>
                     <l>Let me know therfor what your differnce is.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>ADIBAR.</speaker>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Zegry</hi> in vaine you interpoſe your ſelf</l>
                     <l>To hinder the proceeding, my revengt</l>
                     <l>Is juſt, and your cares but prolong his life</l>
                     <l>For ſome few minures. — 
<stage>Exit Adibar.</stage>
                     </l>
                  </sp>
               </div>
               <div n="10" type="scene">
                  <head>SCENE. X.</head>
                  <stage>ZEGRY, ALMANSOR.</stage>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>ZEGRY.</speaker>
                     <l>DEare <hi>Almanſor tell me</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>Whence comes ſo ſtrong a hate between you two?</l>
                     <l>Relate the cauſe on't,</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>ALMANSOR.</speaker>
                     <l>Tis not worth the labour;</l>
                     <l>This petty difference which troubles thee,</l>
                     <l>Should be determined ere known.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>ZEGRY.</speaker>
                     <l>In vain</l>
                     <l>Thon doſt perſiſt to hide this ſecret from me:</l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Almanſor,</hi> I gheſſe at it; ſure, ſome
Beauty</l>
                     <l>Embroils you; I've heard heer two different conſorts.</l>
                     <l>The reſt I do divine.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>ALMANSOR.</speaker>
                     <l>Friend, I confeſſe it;</l>
                     <l>We both at one time gave our Evering Muſick</l>
                     <l>To one and the ſame Miſtreſſe.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <pb n="62" facs="tcp:50497:38"/>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>ZEGRY.</speaker>
                     <l>May not I</l>
                     <l>Know her name, Friend?</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>ALMANSOR.</speaker>
                     <l>Heavens how am <hi>I</hi> put to <g ref="char:punc">▪</g>t?</l>
                     <l>Should I tell him that I adore his ſiſter? — 
<stage>aſide.</stage>
                     </l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>ZEGRY.</speaker>
                     <l>Friend, this reſervednes ſuits not that name,</l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>I</hi> did not hide my amours for <hi>Fatima</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>From thee.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>ALMANSOR.</speaker>
                     <l>He hath already promiſed</l>
                     <l>His ſiſter; I'm confounded; if <hi>I</hi> dare</l>
                     <l>To name her, what will he not ſay? — 
<stage>aſide.</stage>
                     </l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>ZEGRY.</speaker>
                     <l>This confuſ'd ſilence should ſufficiently</l>
                     <l>Inſtruct me that he doth adore <hi>Fatima,</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>And dares not tell it me — 
<stage>aſide.</stage>
                     </l>
                     <l>What! shall I not</l>
                     <l>Know then what object hath ſubjected thee?</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>ALMANSOR.</speaker>
                     <l>Her fair name uttered would make us enemies,</l>
                     <l>Inſtead of doing thee a courteſy</l>
                     <l>I should do thee an injur<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>; adiew;</l>
                     <l>Diſpenſe me to ſay more on't.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>ZEGRY.</speaker>
                     <l>How is this!</l>
                     <l>Wilt thou not go unto my houſe?</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>ALMANSOR</speaker>
                     <l>Exouſe me,</l>
                     <l>This night I am engag'd by promiſe to</l>
                     <l>Lodge at <hi>Gomella's.</hi>
                     </l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>ZEGRY.</speaker>
                     <p>How! <hi>Gomella's,</hi> ſayſt thou?</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>ALMANSOR.</speaker>
                     <l>Yes, I fear that he ſtays for me, adiew,</l>
                     <pb n="63" facs="tcp:50497:38"/>
                     <l>I'ue promiſed him, and I can't fail my word. 
<stage>Exit Almanſor.</stage>
                     </l>
                  </sp>
                  <stage>Zegry alone.</stage>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>ZEGRY</speaker>
                     <l>The traitor Loves <hi>Fatima:</hi> and intends</l>
                     <l>To marry her: to judge on't otherwiſe,</l>
                     <l>Is to abuſe my ſelf; yes owing me,</l>
                     <l>His life, he makes uſe of it to deſtroy me;</l>
                     <l>But he that could ſave it, can alſo ruine it;</l>
                     <l>And his death loudly shall proclaime to all</l>
                     <l>That the ſame arm which ſerves the innocent,</l>
                     <l>Can punish the ingratefull inſolent.</l>
                  </sp>
               </div>
               <trailer>The End of the third Act.</trailer>
            </div>
            <div n="4" type="act">
               <head>ACT IV.</head>
               <div n="1" type="scene">
                  <head>SCENE I.</head>
                  <stage>ALMANSOR, GOMELLA</stage>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>ALMANSOR.</speaker>
                     <l>YOu shal not go alone to meet my mother,</l>
                     <l>I <g ref="char:punc">▪</g>l follow you, <hi>Gomella.</hi>
                     </l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>GOMELLA</speaker>
                     <l>That needs not</l>
                     <l>Her order doth oblige you to expect her</l>
                     <l>Here at my houſe.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>ALMANSOR.</speaker>
                     <l>But nature doth impoſe</l>
                     <l>A ſtronger law upon me.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>GOMELLA.</speaker>
                     <l>Sir she hath not</l>
                     <pb n="64" facs="tcp:50497:39"/>
                     <l>Vnderſtood of your comming yet, your ſight</l>
                     <l>Will be too ſudden a ſurpriſe, for bear</l>
                     <l>Till I acquaint her with it.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>ALMANSOR</speaker>
                     <l>I expect</l>
                     <l>No blame in this encounter; If I should</l>
                     <l>Surpriſe her, it would be delightfully:</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>GOMELLA.</speaker>
                     <p>Seeing you will, let's go together then.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>ALMANSOR.</speaker>
                     <p>I do but what I ought.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>GOMELLA.</speaker>
                     <p>I ſpeak my thoughts.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>ALMANSOR.</speaker>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Zegry</hi> comes forth his houſe; before <hi>I</hi>
go,</l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>I</hi> muſt embrace him.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>GOMELLA.</speaker>
                     <p>Stay, you may not do it.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>ALMANSOR.</speaker>
                     <l>Conſtraint's unjuſt, as much as it is cruell:</l>
                     <l>Ought I to fly a friend ſo dear, ſo faithfull?</l>
                     <l>Suffer me to ſpeak to him, and I'l follow you</l>
                     <l>Immediately.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>GOMELLA.</speaker>
                     <l>I cannot, for I have an expreſſe order</l>
                     <l>Vnto the contrary. — 
<stage>Exeunt.</stage>
                     </l>
                  </sp>
               </div>
               <div n="2" type="scene">
                  <head>SCENE II.</head>
                  <stage>ZEGRY, ORMIN.</stage>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>ZEGRY.</speaker>
                     <l>
                        <hi>ORmin,</hi> did'ſt thou obſerve how carefully</l>
                     <l>That traitor shun'd me aſſoon as he ſaw me?</l>
                     <l>Did'ſt mark how he was troubled at firſt,</l>
                     <l>How he advanc'd, a ſtep or two to Wards me,</l>
                     <pb n="65" facs="tcp:50497:39"/>
                     <l>And then went back again, how he reſign'd</l>
                     <l>The place unto me in confuſion,</l>
                     <l>Preſs'd with the ſtings of his ingratitude?</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>ORMIN.</speaker>
                     <l>What ever I obſerved, it can never</l>
                     <l>Enter into my thought <hi>Almanſor</hi> should</l>
                     <l>Be guilty of ſo baſe and black a crime;</l>
                     <l>And though in shew I find him culpable,</l>
                     <l>I eſteem him incapable to commit</l>
                     <l>Any baſe act; he ſtill appear'd vnto me</l>
                     <l>A perſon of much honour, and too jealous</l>
                     <l>Thereof, ſo ill t'imploy the life which he</l>
                     <l>Holdeth of you: beſides I find within me</l>
                     <l>A certain ſecret inſtinct which <hi>I</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>Can't comprehend, that when <hi>I</hi> should accu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſe
him,</l>
                     <l>Forceth me to defend him.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>ZEGRY.</speaker>
                     <l>Seeing me</l>
                     <l>To cheris'h that too much belov'd Ingratefull,</l>
                     <l>Thou art accuſtom'd alſo to careſſe him.</l>
                     <l>I can't believe, neither that he betrays me,</l>
                     <l>Nor can I doubt ont, that's my punishment.</l>
                     <l>And thoſe ſweet motions, which I ſcarce can
banish,</l>
                     <l>Aggravate his offence, inſtead of leſſening it:</l>
                     <l>Iudge then how much I am to be lamented</l>
                     <l>In this condition, the onely good</l>
                     <l>That reſts to me, is to fear nothing more.</l>
                     <l>Fortune would not afflict me heer by halfs;</l>
                     <l>I loſe a Miſtreſſe, and a friend together:</l>
                     <l>Both injure me, and I have ſo much weaknes,</l>
                     <l>That I can't hate the Miſtreſſe, nor the Friend;</l>
                     <l>But could'ſt thou yeſterday learn from
<hi>Charifa</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>Why fair <hi>Fatima</hi> hath ſo much contempt</l>
                     <l>Within her boſome for me? thou haſt told me</l>
                     <pb n="66" facs="tcp:50497:40"/>
                     <l>That <hi>Adibar</hi> doth charm her, but thou haſt not</l>
                     <l>Tould me from whence her hatred doth pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceed.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>ORMIN.</speaker>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Fatima,</hi> if I may believe what hath</l>
                     <l>Been told me, alwaies did abhore you for</l>
                     <l>Vnfaithfullnes, she hath ſome reaſon to</l>
                     <l>Believe you falſe, and this is that as far</l>
                     <l>As I can underſtand, which doth oblige her</l>
                     <l>To be ſo cruell to you.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>ZEGRY.</speaker>
                     <l>Falſe, ſayſt thou?</l>
                     <l>I never was ſo.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>ORMIN.</speaker>
                     <l>She hath underſtood though,</l>
                     <l>That a maid call'd <hi>Zelinda,</hi> faire enough,</l>
                     <l>Very young, and of an illuſtrious family,</l>
                     <l>And who received ſometime many ſervices</l>
                     <l>From you, being almoſt on the point to ſee you</l>
                     <l>Her husband, and when all things were diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſ'd</l>
                     <l>And ready for the mariage was fouly</l>
                     <l>For ſaken by you and deſpis'd; it ſeems</l>
                     <l>That this example toucheth, and doth teach her</l>
                     <l>That who can once, can cha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ge a thouſa<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d times.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>ZEGRY.</speaker>
                     <p>Ormin, this change is no inconſtancy.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>ORMIN.</speaker>
                     <p>It would be very hard to prove it innocent:</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>ZEGRY.</speaker>
                     <l>VVithout doubt this pretended mariage</l>
                     <l>Made a great noiſe; but I wil tell thee all</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>ORMIN.</speaker>
                     <l>VVhat will th'ing ratefull ſay? — 
<stage>aſide</stage>
                     </l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>ZEGRY:</speaker>
                     <l>Before that mariage was concluded which</l>
                     <pb n="67" facs="tcp:50497:40"/>
                     <l>VVas to unite us to <hi>Abencerage</hi> blood,</l>
                     <l>And by that means at laſt to quench the heat</l>
                     <l>Of an old hatred, fair <hi>Fatima</hi> was</l>
                     <l>Already Miſtreſſe of my heart; to make me</l>
                     <l>Take a new chain, <hi>Zelinda,</hi> who<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> they offered me</l>
                     <l>In my opinion, was not fair enough:</l>
                     <l>So that I ſaw her without loving her:</l>
                     <l>Her feeble Beauty could not shake the fetters</l>
                     <l>VVhich tied me, yet I indeavoured</l>
                     <l>To have ſom kindnes for her, but her eyes</l>
                     <l>Or my heart were not ſtrong enoug to work it;</l>
                     <l>And if I did her any ſervices,</l>
                     <l>It was but in deſign to pleaſe my parents:</l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Fatima</hi> there fore is to blame to think</l>
                     <l>That <hi>I</hi> am falſe: ſince <hi>I</hi> had never
love</l>
                     <l>For any but for her.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>ORMIN.</speaker>
                     <l>Alas! I need not</l>
                     <l>Doubt more of his contempt! I was inquiſitive</l>
                     <l>To know too much, and now <hi>I</hi> doe repent it. — 
<stage>aſide.</stage>
                     </l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>ZEGRY.</speaker>
                     <l>This is a truth, which eaſily can bee ptov'd?</l>
                     <l>But how comes it my ſiſter, sup ſo ſoon?</l>
                  </sp>
               </div>
               <div n="3" type="scene">
                  <head>SCENE III.</head>
                  <stage>ZAIDA, MEDINA, ZEGRT, ORMIN.</stage>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>ZAIDA,</speaker>
                     <l>Brother, have you receiv'd th' intelligence</l>
                     <l>Is given me of the death of him which was</l>
                     <l>Deſigned for my husband?</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>ZEGRY.</speaker>
                     <l>Yes, I've heard it;</l>
                     <l>It is too true, he died in <hi>Argier</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>O'th ſpotted feaver.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <pb n="68" facs="tcp:50497:41"/>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>ZAIDA.</speaker>
                     <l>I'm unhappy by it;</l>
                     <l>But you are neer your ioy, and may diſcourſe</l>
                     <l>Of mariage and love.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>ZEGRY.</speaker>
                     <l>Oh, Siſter, rather</l>
                     <l>Say that I muſt no longer now diſcourſe</l>
                     <l>Of love nor Mariage: ſay that I muſt punish</l>
                     <l>A baſe and an ingratefull ſpirit with death</l>
                     <l>One that hath wickedly betray'd my frie<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>dship:</l>
                     <l>Fury alone preſides now in my ſoul,</l>
                     <l>And I muſt think nor ſpeak of any thing</l>
                     <l>But of destroying a perfidious wretch.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>ZAIDA.</speaker>
                     <l>Who is that traitor? let me know, I pray you,</l>
                     <l>What ſignall crime provoketh you ſo highly.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>ZEGRY.</speaker>
                     <l>Thou know'ſt too well the Authour of my in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jury</l>
                     <l>His name's <hi>Almanſor,</hi> his love is his crime,</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>ZAIDA.</speaker>
                     <p>His love! what hear I?</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>ZEGRY.</speaker>
                     <l>Siſter, tis too true.</l>
                     <l>His inſolent love hath ſtirred up mine anger.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>ZAIDA.</speaker>
                     <l>He knoweth that <hi>Almanſor</hi> loveth me,</l>
                     <l>And that is it enrageth him. — 
<stage>aſide.</stage>
                     </l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>ZEGRY.</speaker>
                     <l>His death,</l>
                     <l>Is juſt, add he shall die, baſe, and ingratefull!</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>ZAIDA.</speaker>
                     <l>Brother, you should examine without paſſion</l>
                     <l>All that which might be of a friend ſuſpected,</l>
                     <l>And we should never judge of his offence</l>
                     <l>But with much care and much indulgence: al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>waies</l>
                     <pb n="69" facs="tcp:50497:41"/>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Almanſor</hi> htth appear'd too generous</l>
                     <l>To mingle any foul or unjuſt thing</l>
                     <l>In his affections; and he oweth you</l>
                     <l>Too much, to have a thought to wrong a frie<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d</l>
                     <l>That ſav'd his life.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>ZEGRY.</speaker>
                     <l>Siſter, thou doſt oblige me;</l>
                     <l>Thy arguments with little contradiction</l>
                     <l>Diſarm all my reſentments quite; <hi>Almanſor</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>Is ſo dear to me, that how ere he wrongs me,</l>
                     <l>Thou wilt do me a coutteſie, to ſtop</l>
                     <l>My anger.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>ZAIDA.</speaker>
                     <p>Perhaps, you have accuſed him unjuſtly.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>ZEGRY.</speaker>
                     <l>Would that it pleaſed Heaven <hi>I</hi> were abus'd!</l>
                     <l>But alas! my ſuſpition is too juſt,</l>
                     <l>I'l tell't thee now; he loveth</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>ZAIDA.</speaker>
                     <p>Who?</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>ZEGRY.</speaker>
                     <p>
                        <hi>Fatima:</hi>
                     </p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>ZAIDA.</speaker>
                     <l>How! should he love <hi>Fatima?</hi> really</l>
                     <l>That crime is black:</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>ZEGRY.</speaker>
                     <l>The better to aſſure thee on't, tis beſt</l>
                     <l>Thou go to viſſit her, I do believe</l>
                     <l>Thou'lt vnderſtand fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> her that he adores her,</l>
                     <l>And that he's falſe to me.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>ZAIDA.</speaker>
                     <l>Tra<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>itor! Inconſtant!</l>
                     <l>Pernitious Spirit!</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>ZEGRY.</speaker>
                     <l>But, Siſter, VVhy appear you</l>
                     <l>So troubled in your eyes and countenance?</l>
                  </sp>
                  <pb n="70" facs="tcp:50497:42"/>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>ZAIDA.</speaker>
                     <l>The trouble of mine eyes cleerly denotes</l>
                     <l>That my heart feels the evils which your friend doth
you,</l>
                     <l>Your frie<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d, what haye I ſaid? that name ſuits ill</l>
                     <l>With his condition, if he be your Rivall,</l>
                     <l>He's not your friend. Goe perſently to quench</l>
                     <l>His life and Love, and wash away the crimes</l>
                     <l>Of his ſoul in his blood.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>ZEGRY.</speaker>
                     <l>No, Siſter, no;</l>
                     <l>We should examine without paſſion</l>
                     <l>All that which might be of a friend ſuſpected,</l>
                     <l>And one should never judge of his offence</l>
                     <l>But with much care and much indulgence; al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>waies</l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Almansor</hi> hath appear'd too generous,</l>
                     <l>To mingle any foul, or vnjuſt thing</l>
                     <l>In his affections; and he oweth me</l>
                     <l>Too much, to have a thought to wro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>g a frie<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d</l>
                     <l>That ſau'd his life.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>ZAIDA.</speaker>
                     <p>In what an errour are you?</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>ZEGRY.</speaker>
                     <l>If I am in an errour, I receiv'd it</l>
                     <l>From you: theſe were your ſentiments, good Siſter,</l>
                     <l>And shall be mine.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>ZAIDA.</speaker>
                     <l>Then knew I not his crime;</l>
                     <l>But now that it is plain, take your revenge,</l>
                     <l>I will no more reſtrain you.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>ZEGRY.</speaker>
                     <l>Stop me rather;</l>
                     <l>Condemn my anger, not my amity.</l>
                     <l>In favour of <hi>Almanſor</hi> I would be</l>
                     <pb n="71" facs="tcp:50497:42"/>
                     <l>Abus'd; I will accuſe him, but I would</l>
                     <l>That others should excuſe him, I ſpeak of</l>
                     <l>Revenge, but ſeek it not, and threaten only</l>
                     <l>But to the end to have my arme reſtrain'd.</l>
                     <l>His paſſion, perhaps, may be condemn<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>d</l>
                     <l>Vnjuſtly: poſſibly i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap> might be born.</l>
                     <l>Before our friendship, and, perhaps <hi>Fatima</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>Anſwereth unto it, and that to unite them,</l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Gomellas</hi> orders do invite him heer;</l>
                     <l>If it be ſo, to free my ſelf from crime,</l>
                     <l>Siſter, tis juſt I yeild <hi>Fatima</hi> to him:</l>
                     <l>I'l break my chains, and with a ſetled heart</l>
                     <l>Will make the pleaſures of my friend mine own.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>ZAIDA.</speaker>
                     <l>what ſtrange abuſe, what ſeeret charm thus
ſoftens</l>
                     <l>Your heart in the behalf of an Ingratefull:</l>
                     <l>He owes his life unto you: ought he not</l>
                     <l>T'acquit him ſelf to wards you by all poſſible</l>
                     <l>Indeavours? if he be our Rivall, can you</l>
                     <l>Without much weaknes tamely give him up</l>
                     <l>Your Miſtreſſe? if he be your friend, as you</l>
                     <l>Eſteem him, ought he not to give you up</l>
                     <l>The object which you love.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>ZEGRY.</speaker>
                     <l>Without reply</l>
                     <l>Go preſently to viſit fair <hi>Fatima:</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>And fail not fully to inform your ſelf</l>
                     <l>Of their intelligence. — 
<stage>Exit Zegry.</stage>
                     </l>
                  </sp>
                  <stage>MEDINA ZAIDA.</stage>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>MEDINA.</speaker>
                     <l>YOu aſtonish me;</l>
                     <l>I can't conceive how one can love a man,</l>
                     <l>And preſſe his death.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <pb n="72" facs="tcp:50497:43"/>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>ZAIDA.</speaker>
                     <l>Oh! ſay not that I love</l>
                     <l>Such an ingratefull and inconſtant wretch:</l>
                     <l>Believe that if I have fires, they are fires</l>
                     <l>Of rage, and that my heart will ne'r be qui<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="2 letters">
                           <desc>••</desc>
                        </gap>
                     </l>
                     <l>Till this perfidious Lover be a ſacrifice</l>
                     <l>To my juſt anger.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>MEDINA.</speaker>
                     <p>But you weep, Madam.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>ZAIDA.</speaker>
                     <l>True, I weep, Medina:</l>
                     <l>If that falſe one should perish, I should die;</l>
                     <l>I feel that rage and tendernes, hate and love</l>
                     <l>Triumph by Turns within me: I'm his Enemy</l>
                     <l>And yet I am his Lover, when my anger</l>
                     <l>Encreaſeth, th'other Kinder paſſion ſprings:</l>
                     <l>And though that he be louely, and hath fal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſely</l>
                     <l>Betray'd me, <hi>I</hi> can neither love, nor hate him</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>MEDINA.</speaker>
                     <l>Madam, ſpeak ſofter, you will elce be heard.</l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Adibar</hi> comes to wards us.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>ZAIDA.</speaker>
                     <p>I'l not ſtay.</p>
                  </sp>
               </div>
               <div n="4" type="scene">
                  <head>SCENE V.</head>
                  <stage>ADIBAR, ZAIDA, MEDINA.</stage>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>ADIBAR.</speaker>
                     <p>
                        <hi>Zaida,</hi> where go you with my heart?</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>ZAIDA.</speaker>
                     <l>I pray you,</l>
                     <l>Leave me alone, and do not trouble me,</l>
                     <l>Adieu.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <pb n="73" facs="tcp:50497:43"/>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>ADIBAR.</speaker>
                     <p>
                        <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>eceive my
ſervices.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>ZAIDA,</speaker>
                     <l>
                        <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap> have</l>
                     <l>
                        <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>o need of
them.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>ADIBAR.</speaker>
                     <p>
                        <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap> do
beſeech you, hear me.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>ZAIDA.</speaker>
                     <p>You muſt excuſe me, I have other buſines.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>ADIBAR.</speaker>
                     <l>With a look onely, conſolate my griefs;</l>
                     <l>
                        <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>is you I
ſeek.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>ZAIDA.</speaker>
                     <p>And tis you that I fly.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>ADIBAR.</speaker>
                     <p>How! treat you ſuch a faithfull I over ſo?</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>ZAIDA.</speaker>
                     <p>
                        <hi>Fatima</hi> there will be leſſe cruell to you.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>ADIBAR.</speaker>
                     <l>Mock not at her, <hi>Fatima</hi> is as fair,</l>
                     <l>Although leſſe proud then you.</l>
                  </sp>
               </div>
               <div n="5" type="scene">
                  <head>SCENE VI.</head>
                  <stage>FATIMA, ZAIDA, ADIBAR, CHARIFA, MEDINA.</stage>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>FATIMA.</speaker>
                     <l>VVHat <hi>Adibar</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>Still with this ſcornfull? my revenge is juſt.</l>
                     <l>'Tis time that it break forth. <hi>Zaida, I</hi> find
you</l>
                     <l>In ſuch a black and heavy melancholy,</l>
                     <l>That I loſe the deſign which brought me hither:</l>
                     <l>Shall I dare ſpeak of dances, revels, feaſts,</l>
                     <l>And of a mariage in the condition</l>
                     <l>Wherein you are?</l>
                  </sp>
                  <pb n="74" facs="tcp:50497:44"/>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>ZAIDA.</speaker>
                     <p>What ſay you, of a mariage?</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>FATIMA.</speaker>
                     <l>Since you preſſe me,</l>
                     <l>You shall know all; know that my <hi>Father</hi> ha<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>
                     </l>
                     <l>Provided one for me.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>ZAIDA.</speaker>
                     <p>For you, <hi>Fatima?</hi>
                     </p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>FATIMA.</speaker>
                     <p>Yes, <hi>Zaida,</hi> and she bufimes is well forwar<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>
                     </p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>ZAIDA.</speaker>
                     <l>In your contents I claim an intereſt:</l>
                     <l>I should be glad to know your Lovers name.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>FATIMA.</speaker>
                     <l>He's an accomplish<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>d man, noble, and bra<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="2 letters">
                           <desc>••</desc>
                        </gap>
                     </l>
                     <l>And of a charming preſence, and rare meri<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>
                        <g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
                     </l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>I</hi> doubt not but you will approve the choice</l>
                     <l>My Father hath made of him.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>ZAIDA.</speaker>
                     <l>How she makes me</l>
                     <l>Languish to meet death? — 
<stage>aſide.</stage>
                     </l>
                     <l>Well, who is the man?</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>FATIMA.</speaker>
                     <l>You know him very well;</l>
                     <l>He made long time his ordinary reſidence</l>
                     <l>At home with you; your brother Zegrys frie<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="2 letters">
                           <desc>••</desc>
                        </gap>
                     </l>
                     <l>Have I yet ſaid ynough?</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>ZAIDA.</speaker>
                     <p>Tell me his name too.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>FATIMA,</speaker>
                     <p>Divine you not that he is call'd <hi>Almanſor!</hi>
                     </p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>ZAIDA.</speaker>
                     <p>I can no more, but faint and die. — 
<stage>aſide.</stage>
                     </p>
                  </sp>
                  <pb n="75" facs="tcp:50497:44"/>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>FATIMA</speaker>
                     <l>How she</l>
                     <l>Is chang<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>d, she feels my pain, and I'm re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veng'd</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>ADIBAR.</speaker>
                     <p>I have much intereſt in this event.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>ZAIDA.</speaker>
                     <p>This match without doubt cannot chuſe but pleaſe
you.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>FATIMA.</speaker>
                     <l>True, I am not of thoſe who through a maxi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>me</l>
                     <l>Of I know not, what modeſty, blush at ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riage</l>
                     <l>As if it were a crime, feign to ſigh at it,</l>
                     <l>And yet in ſecret are ſad at the heart,</l>
                     <l>If it should not be conſummate. I aſſure you.</l>
                     <l>Vpon this point I not diſſemble with you:</l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>I</hi> no way hate the Lover that<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>s deſign'd
me,</l>
                     <l>I prize his love, his ſervices, his merit</l>
                     <l>At a high rate, and if he loves me much,</l>
                     <l>He is no leſſe belov'd.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>ZAIDA.</speaker>
                     <l>It ſeemeth then,</l>
                     <l>He loves you very much.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>FATIMA.</speaker>
                     <l>I can't expreſſe it:</l>
                     <l>He lives but for me, breatheth but for me:</l>
                     <l>I am the ſole original of his good</l>
                     <l>Or evill fortune when he ſees me not,</l>
                     <l>He is in torments, and when hazard bring me</l>
                     <l>Vnto his ſight, again, I have great cauſe</l>
                     <l>To fear that he might die with ſudden joy;</l>
                     <l>Laſtly if any truth be in his oaths,</l>
                     <l>All other beauties are contemptible to him.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <pb n="76" facs="tcp:50497:45"/>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>ZAIDA.</speaker>
                     <l>Oh Heaven! what hear <hi>I,</hi> where am <hi>I?</hi> oh
traitor!</l>
                     <l>Ingratefull wretch! — 
<stage>aſide.</stage>
                     </l>
                     <l>But could you ſo ſoon love him</l>
                     <l>Before yov knew him?</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>FATIMA.</speaker>
                     <l>I cannot be blam<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>d</l>
                     <l>For this quick love, I ſaw in him at firſt</l>
                     <l>All things that might induce a maid to love</l>
                     <l>Beſides heerein <hi>I</hi> execute the order</l>
                     <l>My Father doth ordain, I willingly</l>
                     <l>Obey his will; and ſince he hath choſen him</l>
                     <l>For ſon in law and for ſupport, I think</l>
                     <l>That he is worthy of it, and conform</l>
                     <l>My ſelf unto him.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>ZAIDA.</speaker>
                     <l>But what are your thoughts</l>
                     <l>Of <hi>Adibar?</hi>
                     </l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>ADIBAR.</speaker>
                     <l>
                        <hi>I</hi> dare not to pretend</l>
                     <l>To her paſſ'd goodneſs more.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>FATIMA.</speaker>
                     <l>He deſerv'd not</l>
                     <l>The honour of my love; he changed firſt,</l>
                     <l>And I change at my turn.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>ZAIDA.</speaker>
                     <l>He was not alwaies</l>
                     <l>Vnworthy to pleaſe you; can you forget him.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>FATIMA.</speaker>
                     <l>Yes, and with much juſtice, and reaſon too,</l>
                     <l>He is to me the moſt ingratefull perſon</l>
                     <l>Vpon the earth; his contempt was unjuſt,</l>
                     <l>But mine is not ſo. Let us ceaſe to ſpeak</l>
                     <l>Of that inconſtant Lover; I will pay him</l>
                     <l>Hatred for hatred, contempt for contempt.</l>
                     <pb n="77" facs="tcp:50497:45"/>
                     <l>Let us again talk of our mariage,</l>
                     <l>And let me know if <hi>I</hi> may have the honour</l>
                     <l>To ſee you there,</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>ZAIDA.</speaker>
                     <l>Excuſe me, <hi>I</hi>'m oppreſſ<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>d</l>
                     <l>With a great pain, which is redoubled</l>
                     <l>Since your diſcourſe, ſo that I'm rendered</l>
                     <l>Incapable to be preſent there, and am</l>
                     <l>Inforc'd to quit you at this very inſtant.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>ADIBAR</speaker>
                     <l>I wait you; ſuffer me to pay the ſervice</l>
                     <l>I owe you. — 
<stage>He leads her by the arm?</stage>
                     </l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>ZAIDA,</speaker>
                     <l>I am forced through my weaknes</l>
                     <l>To accept your ſupport. — 
<stage>Exeunt Zaida &amp; Adibar</stage>
                     </l>
                  </sp>
               </div>
               <div n="6" type="scene">
                  <head>SCENE VII.</head>
                  <stage>FATIMA, CHARIFA.</stage>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>FATIMA,</speaker>
                     <l>
                        <hi>ZAida</hi> feels my diſcaſe, but <hi>Adibar</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>Flies me: herein my revenge is compleat,</l>
                     <l>Though my hope be deſtroyd.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>CHARIFA.</speaker>
                     <l>You have loſt nothing</l>
                     <l>By that, <hi>Almanſor's</hi> worth a thouſand of him</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>FATIMA.</speaker>
                     <l>Iudge better of my plaint, what I have ſaid</l>
                     <l>Is but a fiction; I perceive <hi>Medina</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>And thou are intimate, she could not chuſe</l>
                     <l>But tell thee that <hi>Almanſor's</hi> very dear</l>
                     <l>To the ingratefull <hi>Zaida,</hi> this <hi>I</hi> heard</l>
                     <l>From thy own mouth.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <pb n="78" facs="tcp:50497:46"/>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>CHARIFA.</speaker>
                     <p>Well.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>FATIMA.</speaker>
                     <l>This deviſe of mine,</l>
                     <l>In feigning that <hi>Almanſor</hi> was to marry me,</l>
                     <l>Is to revenge me of her for admitting,</l>
                     <l>Contrary to her promiſe, my falſe Lover</l>
                     <l>To addreſſe courtship to her, and to punish her</l>
                     <l>For the evills which she hath procured me.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>CHARIFA.</speaker>
                     <p>How cunning are you! this deceit is notable.</p>
                  </sp>
               </div>
               <div n="7" type="scene">
                  <head>SCENE VIII.</head>
                  <stage>ADIBAR FATIMA.</stage>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>FATIMA.</speaker>
                     <p>HOw! quit ſo ſoon the object of your heart?</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>ADIBAR.</speaker>
                     <p>I ſtudied more her reſt then my content.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>FATIMA.</speaker>
                     <l>You appear ſeiſed with an extream ſadnes.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>ADIBAR.</speaker>
                     <l>
                        <hi>I</hi> cannot ſee that ſuffer which I love</l>
                     <l>Without grief.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>FATIMA.</speaker>
                     <p>
                        <hi>Zaida</hi> ſure, repulſed you.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>ADIBAR.</speaker>
                     <l>My reſpect only put me of, and not</l>
                     <l>Her cruelty,</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>FATIMA.</speaker>
                     <l>If she were juſt, or generous</l>
                     <l>She would deſpiſe a lover that's unſaithfull.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>ADIBAR.</speaker>
                     <p>I were to blame, if I should complain of her.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <pb n="79" facs="tcp:50497:46"/>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>FATIMA.</speaker>
                     <p>
                        <hi>Almanſers</hi> fortune is more ſweet with me.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>ADIBAR.</speaker>
                     <p>I'm to well ſatisfied, to be jealous of it.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>FATIMA.</speaker>
                     <l>You do but flatter you with a vain hope,</l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Zaida</hi> hath but diſdain, and hate for you.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>ADIBAR.</speaker>
                     <l>Her hate and her diſdain are ended now;</l>
                     <l>And our hearts ſpeedily shall be united</l>
                     <l>By mariage.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>FATIMA.</speaker>
                     <l>But Sir, you may be miſtaken</l>
                     <l>In your accompt, and hope; do you not know</l>
                     <l>That <hi>Zaida's</hi> promiſ'd?</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>ADIBAR.</speaker>
                     <l>Rather you may be</l>
                     <l>Deceived in this point: perhaps you know not</l>
                     <l>That he who was to marry her, is dead.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>FATIMA.</speaker>
                     <p>How is he dead?</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>ADIBAR.</speaker>
                     <l>Yes Madam, and fair <hi>Zaida</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>Propitious at laſt, will render juſtice</l>
                     <l>To my devout affection, and did</l>
                     <l>Aſſure me when I took my leave of her</l>
                     <l>That she would marry me, if I could get</l>
                     <l>Her brother to conſent unto't; adiew;</l>
                     <l>To obtain this ſo dear and pretious Beauty,</l>
                     <l>I muſt addreſſe me to her brother, and</l>
                     <l>Solicit my beſt friends. — 
<stage>Exit Adibar.</stage>
                     </l>
                  </sp>
               </div>
               <div n="8" type="scene">
                  <pb n="80" facs="tcp:50497:47"/>
                  <head>SCENE IX.</head>
                  <stage>FATIMA, CHARIFA.</stage>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>FATIMA.</speaker>
                     <l>WHat have I done?</l>
                     <l>Alas! my fiction hath only ſerv<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>d</l>
                     <l>To diſpoſe <hi>Zaida</hi> to deprive me of</l>
                     <l>My Lover.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>CHARIFA.</speaker>
                     <p>Madam. —</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>FATIMA.</speaker>
                     <l>Leave me; in a fate</l>
                     <l>So ſad as this, every thing hurts, deſtroyes,</l>
                     <l>And makes me deſperate.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>CHARIFA,</speaker>
                     <p>Will you not hear me?</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>FATIMA.</speaker>
                     <l>No, I hear nothing but the fury which</l>
                     <l>Raigns in my confef'd ſpirits, grief ſeiſeth me</l>
                     <l>And anger doth tranſport me.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>CHARIFA.</speaker>
                     <p>Madam, comfort you.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>FATIMA.</speaker>
                     <l>Oh that I were dead! ceaſe to comfort me</l>
                     <l>In ſuch a juſt deſpair put me to bed,</l>
                     <l>Or in my grave there to lye buried.</l>
                  </sp>
               </div>
               <trailer>The End of the fourth Act.</trailer>
            </div>
            <div n="5" type="act">
               <pb n="81" facs="tcp:50497:47"/>
               <head>ACT V.</head>
               <div n="1" type="scene">
                  <head>SCENE I.</head>
                  <stage>GOMELLA, LINDARACHE, ALMANSOR.</stage>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>GOMELLA.</speaker>
                     <l>YOu ſee the cote where I make my abode.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>LINDARACHE.</speaker>
                     <l>Sir, if you pleaſe, I shall defire to be</l>
                     <l>Private a while here with my ſon, and pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſently</l>
                     <l>I'm yours.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>ALMANSOR.</speaker>
                     <l>Oh Madam, oh dear Mother,</l>
                     <l>In this bleſt time shal I obtain the honour</l>
                     <l>Of your embracements?</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>LINDERACHE.</speaker>
                     <l>Stay, <hi>Abencerage,</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>Know our dishonour firſt, and shew thy ſelf</l>
                     <l>My ſon before I embrace thee, I was mother</l>
                     <l>Of two fair children, when a Ravisher</l>
                     <l>Stole away both my Daughter, and thy Siſter.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>ALMANSOR.</speaker>
                     <p>Good God! what do you tell me?</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>LINDARACHE</speaker>
                     <l>That thy Siſter</l>
                     <l>Is ravished.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>ALMANSOR.</speaker>
                     <l>Name but the Ravisher,</l>
                     <l>And he is dead.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>LINDERACHE.</speaker>
                     <l>Come, now embrace me, Son, this ſaying makes me</l>
                     <l>Believe that Heaven hath given thee me for to</l>
                     <l>Revenge me.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <pb n="82" facs="tcp:50497:48"/>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>ALMANSOR.</speaker>
                     <l>Let me know his name, I ſwear</l>
                     <l>By th' holy <hi>Prophet,</hi> that his blood shal wash</l>
                     <l>The injury, and that this arm of mine</l>
                     <l>Shall ſacrifice him in ſtautly unto you.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>LINDARACHE</speaker>
                     <l>Thou shall know all, hearken, and let me ſpeak:</l>
                     <l>Thou art not ignorant of the enmity.</l>
                     <l>which raign'd for many ages twixt the houſes</l>
                     <l>O'th' <hi>Zegries,</hi> and of the <hi>Abencerages:</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>Now thou muſt know that on th' opinion</l>
                     <l>Conceived that a mariage would put end</l>
                     <l>To this contention, my daughter was</l>
                     <l>Deſign'd for wife to <hi>Zegry;</hi> every thing</l>
                     <l>Was ready, and the day appointed, when</l>
                     <l>Through an averſion, or rather through</l>
                     <l>Contempt, the trecherous <hi>Zegry</hi> flying our</l>
                     <l>Alliance, haſtily embark'ed himſelf</l>
                     <l>For <hi>Argser:</hi> and to add unto our griefs,</l>
                     <l>Aſſoon as this report was ſpread, my daughter</l>
                     <l>Was ſeen no more.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>ALMANSOR.</speaker>
                     <l>O Heaven! who should be cauſe</l>
                     <l>Of this misfortune?</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>LINDERACHE.</speaker>
                     <l>Read this letter heer,</l>
                     <l>It will inform thee fully</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <stage>Almanſor reads the Letter.</stage>
                     <floatingText type="letter" xml:lang="eng">
                        <body>
                           <head>LETTER.</head>
                           <l>YOu, from whom, I receiv'd my breath,</l>
                           <l>Know that a ſad fate worſe then death</l>
                           <l>Is hapened to me, all our name</l>
                           <l>In my loſſe bear an equall shame:</l>
                           <pb n="83" facs="tcp:50497:48"/>
                           <l>The falſe and cruel <hi>Zegry</hi> is</l>
                           <l>The Author of my miſeries;</l>
                           <l>For he it it that by his charms</l>
                           <l>Hath taken me out of your arms.</l>
                           <closer>
                              <signed>Zelinda.</signed>
                           </closer>
                        </body>
                     </floatingText>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>ALMANSOR</speaker>
                     <p>What have <hi>I</hi> heard!</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>LINDERACHE.</speaker>
                     <p>Abominable truths.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>ALMANLOR.</speaker>
                     <p>
                        <hi>Zegry</hi> her ravisher! oh fatall news!</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>LINDERACHE.</speaker>
                     <l>In this misfortune <hi>I</hi> had ſo much judgment</l>
                     <l>To hide this our dishonour, and her rape:</l>
                     <l>By the advice of the illuſtrious.</l>
                     <l>And wiſe <hi>Gomella, I</hi> ſpread every where</l>
                     <l>The rumour of her death, and ſent thee order</l>
                     <l>At the ſame time to depart from <hi>Tremiſſa</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>And to come heer: laſtly in <hi>Tunis</hi> ſtaying</l>
                     <l>Thy comming, I paſſed an unknown life</l>
                     <l>In tears and lamentation: and ſeeing</l>
                     <l>The time of thy return to be at hand,</l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>I</hi> came heer to this fatall reſidence:</l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>I</hi> find thee, and my grief is charm'd already,</l>
                     <l>To ſee my juſt rage in thy ſoule imprinted,</l>
                     <l>And thy brave arm diſpoſ'd to take revenge,</l>
                     <l>And to deprive that wretch of life, who hath</l>
                     <l>Deprived us of honour.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>ALMAOSOR.</speaker>
                     <l>Oh how many</l>
                     <l>Afflictions ſeiſe! my heart!</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>LINDARACHE.</speaker>
                     <l>Tis time to punish,</l>
                     <l>Not to deplore, in ſuch a fatall fortune</l>
                     <pb n="84" facs="tcp:50497:49"/>
                     <l>Expreſſe thy grief by bloody brave effects</l>
                     <l>Of rage and courage, vain regrets, and ſighs</l>
                     <l>Suit with my ſex, revenge belongs to thee.</l>
                     <l>Thou knoweſt the offender, go repair</l>
                     <l>Th offence: I would not have reſerv'd for thee</l>
                     <l>Th Imployment, if I could revenge my ſelf</l>
                     <l>Without thee; and I had already ſeen</l>
                     <l>The punishment of <hi>Zegry,</hi> If I would</l>
                     <l>Have uſ<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>d <hi>Gomellas</hi> ſervice; thy arm
only</l>
                     <l>Muſt wash the ſtam of from tby brow; take all</l>
                     <l>The reuenge to thee, as th' affront's all thine:</l>
                     <l>See me no more until thou haſt reveng'd</l>
                     <l>Thy Siſter, Goe, ſeek, find and punish fully</l>
                     <l>Her barbarous ravisher; adiew, perform</l>
                     <l>Thy duty, and make thy ſelf to appear</l>
                     <l>A worthy branch of that ill ſtrions ſtock</l>
                     <l>Of Heros, from whoſe loines thou art deſce<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ded;</l>
                     <l>To end our common miſeries and fears,</l>
                     <l>Go thou to shed blood, I goe to shed tears. — 
<stage>Exit Lindarache.</stage>
                     </l>
                  </sp>
               </div>
               <div n="2" type="scene">
                  <head>SCENE II.</head>
                  <stage>
                     <hi>ALMANSOR</hi> alone.</stage>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>ALMANSOR.</speaker>
                     <l>OH heard extremities! oh cruel violence!</l>
                     <l>Alas! the friend that doth oblige me, is</l>
                     <l>The enemy that wrongs me; I owe then</l>
                     <l>My ſafety unto him that robs me of</l>
                     <l>My honour, a<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d the man that ſav'd the brother</l>
                     <l>Hath ruined the Siſter! in this caſe</l>
                     <l>What counſell should I take? shall I become</l>
                     <l>Ingratefull, or be infamous, shal I</l>
                     <l>Break the bond of a holy amity?</l>
                     <l>Shal I let forth the blood which preſerv'd mine,</l>
                     <pb n="85" facs="tcp:50497:49"/>
                     <l>That blood in which love will that <hi>I</hi> have
In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tereſt?</l>
                     <l>And to ſay all, the blood of my fair Miſtreſſe?</l>
                     <l>She comes forth, and without doubt aymeth here</l>
                     <l>Honour will that I fly, but Love reſtrains me:</l>
                  </sp>
               </div>
               <div n="3" type="scene">
                  <head>SCENE III.</head>
                  <stage>ALMANSOR, ZAIDA, MEDINA.</stage>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>ZAIDA.</speaker>
                     <l>HE dares not to advance, his crime intimida<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tes him.</l>
                     <l>We will paſſe by the traitor, without ſpeaking</l>
                     <l>A word.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>ALMANSOR.</speaker>
                     <l>Deare object of all my affections,</l>
                     <l>Charme of my Spirits!</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>ZAIDA.</speaker>
                     <l>Surely, you are miſtaken.</l>
                     <l>You would ſpeak to ſome other.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>ALMANSOR.</speaker>
                     <l>Suffer me</l>
                     <l>T'expreſſe my paſſion unto your faire eyes,</l>
                     <l>Love, —</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>ZAIDA.</speaker>
                     <p>You take me without doubt for <hi>Fatima.</hi>
                     </p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>ALMANSOR.</speaker>
                     <l>How for <hi>Fatima;</hi> this wotd doth acquaint me</l>
                     <l>Confuſedly with the unjuſt ſuſpition</l>
                     <l>From whence this chang ſprings: poſſibly you have</l>
                     <l>Believed that I ſeck to pleaſe her, ſeeing</l>
                     <l>The league that it between me, and her Father;</l>
                     <l>But Heaven, and Love my conquerour, be witnes,</l>
                     <l>That your fair Image wholy doth poſſeſſe</l>
                     <l>My heart, that to remove you thence, <hi>Fatima</hi>
                     </l>
                     <pb n="86" facs="tcp:50497:50"/>
                     <l>Is altogether incapable, that I look on</l>
                     <l>Al that is lovely in her without love</l>
                     <l>And that as ſenſible only of the darts</l>
                     <l>Of your rare beauties, I confine my thoughts</l>
                     <l>And actions to civilities for her.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>ZAIDA.</speaker>
                     <l>How do you look upon <hi>Fatima</hi> then</l>
                     <l>With an indifference?— Let me ſee how far</l>
                     <l>His impudence will go — 
<stage>aſide.</stage>
                     </l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>ALMANSOR.</speaker>
                     <l>Can you doubt of it? you that have tied all</l>
                     <l>My ſenſes with ſuch ſweet and preſſing
bonds?</l>
                     <l>Can you ſuſpect with any juſtice, Madam</l>
                     <l>My heart of treachery, my oaths of fals hood,</l>
                     <l>And believe that my ſoul hath ſo much black<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes,</l>
                     <l>As to betray my Miſtreſſe, my friend,</l>
                     <l>And my Deliverer? could you imagine,</l>
                     <l>Without being deceiv<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>d, that having once</l>
                     <l>Beheld you, one could love elſewhere? oh no:</l>
                     <l>For me to be inflam'd with a new fire</l>
                     <l>You are too charming, and I'm too much charm'd.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>ZAIDA,</speaker>
                     <l>Too much charm'd, monſter of perfidiouſnes?</l>
                     <l>Wilt thou abuſe me then after thou haſt</l>
                     <l>Betray'd me, and with an unworthy love</l>
                     <l>Carried away, wilt thou join impudence</l>
                     <l>To infidelity?</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>ALMANSOR</speaker>
                     <l>To inſidelity,</l>
                     <l>What ſay you, <hi>Zaida?</hi> this diſcourſe confounds
me.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>ZAIDA.</speaker>
                     <l>I ſee it plainly, wretch; wer't thou leſſe
wic<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ked,</l>
                     <pb n="87" facs="tcp:50497:50"/>
                     <l>Thou would'ſt be leſſe confounded; an ingra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tefull</l>
                     <l>Still blusheth at reproaches.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>ALMANSOR.</speaker>
                     <p>An ingratefull?</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>ZAIDA.</speaker>
                     <l>Doth that word trouble thee? and feareſt thou</l>
                     <l>The name of an ingratefull perſon more</l>
                     <l>Then foul ingratitude it ſelf?</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>ALMANSOR.</speaker>
                     <l>I know not</l>
                     <l>The cauſe of this your anger, ſhould I never</l>
                     <l>So much examine me, <hi>I</hi> ſtill should find</l>
                     <l>My conſcience innocent.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>ZAIDA.</speaker>
                     <l>In thy accompt then</l>
                     <l>Tis nothing to deceive a maid, to wrong</l>
                     <l>Thy friend, to fail thy faith, to love <hi>Fatima,</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>Laſtly</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>ALMANSOR,</speaker>
                     <p>I, ſay you?</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>ZAIDA,</speaker>
                     <p>Yes, thee</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>ALMANSOR.</speaker>
                     <l>Oh! believe me,</l>
                     <l>I love her not.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>ZAIDA.</speaker>
                     <l>Dar'ſt thou to ſay it yet?</l>
                     <l>Doſt thou not love her when thou doſt adore her?</l>
                     <l>Thy falſe equivocations cannot heer</l>
                     <l>Abuſe me, I know that thou art to morrow</l>
                     <l>To marry her.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>ALMANSOR.</speaker>
                     <l>To matry her! o Heaven, believe it not,</l>
                     <l>I ſwear.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <pb n="88" facs="tcp:50497:51"/>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>ZAIDA,</speaker>
                     <l>No, no, forbeare, I believe not</l>
                     <l>The oaths of one that's perjur'd, every one,</l>
                     <l>Knows of this mariage,</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>ALMANSOR.</speaker>
                     <p>Who told it you?</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>ZAIDA.</speaker>
                     <p>A certaine perſon.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>ALMANSOR</speaker>
                     <l>Whoſoe'r it be,</l>
                     <l>That certain perſon ly'd. Tell me his name,</l>
                     <l>And my juſt anger preſently shall carry him</l>
                     <l>The reward of his falſe intelligence.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>ZAIDA.</speaker>
                     <l>Goe punish then Fatima, it was she</l>
                     <l>Her ſelf that told it me.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>ALMANSOR</speaker>
                     <l>Oh give leſſe credit,</l>
                     <l>Ador able Wonder, to ſuch falſe diſcourſes.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>ZAIDA.</speaker>
                     <p>Good God! who ever ſaw ſuch impudence?</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>ALMANSOR.</speaker>
                     <l>The mariage which she hath forged, is</l>
                     <l>A falſity; bear witneſſe thou dread Maſter</l>
                     <l>Of Heaven that this I ſpeak is truth; but if</l>
                     <l>I lie, let thy hand with a thunderbolt</l>
                     <l>Strike me unto the center of the earth:</l>
                     <l>Let my name be foreuer odious,</l>
                     <l>If the fire which <hi>I</hi> feel proceedeth not</l>
                     <l>wholy from your fair eyes, and if my heart</l>
                     <l>Ever conceived for <hi>Fatima</hi> any thing</l>
                     <l>Beyond a weak eſteem.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>ZAIDA.</speaker>
                     <l>I muſt ſift yet</l>
                     <l>This brazen face more throughly. — 
<stage>aſide.</stage>
                     </l>
                     <l>How wilt thou prove</l>
                     <pb n="89" facs="tcp:50497:51"/>
                     <l>The truth of thy aſſertion?</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>ALMANSOR,</speaker>
                     <l>I can produce.</l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>A</hi> hundred proofs to diſabuſe you
preſently.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>ZAIDA.</speaker>
                     <l>I'l have but one, and that too very eaſie;</l>
                     <l>To put an end to the ſuſpitions,</l>
                     <l>Which I ve co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ceiv'd of thee, give me forthwith</l>
                     <l>Both thy hand and thy faith.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>ALMANSOR.</speaker>
                     <l>I give it you</l>
                     <l>With an exceſſe of yoy. — but what would I,</l>
                     <l>Give her a hand that muſt deſtroy her brother,</l>
                     <l>And plung it ſelf in his moſt noble blood? — 
<stage>aſide</stage>
                     </l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>ZAIDA.</speaker>
                     <l>What doſt thou anſwer me ſo ill for ſuch</l>
                     <l>Rare bounties? doſt thou murmur to thy ſelfe,</l>
                     <l>Grow pale and ſtudy, as if thou reſent'ſt ill</l>
                     <l>What I propoſe.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>ALMANSOR.</speaker>
                     <l>Madam, clean contrary</l>
                     <l>I was rap'd with th'unexpected honour,</l>
                     <l>And happines wherewith I ſaw me filled,</l>
                     <l>And th'exceſſe of my joy tranſported me:</l>
                     <l>I feare through my obedience to betray you,</l>
                     <l>To make detraction to ſpeak againſt you,</l>
                     <l>And to treat <hi>Zegry</hi> too unciviliy</l>
                     <l>In giving without his conſent my hand</l>
                     <l>And faith; but this weak fear yeilds to my flame</l>
                     <l>Duty prevails not now upon my ſoul,</l>
                     <l>And cannot take from me the glorious pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe</l>
                     <l>Of giving you my heart and hand together.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <pb n="90" facs="tcp:50497:52"/>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>ZAIDA.</speaker>
                     <l>Thou thinkeſt on't too late, my mind is chang'd,</l>
                     <l>And n'er shall cha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ge again, know that I feign'd,</l>
                     <l>Only to try thee, that exceſſe of goodnes,</l>
                     <l>And thy fires for <hi>Fatima</hi> preſently</l>
                     <l>Burſt forth.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>ALMANSOR.</speaker>
                     <p>Oh! I had never any for her!</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>ZAIDA.</speaker>
                     <l>Thy deceit 's plain enough, <hi>I</hi>'m very well</l>
                     <l>Aſſured of this fatall matiage:</l>
                     <l>When I preſs'd thee to paſſe thy faith unto me,</l>
                     <l>I faw that thy remorſes for <hi>Fatima</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>Accuſed thee, and thy confuſion</l>
                     <l>Confirmed me in my belieft that she</l>
                     <l>Receiv'd the faith which I demanded of thee.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>ALMANSOR.</speaker>
                     <p>I offer it unto you.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>ZAIDA.</speaker>
                     <l>No thou cauſt not</l>
                     <l>Diſpoſe of it. Thou haſt already given it,</l>
                     <l>And wilt abuſe me.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>ALMANSOR.</speaker>
                     <l>You abuſe your ſelf</l>
                     <l>Wiih too much warines.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>ZAIDA.</speaker>
                     <l>Haſt thou the boldnes</l>
                     <l>To reply yet? Go, go to thy <hi>Fatima,</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>To morrow is your mariage day, I know it.</l>
                     <l>She hath affections for thee, ſince thou haſt</l>
                     <l>Refuſed me.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>ALMANSOR.</speaker>
                     <p>Hear me, <hi>I</hi> do beſeech you.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>ZAIDA,</speaker>
                     <l>No, no? that were too great a weaknes in me:</l>
                     <pb n="91" facs="tcp:50497:52"/>
                     <l>Know that I leave thee, n'er too ſee thee more.</l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>A</hi> ſecret poiſon's hid in the diſcourſe</l>
                     <l>Of an Ingratefull perſon, and each word</l>
                     <l>Atraitor ſpeaks, deſtroys worſe then the ſword.</l>
                     <stage>Exit Zaida.</stage>
                  </sp>
               </div>
               <div n="4" type="scene">
                  <head>SCENE IV.</head>
                  <stage>ALMANSOR, alone.</stage>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>ALMANSOR.</speaker>
                     <l>STrange ſucceſſe, this! How is my ſoul
poſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeſs'd</l>
                     <l>Still with new troubles? muſt I ſuffer then</l>
                     <l>The punishment of a fault which I have not</l>
                     <l>Committed? when revenge doth preſſe me to</l>
                     <l>Deſtroy a friend, muſt I at the ſame time</l>
                     <l>Deſtroy a Miſtreſſe too? muſt I loſe
<hi>Zaida?</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>Yes my heart, I muſt looſe her preſently,</l>
                     <l>Since in depriving her of a dear brother,</l>
                     <l>My arm will draw her hate and anger on me:</l>
                     <l>I should hence forth no longer be ſo ſoft,</l>
                     <l>Tis time to think of <hi>Zegrys</hi> death, he muſt</l>
                     <l>Pay his blood to repair the honout which</l>
                     <l>He robs me of. This Enemy ſo dear</l>
                     <l>Muſt die, and I muſt ſacrifice him to me;</l>
                     <l>He comes: at his approach ſome te<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>der motions</l>
                     <l>Oppoſe my juſt reſentments, and indeed</l>
                     <l>Render them weak, my friendship combateth</l>
                     <l>The anger that poſſeſſeth me, my tendernes</l>
                     <l>Is leſſe weak, and my fury is leſſe ſtrong.</l>
                     <l>He ſav'd my life, he ravished my Siſter;</l>
                     <l>Shall I go to embrace him, or to kill him?</l>
                  </sp>
               </div>
               <div n="5" type="scene">
                  <pb n="92" facs="tcp:50497:53"/>
                  <head>SCENE V.</head>
                  <stage>ZEGRY, ORMIN, ALMANSOR.</stage>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>ZEGRY.</speaker>
                     <l>AT laſt <hi>I</hi>'ve met with him that wro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>geth me.</l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Ormin</hi> leave us alone.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>ORMIN.</speaker>
                     <l>I will retire me.</l>
                     <l>Into this thicket ſecretly to ſee</l>
                     <l>What paſſeth, I doubt there will be a quarrel: — 
<stage>aſide.</stage>
                     </l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>ALMANSOR.</speaker>
                     <p>You appear troubled.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>ZEGRY.</speaker>
                     <p>
                        <hi>I</hi>'ve much cauſe to be ſo.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>ALMANSOR.</speaker>
                     <p>What troubles you ſo much?</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>ZEGRY.</speaker>
                     <l>A wretch, a Traytor,</l>
                     <l>Whoſe crime gives me an infinite regret,</l>
                     <l>And doth deſerve more then a ſingle death</l>
                     <l>To punish it.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>ALMANSOR.</speaker>
                     <p>May I ſerve you herem?</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>ZEGRY.</speaker>
                     <p>Yes, I can't finish my revenge without thee.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>ALMANSOR.</speaker>
                     <p>
                        <hi>Zegry,</hi> you can diſpoſe of all my blood.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>ZEGRY.</speaker>
                     <p>It is an offer which I can<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>t refuſe.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>ALMANSOR.</speaker>
                     <p>Who is th' affronter?</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>ZEGRY.</speaker>
                     <l>Thou art extream bold:</l>
                     <pb n="93" facs="tcp:50497:53"/>
                     <l>Know'ſt thou not, traitor, that it is thy ſelf?</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>ALMANSOR.</speaker>
                     <p>I?</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>ZEGRY,</speaker>
                     <l>Thou; n'er ſeem to wonder at the thing.</l>
                     <l>Only defend thy felf.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <stage>ALMANSOR <hi>embracing him.</hi>
                  </stage>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>ALMANSOR.</speaker>
                     <l>How much am I.</l>
                     <l>Indebted to thee for this ſudden paſſion,</l>
                     <l>Tis now the chief point of thy amity:</l>
                     <l>Thy anger doth oblige me, though it wro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>gs me.</l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>I</hi> had already in my heart reſolu<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>d</l>
                     <l>The deſign of thy death, and juſtly too:</l>
                     <l>My arm was ready for it, when inſpight</l>
                     <l>Of all my fury, at thy firſt approach</l>
                     <l>My heart grew tender, and had been reduc'd</l>
                     <l>To balance the fierce darts which I had level'd</l>
                     <l>Againſt thee, if thy furious tranſport</l>
                     <l>Had not call'd home my choler unto me,</l>
                     <l>And banished my tendernes.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>ZEGRY.</speaker>
                     <l>
                        <hi>I</hi>'l hear</l>
                     <l>No more diſcourſe, once again guard thy felf</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>ALMANSOR.</speaker>
                     <l>So fierce a fight can't but be ſweet unto me</l>
                     <l>Honour ſolicits me more juſtly to it</l>
                     <l>Then thee, but let me know at leaſt the cauſe</l>
                     <l>That doth provoke thee; I will make it plainly</l>
                     <l>appear that thou complaineſt wrongfully,</l>
                     <l>And juſtify my ſelf in Killing thee.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <pb n="94" facs="tcp:50497:54"/>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>ZEGRY.</speaker>
                     <l>How! feignſt thou to be ignorant, and inſtead</l>
                     <l>Of making a confeſſion, doſt thou threaten me?</l>
                     <l>Thy baſe crime groweth greater by thy bold<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>ALMANSOR.</speaker>
                     <p>Let me at Iaſt know what that baſe crime is.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>ZEGRY.</speaker>
                     <l>Conſult thy conſcience, and thou shalt know it,</l>
                     <l>It will inſtruct thee that with a falſe heart</l>
                     <l>In recompenſe of all my kindnes to thee</l>
                     <l>Thou rob ſt me of my Miſtreſſe, and that</l>
                     <l>Through treacheries which cannot be excus'd,</l>
                     <l>Thou art to marry her to morrow privately.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>ALMANSOR.</speaker>
                     <l>If I am criminall, aſſure thy ſelf,</l>
                     <l>It is not in this point: I never did</l>
                     <l>Look on <hi>Fatima</hi> with deſires of love;</l>
                     <l>Only thou mayſt reproach my heart for ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving</l>
                     <l>Sight for thy Siſter without thy conſent.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>ZEGRY.</speaker>
                     <p>How! doſt thou love her?</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>ALMANSOR.</speaker>
                     <l>No, no, it would be</l>
                     <l>An extream errour, I ſay, I adore her,</l>
                     <l>I dare not ſay I love her. That which I</l>
                     <l>Reſent now for her beauties doth ſurpaſſe</l>
                     <l>The thing that's called Love.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>ZEGRY.</speaker>
                     <l>By this confeſſion,</l>
                     <l>Dear friend, thou haſt reſtored life unto me.</l>
                     <l>My griefs and troubles now are waited on</l>
                     <pb n="95" facs="tcp:50497:54"/>
                     <l>By an exceſſe of pleaſure; <hi>Zaida</hi> is</l>
                     <l>Too happy, and her thoughts could never hope</l>
                     <l>A more illuſtrious husband: she is free.</l>
                     <l>The Lover unto whom I gave my word,</l>
                     <l>Hath ſeen his deſtiny determined</l>
                     <l>By death, and my repoſe shall fully be</l>
                     <l>Setled to meet a brother in the perſon</l>
                     <l>Of my moſt deare friend.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>ALMANSOR.</speaker>
                     <l>What thou offereſt me</l>
                     <l>Should be moſt dear unto me; but doſt thou</l>
                     <l>Know him whom thou mak<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>ſt choice of for thy brother?</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>ZEGRY.</speaker>
                     <l>
                        <hi>I</hi> think, I doe; thy country is
<hi>Tremiſsa,</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>Thy name, <hi>Almanſor,</hi> and thy family</l>
                     <l>Is noble and illuſtrious; and if I</l>
                     <l>May believe thee, thy greateſt glory is</l>
                     <l>To be my friend.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>ALMANSOR.</speaker>
                     <l>Thou know ſt me but by half yet;</l>
                     <l>I was born heer, and born thy enemy,</l>
                     <l>More then one juſt and honeſt motive doth</l>
                     <l>Engage me to thy ruine; not to hold thee</l>
                     <l>Long in ſuſpence, I am <hi>Abencerage.</hi>
                     </l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>ZEGRY.</speaker>
                     <p>
                        <hi>Abencerage.</hi>
                     </p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>ORMIN.</speaker>
                     <p>O Heaven! — 
<stage>aſide.</stage>
                     </p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>ALMANSOR.</speaker>
                     <l>That wotd doth tell thee.</l>
                     <l>Our difference, and my duty.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>ZEGRY.</speaker>
                     <l>I aſwell</l>
                     <pb n="96" facs="tcp:50497:55"/>
                     <l>Know as thy ſelf the mutuall hatred which</l>
                     <l>In our two houſes ſeemes almoſt as twere</l>
                     <l>To be immortall; but thy blood which now</l>
                     <l>Thou oweſt to my ſuccour, should for me</l>
                     <l>Stop the courſe of it in thy ſoul; and though</l>
                     <l>My friendſhip ſeems to ſtagger on this point,</l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>I</hi> will content my ſelf to hate thy name,</l>
                     <l>And love thy perſon. Yes, purſue thy love</l>
                     <l>Vnto my Siſter; by a mariage</l>
                     <l>We may be tied with new knots, and by</l>
                     <l>That holy flame, the irreligious heat</l>
                     <l>Of that ſo old, and fatal enmity,</l>
                     <l>Will be extinct.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>ALMANSOR.</speaker>
                     <l>This mariage would be ſweet,</l>
                     <l>But I can't think of it till by thy death</l>
                     <l>I have reveng'd my ſelfe upon thee.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>ZEGRY.</speaker>
                     <p>How!</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>ALMANLOR.</speaker>
                     <l>It is not that which thou believ'ſt provoke me,</l>
                     <l>Thy name I hate not, but I hate thy perſon,</l>
                     <l>And <hi>I</hi> cannot but in thy blood repair</l>
                     <l>The wrong which
<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>hou haſt done me.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>ZEGRY.</speaker>
                     <p>
                        <hi>I?</hi>
                     </p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>ALMANSOR.</speaker>
                     <l>Yes, Thou.</l>
                     <l>How ill thou acteſt the aſtonished,</l>
                     <l>Thy baſe crime groweth greater by thy boldnes.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>ZEGRY.</speaker>
                     <p>Let me at laſt know what that baſe crime is.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>ALMANSOR.</speaker>
                     <p>Conſult this letter, read, and thou sha<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap> know it.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <pb n="97" facs="tcp:50497:55"/>
                  <sp>
                     <stage>ZEGRY reads.</stage>
                     <floatingText type="letter" xml:lang="eng">
                        <body>
                           <l>YOu, from whom I derive my birth,</l>
                           <l>Know that a ſad fate worſe then death</l>
                           <l>Is hapned to me; all our name</l>
                           <l>In my loſſe bear an equall shame;</l>
                           <l>The falſe and cruel Zegry is</l>
                           <l>The Authour of my miſeries,</l>
                           <l>For he it is that by his charms</l>
                           <l>Hath taken me out of your arms.</l>
                           <closer>
                              <signed>Zelinda.</signed>
                           </closer>
                        </body>
                     </floatingText>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>ORMIN.</speaker>
                     <p>Without doubt they will both miſtake them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>ZEGRY.</speaker>
                     <p>I cannot comprehend this dark Aenigma.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>ALMANSOR.</speaker>
                     <l>It is too plain to me here that my ſiſter</l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Zelinda</hi> giveth us to underſtand</l>
                     <l>That thou art her baſe ravisher.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>ZEGRY.</speaker>
                     <l>Canſt thou</l>
                     <l>Suſpect me of ſo foule an action?</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>ALMANSOR.</speaker>
                     <p>Canſt thou deny it, traitor? and can I Believe it?</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>ZEGRY.</speaker>
                     <p>Hear me but a word or two.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>ALMANSOR.</speaker>
                     <l>It would be to no purpoſe, guard thy ſelf,</l>
                     <l>I'l hear no more.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>ZEGRY.</speaker>
                     <l>How! dares the man that ows me</l>
                     <l>His life, to aſſault mine?</l>
                  </sp>
                  <pb n="98" facs="tcp:50497:56"/>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>ALMANSOR.</speaker>
                     <l>That obligation</l>
                     <l>Cannot divert me from my juſt reveng:</l>
                     <l>Thou wronght'ſt my ſafety, and my ſiſters rape,</l>
                     <l>And ſo much as life is leſſe dear then honour,</l>
                     <l>So much an affront which reflects upon it,</l>
                     <l>Carries it in my ſoul upon a benefit,</l>
                     <l>And I am leſſe afraid to be ingratefull,</l>
                     <l>Then to be infamous; but let us leave</l>
                     <l>Diſcourſe, and come to action.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>ZEGRY.</speaker>
                     <l>Stay, Ingratefull,</l>
                     <l>Stay yet a little.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>ORMIN.</speaker>
                     <p>Help, Oh help;</p>
                  </sp>
               </div>
               <div n="6" type="scene">
                  <head>SCENE VI.</head>
                  <stage>And the laſt. ADIBAR, ZAIDA, MEDINA, ALABEZ, LINDARACHE,
GOMELLA, FATIMA, CHARIFA, ALMANSOR, ZEGRY, ORMIN, GASUL.</stage>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>ZAIDA.</speaker>
                     <l>WHat noife</l>
                     <l>Is this I heare?</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>LINDARACHE.</speaker>
                     <p>what rumour is raiſ'd up?</p>
                  </sp>
                  <pb n="99" facs="tcp:50497:56"/>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>ADIBER.</speaker>
                     <p>Hold, hold!</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>LINDARACHE.</speaker>
                     <l>No, no, go on,</l>
                     <l>My ſon, finish thy work.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>GOMELLA.</speaker>
                     <l>Their quarrel, <hi>Adibar,</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>Cannot be taken up, therefore let's leave it</l>
                     <l>To be decided.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>ADIBER.</speaker>
                     <l>No, ſuch a third perſon</l>
                     <l>As I, shall never ſuffer them to fight,</l>
                     <l>And to look on.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>GOMELLA.</speaker>
                     <l>Well then, defend your ſelfe.</l>
                     <l>We't fight all four.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <stage>
                     <hi>Ormin</hi> to <hi>Almanſor.</hi>
                  </stage>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>ORMIN.</speaker>
                     <l>Oh! brother rather lift</l>
                     <l>Your arm up againſt me, I'in guilty only,</l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Zegry</hi> is innocent,</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>LINDARACHE.</speaker>
                     <p>Whom do I ſee?</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>ORMIN.</speaker>
                     <l>you ſee <hi>Zelinda</hi> your unfortunate Daughter,</l>
                     <l>Who left your family to follow <hi>Zegry;</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>And who in changing fate and habit only,</l>
                     <l>Could not enforce her ſoul to the leaſt change:</l>
                     <l>My heart which was pleaſed in ſlavery</l>
                     <l>By him, forgat it ſelf in following.</l>
                     <l>Somwhat too conſtantly this fleeting Lover;</l>
                     <l>But having known him to be taken with</l>
                     <l>Another Object. I feard in diſcovering</l>
                     <pb n="100" facs="tcp:50497:57"/>
                     <l>My ſelf, to draw upon me his contempt,</l>
                     <l>And would ſtill ſuffer the ſame violence,</l>
                     <l>If his own intereſt brake not my ſilence.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>LINDERACHE.</speaker>
                     <p>Oh, Daughter!</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>ALMANSOR.</speaker>
                     <p>Oh! my Siſter!</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>ZEGRY.</speaker>
                     <l>Fair <hi>Zelinda,</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>Revenge your ſelf, I mourn you, I accuſe</l>
                     <l>My ſelf, and yeild my boſome to your ſtroak.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>ORMIN.</speaker>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Zegry,</hi> You need not to fear any thing</l>
                     <l>From my reſentments, if you pitty me,</l>
                     <l>I am not to be pittied</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>ZEGRY.</speaker>
                     <l>I blush</l>
                     <l>That after ſo much goodnes as you have</l>
                     <l>Expreſſed to me, I have but one ſoul</l>
                     <l>Too give you; and if the conſent of your</l>
                     <l>Parents and friends will be propitious to us,</l>
                     <l>There's nothing can impede our mariage.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>LINDARACHE</speaker>
                     <p>This mariage is the chief of all my wishes.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>ALMANSOR.</speaker>
                     <l>Friend, thou canſt make me happy too, thy Siſter</l>
                     <l>Dependeth on thee, thou know'ſt, I adore her.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>ZEGRY.</speaker>
                     <l>I offered her unto thee, a while ſince,</l>
                     <l>And now I do again with height of joy.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>ZAIDA.</speaker>
                     <l>All my ſuſpitions are extinguished,</l>
                     <l>And you muſt know that following my duty,</l>
                     <l>I follow my deſires; but <hi>Adibar</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>Will complain of it.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <pb n="101" facs="tcp:50497:57" rendition="simple:additions"/>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>ADIBAR.</speaker>
                     <l>Madam, y'are deceiv<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>d,</l>
                     <l>When I loſe all hope, I loſe all my flame:</l>
                     <l>And to expreſſe unto you that I do not</l>
                     <l>Reſent it, I will ſacrifice my heart</l>
                     <l>In flames of loue to that fair Saint, for whom</l>
                     <l>I burned formerly; <hi>Gomella.</hi> may I</l>
                     <l>Hope your incomparable Daughter?</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>GOMELLA.</speaker>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Adibar,</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>My family is honoured by your choice.</l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Fatima,</hi> take your husband from my hand.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>FATIMA.</speaker>
                     <l>Such pleaſing orders I shall willingly</l>
                     <l>Obey.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>ZEGRY.</speaker>
                     <l>Come, let us go unto the <hi>Moſquè</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>Together, to give thanks unto the goodnes</l>
                     <l>Of Heaven that ſet an end to our misfortunes,</l>
                     <l>And made appear by this happy ſucceſſe,</l>
                     <l>That one may be ingrate, yet generous.</l>
                  </sp>
               </div>
            </div>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
         <div type="epilogue">
            <pb facs="tcp:50497:58"/>
            <head>EPILOGUE</head>
            <l>THe Prologue promiſ'd ſomething for the Play</l>
            <l>Vnder a penalty, I come to pay</l>
            <l>What he engag'd for, not to beg applauſe,</l>
            <l>But, if we have transgreſs'd the Comick laws,</l>
            <l>To ſuffer punishment; Beauties, to you</l>
            <l>Firſt <hi>I</hi> addreſſe me for the Poets due;</l>
            <l>He ſeeks but juſtice from your <hi>I</hi>vorie hands,</l>
            <l>As you like or diſlike he falls or ſtands:</l>
            <l>Smile on the peice, and no man dares to frown,</l>
            <l>Your vote ſwayes both the Cavaleer and Clown:</l>
            <l>Yours are the leading voices, in your looks</l>
            <l>We read our fortune better then in books;</l>
            <l>Y<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> are pleaſ'd, for Heaven's diſplaid in ſmiles, ſo
thi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>
               <g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
            </l>
            <l>I need ſay nothing to you,, Gentlemen.</l>
         </div>
      </body>
      <back>
         <div type="errata">
            <pb facs="tcp:50497:58"/>
            <head>ERRA<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>A.</head>
            <p>Page the 8. laſt Line, for <hi>comet,</hi> re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ad <hi>comes.</hi>
Page the 13. Line the 2. for <hi>follow,</hi> read <hi>fellow.</hi> Page the 21
Line the 7. for <hi>unworthly.</hi> read <hi>unworthyly.</hi> Page the 24.
Li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ne the 11th, for <hi>querched,</hi> read <hi>quenched.</hi> Page the 29.
Line the 8. for <hi>trough</hi> read <hi>through.</hi> Page the 39. Line the
16. for <hi>wit</hi> read <hi>with.</hi> Page the 74 Line the 6. for
<hi>she,</hi> read <hi>the.</hi>
            </p>
            <pb facs="tcp:50497:59"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:50497:59"/>
         </div>
      </back>
   </text>
</TEI>
