<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>The honest lavvyer Acted by the Queenes Maiesties Seruants. Written by S.S.</title>
            <author>S. S., fl. 1616.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1616</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 176 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 39 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-12">2011-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A68683</idno>
            <idno type="STC">STC 21519</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC S116335</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99851552</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99851552</idno>
            <idno type="VID">16830</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A68683)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 16830)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 1392:25, 1735:7)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>The honest lavvyer Acted by the Queenes Maiesties Seruants. Written by S.S.</title>
                  <author>S. S., fl. 1616.</author>
                  <author>Sheppard, S. (Samuel), attributed name.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[78] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed by George Purslowe for Richard Woodroffe, and are to be sold at his shop neere the great north-dore of Paules, at the signe of the guilded Key,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1616.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Doubtfully attributed to Samuel Sheppard.</note>
                  <note>Partly in verse.</note>
                  <note>Signatures: A-K⁴ (-A1).</note>
                  <note>The last leaf is blank.</note>
                  <note>A later variant of the edition with imprint reading: for Richard Woodruffe, and are to be sold at the great north-dore ..</note>
                  <note>Identified as STC 21519a on UMI microfilm reel 1735.</note>
                  <note>Reproductions of the originals in the Henry E. Huntington Library and Art Gallery and the British Library.</note>
                  <note>Appears at reel 1392 (Henry E. Huntington Library and Art Gallery copy) and at reel 1735 (British Library copy).</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2011-03</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-04</date>
            <label>Apex CoVantage</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-05</date>
            <label>Susie Lorand</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-05</date>
            <label>Susie Lorand</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-06</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <p>
               <pb facs="tcp:16830:1"/>
               <pb facs="tcp:16830:1"/>
THE HONEST Lavvyer.</p>
            <p>ACTED BY The QVEENES Maieſties SERVANTS.</p>
            <p>WRITTEN <hi>By</hi> S. S.</p>
            <q>
               <l>
                  <hi>—leuis eſſe videtur</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Fabula, quae poſci vult, &amp; ſpectata reponi.</hi>
               </l>
            </q>
            <p>LONDON, Printed by <hi>George Purſlowe</hi> for <hi>Richard Woodroffe,</hi> and are to be ſold at his Shop neere the great North-dore of Paules, at the ſigne of the guilded Key. 1616.</p>
            <pb facs="tcp:16830:2" rendition="simple:additions"/>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="play">
            <pb facs="tcp:16830:2"/>
            <head>THE HONEST <hi>LAWYER.</hi>
            </head>
            <div n="1" type="act">
               <head>Act. Prim.</head>
               <stage>
                  <hi>Enter</hi> Vaſter <hi>weapon'd.</hi>
               </stage>
               <l>A Cuckold? why now it is a common name,</l>
               <l>As the ſhee-Goſsip<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> are that giue it vs.</l>
               <l>Why doth it not deriue, and ſpread it ſelfe.</l>
               <l>To all the generations we produce?</l>
               <l>Why ſhould not euery child of mine be call'd</l>
               <l>Cuckold, as well as <hi>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>aster,</hi> Woman, woman</l>
               <l>Thou ſad vndoer of the faireſt building,</l>
               <l>That euer earth bragg'd to be pauement to.</l>
               <l>Man, Man; the pride of heauens creation,</l>
               <l>Abſtract of Nature, that in his ſmall volume</l>
               <l>Containes the whole worlds Text, and heauens impreſsion:</l>
               <l>His Makers Image, Angels mate, Earths great wonder,</l>
               <l>Made to guide all, by woman is brought vnder.</l>
               <l>That harmonie, faire Nature made to ſtand,</l>
               <l>Is forced out of tune by womans hand.</l>
               <l>A woman hath deform'd me. See, I looke</l>
               <l>Like any beaſt has hornes: an Aſſe may boaſt</l>
               <l>Himſelfe a horne-leſſe Gentleman before me.</l>
               <l>Yet let not clouds of paſsion choke my reaſon.</l>
               <l>Why? what's a Cuckold? let's ſee: define him:</l>
               <p>It is a man, whoſe wife playes the whore. Zilid, what's that to him? It is all one, as if a proper Gentleman ſhould ride on a hal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting Iade; or a good Muſician play on a broken fiddle. Oh but t'will be ſayd: Woman could not be ſo light a ſhippe, if her huſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>band could well ballaſt her. It is his inſufficiencie. A poxe it is.
<pb facs="tcp:16830:3"/>
Had ſhe <hi>Hercules</hi> to her husband, ſhee would enter the liſtes with ſome crinkle-hamm'd tilting Courtier. Well then,</p>
               <l>I ſee no reaſon, that a womans euill,</l>
               <l>Should thus transforme man to a horned deuill,</l>
               <l>No: 'twas <hi>Acteons</hi> luſts, and not his wife,</l>
               <l>That ſo beſtagg'd him. Hence ſprouts al my ſhame.</l>
               <l>Fuller of truth then age, thi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> rule hath beene:</l>
               <l>" Nothing deformes a man, but his owne ſinne.</l>
               <stage>Enter Robert Vaſter.</stage>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Rob.</speaker>
                  <p>Sir, my mother prayes—</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>aſt.</speaker>
                  <l>No more of her. Her prayers.</l>
                  <l>Are putrid ſacrifices: like foule ayres,</l>
                  <l>Too thicke to mount vp to yon glorious feeling.</l>
                  <l>" When blacke hands are rear'd vp, heauen has no feeling.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Rob.</speaker>
                  <p>She is your wife, my mother, Sir.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Vaſt.</speaker>
                  <p>What then Sir?</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Rob.</speaker>
                  <p>Nothing, but that you wrong her, ô my conſcience.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>aſt.</speaker>
                  <p>Oh tis a braue Puritan-world, when boyes talke of con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcience! Conſcience muſt lye at the ſtake, when they play but at blow-point. Sirrah, as you loue your Conſcience, hate a wife. Zlid, if I thought thou wouldſt marry, I would vnbleſſe thee, as I haue diſinherited thee already: Get baſtards, as I would ha' got thee. A woman may ſerue to lye withal: none good enough to marry.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Rob.</speaker>
                  <l>Oh were you not my father, I would let</l>
                  <l>This paſsion out of your impoſtum'd heart—</l>
                  <l>Why ſhould not I forget, that your bloud moues</l>
                  <l>In any veines of mine; when you forgoe</l>
                  <l>The reaſon of a father, husband, man?</l>
                  <l>And ſticke degeneration on your name?</l>
                  <l>If I ſayle ill, know your example ſteer'd</l>
                  <l>My voyage and my veſſell. Fathers are more</l>
                  <l>Then priuate men: their liues are the ſet copies.</l>
                  <l>Their children write by; and ſhould there giue</l>
                  <l>Their imitation patternes how to liue.</l>
                  <l>Hell's a ſad place, they ſay:—Oh, Ile dare neuer</l>
                  <l>To follow my owne father leading thither.</l>
                  <stage>Exit Rob.</stage>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Vaſt.</speaker>
                  <l>Sirra, call your mother. This boy's a Puritan.</l>
                  <l>
                     <pb facs="tcp:16830:3"/>
I that had nere lou'd my ſelfe to be thought good,</l>
                  <l>Am highly pleaſd to ſee it in my blood.</l>
                  <l>From whom deriues this ſprigge ſuch fruitfull iuyce;</l>
                  <l>The father being bad, the mother worſe.</l>
                  <l>Sure, he did ſucke this goodneſſe from his Nurſe.</l>
                  <l>Poore boy, my riot has vndone thee: poore</l>
                  <l>Thou'rt made by me, I by a wife turnd whore.</l>
                  <l>My ſtate is morgag'd to the vſurous hand</l>
                  <l>Of <hi>Gripe:</hi> my goods are waſted: all my hopes life</l>
                  <l>Breathes thus: hauing ſold all, Ile ſell my wife.</l>
                  <stage>Enter Vaſters wife and Robin.</stage>
                  <p>Y' are welcome, Looſeneſſe.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Rob.</speaker>
                  <l>Looſeneſſe Sir? Oh hell!</l>
                  <l>She is my mother; pray you, vſe her well.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ast.</speaker>
                  <p>Be gone.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Rob.</speaker>
                  <p>I cannot Sir.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Wife.</speaker>
                  <l>Good ſonne, a way.</l>
                  <l>A father giues command.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Rob.</speaker>
                  <p>I muſt obay.</p>
                  <stage>Exit. Rob.</stage>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ast.</speaker>
                  <p>Make much of you? I will, I will. Neuer man made more of his wife, when he ſold her to her ſmocke. Ile ſell thy fleſh too Gypſey.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Wife.</speaker>
                  <l>Deare husband, I am yet cleare; Oh do not you</l>
                  <l>Force me to ſinne, Ile be for ouer true.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>aſt.</speaker>
                  <l>True? true to the brothell, to the ſpittle, to the graue.</l>
                  <l>Thou art deaths agent: a whore is one of his Beadles.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Wife.</speaker>
                  <p>Heauen pardon your blacke ſlanders.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ast.</speaker>
                  <p>Come, I'm poore.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Wife.</speaker>
                  <p>Who made you?</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Vaſt.</speaker>
                  <p>Thou, my content, turn'd whore.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Wife.</speaker>
                  <p>Ile worke, or beg for you.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Vast.</speaker>
                  <l>No, thou haſt wrought</l>
                  <l>Too much already. Here, here's thy worke.</l>
                  <stage>points to her.</stage>
                  <l>Wilt thou doe one thing?</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Wife.</speaker>
                  <p>Any thing.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>aſt.</speaker>
                  <l>Then ſweare.</l>
                  <l>And keepe thy oath. Ile trauell to the warres,</l>
                  <l>And turne thee vp, as ſome Captaines wont; and trie,</l>
                  <l>If thou canſt liue by thy old trade, or die.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Wife.</speaker>
                  <p>Will you forſake me then?</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Vaſt.</speaker>
                  <l>Yes, and am iuſt.</l>
                  <l>Since thou forſook'ſt me, and thine innocence,</l>
                  <l>
                     <pb facs="tcp:16830:4"/>
Be thy reward proportion'd I muſt hence.</l>
                  <l>Whiles thou waſt good, to thee I had free deſire.</l>
                  <l>Now thou art prou'd a whore receaue thy hire.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Wife.</speaker>
                  <l>Take place, thou tyrant will. Thicke woes here houer.</l>
                  <l>My ſtate is lower then fate can recouer.</l>
                  <l>My obedience waits your pleaſure.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>aſt.</speaker>
                  <l>Hoh, within there.</l>
                  <stage>Enter Miſtreſſe Marre-maide, Bawde.</stage>
                  <l>Aunt <hi>Marre-maid</hi> I haue brought you the girle</l>
                  <l>I promiſd. Is the mony ready?</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Marm.</speaker>
                  <p>By that little honeſty I haue to ſweare by; a handſome wench. I muſt pay fiftie pound for her: but if ſhee were as yong, as faire, I would get fiue hundred pound by her within this moneth.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>aſt.</speaker>
                  <p>Aunt, pray' vſe her well: ſhe's my owne ſiſter.</p>
                  <p>Be petula<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t you whore, ſprightly frollick—as a Dutch Tanikin.—or—This woman is a Bawd, a very Bawd; you like her the better for that. Come, skippe about, quicke ſiluer: Dance like a Curteſan, or Ile fiddle ye. You ha' more trickes in priuate, then a Fencer can teach a Lord, or the diuell a Fencer. Life, doe you pule? I muſt haue fiftie pound for you: Doe y' heare? Let your heeles caper, and your tongue grow wanton, or by theſe horns Ile gore you—Aunt, ſhee's ſomewhat ſicke of that rare diſeaſe, cald Modeſty. But in priuate ſhe's more inſatiate then a Puritan.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Marm.</speaker>
                  <p>How old are you, faire ſiſter?</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Vaſt.</speaker>
                  <p>Not ſixteene.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Wife.</speaker>
                  <p>About ſome ſixe and fortie.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>aſt.</speaker>
                  <p>Oh you Witch—Aunt, ſhe lies eight and twentie, at leaſt </p>
                  <l>Harke ye ſiſter,—</l>
                  <l>Pleaſe this old Hagge, make her beleeue y' are right,</l>
                  <l>And anſwerable to her Stygian ſpels:</l>
                  <l>Or I will beare thee to an Armie, and there</l>
                  <l>Ha'thy ſod fleſh ſold, lent; and preſtituted,</l>
                  <l>And my ſelfe Cuckolded fortie times a day.</l>
                  <l>Leaue this forc'd ſo berneſſe—Aunt, will you heare her ſpeake?</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Wife.</speaker>
                  <l>I can skippe lighter then the wanton Doe,</l>
                  <l>And ierke it through the Dale,</l>
                  <l>I cannot hold, neither my tongue, nor heeles,</l>
                  <l>(Nor nailes from ſcratching out a Leachers eyes)</l>
                  <l>
                     <pb facs="tcp:16830:4"/>
Sure, I am compoſd moſt of the nimbler elements:</l>
                  <l>But little water in me, farre leſſe earth, ſome aire,</l>
                  <l>To keepe me humid, mutable, and tender,</l>
                  <l>And apt for conuolution: but their mixture</l>
                  <l>Is ſcarce diſcernible, th' are ſo diſpers'd.</l>
                  <l>For my predominant qualitie is all fire,</l>
                  <l>Pure, radiant, ſubtle fire.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Vaſt.</speaker>
                  <l>I haue oft ſeene a couple of light heeles</l>
                  <l>Carry a ſober head: a womans tongue</l>
                  <l>Reade lectures of ciuilitie; her face</l>
                  <l>A printed booke, each dimple a ſweet line,</l>
                  <l>That doth to good the Readers eye incline,</l>
                  <l>Neuer till now a body forc'd to doe,</l>
                  <l>What the poore mind loaths to conſent vnto.</l>
                  <l>She danceth weeping, laughes and ſighes in paine.</l>
                  <l>So I haue ſeene (me thinkes) Sun-ſhine in raine.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Marm.</speaker>
                  <p>Enough, I long to imploy her. Couſin, heres the mony. She's mine. Whats your name?</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Vast.</speaker>
                  <p>Florence.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Marm.</speaker>
                  <p>Florence. I like the name well.</p>
                  <p>Its a good lucky name to make a whore on. You'l ſtay with me, Florence.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Wife.</speaker>
                  <p>Till you are weary of me. Ile but take leaue of my brother, and follow you.</p>
                  <stage>Exit Marmaid.</stage>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ast.</speaker>
                  <p>What with me?</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Wife.</speaker>
                  <p>Am I not worthy of one kiſſe?</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>aſt.</speaker>
                  <p>There—now be gone.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Wife.</speaker>
                  <l>Be gone? Death could not ſpeake a word more fatall.</l>
                  <l>Yet one more—ſo now farewell—</l>
                  <l>Vniuſt—vnkind—my woe-diuining heart.</l>
                  <l>By this we firſt embrac'd, by this we part.</l>
                  <stage>Exit Wife.</stage>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Vaſt.</speaker>
                  <l>I am a villaine, but ſhe makes me weepe.</l>
                  <l>Why doe I thinke ſhe's falſe? I neuer ſaw't.</l>
                  <l>Tut, all bels ring that tune. It is too true.</l>
                  <l>I told her that this fiftie pound ſhould carry me to the warres;</l>
                  <l>But I haue a battle to fight ere I goe.</l>
                  <l>Old Gripe that has the morgage of my lands,</l>
                  <l>Lies ſicke of the Goute, and ſeldome ſtirres abroad.</l>
                  <l>Some of that race Ile kill, or leaue my owne life</l>
                  <l>In pawne I would haue done 't. I ha' chalenged</l>
                  <l>
                     <pb facs="tcp:16830:5"/>
                     <hi>Beniamin</hi> Gripe the ſonne, whom the world cals</l>
                  <l>The Honeſt Lawyer. He comes.</l>
                  <stage>Enter Beniamin Gripe.</stage>
                  <p>Y'are the ſonne of a villaine.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Ben.</speaker>
                  <p>If I were, I could not helpe it.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Vaſt.</speaker>
                  <p>Thy ſelfe's a villaine.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Ben.</speaker>
                  <p>Its a ranke lie.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Vaſt.</speaker>
                  <l>Lie? Thou exaſperatſt</l>
                  <l>One mad already, that would haue hazard heauen</l>
                  <l>To make this earth drunke with thy bloud.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Ben.</speaker>
                  <l>Its deare, ſo bought. Twil not redeeme your ſoule.</l>
                  <l>Say, with deepe ſluces, all theſe liuely ſprings,</l>
                  <l>That runne through the ſoft channels of my veines,</l>
                  <l>Should be exhauſt by thee, or thine by me,</l>
                  <l>And burning malice ſhould be quencht in bloud:</l>
                  <l>He that ſpeeds beſt, wins what he ſhould abhorre,</l>
                  <l>And glories to be curſt a conqueror.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Vast.</speaker>
                  <l>Let Sophiſters alone with theſe diſtinctions.</l>
                  <l>Our moderators are our ſwords: the queſtion,</l>
                  <l>That cals vs forth, as warlike diſputants</l>
                  <l>Beyond deciſion of the gowne-furr'd peace.</l>
                  <l>Draw then thy argument, and let's talke indeed.</l>
                  <l>We cannot reaſon ſoundly, till we bleed.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Ben.</speaker>
                  <l>Let's thinke the tearmes, on which we venture bloud.</l>
                  <l>Th'ffects are waighty, let the cauſe be good.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Vaſt.</speaker>
                  <l>Thy father hath vndone me, and mine iſſue.</l>
                  <l>The law affords no ſuccour: what remaines,</l>
                  <l>But onely to let him bleed through thy vaines?</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Ben.</speaker>
                  <p>How haue I wrongd thee?</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Vaſt.</speaker>
                  <l>Aske no more. The State</l>
                  <l>Of our ſtrife is, thou art his Sonne, I hate.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Ben.</speaker>
                  <l>No helpe? let fury arbitrate the reſt.</l>
                  <l>This paſſion muſt but center in one breſt.</l>
                  <l>Yet let's embrace, and pardon; and euen loue</l>
                  <l>In hate. O ſuffer not the dying blood</l>
                  <l>To preiudice the ſad ſuruiuours good.</l>
                  <stage>They fight.</stage>
                  <stage>Enter Curfew the Abbot.</stage>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Curf.</speaker>
                  <l>What vnexpected clangor frights the peace</l>
                  <l>
                     <pb facs="tcp:16830:5"/>
Of my delighted ſolitary walkes?</l>
                  <l>What ſonnes of miſchiefe in their fury tread</l>
                  <l>Theſe vnfrequented pathes?—ſtay—hold.</l>
                  <l>My ſonnes, heare age but ſpeake; wiſedome is old.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Vast.</speaker>
                  <p>Peace, Dotard.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Curf.</speaker>
                  <l>On my knees, which doubling age</l>
                  <l>Hath ſcarce left able to ſupport my corps:</l>
                  <l>By the remaining teares of fortie yeares</l>
                  <l>Spent in this penitentiall order: the laſt drops,</l>
                  <l>The drying hand of age hath left to dew</l>
                  <l>This witherd garden: I implore—beſeech.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>aſt.</speaker>
                  <p>Father, you ſpeake to rocks, or the ſurd waues.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Curf.</speaker>
                  <l>Then on this innocent boſome turn your ſwords,</l>
                  <l>And eaſe a weake ſoule of her tedious portage,</l>
                  <l>Some houre before her time. O do not flie me.</l>
                  <l>Let the few drops of my ſlow-pacing blood,</l>
                  <l>That ſtands in my cold channels, expiate yours.</l>
                  <l>Oh let a falling trunke redeeme two plants.</l>
                  <stage>ſight still.</stage>
                  <l>No remedie? let me exclaime for helpe.</l>
                  <p>(The diuell part you:) if I ſhould now ha'paid for my charitie—well: twas this Church-coate that ſau'd me.</p>
                  <stage>Exit crying helpe.</stage>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Vast.</speaker>
                  <l>Oh thou haſt ſlaine me: hold thy conquering hand.</l>
                  <l>Heauens, you are too iuſt pay-maſters. Thy ſword,</l>
                  <l>With a fate-ſign'd direction, hath cut ſhort</l>
                  <l>My hoped fortunes in a longer breath.</l>
                  <l>But I forgiue thee. Flie—ſtay.</l>
                  <l>I haue two Orphans in this houre depriu'd</l>
                  <l>Of a bad Parent. For their mother—nothing.</l>
                  <l>She has a trade to liue on. O let my dying breath</l>
                  <l>Beg this one mercie at thy bloud-ſtaind hands:</l>
                  <l>Releeue them with now thine, once their owne lands.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Ben.</speaker>
                  <l>Forgiue my deed, and by that mercie, I</l>
                  <l>Depend on for my ſinnes; my mercy ſhall</l>
                  <l>Raiſe vp the children for the fathers fall. Farewell.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Vaſt.</speaker>
                  <l>He's gone. Now vp againe. My wounds</l>
                  <stage>Exit Ben.</stage>
                  <l>Are ſlight, yet through their windows, heare I breath</l>
                  <l>Out all my malice. Noble youth, I loue thee.</l>
                  <l>
                     <pb facs="tcp:16830:6"/>
How little of thy father haſt thou in thee!</l>
                  <l>Now for ſome ſtrange diſguiſe, till time I find,</l>
                  <l>To pleaſure him that was to me thus kind.</l>
                  <stage>Exit.</stage>
                  <stage>Enter Valentine.</stage>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Valen.</speaker>
                  <p>Well, I ſee there's no liuing in London, The foure winds haue conſpirde to blow all the villany of the world thither. When I returnd from my ſhort trauell, I inquir'd, for the knot of my old companions. But like an old Ladie, that has much vſd painting, how ſuddenly are they broken! I heard of three or foure in Bed<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lam. Fiue or ſixe in Bridewell. Halfe a ſcore ith' Counter. a whole dozen at Tyburne. But Oh, numbers, numbers, vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der the hands of Barber-Surgions. Some turnd Squires to a Bro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thell. Others walke New-gate lane. Some cheating in Ordina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries. Others prigging in crowds. And the reſt, either ſwomme o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer ſea, or drownd vpon a hill. Well, I do not like theſe procee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dings; there bee ſo many rubbes. I could now begge in Dutch, but its no ſpeeding language. Now my villanie failes on the ſea, Ile trie what cheates the land has to worke on. I learn'd ſome ſcuruie medicins of our Surgion of the ſhip: &amp; had no ſooner ſet vp my bils in Bedford here; but a Goutie cure comes halting to mee. Fifty pounds I muſt haue to heale him. Fiue and twentie I haue in pawne: for the reſt, Ile leaue it with the next Quackſaluer, that with more skill ſhall doe him as little good.</p>
                  <stage>Enter Gripe halting, Nice and Thirſty.</stage>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Grip.</speaker>
                  <p>Couſin <hi>Nice,</hi> and my man <hi>Thirſty.</hi>
                  </p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Thirst.</speaker>
                  <p>Shall I fetch you ſome drinke, Sir?</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Grip.</speaker>
                  <p>No. Thy mind runs all oth' pot.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Thirst.</speaker>
                  <p>So 't had need, for you keepe mee Thirſty, ſpight o' my teeth.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Gripe.</speaker>
                  <p>Goe you two to the vnder-Sheriffe; and bid him by ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tue of this morgage, giue you poſſeſſion of <hi>Vasters</hi> lands. The beg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gerly ſlaue has broken with me, and Ile take the forfeit. Go quicke, quicke. I will not loſe an houre.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Nic.</speaker>
                  <p>Ile but goe to the Church for a little holy-water—</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Grip.</speaker>
                  <p>Be drownd in holy-water.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Nic.</speaker>
                  <p>No, but a little ſprinkled Sir. We ſhall haue the better ſuc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſe in our buſineſſe.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <pb facs="tcp:16830:6"/>
                  <speaker>Grip.</speaker>
                  <p>I pree thee good <hi>Nice,</hi> diſpatch, diſpatch.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Thir.</speaker>
                  <p>I, come, come maſter <hi>Nice.</hi> There's good licour it h' houſe. You may ſprinkle your throte with that. Its better then holy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>water.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Nic.</speaker>
                  <p>One thing Sir. I do not like going to day. Sure tis not a luckie time. For the firſt Crow I heard this morning, cryed twice. This Euen, Sir, is no good number.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Grip.</speaker>
                  <p>Poxe o' Crowes and numbers. If thou hadſt giuen her a peece of carrion, ſhe would ha' cryed againe. Away.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Nic.</speaker>
                  <l>I go, Sir—ſtay, what if there be a Rauen about the ground?</l>
                  <l>Shall we then take poſſeſſion? Oh tis an vnluckie bird.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Grip.</speaker>
                  <l>Why, let her croke the downfall of his houſe.</l>
                  <l>Whats that to me? prethee good <hi>Nice</hi> make haſte.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Nic.</speaker>
                  <p>Nay, too much haſte will make one ſtumble: and thats no good ſigne.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Grip.</speaker>
                  <p>Now, <hi>Valentine,</hi> Haſt all things ready? how now—a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gaine?</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Nic.</speaker>
                  <p>A toy comes in my head.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Valen.</speaker>
                  <p>Poxe o' that head: more toyes yet?</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Ni.</speaker>
                  <p>How if a Catte ſits on the Buttry hatch? Thou we'ſt pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceed no further. My Grandam told me that a Cat ſitting on the hatch, was an ill ſigne.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Grip.</speaker>
                  <p>Mew. Beate her off, daſh out her braines. Good <hi>Nice</hi> be not ſo curious.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Ni.</speaker>
                  <p>Oh Sir, it's good doubting the worſt.</p>
                  <stage>Exeunt Nice. Thir.</stage>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Grip.</speaker>
                  <p>Are all things ready, <hi>Valentine?</hi> this foole troubles mee worſe then the gowte.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>al.</speaker>
                  <p>Sir, the remedie is verie painfull. I could giue a tedious courſe of phyſicke, worſe then any ſickneſſe. Keepe you faſting ſixteene dayes together, ſaue the dyet I giue you. Binde you to the poſt of patience euery day tenne houres; and haue one ſtill poure ſcaulding water on you: purge your very heart out: ſend your eyes out of their holes, to ſee how your feete doe: make your guttes barke worſe, then an hundred dogges at a beare-bayting. But my medicine is ſharpe and ſhort, but paſsing ſure. Sir, there be foure kindes of gowte.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Gripe.</speaker>
                  <p>No more of kinds. There's no gowte kind to any man, I thinke, but to Phyſicians. Your remedy ſhort-ſhort.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <pb facs="tcp:16830:7"/>
                  <speaker>Val.</speaker>
                  <p>Sir, nothing: ſpecially of no coſt. Do y' ſee this ten-pen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny naile?</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Gripe.</speaker>
                  <p>Yes: What of that?</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Val.</speaker>
                  <p>This naile I muſt driue through your great toe.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Grip.</speaker>
                  <p>What? through the bone?</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Val.</speaker>
                  <p>Yes, bone &amp; fleſh too.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Grip.</speaker>
                  <p>Oh-oh-giue me my money. This medicine's worſe then any gowte. Oh good <hi>Valentine,</hi> your tent's too long—too long.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Val.</speaker>
                  <p>Then ſit and rot: be rack'd ſtill, Ile be gone.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Grip.</speaker>
                  <p>Nay, good <hi>Valentine:</hi> would not a ſixe-penny naile ſerue?</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Val.</speaker>
                  <p>You'l be Phyſician, will you? If you'l ſit downe and be cur'd, ſo: if not, farewell.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Grip.</speaker>
                  <p>Nay, good <hi>Valentine:—</hi>euen do thy will.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Val.</speaker>
                  <p>Endure it manfully. It's but a brunt—ſo. <stage>nailes him.</stage> You ſhall ſit but a quarter of an houre, till I ha' been at the Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thecaries, and then Ile looſe you. Now farewell, gowty foole, Thou took'ſt no purge, yet haſt a moſt ſharpe ſtoole. Pray heauens, this kill him not. Well, let him ſit. <stage>he takes away his purſe with his keis</stage> And this ſhal go with me. I pray S<hi rend="sup">r</hi> take your caſe. This plot has tooke; try if ſome new may hit.</p>
                  <stage>Exit Val.</stage>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Grip.</speaker>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Come-come-Valentine.</hi> Oh-neuer was man ſo farre in my bonds, as I am in this Phyſicians. H' has nayl'd me to him. That euery whore in London, were but i' my caſe now. Why <hi>Valentine—</hi>
                  </p>
                  <stage>Enter Nice panting. Thirſty.</stage>
                  <p>Oh he's come. How now? are you return'd? where's my mor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gage? out Villaines, where's my morgage? Oh my toe—oh my morgage. I'm vndone.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Thirſt.</speaker>
                  <p>Me thinkes you are too faſt, Sir.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Ni.</speaker>
                  <p>Plague o' you and your morgage. Oh my heart-it beats ſo, that it has broke my buttons. I would not bee ſo frighted a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gaine to be made your heire. puffe.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Grip.</speaker>
                  <p>What's the newes <hi>Thirſty?</hi> what, what, good <hi>Thirsty?</hi>
                  </p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Thir.</speaker>
                  <p>Let me vndoe you Maſter.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Grip.</speaker>
                  <p>No, not till I heare of my morgage. What's the mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter? oh—</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Ni.</speaker>
                  <p>The matter? I would not ha' ſuch another croſſe, for all the croſſes i' your purſe.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Grip.</speaker>
                  <p>What? oh—what? Is my morgage ſafe? Hath the vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der-Sheriffe done a miracle, and playd the honeſt man? what good <hi>Thirſty?</hi>
                  </p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <pb facs="tcp:16830:7"/>
                  <speaker>Thirſt.</speaker>
                  <p>Nothing Sir, but a Hare croſs'd the way; and hee, poore timorous ſoule, durſt goe no further for feare of ſprights.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Grip.</speaker>
                  <p>Oh rogues, pernicious villains, you conſpire to couzen me: get out the naile, <hi>Thirſty.</hi> Hares, and Rauens, and Diuels.</p>
                  <stage>Enter Beniamin.</stage>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Ben.</speaker>
                  <p>Who has abus'd you thus Sir? could you be ſo credulous, to thinke this a receyte good for the Gout? Sir, giue me leaue to helpe you.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Grip.</speaker>
                  <p>Do, good <hi>Ben.</hi> but not in this, <hi>Ben.</hi> not in this. Oh my mor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gage man, my morgage—run. I ſhall loſe a dayes fruits of my mor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gage.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Ben.</speaker>
                  <l>Come Sir, reſpect your health aboue your gaine.</l>
                  <l>I would not for your wealth haue halfe your paine.</l>
                  <stage>looſeth him.</stage>
                  <l>Go in Sir, get ſome broth, looke to your wound.</l>
                  <l>Your morgage leaue to me, Ile keepe that ſound.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Grip.</speaker>
                  <p>Take my couſin <hi>Nice</hi> with you. Come <hi>Thirſty,</hi> helpe <hi>Thirſty.</hi>
                  </p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Ben.</speaker>
                  <l>Now for ſome cleanly tricke to ſhift my hands</l>
                  <stage>Exit.</stage>
                  <l>Of this ſame ſhallow ſuperſtitious foole.</l>
                  <p>Now couzen, I'am ſure you are not without an <hi>Erra Pater</hi> i' your pocket. They ſay this is like to be a very ſtrange yeare.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Nice.</speaker>
                  <p>Moſt ſtrange, and full of prepoſterous, prodigious, turbu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lent, diſmall, fatall, amazing, terrifying—</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Ben.</speaker>
                  <p>Bleſſe vs. What?</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Nic.</speaker>
                  <p>Wonders. The effects whereof wil appeare in riſings, part<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly biformed, and partly circular, on mens forheads, and womens mountaines.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Ben.</speaker>
                  <p>Is there no ſad mortality to enſue?</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Ni.</speaker>
                  <p>Yes, my Almanacke ſpeakes of a moſt fearefull peſtilence, eſpecially to happen amongſt Taylors and Gold-end-men.</p>
                  <p>Ther's a ſtatute-lace ſhall vndoe them ifayth. A Taylours Bill ſhal be no more ſo deadly as the plagues.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Ben.</speaker>
                  <p>Sirrah <hi>Nice,</hi> I had a dreame to night.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Nic.</speaker>
                  <p>Paſſion o' my heart! a dreame? what? I do not like theſe dreames.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Ben.</speaker>
                  <l>Ile tell thee what. Me thought, my troubled fancie</l>
                  <l>Led me into a Garden proudly deckt</l>
                  <l>With Natures glory, and the ſweeteſt flowers,</l>
                  <l>
                     <pb facs="tcp:16830:8"/>
That ere my breath ſuck'd vp: where the greene graſſe</l>
                  <l>Tempted my ſleepy ſpirits to ſoft repoſe.</l>
                  <l>There came, me thought, a friend (dead now long ſince)</l>
                  <l>And ſhooke me by the hand, and queſtion'd me</l>
                  <l>Of many ſad euents, whoſe conference</l>
                  <l>So vex'd me that I woke. Why ſtand'ſt amaz'd?</l>
                  <l>Thou wilt not leaue me Coz.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Nic.</speaker>
                  <p>Yes, and you were ten Couſins. Dreame of a garden, and greene ruſhes, and a dead friends ſalutation? Couſin, make your will, be rul'd and make your will: you cannot liue.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Ben.</speaker>
                  <l>Wilt thou be a foole of fate? who can</l>
                  <l>Preuent the deſtinie decreed for man? Ile on.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Nic.</speaker>
                  <p>So will not I. Good Coz, I leaue you to your deſtinie. The next newes I heare, the Lawyer's a dead man. Dreames quoth a! and he will not beleeue a dreame, he's an Infidell. One night I dream't that I found gold at a play. Next day I came thi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, ſlatter'd with theſe hopes. Zlid, before the <hi>Prologue</hi> had done, I had loſt my purſe.</p>
                  <l>Coz<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> if you ha'no faith in dreames, farewell.</l>
                  <l>I would not dreame of heauen, leſt I find hell.</l>
                  <stage>Exit.</stage>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Ben.</speaker>
                  <l>This charme has caſt him off, now to my morgage.</l>
                  <l>Oh <hi>Vaster,</hi> thou art dead; thy hapleſſe iſſue,</l>
                  <l>Expos'd to the bleake ayre of theſe cold times.</l>
                  <l>I haue no meanes to expiate the wrongs,</l>
                  <l>My cruell Father, and my ſelfe more bloudy,</l>
                  <l>Haue done thee, but by charitie to thine,</l>
                  <l>All the poore pieces that remaine of thee.</l>
                  <l>So with the plaiſters of our broken good,</l>
                  <l>We hide the wounds, firſt hauing ſhed the bloud.</l>
                  <l>Within there Hoh.</l>
                  <stage>Enter Robert, and Anne Vaſter.</stage>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Rob.</speaker>
                  <p>Thou com'ſt vpon thy death, infectious iſſue of the worlds plague; if thy bloud ſtained foote enter theſe dores. Our parents are from home. Till their returne, Ile keepe poſſeſsion. Or loſe it with my life.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Ben.</speaker>
                  <l>Incenſed Youth.</l>
                  <l>Thou fight'ſt 'gainſt power with a ſword of ſtraw:</l>
                  <l>As good cope with the diuell, as with the Law.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Anne.</speaker>
                  <l>Me thinks, Sir, there ſhould dwell ſome pittie in your looke.</l>
                  <l>
                     <pb facs="tcp:16830:8"/>
Oh, caſt an eye of mercie on the woes,</l>
                  <l>Of two moſt wretched Orphans; doubly loſt,</l>
                  <l>Firſt in their Parents miſeries: but, oh! moſt</l>
                  <l>In their vntimely deaths; for we doubt ſore,</l>
                  <l>We neuer ſhall behold their faces more.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Ben.</speaker>
                  <l>My griefe requites you both.</l>
                  <l>No matter, had it ſo pleas'd the high powers,</l>
                  <l>If that my Father had excuſed yours.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Ann.</speaker>
                  <p>Good Sir, forget your ſtrength; and do not triumph ouer the proſtrate fortunes of two wretches,</p>
                  <l>Expos'd to vnreſiſted tyrannie.</l>
                  <l>Behold a Mayden begging on her knee—</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Ben.</speaker>
                  <l>Riſe: that's heauens due. Theſe armes now thee intwine,</l>
                  <l>That wiſh for euer, to be called thine:</l>
                  <l>A ſtrange new influence runs through my affections,</l>
                  <l>Into my panting heart; and there inthron'd,</l>
                  <l>Commands my lower faculties to loue</l>
                  <l>This poore diſtreſſed Virgin. I am flam'd</l>
                  <l>With pittie and affection; whether more!</l>
                  <l>Yet let my ſenſes ſome coole reaſon gather:</l>
                  <l>What, loue the daughter, and haue ſlaine the father?</l>
                  <l>(I muſt: heauen knowes I muſt). See, my lov'd friends:</l>
                  <l>My comming to you is for other ends.</l>
                  <l>My Father ſent me to inuade your lands.</l>
                  <l>A while ſtand free redeemed with my hands.</l>
                  <l>There's money to relieue you: that done, you ſhall haue more.</l>
                  <l>Deſpaire not: heauen will not forſake the poore.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Rob.</speaker>
                  <l>Right noble ſonne of ſo profeſt a foe,</l>
                  <l>Heauen be as kinde to you, as you t' our woe.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Ben.</speaker>
                  <l>I burſt, if I containe my paſsion. Faireſt Virgin,</l>
                  <l>If thou dar'ſt credite me, <hi>I</hi> loue thee.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Rob.</speaker>
                  <l>Hold. Here take your kindnes back: Though we are poore,</l>
                  <l>My ſiſter was not bred to be a whore.</l>
                  <l>Forbeare to touch her.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Ben.</speaker>
                  <l>Fond Youth, thy rage is vaine.</l>
                  <l>Th'art young: thy errour doth thy vertue ſtaine.</l>
                  <l>I loue her as a wife.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Anne.</speaker>
                  <l>Oh doe not mock me.</l>
                  <l>
                     <pb facs="tcp:16830:9"/>
How can I thinke, you to ſuch fortunes borne.</l>
                  <l>Will looke vpon a Mayd, ſo poore, forlorne?</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Ben.</speaker>
                  <l>Alas! that pouerty ſhould vertue ſmother.</l>
                  <l>Not in my breſt. No, Ile ſtill honeſt be:</l>
                  <l>Vertue in rags are gold's all one to me.</l>
                  <l>Cenſure me both, as you ſhall finde me true,</l>
                  <l>Ile be your father, and your brother too.</l>
                  <stage>Enter old Gripe brought in a chaire, by Nice and Thirſty.</stage>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Grip.</speaker>
                  <l>So, let me downe, till I haue ſeene my new morgage.</l>
                  <l>How now ſon <hi>Beniamin,</hi> ha' you taken poſſeſsion?</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Ben.</speaker>
                  <p>Of that you cannot diſpoſſeſſe me, Sir.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Grip.</speaker>
                  <p>No knaue? what wilt thou take my lands before I'm dead?</p>
                  <p>You are a braue ſon indeed. But this is the world. If the father be poore, the ſonne would be ridde of him, to ſaue charges. If rich, he muſt haue his lands ere his bones be cold.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Thir.</speaker>
                  <p>They may be cold, for they ha' been rotten theſe dozen yeeres.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Nic.</speaker>
                  <p>I am very hungry.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Thir.</speaker>
                  <p>I am very thirſty.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Ni.</speaker>
                  <p>But dare not eate, becauſe I was dream'd to night of cho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Ann.</speaker>
                  <l>Now brother w' are, vndone.</l>
                  <l>The damned father will peruert the ſon.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Rob.</speaker>
                  <l>Gowt, dropſie, lameneſſe, rotten legges can haſten</l>
                  <l>T'vndoe the poore. Vſurers that ſit</l>
                  <l>Bound to their chaires with charms, &amp; cannot moue</l>
                  <l>But by their porters, can to ill beſtirre them.</l>
                  <l>He needs make haſte, that is at hell before them.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Grip.</speaker>
                  <p>Ha? for 3. Moneths?</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Ben.</speaker>
                  <l>Indeed Sir, by that power you put me in,</l>
                  <l>In charity to their miſerable ſtate,</l>
                  <l>Orphan'd of Parents, and of meanes to liue,</l>
                  <l>I gaue them 3. moneths profite of the lands.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Grip.</speaker>
                  <p>Out Villaine, Charitie's a begger, as thou wut be. 3. mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neths! three weekes, 3. dayes, 3. houres had been more charity, then euer I ſhew'd, or will ſhew to ſuch beggers. Come <hi>Nice, Thirſty,</hi> liſt me: Ile take poſſeſsion my ſelfe.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Ben.</speaker>
                  <p>I hope Sir, you'l not nullifie my deed.</p>
                  <stage>Exit Thirſt.</stage>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <pb facs="tcp:16830:9"/>
                  <speaker>Grip.</speaker>
                  <p>Deed mee no deedes: Ile nullifie thee from being mine heire. Come, helpe me I ſay.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Nic.</speaker>
                  <p>Indeed Sir, I dare not lift you againſt the poore.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Grip.</speaker>
                  <p>Where's my man <hi>Thirsty?</hi>
                  </p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Nic.</speaker>
                  <p>He's gone in to drinke Sir.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Grip.</speaker>
                  <p>Oh he's a good knaue: he has got poſſeſsion ot'h houſe.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Thir.</speaker>
                  <p>Of nothing maſter but the Buttry, I.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Grip.</speaker>
                  <p>As lame as I am, Ile in my ſelfe.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Rob.</speaker>
                  <p>Sit ſtill you lethargie: y' had better drop—</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Ben.</speaker>
                  <l>Containe your ſelfe, young friend. He is my father,</l>
                  <l>Let not the warme neſt of my loue to you,</l>
                  <l>Hatch vp encouragement to my fathers wrongs.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Rob.</speaker>
                  <l>You are my ſterne Sir, at your pleaſure guide</l>
                  <l>This tempeſt-beaten veſſell.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Ben.</speaker>
                  <l>Good Sir confirme</l>
                  <l>This worke of pietie, which I preſum'd,</l>
                  <l>On faith of your good nature to affoord.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Grip.</speaker>
                  <p>Sirrah, your good nature will bring you to th'Almeſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>houſe. Thou ſhalt not inherit a doyt of mine. And for you two Kitlins, Ile make you mew ith Iayle, and there be any law in Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land. So this chaſing fit hath got me the vſe of my legges agame. Oh excellent Surgion; would thou wert here againe, for the other 25. pounds.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Ben.</speaker>
                  <p>Strange! that ſame Quack-ſaluer has done him good, a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt his will. How fare you Sir?</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Grip.</speaker>
                  <p>The worſe for thee Baſtard. Th'haſt too much charitie in thee to be the ſonne of old <hi>Gripe.</hi>
                  </p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Ann.</speaker>
                  <l>Deare brother, yeeld poſſeſſion: wee 'l begge rather,</l>
                  <l>Then this our worthy friend ſhould loſe his father.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Rob.</speaker>
                  <l>Sir, be not ſo incens'd: reſume your ſonne</l>
                  <l>Into your former loue, and I reſigne</l>
                  <l>All right, that his free promiſe hath made mine.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Grip.</speaker>
                  <l>Come then, <hi>Nice, Thirsty.</hi> Oh braue Surgion, I can goe.</l>
                  <l>Oh braue morgage I can enter.</l>
                  <stage>Exit.</stage>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Nic.</speaker>
                  <p>M. <hi>Beniamin,</hi> a ſober word in priuate. If this wench want harbour, I care not if I giue her a nights lodging.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Ben.</speaker>
                  <l>I haue inuited her with her brother to ſupper this night.</l>
                  <l>Will you—</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <pb facs="tcp:16830:10"/>
                  <speaker>Ni.</speaker>
                  <p>Oh it's Fry-day, and I know you haue fleſh.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Ben.</speaker>
                  <p>Thou wouldſt take her any night. Is ſhe not fleſh?</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Nic.</speaker>
                  <p>Sweet Couſin, I would not eate her. If you pleaſe to com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mend me to her: let me ſee, for what—I leaue that to you.</p>
                  <stage>Exit.</stage>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Ben.</speaker>
                  <l>Goe in, let me alone. This petulant foole.</l>
                  <l>Shall be my ſcaffold to erect my plots.</l>
                  <l>Come, friends, vnlode your ſorrowes on my heart.</l>
                  <l>Griefes weight is eas'd; when each one beares his part.</l>
               </sp>
            </div>
            <div n="2" type="act">
               <head>Act. Secund.</head>
               <stage>Enter Curfew Abbot.</stage>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Curf.</speaker>
                  <l>THus am I ſtolne out from the Couent. Abbot,</l>
                  <l>Ly there, thou happy warranted caſe</l>
                  <l>Of any Villaine. Th'haſt been my ſtawking-horſe,</l>
                  <l>Now theſe ten months. So long 'tis ſince the Abbot</l>
                  <l>Went on a ſolemne pilgrimage and left</l>
                  <l>My brother, a good honeſt Fryer, his friend</l>
                  <l>Deputed for him. But my brother ſcarce</l>
                  <l>Warme in his new vice-honour, walking out</l>
                  <l>To viſite me one morning, at my houſe</l>
                  <l>Fell dead of an impoſtume ſuddenly.</l>
                  <l>I bury'd him in priuate; but from's bloud</l>
                  <l>Am purer then the Cryſtall. Studying now,</l>
                  <l>How to turne ſorrow into policie,</l>
                  <l>I haue aſſum'd his ſhape. Who can deny,</l>
                  <l>But that a Dunce may riſe to Dignitie?</l>
                  <l>Blind Ignorance doth not alwaies ſtrut in Sattin.</l>
                  <l>It often walkes a Clergy pace in blacke,</l>
                  <l>And deales the holy Rites with as bold hands,</l>
                  <l>As if it graſp'd <hi>Ioues</hi> thunder: and did iudge it</l>
                  <l>Enough to ſtare, looke bigge, and with a brow</l>
                  <l>More rugged then is <hi>Radamanths,</hi> denounce</l>
                  <l>Torrors againſt ill deeds: the whiles their owne</l>
                  <l>Are not leſſe monſtrous, but leſſe broadly ſhowne.</l>
                  <l>Thus in my ſelfe, how eaſie't is, I proue,</l>
                  <l>To ſweat out iudgements 'gainſt the ſins we loue.</l>
                  <l>
                     <pb facs="tcp:16830:10"/>
As if a garment of world-couzning grace</l>
                  <l>Were impudently good, ſet out by place.</l>
                  <l>Well, I get nothing by this borrow'd forme,</l>
                  <l>But countnance to my thefts. This hollow tree</l>
                  <l>Keeps all my holineſſe: Lie there Abbot, till</l>
                  <l>My worke is done, then doe thou hide my ill.</l>
                  <stage>Enter Valentine gallant.</stage>
                  <l>Maſſe heres comes one already.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Valent.</speaker>
                  <p>Now haue I, like a Paraſite, couerd my backe with braines. Out of my vſurers Gowtie toe, I haue ſpun a faire ſuite. <hi>I</hi> would faine heare, whether the diuell be dead or no. Yet I need not be ſo inquiſitiue, for I'm ſure he has giue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> me nothing in'swill. Now am I in queſt of ſome vaulting houſe. I would faine ſpend theſe crownes, as <hi>I</hi> got them, in cony-catching. I ha'the game in ſent, &amp; will follow it with full cry.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Curf.</speaker>
                  <p>Stand—Giue the word.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Val.</speaker>
                  <p>Word? what word? am I beleaguerd?</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Curf.</speaker>
                  <p>Few words are beſt among friends. Emptie your pockets, and you may vault the lighter. Quicke.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Val.</speaker>
                  <p>Th'art an honeſt fellow, a very honeſt fellow. In good faith I had no great need of mony; but ſince thou haſt brought me ſome, Ile not refuſe it.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Curf.</speaker>
                  <p>Troth, I ha'but a little.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Val.</speaker>
                  <p>Faith nor I. we'll euen draw cuts, who ſhall ha'both.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Curf.</speaker>
                  <p>Agreed.—Shall we breathe?</p>
                  <stage>fight.</stage>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Val.</speaker>
                  <p>Good fortune grant, you be able to pay me for this paines. In ſadnes, <hi>I</hi> deſerue double fees.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Curf.</speaker>
                  <p>Ile make you plead harder, ere you ſit downe to tell your money.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Val.</speaker>
                  <p>Looke that your caſe be good, <hi>I</hi> ſhall picke a hole in't elſe.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Curf.</speaker>
                  <p>Well, let the law paſſe.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Val.</speaker>
                  <p>Not altogether ſo: leſt we be both hange.—Stand your ground. Zlid, I cannot abide theſe running Cockes.</p>
                  <stage>fight.</stage>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Curf.</speaker>
                  <p>
                     <hi>I</hi> haue ſeene a runner winne the battell.—Shall wee draw ſtakes?</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Val.</speaker>
                  <p>Ha? a match—Throw by weapons, and lets embrace.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Curf.</speaker>
                  <p>I am a villaine, but I feare your clutch worſe then a Seriants</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Val.</speaker>
                  <p>As I'm true theefe, thou maiſt truſt me. Ha ſirrah!
<pb facs="tcp:16830:11"/>
                     <hi>Robin Hood,</hi> and the <hi>Pindar</hi> of Wakefield had not a ſtiffer bout. Shall we cling, like a couple of Eeles, not to bee diſſolu'd but by Thunder?</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Curf.</speaker>
                  <p>Moſt liberally. Let's ſet vp ſhop together.</p>
                  <stage>Enter Vaſter diſguiſd.</stage>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>al.</speaker>
                  <p>Done: &amp; to begin our trade, behold a cuſtomer. Stand cloſe.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Vaſt.</speaker>
                  <l>This ruſſet-ſhape of a plaine-dealing yeoman</l>
                  <l>Spirits my hopes with boldneſſe. Sharpe ſuſpition</l>
                  <l>Like to a winking Iuſticer ſhall ſee me,</l>
                  <l>And yet not ſee me. Thus with griefe-ſwolne eyes,</l>
                  <l>Ile match my wife, and childrens miſeries.</l>
                  <l>This fiftie pound Ile husband like a Badger;</l>
                  <l>Buy and ſell Barley: and ſo eaſily wind</l>
                  <l>Into the preſent paſſages of Bedford.</l>
                  <l>How good a ſchoolemaſter is Pouertie!</l>
                  <l>I could not liue on hundreds, that came in</l>
                  <l>By annuall rents; now I begin to thriue</l>
                  <l>On the ſmall fragments. Thus like Prodigals,</l>
                  <l>That once did ſcorne the meate, now glad of pottage.</l>
                  <l>The mannor gone, Ile trie to liue oth' cottage.</l>
                  <l>Bedford, ha'for you.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Curf.</speaker>
                  <p>Stand. Giue the word.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Vaſt.</speaker>
                  <p>The word, y' are a theefe.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Val.</speaker>
                  <p>You might ha'ſhot twice, and not hit it righter.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ast.</speaker>
                  <p>What do you ſhoot at?</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Curf.</speaker>
                  <p>Oh Sir, like your Ieſuite, all at the purſe.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Val.</speaker>
                  <p>Will you caſt out the diuell, and ſaue's a coniuring.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Vaſt.</speaker>
                  <p>Are you ſo cunning at the blacke Art? Ile trie your skill. What, both at once? that's no faire play.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Curf.</speaker>
                  <p>Faire play is for Fencers. Yet thou ſeemſt a good fellow. Thou ſhalt haue it. Stand aſide, partner.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>aſt.</speaker>
                  <p>Saiſt thou me ſo, boy? then there's mony, win't and wear't.</p>
                  <stage>Fight.</stage>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Val.</speaker>
                  <p>Now could I get in and rob 'hem both<hi>—Hercules!</hi> Hee laies about him like <hi>Orlando Furioſo,</hi> or a coward turnd deſperate. Braue boy yfaith. Wee might ha'robd two and twenty Taffata-clok'd rorers, before this freeſe-iacket. Oh, your ſurly Bore is like
<pb facs="tcp:16830:11"/>
a bloudy'd Maſtiffe: when your ſpruce Pantaloun bawles like a whelpe in a Tauerne: yet at the ſight of cold yron runs, as if he had ſeene a Serieant.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Curf.</speaker>
                  <p>Hold, hold: Keepe your caſh.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ast.</speaker>
                  <p>The mony's good mony Sir, if it be not too heauy for you</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Curf.</speaker>
                  <p>Nay, for the weight I could make ſhift, but for the ſcuruy conditions goe with it.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>aſt.</speaker>
                  <p>Hau you any gall to't Sir?</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Val.</speaker>
                  <p>Not not ſo much as pigeon. Put vp thy caſh my braue quin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſſence of Hobbniols. Giue me thy hand. How many thouſand cudgels haſt thou broken i' thy daies about a May-pole?</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Curf.</speaker>
                  <p>I warrant, as many as would make all Bedford chimnies ſmoke a whole winter.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>aſt.</speaker>
                  <p>Ieſt on. Ha' you any more to ſay to me.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Curf.</speaker>
                  <p>Nothing my braue <hi>Clem</hi> o' th <hi>Clough,</hi> but I would thou wouldſt deale with vs. Say, ſhall wee put all our ſtockes together, and ſet out a ſhip of our owne?</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>aſt.</speaker>
                  <p>Ha? firſt tell me truly what you are.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Curf.</speaker>
                  <p>Agreed. Let's ſit downe to counſell. I am the Abbot of Newnham.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Vaſt.</speaker>
                  <p>How? much?</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Curf.</speaker>
                  <p>Ile not bate you an Ace on't, till the old Abbot returnes from Pilgrimage. My chamber ſhall be our Rendeuous. The diuell himſelfe in the ſhape of a blurting Conſtable wil not looke for vs there.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Val.</speaker>
                  <p>I am a ſouldiour, and in this vacation time am forc'd to do like Lawyers; when ſuites do not make them, they make ſuites: becauſe the warres will not maintaine me, I maintaine the warres. I ſet vp my Bils in Bedford here, for a Phyſician, and dealt with <hi>Gripe</hi> for the Gowt. I haue a proiect to ſwell our purſes till they burſt. Will you ſecond me?</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Vaſt.</speaker>
                  <p>As inſeparably, as a condition does an obligation.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Val.</speaker>
                  <p>I haue often heard the gripulous Dotard talke of Fairies: and how rich the houſe proues that they haunt. I haue ripened the bliſter of his imagination to the full. Shall we launce it? I haue keys that ſhall ſecure our conueyance. Is't a match?</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Vaſt.</speaker>
                  <l>The ſafeſt ſtratagem we could deuiſe,</l>
                  <l>By craft, more then by ſtrength, all theeues do riſe.</l>
                  <l>
                     <pb facs="tcp:16830:12"/>
Of many politicke knaues you cannot ſpie one.</l>
                  <l>The Foxe will haue his prey before the Lion.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Val.</speaker>
                  <p>Two or three nights we'le ſcatter ſome ſmall peeces of ſil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer, till opportunitie plumpe our proiect.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Curf.</speaker>
                  <l>I take it rightly. Oh tis quicke and ſharpe.</l>
                  <l>So with a Gudgeon loſt, we'll catch a Carpe. A bootie.</l>
                  <stage>Enter Griffin, Sager, Bromley.</stage>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Griff.</speaker>
                  <p>As I was ſaying, Maſter <hi>Bromley,</hi> why ſhould you take th' aduantage of your neighbour <hi>Sager</hi> here? Y' haue got the reuer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion of his Leaſe. Ther's is but one life to come in't. Wee are all mortall. It may come ere you looke for't. I loue peace, I loue peace.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Brom.</speaker>
                  <p>I ſay, that life is forfeit: and Ile enter on all. The law is on my ſide. Ile not be bound to th' peace.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Griff.</speaker>
                  <p>Nay Sir, Ile bind no man: but if I could perſwade you—to be fleeced both, ſo I might be kept warme in your wooll—How ſay you neighbour <hi>Sager?</hi>
                  </p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Sag.</speaker>
                  <l>Alas Sir, I do but defend my owne.</l>
                  <l>Nay could be wel-contented to ſit downe</l>
                  <l>With ſome (though vniuſt) loſſe. I iudge it beſt.</l>
                  <l>Though with ſome preiudice to buy my reſt.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Griff.</speaker>
                  <p>Therein you wrong your ſelfe: the law is impartiall, like a Bell, as ſound on one ſide, as on th' other, if the clapper be right. Maſter <hi>Bromley</hi> a word—What will you iudge me worthy of, If I perſwade him to relinquiſh his right? You know your caſe—.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Brom.</speaker>
                  <p>Here's twenty angels: worke it good Maſter <hi>Griffin,</hi> work it; and you ſhall be my euerlaſting Atturney. But if you faile, you muſt returne.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Griff.</speaker>
                  <p>Piſh, neuer talke o' that man—M<hi rend="sup">r</hi>. <hi>Sager,</hi> a word—I loue peace, though I cannot liue by't. I reſpect my conſcience aboue my purſe—when t' has no money in't.—What will you giue mee to draw <hi>Bromley</hi> to a good handſome compoſition?</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Sag.</speaker>
                  <p>Not a pennie, till y' haue done't.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Griff.</speaker>
                  <p>You know twill go againſt you, but I loue peace.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Sag.</speaker>
                  <l>(I neuer knew't in any of your Tribe.</l>
                  <l>Th' euent be what it will, Ile giue no bribe.)</l>
                  <l>Sir, as I like your end—God and my cauſe,</l>
                  <l>Are coate of ſteele, gainſt the ſharpe fangs of lawes.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <pb facs="tcp:16830:12"/>
                  <speaker>Grif.</speaker>
                  <p>Shall we walke on? our iourney's long.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Curf.</speaker>
                  <p>Not ſo long as you take't. Stand, good Mr. Lawyer, ſhall I puta caſe to you now?</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>al.</speaker>
                  <p>Come, vntruſſe, we haue haſt of buſineſſe?</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Curf.</speaker>
                  <p>Quicke ſirrah, <hi>I</hi> ſhall ſerue an Execution o' your throte elſe</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Grif.</speaker>
                  <p>Indeed Gentleme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, I am ſorry that I'm not better ſtored for you. If you had tooke me comming from terme, I could haue ſerued your turnes better.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Valen.</speaker>
                  <p>Bind them, hamper the rogues. Serue a <hi>Habeas corpus</hi> on that <hi>fieri facies.</hi>
                  </p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Curf.</speaker>
                  <l>How happy were this common wealth! how ſound!</l>
                  <l>If euery corrupt Lawyers fingers were thus bound.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Vast.</speaker>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Sager,</hi> I know thee poore: here take thy purſe.</l>
                  <l>Though I rob theſe, no poore man ſhall me curſe.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Val.</speaker>
                  <p>Tarry till I lay the Lawyer in the midſt of his clients.</p>
                  <p>Are your talons bound <hi>Harpy?</hi> Thou lieſt now like a Stallion new gelt, betwixt two Mares. This is a Diſtring is, ſirrah.</p>
                  <p>Farewell pettie-fogger.</p>
                  <stage>Secedunt fures.</stage>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Grif.</speaker>
                  <p>Oh neighbours, I'am vndone, vndone.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Brom.</speaker>
                  <p>Then helpe to vndoe me. Ile haue my action againſt the Rogues.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Sag.</speaker>
                  <l>Stay till you catch them maſter <hi>Bromley.</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>Well, ſomwhat this my falling ſtate releeues:</l>
                  <l>That honeſty ſpeeds well euen amongſt theeues</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Brom.</speaker>
                  <p>Helpe, helpe. Good maſter <hi>Griffin,</hi> your breath's ſtron<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geſt, yawle, yawle. Your tongue could neuer ſtand your Clients in more ſtead.</p>
                  <stage>Enter Vaſters wife.</stage>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Wife.</speaker>
                  <l>I heard this way ſome mans diſtreſſed voyce,</l>
                  <l>Crying for helpe: ſome robbery. Oh tis no wonder!</l>
                  <l>A theefe and bawdy houſe are ne're farre aſunder.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Grif.</speaker>
                  <p>Oh good woman helpe, helpe to vntie vs.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Wif.</speaker>
                  <l>I know 'hem all. Two knaues, one honeſt man.</l>
                  <l>They know not me in this tranſlation.</l>
                  <l>Come Sir, Ile looſe you firſt, helpe you the reſt.</l>
                  <l>Do well to all, but to the good do beſt.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Grif.</speaker>
                  <p>Oh that I had the villaines vpon an execution now.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <pb facs="tcp:16830:13"/>
                  <speaker>Wife.</speaker>
                  <p>Would you turne hang-man, Sir?</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Grif.</speaker>
                  <p>I faith ſweet wench, I would ſhew 'hem the law.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Wife.</speaker>
                  <l>Oh pitie them: neceſſitie has no law.</l>
                  <l>Perhaps want forc'd them; though it was not good.</l>
                  <l>What Horſeleaches are they, that full, ſucke blood!</l>
                  <l>There is an Inne, enter, refreſh your ſelues.</l>
                  <stage>Exeunt.</stage>
                  <l>Their loſſe is money, yet I mone their ſtate.</l>
                  <l>Who pities me moſt, moſt vnfortunate!</l>
                  <l>Robd of a husbands loue, now of himſelfe.</l>
                  <l>How farre is this beyond all loſſe of pelfe!</l>
                  <l>He ſold me hither; may that ſinfull price</l>
                  <l>Of my deepe ſorrow neuer preiudice</l>
                  <l>His happineſſe, what climate euer holds him.</l>
                  <l>Be bleſt, ſweet husband; let my ruine buy</l>
                  <l>Thy wiſhd content, though I forſaken die.</l>
                  <l>This witch has tyr'd me with her cuſtomers,</l>
                  <l>Whom I haue all ſent home with betterd minds.</l>
                  <l>Againſt her vicious will, I force her ſtriue</l>
                  <l>By vertue rather, then by luſt to thriue.</l>
                  <l>I know, I am expected.</l>
                  <stage>Exit.</stage>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Curf.</speaker>
                  <p>The Iackes be now vncag'd, and flutterd hence.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Vaſt.</speaker>
                  <l>(The woman, that releaſd them, I ſhould know.</l>
                  <l>She frees them from this bondage to a worſe.</l>
                  <l>There is no theefe, like whore, to picke the purſe.)</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Val.</speaker>
                  <p>Shall we not ſhift ground?</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Curf.</speaker>
                  <p>By no meanes. A theefes ſafeſt reſidence is in the ſame plat he did the robberie. There, of all places, the Cuckoldly hue will ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer crie after him.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Vaſt.</speaker>
                  <l>When ſhall we ſhare the booties, and be proud,</l>
                  <l>How liberally our diuiſion mounts?</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Curf.</speaker>
                  <p>The daies worke done, we'l caſt vp the accounts.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Val.</speaker>
                  <p>Where's the pettie-foggers Portmanteau?</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Curf.</speaker>
                  <p>Here.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Val.</speaker>
                  <p>Lay't there. So, you ſhall ſee me catch a fat Pickerell, with this Gudgeon preſently. Stand cloſe.</p>
                  <stage>Enter old Gripe, Nice, Thirsty.</stage>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Nic.</speaker>
                  <p>Vncle, vncle, I had a certaine ſcuruy dreame to night.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Grip.</speaker>
                  <p>Dreame? what of dreames? good couſin be not ſo nice.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Nic.</speaker>
                  <p>I dreamt—</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Grip.</speaker>
                  <p>Be hang'd.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <pb facs="tcp:16830:13"/>
                  <speaker>Ni.</speaker>
                  <p>Be you hang'd, Vncle.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Thirst.</speaker>
                  <p>Behang'd both, except I may haue ſome drinke.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Nic.</speaker>
                  <p>Me thought I found a great deale of money.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Gripe.</speaker>
                  <p>I would we had it, couſin, without dreaming.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Thirſt.</speaker>
                  <p>Whoop maſter—no part of my finding.</p>
                  <stage>takes vp the Portmantean</stage>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Grip.</speaker>
                  <p>No matter for a part: all's mine.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Nic.</speaker>
                  <p>Nay, all's mine for dreaming.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Thirſt.</speaker>
                  <p>Nay, all's mine for finding: and Ile keep't.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Val.</speaker>
                  <p>Soft, ſirrah: it lies there for a wager.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Nic.</speaker>
                  <p>What wager, Sir?</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Val.</speaker>
                  <p>Marry, that who euer finds it, ſhall looſe all the money in's purſe.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Nic.</speaker>
                  <p>Ile not meddle with it.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Grip.</speaker>
                  <p>Ile ha' no part in't.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Val.</speaker>
                  <p>Iudgement, Gentlemen: ha' they not loſt the wager?</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Curf.</speaker>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Vaſt.</hi> Loſt, loſt; as ſure as Virginitie; no ſooner laid then loſt.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Val.</speaker>
                  <p>Come then to pay, to pay. (Sure this is <hi>Gripe,</hi> my Bedford-Gowtie-Vſurer. Plague o<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> your ſtilts; what Carpenter ſet 'hem vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>right? not my wimble, I hope.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Nic.</speaker>
                  <p>Oh I am ſpoyld, ſpoyld; this tis to dreame of ſinding mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ney—I knew, what twould come to.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Thirst.</speaker>
                  <p>Saue your labour, good maſter Theefe: for my breeches are ith' faſhion, a great deale of pocket, but no lining.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Vaſt.</speaker>
                  <l>This is the rocke that ſplit me. Oh good fate!</l>
                  <l>That thou hadſt now about thee halfe my ſtate.</l>
                  <l>Is't ſinne to rob the Theefe? by vſurious courſe,</l>
                  <l>He once robd me, now I rob him by force.</l>
                  <l>No difference but this, twixt him and me.</l>
                  <l>I ha' not ſuch protection, as had he.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Grip.</speaker>
                  <p>Oh I am a poore man, a verie poore man.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Vaſt.</speaker>
                  <l>Thou art indeed; wealth without vſe doth free</l>
                  <l>No ſoule from the bleake ſtormes of pouertie.</l>
                  <l>Who cannot natures requeſts ſatisfie</l>
                  <l>Out of his wealth, his coffer's rich, not he.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Val.</speaker>
                  <p>Be they all bound to the good forberance?</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Vaſt.</speaker>
                  <l>Thus farre quits my reuenge. The Vſurer lies,</l>
                  <l>As faſt in mine, as <hi>I</hi> am in his tyes.</l>
                  <l>Now let me kill him. No, bloud ſhall not die</l>
                  <l>
                     <pb facs="tcp:16830:14"/>
My other ſinnes in purple. Lye there. Loe!</l>
                  <l>That the wiſe lawe would ſerue all vſurers ſo.</l>
                  <l>How few in thy bonds didſt thou ere vntie?</l>
                  <l>Now bound thy ſelfe, ſo without mercy lie.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Curf.</speaker>
                  <p>Come, let's retire to our refuge.</p>
                  <stage>Secedunt.</stage>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Nic.</speaker>
                  <p>Vncle, vncle. I would this all were but a dreame too.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Grip.</speaker>
                  <l>Oh coz, I am damnd, damnd, my mony's gone.</l>
                  <l>Elſtow morgage is loſt. Wallow to me, <hi>Nice.</hi>
                  </l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Nic.</speaker>
                  <p>Oh vncle, its dangerous tumbling, ſnakes i' the graſſe.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Grip.</speaker>
                  <p>Wallow to me, <hi>Thirſty.</hi>
                  </p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Thirſt.</speaker>
                  <p>Maſter, I'm ſo drie, I cannot ſtirre my feet.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Grip.</speaker>
                  <p>Helpe.—</p>
                  <stage>Enter Vasters wife.</stage>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Wife.</speaker>
                  <l>More robberies yet? tis ſtrange, how villains ſwarme!</l>
                  <l>Miſchiefes hold cloſe to keepe each other warme.</l>
                  <l>Three ranke corruptions make their neere abode.</l>
                  <l>An Abby, Bawd'houſe, and a Theeuiſh rode.</l>
                  <l>Where be theſe men diſtreſſed?—how? my Vſurer?</l>
                  <l>Shall I vnbind him, that hath bound my husband</l>
                  <l>In mercileſſe fetters? Yes, I'm bidden, ſtill;</l>
                  <l>With good deeds to requite my enemies ill.</l>
                  <l>Come, diuell, Ile vnloſe thee.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Grip.</speaker>
                  <l>Oh how I'm croſt!</l>
                  <l>My mony, and my morgage, all, all loſt.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Nic.</speaker>
                  <p>Maſſe, a prety wench—If ſhe lay thus bound before mee, I would not looſe her, but vpon ſome conditions.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Wife.</speaker>
                  <p>VVill you go in Sir, and refreſh your ſelfe?</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Grip.</speaker>
                  <p>Ile follow thee, ſweete girle. Would I could cope This morgage, though my other be paſt hope.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Thirſt.</speaker>
                  <p>Doe they brew wine here?</p>
                  <stage>Exeunt</stage>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Vaſt.</speaker>
                  <l>See how this woman ſtill me quits, and croſſes.</l>
                  <l>I rob and binde, and ſhe releeues their loſſes.</l>
                  <l>Why doth ſhe thus? Its but a tricke of hers:</l>
                  <l>By charitie to draw in cuſtomers.</l>
                  <l>I am now patient, but more Cuckold ſtill.</l>
                  <l>I helpe her to ſupply, gainſt my owne will.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <pb facs="tcp:16830:14"/>
                  <speaker>Curf.</speaker>
                  <p>Shall we retire to my chamber, and ſhare?</p>
                  <stage>Enter Beniamin.</stage>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Val.</speaker>
                  <p>Tarry. Here comes another Iack-daw: let's plucke him, and take his feathers with vs—ſtand.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Ben.</speaker>
                  <p>Thou durſt not ſay ſo, were we on iuſt tearmes.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Valen.</speaker>
                  <p>You ſhould bee ſome Lawyer, you ſtand ſo on your termes</p>
                  <p>Faith, we muſt change profeſſions with you, you muſt giue's our fees.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Ben.</speaker>
                  <p>Youle earne them firſt?</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Val.</speaker>
                  <l>Braue Sir, ſo do not Lawyers alwayes.</l>
                  <l>But when you'r payd your ſelfe, you'l giue's our due.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Vast.</speaker>
                  <p>Hold, Gentlemen, this is my friend.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Curf.</speaker>
                  <p>Thine, noble <hi>Valoys?</hi> thou ſhalt begge hisranſome then.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>aſt.</speaker>
                  <p>Hee ſtands ſecure. Haſte to your chamber. There Ile meet you preſently, and then wee'l ſhare.</p>
                  <stage>Exeunt.</stage>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Ben.</speaker>
                  <l>Are thy ends good in this giuen libertie?</l>
                  <l>Or doſt it here alone to murder me?</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>aſt.</speaker>
                  <p>Not with my ſword, but with a tale ſhall wound thy a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mazed heart—come, let's ſit downe.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Ben.</speaker>
                  <l>What tale? good friend, be plaine and ſhort.</l>
                  <l>Woe to a heart, by expectation centuples the ſmart.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Vaſt.</speaker>
                  <p>I haue commendations to you from one <hi>Vaster:</hi> For by's deſcription you ſhould be the man.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Ben.</speaker>
                  <p>Liues <hi>Vaster</hi> then?</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Vaſt.</speaker>
                  <l>'Las Sir, you know he's dead.</l>
                  <l>And by your bloudy hand was murdered.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Ben.</speaker>
                  <p>By me?</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Vaſt.</speaker>
                  <p>Is not your name Sir <hi>Beniamin Gripe!</hi>
                  </p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Ben.</speaker>
                  <p>What then?</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Vaſt.</speaker>
                  <l>You kill'd him, Sir. Poore man he dy'd</l>
                  <l>With penitence to heauen, to you remiſsion.</l>
                  <l>Sayd, that you did it like a man, prouok'd</l>
                  <l>By his intemperate rage. Fate gaue that I</l>
                  <l>Keeping his walke, came to cloſe vp his eye.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Ben.</speaker>
                  <p>Heauen pardon me. What ſayd the dying <hi>Vaſter?</hi>
                  </p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <pb facs="tcp:16830:15"/>
                  <speaker>Vaſt.</speaker>
                  <l>He charg'd me ſeeke you out, and gaue me gold,</l>
                  <l>To bury him in ſecret; leſt his death</l>
                  <l>Should hazard yours, and charm'd my ſilent breath.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Ben.</speaker>
                  <l>His loue giues fire to my greene pile of ſorrowes.</l>
                  <l>May his bones reſt in peace: in griefe I liue;</l>
                  <l>Leſſe he and heauen do my blacke fault forgiue.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Vaſter.</speaker>
                  <l>He hath forgiuen you, only this he begges;</l>
                  <l>That to the ſcatter'd pieces of himſelfe,</l>
                  <l>Left to ſuruiue his miſeries vncomplete,</l>
                  <l>His Widow and his Orphans, you would yeeld</l>
                  <l>Some pittie for your owne, heauens, and his ſake:</l>
                  <l>And teach that hand, (from which he hop'd ſome good)</l>
                  <l>To ſuccour theirs, that tooke away his blood.</l>
                  <l>He bad me tell you, now all meanes were gone,</l>
                  <l>To expiate that ſinne, ſaue only one:</l>
                  <l>To hold thoſe vp, that on the worlds ſea ſwimme:</l>
                  <l>Since he had them vndone, you vndone him.</l>
                  <l>That you would be to them, as he ſhould be:</l>
                  <l>This he bequeath'd you as a Legacie.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Ben.</speaker>
                  <l>Ile be a iuſt Executor of his will.</l>
                  <l>Good friend, great thankes: my purſe th'haſt ſpar'd to ceaz</l>
                  <l>But what is worſe, haſt robb'd me of my peace.</l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>
                        <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>aſter,</hi> th'art dead: if thy transformed ſoule,</l>
                  <l>Could from the battlements of you high Tower,</l>
                  <l>Behold the vow'd endeuours of my heart,</l>
                  <l>To ſatisfie thy will and my huge debt,</l>
                  <l>In thee, to thine, thou wouldſt my merit ſet</l>
                  <l>'Mongſt thy beſt friends: yet narrow are my bounds;</l>
                  <l>To giue them plaiſters, that firſt gaue them wounds.</l>
                  <stage>Exit.</stage>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Vaſt.</speaker>
                  <l>Farewell Sir, thinke on <hi>Vaſter.</hi>
                  </l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Ben.</speaker>
                  <l>Friend adieu. To <hi>Vaſter</hi> and my vowe I will be true.</l>
                  <l>How thicke the ſharpe pulſe of my conſcience beares!</l>
                  <l>How ſtrangely my diſtracted Phantſie threats!</l>
                  <l>Oh vnappeaſed murder, that ſtill keepes</l>
                  <l>The ſenſitiue committer from faſt ſleepes:</l>
                  <l>And murmurs in the eares a fatall knell</l>
                  <l>Of reſtleſſe thoughts on earth, of worſe in hell,</l>
                  <l>How deepe thou ſtrik'ſt me with a ſilent blow!</l>
                  <l>
                     <pb facs="tcp:16830:15"/>
Be patient heart, to thy fate humbly bow.</l>
                  <l>Fetch him againe I cannot; oh his ſowne</l>
                  <l>Is too too mortall. Why then hurl'd I downe</l>
                  <l>My ſinking ſpirits? Let me ſlye to mirth,</l>
                  <l>And burden cares with wine, to make them ſinke.</l>
                  <l>The worlds rule is, Who feels the lode of conſcience let him drink.</l>
                  <l>But oh importunate griefe! too hard it is,</l>
                  <l>To counterfet a falſe and forged bliſſe!</l>
                  <l>Yet once Ile force a tryall; I haue here an Inne,</l>
                  <l>I heare and wonder, is turn'd houſe of ſinne.</l>
                  <l>Ile ſee, if the looſe ſprawles, with their ſharpe wit,</l>
                  <l>Can giue my mind a medicine for this fit.</l>
                  <l>Whores I abhorre, as Gardiners Iayes: no matter;</l>
                  <l>Once for experiment, Ile heare them chatter.</l>
                  <stage>Enter Vasters Wife.</stage>
                  <p>Preuention! I thinke here's one of the iourney-women come, to proffer me her ſeruice. Black proſtitution! that any ſuch face ſhould euer waite vpon thee. Siſter, what ſeeke you?</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Wife.</speaker>
                  <l>What is hard to find:</l>
                  <l>An honeſt man, or els my eyes are blinde.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Ben.</speaker>
                  <l>Fut, if I ſay I'm one, I then fall ſhort,</l>
                  <l>Of the occaſion I intend for ſport.</l>
                  <l>I'm ſuch a foole in this <hi>Priapus-rode.</hi>
                  </l>
                  <p>Mee thinks, ſweet-heart, your honeſt-man ſhould bee one, that ſhould pleaſe your appetite, ſtirre your veines, tickle your bloud, and make you laugh delight into your panting ſpleene.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Wife.</speaker>
                  <l>An honeſt diuell.</l>
                  <l>Th'are friends to hell, that tempt weake ſoules to euill.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Ben.</speaker>
                  <l>Come, let me kiſſe thee—ſo: this was with eaſe;</l>
                  <l>Words are ayry ſhades, th'are deeds that pleaſe.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Wife.</speaker>
                  <l>Sir, do not thinke to enter my chaſte fort,</l>
                  <l>Encourag'd by this parle. You preſume—</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Ben.</speaker>
                  <l>Not to vnlocke thy treaſures with ſuch keyes.</l>
                  <l>Gold only can ſurpriſe ſuch holds as theſe.</l>
                  <l>And I haue that will doo 't.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Wife.</speaker>
                  <l>Then vſe it well.</l>
                  <l>How's wealth abus'd, when it conducts to hell!</l>
                  <l>
                     <pb facs="tcp:16830:16"/>
Sir, I will ſet no price on your deſires.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Bon.</speaker>
                  <p>Ile be the franker Pay-maſter.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Wife.</speaker>
                  <l>You muſt: Then pay me for my vertue: ſo Ile<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> take it.</l>
                  <l>What ſtarues luſt, is well bought; not what it feedes.</l>
                  <l>'Tis follies dregges, with coyne to buy ill deedes.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Ben.</speaker>
                  <l>Come, come; why ſhould you be ſo quaint, and nice,</l>
                  <l>That know what belongs to 't? 'Dsſo, a Virgin</l>
                  <l>At thirteene, or perhaps a little vnder,</l>
                  <l>Could not with whuling nay's be ſo peruerſe,</l>
                  <l>In her beworded Mayden-head.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Wif.</speaker>
                  <p>I muſt.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Ben.</speaker>
                  <l>Thou doſt not rightly of my merits deeme.</l>
                  <l>I would not know you ſuch, as you now ſeeme.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Ben.</speaker>
                  <l>The golden footed law, that goes or runs,</l>
                  <l>Staies, and turnes backe, as we giue motion to it,</l>
                  <l>Shall ſtep the paſe, which thou would'ſt haue it. Nay,</l>
                  <l>Speake as thy tongue inſtructs it. I will change</l>
                  <l>Thy pouerty to gold, rich robes, a Coach,</l>
                  <l>And prauncing Courſers, that ſhall whirle thee through</l>
                  <l>The popular ſtreets; and when thou ſitſt in pride,</l>
                  <l>The tamed law ſhall lacquay by thy ſide.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Wife.</speaker>
                  <l>Theſe are ſome incitations to a heart</l>
                  <l>Tainted with malice, or that thinkes a heauen</l>
                  <l>In glorious oſtentation; or would ſtand</l>
                  <l>Affected with the bane of prurient luſt.</l>
                  <l>I'm of another temper. Pray you leaue me.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Ben.</speaker>
                  <l>Thou ſhalt <hi>Nectar</hi> drinke:</l>
                  <l>Make ebrious waſte of the ſweet Gnoſſian wines;</l>
                  <l>Feſants ſhall be courſe dyet: refin'd marow,</l>
                  <l>Small pounded nuts, and loſſeng'd <hi>Amylum,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>Scrap'd pearle and date-ſtones ſprinkled on each ſlice,</l>
                  <l>And ſtrew'd with ſugar, like white froſt on yce.</l>
                  <l>Grant me but loue, Ile raine a ſhowre of Gold</l>
                  <l>Into thy lappe, out-ſhining <hi>Ioue,</hi> when he</l>
                  <l>Wrapt in his glory courted <hi>Danae.</hi>
                  </l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Wife.</speaker>
                  <p>Thy language does affright me. Oh my ſtarres!</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Ben.</speaker>
                  <p>O let not teares ſpoile ſuch a beauty. Tell mee; Why ſpill you water like a Crockodile, to captiue mee; that might haue don't with mirth, nimbler then ayre?</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <pb facs="tcp:16830:16"/>
                  <speaker>Wife.</speaker>
                  <p>Sir, I haue no deſire,</p>
                  <p>To take your luſt, but pittie. Some what prompts my credulous heart, there is ſome goodneſſe in you.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Ben.</speaker>
                  <p>My truth ſhall quite thy faith, Impart thy mind.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Wife.</speaker>
                  <p>Ile truſt you, Sir. I am a wretched woman,</p>
                  <p>The widow or the wife, I know not whether, of the diſtreſſed or dead <hi>Vaſter.</hi>
                  </p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Ben.</speaker>
                  <l>How? I faint to tell thee; thou art then a widow:</l>
                  <l>The warres haue ended his infortunate dayes.</l>
                  <l>Nay, let not griefe oppreſſe thy ſpirits. Oh,</l>
                  <l>I haue kill'd the wife and husband with one blow.</l>
                  <l>Lift vp thy ſowning eyes.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Wife.</speaker>
                  <p>Oh let me dye. Rather ſhort death, then lingring miſerie.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Ben.</speaker>
                  <l>Reuiue thy heart: <hi>Vaſter</hi> yet liues in me:</l>
                  <l>I am his ſonne, that hath thy husbands lands.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Wife.</speaker>
                  <p>And can I looke for mercy at your hands?</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Ben.</speaker>
                  <p>Receiue this earneſt; all my ſtate is thine.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Wife.</speaker>
                  <p>You cannot with theſe ſpels charme me to ſinne.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Ben.</speaker>
                  <l>I do not: when I taint thy chaſter eares</l>
                  <l>With motions of blacke luſt, pronounce me Villaine.</l>
                  <l>Tell me, who brought you to this Brothell-Inne?</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Wife.</speaker>
                  <l>He, to whom heauen (I truſt) hath clear'd all ſin.</l>
                  <l>My <hi>Vaſter</hi> ſold me hither. I was content.</l>
                  <l>Thus to relieue his ſtate, when all was ſpent.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Ben.</speaker>
                  <p>But couldſt thou liue infectleſſe in this ayre?</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Wife.</speaker>
                  <p>I haue, and will.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Ben.</speaker>
                  <p>Will? This giues ſtrange ſuſpicion.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Wife.</speaker>
                  <l>I made a promiſe, that without conſent</l>
                  <l>Of her that bought me, <hi>I</hi> would not depart.</l>
                  <stage>Enter Mar-mayde.</stage>
                  <l>See where th' Inchantreſſe comes.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Marm.</speaker>
                  <p>Now minion, you muſt be gadding. Cry you mercie, Land-lord: if you'l haue any ſport, walke in, walke in. You ſhall take out your rent here, Land-lord. She ſhall be your own Vaca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion and Terme too, Land-lord.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Ben.</speaker>
                  <l>So, you pernicious Damme of luſts foule littour,</l>
                  <l>You that buy beauty and do ſell 't againe;</l>
                  <l>
                     <pb facs="tcp:16830:17"/>
And liue by th'occupation. Heare you? Free</l>
                  <l>This woman from your brothell ſlauerie.</l>
                  <l>Or I ſhall bring you to the cart and laſh.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Marm.</speaker>
                  <p>Oh I am caſt away; ſhe coſt me fifty pounds, I ne're got foure grotes by her yet.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Ben.</speaker>
                  <p>Thou ſhalt loſe more by keeping her. Goe cleanſe the houſe from this diſorder, or I here diſcharge thee.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Marm.</speaker>
                  <p>Good Land-lord, beſtow her where you will. I am content to be rid of her, ſo I may hold your fouour—</p>
                  <l>Foxe pull your honeſty. Is this the dancing mayde?</l>
                  <l>One more ſuch purchaſe will vndoe my trade.</l>
                  <stage>Enter Gripe.</stage>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Grip.</speaker>
                  <p>Hoſtice, Oſtice, wher's your kinſwoman?</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Marm.</speaker>
                  <p>Yonder Sir, talking with my Land-lord, your Wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhips ſonne.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Gripe.</speaker>
                  <p>Son <hi>Benlamin?</hi> yea faith, are you ſo cloſe with a wench? Come hither—ſhe's a whore, Take heed on her.</p>
                  <stage>Exit Mar.</stage>
                  <l>If ſhe want mennes, bring her home: ſhe ſhall keep my houſe.</l>
                  <l>Faith, I grow old, and cannot now long liue:</l>
                  <l>Oh ſuch a Wench would be reſtoratiue</l>
                  <l>Perſwade her <hi>Ben.</hi>
                  </l>
                  <stage>Exit Gripe.</stage>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Ben.</speaker>
                  <l>Ile do my beſt, Sir<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> See,</l>
                  <l>The pleaſed fates conſent to ſuccour thee.</l>
                  <l>My fathers houſe ſhall ſhelter thee vnknowne.</l>
                  <l>Pleaſe the old man with words, but hold your owne.</l>
                  <l>If my plot takes, as I can hope no leſſe,</l>
                  <l>This luſt of his ſhall thy good fortunes bleſſe.</l>
               </sp>
            </div>
            <div n="3" type="act">
               <head>Act. Tertius.</head>
               <stage>Enter Robert Vaſter, and Anne.</stage>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Rob.</speaker>
                  <l>COme, ſiſter to my ſorrowes, and my ſelfe.</l>
                  <l>They ſay, ſociety in woes doth lighten</l>
                  <l>Our preſſures; but I finde the contrary.</l>
                  <l>My woes are heauier by thy companie</l>
                  <l>My griefe for thy diſtreſſe, doubles mine owne.</l>
                  <l>I ſhould be farre leſſe wretched, if alone.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <pb facs="tcp:16830:17"/>
                  <speaker>Ann.</speaker>
                  <p>Sweet brother. ſince we muſt both ſuffer, thinke it ſome comfort, that we ſhare an equall fortune.</p>
                  <l>Griefe has leſſe power to worke on our ſad hearts;</l>
                  <l>Where mutuall loues contend to beare their parts.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Rob.</speaker>
                  <l>Little once thought thy mother, that thy fate</l>
                  <l>Should ſtoope to ſeruice to relieue thy ſtate:</l>
                  <l>We are not try'd, but in our miſerie.</l>
                  <l>He is a cunning Coach-man that can turne</l>
                  <l>Well in a narrow roome. To manage plenty</l>
                  <l>In a right forme, commends the ſtate, not perſon.</l>
                  <l>Hee's bleſt, that to be rich can giue conſent</l>
                  <l>With honeſtie, or reſt poore with content.</l>
                  <l>I wonder, <hi>Benjamin</hi> doth not viſit vs.</l>
                  <l>His laſt reliefe is done, if that ſpring drye,</l>
                  <l>We faint for ſuccour, and muſt fainting dye.</l>
                  <stage>Enter Bromley.</stage>
                  <p>See, here comes <hi>Bromloy,</hi> once our fathers Steward: Sure, hee'l ſupport vs. Siſter, cry his kindneſſe: thy ſpeech is more pathetical.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Brom.</speaker>
                  <p>Theeues, Lawyers, Rogues, Harlots, and Inne-keepers, are mens purgations. <hi>Griffin</hi> has cheated mee: tooke twenty an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gels from me; theeues tooke 'hem from him. He promis'd to draw <hi>Sager</hi> to compound; now the day's gone againſt me.</p>
                  <l>Oh I could wiſh my nailes turn'd Vulturos tallons,</l>
                  <l>That I might teare their fleſh in mammocks, raiſe</l>
                  <l>My loſſes from their carcaſes turn'd Mummy.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Ann.</speaker>
                  <p>Good Sir, a word—</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Brom.</speaker>
                  <p>Now Kitlin, what would you haue?</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Ann.</speaker>
                  <p>Sir, remember we are the miſerable children of loſt <hi>
                        <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ster;</hi> whom once you ſeru'd.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Brom.</speaker>
                  <p>What's that to me?</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Ann.</speaker>
                  <p>I hope, Sir, you can ſpare ſomewat to vs diſtreſſed.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Brom.</speaker>
                  <l>This is plaine begging. Minion, fall to worke,</l>
                  <l>And earne ſupply to wants with diligent labour.</l>
                  <l>For <hi>Vaſters</hi> ſake I will not vrge the Statute.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Rob.</speaker>
                  <l>The Statute, <hi>Iudas?</hi> w' are no Beggers, though</l>
                  <l>We try'd thy courteſie. Curſed be thy fate,</l>
                  <l>Thou from our father gott'ſt thy whole eſtate.</l>
                  <p>
                     <pb facs="tcp:16830:18"/>
Yet grudgeſt vs ſome fragments. Hence, out Dogge: If thou ſtay'ſt miſcreant—</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Brom.</speaker>
                  <p>Boy, Ile ſmoke you for't.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Rob.</speaker>
                  <p>Do thy worſt, diuell. An inſatiate worme ſtrike deepe in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to thy conſcience, ſile thy heart ſtrings with rubbing flets: And turne thy derogated name,</p>
                  <l>On foggy blaſtings of eternall ſhame.</l>
                  <stage>Exit.</stage>
                  <stage>Enter Gripe.</stage>
                  <l>Ingratitude is gone; and in his roome,</l>
                  <l>Extortion and a fiend is hith or come.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Grip.</speaker>
                  <p>I'm going to ſee my morgage—</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Ann.</speaker>
                  <p>Good Sir, ſhew mercy on two wretched Orphans.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Grip.</speaker>
                  <p>Out beggers, mercie? what doſt talke to me of mercy? I'm going to let my grounds. I haue no leaſure for mercy.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Rob.</speaker>
                  <l>Goe thou accurſed <hi>Cain:</hi> in miſerie,</l>
                  <l>When thou begg'ſt mercy, be't as farre from thee.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Ann.</speaker>
                  <p>Sir, y' have vndone our Parents; pittie vs.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Grip.</speaker>
                  <p>I cannot ſtay to heare you, I haue buſineſſe.</p>
                  <stage>Exit.</stage>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Rob.</speaker>
                  <l>Heauen be as deafe to thee, when thy ſoule breath</l>
                  <l>Shall begge ſome reſpite at thy violent death.</l>
                  <stage>Enter Nice.</stage>
                  <l>This fellow ſure will ſuccour vs.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Nic.</speaker>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Iune, Iuly, August, September—</hi>the firſt day—</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Ann.</speaker>
                  <p>Sir, raiſe our proſtrate fortunes with ſome helpe: Some little helpe, you know vs.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>N<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>c.</speaker>
                  <p>Yes, yes, I remember I haue ſeene you. Let's ſee—The fourteenth day—bad. <hi>I</hi> muſt do no deed of charitie to day; I haue preſident for it. 't is loſt.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Rob.</speaker>
                  <l>Now I remember, when I went to ſchoole,</l>
                  <l>I read of one <hi>Veſpaſian</hi> a good Emperour,</l>
                  <l>That told his Courtiers if a day out-ſlipt him,</l>
                  <l>Wherein he did nor good, that day was loſt.</l>
                  <l>The next he would redeem't with double coſt.</l>
                  <l>Ill colour'd ſinne, how ſhamefull doſt thou looke,</l>
                  <l>In them that plead thy warrant from their booke!</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Nic.</speaker>
                  <p>Fourteenth day. A good turne forgotten. Oh heres lear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning from the ſtarres.</p>
                  <l>
                     <pb facs="tcp:16830:18"/>
Though I do little good ere I am rotten,</l>
                  <l>Like citizens, I would not ha't forgotten.</l>
                  <l>Yet let me ſtudy on't: though a man may not giue, he</l>
                  <l>May buy, I hope without danger. Faire ſiſter,</l>
                  <l>What ſhall I giue you for your maiden-head?</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Rob.</speaker>
                  <p>Thus much: a broken head.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Ni.</speaker>
                  <p>Oh—Oh—Forgiue me, good Calender—I perceiue now, thy counſel's true. It's an euil day indeed: I ſhould neither haue bought nor ſold on't.</p>
                  <stage>Exi.</stage>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Rob.</speaker>
                  <l>Hence, skie-conſulting Gypſie: men commit</l>
                  <l>Sinnes darke as night, and blame the ſtarres for it.</l>
                  <stage>Enter Sager.</stage>
                  <l>Another paſſenger—Oh this is <hi>Sager.</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>His wife was once a ſeruant to our mother.</l>
                  <l>Alas, when theſe built from our ruinous woe</l>
                  <l>Releeue vs not, what ſhould this poore man doe.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Sag.</speaker>
                  <l>I long to heare from London; how my ſuite</l>
                  <l>Ends, or depends: if loſt, I'm loſt with it.</l>
                  <l>Who would truſt any barres this tottring world</l>
                  <l>Can plot to fortiſie our wheeling ſtates!</l>
                  <l>When the ſtrong dores of Iuſtice may be broke,</l>
                  <l>Or lifted from the hinges by the force</l>
                  <l>Of politike engines: or the ſafeſt locke</l>
                  <l>Be pickt with a falſe key.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>An.</speaker>
                  <p>Sir, dwels there any mercie in your heart?</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Sag.</speaker>
                  <p>Yes: or of mercy, I muſt hope no part.</p>
                  <p>I know you, and your wants. My wife was once your Parents ſeruant.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>An.</speaker>
                  <l>True, but that time is paſt,</l>
                  <l>And in her ſeruice now I would be plac't.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Sag.</speaker>
                  <l>That were too lauiſh yeelding to your woe.</l>
                  <l>I am but poore, troubles haue made me ſo,</l>
                  <l>Yet of that ſmall life-blood, which my drencht ſtate</l>
                  <l>H'as left it by the Lawes ſharpe ſurgerie,</l>
                  <l>Embrace a portion, as your needs require;</l>
                  <stage>Enter Beniamin.</stage>
                  <l>And I may giue. Here comes your enemies Sonne.</l>
                  <pb facs="tcp:16830:19"/>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Ben.</speaker>
                  <l>I haue bene ſeeking all you three with nowes.</l>
                  <l>Good newes; friend <hi>Sager,</hi> the day's yours.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Sag.</speaker>
                  <p>It's welcome. I haue the better meanes to ſuccour theſe.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Ben.</speaker>
                  <l>You haue preuented my requeſt: I purpos'd</l>
                  <l>To beg that kindneſſe of you. <hi>Robin,</hi> I would</l>
                  <l>Intreat you to accept my ſeruice, but</l>
                  <l>I meane the name of it: for in deed Ile vſe thee</l>
                  <l>As my moſt equall and reſpected friend.</l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Nan,</hi> in thine armes <hi>I</hi> throw and locke my ſelfe;</l>
                  <l>My fortunes be all thine: the key's thy loue;</l>
                  <l>Let this kiſſe be the ſeale. Ye ſacred powers</l>
                  <l>Make indiſſoluble this knot of ours.</l>
                  <l>Now, maſter <hi>Sager,</hi> giue her that reſpect,</l>
                  <l>You would my wife: all charges are my debt.</l>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Robin,</hi> you know the houſe; conduct your ſiſter thither; that done, conucy theſe letters to the widdow <hi>Sorrow;</hi> (that's her borrowed name) ſhe lies at my fathers.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Rob.</speaker>
                  <l>With iuſt hands.</l>
                  <l>I'm prouder of thy loue, then of thy lands.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Ann.</speaker>
                  <l>Oh pure quinteſſence of thy profeſſion.</l>
                  <l>How many haſt thou robd, thus to make vp</l>
                  <l>Thy perfect godneſſe! as if wiſer nature</l>
                  <l>Had made an extract of ten thouſand Lawyers,</l>
                  <l>And thriſe refin'd it with immortall fires:</l>
                  <l>Then ſet it like a ſanctified Lampe</l>
                  <l>On th' Altar of thy ſoule; to giue exemplar light,</l>
                  <l>In the dull darkeneſſe of this ſinne-borne night.</l>
                  <stage>Exeunt.</stage>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Ben.</speaker>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Bromley</hi>'s growne mad with rage: I'm iealous of him. You know the hopes of your poſteritie dwell on your preſent fortunes: all which burne with the ſhort Taper of your ſingular life, Say he ſhould quench it.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Sag.</speaker>
                  <p>How Sir? murder me?</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Ben.</speaker>
                  <l>I cannot tell, it's but my iclaouſie.</l>
                  <l>Tis not amiſſe, to keepe preuentions eye</l>
                  <l>Open and wary. Inſtruments of death</l>
                  <l>Stand ready preſt to a malicious arme.</l>
                  <l>And policie, like a cunning Ieſuite,</l>
                  <l>Watches behind that Arras for a call.</l>
                  <l>
                     <pb facs="tcp:16830:19"/>
The deed once done, helpe it who can, or ſhall.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Sag.</speaker>
                  <p>What ground for this ſuſpition find your thoughts?</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Ben.</speaker>
                  <l>The fury of his madneſſe, Enuies ſome,</l>
                  <l>That ſurges from the poyſon'd auarice</l>
                  <l>Of his ſwolne heart: his broken reſolutions,</l>
                  <l>Wherein his traitor-tongue can ſcarce forbeare</l>
                  <l>The proteſtation. Giue me leaue to feare.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Sag.</speaker>
                  <p>What will you counſell me?</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Ben.</speaker>
                  <p>That muſt be ſtudy'd. Thus—Liſten—We'll trie what miſcheefes he can warpe: With woodden waſters learne to play at ſharpe.</p>
                  <stage>Exit Sager.</stage>
                  <stage>Enter Gripe, Nice, Thirsty.</stage>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Grip.</speaker>
                  <p>Oh my backe, my backe—</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Ben.</speaker>
                  <p>How do you, Sir?</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Grip.</speaker>
                  <p>Oh ſonne, ſonne, worſe then euer. The Gowt was but a ſtitch to this. Oh the Collicke, the Collicke and ſtone.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Thirst.</speaker>
                  <p>There be two of them maſter, aske the widdow elſe.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Grip.</speaker>
                  <p>Sure it will rend my bowels out.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Ben.</speaker>
                  <p>It's iuſt: The ſtone ith' bladder now ſhould make him ſmart That has ſo long bene ſicke of ſtone ith' heart.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Grip.</speaker>
                  <p>Oh that I knew where my old Phyſician liu'd.</p>
                  <stage>Enter Vaster and Curfew.</stage>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Vaſt.</speaker>
                  <p>Keepe on your habite. Our walke's turn'd Pouls, I thinke.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Curf.</speaker>
                  <p>Zlid, if our third party were here, wee would venter on 'hem all. Th'are but welſh freeze; they would ſhrinke at the ſenſe of yron.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>aſt.</speaker>
                  <l>Let's muffle vp our villaines with the ſhadow</l>
                  <l>Of ſome great conference: if a cheate be offer'd,</l>
                  <l>We'll not refuſe: but now to compaſſe it,</l>
                  <l>Muſt not be done by force of armes, but wit.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Grip.</speaker>
                  <l>Sonne <hi>Beniamin,</hi> you muſt to Goldington,</l>
                  <l>To view yong <hi>Bruſters</hi> lands: th'are offer'd me</l>
                  <l>This morne in morgage. Harke you—</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Nic.</speaker>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Thirſty,</hi> come hither.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Thirſt.</speaker>
                  <p>Ha'you any drink there?</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Nic.</speaker>
                  <p>No; but come drinke thy ſelfe drunke with Poetrie.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Thirſt.</speaker>
                  <p>Faith, Poetrie now a daies will ſcarce make a man drink. <hi>I</hi> had as liefe be a pot as a Poet: then I ſhould ſometimes be full of good liquour.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <pb facs="tcp:16830:20"/>
                  <speaker>Nic.</speaker>
                  <p>Oh, your Poet is too full of that, it makes him thred bare. Sirrah, I ha'made a Sonnet here to my Miſtreſſe; ſhe n'ere wrought ſuch a one on her Samplar. Lay thine eare cloſe to my muſicall tongue, I ſhall rauiſh her.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Thirst.</speaker>
                  <p>You ſhall be hang'd for't then.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Ni.</speaker>
                  <l>Open thine eares, like an Oyſter a ſunning</l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Euen as the bird, which we Camelion call, doth liue on aire for aye:</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>So my kinde heart, euer like a stocke-Doue ſhall feede on thy loue all day.</hi>
                  </l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Thirſt.</speaker>
                  <p>I, and all night too.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Nic.</speaker>
                  <p>I, and all night too: but that night would make the verſe too long. Now I talke of night, let me ſee what time of day it is. I haue buſineſſe, muſt not be rim'd away.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Curf.</speaker>
                  <p>Pray y' Sir, how ſpeakes your watch? One? mine lies in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clining to two You haue a prettie interpreter of the time there. Who made it, French or Dutch? You need not doubt me, Sir, I am the new Parſon of Saint <hi>Peters</hi> in Bedford.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Nic.</speaker>
                  <p>Sir, then as I may ſay, haue ioy in your new Benefice, for bel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly-peece you muſt ha'none. Pray' lets peruſe your watch, ſee you mine.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Vaſt.</speaker>
                  <p>Fezz 'Sir, y' haue a braue waſh there. Chill warrant the Kings waſh-maker made it. Beſeech you mozter <hi>Nice,</hi> let me ſee maſter Parſon waſh. Maſter Paſon will you zell your waſh, chill giue you good caſh for it.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Curf.</speaker>
                  <p>No, my honeſt friend, I will not ſell it.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Vaſt.</speaker>
                  <p>Will you runne with me for it?</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Grif.</speaker>
                  <p>Runne? no.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Vaſt.</speaker>
                  <p>Cheuore ye runne for't, you ſhall nere ha't elſe.</p>
                  <stage>Excurrit.</stage>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Curf.</speaker>
                  <p>Oh my watch<hi>—Nic.</hi> Oh my watch.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Curf.</speaker>
                  <p>Stop the theefe, ſtop the theefe.</p>
                  <stage>Vaſter runs away with Curfews watch: Cur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>few with Nices.</stage>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Nic.</speaker>
                  <p>Stop the Prieſt, ſtop the Prieſt.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Thirſt.</speaker>
                  <p>Let him go, he runs for a wager.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Ben.</speaker>
                  <l>How now? is my couſin <hi>Nice</hi> playing at Bace?</l>
                  <l>I know one of them well, by his ſad tale</l>
                  <l>Of <hi>Vaſters</hi> death: for that Ile not purſue him.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Grip.</speaker>
                  <l>Son, I did reſt me, hoping to go forward.</l>
                  <l>But ſo increaſe my paines, I am not able.</l>
                  <l>Suruey you <hi>Bruſters</hi> lands, and ſpeed returne.</l>
                  <l>
                     <pb facs="tcp:16830:20"/>
All's for your good, for I am now out-worne.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Ben.</speaker>
                  <l>I goe Sir—All's for me; yet whileshe liues,</l>
                  <l>And his hydroppicke ſpirits can looke through</l>
                  <l>His bodies loope-holes, and conuey the pleaſure</l>
                  <l>Of his contemplate gold, his luſts ſole God,</l>
                  <l>Through thoſe windowes to th' admiring heart:</l>
                  <l>Nothing comes from him; not the ſuperfluities</l>
                  <l>Of baſers things, not being firſt improu'd.</l>
                  <l>I am his onely iſſue, and on me</l>
                  <l>I thinke he meanes to ſettle all his ſtate.</l>
                  <l>It's the onely way to giue me curſt and poore,</l>
                  <l>To build my neſt on ſuch extorted ſtore.</l>
                  <l>Thoſe fathers, that diſtreſſ'd mens ruines vſe,</l>
                  <l>" As ſcaffolds to build vp their racked wealth,</l>
                  <l>" Proue in the end, like citie-houſes, that</l>
                  <l>" On ſmall foundations carry ſpacious roofes:</l>
                  <l>" When the incenſed heauens in tempeſts frowne,</l>
                  <l>" Their owne top-heauy weight tumbles them downe.</l>
                  <l>" The firſt or ſecond generation ſpils</l>
                  <l>" By ryot, what by wrong the father fils.</l>
                  <l>In this Ile be a mirror to theſe times:</l>
                  <l>And by the hand of charitie returne</l>
                  <l>To euery man, what by his couetous rape</l>
                  <l>Their ſtates are rauiſh'd of: ſo worke my reſt.</l>
                  <l>Th'ill gotten gone, that which remaines is bleſt.</l>
                  <stage>Exit.</stage>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Grip.</speaker>
                  <p>Oh <hi>Thirſty,</hi> honeſt <hi>Thirsty.</hi> Thy old maſter is but a dead man. I cannot piſſe man: my vrine's ſtop'd.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Thirſt.</speaker>
                  <p>You ſhould drinke, hard, maſter: all this comes with pinching your ſelfe of your liquour. This is the reaſon, that ſo few Dutchmen are troubled with the ſtone. Your miſerable Churle dribbles like the piſſing Conduit: but his iouiall ſonne with a ſtreame like Ware-water-ſpout. This is the cauſe, the Vſurer falling ſicke, ſo ſeldome riſes by the ſtaffe of Phyſicke: for he has no water for the Phyſician to caſt.</p>
                  <stage>
                     <pb facs="tcp:16830:21"/>
Enter Nice blowing.</stage>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Nic.</speaker>
                  <p>Now the Gowt, Dropſie, Lethargie take poſſeſſion of their legs. I ha'loſt my wind, and my watch, and I feare, my wench too.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Thirſt.</speaker>
                  <p>You haue watch'd faire: ſure that Parſon was ſome Iriſhman.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Nice.</speaker>
                  <p>Some hangman vncaſe him. I ha'bene at the Parſons, and he's no ſuch manner of man.</p>
                  <stage>Enter Marre-maide, Conſtable, with Valentine.</stage>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Grip.</speaker>
                  <p>What crew's this?</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Mar.</speaker>
                  <p>Bleſſe your worſhip: I am your Worſhips ſonnes Tenant. I ha'brought a rogue to your worſhip, to be examin'd.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Grip.</speaker>
                  <p>What fault hath has he committed? Clarke, to your office: take his examination. Now neigbour <hi>Sleepy,</hi> are you Conſtable?</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Thirst.</speaker>
                  <p>A good harmeleſſe Conſtable, a theefe may take him napping.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Marm.</speaker>
                  <p>An't pleaſe your worſhip, the rude Raggamuſſin comes into my houſe, cals for drinke; and when the Tapſter came with a reckoning, he broke the pot about's head; becauſe he had not a cleane Apron on.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Val.</speaker>
                  <p>No, becauſe he miſreckoned me.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Mar.</speaker>
                  <p>Whoſe fault was it, to wipe out the ſcore?</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>al.</speaker>
                  <p>Not mine. Indeede I anointed the ſcore with butter, and the Tapſters owne dog lick't it out.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Nic.</speaker>
                  <p>Vncle, vncle, as ſure as my watch is loſt, this is maſter <hi>Valentine</hi> the Phyſician.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Grip.</speaker>
                  <p>Oh Coz, that it were true. Pray' Sir, let me mooue a queſtion.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Val.</speaker>
                  <p>You may command my anſwer Sir, y' are a Iuſtice.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Grip.</speaker>
                  <p>Were not you the man, that heald me o' the Gowt?</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Val.</speaker>
                  <p>Troth Sir, I haue done ſo many cures, that I forget a number of my patients. Th'other day I cured a lunaticke
<pb facs="tcp:16830:21"/>
Cobler, pitifully run out at ſoule, when hee was giuen ore by the Phyſicians. I let him bloud, tooke three Hen-egges, ſuck'd 'hem out, into the ſhels I put his bloud, ſet them vnder a brood-Gooſe. When ſhe had hatcht the reſt, I gaue theſe three putrified egges to a Dogge: the Dogge grew madde, the Cobler ſober. And now my memorie runs backe, I call to mind one of <hi>Bedford,</hi> ſicke of the Gowt, whom I cured.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Grip.</speaker>
                  <p>I am the man, my renowned Paracelſian: thou ſhalt haue the other 25. pound. Conſtable, I diſcharge you. Oſtice, I'le ſee you payd: ſet your recknoning on my ſcore: trouble me no further: leaue vs, leaue vs. Now my deepe diuer into the ſecrets of nature, I haue a cure for thee, more deſperate then the former.</p>
                  <stage>Exeunt.</stage>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Val.</speaker>
                  <p>What is't Sir, that my Art cannot extend to?</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Grip.</speaker>
                  <p>The ſtone, the ſtone: I am pittifully grip'd with the ſtone, I ha'loſt my piſſing.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Val.</speaker>
                  <l>Sir, the diſeaſe is ſomewhat dangerous.</l>
                  <l>Yet if that your expulſiue facultie</l>
                  <l>Retaine true force, I'le warrant to make you piſſe.</l>
                  <l>I muſt awhile withdraw to ſtudy Sir.—</l>
                  <l>Now am I puzzled: bloud, what medicine</l>
                  <l>Should I deuiſe to do't? It muſt be violent.</l>
                  <l>Giue him ſome <hi>Aqua-fortis;</hi> that would ſpeed him.</l>
                  <l>Let's ſee. Me thinks—a little Gun-powder</l>
                  <l>Should haue ſome ſtrange relation to this fit.</l>
                  <l>I haue ſeene Gun-powder oft driue out ſtones</l>
                  <l>From Forts and Caſtle-walls, huger then he</l>
                  <l>Has any in his reynes or bladder, ſure.</l>
                  <l>Faith,' cauſe I am a ſouldier, i'le make triall</l>
                  <l>Of that ſame blacke and vaporous Minerall.</l>
                  <l>I'le ſhoote into his belly: if the gunne hold,</l>
                  <l>I<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>le giue him charge enough: ſome Aquavitae</l>
                  <l>Firſt brewd together would allay it well.</l>
                  <l>Ile ſweare to try it, if I doe not miſſe,</l>
                  <l>By a ſtrange tricke Ile make my Vſurer piſſe.</l>
                  <l>Sir, Ile goe in and prepare for aou.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Grip.</speaker>
                  <p>Doe ſo. Here, <hi>Thirſty,</hi> there be the Keys of the Buttry:
<pb facs="tcp:16830:22"/>
attend vpon him good <hi>Thirsty:</hi> let him lacke nothing, as thou lou'ſt me.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Thirst.</speaker>
                  <p>I loue you Maſter, but here's a good key <hi>I</hi> loue better. Sweete inſtrument of my ioy, let me kiſſe thee. A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>las, that thou and I ſhould be ſuch ſtrangers. Wee ha' but one barrell: now if that ſhould bee in my maſters diſeaſe, troubled with the ſtrangullion, and could not runne—well, if it bee not emptie, Ile giu't a ſcowring.</p>
                  <stage>Exit.</stage>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Grip.</speaker>
                  <p>Now if this rare wonder of leaches can cure mee of this griping, that I may haue ſome fortie or threeſcore yeares more to gather in, by that time <hi>I</hi> ſhall gather enough to keepe me all the reſt of my life. When a man growes vp to to ſixe or ſeuen ſcore, it is high time to thinke of mortalitie, and to take ſome eaſe. Theſe three or foure nights I ha' bene haunted with Fairies: they dance about my bed-ſide, poppe in a peece of gold betweene the ſheetes, ſcatter here and there fragments of ſiluer, in euery corner. I keepe my cham<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber ſwept, cleane linnen, fire to warme them euery night. I was at firſt a fraide, they had beene ſpirits; now I ſee, they are good harmeleſſe Fairies. If I can pleaſe them, I ſhall grow rich, rich.</p>
                  <p>Sonne I haue ſtayd for you.</p>
                  <stage>Enter Beniamin.</stage>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Ben.</speaker>
                  <p>You haue done your health the more wrong, Sir.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Grip.</speaker>
                  <p>How doſt like my morgage?</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Ben.</speaker>
                  <p>It's a faire liuing, Sir; but I would not haue you med<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dle with it.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Grip.</speaker>
                  <p>Why, my wiſe ſonne?</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Ben.</speaker>
                  <l>Oh Sir, good deeds are ſcant,</l>
                  <l>When we aduantage take of poore mens want.</l>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Bruſter</hi>'s an honeſt man; lend him ſome money without ſuch ſharpe ſecuritie.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Grip.</speaker>
                  <p>Not a doyt. If he come to me, and conuey the morgage I haue it ready; els I haue no money.</p>
                  <p>Sonne come and ſup with me.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <pb facs="tcp:16830:22"/>
                  <speaker>Ben.</speaker>
                  <l>I follow, Sir. Prepoſterous tranſuerſion of our ſelues!</l>
                  <l>Th'erection of our faces ſhould inſtruct</l>
                  <l>Our groueling thoughts t' aſcend. How do men thwart</l>
                  <l>The teaching hand of Nature, and our birth!</l>
                  <l>Our heads cut aire, and yet our hearts plow earth:</l>
                  <l>I looke for <hi>Sager</hi> here. He's come.</l>
                  <stage>
                     <hi>Enter</hi> Sager.</stage>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Sag.</speaker>
                  <p>Heer's my owne caſe and counterfeit; by this danger<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſſe plummet, we may ſound the depth of his more cloſe and intricate ſtratagems.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Ben.</speaker>
                  <l>So wiſer maſters lay ſome eaſie baites,</l>
                  <l>At once to tempt and trie their ſeruants truth.</l>
                  <l>The ſubiect for quack-ſaluing Empirickes</l>
                  <l>To exerciſe their inexperience on,</l>
                  <l>Should not be men, but malkins.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Sag.</speaker>
                  <p>Do you thinke, that he would doe me violence a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſleepe? would he not wake me to ſome conference?</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Ben.</speaker>
                  <l>No, hee's a moſt ranke Coward; and I know,</l>
                  <l>Dares not come neere thee, though thou wert aſleepe.</l>
                  <l>If he does ought, he'l do't by that long Engine.</l>
                  <l>Conceale your ſelfe awhile. How fares my name?</l>
                  <l>How does ſhe brooke my ſlow-pac'd comming to her?</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Sag.</speaker>
                  <l>Faith, in your conſtancie lightens all griefe.</l>
                  <l>She neuer heares you mention'd, but ſhe ſtartles:</l>
                  <l>As if your name like ſome celeſtiall fire</l>
                  <l>Quicken'd her ſlow-pac'd ſpirits with new life.</l>
                  <l>I neuer knew vertue and beauty meete</l>
                  <l>In a more happy mixture. I remoue.</l>
                  <stage>Exit.</stage>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Ben.</speaker>
                  <l>I loue her freely: ſhee's to me as th'ayre.</l>
                  <l>Her beauty is beſt and bleſt, whoſe ſoule is faire.</l>
                  <l>The Wolfe is come.</l>
                  <stage>
                     <pb facs="tcp:16830:23"/>
Enter Bromley with a fowling piece.</stage>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Brom.</speaker>
                  <p>Good euening to you Sir.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Ben.</speaker>
                  <l>My wiſh requite you.</l>
                  <l>You walke to haue a ſhoot, Sir: I depart.</l>
                  <l>I would be loth to preiudice your ſport.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Brom.</speaker>
                  <p>Saw you not M<hi rend="sup">r</hi> 
                     <hi>Sager,</hi> Sir, of late? This is his walke: I would faine ſpeake with him.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Ben.</speaker>
                  <p>Why would you ſpeake with him?</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Brom.</speaker>
                  <p>Sir, for no harme.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Ben.</speaker>
                  <p>I do not thinke you meane it; but you know, hee's valiant like a Lyon: if croſſe words ſhould ſtirre your blouds to quarrell—Sir, take heed. Hee'l be too hard for you, and your long weapon. This medow is his euening walke. Farewell to you Sir.</p>
                  <stage>Exit Ben.</stage>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Brom.</speaker>
                  <l>Good night M. <hi>Beniamin;</hi> you need not doubt me.</l>
                  <l>If I could meet him at th' aduantage now,</l>
                  <l>He is the Fowle I'd ſhoot at. His life done,</l>
                  <l>The Farme is mine. Oh ye, whoſe hopes depend,</l>
                  <l>Like Imgring ſhadowes, on anothers end,</l>
                  <l>What need you waite with patience natures leaſure,</l>
                  <l>When ſuch an engine can ſoone work your pleaſure?</l>
                  <l>Tarry: yonder's a man—now by his habite</l>
                  <l>It ſhould be <hi>Sager.</hi> What? and faſt aſleepe?</l>
                  <l>Wiſh'd opportunity to my reuenge.</l>
                  <l>Ile kill him ere he wakes. Stay, grant he ſhould</l>
                  <l>In this vnbeaten medow lately act</l>
                  <l>Some horrid ſinne, pleaſe his adulterous luſt:</l>
                  <l>I ſhould then with his body ſtrike his ſoule,</l>
                  <l>And ſinke them both together. Reaſon no further</l>
                  <l>Thou chiding conſcience. See, the Fates haue plac't</l>
                  <l>Him ſit for vengeance: enemie, ſleepe thy laſt.</l>
                  <l>Hee's Planet-ſtrucke, falne downe: now to my Farme.</l>
                  <l>He that would riſe, muſt thanke his wit or arme.</l>
                  <l>Oh but my murder! piſh, who euer ſtood</l>
                  <stage>Exit.</stage>
                  <l>In fortunes height, without ſome touch of blood?</l>
                  <stage>
                     <pb facs="tcp:16830:23"/>
Enter Beniamin and Sager at ſeuerall wayes.</stage>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Ben.</speaker>
                  <p>This I diuin'd.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Sag.</speaker>
                  <p>Happy preuention!</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Ben.</speaker>
                  <l>Goe, thou deſpairing wretch, and for thy will,</l>
                  <l>Ten thouſan ſwords ſhall thy vex'd conſcience kill.</l>
                  <l>'T was a vaine blow to vs, and no bloud ſpilt,</l>
                  <l>Not leſſe in thy intention is thy guilt.</l>
                  <l>This Clergy-habite which you haue aſſum'd,</l>
                  <l>Make good a while for your ſuppoſed death;</l>
                  <l>Allow his tyrannie free ſcope: liue cloſe:</l>
                  <l>Till time ſhall ripen thoſe euents, we ſtriue</l>
                  <l>To build on this vile ground. Hold, ther's my key:</l>
                  <l>Into my chamber; I ſup at my fathers.</l>
                  <stage>Exit Sager.</stage>
                  <l>What, come againe?</l>
                  <stage>Enter Bromley.</stage>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Brom.</speaker>
                  <l>I cannot be at reſt: <hi>I</hi> muſt needes ſee,</l>
                  <l>If this late murdered corps remoued be.</l>
                  <l>Some gold I haue put vp in this Portmantua:</l>
                  <l>If I ſhould be purſu'd, this may relieue me.</l>
                  <l>Ay me! the bodi's gone: ſure it's reueal'd:</l>
                  <l>Murder from heauens eye cannot be conceal'd.</l>
                  <l>What ſhall <hi>I</hi> doe? ſit downe: lye there, my gold.</l>
                  <stage>
                     <hi>Enter Nice, and Thirſty, on either ſide, crying</hi> So ho.</stage>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Nic.</speaker>
                  <p>Holla, Couſin <hi>Beniamin.</hi> So ho ho.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Thir.</speaker>
                  <p>Oh ho ho.</p>
                  <stage>excurrit.</stage>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Brom.</speaker>
                  <p>Oh me, the Countrie's vp, what ſhall I do?</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Ben.</speaker>
                  <l>This foole hath frayd him.</l>
                  <l>Oh guilt! how haſt thou made</l>
                  <l>Cowherd of man to fly at his owne ſhade!</l>
                  <l>Now Couſin <hi>Nice,</hi> what holla you for?</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Nic.</speaker>
                  <p>You had need of a bell to ring you in. Your father has ſtayd ſupper for you this houre.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Ben.</speaker>
                  <p>Come then, let's walke on—what's here a Port<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mantua?</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Nic.</speaker>
                  <p>Oh, oh, do not touch it: it's venome.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Ben.</speaker>
                  <p>Why my wiſe Couſin? why are you ſo timorous?</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <pb facs="tcp:16830:24"/>
                  <speaker>Nic.</speaker>
                  <p>Oh it lies there for a wager: there be theeues about it. Take heed Couſin; I found a Portmantua once, and loſt all the money in my purſe. Fly, fly—</p>
                  <stage>Exit.</stage>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Ben.</speaker>
                  <p>Are you gone? Well, I ſee now, hee that will be wiſe by Calender, ſhall be a foole by deſtinie.</p>
                  <l>Sure, this is <hi>Bromleys</hi> budget, and has gold</l>
                  <l>Put vp for his eſcape: 'tis ſo by th'weight.</l>
                  <l>It falls into my hands moſt luckily:</l>
                  <l>For I haue need of caſh in theſe occaſions.</l>
                  <l>Yet Ile repay't againe: my honeſtie</l>
                  <l>Shall be his friend, whoſe feare was friend to me.</l>
                  <l>Oh, in this glaſſe my repreſented ſoule</l>
                  <l>Stands manifeſt to my impartiall eye.</l>
                  <l>Ye heauens rayne ſhowers of mercy on my ſins:</l>
                  <l>Leſt where my pleaſure ends my wo begins.</l>
               </sp>
            </div>
            <div n="4" type="act">
               <head>Act. Quart.</head>
               <stage>Enter Vasters Wife.</stage>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Wife.</speaker>
                  <l>RVnne faſter, ye dull legges of motion,</l>
                  <l>That time may follow with a ſwifter paſe.</l>
                  <l>Let wanton Epicures wiſh you creeple-limbes,</l>
                  <l>Inſatiate with the ryot of their ioyes;</l>
                  <l>And chide the haſty forwardneſſe of day,</l>
                  <l>That will not dance attendance on their play.</l>
                  <l>My ſpirits wrought vpon with tedious woes,</l>
                  <l>Thinke that each houre lingring and lazy goes.</l>
                  <l>Impartiall fates, how you delude our thoughts!</l>
                  <l>Guiding euents to their determin'd ends,</l>
                  <l>Whether our ſtrength with or againſt contends.</l>
                  <l>Whether the paſſenger wake, or ſleepe his fill,</l>
                  <l>The waue and wind-mov'd veſſell goes on ſtill.</l>
                  <l>Patience then heart! they do not valour know,</l>
                  <l>That weary faint, but who can ſuffer woe.</l>
                  <l>Who's this?</l>
                  <stage>Enter Rob. Vaſter with the Letter.</stage>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Rob.</speaker>
                  <p>By your leaue, Miſtris Sorrow.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <pb facs="tcp:16830:24"/>
                  <speaker>Wife.</speaker>
                  <l>Right, th'haſt hit my name.</l>
                  <l>Yet cleare of ſinne, my ſorrow has no ſhame.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Rob.</speaker>
                  <p>I haue letters from Mr. <hi>Ben. Gripe.</hi>
                  </p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Wife.</speaker>
                  <l>They're welcome. (poore boy how am I vndone!</l>
                  <l>Tis hard, a mother muſt not owne her ſonne.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Rob.</speaker>
                  <l>Sure I ſhould know that face and language too.</l>
                  <l>A chill diſquiet troubles my ſoft peace,</l>
                  <l>And runs like a cold feuer through my bloud.</l>
                  <l>I'm very ſicke of ſomewhat. Oh 'tis then</l>
                  <l>Errour, the ſickneſſe in all minds of men.</l>
                  <l>But that I know her abſence giues her dead.</l>
                  <l>I' would ſweare it was my mother. 'las vaine thoughts,</l>
                  <l>How you would flatter me!</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Wife.</speaker>
                  <l>—Your prouident friend, <hi>Beniamin Gripe.</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>Leaue out that <hi>Gripe:</hi> it's an vnproper name;</l>
                  <l>Cannot denominate thee for ſuch a creature.</l>
                  <l>A name can neuer conſtitute a nature.</l>
                  <l>If bleſſed mankinde haue a <hi>Phaenix</hi> left;</l>
                  <l>And vice of that good hath not time bereft;</l>
                  <l>In this degenerate worlds apoſtacie;</l>
                  <l>The plurall number's loſt: that one is hee,—Sonne</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Rob.</speaker>
                  <p>Zlid ſhe calls me Sonne.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Wife.</speaker>
                  <l>That word's oreſlipt.</l>
                  <l>How eaſily loue is in her language trip't.</l>
                  <l>Sonne—of compelling nature not forbeares:</l>
                  <l>Paſſion muſt vent it ſelfe in ſpeech or teares.</l>
                  <l>Doſt thou not know me?</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Rob.</speaker>
                  <l>Yes: this teſtifie.</l>
                  <l>I begge your bleſsing on my humbled knee.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Wife.</speaker>
                  <p>Riſe with heauen's benediction.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Rob.</speaker>
                  <p>Liues my Father?</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Wife.</speaker>
                  <p>Gueſſe by my greefe and ſilence.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Rob.</speaker>
                  <l>Vm'h my doubts</l>
                  <l>Wrappe me in further maze. My father dead?</l>
                  <l>My mother liuing in his enemies houſe?</l>
                  <l>Let's ſtudy. Oft I haue heard my father mone,</l>
                  <l>That this ſame womans luſt had him vndone.</l>
                  <l>
                     <pb facs="tcp:16830:25"/>
This giues ſtrong faith. Why ſhould ſhee els liue here,</l>
                  <l>But to ſome ſuch vile end? By heauen tis cleare.</l>
                  <l>Oh that this ſappe, which my life feedes vpon,</l>
                  <l>Did not confeſſe a deriuation</l>
                  <l>From that corrupted trunke! Well, I will force</l>
                  <l>Nature runne backe with a prepoſterous courſe.</l>
                  <l>Ile faſhion a forgetfull lunacie,</l>
                  <l>That ere I was her ſoone. But on my ſoule,</l>
                  <l>Not touch her with leaſt hurt.—Woman come hither.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Wife.</speaker>
                  <l>Woman! Deare <hi>Robin,</hi> not thy mother? bleſſe mee.</l>
                  <l>Why doſt thou gripe me thus? Oh ſome blacke ſtorme</l>
                  <l>Is riſing on thy brow.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Rob.</speaker>
                  <p>Storme? No, tis thunder. Can you read this?</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Wife.</speaker>
                  <p>Yes, I can ſpell't too well. It ſpeakes my death, deare ſonne—</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Rob.</speaker>
                  <l>Come, come, forget</l>
                  <l>Theſe filiall rights, and Natures attributes.</l>
                  <l>Prepare your ſelfe to—</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Wife.</speaker>
                  <l>What? Oh deſperate child.</l>
                  <l>Oft haue thy bended knees with a iuſt dutie</l>
                  <l>Kiſs'd the cold earth, to begge my prayers to heauen,</l>
                  <l>For thy proſperity: oft deſir'd forgiueneſſe</l>
                  <l>Of thy wild infant-errors. Oft haue theſe</l>
                  <l>Borne thee with ſoft indulgence: but now, ſee,</l>
                  <l>A wofull mother bends her humble knee</l>
                  <l>To her incenſed ſonne; not to conſerue</l>
                  <l>This fleſh from death, but thy black ſoule from hell:</l>
                  <l>Th' vnſcaped dungeon, where all Parricides dwell.</l>
                  <l>Thinke: if thy ſpirits be not growne mad and wild,</l>
                  <l>Pitie a mother kneeling to her child.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Rob.</speaker>
                  <l>I'm deafer then an Vſurer to your mones.</l>
                  <l>I muſt, like <hi>Nero,</hi> ſee the place I bred in.</l>
                  <l>Be briefe in anſwere: did you neuer wrong my fathers nuptiall bed.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Wife.</speaker>
                  <p>Neuer.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Rob.</speaker>
                  <l>Take heede.</l>
                  <l>Clogge not that breſt with more ſin, that muſt bleed.</l>
                  <l>Speake truth and ſaue your ſoule.</l>
                  <l>
                     <pb facs="tcp:16830:25"/>
Lye you not here to ſatiate his luſt,</l>
                  <l>That robb'd my father? ſpeake, or y' are but duſt.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Wife.</speaker>
                  <p>No on my ſoule.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Rob.</speaker>
                  <l>Now on thy ſoule thou lyeſt.</l>
                  <l>Confeſſe, be plaine, or without pawſe thou dyeſt.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Wife.</speaker>
                  <p>Helpe, heauens or men.</p>
                  <stage>Within, breake open dore.</stage>
                  <stage>Enter Benia. Valentine, Gripe, Nice, Thirſty.</stage>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Ben.</speaker>
                  <p>What prodigie's this?</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>VVife.</speaker>
                  <p>Nothing Sir, alas nothing: 'twas but my feare.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Ben.</speaker>
                  <p>It is my ſeruant Sir; he meant no ill.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Grip.</speaker>
                  <p>Sonne, ſonne, howſoeuer he ſerues you, I'm ſure he does not ſerue God. Without queſtion, he would haue ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uiſh'd her.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Thir.</speaker>
                  <p>He would haue refreſh'd her, Sir.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Grip.</speaker>
                  <l>Speake widow, is 't not true?—away with him.</l>
                  <l>Couſin <hi>Nice,</hi> make his <hi>mittimus.</hi>
                  </l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Wife.</speaker>
                  <l>It's not amiſſe to let him feele ſome ſmart.</l>
                  <l>His life they cannot touch: what his offence</l>
                  <l>Deſerues in heauens, ſtrict iuſtice, mercy pardon.</l>
                  <l>Parents learne this in tendring Childrens ſtate:</l>
                  <l>Too much indulgence is not loue but hate.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Nic.</speaker>
                  <p>Sure his complexion doth not giue it: let me ſee your hand, Sir.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Rob.</speaker>
                  <p>Will you feele it, Sir? </p>
                  <stage>ſtrikes him.</stage>
                  <stage>Exeunt.</stage>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Ben.</speaker>
                  <l>(Sonne offer violence to the mother?) ſtrange!</l>
                  <l>Till I can ſound this myſterie of ill,</l>
                  <l>Ile to the priſon and relieue him ſtill.</l>
                  <stage>Exit.</stage>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Gripe.</speaker>
                  <p>You will be gone M<hi rend="sup">r</hi>. <hi>Valentine;</hi> but I hope you wil viſit me ſhortly againe.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Val.</speaker>
                  <l>Before you looke for me, Sir,—if all fall right,</l>
                  <l>I vowe to viſite you againe this night.</l>
                  <stage>Exit.</stage>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Grip.</speaker>
                  <p>Ha widow! I am cleere of the ſtone now.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Wife.</speaker>
                  <p>The leſſe able to do a widow pleaſure, Sir.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Grip.</speaker>
                  <p>Tut, wench, I meane the diſeaſe, the diſeaſe.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Wife.</speaker>
                  <l>(No Sir: you haue a worſe diſeaſe behind:)</l>
                  <l>The body hath no ſickneſſe like the mind.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Gripe.</speaker>
                  <p>Try me, ſweet. I'm like a leeke, though I haue
<pb facs="tcp:16830:26"/>
a gray head, I haue a greene—wut? wut be my medicine for the ſtone? when? when?</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Wife.</speaker>
                  <p>When you haue married me I will be your wife.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Gripe.</speaker>
                  <p>Piſh: firſt make triall how thou likeſt me: there is no wit, to marry before experience.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Wife.</speaker>
                  <p>Your houſe Sir, is too publike.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Grip.</speaker>
                  <p>Hold, ther's the key of my cloſſet. Be thine owne pandar for conuayance. I muſt receiue a little money: profit is aboue pleaſure: about ten—</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Wif.</speaker>
                  <l>Good lucke direct my hands vnto the morgage.</l>
                  <l>That found, if or my witte or ſtrength hold tacke,</l>
                  <l>I haue a medicine Sir, to coole your backe.</l>
                  <stage>Exit.</stage>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Grip.</speaker>
                  <p>'Las poore wench: now ſhee's got into my Cloſſet, ſhe hugges her hopes, as a Polititian his ayery plotte, and cryes a prize, a prize. She ſhall be double cony-catch'd. Wel, it growes Fairy-time. Oh the fine dapper laddes, how they friske about my chamber: when at euery ſtep here droppes a grote, there a teſton. Many drops make a floud. Sure, I'm ſome wonderfull honeſt man, that they loue me thus. I muſt to bed. Tarry, how then ſhall I keepe touch with the widow? Tha't, Ile ſit downe in my chaire, and faine my ſelfe in a ſlum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber. Oh 'twill be a golden waking dreame.</p>
                  <stage>Enter Vaſter, Valentine, Curſew, like Fairies, dancing antickes: pinching Gripe, as they paſſe by him.</stage>
                  <p>Oh-oh-th' are angry. Would I were rid of 'hem. Oh—ſweet ſpirit—oh—doe not terrifie mee thus. What haue I done to prouoke you?</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>aſt.</speaker>
                  <p>Confeſſe thy ſinnes. Th' haſt ſome wench in a cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Grip.</speaker>
                  <p>I haue, I haue—oh—but Ile not meddle with her.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Vast.</speaker>
                  <l>Whiles thy houſe was cleanly ſwept,</l>
                  <l>And thy conſcience chaſtly kept:</l>
                  <l>Neat linnen, fire and water ready;</l>
                  <l>And thy purpoſe good and ſteady:</l>
                  <l>
                     <pb facs="tcp:16830:26"/>
Whiles thou neuer ſentſt the poore</l>
                  <l>Vnrewarded from thy doore.</l>
                  <l>Whiles thou wakendſt with the chimes,</l>
                  <l>Becauſe thou wentſt to bed betimes,</l>
                  <l>We brought thee wealth; but <g ref="char:punc">▪</g>twas in vaine:</l>
                  <l>For now we'll fetch it backe againe.</l>
                  <l>Come deliuer the keys of your trunkes.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Grip.</speaker>
                  <p>Oh theenes, you'll robbe me, you'll vndoe me.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Curf.</speaker>
                  <p>No, Gowtie bliſter, well bind thee, vndoe thee, who will—.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Val</speaker>
                  <l>Open thy iawes thou yawning ſepulcher:</l>
                  <l>Here is a morſel for an Vſurer.</l>
                  <stage>Gagge him,</stage>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Vaſt.</speaker>
                  <l>A peece of Cheeſe of the Low-country Dairies.</l>
                  <l>This is the vſuall diet of the Fairies.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Curf.</speaker>
                  <l>Now we will rip the lining of thy trunkes.</l>
                  <l>Better the Fairies haue it then thy punkes.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Val.</speaker>
                  <p>Lucke more, then we can carry, hath aſſign'd vs.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Curf.</speaker>
                  <p>Each horſe his lode: we'll leaue the reſt behind vs. Thou greedy <hi>Panther.</hi>
                  </p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Val.</speaker>
                  <p>Sauage Wolfe.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Vaſt.</speaker>
                  <p>Man-eater. Thou fettting Canker.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Val.</speaker>
                  <p>Co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mons horſleech.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Cur.</speaker>
                  <p>Cheater</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>aſt.</speaker>
                  <l>Whoſe belly has iuſt cauſe to ſue an action</l>
                  <l>Of treſpaſſe, gainſt thy couetous luſts exaction:</l>
                  <l>For detinie of many hundred meales,</l>
                  <l>Which it from others, and thy ſelfe too; ſteales.</l>
                  <l>The Gowt.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Val.</speaker>
                  <p>The Dropſie.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Curf.</speaker>
                  <l>Collicke, Lunacie,</l>
                  <l>Like Sprites and Fairies haunt thy company.</l>
                  <l>And as thou gap'ſt now, let ſome Batte or Owle</l>
                  <l>Spet backewards i' thy mouth.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Vaſt.</speaker>
                  <l>No more. If thou do not</l>
                  <l>Repent, reſtore, turne good, ſit till thou rot.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Val.</speaker>
                  <p>What does Vſurie ſticke in thy teeth? ſpet out, Dog, ſpet out. Now thou gap'ſt for a morgage. Doſt?</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Vaſt.</speaker>
                  <p>Fare-ill. To thoſe that aske how came this euill, Giue anſwer thus: The Fairies robd the Diuell.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Grip.</speaker>
                  <p>Oh—Oh—Oh.</p>
                  <stage>Exeunt.</stage>
                  <stage>
                     <pb facs="tcp:16830:27"/>
Enter Bromley, Nice, Vasters wife.</stage>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Bro.</speaker>
                  <p>Ho maſter <hi>Gripe?</hi> what, your chamber doore ope thus carely? how now, bound? gagg'd? what rogues ha' bene here?</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Nic.</speaker>
                  <p>Speake to mee vncle, ſpeake: the gagge's out.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Grip.</speaker>
                  <p>Saue the gagge. I will hang the whole ſhire, but Ile find 'hem. Iugglers, Fairies, incarnall ſprites! My money, my heart, my guts, my ſoule—Let me curſe my ſelfe into the ground, and ſaue a Dirge. Run, cry, ride, charge the Conſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bles with 'hem.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Brom.</speaker>
                  <p>Where be they, Sir?</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Grip.</speaker>
                  <p>Gone to the Diuell. Runne to a Coniurer, caſt me a fi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gure.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Nic.</speaker>
                  <p>Oh, Sir, all the Coniurers are o' their owne trade. A miſchiefe on't, I thought there was ſome ſcuruy luck towards; the Crickets did ſo cry ith' Ouen yeſterday. And this verie houre, as we came in, there was an Owle whoo-whooping in the top of the chimney: and iuſt at the threſhold, maſter <hi>Brom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ley</hi> here ſtumbled Signes, ſignes.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Grip.</speaker>
                  <p>Plucke downe the ſignes. Ile vndo all the Innes in the towne: they harbour the theeues.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Brom.</speaker>
                  <p>You ſaid they were Fairies.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Nic.</speaker>
                  <p>Now in ſinceritie, I heard a great ratling of chaines.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Wife.</speaker>
                  <p>(This makes mee wonder! ſuch a robbery, and I not heare it?</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Brom.</speaker>
                  <p>Come bridle vp this furie. What will you ſay, if I can produce you the plotter, abbettor, or at leaſt acceſſary to this villanie? What if the pick-locke can open the cheſt of all this ſtratagem?</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Grip.</speaker>
                  <p>'Las, poore widdow, ſhe was faſt, I warrant you.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Brom.</speaker>
                  <p>No, ſhe was looſe I warrant you: how could we haue got in, if ſhe had not open'd the dore? Your couſin <hi>Nice</hi> and I came from a hurly-burly ith' Iaile. Your ſonnes man has broke from his keeper. And as we were comming, wee met this wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man verie ſupitiouſly ſtealing out.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Wife.</speaker>
                  <l>My heart miſgaue me thus: this diuels tongue</l>
                  <l>Would worke my miſdeem'd innocence ſome wrong.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <pb facs="tcp:16830:27"/>
                  <speaker>Grip.</speaker>
                  <p>No more words. Couſin, neighbor, take her to the next Iuſtice. I muſt not deale in my owne buſineſſe. Let her bee examin'd ſoundly, ſoundly: ſent to the Iayle, roundly, roundly.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Wife.</speaker>
                  <p>Sir, I beſeech you.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Grip.</speaker>
                  <l>No more. Do not you know, I know you for a whore!</l>
                  <l>Away with her, I will not heare her ſpeake.</l>
                  <l>My gold, my ſiluer—Oh my heart will breake.</l>
                  <stage>Exit.</stage>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Brom.</speaker>
                  <p>Come, will you walke? Ile leade, widdow, come you next. Maſter <hi>Nice,</hi> you'll follow.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Nic.</speaker>
                  <l>As cloſe, as beggery followes drunkenneſſe.</l>
                  <l>Let me ſee your hand, widdow—Oh the caſe is cleare.</l>
                  <l>A yellow ſpot doth on your hand appeare.</l>
                  <l>Gather vp your heeles, widdow: Iuſtice <hi>Surly</hi> dwels hard by.</l>
                  <stage>Enter Robert Vaſter.</stage>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Rob.</speaker>
                  <p>How now? my mother guarded? with two rogues?</p>
                  <p>Sword, thou didſt faine to kill her—but—Sirrah—you—deliuer me this woman, or Ile make thy yellow ſtarch'd face ſerue me for a cut-worke band.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Brom.</speaker>
                  <p>Oh Sir, y' are well met; you broke from the Iayle laſt night. Apprehend him maſter <hi>Nice.</hi>
                  </p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Nic.</speaker>
                  <p>I'am ſomewhat dainty and ſhy on him, Sir. He lookes vile ſharpe on't.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Brom.</speaker>
                  <p>Let him looke as ſharpe, as an Apparitors nailes, we'll blunt him I warrant ye. Sirrah, I charge you ſtand.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Rob.</speaker>
                  <p>Sirrah, you ſee I ſtand charg'd already. Will you haue me run?</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Brom.</speaker>
                  <p>Oh helpe, helpe—</p>
                  <stage>Exit.</stage>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Nic.</speaker>
                  <p>Hold, hold, I ha' not made my will.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Rob.</speaker>
                  <p>No matter for thy prayers; diſpatch it quickely then.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Nic.</speaker>
                  <p>You'l giue me leaue, Sir, to make my will.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Rob.</speaker>
                  <p>Yes.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Nic.</speaker>
                  <p>Then my will is—to runne away.</p>
                  <stage>Exit.</stage>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Wif.</speaker>
                  <l>Thankes, ſonne; but now do you not, like the Lion,</l>
                  <l>Saue the diſtreſſed Lambe from the Wolfes pawes,</l>
                  <l>For ſacrifice to his owne bloudie lawes?</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Rob.</speaker>
                  <p>Deare mother, pardon; be ſecure—</p>
                  <stage>
                     <pb facs="tcp:16830:28"/>
Enter Bromley, Nice, Beniamin, Sager diſguiſed, Anne Vaſter.</stage>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Brom.</speaker>
                  <p>This way, this way: here—Oh haue we found you?</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Ben.</speaker>
                  <l>How do theſe miſchiefes flutter in thicke heapes!</l>
                  <l>And cloud my vnderſtanding from the light,</l>
                  <l>I look'd the Sunne ſhould ſhine, find it darke night</l>
                  <l>I cannot ſtand t' examine circumſtances.</l>
                  <l>Now maſter <hi>Bromley,</hi> whither are you bound?</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Brom.</speaker>
                  <l>Your father gaue vs charge to haue the widdow</l>
                  <l>To maſter Iuſtice <hi>Surly's;</hi> he ſuſpects her</l>
                  <l>To haue ſome hand i'th robberie to night.</l>
                  <l>Sir it concernes you; he has loſt 300. pound.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Ben.</speaker>
                  <l>Vmh. My father robd? the widdow charg'd with it?</l>
                  <l>Her ſonne vniayld himſelfe? theſe are harſh turnes.</l>
                  <l>Well, go you two before, prepare the Iuſtice.</l>
                  <l>You haue my word for their appearance. Go.</l>
                  <stage>Exeunt. Br. Nic.</stage>
                  <l>VViddow, and <hi>Robin,</hi> now here's none but friends:</l>
                  <l>You'l giue me leaue to wonder at theſe ends.</l>
                  <l>Of that anone.</l>
                  <l>Meane time I here preſent you with a gift,</l>
                  <l>Dearer to me, then is the Sunne to earth.</l>
                  <l>So; narrow vp your paſſions for a ſpace:</l>
                  <l>H'you the morgage-deeds? giue them my hands.</l>
                  <l>Yet the ſucceſſe on my innention ſtands.</l>
                  <l>Mother, and brother, (ſo I hope your titles)</l>
                  <l>My ſelfe, and friend here, whom you do not know,</l>
                  <l>VVill baile you both. That done, I haue an Inne,</l>
                  <l>Now voyd of Tennant; there dwell all together.</l>
                  <l>My friendſhip to the power ſhall pledge your faith.</l>
                  <l>Meaſure good deeds by what man would, not hath.</l>
                  <stage>Exeunt</stage>
                  <stage>Enter Griffin.</stage>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Griff.</speaker>
                  <p>VVhat Damn'd fortune's this, that I cannot ſmell out theſe theeues? I would ſweate them to the Gallous, as well as they ſwore me out of my money. An oath like a ſtrong charme, ſhould coniure their neckes into the circle of a rope.</p>
                  <stage>
                     <pb facs="tcp:16830:28"/>
Enter Bromley, Beniamin.</stage>
                  <p>Oh, here comes my fellow-Patient; wee both tooke Phyſicke together; purg'd, purg'd: but <hi>I</hi> haue a cordiall for him. Saue you, brother <hi>Gripe.</hi> M<hi rend="sup">r</hi>. <hi>Bromley,</hi> newes, good newes. It's repor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted, that <hi>Sager's</hi> dead.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Brom.</speaker>
                  <p>Dead? Ile go take poſſeſſion preſently.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Ben.</speaker>
                  <p>Do not with too ſtrict rigour exerciſe your power on his diſtreſſed family.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Brom.</speaker>
                  <p>My time is come, I will not loſe an houre.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Grif.</speaker>
                  <p>It's iuſt, that euery man ſhould take his owne.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Ben.</speaker>
                  <l>Sir, you ſpeake law, not charitie. He that will</l>
                  <l>Be nothing more then iuſt, is vniuſt ſtill.</l>
                  <l>Wo to that quited ſoule, to whom from heauen</l>
                  <l>All iuſtice, and no mercie ſhall be giuen.</l>
                  <l>Your mercy to the widdow, to the Orphans.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Brom.</speaker>
                  <p>As much as a Puritan has vpon a good feaſt.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Ben.</speaker>
                  <l>Well—let me tell you this<hi>—Sager</hi> is dead.</l>
                  <l>So flies report, borne on preſumptions wings.</l>
                  <l>But how he dy'd, that aerie bird not ſings.</l>
                  <l>Kild—but by whom—waight deeply—I muſt hence.</l>
                  <l>The muttring's ſtrong—looke to your conſcience.</l>
                  <stage>Secedit</stage>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Grif.</speaker>
                  <p>How's this? kild?—muttering? and conſcience? Looke, his ghaſtly melancholy points him out for the murderer. As ſure, as a hatte-brinkes puld downe declares a cuckold, this darkeneſſe diſcouers him.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Brom.</speaker>
                  <p>I am a villaine.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Grif.</speaker>
                  <p>Tell him, that knowes it not.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Brom.</speaker>
                  <l>My narrow heart cannot be capable</l>
                  <l>Of this huge bulke of ſorrow. It muſt out.</l>
                  <l>Now, to whoſe boſome better then my friends?</l>
                  <l>This hand kild <hi>Sager.</hi>
                  </l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Grif.</speaker>
                  <p>How?</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Brom.</speaker>
                  <l>Nay, do your worſt.</l>
                  <l>Twas but chance medley, accidentall ſlaughter.</l>
                  <l>Intending with my Peece to ſtrike a fowle,</l>
                  <l>Againſt my will the cocke went downe, and he</l>
                  <l>
                     <pb facs="tcp:16830:29"/>
Stood in deaths way. It was his deſtinie.</l>
                  <l>But <hi>Griffin,</hi> harke you—let not your tongue ſtirre.</l>
                  <l>Do not I know you for a forgerer?</l>
                  <l>And more—you wot—let not your tongue be looſe.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Ben.</speaker>
                  <p>Thus are two Foxes catch'd in one poore nooſe.</p>
                  <stage>Exit Ben,</stage>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Griff.</speaker>
                  <l>Our guilt ſhall bind our ſecrecie; who liues</l>
                  <l>An vnſuſpected villaine, winks at others</l>
                  <l>Vnlawfull deeds, to teach their eye-lids how</l>
                  <l>To winke at his—Shall we go to our new Hoſtice?</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Brom.</speaker>
                  <p>Where? who?</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Griff.</speaker>
                  <p>For your where, at the Maiden-head, a good likely place. For your who: the wid dow that old <hi>Gripe</hi> ſuſpects for the robbery; but young <hi>Gripe</hi> hath tenanted to his Inne. Maſſe, ſhe preuents vs. Widdow, we were comming.</p>
                  <stage>Enter Wife</stage>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Wife.</speaker>
                  <p>Pray' Gentlemen walke in; you ſhall haue attendance.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Brom.</speaker>
                  <p>Your company, ſweete widdow.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Wife.</speaker>
                  <l>Ile not be long from you, Sir.</l>
                  <stage>Exeunt.</stage>
                  <l>Oh, ſome retiring from this houſe of ſinne.</l>
                  <l>Fate! I was neuer bred to keepe an Inne.</l>
                  <stage>Enter Curfew, Valentine as themſelues, Vaster diſguis'd.</stage>
                  <l>More cuſtomers? that which all Innes would ſee;</l>
                  <l>Great ſtore of gueſts: this is a plague to me.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Vast.</speaker>
                  <p>Yonder's mine Hoſtice. Now the water's vp, that we cannot get ouer to the Abbey, it is our ſecureſt courſe to com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mit the money to her cuſtodie. If any ſearch ſhould be made, and theſe tokens found about vs, we are all dead men: there's not ſo much mercie in <hi>Gripe,</hi> as in the Plague.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Curf.</speaker>
                  <p>Agreed. Widdow, we haue ſome money to pay to a Londoner in Bedford here; and he's not yet come to receiue it. Will you locke it vp ſafe for vs?</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Val.</speaker>
                  <p>But heare you? Deliuer it not to any one of vs. Except all three demand it to gether, keepe it ſtill.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Vaſt.</speaker>
                  <l>Helpe her to beare it in, and ſee't layd vp.</l>
                  <stage>Exeunt</stage>
                  <l>Zlid, my wife takes degrees; ſhe riſes fairely.</l>
                  <l>
                     <pb facs="tcp:16830:29"/>
I ſold her hither whore ſome trickes to do.</l>
                  <l>Now ſhe's turn'd whore, and Bawd, and Hoſtice too.</l>
                  <l>Stand cloſe deare wits, and ſhadow me diſguiſe.</l>
                  <l>She caſt me downe, and by her fall Ile riſe.</l>
                  <l>Husbands that loue your honour as your life;</l>
                  <l>Learne now to be reueng'd, on a falſe wife.</l>
                  <stage>Enter wife.</stage>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Wif.</speaker>
                  <p>Your friends expect you Sir.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Vast.</speaker>
                  <l>Sweet, I would go.</l>
                  <l>But here's a charming beauty, that ſayes no.</l>
                  <l>Will you walke off a little—to the meddow?</l>
                  <l>I haue a tiny buſineſſe with you, widdow?</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Wife.</speaker>
                  <p>What is your will, Sir? I'm in haſte: be ſhort.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Vaſt.</speaker>
                  <p>The thing thou wotſt on, halfe a minutes ſport.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Wif.</speaker>
                  <p>Forbeare, libidinous Groome.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>aſt.</speaker>
                  <l>Groome? I'm a man.</l>
                  <l>And can do, Hoſtice, what another can.</l>
                  <l>Come, ſhall I ſpeake in gold, and action?</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Wif.</speaker>
                  <l>Be damn'd, inchanter, with thy golden ſpelss.</l>
                  <l>Thou thinkſt, gold can buy luſt, when nothing els.</l>
                  <l>Yet I do loue thy ſoule. Think, ethinke, how deare,</l>
                  <l>A moments ioy is bought with endleſſe feare.</l>
                  <l>How ill the fleſh ſteales his vniuſt delight,</l>
                  <l>When the ſoule ſuffers an eternall night.</l>
                  <l>Flatter thy glowing hopes with heate no more.</l>
                  <l>Be not deceiu'd; thy Hoſtice is no whore.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>aſt.</speaker>
                  <l>So: ſpoke my out-ſide braue; did my rich huske</l>
                  <l>Allow me impudent; and my vndown'd chinne</l>
                  <l>Promiſe my bloud vnſuck'd out by this ſinne,</l>
                  <l>You would runne madde on me.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Wif.</speaker>
                  <l>Sooth, thou much erreſt.</l>
                  <l>I neuer ſaw that perſon (except one,</l>
                  <l>Who iuſtly claim'd my loue, now dead and gone)</l>
                  <l>In whoſe embracements I would ſooner locke the treaſures of my heart.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>aſt.</speaker>
                  <p>Now, now, ſhe's comming.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Wif.</speaker>
                  <p>If you had mou'd my eares with a chaſt ſuite, I ſhould haue liſtn'd.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ast.</speaker>
                  <p>Braue! ſhe's mine already.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Wif.</speaker>
                  <p>I cannot loue theenow.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Vaſt.</speaker>
                  <p>No?</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Wif.</speaker>
                  <p>No, I cannot
<pb facs="tcp:16830:30"/>
conceiue a good thought of thee.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Vaſt.</speaker>
                  <p>No?</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Wif.</speaker>
                  <p>I hate thee.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Vast.</speaker>
                  <l>Heigh? handy, dandy, faſt and looſe, braue diuell.</l>
                  <l>Ile coniure you for this. Come, will you loue me?</l>
                  <l>Or no matter for your loue, will you lie with me?</l>
                  <l>Doe, or lie alone i'th meddow here. I ſhall leaue your temp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting eyes for the Crowes to picke out.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Wif.</speaker>
                  <p>Defend me goodneſſe.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Vast.</speaker>
                  <p>Whiſtle not ſo lowd, leſt I cut your pipe, Come on.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Wif.</speaker>
                  <l>Honour or life, how ſhall I ſaue you both?</l>
                  <l>Sir, I ſhall ſpoyle you. I ha'bene long a ſinner.</l>
                  <l>A common ſinner, Sir, and am not ſound.</l>
                  <l>You cannot ſcape infection, if you touch me.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Vast.</speaker>
                  <p>Humh! the poxe, ſay you? well, you'l not reueale me.</p>
                  <stage>Exit</stage>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Wife.</speaker>
                  <l>You need not, Sir, diſtruſt my ſilence. Wrongs</l>
                  <l>That ſcape heauens hand, need not feare mortall tongs.</l>
                  <l>This world's turn'd Bedlam, rauing, deſperate-badde.</l>
                  <l>It ſtagger'd drunke before, now it runs mad.</l>
                  <l>More cuſtomers?</l>
                  <stage>Enter old Gripe and Beniamin.</stage>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Ben.</speaker>
                  <p>But, Sir, reſpect your life, your conſcience.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Grip.</speaker>
                  <p>Thou ſaiſt well, for my life. But for my conſcience<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> Tis like a Surgions, that takes money for letting out blood. Thinke o' my morgage.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Ben.</speaker>
                  <l>Vpon my life, he'll kill her. O preſumption,</l>
                  <l>How doſt thou dare heauens iuſtice? I muſt ſtudy</l>
                  <l>To interpoſe prevention. Sir, I'm your ſonne:</l>
                  <l>This breſt you gaue me, and Ile ſtill conſerue it,</l>
                  <l>A faithfull cloſet to locke vp your ſecrets.</l>
                  <l>How will you ſtrike? Piſtoll her?</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Grip.</speaker>
                  <l>No: that ſpeakes</l>
                  <l>Like an obſtreperous Aduocate, too loud,</l>
                  <l>In th'cares of iuſtice. Murder, like your Ieſuite,</l>
                  <l>Should whiſper death in ſilence—ſleeping ſilence.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Ben.</speaker>
                  <l>I apprehend it, poyſon. Sir, Ile buy you</l>
                  <l>A ſpeedy potion.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Grip.</speaker>
                  <l>Not too deare, good ſonne.</l>
                  <l>I would not ha't too deare: my mony's gone.</l>
                  <l>Two peny-woorth of Rats-bane, w' haue experience,</l>
                  <l>W'll do't; do't throughly.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Ben.</speaker>
                  <l>Ile prouide it, Sir.</l>
                  <l>Ile be your Apothecarie; but by no meanes</l>
                  <l>
                     <pb facs="tcp:16830:30"/>
Miniſter it my ſelfe. You muſt do that, Sir:</l>
                  <l>I cannot doe you better ſeruice. Rare!</l>
                  <l>Then bring my father to the Galhouſe.</l>
                  <l>Be petulant, and let your wanton mirth,</l>
                  <l>Giue you forgetfull of all wrong.</l>
                  <stage>Enter.</stage>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Gripe.</speaker>
                  <p>Come widow, I forgiue thee now: I hope thou't forgiue me too. I'm come to drinke downe all malice.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Wife.</speaker>
                  <l>Pray' Sir, lead the way. Ile follow.</l>
                  <l>Looke vp, deare friend: what thus deiects you?</l>
                  <stage>Exit Grip.</stage>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Ben.</speaker>
                  <l>Wonders, miracles<hi>—I</hi> muſt needs poyſon thee.</l>
                  <l>Be not diſmay'd, my poyſon ſhall not hurt thee:</l>
                  <l>Ile tell thee all<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
                  </l>
                  <stage>Enter Vaſter in haſte.</stage>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Vaſt.</speaker>
                  <p>Hoſtice, Pray 'helpe me to the money quickly. <hi>I</hi> muſt pay't inſtantly.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Wife.</speaker>
                  <p>You ſhall Sir.</p>
                  <stage>Exeunt.</stage>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Vaſt.</speaker>
                  <l>So, if my new-borne plots hold conſtant life<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
                  </l>
                  <l>Ile cheate my theeues, but aboue all, my wife.</l>
                  <stage>Enter Wife &amp; Rob. with money.</stage>
                  <l>Thanke you, good Widow. Youth, tel the</l>
                  <l>Gentlemen I'm gone to tender the money. Bid</l>
                  <stage>Exit Rob.</stage>
                  <p>'hem be merry and continue their healths. Ile take my round, when I come againe. Farewell Oſtice.</p>
                  <stage>Exit.</stage>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Wife.</speaker>
                  <p>Y'are welcome Sir, </p>
                  <stage>Enter Curfew, Valentine, Robin.</stage>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Val.</speaker>
                  <p>Gone, ſayſt thou? and with the mony? fire and gun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>powder! how are we blowne vp?</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Curf.</speaker>
                  <p>Prettie handſome!</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Val.</speaker>
                  <p>Oſtice—</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Rob.</speaker>
                  <p>Good leach, ſtand further off: your breath's too violent<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
                  </p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Curf.</speaker>
                  <p>Did we not charge you not to deliuer the money, but to vs all three together?</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Rob.</speaker>
                  <p>Maſſe, tis true. How forgetfully are we cheated?</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Val.</speaker>
                  <p>You are a coozening woman.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Rob.</speaker>
                  <p>You doe lye!</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Curf.</speaker>
                  <p>Keepe the peace. Oſtice, you'l make it good to vs, three hundred pound, a pretty competent ſumme.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Val.</speaker>
                  <p>Furies and Fiends! wits, you do fairly ſtriue.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Curf.</speaker>
                  <p>I thought this faiery mony would nere thriue.</p>
                  <stage>Exeu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t</stage>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Ben.</speaker>
                  <l>I haue heard all this roguerie.</l>
                  <stage>Enter Ben.</stage>
                  <l>Cheare, Widow: let not ſorrow make thee ſicke.</l>
                  <l>Perhaps, Ile catch the knaues at their owne tricke.</l>
                  <stage>Ent. Thir.</stage>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Thir.</speaker>
                  <p>So ho-my maſter's turn'd Reueller. I neuer loſt my name
<pb facs="tcp:16830:31"/>
ſince I came into his ſtaruice, till now. Vck! a miracle, I am not <hi>Thirſty.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <stage>Enter Nice.</stage>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Ben.</speaker>
                  <p>Now my wiſe kindred, why looke you ſo pale?</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Nic.</speaker>
                  <p>O, Ile put off my wedding. I will not for all Bedford marry to morrow.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Ben.</speaker>
                  <p>No? why?</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Nic.</speaker>
                  <p>O, my Vncle reaching for a Cup, ouerthrew the ſalt towards me—towards me. O tis ominous.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Ben.</speaker>
                  <p>The falling of a ſalt keep thee from mariage! well, I haue a ſtrange medicine, of quick cure to this conceited ſick<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe. <hi>Robin,</hi> fetch me ſome wine. Coz, how doſt feele thy ſelfe?</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Thir.</speaker>
                  <p>Hee ſhakes as if he had the gurning agew.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Nic.</speaker>
                  <p>Perplexed Couſin, perplexed. I had rather a good Lordſhip had falne toward me.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Ben.</speaker>
                  <l>Tut man, ſalt ſeaſons all things; fiſh or fleſh.</l>
                  <l>And troth, thou need'ſt it: for thy witte's but freſh.</l>
                  <l>Here bloud, I drinke to thee.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Thir.</speaker>
                  <p>Now could I dance like a Dutch Froe: my heeles are as light as my head.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Nic.</speaker>
                  <p>Oh I recant. Couſin, I will marry.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Ben.</speaker>
                  <p>What meant you Sir, to ſpill the wine vpon him?</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Rob.</speaker>
                  <p>'Twas a miſchance Sir.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Nice.</speaker>
                  <l>No: it was good hap.</l>
                  <l>Tis a good ſigne, t' haue wine ſpilt in ones lappe:</l>
                  <l>This makes amends for the ſalt, Sir.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Ben.</speaker>
                  <l>I thought this docke would fetch your nettle out.</l>
                  <l>I ſee. ſmall wind turnes a fooles mill about. Let's goe.</l>
                  <stage>Exeu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t.</stage>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Wife.</speaker>
                  <p>Yonder comes my Phyſician and his potion.</p>
                  <stage>Enter Gripe.</stage>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Grip.</speaker>
                  <p>I haue here two papers: one of ſugar, and that's for my ſelfe: another of poyſon, and that's for my Oſtice. Let me be right-right. I ſhould make faire worke, if I were miſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken now. Ha widow! th' art a Churle-a very churle, that wouldſt not keepe companie with thy gueſts. I ha' brought thee a cup of wine here: health and bloud to thee, ſweete Widow.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <pb facs="tcp:16830:31"/>
                  <speaker>Rob.</speaker>
                  <p>A miracle: An Vſurer drunke at's owne coſt.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Gripe.</speaker>
                  <p>There's a whole cup for thee: pledge mee chucke. Nay tarry, tarry: thou muſt haue ſugar to 't; women loue ſweet things, I know. So, off with't bottome and all: the dee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per the ſweeter. Ha Oſtice, my ſonne ſhall giue thee a leaſe of thine Inne.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Wife.</speaker>
                  <p>I would hee could grant me a leaſe of my life: for I grow ſick ſir. <hi>Robin,</hi> looke in.</p>
                  <stage>Exit Rob.</stage>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Gripe.</speaker>
                  <p>(Excellent ratteſ-bane) it workes already. Widow, doſt remember ſince thou waſt in my ſtudie? and y faith what foundſt there?</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Wife.</speaker>
                  <p>Nothing, but what I left behinde me, Sir. I'm ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry ſicke.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Gripe.</speaker>
                  <p>(Ile nere truſt poyſon els.) This cottons wel yet. No ſooner dead, but my ſonne ſhall ceaze on all the goods. Search the coffers for my morgage. If it be loſt, yet now ſhee I keepe counſell.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Wife.</speaker>
                  <p>This wine hath made me thirſty: I'm not well.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Gripe.</speaker>
                  <p>Hye thee to bedde and ſweat. A little poſſet with two-penny worth of horſe-ſpice. O tis excellent to put one into a ſweat. Farewell widow.</p>
                  <stage>Exit.</stage>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Wife.</speaker>
                  <l>So I'm recouerd now: thy abſence cures me.</l>
                  <l>O earth! thou center of the world and ſinne;</l>
                  <l>Tſty Paradiſe is loſt t'th'art only now</l>
                  <l>A larger ſtable, where all vices dwell.</l>
                  <l>Did not the Sunne ſhine, I ſhould thinke thee hell.</l>
                  <stage>Enter Vaſter.</stage>
                  <p>Lucky! here comes the cheater. Sir, the money is askt for by the Gentlemen, your friends: They threaten to arreſt me, but I hope ſir, you'l be my quittance.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>aſt.</speaker>
                  <l>Yes: on this condition.</l>
                  <l>Let me enioy thy loue on this ſoft ground:</l>
                  <l>Ile pay it backe, were it three hundred pound.</l>
                  <l>Stirre not: this chargeth you: are you not content?</l>
                  <l>Come, with a ſilent kiſſe ſeale your conſent.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Wife.</speaker>
                  <p>Sir, you know my diſeaſe. I'm dangerous.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Vast.</speaker>
                  <p>The poxe? O I haue knowne <hi>London</hi> too long to bee
<pb facs="tcp:16830:32"/>
afraid of the poxe. Come, will you vnlocke? I ha' the golden key. If not, Ile to <hi>Virginia,</hi> like ſome cheating Bankrout, and leaue my Creditour ith' ſuddes. You know the Iayle. Ha you neuer bin hir'd to yawle for the whole priſon? and whule to the paſſengers?</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Wife.</speaker>
                  <p>Sorcerer, thy circle cannot hold me.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>aſt.</speaker>
                  <p>No, I would haue yours holde mee. Come, will you fadge?</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Wife.</speaker>
                  <l>Not, if thou killſt me: not if thy murderous hand</l>
                  <l>Could put me to a death<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> (like Ieſuites poiſon)</l>
                  <l>Ten yeeres a dying.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Vast.</speaker>
                  <p>No? you will repent.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Wife.</speaker>
                  <l>So wilt thou neuer: take my carcaſe, ſlaue:</l>
                  <l>Whiles there's a ſoule within; no luſtfull hand</l>
                  <l>Did or ſhall euer touch it.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Vast.</speaker>
                  <l>Politick whore!</l>
                  <l>What do you ken me now?</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Wife.</speaker>
                  <l>My husband? ô,</l>
                  <l>Into your armes I flie.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>aſt.</speaker>
                  <l>Infection, no.</l>
                  <l>Y are dangerous by your owne confeſſion.</l>
                  <stage>diſcouers himſelfe.</stage>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Wife.</speaker>
                  <l>Alas! I forg'd that anſwere, to auoid</l>
                  <l>Sinfull embracings. Brothels ſicke indeed</l>
                  <l>Of that contagion, ſooth and ſmother't vp,</l>
                  <l>To tempt diſtruſtfull commers on, at once</l>
                  <l>To their owne profit, and the others ruine.</l>
                  <l>They ſpeake falſe, to do falſe the ſafer. I</l>
                  <l>To ſaue my conſcience did my fleſh bely.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Vaſt.</speaker>
                  <l>You cannot tempt me Siren; I am reſolute.</l>
                  <l>Thou art a cunning Bitch, and I am proud</l>
                  <l>Of ſuch expected meanes to my reuenge.</l>
                  <l>Harke, how Ile quittance thy abhorred luſts.</l>
                  <l>Firſt, thou ſhalt be arreſted for the money,</l>
                  <l>Whereof I cheated thee: ſo be reſtrain'd</l>
                  <l>From thy old ſtraggling, mew'd vp like a haggard;</l>
                  <l>Till the Aſsiſe comes, then thou ſhalt be hang'd.</l>
                  <l>I heare thou ſtandſt bound ouer for ſuſpicion</l>
                  <l>Of robbing <hi>Gripe.</hi> I did the villanie.</l>
                  <l>Ile ha't prou'd thine: ſo thou ſhalt hang for me.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Wife.</speaker>
                  <p>Deare husband, do ſo.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Vaſt.</speaker>
                  <l>Husband me no more:</l>
                  <l>That name was cancell'd when you firſt playd whore.</l>
                  <l>
                     <pb facs="tcp:16830:32"/>
Now garden-pot, you water your ſad feares,</l>
                  <l>But I am no loue-foole, wonne with womans teares.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Wife.</speaker>
                  <l>O proſecute your wil. Thus on my knees,</l>
                  <l>And with a heart more humbled, I intreat,</l>
                  <l>And I muſt haue it granted ere I riſe;</l>
                  <l>Be pleas'd to make this life a ſacrifice,</l>
                  <l>To expiate your wrath. I freely yeeld it,</l>
                  <l>For your redemption. For your hate I dye;</l>
                  <l>That might not liue in your loues companie.</l>
                  <l>If <hi>I</hi> confeſſe not guilty, to ſaue you,</l>
                  <l>Imagine then all your ſuſpicions true.</l>
                  <l>But when for your debts I haue payd this life,</l>
                  <l>Beleeue but then, you had a faithfull wife.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Vaſt.</speaker>
                  <l>O, thou wouldſt melt a rocke. My heart's too dead,</l>
                  <l>To ſprout at this wet <hi>Aprill.</hi> Fare you well.</l>
                  <stage>Exit.</stage>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Wife.</speaker>
                  <l>Peace and content attend you: and let ſtill</l>
                  <l>Mercie forgiue, and rectifie your ill.</l>
                  <stage>Enter Ben.</stage>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Ben.</speaker>
                  <l>What? not dead yet? but weeping? come, come dry</l>
                  <l>Vp all thy teares: goe hye thee in, and dye.</l>
                  <l>Much villanie is now together pack't.</l>
                  <l>The Scene growes full. Your patience this laſt act.</l>
                  <stage>Exeunt.</stage>
               </sp>
            </div>
            <div n="5" type="act">
               <head>Act. Quint.</head>
               <stage>Enter old Brace, the true Abbot. Abbot.</stage>
               <l>TO man, how ſweet is breath! yet ſweeteſt of all,</l>
               <l>That breath, which from his natiue ayre doth fall.</l>
               <l>How many weary paſes haue I meaſur'd!</l>
               <l>How many knowne and vnknowne dangers paſt,</l>
               <l>Since I commenc'd my tedious Pilgrimage,</l>
               <l>The laſt great worke of my death-yeelding age!</l>
               <l>Yet am I bleſt, that my returning bones</l>
               <l>Shall be rak't vp in Englands peacefull earth.</l>
               <l>
                  <pb facs="tcp:16830:33"/>
Oh happy Engliſhmen, if your ſore eyes</l>
               <l>Did not looke ſquint on your felicities!</l>
               <l>How other Countries enuy, what you loth,</l>
               <l>And ſurfet on: and would make that their pride,</l>
               <l>Which is by your contempt ſtill vilefied!</l>
               <l>This ſickneſſe fulneſſe breedes in moſt mens blood;</l>
               <l>None leſſe, then the poſſeſſors, know what's good.</l>
               <l>Now to my deputy: here his glories end.</l>
               <l>But ſtay: he comes to meet me. Ile attend.</l>
               <stage>Enter Curfew.</stage>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Curf.</speaker>
                  <p>Confound this damn'd foxe: he has cheated mee of the beſt prey, I euer ſhark'd for. Would I could light on him; I haue a Conſtable here ſhould make him ſtand.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Brac.</speaker>
                  <l>What's this? ſharking, foxing, and a piſtoll?</l>
                  <l>Th'embleme of theefe, cheater, murderer?</l>
                  <l>Sure, this vile Elderne was not of my planting.</l>
                  <l>I know him: Tis his brother, to whoſe truſt I did infeoffe my place.</l>
                  <stage>Enter Meſſenger.</stage>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Meſſ.</speaker>
                  <p>I was directed this way to the Abbot.</p>
                  <p>My lord—the Iudge detain'd by ſickneſſe from to morrow's Seſſion, deſires your lordſhips ayde to the ſupply of his owne place. Th' aſsiſtant Iuſtices reſt their determining ſentence on your lippes.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Curf.</speaker>
                  <p>Ile giue my old attendance.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Meſſ.</speaker>
                  <p>Your lordſhips leaue.</p>
                  <stage>Exeunt Meſſ. &amp; Curf.</stage>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Bra.</speaker>
                  <l>I leaue your lordſhip too.</l>
                  <l>I muſt about this miſchiefe to preuent:</l>
                  <l>Ile force you both your offices repent.</l>
                  <stage>Exit.</stage>
                  <stage>
                     <pb facs="tcp:16830:33"/>
Enter Iaylour, Gripe, Bromley, Griffin.</stage>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Iay.</speaker>
                  <p>So, ſo, ſo. My cuſtomers drop in roundly. Welcome, M<hi rend="sup">r</hi>. <hi>Gripe,</hi> and the reſt of my good friends, welcome! I am very glad to ſee you here. My houſe was not grac'd with an Vſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rer, and vnder-Sheriffe, many a day before; though I ha' been peſter'd with abundance of honeſter fellowes. Speake, ſhal'<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> be merry? what will you haue to dinner?</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Gripe.</speaker>
                  <p>A rope. What doſt thou tell me of dinner?</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Iay.</speaker>
                  <p>No Sir, that ſhall be kept for your ſupper.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Brom.</speaker>
                  <p>Giue me ſo me Sacke and <hi>Aqua vitae.</hi> I wil be drunk preſently.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Grif.</speaker>
                  <p>It's cleere. I haue twenty caſes for't.</p>
                  <p>The concealing of murder is but man-ſlaughter. I muſt ha' my booke.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Brom.</speaker>
                  <p>Giue 's ſome Sacke, I ſay: mun tut, &amp;c.</p>
                  <stage>Enter Nice.</stage>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Nice.</speaker>
                  <p>My Vncle committed? Iuſtice it ſelfe ſent to the Iayle?</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Gripe.</speaker>
                  <p>Couſin, ſweet Couſin, runne, ſcudde, fly—to Sir <hi>Bare Notwithſtanding:</hi> he lyes but three miles off; he's in my debt: bid him releaſe me, and Ile releaſe him.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Griff.</speaker>
                  <p>Stay Sir. He's in my debt too: I ha' ſolicited for Sir <hi>Bare</hi> theſe ſeuen yeeres, and haue nothing but bare thankes.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Brom.</speaker>
                  <p>Nay then, take me with you. Thus—</p>
                  <stage>Enter Beniamin, Robin, Thirſty; Thirſty climbing vp into a tree. Rob. into a buſh.</stage>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Ben.</speaker>
                  <p>Ha you your leſſon perfect?</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Thirſt.</speaker>
                  <p>Yes, yes: as a Mid-wife her errand to a Citizens wife. There's not an Owle in an Iuy-buſh, nor a Parrat at a Drugſters dore, has whoo whoop, or walke Knaue, more perfit.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <pb facs="tcp:16830:34"/>
                  <speaker>Ben.</speaker>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Robin,</hi> do't cunningly. My Dad ſhall be</l>
                  <l>Only to me beholding for his life.</l>
                  <l>By that aduantage I recall his loue.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Grip.</speaker>
                  <p>Couſin, fly euery ſtep. Remember, like a Iury-man, you goe vpon life and death.</p>
                  <stage>Exit Nice.</stage>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Brom.</speaker>
                  <p>Happineſſe grant, that no Hare croſſe him ith' way: his ſuperſtitious legges will retire, though wee hang for't. Come, ſhall we keep the rule of the place, and drinke drunke now?</p>
                  <stage>Exeunt.</stage>
                  <stage>Enter Nice.</stage>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Ben.</speaker>
                  <p>Now kindred, whither trot you ſo faſt?</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Nic.</speaker>
                  <p>Oh Couſin, about a deede of charitie; to ſaue your father, and two or three knaues more from hanging. I am go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to Sir <hi>Bare Notwithſtanding;</hi> to ſaue them out of priſon: they haue ſau'd him often.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Ben.</speaker>
                  <p>Sir <hi>Bare Notwithſtanding,</hi> he's a great man, Couſin.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Nic.</speaker>
                  <p>Hee had three Lordſhips fell to him at a clappe; the worſt worth 400. a yeere.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Ben.</speaker>
                  <p>Yet hee's bare notwithſtanding.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Nic.</speaker>
                  <p>Hee has ſold his Caroch with foure Flanders mares, becauſe he would retire himſelfe and liue ith' Country.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Ben.</speaker>
                  <p>Yet he's <hi>Bare Notwithſtanding.</hi> But to himſelfe Cou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſin, farewell.</p>
                  <stage>Exit Ben.</stage>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Nic.</speaker>
                  <p>To him, quoth he? I will to him, were the diuell in my way.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Thirſt.</speaker>
                  <p>Porke, porke.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Nic.</speaker>
                  <p>The diuell porke you. What diſmall bird crokes diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>aſter to my iourney!</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Thir.</speaker>
                  <p>Porke.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Nic.</speaker>
                  <p>Nay, if the deſtinies haue ſet the Rauen againſt mee, Ile rerurne ſure—yet let me ſee. So my Vncle may bee hang'd, Ile on, come what will.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Thir.</speaker>
                  <p>Porke.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Nic.</speaker>
                  <l>O this blacke bird tolles like a paſsing-bell,</l>
                  <l>My owne ſad miſchiefe and my Vncles knell.</l>
                  <l>Yet why am I ſo timorous; when charitie</l>
                  <l>Bids me go on, ſhall a Rauen hinder me?</l>
                  <l>Ile keep alooſe and paſſe—oh a ſpirit, a ſpirit.</l>
                  <stage>Rob. flaſhes powder.</stage>
                  <l>
                     <pb facs="tcp:16830:34"/>
The Widdowes Ghoſt. <hi>Bromley,</hi> Lawyer, Vncle, hang.</l>
                  <l>Take all your fortunes, I'le no further gang.</l>
                  <l>It's an vnhallow'd place, a diſmall day.</l>
                  <l>Betide what will, Il'e backe againe ſome way.</l>
                  <stage>Exit.</stage>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Rob.</speaker>
                  <p>Come downe, Rauen.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Thirſt.</speaker>
                  <p>Come out, Spirit.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Rob.</speaker>
                  <l>Blind, credulous foole! He that ſhall truſt at need</l>
                  <l>Such nice and tottring cockſcombes, ſhall thus ſpeed.</l>
                  <l>Should his ſicke father ſend him for ſome drugges,</l>
                  <l>Hee would turne backe at ſuch imagin'd bugges.</l>
                  <stage>Enter Beniamin, Sager, VVife, Anne.</stage>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Ben.</speaker>
                  <l>Come, mother, friend, and wife; take theſe back places,</l>
                  <l>Where you may heare vnſeene: that when time ſerues,</l>
                  <l>I may produce you. Works and houres are ſpent</l>
                  <l>Then well, when we doe good, or ill preuent.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Wif.</speaker>
                  <l>I cannot iudge, what is this dayes ſucceſſe.</l>
                  <l>All-ruling powers the doubtfull ſequele bleſſe.</l>
                  <stage>Enter Curfew with other aſſiſtants, <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>aster in a Prieſts habit, <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>alentine like a Phyſician, the Iaylor with Gripe, Bromley, Griffin, &amp;c.</stage>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Curf.</speaker>
                  <l>My Lord, whoſe place I perſonate, being ſicke,</l>
                  <l>Hath thus deſign'd mee, both to heare and cenſure</l>
                  <l>The criminall cauſes, which offend the peace</l>
                  <l>Of our dread Soueraigne, and his ſubiects weale.</l>
                  <l>Whiles we launce Vlcers, we the body heale.</l>
                  <l>The charge I giue in ſhort, you of the Iury,</l>
                  <l>Looke to your Oath and conſcience: let not fauour</l>
                  <l>Shut vp your eyes, nor malice open them</l>
                  <l>Too wide. You vnderſtand, our lawes are good.</l>
                  <l>Tis pitie that they ſhould be writ in blood.</l>
                  <l>But ſince conniuence at vnlawfull deeds</l>
                  <l>Giues but encouragement, and wee cannot ſtrike</l>
                  <l>With ſword of Iuſtice the deſeruing faults,</l>
                  <l>Except you giue the perſons to our hands:</l>
                  <l>
                     <pb facs="tcp:16830:35"/>
All on your vigilant information ſtands.</l>
                  <l>Proceede to the Inditements.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Grip.</speaker>
                  <p>We are all caſt away. Sir <hi>Bare</hi> is not come.</p>
                  <stage>Enter Abbot with guide.</stage>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Ab.</speaker>
                  <l>Pull downe that counterfeit, proud, arrogant, puffe:</l>
                  <l>Could your intruſion not content it ſelfe</l>
                  <l>T'vſurpe my office, but you muſt abuſe</l>
                  <l>The Kings deputed Iudge?</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>All.</speaker>
                  <p>Downe with him, downe with him.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Abb.</speaker>
                  <l>Iaylor, receiue him to your cuſtodie,</l>
                  <l>Till our iuſt cenſure giue him puniſhment.</l>
                  <l>Foxe, I ſhall hunt you out.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Curf.</speaker>
                  <l>Do't with a poxe.</l>
                  <l>The gooſe ſometimes muſt ſit and iudge the Fox.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Abb.</speaker>
                  <p>Proceed; the day haſtens.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Clark.</speaker>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Marian Sorrow</hi> widow, yeeld thy body, and ſaue thy baile.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Ben.</speaker>
                  <p>Sir, ſhee is dead: her felonie is anſwer'd Before a higher Court.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Clarke.</speaker>
                  <p>That is the woman that <hi>Gripe</hi> is ſuſpected to haue poyſon'd. <hi>Godfrey Gripe</hi> ſtand to the Barre. You are indi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted for the murther of <hi>Marian Sorrow</hi> widdow: guilty or not?</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Grip.</speaker>
                  <p>Not guilty, my Lord: let all the world teſtifie of my honeſt carriage. I haue liued all my dayes in good name and fame.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Abb.</speaker>
                  <l>Stand not vpon your credit and good deeds.</l>
                  <l>Your harueſt would be ſmall, if like your ſeeds.</l>
                  <l>If all that know thee ſtood about this place,</l>
                  <l>And had free liberty to ſpeake their thoughts,</l>
                  <l>Round ecchoing curſes would amaze thy ſoule,</l>
                  <l>And with hells damned crue thy name enroule.</l>
                  <l>But when the Widdow, Orphane call for plagues</l>
                  <l>On thy blacke life, thou hy'ſt vnto thy bagges;</l>
                  <l>
                     <pb facs="tcp:16830:35"/>
There doſt applaud and hugge thy wretched ſelfe:</l>
                  <l>As ſolace 'gainſt all woes lay in thy pelfe.</l>
                  <l>Thou haſt no god but gold: that Deitie</l>
                  <l>Thou ſhouldſt adore, and would ſtill ſuccour thee,</l>
                  <l>Is quite reiected. And that Idol, money,</l>
                  <l>Which beares away thy confidence and heart,</l>
                  <l>When thou art plagued, aggrauates thy ſmart.</l>
                  <l>Thou art the Deuils Executioner.</l>
                  <l>His rankeſt plague on earth's an Vſurer.</l>
                  <l>Spirits in hell whip ſoules: extorting ſlaues</l>
                  <l>Torment poore bodies ſo before their graues.</l>
                  <l>Thou art a gulfe, poore mens eſtates to drinke.</l>
                  <l>A quagmire; none paſſe ore thee, but they ſinke.</l>
                  <l>Vnleſſe <hi>Strepſiades-like,</hi> men could deuiſe</l>
                  <l>To plucke the Moone by Sorcerie from the skies;</l>
                  <l>Thy moneth and gaine will come. Like ſome at ſea,</l>
                  <l>(Yet dangerleſſe of ſhipwracke more then they)</l>
                  <l>Thou ſlumbreſt in a baſe lethargicke ſwoone.</l>
                  <l>Let others toyle, thy iournye's done as ſoone.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Ben.</speaker>
                  <p>Will not this moue him?</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Abb.</speaker>
                  <l>Nature in all inferiour things hath ſet</l>
                  <l>A pitch or terme, when they no more ſhall get</l>
                  <l>Increaſe and off-ſpring. Vnrepayred houſes</l>
                  <l>Fall to decay: old Cattell ceaſe to breed.</l>
                  <l>And ſappeleſſe trees deny more fruite or ſeed.</l>
                  <l>The earth would hart-leſſe and infertile be,</l>
                  <l>If it ſhould neuer haue a Iubile.</l>
                  <l>Only the Vſurers money genders ſtill:</l>
                  <l>The longer, luſtier: Age this doth not kill.</l>
                  <l>He liues to ſee his moneys moneys money,</l>
                  <l>Euen to a hundred generations reach.</l>
                  <l>He, whiles his intereſt money in do's troule,</l>
                  <l>Cares not to loſe the principall, his Soule.</l>
                  <l>He like a cleanly Alchymiſt can ſoke</l>
                  <l>And draw much ſiluer, yet waſte none in ſmoke.</l>
                  <l>Thou lendſt, like water powr'd on ſea-cole fire,</l>
                  <l>Or on a lode of Lime a ſhowre of rayne.</l>
                  <p>
                     <pb facs="tcp:16830:36"/>
It ſeemes to coole heate, but doth more enflame.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Ben.</speaker>
                  <p>His conſcience has deafe eares.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Abb.</speaker>
                  <l>When all is done,</l>
                  <l>And thou haſt ſwel'd thy heapes; to ſay no more,</l>
                  <l>Thy coffer's onely rich, and thou art poore.</l>
                  <l>This common plague is on all Vſurers ſhowne:</l>
                  <l>Th'haue much, yet are not maſters of their owne.</l>
                  <l>One day thy ſtintleſſe mind ſhall haue enough;</l>
                  <l>When the diuided peeces of thy ſelfe</l>
                  <l>Shall in their ſeuerall doomed manſions dwell:</l>
                  <l>Enough of mould in graue, of fire in hell.</l>
                  <l>But I ſpend breath in vaine; come, let's proceed.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Gripe.</speaker>
                  <l>No further. You haue made my conſcience bleed.</l>
                  <l>I heere confeſſe my ſelfe guilty of all,</l>
                  <l>Euen of this murder too.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Abbot.</speaker>
                  <p>Let mercie fall on thy diſtreſſed ſoule. Now to the reſt.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Clark.</speaker>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Nicholas Bromley,</hi> you are indited for the murther of <hi>William Sager,</hi> &amp;c. Guilty or not?</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Brom.</speaker>
                  <p>Not guilty? Who teſtifies againſt me!</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Ab.</speaker>
                  <l>In caſe of Murder ſhould we neuer iudge</l>
                  <l>By circumſtanciall likelihoods and preſumptions,</l>
                  <l>No life could be ſecure.</l>
                  <stage>Enter Nice.</stage>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Nic.</speaker>
                  <p>Puffe! ſhift for your ſelues; Sir <hi>Bare Notwithſtanding</hi> dares not be ſeene.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Brom.</speaker>
                  <l>O, I am loſt.</l>
                  <l>My Lord, I'm guilty: ſo is <hi>Griffin</hi> too:</l>
                  <l>He did conceale the fact, that I did doe,</l>
                  <l>We ſhar'd the Lands together.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Abbot.</speaker>
                  <l>Powerfull truth!</l>
                  <l>Murder will out, though by the Actors mouth.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Gripe.</speaker>
                  <l>O <hi>Beniamin,</hi> I haue vndone</l>
                  <l>My life, my ſtate, my credite, and my Sonne.</l>
                  <l>
                     <pb facs="tcp:16830:36"/>
But I'm reſolu'd to dye, ſo Monarchs muſt:</l>
                  <l>Rich men as well as poore, muſt turne to duſt.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Ben.</speaker>
                  <p>Me thinkes I could preuent all this.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Gripe.</speaker>
                  <p>Alas, thou lov'ſt me; but tis not poſsible.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Ben.</speaker>
                  <l>Sir, I haue here a booke already drawne,</l>
                  <l>Seale to it freely, and Ile ſaue your life.</l>
                  <l>You ſhall confirme me your vndoubted heire,</l>
                  <l>And then ſurrender <hi>Vaſters</hi> morgag'd lands.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Grip.</speaker>
                  <p>Tis done.</p>
                  <stage>ſeales.</stage>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Ben.</speaker>
                  <l>My Lord and all this bench be witneſſe to it.</l>
                  <l>Then thus I quit you, widdow, appeare in Court.</l>
                  <l>In earneſt, ſee, ſhe liues, that dy'd in ſport.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Wife.</speaker>
                  <l>Sir, thanke your Drugſter, elſe I had dy'd by you.</l>
                  <l>And you for me receiu'd a murderers due.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Grip.</speaker>
                  <p>So, I am couſen'd finely, finely—</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Val.</speaker>
                  <p>My Lord, I challenge this widdow for cheating me of 300. pounds. This is one of her old trickes.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Abb.</speaker>
                  <p>How's this?</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Val.</speaker>
                  <l>My Lord, my ſelfe and two intruſted friends</l>
                  <l>Came hither to pay money on a bond,</l>
                  <l>Whiles the receiuer did deferre his comming;</l>
                  <l>We gaue this coozening woman, being Hoſtice,</l>
                  <l>The whole ſumme to lay vp: and ſtraightly charg'd her,</l>
                  <l>Not to deliuer't, but to vs all together.</l>
                  <l>She ſayes one of vs three demanded it</l>
                  <l>Of her in haſte, and ranne away: and thus</l>
                  <l>We loſt our money, and the bond lies forfeit.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Ben.</speaker>
                  <l>Your Lordſhips leaue. Tis true, ſhe not denies,</l>
                  <l>But they ſo charg'd her, and ſhe was ſo coozend.</l>
                  <l>Therefore ſhe yeelds to paiment. Let 'hem come</l>
                  <l>All three together, they ſhall haue the money.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Grif.</speaker>
                  <p>Vpon my faith, a prettie quillet.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Abb.</speaker>
                  <l>Wittie and iuſt. How ſay you? heere produce</l>
                  <l>The other two, your ſatisfaction's ready.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Ben.</speaker>
                  <l>The widdow's cleard: but maſter <hi>Valentine—</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>Nay, man, come neerer, you'd haue preſent pay.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Val.</speaker>
                  <p>No, Sir, let it euen goe.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Ben.</speaker>
                  <l>So muſt not you.</l>
                  <l>
                     <pb facs="tcp:16830:37"/>
You gaue 300. pound to her: tis true.</l>
                  <l>Which like a ſubtle Quackſaluer, you robd</l>
                  <l>My father of; Sprites, Fairies—</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Val.</speaker>
                  <p>I am cob'd.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Grip.</speaker>
                  <p>It's true, my lord: this is one of the Fairies. Iuſtice, Iuſtice.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Val.</speaker>
                  <l>Well, if there be no remedie, I hope,</l>
                  <l>I ſhall not dance alone vpon the rope.</l>
                  <l>My lord, here's the other Fairie.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Abb.</speaker>
                  <l>O Sir, haue I found you?</l>
                  <l>Pull off that borrowd habite from his backe.</l>
                  <l>O that ſuch foule deeds ſhould be hid in blacke.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Gripe.</speaker>
                  <l>My Lord, this Widow's acceſſary too:</l>
                  <l>She plotted, ſhe receiu'd. Iuſtice, iuſtice.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Ab.</speaker>
                  <l>But late thy ſong was mercy, now all iuſtice?</l>
                  <l>Here's all the goodnes of an Vſurer.</l>
                  <l>She ſau'd his life, he would now hang her.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Gripe.</speaker>
                  <p>She has robb'd me, vndone me.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Val.</speaker>
                  <p>It is moſt true, my lord, ſhe plotted all.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Curf.</speaker>
                  <l>(Your villanie, Oſtice, we ſhall now retort.</l>
                  <l>You cheated vs, and we will hang you for't.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Ben.</speaker>
                  <p>How doe theſe miſchiefes grow, like <hi>Hidra</hi>'s heads, faſter by cutting off!</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Vast.</speaker>
                  <l>Prodigious villaines! will they thus caſt away an innocent woman?</l>
                  <l>Yet I moſt vile of all, that thus ſtand by,</l>
                  <l>And for my fault behold my poore wife dye.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Ben.</speaker>
                  <l>My lord, vpon my ſoule this woman's cleare:</l>
                  <l>And only malice thus accuſeth her.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Ab.</speaker>
                  <p>Speake, woman, art thou guilty?</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Wife.</speaker>
                  <l>My lord, I begge a word with my Confeſſor,</l>
                  <l>Then I ſhall anſwere. Sir, a word in priuate.</l>
                  <stage>To Vaſter.</stage>
                  <l>Now <hi>Vaſter,</hi> ope thy vnbeleeuing eyes:</l>
                  <l>Lo, thy deuoted wife for thy ſinne dyes.</l>
                  <l>Yeeld but this kindneſſe to my lateſt breath,</l>
                  <l>Thou hate'ſt me liuing, loue me yet in death.</l>
                  <l>Farewell—My lord, I will not ſay, I'm guilty;</l>
                  <l>Do as your euidence and wiſedome leades you.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Ab.</speaker>
                  <p>This knot is hard to vndo.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Vaſt.</speaker>
                  <l>My lord, Ile help you.</l>
                  <l>
                     <pb facs="tcp:16830:37"/>
Loe, <hi>I</hi> am that third Fairy, that pronounce</l>
                  <l>This woman cleare, and thoſe two periur'd knaues.</l>
                  <l>We three are guilty: let your ſentence come.</l>
                  <l>I haue deſeru'd, will not deſpaire my doome.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Wife.</speaker>
                  <p>My lord, he ſayes not true: hee's innocent: I guilty.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Ab.</speaker>
                  <p>Speake on your ſoules, which of theſe tongues ſpeak truth.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Val.</speaker>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Curf.</hi> My lord, the woman's cleare.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Ab.</speaker>
                  <l>Pernicious Villaines, hopeleſſe to be good:</l>
                  <l>That thus haue ſtroue to ſpill the guiltleſſe bloud.</l>
                  <l>Widow, y' are quitted. Sir, waite you your doome.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Vast.</speaker>
                  <p>With patience. <hi>Beniamin Gripe,</hi> I here accuſe you for murdering <hi>Richard Vaſter.</hi>
                  </p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Ab.</speaker>
                  <p>How?</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Vast.</speaker>
                  <l>My lord, I found that <hi>Vaſter</hi> dying, bury'd him,</l>
                  <l>Saw him receiuing death by this mans ſword.</l>
                  <l>Theft's a great ſin, but murder moſt abhorr'd.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Ab.</speaker>
                  <p>Speake; is this poſsible?</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Ben.</speaker>
                  <l>We met in ſingle combate in the field:</l>
                  <l>It ſeemes his life vnto my ſword did yeeld.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Ann.</speaker>
                  <p>Ay me, my father ſlaine?</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Rob.</speaker>
                  <l>And by his friend?</l>
                  <l>Fate, whither will thy proiects tend!</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Ann.</speaker>
                  <l>My husbands hand my fathers life vndoes:</l>
                  <l>For this fact he muſt dye: thus both I loſe.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Ben.</speaker>
                  <l>Forgiue me all, by me you all haue loſt,</l>
                  <l>The wife a Husband, children a deare Parent:</l>
                  <l>Thus I returne you all ſome recompence.</l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Nan</hi> thou ſhalt loſe a husband.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>An.</speaker>
                  <p>Heauens defend.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Ben.</speaker>
                  <p>Mother, you loſe a ſon, brother a friend.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Wife.</speaker>
                  <p>Can nature ſo degenerate, that a man ſhould liue, ſtand by, and ſee another ſuffer for murdering him?</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Vaſt.</speaker>
                  <l>Once againe off diſguiſe.</l>
                  <l>My lord, thus I preuent this fear'd diſaſter</l>
                  <l>My ſecond caſe pull'd off, I am plaine <hi>Vaſter.</hi>
                  </l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Rob.</speaker>
                  <p>My father?</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Wife.</speaker>
                  <p>My deare husband.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Vast.</speaker>
                  <l>Moſt, moſt deare friend.</l>
                  <l>My loue to you doth beyond bounds extend.</l>
                  <l>
                     <pb facs="tcp:16830:38"/>
My Lord, firſt to this honourable Bench,</l>
                  <l>I'here preſent the Kings moſt gtacious pardon</l>
                  <l>For vs three here: heauen no leſſe pardon vs.</l>
                  <l>Now to my wife: ſee wench, I am new borne;</l>
                  <l>Renc'd from the plague of a ſuſpected horne.</l>
                  <l>Blacke Iaundeys of the minde, thou fained ſpirit,</l>
                  <l>That haunts mens quiet thoughts with troubling ſhades.</l>
                  <l>Pernicious Ielouſie, that like needleſſe Phyſicke</l>
                  <l>Diuerteſt health to voluntary ſickneſſe,</l>
                  <l>I bruſh thee off like duſt. See, I am now</l>
                  <l>New marry'd to my loue and to my life.</l>
                  <l>Neuer could man boaſt a more conſtant wife.</l>
                  <l>Deare <hi>Beniamin,</hi> now Sonne, what I haue left</l>
                  <l>Of all my ſhipwrack'd fortbnes, ſhall be thine.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Ben.</speaker>
                  <p>Reſume your former ſtate, my father yeelds it.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Vaſt.</speaker>
                  <l>Thankes to your honeſtie, not his; yet thus,</l>
                  <l>Some meanes of ſatisfaction I haue found;</l>
                  <l>Ile pay him backe his loſt three hundred pound:</l>
                  <l>The fairie money, which was iuſt the price</l>
                  <l>Of my redeemed lands.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Ben.</speaker>
                  <l>Now maſter <hi>Bromley,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>That vniuerſall mercie to our guilt,</l>
                  <l>May be affoorded, and no blood be ſpilt:</l>
                  <l>Surrender vp your leaſe for the three liues</l>
                  <l>To <hi>Sagers</hi> wife and children, and Ile quit you.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Brom.</speaker>
                  <p>I do moſt freely yeeld it.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Sag.</speaker>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Sager</hi> liues,</l>
                  <l>And hartie thankes for your forc'd kindneſſe giues.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Abb.</speaker>
                  <l>Happy deluſions! in ſuch waies of ill,</l>
                  <l>I wiſh men may be thus miſtaken ſtill.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Nic.</speaker>
                  <p>Rauens, and Sprites, and Fairies, and Hares and diuels-Thus haue I loſt my wench, loſt my money, loſt my watch, loſt my wits. I doe here renounce the faith of all Almanackes, Phyſiogmoners, Palmiſts, Fortune-tellers. <hi>Erra Pater</hi> was an Aſſe, and ſo are Prognoſticators, his children, from generation to generation.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Grip.</speaker>
                  <l>I haue drunke powerfull phyſicke, and the Dropſie</l>
                  <l>
                     <pb facs="tcp:16830:38"/>
Of my (till now) nere quenched auarice,</l>
                  <l>Dries vp like dew at the aſcending Sunne.</l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Vaſter,</hi> take back your lands; and for the money,</l>
                  <l>Giue it my ſonne in portion with your daughter.</l>
                  <l>Hencefoorth Ile ſtudy to requite the wrongs,</l>
                  <l>Which I haue done poore men by vſurie,</l>
                  <l>And vomit vp th'extortions, that doe lie</l>
                  <l>As vndigeſted crudities on my conſcience.</l>
                  <l>My future life ſhall bee in mercie ſpent.</l>
                  <l>I'm <hi>Gripe</hi> no more; that name I doe repent.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Abb.</speaker>
                  <l>All Chronicles be fill'd with this; and let it</l>
                  <l>Beas a wonder to all eares imparted.</l>
                  <l>England had once an Vſurer conuerted.</l>
               </sp>
            </div>
         </div>
      </body>
      <back>
         <div type="epilogue">
            <pb facs="tcp:16830:39"/>
            <head>EPILOGVE.</head>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Ben.</speaker>
               <l>THe Seſſion now diſſolues: each Iuſtice riſes:</l>
               <l>No hurt is done; this is the milde Aſſiſes.</l>
               <l>We haue ſcap'd faire thus farre: yet there remaines</l>
               <l>A ſtronger iudgement to paſſe on our paines.</l>
               <l>Too much to hope or doubt we muſt not dare.</l>
               <l>We humbly then ſtand at your cenſures barre.</l>
               <l>If the worſt comes that may be, yet I looke</l>
               <l>For this grace, to be ſaued by my booke.</l>
               <l>But if with your applauſe our merit ſtands:</l>
               <l>Faith then be friends with vs, and giue's your hands.</l>
            </sp>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </back>
   </text>
</TEI>
