<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>A briefe vievve of the weake grounds of popery as it was propounded to D. Norrice, priest, by T.V. gent: and returned without answere.</title>
            <author>Udall, Thomas.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1606</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 203 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 67 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2012-10">2012-10 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A68832</idno>
            <idno type="STC">STC 24508.5</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC S119623</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99854830</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99854830</idno>
            <idno type="VID">20283</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A68832)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 20283)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 1533:09)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>A briefe vievve of the weake grounds of popery as it was propounded to D. Norrice, priest, by T.V. gent: and returned without answere.</title>
                  <author>Udall, Thomas.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[24], 101, [9] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Imprinted by Humfrey Lownes, for Samuel Macham, and Mathew Cooke, and are to be sold in Pauls Church-yard, at the signe of the Tigers head,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>At Londn [sic] :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1606.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>T.V. = Thomas Udall.</note>
                  <note>Running title reads: The weake grounds of popish religion.</note>
                  <note>Formerly STC 24567.</note>
                  <note>Identified as STC 24567 on UMI microfilm.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the Cambridge University Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Catholic Church --  Controversial literature --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2011-12</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-12</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-01</date>
            <label>Judith Siefring</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-01</date>
            <label>Judith Siefring</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-05</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:20283:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:20283:1"/>
            <p>A BRIEFE VIEWE of the weake Grounds of Popery; <hi>As it was propounded to D.</hi> NORRICE, Prieſt, by T.V. Gent: and returned without anſwere.</p>
            <p>AT LONDN Imprinted by <hi>Humfrey Lownes,</hi> for <hi>Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>muel Macham,</hi> and <hi>Mathew Cooke,</hi> and are to be ſold in <hi>Pauls</hi> Church-yard, at the ſigne of the Tigers head. 1606.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="preface">
            <pb facs="tcp:20283:2" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:20283:2"/>
            <head>To my deareſt Couſins, A. B. C. D.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">M</seg>Y deareſt Couſins: with what zeale and feruencie (both in my prayers, and other indeuours) I haue euer deſired wee might be of one mind &amp; heart, God,<note place="margin">Act. 6.</note> and mine owne conſcience can beſt teſtifie, and your ſelues may partly witnes with me. For, as touching the means to this our atonement (namely, conference with the learned of ech others ſide, and reading their bookes) you know well, I (for my part) haue neuer refu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed it, but euermore gladly imbraced, and di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligently ſought after it: that ſo, if truth (wher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of great vaunts were made) had been found on your ſide, my heart firſt, &amp; then my hand, might readily haue ſubſcribed thereto. But, when I conſider the doctrine of your Rhe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſts,<note place="margin">Tit. 3. Sect.</note> (and the anſwerable practiſe of their diſciples) forbidding you not onely to reade our bookes, but to hold conuerſation (much more to haue conference) with vs, (who muſt
<pb facs="tcp:20283:3"/> be Heretikes becauſe they tearme vs ſo): yea, when I ſee they bluſh not to affirme, That <hi>we are not to be heard;</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>f<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>r. 3. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ect. 2.</note> 
               <hi>no, not though we ſpeake the trueth:</hi> I almoſt deſpaire of your conuer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion; ſeeing the means are prohibited. Now, how much meeter it were, in a caſe of ſuch conſequence (being no leſſe than the eternal ſafegard of your ſoules) to leaue them, with their errors; and to hearken rather, and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forme your faith, to the doctrine of Chriſt and his Apoſtles, I referre it to any ſeeing iudgement. For, the vniuerſall conſent of all the ancient Fathers, alloweth <hi>the Scriptures for the onely Rule of faith; as conteining in them, all doctrine neceſſary to ſaluation.</hi> And albeit I haue ſufficiently (among others) cleared that queſtion in this ſmal Treatiſe following; yet will I ſomewhat inlarge the proofe of it in this place; to the end you may better knowe, That though you ſend vs (for inſtruction) to to the Fathers: yet they ſend vs backe again to the <hi>Scriptures, as the onely and ſufficient Rule to direct vs.</hi> And, in handling this point, I will not much inſiſt vpon diuine authority; ſince I know you relye chiefly (if not wholly) on the Fathers. Onely I will vrge theſe few te<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtimonies of Scripture: which ought to pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uaile more with euery true Chriſtian, than all
<pb facs="tcp:20283:3" rendition="simple:additions"/> the Fathers, how learned ſoeuer. Firſt, our Sauiour willeth vs, <hi>to ſearch the Scriptures, for that in them we thinke to haue eternall life.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Io. 5.39. Mark. 1224.</note> And he taxeth the Phariſes of error, becauſe they were ignorant of the Scriptures.<note place="margin">2. Tim. 3.15, 16, 17.</note> S. <hi>Paul</hi> like<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe affirmeth that they are able to make vs <hi>wiſe vnto ſaluation; that the man of God may be perfite, inſtructed to euery good worke.</hi> And if this perſwade you not, I haue no hope that any Father can: for as Chriſt ſaith,<note place="margin">Luk. 16.29, 30, 31.</note> 
               <hi>They haue Moyſes and the Prophets, if they will not heare them, neither will they beleeue if one roſe from the dead.</hi> Now, as to the Fathers, though your ſide pretend ſo much to reuerence them, yet in this queſtion, they wholly reiect them, and that indeede not without cauſe; ſeeing their authority in this one point, might proue the downefall of your whole Religion: it be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing confeſſed by ſome great Champions on your ſide, That many and moſt of the do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrines wherin you varie from vs, are groun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded on Traditions, and not on the Scriptures: as any that will take the paines to reade, may ſee, in <hi>Peter Soto,</hi> againſt <hi>Brentius;</hi> in the fift chapter of <hi>Caniſius</hi> Catechiſme, &amp; in the<note n="*" place="margin">In fine fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bulae, 6.</note> 5 booke of <hi>Lyndans Panoply:</hi> yea,<note n="*" place="margin">Scripto ſu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> aedito tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pore Trid. Concil.</note> 
               <hi>Andradius</hi> ſaith, That the greateſt part of <hi>Catholike Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion is left vnto Traditions of the Church not
<pb facs="tcp:20283:4" rendition="simple:additions"/> written.</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>anopl. li. 1. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>. 22. deme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ſſimae inſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>iae,</note> And the ſaid <hi>Lyndan</hi> ſaith, <hi>It is moſt extreme madnes to think, that the whole &amp; entire Body of Euangelicall doctrine is to be fetched out of the Apoſtolike letters written with inke, and out of that little booke of the new Teſtament.</hi> And therefore ſo much the more are your leaders &amp; ſeducers to be taxed, who perſwade their folowers, that the greateſt differe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce between them and vs, is touching the <hi>Senſe of the Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture:</hi> wheras euery man of common ſenſe wil eaſily iudge, that, <hi>where there is no Text, there needs no Interpreter.</hi> But let vs briefly ſee what opinio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the Fathers were of, in this co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>trouerſie betweene vs, and how they haue vnderſtood that Scripture, which D. B. P. calles the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſtants <hi>Achilles,</hi> which hee onely barkes at, without further hurt.<note place="margin">
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> B. booke <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>gainſt M <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>erkins, cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ed the 1. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>im. 3. the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>rot. Achil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>es. Hom. 9.</note> 
               <hi>Chryſoſtome</hi> vpon the ſame Text ſayth, <hi>If any thing be needefull for vs to learne, or to be ignorant of, there</hi> (meaning in the Scriptures) <hi>ſhal we learne it: If to reproue falſehood, from thence ſhal we draw it; if any thing lacke to be corrected or rebuked; which muſt be had vnto exhortation, vnto comfort: there alſo doe we learne it.</hi> Likewiſe Ho. 8. vpon the 15. verſe he ſaith, <hi>The ſcriptures do teach both what things are to be done, &amp; what not to be done. The<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>odoret</hi> vpo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the ſame place ſaith, <hi>The ſcripture is inſpired of God, Therfore he teacheth the kinds
<pb facs="tcp:20283:4"/> of vtilitie: It is profitable to teach; for, whatſoeuer we know not, we learne out of it: To reproue; It re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proueth our wicked life: To correct; for it exhor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teth, that they which haue gone aſtray, returne to the right way: To inſtruct in righteouſneſſe; for it teacheth vs the kinds of vertue, that the man of God may bee perfit, furniſhed to all good workes. All theſe things doe attribute and aſcribe perfe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction to the God of all. Primaſius</hi> ſaith, <hi>Out of the ſcriptures he that is ignorant is taught; Hee that is inſolent, is reprooued; He that erreth, is corrected; He that can keep no meaſure, is inſtru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cted to Iuſtice; to euery good worke, not vnto one. Oecumenius</hi> ſayth, after he hath rehearſed the particular vtilities, to teach all true opinions, and good works, to reprooue errors &amp; vice, he concludeth, that the man of God may be, <hi>not onely partaker after a vulgar maner of euery goodworke, but perfect and compleate by the do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrine of the ſcriptures. Not to ſome kind of good worke, and to ſome not: But to all and euery good worke,</hi> ſaith <hi>Theophilact. Athanaſius</hi> ſaith,<note place="margin">Atha. contr. gent. Chryſ. ope<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> imperf. in Mat. Ho. 41. Aug. in Ioh<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> Tract. 44.</note> 
               <hi>The holy ſcriptures inſpired from heauen are ſuffi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cient for all inſtruction of trueth. Chryſoſtome</hi> ſaith, <hi>whatſoeuer is requiſite for ſaluation; all that is fully laid downe in the Scripture.</hi> S. <hi>Augu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtine</hi> ſayth, <hi>There were choſen to be written, ſuch things as ſeemed (to the holy Ghoſt) ſufficient for
<pb facs="tcp:20283:5"/> the ſaluation of the faithfull.</hi> And in his ſecond booke againſt <hi>Creſconius,</hi> the Gra<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>marian, he ſaith, <hi>That there is an Eccleſiaſticall Canon or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dained, whereunto belong the bookes of the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phets and Apoſtles: By which bookes, we iudge all other writings both of the faithful, &amp; of the Infi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dels.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Hier. ſup. Agge. cap. 1.</note> 
               <hi>Hierom</hi> ſayth, <hi>Thoſe things which of their owne heads they deuiſe, as though they came by Apoſtolike Tradition, without the authority and teſtimony of the holy Scriptures, the ſword of Gods word ſtriketh.</hi> Infinite be the Authorities of the Fathers, which might be brought to this purpoſe: but I will conclude the point with <hi>Vincentius Lirinenſis</hi> (whome D.B.P. in his booke againſt M. <hi>Perkins,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Vincent. ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer. Haereſ.</note> beleeueth not to haue any ſuch wordes) who ſaith, <hi>The Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>non of the Scripture is perfect and ſufficient, and more then ſufficient to al things.</hi> And again, <hi>Not that</hi> (ſaith he) <hi>the Canon alone is not ſufficient for all things.</hi> Theſe Fathers I hope knew the Scriptures aſwell as D.B.P. or any other Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piſt: and yet notwithſtanding al his (&amp; their) obiections, the Proteſta<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ts <hi>Achilles</hi> (as he tear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>meth it) ſtands vnimpeacht by any thing that this (or any other) cauiller hath ſaid. And yet notwithſtanding theſe euident places, brought by the general conſent of all the Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers againſt the <hi>fundame<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tal Ground of Popery:</hi>
               <pb facs="tcp:20283:5" rendition="simple:additions"/> Your Rhemiſts wil tel you,<note place="margin">Rhem. Teſt. 2. Theſ. 2. ſect. 18.19.</note> if you wil beleeue them, that they haue (to the contrary) <hi>plaine Scriptures, all the fathers, moſt euident reaſons, that wee muſt either beleeue Traditions, or no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing at all.</hi> And that S. <hi>Auguſtine</hi> often wri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teth, <hi>That many of the articles of our Religion, and points of higheſt importance, are not ſo much to be prooued by Scriptures, as by Tradition.</hi> But if we aske them where S. <hi>Austine</hi> wrote this <hi>(often),</hi> and that <hi>(of many articles of Religion and poynts of higheſt importance)</hi> it muſt be re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turned with <hi>Non est inuentus; Not to be found in S.</hi> Auſtin. But they perceiuing the whole waight of their cauſe to lie in this,<note place="margin">Rhem. Teſt. fol. 559.</note> haue mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhalled nine Fathers in a ranke, to proue, <hi>that we must either beleeue Traditions, or nothing:</hi> And yet the very ſame Fathers haue ſhewed, That no matter of faith, or of any moment to ſaluation, muſt bee receiued or beleeued without the Scriptures;<note place="margin">Cypr. ad Pomp. cont. epiſt. Stepha. Baſil. contr. Eunomium. lib. 3.</note> and the Fathers often times by <hi>Traditions</hi> vnderſtand matters con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tained &amp; proued out of the ſcriptures, &amp; that in regard the ſame was deliuered alſo by word. And many times by <hi>Traditio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s</hi> they vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſta<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d ceremonies and cuſtoms. Now chuſe whether you will grant, <hi>a flat contradiction in the Fathers;</hi> or reconcile them thus; and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clude with vs, <hi>Ergo, the Traditions they meane,
<pb facs="tcp:20283:6" rendition="simple:additions"/> be no parts or points of the Chriſtian faith:</hi> For we haue their plain confeſſion, <hi>That all things neceſſary to ſaluation, are compriſed in the ſcrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures:</hi> you produce them to witnes, <hi>That your Traditions be not compriſed in the ſcriptures. Er<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>go,</hi> by your owne deponents wee conclude, <hi>That your Traditions be neither neceſſary to ſal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uation, nor points of the Catholike faith.</hi> Looke wel to this <hi>Iſſue,</hi> They muſt either diſſent fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> you, or from themſelues. Now if you will compare the late doctrine of the <hi>Romiſh Church,</hi> with theſe Fathers; it ſhal be euident, That they haue not only diſſented fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> them, but alſo vttered open blaſphemy againſt the ſacred Scriptures. Firſt Cardinal <hi>Cuſanus</hi> inti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuleth his booke, <hi>De authoritate eccleſiae &amp; Co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cilij ſupra &amp; contra ſcripturam: Of the the au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thority of the Church &amp; Cou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>cel aboue &amp; againſt the ſcriptures. Sylueſter Prierias,</hi> maſter of the Popes palace,<note place="margin">Contr. Lu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther. co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>cluſi. de pot. Papae</note> ſaith, <hi>That indulgences are war<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ranted vnto vs, not by the authority of the ſcrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, but by the authority of the Church and Pope of</hi> Rome, <hi>which is greater.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Boniface</hi> the Archbiſhop of <hi>Mentz,</hi> ſaith, <hi>That all men ſo reuerence the Apoſtolike See of</hi> Rome, <hi>that they rather deſire the ancient inſtitu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of Chriſtian Religio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> from the Pope, than from the holy ſcripture.</hi> This ſaying the Pope hath
<pb facs="tcp:20283:6"/> ſo approued, that he hath cauſed it to be in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerted into the Cannon lawe.<note place="margin">Diſt. 40. c. Si Papa.</note>
            </p>
            <p>Another ſaith, <hi>whoſoeuer reſteth not on the doctrine of the Roman Church, and B. of</hi> Rome,<note place="margin">Sylueſt. Pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er. contr. Luther.</note> 
               <hi>as the infallible rule of God; à qua ſacra ſcriptura roburtrahit &amp; auctoritatem: from which the ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cred ſcripture draweth ſtrength and authority, he is an heretike. Eckius</hi> ſaith,<note place="margin">De Eccleſia.</note> 
               <hi>Scriptura niſi eccle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiae auctoritate non eſt authe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tica: The ſcripture is not authe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tical, but by the authority of the church.</hi> Cardinal <hi>Hoſius</hi> ſaith,<note place="margin">De expreſſo verbo Dei.</note> 
               <hi>If any man haue the in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terpretation of the Church of</hi> Rome, <hi>concerning any place of ſcripture, although he neither knowe, nor vnderſtand, whether, and how it agreeth with the words of the ſcripture, notwithſtanding he hath</hi> ipſiſſimu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> verbu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> Dei, <hi>the very word of God.</hi> Cardinal <hi>Cuſanus</hi> ſaith,<note place="margin">Nicol. Cu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſan. ad Bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hem. epi. 7.</note> 
               <hi>It is no maruel though the practiſe of the Church, expound the ſcriptures at one time one way, and at an other time another way: for the vnderſtanding or ſenſe of the ſcrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture runneth with the practiſe: And that ſenſe a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>greeing with the practiſe, is the quickening ſpirit:</hi>
               <note place="margin">Henric. do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctor Magi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter ſacripa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>latij Romae ad Legatos Bohemicos ſub Felice Papa 1447. Ad Bohem. ep. 2.</note> 
               <hi>and therefore the ſcriptures follow the Church; but contrariwiſe, the Church followeth not the ſcriptures.</hi> Another ſaith, <hi>The Pope may change the holy Gospel, and may giue to the Gospel ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to place and time another ſenſe.</hi> To con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clude therfore with Cardinal <hi>Cuſanus, This is
<pb facs="tcp:20283:7"/> the iudgement</hi> (ſaith he) <hi>of all them that thinke rightly, that fou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d the authority &amp; vnderſtanding of the Scriptures, in the allowance of the Church: and not contrariwiſe lay the foundation of the Church in the authority of the ſcriptures.</hi> I will not mention others that haue blaſphemouſly ſaid,<note place="margin">Vid. Chem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nit. exa. par. 1. pag. 47.</note> 
               <hi>That the ſcriptures without the authority of the Church are no better than</hi> Aeſops Fables. Thus you ſee how the Grounds of our Reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> are iuſtified by the Fathers, againſt theſe blaſphemies of the Romiſh Church. And for that I knowe it commonly obiected, that we refuſe in diſputation &amp; conference to handle the grou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ds of Religion: I haue thought good in this ſmal Tract to examin (though briefly) the Grounds of your Romiſh Religion, dia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>logue-wiſe; to the end, the truth may be the more liuely diſcerned, by the obiections and anſwers. Wherein if I haue not truely laid downe the Grou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ds of your Religion for the ſubſtance therof: Or that they haue either bin miſtaken by me; or, that (vſing that breuity I haue done) they might be more ſtrongly or effectually vrged on your ſide; or, that the reaſons vrged on our behalfe, be either falſly alleaged, or not truly handled: I ſhall take it as a ſpeciall grace done vnto me; &amp; an argu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t of a reciprocal loue in you, that the faults
<pb facs="tcp:20283:7" rendition="simple:additions"/> thereof may bee ſhewed and manifeſted by ſome of the great Rabbies of your ſide: to the end that the weaknes of our cauſe being laid open, I may be drawen to ioine with you in the religion you profeſſe; &amp; may be brought home to that fold, out of which, &amp; fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> which I am ſure in your iudgeme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ts I am departed &amp; gone aſtray as a loſt ſheep. T<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>is is a charita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble requeſt, &amp; ought not with any colours or ſleights to be refuſed by any of thoſe learned Prieſts in whom you haue intereſt; ſince they know of how great merite the winning of ſoules is. And they may the rather be incou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raged thereto, becauſe theſe things as they are collected by me, are but the doings of a meere lay man; &amp; therfore (if at all) may with greater facility be refuted. But if the ſame ſhall be paſt ouer with general tearms (as heretofore it hath bin in the like) as a thing vnworthy the anſwe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring: Or that I am an heretike &amp; obſtinate, and not to be dealt with: the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> may you eaſily iudge, that either your credit is ſmall with thoſe of your profeſsion: Or your loue &amp; charity very little to me, that ſo earneſtly out of the ſimpli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>city of my heart deſire an anſwer: Or elſe that the weaknes &amp; badnes of your cauſe, cannot a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bide the touchſtone of truth; notwithſtanding their great &amp; ſwelling brags, of challenging vs
<pb facs="tcp:20283:8" rendition="simple:additions"/> to diſpute with them, be ſo often ſounded i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> your ears. And I would to God I might truly ſay of you, that I preſume of my ſelf, that yo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> would reade &amp; ponder theſe things with in differencie, &amp; abandon partiality. To the ef<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>fecting wherof, beſides my praiers, I haue no better meanes than the <hi>Apoſtles doctrine,</hi>
               <note place="margin">1. Theſſ. 5.21 Iames. 1. Cor. 2.5. 2. Cor. 13.5 Iohn 4.1. Act. 17.11.</note> who willeth you &amp; vs all <hi>to examine all things, &amp; to hold faſt that which is good, and not to haue the faith of our Lord Ieſus Chriſt with reſpect of per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons; but to try the ſpirits whether they be of God</hi> therein following the example of the men o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> 
               <hi>Berea, who ſearched the ſcriptures daily,</hi> whether thoſe things were ſo. Thus hauing ſome hope you wil folow this Councel &amp; co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dement comming from ſo high an authority as the Spirit of God: and alſo for my ſatisfa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction (if not for your owne) effect this my ſo charitable &amp; reaſonable a requeſt, as the an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwering hereof, I ſhal ſtil continue my pray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers, to ope<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> our eyes that we may ſee the truth, and that we may be made one flocke &amp; one fold of that great Shepherd Chriſt Ieſus, the Biſhop of our ſoules: To whome, with the Father and the holy Spirit, be all honor, and praiſe, now and for euer. Amen.</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>Yours, in the Lord, T. <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="to_the_reader">
            <pb facs="tcp:20283:8"/>
            <head>The Author to the Reader.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>His ſmal Tract, Chriſtian Reader, was at the firſt compoſed out of a religious zeale, and feruent deſire I had to haue withdrawen ſome of my beſt friends from that Egyptian darkeneſſe of Popiſh ſuperſtition. And this argu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment I the rather made choice of, becauſe it was often obiected, (though very vntruely) that we durſt not handle the Grounds of Religion. After I had finiſhed the ſame, I reco<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mended it to my beſt friends as you may ſee by the Preface thereof: the which was by them reciprocally receiued, hauing no leſſe loue and deſire to reclaime me, than I had to winne them. To which purpoſe they ſent it to ſome one of the learned on their part, by whoſe ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficiencie the ſame might bee fully refuted; which, I aſſure my ſelfe by many probable coniectures was Doctor <hi>Norris.</hi> After I had ſtaied ſome thir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teene weeks, with deſiee and expectation to ſee the anſwere therof; &amp; hauing often ſolicited the ſame: about that time I receiued a Letter (as I take it, from the ſaid D.N.) importing (among many ſeuerall reproches wherewith hee had laboured to
<pb facs="tcp:20283:9"/> giue ſatisfaction to them, and to impeach the cre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dit both of me and my booke) that if I would pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cure two or three of the beſt learned of our ſide to auow it vnder their hands to be the doctrine of our Church; That then hee would take vpon him to proue <hi>14.</hi> or <hi>15.</hi> ſeueral abſurdities, and vntruths therein, as by his Letter here likewiſe ſet downe <hi>verbatim,</hi> may truely appeare. This Letter I then anſwered, as it is here likewiſe inſerted. And when I had ſtayed another quarter of a yeere, and heard of no anſwere made, or inte<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ded to be made, I procured with much importunitie, the redeliue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry of the booke. After which, becauſe I would leaue the ſaid D.N. (as I take it) without all ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuſe, and alſo let my friends ſee, I would preſſe it to the vtmoſt, I procured two reuerend and lear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned Miniſters, M.D. <hi>Sutcliffe,</hi> and M. <hi>Antho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny Wootton,</hi> to ſubſcribe the ſame booke vnder both their hands, in this forme following; <hi>viz, The ſumme and ſubſtance of the doctrine contai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned in this booke is ſound, and ſhal be main<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tained, by the grace of God, againſt the whole packe of Ieſuits and Maſſe-prieſts of the Romiſh Synagogue.</hi> After this, vpon the late diſcouery of thoſe helliſh and matchleſſe trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons againſt our dread Soueraigne, and the whole body of the Realm; hauing heard, that the ſaid D. N. was apprehended and committed to <hi>Bridewel</hi>
               <pb facs="tcp:20283:9"/> (where I likewiſe vnderſtood that he was not cloſe priſoner) I repaired vnto him, and ſhewed him this my booke, with the ſubſcriptio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> annexed and before ſpecified, dema<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ding of him whether he had ſeen the booke, and were the author of that Letter. Which hee denied, affirming that he had neuer ſeen it till the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>: reſeruing belike (according to their maner of Equivocating) that he had neuer ſeen it till then, ſubſcribed in that maner, or with ſome ſuch men<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tall reſeruation. All which conſidered (though I am ſtil perſwaded, that he was the Author ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of) I haue preferred the publiſhing of it (though therein mine own wants &amp; defects for the maner of handling, might by the iudicious &amp; learned be in ſome ſort taxed) rather than to bury it in ſile<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce: for that I hope it may bring ſome benefit (not vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>worthy my trauel) to the indifferent Reader, and may happily effect that which thereby I firſt inten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded; when they ſhall ſee I am not afraid (in regard of the doctrine therin) to diuulge it to the whole world. And the rather I am incouraged hereto; for that the ſame is not onely the doctrine of the beſt learned writers of this our age &amp; Nation (as it is by me collected) but alſo is warra<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ted to be iuſtified by men of ſo great ſufficiencie, that I ſhall not need to feare ſhipwracke though the ſeas ſwell, and the ſtorme riſe neuer ſo hie. And ſo farewel in Chriſt.</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>T. <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="letter">
            <pb facs="tcp:20283:10"/>
            <head>The true Copie of the Letter I receiued.</head>
            <p>I Haue peruſed your Treatiſe dedicated to your deareſt Couſins: which I find to be a vaine bun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dle of words, without ſubstance, order, learning, or trueth: and if you can procure, that two or three of the beſt learned of your ſide, will auow it vnder their hands to be the doctrine of your Church (elſe I knowe they will all diſclaime from it, hauing ſeen the errors and weakneſſe thereof) I will take vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on me to ſhew, that in ſo ſhort and friuolous a diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>courſe, you could hardly compile more abſurdities than there are couched. I wil proue, for example, that you mistake, and vnderſtand not the queſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons your ſelfe would ſeeme to handle: that you moſt ſhamefully belie our Catholike writers: guilefully alleage both Fathers and Scriptures: heap teſtimo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nies of ancient writers, without end or purpoſe: make obiections to your ſelfe, and anſwere the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> not at all: I will proue that you alleage falſe Councels amongst the nu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ber of true, without any difference or diſtinctio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>: that you reproue Fathers writings as counterfeit, which are moſt approued: count bookes of Scriptures Apocrypha, which are Cano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nicall. I will prooue, in theſe few lines, you write contrary to your ſelfe: contrary to your owne wri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters.
<pb facs="tcp:20283:10"/> I will prooue that the booke is fraught with moſt palpable lies, errors, corruptions, &amp; falſifica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions: if you wil but procure, as I ſayd before, that it may be countenanced by publike authority, with the ſubſcriptio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s of <hi>2.</hi> or <hi>3.</hi> the moſt deepeſt ſchollers of your Sect. In the meane time I let it paſſe with this bare cenſure; and intreate you but to reade <hi>Bellarmine de Pont. &amp; de Concil.</hi> where you ſhall find moſt of your obiections of the errors of Popes and Councels already refuted.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="letter">
            <head>The true Copie of my Letter in anſwere hereof.</head>
            <p>TO accuſe without proofe, to ſay and ſhewe no reaſon (of all which, you in your Letter may iuſtly be taxed) might truely argue mee to want both ſubſtance, order, learning and trueth, accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to your owne phraſe. And, to free your ſelfe from the ſame imputation, haue you yeelded any other reaſon againſt my booke (which you intitie a vaine bundle of words) than a boaſting bundle of vaine brags? <hi>Turpe eſt doctori, &amp;c.</hi> But you would ſeem to giue a reaſon why your bare cenſure (as you rightly haue cenſured your ſelfe) ſhould be a ſufficient anſwere to my booke; vnleſſe I can pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cure two or three of the beſt learned of our ſide, to
<pb facs="tcp:20283:11"/> auow it vnder their hands to be the doctrine of our Church: Elſe you knowe (or elſe you are a falſe prophet) they will all diſclaime from it, hauing ſeen the errors and weakeneſſe thereof. But leſt I ſeeme to taxe you with want of learning and truth, with bare words onely, without proofe; as you in the height and eminency of your iudgement haue cen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſured me: Can there be greater ſhew of ignorance, tha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> to require that to be auowed to be the doctrine of our Church, which hath beene already by the learned of our ſide publiſhed to the whole world in many of their ſeueral books daily exta<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t to be ſeen? And, that I co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mit not your fault, To ſpeake with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out proofe: do you but inſtance any one point of do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrine in all my booke; and if I doe not ſhew where the ſame is iuſtified by the learned of our ſide; I will willingly acknowledge that error wherewith I haue here charged your ſelfe. And to make it yet more euident: if I ſhould require you to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firme the doctrine you ſhould deliuer by two or three of your best Diuines; when the ſame had been publiſhed already by <hi>Bellarmine, Gregori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>us Valencia,</hi> your <hi>Rhemiſts</hi> and others: could any thing conuince me of groſſer ignorance? It ſeemes (notwithſtanding your vaine brag, That that you would prooue <hi>15.</hi> particularities where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>with you haue charged me and my booke) that you are but meanely read in controuerſies: otherwiſe
<pb facs="tcp:20283:11"/> you could not be ignorant, that there is no doctrine in my booke that is not auowed &amp; publiſhed, either by <hi>Iewel</hi> againſt <hi>Harding,</hi> or the B. of <hi>Win<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cheſter</hi> that now is, or by D. <hi>Rainolds,</hi> D. <hi>Whit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taker,</hi> D. <hi>Fulke,</hi> D. <hi>Sparke,</hi> with many others. And albeit I could not haue co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>firmed thus much by theſe cleere teſtimonies: yet if you had Chriſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>anly and charitably weighed with what mind my requeſt was made in my Preface to my Kinſmen (wherin I had intreated in theſe very words, That if I had not truely layd downe the Grounds of your Religion for the ſubſtance; or, if they had been mistaken by mee; or, vſing that breuity I had done, they might more ſtrongly haue been vrged; or, if the reaſons I had vrged, had been falſly allea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged; or not truely handled &amp;c. That I would haue taken it as a ſpeciall grace done vnto me, &amp;c. to haue had the faults thereof manifeſted &amp; ſhewed, that I might haue been drawen to haue been of the ſame profeſſion with them, &amp;c.) you would neuer haue inſisted vpon ſuch a ſubſcription of the dee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pest ſchollers of our Sect, thereby to haue cauilled and ſhifted off the anſwere of my booke; how vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>learned ſoeuer it had been, either for the methode, or matter. But you imagined, your wordes were ſo powerfull; that it was ſufficient for your follow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers, that you had onely giuen your cenſure, with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out ſhewing any further reaſon. Beſides (my re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quest
<pb facs="tcp:20283:12"/> being ſo charitable &amp; reaſonable) it ſeemes you haue ſmall care of winning of ſoules: other<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe I perſwade my ſelfe (if you had been aſſured of your owne ſufficiencie to haue anſwered the booke) you would neuer haue inſiſted vpon ſo fri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uolous a requeſt: Nor haue preferred the vaine<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>glory of hauing a learned aduerſary, before the hope you might (not without good probabilitie) haue conceiued in reducing many by my conuerſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on (or rather indeede peruerſion) to haue been of your profeſſion. I profeſſe, for my part, I can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not ſee any other ground of your Letter directed to me, than to inlarge your own oſtentation and glory to your followers. For, to vndertake that you would prooue this, and this, and not to haue returned the booke, whereunto you required the ſubſcription; what can be inferred thereof, but that you would winne time to delay and ſhift off the anſwere? But if you will proceede according to my requeſt in the Preface of my booke, &amp; proue as much as by your Letter you haue preſumed, without ſeeking ſome new ſhift to delay the time further: I will engage my ſelfe, that the ſame ſhall bee replied to, by one euery way equall to your ſelfe in all knowledge and literature: who (notwithſtanding the aduan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tage you promiſe to your ſelfe, of the abſurdities committed by me) ſhall defend the cauſe I ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nage, and ſubſcribe the ſame defence with his
<pb facs="tcp:20283:12"/> owne hand: Otherwiſe, you ſhall gaine thus much by your trauell, that I wil willingly ſubmit my ſelfe to be a member of your Church. If you refuſe theſe reaſonable conditions, I muſt vſe your owne olde phraſe, and tell you, that I muſt needs thinke your cauſe ſo weake, that it cannot bee maintained. I omit to charge you with inciuility, in giuing me the Lie: For that I cannot but pitie your ignorance that cannot, as it ſeemes (though all were falſe I had ſayd, ſpeaking by relation) distinguiſh be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tweene a lie and vntrueth. And whereas you re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferre me, in the concluſion of your Letter, to <hi>Bel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>larmin de Pont. &amp; de Concilijs,</hi> where you ſay, I ſhall find moſt of my obiections of the errors of Popes and Councels refuted: So can I whenſoeuer you ſhall inſtance any ſuch particular refutation (which may eaſe you of ſome paines, if it be ſo ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficiently performed) referre you to ſome of the au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thors of our ſide, where the ſame reaſons haue been with no leſſe ſufficiencie handled and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plied to: aſſuring my ſelfe; That neither any of you haue, or can, make any obiections againſt the doctrine, we profeſſe, that hath not beene alrea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy obiected, and likewiſe by vs anſwered. And if any will ſhew me the contrary, I will be beholding to him, neither will I ſhut mine eyes againſt the trueth. If this which I haue ſayd may any whit preuaile with you to make ſhew of that great lear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning
<pb facs="tcp:20283:13"/> whereof in your Letter you haue boaſted, by your liberall vndertaking to proue ſo many parti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>culars (which hitherto as great Clerkes, as your ſelfe haue failed in) I ſhall be ready and willing to performe whatſoeuer I haue herein promiſed. O<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>therwiſe I pray you returne the booke, as you re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiued it; and you ſhall ſee, that ſome ſuch courſe ſhal be taken, as ſhal make you bluſh to haue cenſured ſo raſhly.</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>
                  <hi>Your friend, in Chriſtianity and Charitie,</hi> T. <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:20283:13"/>
            <head>A briefe view of the weak<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe of the Grounds of Popiſh <hi>Religion, as is euident by theſe</hi> ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerall Obiections and <hi>An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſweres following.</hi>
            </head>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Proteſtant.</speaker>
               <p n="1">
                  <hi>1</hi> 
                  <seg rend="decorInit">W</seg>Hereupon doe you ground your Religion?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Papiſt.</speaker>
               <p>
                  <hi>Vpon the word of God in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terpreted by the Church, which cannot erre.</hi>
               </p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Proteſtant.</speaker>
               <p n="2">
                  <hi>2</hi> What do you vnderſtand by the Word of God?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Papiſt.</speaker>
               <p>
                  <hi>The Scriptures and Traditions.</hi>
               </p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Proteſtant.</speaker>
               <p n="3">
                  <hi>3</hi> What doe you vnderſtand by the Church?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <pb n="2" facs="tcp:20283:14"/>
               <speaker>Papist.</speaker>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">Stapl. princi. doct. l. 7, ca. 10. l. 11, ca. 5 Hervaeus de poteſt. pap. &amp; R. Cupers Petrus de Palude de poteſt. papae, A<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>. 4.</note>
                  <hi>The Church is ſometimes taken for the auncient Fathers; ſometimes for generall Councels; Sometimes we preferre the head of the Church, the Pope, before both.</hi>
               </p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Proteſtant.</speaker>
               <p n="4">
                  <hi>4</hi> Well: that we may procéede orderly in the handling of theſe particulars: Doe you re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiue all the bookes of the Old and Newe Te<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtaments, with equall authoritie?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Papiſt.</speaker>
               <p>
                  <hi>No; but following the Tradition of the Church, we diſtinguiſh betweene the Cano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nicall and the Apocrypha.</hi>
               </p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Proteſtant.</speaker>
               <p n="5">
                  <hi>5</hi> Which are the Bookes which you call Apocrypha?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Papiſt.</speaker>
               <p>
                  <hi>Wee hold as Apocrypha; The prayer of <hi>Manaſſes;</hi> the third and fourth booke of Eſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dras: Alſo, others that are not vſuall in your Engliſh Bibles: as an Appendix to the booke of <hi>Iob;</hi> The 151. Pſalme; A preface to the Lamentations of <hi>Ieremie;</hi> The third and fourth booke of Maccabees.</hi>
               </p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Proteſtant.</speaker>
               <p n="6">
                  <hi>6</hi> Well, we agrée with you in the reiecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of theſe Bookes: And we likewiſe conſent
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:20283:14" rendition="simple:additions"/> with you, That all the bookes of the New Te<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtament, as they ſtand, are to be receiued of all for Canonicall Scripture: What are then the Bookes that are in queſtion betwéene vs?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Papist.</speaker>
               <p>
                  <hi>There be 7. Chapters of <hi>Hester,</hi> certaine Stories annexed to <hi>Daniel;</hi> as, Of <hi>Bel</hi> and the Drago<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, Of <hi>Suſanna,</hi> Of the three childre<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>; Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo the Epiſtle of <hi>Baruch,</hi> ioyned to <hi>Ieremie;</hi> Then the books of <hi>Tobie; Iudeth;</hi> The Wiſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom of <hi>Salomon;</hi> Eccleſiaſticus; Two bookes of the Maccabees: Theſe we repute as Cano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nical, both by the teſtimony of the Fathers, and by the authoritie of the Church.</hi>
               </p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Proteſtant.</speaker>
               <p n="7">
                  <hi>7</hi> Well, Since I ſhall haue cauſe here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>after to ſpeake of the Church, I wil but brief<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly giue a touch to the reaſon of the refuſall of theſe Bookes. All Canonicall Scriptures in the old Teſtament, were written by the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phets: <hi>We haue a ſure word of the Prophets,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">2. Pet. 1.19</note> ſaith Saint <hi>Peter.</hi> And Saint <hi>Paul</hi> calleth them <hi>The Scriptures of the Prophets.</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Rom. 16.2<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>
                  </note> But none of thoſe Bookes afore named, of <hi>Tobias,</hi> of <hi>Iudeth,</hi> and the reſt, were written by the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phets: Therefore none of thoſe Bookes are Canonical. All the Bookes of the olde Teſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, that were Canonicall, were acknow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledged
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:20283:15"/> of the Iewes and Hebrewes, and writ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten in Hebrew: But the Iewes receiued none of theſe Books into y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Canon of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Scriptures, though to them were committed the Oracles of God, as Saint <hi>Paul</hi> ſayth: neither were they in the Hebrew tongue, <hi>Ergo,</hi> they are not Canonicall. But to the end you may ſée how well the Church, of which you boaſt, agrées with the teſtimonies of the Fathers, both anci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ent &amp; moderne;<note place="margin">Hier: prol: galeat: &amp; E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>i. ad Pauli. &amp; in praefat. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>i. Reg: &amp; in praefat. in <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ro. Salom.</note> I wil giue you this taſte brief<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly. <hi>S. Hierom</hi> ſaith, The Church readeth thoſe bookes, but receiueth them not amongſt the Canonicall Scriptures. The ſumme of all which is confirmed by theſe teſtimonies fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowing: whoſe particular ſpéeches to this pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe for breuitie ſake I omit, referring you to the places themſelues, as they are here follow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing ſet down. As <hi>Rufinus</hi> in his expoſition vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on the Créede: <hi>Cyril</hi> of <hi>Hieruſalem</hi> in the <hi>4.</hi> of his Catechiſme: <hi>Athanaſius in Synop. Sacr. Scriptur. Nazianzen in Carminis: Epiphan. li. de Menſur. &amp; ponder. Cyprian</hi> vpon the Créed: <hi>Damaſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>en. ca. 49. Hugo de Sanct. Vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctor. de Sacram. in prol. li. 1. ca. 7. Radulphus in Leuit. li. 14. c. 1. Lyra in prol. in li. Apocry. Hugo Cardina. in prol. Ioſu.</hi> All theſe contra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dict the opinion of the Papiſts in this contro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerſie: yea, <hi>Arias Montanus,</hi> a chiefe Papiſt,
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:20283:15" rendition="simple:additions"/> in his Hebrew Bible, writeth in the forefront, &amp; principal leafe of the booke; There are added, (ſaith he) in this Edition, the bookes written in Gréek; which the Catholike Church following the Canon of the Hebrews, reckoneth amongſt the Apocrypha.</p>
               <p>The Councel of <hi>Laodicea,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Can. 59. Conſtanti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nop: in Trul lo Can. 2.</note> allured by a ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neral Councel of <hi>Conſtantinople</hi> in <hi>Trullo,</hi> did ſet downe the ſame Canon of the ſcriptures, which both the old Church had, &amp; our church doth hold: &amp; commandeth, <hi>Ne aliqui praeterea le<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gantur, &amp; in auctoritate<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> recipia<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tur: <hi>That none beſides be read &amp; receiued into authority.</hi>
                  </hi> I omit many ſeueral contradictions in al, or moſt of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> books which we reiect, &amp; they allow, wherby they may be conuinced not to be written by y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſpirit of God: which is alwaies one &amp; the ſame. Sée the <hi>4. Eſdras 10.20. &amp; 2. Maccab. 2.4. &amp; 1. Mac. 1.6. &amp;. 8.</hi> touching <hi>Antiochus:</hi> yea, we wil confeſſe w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> 
                  <hi>Bellarmin,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Bellar. de ver. Dei, li. 1. cap. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>.</note> That the ſcriptures may be proued, to be the Word of God, by the conſtant &amp; perpetual truth of the Prophecies: By y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> wonderful harmony &amp; conſent of the holy writers of the Scriptures: By the Spirit of God, which is a principall witnes vnto vs: By the ſcripture it ſelfe, <hi>2. Tim. 3.</hi> Laſtly, by y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny &amp; great miracles wrought by the Prophets &amp; Apoſtles; which do teſtifie for y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> truth thereof.</p>
               <pb n="6" facs="tcp:20283:16"/>
               <p>To the which touchſtone, if the Scriptures whith wee reiect, were brought to the triall, they would eaſily bee conuinced, to bee but droſſe, and vnworthy to ſtand in the rankes of thoſe that are Canonicall. But how doe you knowe which are the Scriptures? and in them, which be Canonicall, which be Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crypha?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Papist.</speaker>
               <p>
                  <hi>I knowe by the teſtimonie of the Church which be the Scriptures: and in them, which be Canonicall, and which be Apocrypha.</hi>
               </p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Protestant.</speaker>
               <p n="8">
                  <hi>8</hi> How do you know which is the Church? And by what meanes may it be knowen, that the Church hath authoritie to determine, which be Scriptures, and which of them be Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nonicall, and which be Apocrypha?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Papiſt.</speaker>
               <p>
                  <hi>There be many notes and markes recko<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned vp by the learned of our ſide, by which the Church may be knowen: But we inſiſt chiefly vpon theſe; Antiquitie, Vnitie, Vni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerſality, Succeſsion, and the power of Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>racles. And for the authority of the Church, it is prooued by the Scriptures.</hi>
               </p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Proteſtant.</speaker>
               <p n="9">
                  <hi>9</hi> This anſwere is common to all Here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tikes:
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:20283:16"/> for they alleage, ſomtimes the<note n="a" place="margin">Author. ope Imper. in Mat. Ho. 48.</note> Church; ſometime<note n="b" place="margin">Iren. adu Haere, lib. 3. cap. 2.</note> Traditions; ſometime<note n="c" place="margin">Aug. co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tr Maxim. Ari<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> epiſc. li. 1.</note> Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cels; ſometime<note n="d" place="margin">De Bapt. c. 6. li. 3.</note> Fathers; ſometime<note n="e" place="margin">In Ioh. ca 2. tract. 13</note> Mira<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cles; ſometime<note n="f" place="margin">De vnit. eccle c. 16.</note> Viſions; &amp; ſometime<note n="g" place="margin">Epiſt. 65. ad gener.</note> Suc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſion of Biſhops: yea,<note n="h" place="margin">Act. 19.27</note> 
                  <hi>Demetrius</hi> preten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded Vniuerſalitie. And the<note n="i" place="margin">Act. 17, 18, 19.</note> Philoſophers, Epicures, and Stoickes, Antiquity. And<note n="k" place="margin">Vinc. Lir. ca. 6, ca. 4.</note> 
                  <hi>Vincentius Lirinenſis</hi> diſproueth Vniuer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſalitie, by the example of the <hi>Arrians:</hi> and Antiquity by the example of the Donatiſts. And for their<note n="l" place="margin">In Chron. Suput. Rom. prat. Sigon de Regn. Ital li. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>.</note> Vnitie, let that appeare in the ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerall oppoſitions of their Popes, one con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demning the decrées of another; and decrée<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing one contrary to another. And therefore, this is no ſufficie<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t reaſon, for a man to ground his faith and Religion, if we beléeue the<note n="m" place="margin">Stapleto<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, Fortreſſe, &amp; Hart. ag. Ra. pag. 118.</note> Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piſts in the like cauſe: for it is a common ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iection by them, that becauſe Heretikes al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leage the Scripture, therefore they are no ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fieient rule. Moreouer, this anſwere paſſeth the limits of the propoſition; for it preſuppo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeth the authoritie of the Church to be prooued by the Scriptures, and the Scriptures to be prooued by the authority of the Church; which is, <hi>Ignotum per ignotius; Idem per idem;</hi> A proofe of a thing vnknowen, by a thing leſſe knowen, and ſo no proofe at all. Therefore to procéede to the next part of the diuiſion, what doe
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:20283:17"/> you vnderſtand by Traditions?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Papiſt.</speaker>
               <p>
                  <hi>I vnderſtand Apoſtilicall doctrine, com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monly called vnwritten verities: and as D.B. P. in his booke againſt M. <hi>Perkins,</hi> diuides them; Some are Diuine, ſome Apoſtolicall, and ſome Eccleſiaſticall: all which (accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to the Councel of <hi>Trent</hi>) are to be recei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued with equall reuerence,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Conc. Trid. Seſſ. 4.</note> 
                  <hi>and religious af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fection, as we do the Scriptures.</hi>
               </p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Proteſtant.</speaker>
               <p n="10">
                  <hi>10</hi> How doe you proue Traditions, or vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>written verities to bee Apoſtolicall doctrine, and that they be Diuine, Apoſtolicall, and Ec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cleſiaſticall; and that they are to bee receiued with equall reuerence, and religious affection, as we doe the Scriptures?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Papist.</speaker>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">2. Theſſ. 2, 15.</note>
                  <hi>I proue it by the Scriptures interpreted by the Church. Saint <hi>Paul</hi> ſaith, <hi>Hold the Tra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions which yee haue learned, whether it bee by word,</hi>
                  </hi>
                  <note place="margin">Conc. Trid. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>eſſ. 4.</note> 
                  <hi>or by Epistle; <hi>which by the Churches expoſition, proueth vnwritten verities to be receiued, with equall authoritie to the Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures: and to explane the ſame D.B.P. afore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſayd affirmeth, that Diuine Traditions come from our Sauiour Chriſt; Apoſtolicall Tra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ditions from the Apoſtles; And the Decrees
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:20283:17"/> of the Church, hee tearmeth Eccleſiaſticall Traditions; which are likewiſe of equall au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thoritie with the Scriptures.</hi>
                  </hi>
               </p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Protestant.</speaker>
               <p n="11">
                  <hi>11</hi> This is a common fault with you, to vſe this point of Sophiſtrie, called by the Logici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans, <hi>Petitio principij:</hi> for you wil ſtil take it for graunted, that you are the Church, though you neuer prooue it. And this is a neceſſary conſequence, That if the trueth be doubted of, the church muſt néedes bee much more doub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted of: becauſe the Church is the number of men profeſſing the trueth; And how can the profeſſors of the trueth be ſeuered from others, ſo long as the trueth, by which they ſhould bee knowen, is in queſtion: Therefore the ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſing your ſelues to be y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> church, when your faith &amp; Religion ſhould be tried, is fond &amp; vain. But if S. <hi>Paul</hi> in that place by <hi>(Deliuered)</hi> &amp; <hi>(Tradition)</hi> meane nothing but the doctrine deliuered to them by word of mouth, &amp; yet com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>priſed in Scripture too, then muſt you graunt, that you are deceiued to thinke, that vnwrit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten Traditions are approued by <hi>S. Pauls</hi> Tra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ditions. Now what the things were which S. <hi>Paul</hi> deliuered by word, to y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Theſſalonians, is ſhewed in the <hi>17</hi> of the <hi>Acts,</hi> ſaying, Now as they paſſed thorow <hi>Amphipolis,</hi> and <hi>Apolonia,</hi>
                  <pb n="10" facs="tcp:20283:18" rendition="simple:additions"/> they came to <hi>Theſſalonica,</hi> where was a Syna<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gogue of the Iewes; and <hi>Paul,</hi> as his maner was, entred in vnto them, and thrée Sabbath dayes hee diſcourſed vnto them out of the Scriptures, opening and alleaging, That Chriſt muſt haue ſuffered and riſen againe, &amp;c. In which wordes it is opened, both what <hi>Paul</hi> deliuered to the Theſſalonians, by word; and from whence. From whence? Out of the Scriptures. What? That it behooued Chriſt to ſuffer and riſe againe. Beſides, Saint <hi>Paul</hi> witneſſeth both to ſmall and great, that hee ſaid no other thing, than that which the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phets and <hi>Moyſes</hi> did ſay ſhould come.<note place="margin">Act. 26, 22</note> The Traditions therefore that <hi>Paul</hi> doth exhort the Theſſalonians to hold; is the Tradition of the Goſpel: as Saint <hi>Ambroſe</hi> writing vpon the ſame place, calleth it very well; which the reaſon alſo doth prooue, that Saint <hi>Ambroſe</hi> noteth that <hi>Paul</hi> doth there gather, ſaying, God hath raiſed you to ſaluation by our Goſpel: therefore ſtand ye faſt, and holde the Traditions which ye haue learned, whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther it be by word, or by Epiſtle. Now I hope there is none ſo impudent to denie, that the Goſpel is written. But here another difficul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie incounters vs: If it were granted by the Churches interpretation; that there were do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrines
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:20283:18"/> or Traditions, Diuine, Apoſtolicall, or Eccleſiaſticall, deliuered by word of mouth: vpon what ſure grounds might wee be aſſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red, which be the Traditions, that were ſo deliuered by Chriſt, his Apoſtles, or the Church.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Papiſt.</speaker>
               <p>
                  <hi>The ancient Fathers &amp; chiefe Papiſts, doe plainely teach, that many points of doctrine, wherein you varie from vs: as, halowing the Font, the bleſsing of the oyle, the anointing the Baptized, Exorciſmes, Faſtes, Feſtiuities, prayer for the dead, prayer to Saints, wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhipping of Images, the oblation of the Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crifice, their Annealing, their Primacie of <hi>Rome,</hi> their fiue pretended Sacraments, the merit of workes, their ſatisfactions, the numbring their ſinnes to the Prieſt, their Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>al preſence, their halfe Communio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, &amp;c.</hi> (See the preface for Prieſts: <hi>and,</hi> See Maſter <hi>Middletons</hi> booke; called <hi>Papiſto-Maſtix, Sect. 5.) &amp; almoſt all theſe things which you defend againſt vs, are proued by the Fathers to be deliuered by Tradition.</hi>
               </p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Proteſtant.</speaker>
               <p n="12">
                  <hi>12</hi> This ſheweth euidently, that you are guilty of the ſame fault, that the Phariſes
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:20283:19" rendition="simple:additions"/> were,<note place="margin">Mark. 7.9</note> by Chriſts owne reproofe, ſaying, <hi>You cast aſide the commaundements of God, to main<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine your owne Traditions:</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Mat 15.9.</note> 
                  <hi>teaching for do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrine, mens precepts.</hi> So that as Saint <hi>Peter</hi> hath cenſured you,<note place="margin">1. Pet. 2.18</note> 
                  <hi>Yee are not redeemed from the vaine Traditions of your Fathers.</hi> Beſides you chuſe rather to make the Fathers to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tradict themſelues, (as I haue ſhewed in the preface of this treatiſe) than to acknowledge with vs as the trueth is, that the Traditions mentioned by the Fathers, are no parts or points of the Catholike faith. But doeth your Church practiſe all thoſe Traditions which are deliuered by the Fathers, to be either Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uine, Apoſtolicall, or Eccleſiaſticall?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Papist.</speaker>
               <p>
                  <hi>Yes: and although ſhe did not, yet is the Churches authority ſufficient to abrogate, or admit, which ſhe pleaſeth.</hi>
               </p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Proteſtant.</speaker>
               <p n="13">
                  <hi>13</hi> Indéede you take that libertie to your ſelues, without all warrant, either of Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture or Fathers: For S <hi>Hierome,</hi> which is one of the Fathers alleaged by you for Tra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ditions,<note place="margin">Dialo. co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tr: Lucif. ca. 4.</note> deliuereth it as an Apoſtolike Tradi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion; On the Lords day, and throughout euery Penticoſt, neither to pray on the knées, nor to faſt. The temper of milke and honie, giuen to
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:20283:19"/> them that were newly baptiſed,<note place="margin">Tertul. de Coro. Milit. Nu. 3.</note> is confirmed by <hi>Tertullian,</hi> who likewiſe reckoneth vp a number of Rites grounded vpon Tradition: As, that the baptized ſhould abſtaine from waſhing, a whole wéeke after Baptiſme, with much croſſing at euery going out, at euery ſteppe, at euery comming in, at putting on of apparel, at putting on of ſhooes, at waſhings, at tables, at lights, at beddes, at ſeates, &amp;c. all theſe are deliuered as the Apoſtles Tradi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions: which yet the Papiſts themſelues ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerue not. And if theſe be not Apoſtolike Tra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ditions, what warrant haue we for any of the reſt? For, as for the Churches authority in aboliſhing of theſe; you may ſay as much of the holy Scriptures: for you haue ſaid before, That Traditions vnwritten,<note place="margin">Conc. Trid. Seſſ. 4.</note> were of equall authoritie with the Scriptures. But doe you thinke the authority of the ancient Fathers, to be a ſufficient ground, to leade vs to accept of all the Doctrine deliuered by Tradition: and that whatſoeuer is deliuered by them, is to be receiued without exception.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Papiſt.</speaker>
               <p>
                  <hi>Yes, the ioynt conſent of the Fathers,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Sta. prine. doctr. li. 7. ca. 13. &amp; li. 1<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> ca. 5. Hart. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> ag: Ray. ca. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>
                     <g ref="char:punc">▪</g> diui. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>.</note> 
                  <hi>is an abſolute Rule; being indeede the Chur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches expoſition.</hi>
               </p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <pb n="14" facs="tcp:20283:20" rendition="simple:additions"/>
               <speaker>Protestant.</speaker>
               <p n="14">
                  <hi>14</hi> Then muſt you wholly relinquiſh all your doctrine and Traditions vnwritten: for all the Fathers doe with ioint conſent yéelde all their authority to the Scriptures; laying it for a Ground, that nothing neceſſary to ſal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uation, is to be beléeued without the authori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie of the Scriptures; nay, that themſelues, are not to be credited without the ſcriptures, as ſhal manifeſtly appeare by y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> teſtimonies of theſe Fathers following: yea, <hi>S. Auguſtine</hi> is ſo abſolute for vs in moſt of his bookes<note n="*" place="margin">Aug: Ep: 19 ad Hiero: E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pi. 48, Vin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cent: Ep 111, Fortunatia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>no. Epi 112, to Paulina. Cont. Faſtu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> li 11, c. 5. Contr. Creſ. gram: li. 2, ca: 11 &amp; 32, De Bap: co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t: Don li. 2. c. 2 De merit. &amp; remiſſ. pec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cat. cont. Pelag. lib: 3, cap: 7. De natur. &amp; gra. ca. 61, De gracia Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſti co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tra Pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lag. cap. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>. De nuptijs &amp; concupiſce<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t: lib. 2, ca. 23.</note>; that he would haue the Church, ſought onely in the ſcriptures; &amp; heretikes confuted onely by the ſcriptures. To whoſe only authority in many places he profeſſeth, that he himſelfe will be bound. So that you muſt either make theſe Fathers contrary to themſelues: Or elſe grant that Traditions are not of abſolute ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſitie to be receiued. But for that this is a maine point, which the Papiſts inſiſt on; I will cleare the ſame euidently by foure iuſt exceptions, which I referre to the indifferent cenſure of anie. Firſt, I will prooue, that the Fathers haue attributed all ſufficiencie to the Scriptures, and haue ſubmitted all their au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thorities vnto them. Secondly, That the Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers haue held diuers errors: vpon which it
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:20283:20"/> neceſſarily followeth, that if they might erre in one thing, they might erre in another. Third<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, that they are often reiected by the Papiſts; yea, euen the greater number ſometimes: contrary to their owne rule; and therefore may with as great reaſo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> be reiected by vs. Fourth<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, That there are many counterf<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>its bearing the names of ancient Fathers; and that often times they are alleaged by the Papiſts to a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>buſe vs: all which particular exceptions I will briefly prooue in order as they lie.</p>
               <p>Firſt, Saint <hi>Baſil</hi> ſaith,<note place="margin">Tract. de fide.</note> it is a moſt certain argument of infidelity, and a moſt certaine ſigne of pride, if any man wil reiect any of thoſe things that are written; or bring in any thing that is not written: when our Lord ſaith, <hi>My ſheepe, heare my voice,</hi> and, <hi>a ſtranger they will not heare.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Tertullian</hi> ſaith,<note place="margin">De reſurrect<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> carnis.</note> Take away from Here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tikes thoſe things which they hold with Eth<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nikes, that they may ſtay their queſtions vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on the Scriptures onely, and they are not able to ſtand.</p>
               <p>Saint <hi>Auguſtine</hi> ſaith,<note place="margin">De doctr. Chriſt. li. 2. ca. 9.</note> All things that con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerne faith and manners, or beliefe and life, are plainely written in the Scriptures.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Chryſoſtome</hi> ſaith,<note place="margin">In 2. ad Theſſa. Ho. 3</note> That euery thing is cleare and euident by the Scriptures; and
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:20283:21"/> whatſoeuer things are neceſſary, they are e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uident.</p>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">In Eusng: Ioh. li. 12, cap. 68.</note>
                  <hi>Cyril</hi> ſaith, That ſuch of the things done by Chriſt are written, as the writers thought, to be ſufficient for maners and doctrine.</p>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">Epiſt: 11, inter epiſt: Auguſt.</note>In the controuerſie betw<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>xt S. <hi>Auſtin</hi> and S. <hi>Hierome,</hi> touching <hi>Peters</hi> reproofe; <hi>Hie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rome</hi> alleaged more Fathers on his ſide, and made ſo great account of them, that he deſired <hi>Auſtin</hi> to ſuffer him to erre with ſuch men, if he thought him to erre.<note place="margin">Epiſt: 19.</note> To whom Saint <hi>Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtin</hi> replied, that peraduenture he might finde as many, if he had read much: But I (ſaith he) haue <hi>Paul</hi> the Apoſtle himſelfe, in ſtead of theſe all, and aboue theſe all. To him I doe flie; to him doe I appeale, from all the doctors, his in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terpreters who are of other minds. &amp;c.</p>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">Epiſt: 126, ad Euagrium.</note>S. <hi>Hierome</hi> yéelding his opinion to <hi>Eua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>grius,</hi> a meane man; after he had ſhewed the iudgements of <hi>Origen, Didimus, Hipollitus, Irenaeus, Euſebius Ceſarienſis, Emiſenus, A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pollinarius,</hi> and <hi>Euſtathius</hi> ſaith, To bring foorth the witneſſes it was my part; let it bée yours to iudge of the credit of the witneſſes.</p>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">Orig. Hom: 1, ſuper Ie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>em.</note>
                  <hi>Origen</hi> confeſſeth, That their iudgements, without witneſſe of the Scriptures, were of no credit.</p>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">Hierom. in Pſal. 98.</note>
                  <hi>Hierome</hi> writeth, That all which they
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:20283:21"/> ſpake, they were to proue by the Scriptures:<note place="margin">Hier. in Ma<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>. 23.</note> and ſaith in another place, That which hath not authority from the Scriptures, as eaſily is deſpiſed as approued.</p>
               <p>Saint <hi>Baſil</hi> ſaith,<note place="margin">Baſil in E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thicis defi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> 8.</note> If euery thing that is not of faith be ſinne, as S. <hi>Paul</hi> affirmeth, and faith come by hearing, and hearing <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>y the word of God, <hi>Ergo,</hi> whatſoeuer is without (or beſides) the Diuine Scriptures, becauſe it is not of faith, it is ſinne.</p>
               <p>Saint <hi>Hillary:</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Hillar<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>us ad Conſtan. Auguſt.</note> Séekeſt thou for faith, Em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perour? (ſaith he to <hi>Conſtantius</hi>) heare it not out of the late Scrolles, but out of Gods Bookes. Heare, I beſeech thée that which is written of Chriſt, leſt vnder pretence thereof, things not written be preached. And in ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther place preſſing his aduerſary, Thou,<note place="margin">Idem de Trinitat. li. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>
                  </note> ſaith he, that denieſt things written, what remai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neth but that thou beléeue things vnwritten? You ſée that was counted for a paſſing abſur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dity in that age, which ſince the Papiſts haue eſtabliſhed, as the ſureſt way to diſcerne trueth.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Tertullian</hi> refelling the Heretike <hi>Hermo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>genes:</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Tert, ad Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>de praeſci. ad Haeres.</note> I adore (ſaith hee) the fulneſſe of the Scriptures; let <hi>Hermogenes</hi> ſhew me where this (that he teacheth) is written: If it be not written, let him feare the curſe prouided for
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:20283:22"/> adders and diminiſhers. It ſéemes this Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther vnderſtood the Text of <hi>Deuteronomie,</hi> and the <hi>Apocalypſe,</hi> otherwiſe than <hi>D.B.P.</hi> in his booke againſt M. <hi>Perkins.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">Iren. li. 3. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ap. 1.</note>
                  <hi>Irenaeus</hi> ſaith, The diſpoſition of our ſalua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, we knew by none other, than by thoſe, by whom the Goſpel came vnto vs: the which at firſt they preached by mouth; but afterward by Gods appointment, they did deliuer it to vs in writing, that it ſhould be the foundation and pillar of our faith.</p>
               <p>The mountaines of Iſrael, whereon God promiſed to féede his flocke,<note place="margin">Aug. de pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtor. ca. 11.</note> are, (ſaith <hi>Augu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtine</hi>) The writers of the diuine Scriptures: féeding there you féede ſafely: whatſoeuer you learne thence, count it ſauourie; whatſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>euer is beſides them, refuſe it. Therefore whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther it be touching Chriſt, or his Church, o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> any matter elſe, which concerneth our faith and life,<note place="margin">dem contr. Litt: Petil: li. 3. ca, 6.</note> I ſay not if we, (ſaith Saint <hi>Auſtine</hi>) but as <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>weth in <hi>Paul,</hi> If an Angel from heauen teach any thing beſides that, which you haue receiued in the Scriptures of the law<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> and the Goſpel; holde him accurſed. But I will conclude this point (wherein there is <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> multitude of witneſſes againſt you, which, to auoide tediouſneſſe, I omit): S. <hi>Auguſtin</hi> tea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cheth <hi>Paulina,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Epiſt<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>us:</note> Not to follow his authority, or
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:20283:22"/> to beléeue a thing, becauſe he hath ſaid it, but to beléeue the Canonicall Scriptures.<note place="margin">L<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> 
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap> de pi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> rit, c<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>
                  </note> We ſay therefore with him let vs yéeld and conſent vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the holy Scriptures, which can neither de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiue, nor be deceiued. And againe, I require the voice of the Shepheard, Reade me this matter out of the Prophets,<note place="margin">De paſt<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>. cap. 14.</note> reade it out of the Pſalmes, reade it out of the Lawe, reade it out of the Goſpel, reade it out of the Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtles writings. And ſo I ende with this ſentence of his, I owe my conſent,<note place="margin">De natur<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> &amp; gratia, ca. 61.</note> without gain-ſaying, only vnto the Canonical Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture.</p>
               <p>Now, let the indifferent Reader iudge of the handling of this firſt part; whether he will be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>léeue the Fathers, ſpeaking for, and with the Scriptures: or for Traditions, without and and beſides the Scriptures. Surely had theſe Fathers liued in this age, they had béen con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demned for Heretikes, as we are, for holding the ſame doctrine; ſo well doth this new Pope<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie agrée with Antiquitie. And the Papiſts had néed to haue theſe places, and infinite o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>hers to this purpoſe,<note place="margin">Deut. 4, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>. &amp; 12, 32. &amp; 28.5<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>. Io. 20.31. 2, Tim. 3, 15, 16, 17.</note> to be purged by their <hi>In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dex expurgatorius,</hi> out of the Fathers, leſt this thiefe and fundamentall point agréeing ſo di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rectly with the Scriptures, prooue the downe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>all of all Papiſtrie.</p>
               <pb n="20" facs="tcp:20283:23"/>
               <p>Now let vs briefly procéede to the ſecond Exception, to ſhew the errour of the Fathers.</p>
               <p>Firſt, <hi>Cyprian</hi> condemned the Baptiſme of Heretikes as vnlawfull, wherein a Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cell of <hi>Carthage</hi> of <hi>87.</hi> Biſhops vnder him, erred with him.</p>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ag. de ciui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tate Dei, lib. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>1. c. 17.</note>
                  <hi>Origen</hi> thought, That the diuels themſelues ſhould be ſaued at length.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Tertullian</hi> doeth (with <hi>Montanus</hi>) con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demne ſecond mariage.</p>
               <p>
                  <note n="a" place="margin">In dialog: cum Tri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pho Iud.</note>
                  <hi>Iuſtin</hi> the Martyr,<note n="b" place="margin">Hier. com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men. in Eſay, li. 18, in prae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fat.</note> 
                  <hi>Irenaeus,</hi>
                  <note n="c" place="margin">Euſeb hiſt. Ec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cleſi. lib. 3. ca. 36.</note> 
                  <hi>Papias,</hi>
                  <note n="d" place="margin">De ſpefidel. vt cita ab Hie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rom.</note> 
                  <hi>Tertul<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ian,</hi>
                  <note n="e" place="margin">Hier. ſcrip e<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>cl. in ver. papias.</note> 
                  <hi>Victorinus,</hi>
                  <note n="f" place="margin">Di<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>
                     <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nar. inſtit. lib 7, cap. 23.</note> 
                  <hi>Lactantius,</hi>
                  <note n="g" place="margin">Hierom. comment. in Eſay, lib. 18, in Pſalm.</note> 
                  <hi>Apolinarius,</hi>
                  <note n="h" place="margin">Hierom. come<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>t in Ezech: lib. 11.</note> 
                  <hi>Seue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rus,</hi> and<note n="i" place="margin">Euſeb. Hiſt Eccleſ. lib. 7. cap. 23.</note> 
                  <hi>Nepos</hi> did erre, in that they thought, that Chriſtians after the reſurrection, ſhould raigne a thouſand yéeres with Chriſt vpon the earth in a golden <hi>Ieruſalem,</hi> and there ſhould marrie wiues, beget children, eate, drinke, and liue in cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>porall delights.</p>
               <p>
                  <note n="k" place="margin">Irenaeus ad Hier lib. 5 ca. 2<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>.</note>
                  <hi>Irenaeus,</hi>
                  <note n="l" place="margin">Hilar. diuinar. inſtit. li: 7, ca. 14.</note> 
                  <hi>Hillarie,</hi>
                  <note n="m" place="margin">La<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctant. in Matt. Can. 17.</note> 
                  <hi>Lactan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tius,</hi>
                  <note n="n" place="margin">Hieron. epiſt. 139, ad Cypr.</note> 
                  <hi>Hierom,</hi> and<note n="o" place="margin">Iuſt. M<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>rtyr. Reſpon. ad Orthod. q. 71.</note> 
                  <hi>Iuſtin Martyr</hi> erred, for that they thought that the world ſhould laſt but ſixe thouſand yeres: which opinion<note n="p" place="margin">Aug in Erur. Pſal. 89. &amp; de ciuitate Dei, lib. 18. cap. 33.</note> S. <hi>Auguſtine</hi> doeth reprooue as raſh and preſumptuous.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Hillarie</hi> erred touching the humanitie o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <pb n="21" facs="tcp:20283:23"/> Chriſt, and did not ſpeake of the perſon of the holy Ghoſt as the church ſpeaketh.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Irenaeus</hi> erred, in affirming, That Chriſt died in the fiftith yeare of his age, contrary to the Scriptures, <hi>Luke 3.23.</hi> And <hi>Iohn</hi> the E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uangeliſt remembreth thrée Paſſeouers after the Baptiſme of Chriſt, and in the third he was crucified, as he affirmeth.</p>
               <p>Thus you ſée the ſecond Exception iuſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>fi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fied: but I will forbeare to enlarge this part any further, becauſe I am vnwilling to diſco<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer their nakednes.</p>
               <p>The third Exception is, That the Papiſts themſelues reiect the Fathers,<note place="margin">Briſtowes motiues.</note> notwithſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding the great brags they make of them, as th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ugh they were wholly theirs; wherein I will bee ſhort, as I haue béen in all the reſt. When we affirme by Saint <hi>Hieromes</hi> teſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mony, that Pope <hi>Liberius</hi> ſubſcribed to the <hi>Arrians:</hi> Maſter <hi>Hardin</hi> anſwereth,<note place="margin">Iewel aga. Har. pag 6<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>
                  </note> that <hi>Hie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rome</hi> was deceiued by a rumour, dwelling in the Eaſt.</p>
               <p>The Rhemiſts except againſt <hi>Auguſtines</hi> expoſition of theſe words, <hi>Vpon this Rocke,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Mat. 16, ſect. 8.</note> &amp;c. which he expoundeth not of <hi>Peters</hi> perſon, but of <hi>Peters</hi> faith:<note place="margin">Princ. doct li. 6. cap. 3.</note> Alſo Doctor <hi>Stapleton</hi> calles the ſame expoſition <hi>Lapſus humanus, <hi>An hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mane ouerſight.</hi>
                  </hi> And yet the ſame expoſition
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:20283:24"/> is confirmed by <hi>
                     <hi rend="sup">a</hi> Gregorie Niſſen, <hi rend="sup">b</hi> Cyril, <hi rend="sup">c</hi> Chryſoſtome, <hi rend="sup">d</hi> Ambroſe,</hi> and <hi>
                     <hi rend="sup">e</hi> Hillary:</hi> All agréeing, that this Rocke is the confeſſion of <hi>Peter.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Bellarmine</hi> reiects S. <hi>Auguſtines</hi> interpre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tation of S. <hi>Paul</hi> in this place, He ſhall be ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued, as through fire; which <hi>Auſtine</hi> interpre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teth to be y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> afflictions or tribulatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s of this life. But <hi>Bellarmin</hi> expounds it of Purgatory.</p>
               <p>The Rhemiſts reiect S. <hi>Auguſtines</hi> reading, <hi>Heb. 11. ver. 21.</hi> who ſaith,<note place="margin">
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap> 
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>t. in <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>neſis, q. 162.</note> 
                  <hi>Iacob <hi>by faith wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhipped God vpon the end of his ſtaffe.</hi>
                  </hi> But they tra<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſlate, <hi>Iacob</hi> adored the top of his Rod, to countenance their Idolatrie.</p>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>n confeſ. Aug. i. 2. c. 8. Tit. 5.</note>
                  <hi>Torrenſis</hi> the Ieſuite in the diuiſion of the co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mandements, ſaith, that <hi>3</hi> of them concerne our duty towards God, and <hi>7</hi> towards men. This doctrine is imbraced by y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Papiſts, vpon <hi>Auſtin</hi> and <hi>Clements</hi> authority, contrary to al theſe Fathers folowing: whoſe iudgements they may truely be ſaid to reiect, in preferring two before ſo many. As firſt by the Hebrewes, as<note place="margin">Li. de decal. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap> duob. opuſc. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>le legib. ſpeci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> lib.</note> 
                  <hi>Philo,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Antiquit. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ude. li. 3. ca. 4.</note> 
                  <hi>Ioſephus,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">In Exod. 20.</note> 
                  <hi>Aben Ezra:</hi> next by the Grecians;<note place="margin">In verſib. de <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ecalog.</note> 
                  <hi>Gregory Nazianzen,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">In Exod. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>o. 8.</note> 
                  <hi>O<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rigen,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">In Synop. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>et. Scriptur.</note> 
                  <hi>Athanaſius,</hi> and<note place="margin">In Mat. oper. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>mperf. Ho. 49.</note> 
                  <hi>Chryſoſtome.</hi> Laſtly, by the Latines:<note place="margin">In Epiſt. ad <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ph. cap. 6.</note> S. <hi>Ambroſe,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">In <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>piſt. ad <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>pheſ ca. 6.</note> S. <hi>Hierome.</hi> And one yet ancienter than they both,<note place="margin">Aug. q. vet. Nou. Teſt. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>p. 7.</note> The Author of the queſtions of the Old
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:20283:24"/> and New Teſtament, who all affirme that foure Commandements concerne our duety towards God, and ſixe towards men.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Epiphanius</hi> is reiected by D. <hi>Hardin,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Iewel, pag<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> 548.</note> for breaking of Images.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Cyprian</hi> is condemned by <hi>Dureus,</hi> becauſe he teacheth that onely Chriſt is to be heard.</p>
               <p>Their reiection of the Fathers is ſo com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monly knowen to all that reade Controuer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſies,<note place="margin">See their I<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>
                     <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>dex expur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gatorius.</note> as is euident by the infinite teſtimonies alleaged by vs, out of the Fathers, againſt the Papiſts, that I ſhall not néede to inſiſt of more particularities: in which few may yet be obſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued; that they reiect the greater number (which they tearme the Churches expoſition) when they make againſt them.<note place="margin">Stapleton and Hart.</note>
               </p>
               <p>The fourth Exception is, that there are ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny counterfeits bearing the name of Fathers, which are likewiſe often alleaged by the Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piſts, to abuſe vs with their names. For proofe wherof there be nine volumes of S. <hi>Hieroms</hi> workes, whereof <hi>3</hi> are none of his: and yet <hi>vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tae Patrum,</hi> a Legend, how wrongfully fathe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red on him,<note place="margin">Co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ment. in epi: 2. ad T<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> mo. ca. 4. l<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> cor. Theol<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> li. 11. ca. 6.</note> your <hi>Eſpencaeus</hi> and <hi>Canus</hi> both ſhew. As alſo a barbarous and ſottiſh fable of the natiuity of S. <hi>Mary</hi> as <hi>Canus</hi> calleth it.</p>
               <p>Likewiſe of ten volumes of <hi>S. Auſtins,</hi> there is not aboue one or two, that hath not more or
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:20283:25"/> fewer of ſuch Pamphlets patched to it, both by the cenſure of <hi>Eraſmus,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Cenſura the<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ologoru<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> Lo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uanien<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>um in Appe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>di c Tom<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> ſecun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>di, &amp; cetero<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>um Auguſt.</note> and the Diuines of <hi>Louain,</hi> who ſhew, that ſundry things beare Saint <hi>Auſtines</hi> name, whereof ſome are vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>learned, ſome lewd and hereticall.</p>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">Sixtus <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ne<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ſ. de <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>lc<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> librotum in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcrip. Stapl prin<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>
                     <g ref="char:punc">▪</g> doctr. li. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>, cap. 14.</note> 
                  <hi>Sixtus Senenſis,</hi> whom D. <hi>Stapleton</hi> doeth commend, hath proued that books are fathered falſely, not onely vpon <hi>Auguſtine</hi> and <hi>Hie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rome,</hi> but alſo vpon <hi>Ambroſe, Cyprian, A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thanaſius, Euſebius, Emiſenus, Iunilius, Cy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ril, Eucherius, Arnobius,</hi> and <hi>Thomas</hi> of <hi>A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quine.</hi> And with this diſcourſe hee cloſeth vp the former volume of his holy Librarie: In which he hath ſhewed,<note place="margin">Bibliotheca Sanct<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> lib. 2. &amp; 4.</note> that <hi>Clemens, Abdius, Origen, Chryſoſtome, Hipolitus,</hi> and many mo, haue had their names defaced with the ſame iniurie.</p>
               <p>I will omit diuers others for breuity; and although this may ſéeme no iuſt Exception againſt the Fathers, yet it ought to make vs cautious, how we truſt them to be the true Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers; and not counterfeits: the rather for that the Papiſts, haue often alleaged ſuch coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terfeit Fathers to credit their doctrine with. For proofe whereof, <hi>Torrenſis</hi> the Ieſuite ci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teth ſuch bookes for S. <hi>Auguſtines</hi> as are knowen and granted to bee none of his;<note place="margin">
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>n confeſſ. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ng. li. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>, ca. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>, Tit. 2, &amp;c. aſſi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>.</note> as namely, The Sermon of Saint <hi>Peters</hi> chaire,
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:20283:25"/> and other pretie Pamphlets of the ſame litter. And although in the preface of his confeſſions to the Reader, he makes an exception: yet our of that exception, he ſaith, that although they doe not auaile much to conuince the opinion of Sectaries: Neuertheleſſe, there will be godly men and learned, who will permit and iudge them to be Saint <hi>Auguſtines</hi> owne; and will both take delight and profit by trading them. And yet amongſt the<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>e bookes, there is one that teacheth, contrary to Saint <hi>Auguſtine;</hi> as namely. The booke of viſiting the ſicke: where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in the Baſtard <hi>Auſtin</hi> alloweth the worſhip of images for good,<note place="margin">De viſitat. Infirmor. li 2. ca. 1. De moribu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> Eccleſiae ca. 3<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>.</note> which <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>he true <hi>Auſtin</hi> doth note as an abuſe, and ſaith the Church miſli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>keth it. And yet this booke alleaged by the Ie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſuite for worſhipping of i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ages is ſet as a flower in his <hi>Auſtins</hi> con<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>tions; though it be iudged a baſtard <hi>Auſtin</hi> by the Diuines of <hi>Louain.</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Cenſura Lo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uanienſium. Non eſt Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guſt. princ. doctr. li. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>. cap. 15. Arnob. com in pſal. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>. Hier. de Scri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ptori<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>. eccle. Biblio. ſanct. li. 4. Hiſtor. T<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ip. li. 5. c. 5. Coment. in <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ſal. 105.</note>
               </p>
               <p>D. <hi>Stapleton</hi> alleageth <hi>Arnobius</hi> vpon the Pſalmes, to prooue, that who goeth out of <hi>Peters</hi> church ſhall periſh; and that this is a counterfeit Father, Saint <hi>Hierome</hi> and <hi>Six<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tus Senenſis</hi> dot ſhew, for that the moſt ancient <hi>Arnobius</hi> was elder, than that he might heare of the hereſie of <hi>Photinus;</hi> whereas this <hi>Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nobius</hi> that writeth on the Pſalmes doeth
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:20283:26"/> mention <hi>Photinus</hi> and wrote by name againſt his Hereſie.</p>
               <p>S. <hi>Baſil</hi> is often alleaged by the Papiſts, in many of their bookes,<note place="margin">Baſil de Spir. ſanct. ca. 27.</note> for Traditions not writ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten. Theſe words are vrged as his: Of the do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrines which are taught in the Church; wee haue ſome laid down in writing, ſome againe we haue receiued by Tradition, from the Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtles in a myſtery, that is in ſecret: whereof ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther haue like force to godlines; neither doth any man contradict them, that is but meanly acquainted with y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> lawes of the Church: for if we go about to reiect thoſe cuſtoms which are not written, as of no moment; before we be<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ware, we ſhal condemne thoſe things which are in the Goſpel neceſſary to ſaluatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, yea, rather we ſhal bring the preaching of faith to a naked name. And not long after in the ſame booke, If nothing elſe hath béen receiued without ſcrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures,<note place="margin">Ibid. ca. 29.</note> neither let this be receiued: But if wee haue receiued many ſecrets without writing, let vs alſo receiue this among thoſe many. I thinke it Apoſtolike to cleaue to Traditio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s not written. Now this booke is prooued a counter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feit by the reaſons following: Firſt, though it hath Saint <hi>Baſils</hi> name to it,<note place="margin">Epiſt. Eraſ. dedicat. ad Epiſc. Cul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>menſ. prae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>. ca. 17.</note> yet the later part thereof whence thoſe patches are taken, haue neither S. <hi>Baſils</hi> ſtile, learning, ſpirit, nor age;
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:20283:26"/> which <hi>Eraſmus</hi> confeſſed when he tranſlated the booke. Beſides, this place of <hi>Baſils,</hi> directly contradicts the two places afore mentioned of of S. <hi>Baſil.</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Q. 14. par: 1</note> And this later allegation of the <hi>29</hi> Chap. conuinceth the Author to be but a yong Father in reſpect of S. <hi>Baſil.</hi> For this baſtard <hi>Baſil</hi> in the ſame chapter mentioneth <hi>Meleti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>us,</hi> as a Biſhop of ancient memorie, dead long before his time:<note place="margin">Baſi. deſpi. Sanct. ca. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>9</note> 
                  <hi>Inſuper &amp; Meletium illum ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mirandum eade<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> fuiſſe ſententia narrant quicum illo vixerunt. Sed quid opus eſt vetera commemo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rare? Immò nunc qui ſunt Orientales &amp;c. <hi>More<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouer,</hi> Meletius <hi>(that admirable Biſhop) was of the ſame opinion, as they that liued with him report. But what need I repeat ancient times? The Eaſt Biſhops which are at this day, &amp;c.</hi>
                  </hi>
               </p>
               <p>Now the true Saint <hi>Baſil,</hi> not only liued at the ſame time with <hi>Meletius,</hi> but was made Deacon by him,<note place="margin">Socr: li. 4. ca. 26. Baſilij epi. 56, 57, 58, 89. Socr. lib. 5. ca. 8.</note> and wrote many letters to him, and departed this life before him, as the Church ſtory witneſſeth, affirming <hi>Helladius</hi> S. <hi>Baſils</hi> ſucceſſor, and <hi>Meletius,</hi> were both preſent at the ſecond Generall Councell at <hi>Conſtantinople,</hi> vnder <hi>Theodoſius;</hi> and that muſt néeds be when Saint <hi>Baſil</hi> was dead. I wil yet enlarge this part out of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> 
                  <hi>Rhemes</hi> Te<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtament, becauſe I know you highly eſteeme the booke, and thinke it impoſſible, that ſo
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:20283:27"/> many learned Diuines would abuſe their Readers with counterfeit Fathers to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firme their doctrine.</p>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">Anot. Phe. Teſt. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>. Tim. 4. ſect. 13.</note>Your Rhemiſts alleage a counterfeit Epi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtle of <hi>Alexander,</hi> to prooue Holy water to be <hi>1400.</hi> yéeres olde, and it beareth date when <hi>Traianus,</hi> and <hi>Helianus</hi> were Conſuls, which was neuer; which prooueth it to be a counter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feit.</p>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">Anot. Rhe. Teſt. 1. Cor. 11. ſect. 10.</note>You alleage <hi>Chryſoſtome,</hi> and S. <hi>Iames</hi> Maſſes, for putting water into the wine in the Sacrament: and that theſe Maſſes are forged, are thus prooued:<note place="margin">Balſ. in Can. 32. Conc. Conſtant. 6.</note> Firſt <hi>Balſamon,</hi> Patri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>arch of <hi>Antioch,</hi> ſaith, That the Liturgie of Saint <hi>Iames</hi> was not extant in his time. And in the Liturgy that beareth the name of <hi>Chry<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoſtomes</hi> Maſſe as it is ſet foorth by <hi>Claudius du Sanctis,</hi> There is a prayer for Pope <hi>Ni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cholas</hi> and the Emperour <hi>Alexius:</hi> whereof the one was néere fiue hundreth yéeres, the other <hi>7.</hi> hundreth yéeres after <hi>Chryſoſtome.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>For extreame Vnction, you cite <hi>Auguſtin de viſitatione Infirmor</hi> and <hi>Auſtin de Tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pore.</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Anot. Rhe. Teſt. Cala. 4. ſect. 2.</note> The firſt place is prooued a counterfeit by the cenſure of <hi>Louain,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">In Censur. general. Tom. 10.</note> as I haue ſhewed in the firſt example of theſe counterfeit Fathers: and the other place <hi>de Tempore,</hi> by the ſame warrant.<note place="margin">Oper. de Aug.</note>
               </p>
               <pb n="29" facs="tcp:20283:27"/>
               <p>Saint <hi>Auguſtine,</hi> (or as ſome thinke,<note place="margin">Anot Rhe. Teſt. Acts 1 ſect. 7.</note> 
                  <hi>Ful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gentius</hi>) is alleadged by your Rhemiſts to prooue prayer and preiſes to the bleſſed Virgin <hi>Marie,</hi> ſaying, Who can be able worthily to prayſe, or thanke thée: Receiue our prayers, obtaine vs our requeſts; for thou act the ſpeci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>all hope of ſinners; by thée we hope for pardon of our ſinnes; and in thée, O moſt bleſſed, is the expectation of our rewards, &amp;c. What greater blaſphemie can there be, then to attri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bute that to the creature, which is onely due to the Creator? This is not to honor, but to diſhonour that bleſſed virgin; in giuing thoſe attributes to her, which to proper and peculi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ar to our Sauiour Chriſt. Now for proofe that this is a counterfeit <hi>Auſtine,</hi> he addeth the te<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>himonie of <hi>Iſiodorus,</hi> who liued <hi>200.</hi> yeeres after S. <hi>Auſtine;</hi> which prooueth, that it can neither be Saint <hi>Auguſtine</hi> nor <hi>Folgentius.</hi> Beſides this, <hi>Auguſtine</hi> or <hi>Fulgentius,</hi> in the <hi>39.</hi> ſermon, doubteth of the Aſſumption of the Virgine <hi>Mary,</hi> and yet when he may ſéeme to make for their ſuperſtition, he muſt be vrged as the true <hi>Auſtine.</hi> So little conſcience make they of the abuſing their Readers; if it may hold them in blindneſſe, or giue any colour to their errors. The queſtions of the Olde and New Teſtament, are none of Saint <hi>Auſtins:</hi>
                  <pb n="30" facs="tcp:20283:28"/> for in the <hi>21</hi> queſtion, it is affirmed that <hi>Mel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chiſedech</hi> was the holy Ghoſt: which ſaying, the true <hi>Auſtine,</hi> in his booke <hi>De Haereſ.</hi> re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>futeht as an hereſie.<note place="margin">Bellar. de Sacr. Can. i. 2. ca. 10.</note> This <hi>Bellarmine</hi> confeſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeth, and yet the authoritie of this booke is of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten vrged by the Rhemiſts and other Papiſts. But aboue all their forgeries,<note place="margin">Annot. Rhe. ſeſt. Act. 1.</note> thoſe touching the aſſumption of our Ladie are notable: where for proofe thereof, Saint, <hi>Denis,</hi> S. <hi>Da<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maſcen, Athanaſius,</hi> and S. <hi>Barnard,</hi> are al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leadged. In which they affirme, that S. <hi>Denis</hi> writeth theſe and theſe things; where neither the Author is S. <hi>Denis,</hi> neither writeth he the things which they alleage. Now for proofe that this <hi>Denis</hi> is a counterfeit, <hi>Dionyſius Areo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pagita</hi> (who they here call S. <hi>Denis</hi>) was dead many yéers before the works which beare his name could bee written: for there is<note place="margin">De diuin. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ominib. c. 4</note> ci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted in them a ſaying of <hi>Ignatius,</hi> out of an E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piſtle which he wrote to the Romanes as hee was going to ſuffer martyrdom:<note place="margin">Euſeb. in <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ronic. Methodi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> in Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>rio Dion. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>reopag.</note> in the time of <hi>Traian</hi> the Emperour. Now <hi>Dionyſius</hi> died<note place="margin">Ignat. epi. Epheſ.</note> in the time of <hi>Domitian,</hi> certaine yeers before. And when<note place="margin">Dion. A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>op. Epiſc. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>thenarum</note> 
                  <hi>Ignatius</hi> wrote it, <hi>Oneſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mus</hi> was B. of <hi>Epheſus,</hi> who ſuccéeded <hi>Ti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mothie.</hi> Your counterfeit<note place="margin">Timoth. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>iſc. Ephe.</note> alleageth it to <hi>Timothie,</hi> B. of <hi>Epheſus,</hi> either after his de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceaſe, or before it was written. Beſides it is ſet
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:20283:28"/> down in y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> Annotations that ſhe liued <hi>63</hi> yéers, being <hi>25</hi> yeres after Chriſts Aſcenſion, as it is in their Tables of S. <hi>Paul,</hi> when ſhe is ſuppoſed to be aſſumpted. Now in the ſame Table,<note place="margin">After the Acts of the Apoſtles.</note> it is ſhewed by their owne account, that it was <hi>51</hi> yeres after Chriſts Natiuity, and <hi>18</hi> yeres af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter his Aſcension, before <hi>Dionyſius Areopa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gita</hi> (whom the tearme S. <hi>Denis</hi>) was con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerted by S. <hi>Paul;</hi> which<note n="f" place="margin">Acts 9, 5 Galat. 1.18. Acts 9.26. Galat. 1, 22 Acts 13, 4. Gal. 2.1. Acts 15.4. Acts 16, 5. Acts 17, 34</note> the Scriptures alſo witneſſe, as any that will weigh the particular texts ſhal euidently perceiue: So that he could not be one of the brethren, to witnes her aſſu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>p<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion: She being aſſumpted (taking the largeſt computation) thrée yeres before he was con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerted; being at that time no Chriſtian. Hee might be proued a cou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>terfeit by other reaſons, which I omit. Now touching the things which are by the Rhemiſts fathered on him, he ſaith no more thereof, but that among the Biſhops, inſpired of the holy Ghoſt, <hi>Hierotheus</hi> ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>celled all the reſt (ſaue the Apoſtles) in pray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing Chriſts goodneſſe; when himſelfe and <hi>Timothie,</hi> and many of their holy brethren, came together to behold the body, which re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiued God, and which the Prince of life was in. As for the miracles (falſely forged by the Rhemiſts, and fathered on him) of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Apoſtles broght together; S. <hi>Thomas</hi> co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ming the <hi>3</hi> day
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:20283:29"/> after, the Angels ſinging Hymnes thrée daies, the buriall of the virgins body, the deſire of <hi>Thomas</hi> to ſée it, the Sepulch<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>e opened for his ſake, and the body aſſumpte<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> into heauen, he ſaith not one word of theſe conceits. Nay he rather ſaith againſt them; for he noteth, name<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, That Iames was alſo preſent, the brother of the Lord, and <hi>Peter</hi> the chiefeſt and ancien<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſt top of the Apoſtles. And it is not likely he would haue noted two, if they had beene all preſent: here is no leſſe than ſeuen lies in leſſe than ſixe liues.</p>
               <p>Now let vs ſée how <hi>Damaſcen</hi> &amp; your Por<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſſe agréeth: For <hi>Damaſce<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  </hi> ſaith, The Angels ſung almoſt thrée dayes. The Porteſſe, thrée whole dayes. <hi>Damaſcen</hi> ſaith, The reſt of the Apoſtles, would ſhew to one of them, who was abſent, the bodie. The Porteſſe ſaith, <hi>Tho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mas,</hi> who was abſent, would worſhip the bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>die. Now what thée <hi>Damaſcen</hi> was, let your owne doctors tell you; who except againſt him for his tale of <hi>Gregory</hi> the Pope,<note place="margin">
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>anus loco<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>m Theol, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap>. 11. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>. Heſſels <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>nſure de <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ſtor. ſanct. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>. 3. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>erm. de funct: in <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap>.</note> and <hi>Traiane</hi> the Emperour. Thus <hi>Damaſcen</hi> reporteth, That <hi>Gregorie</hi> while he went ouer the mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ket place of <hi>Traian,</hi> did pray for <hi>Traians</hi> ſoule to God: and behold, a voice from heauen; I haue heard thy prayer, and I pardon <hi>Traian:</hi> but ſee thou pray no more to me for y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> wicked.
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:20283:29"/> Theſe be good places to prooue prayer for the dead: and yet it is againſt popiſh doctrine, that prayer can deliuer any out of hell. And if he had béen in Purgatory, the Pope could haue diſpatched that of himſelfe without praying. The next is <hi>Athan in Euang. de deipara;</hi> who ſpeaks not one word of your miraculous fault. And yet is the ſame <hi>Athanaſius</hi> reiected for a baſtard, in your owne edition.<note place="margin">In edit. Petr. Nannij Lo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uan. praefat. ad epiſcop. Atiebat.</note> The laſt is fiue ſermons of S. <hi>Barnards,</hi> in all which like<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe, there is not one worde of that miracle. So that vnleſſe they were diſpoſed to lie for the whetſtone; it is to be wondred, how they dare thus abuſe their Readers both with the names of counterfeit Fathers, and falſe forgeries. If I ſhould collect all ſuch like ſtuffe, it would growe greater than this ſmal Tract. But let the Chriſtian Reader iudge of the reſt, as hee prooues theſe to be truly brought againſt them. And if any deſire further proofe of the Rhemiſts ſincerity in alleaging Fathers, let him ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerue theſe places, <hi>viz.</hi> The conſtitutions of <hi>Clement, Luk. 4. Sect. 1. Ignatius, Matt. 4. Sect. 2. &amp; 1. Peter 2. Sect. 6 Dionyſius Areo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pag. Act. 8. Sect. 6. Hypolitus Mat. 24. Sect. 5. Policarpus, Act. 6. Sect. 1. Miltiadi Fabi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>an Act. 8. Sect. 6. S. Andrew, S. Martiall, Hebr. 10. Sect. 11.</hi> The Maſſes of S. <hi>Iames,
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:20283:30"/> Baſil,</hi> and <hi>Chryſoſtome, 1. Cor. 11. Sect. 10. Clicton</hi> for <hi>Ciuil, Ioh. 11. Sect. 1.</hi> and <hi>Pauli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nus, Ioh. 9. Sect. 2.</hi> All theſe are counterfeit Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers, and vrged by the Papiſts vnder the names of true Fathers, to countenance their corrupt doctrine. And therefore no maruell if popiſh leaders inſtruct their followers, to get vs into the plaine field of their Motiues, out of our weake and falſe caſtell of onely Scripture, as <hi>Briſtowe</hi> the Licentiate tearmeth it.<note place="margin">Briſt. Motiu. 48.</note> And it is no maruell that they haue ſuch ſtore of the Fathers, and that our new maſters (as they tearme vs) cannot compare with theſe Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers in the doctrines they deliuer, when they bring vs onely the names of fathers. I could giue inſtance likewiſe, how the Fathers are often contrary one to another; yea, contrary to themſelues. Thus I hope it is plainly proo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued, by theſe foure iuſt exceptions, that the Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers iudgements are no infallible rule for a man to build his faith on: though it be im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>belliſht with the churches expoſition. And yet wee reuerence and honor them, as men that haue brought great light to the vnder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding of the Scriptures. But what do<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> you vnderſtand by intituling the ancient Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers with the name of the church?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <pb n="35" facs="tcp:20283:30"/>
               <speaker>Papiſt.</speaker>
               <p>
                  <hi>I meane,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Har<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>g. Rai.</note> 
                  <hi>that the ioint conſent of the Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers in all doctrines deliuered by them is the doctrine of the Church.</hi>
               </p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Proteſtant.</speaker>
               <p n="15">
                  <hi>15</hi> What doe you meane by the ioint con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent of the Fathers.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Papiſt.</speaker>
               <p>
                  <hi>I mean by the ioint conſent of the Fathers, that, which all, or the moſt part of them, doe deliuer for trueth; wherin if there be any dif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ference, the greater number is to be follow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed: for a fewe may bee deceiued more eaſily than many.</hi>
               </p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Proteſtant.</speaker>
               <p n="16">
                  <hi>16</hi> This rule ſéemes to be very vncertaine; for you knowe, that king <hi>Ahab</hi> was deceiued, by the conſent of falſe prophets;<note place="margin">2. Chron. 1<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> 5, 11.</note> euen <hi>400.</hi> a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt <hi>Micaiah:</hi> yea, when the Fathers, in the great Councel of <hi>Nice,</hi> were about to decrée, that Biſhops Prieſts &amp; Deaco<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s ſhould not vſe their wiues; <hi>Paphnutius</hi> alone,<note place="margin">Sozom. li. 1. cap. 2<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>.</note> roſe vp in the midſt of their Councell, and fréely contradicted it, and preuailed. Beſides, in the third Excep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion before, it is plainely ſhewed, that the greater number of Fathers, are by your ſelues reiected in the diuiſion of the co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mandements; and in the controuerſie betwéene S. <hi>Auſtine</hi>
                  <pb n="36" facs="tcp:20283:31"/> and <hi>Hierom</hi> touching <hi>Peters</hi> reproofe, <hi>par. 1.</hi> wherein your ſelues grant,<note place="margin">Torrenſis confeſ. Aug. lib. 2. cap. 1. tim. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>.</note> that <hi>Auſtin</hi> iudged more ſoundly. What is therefore then to be done, that a certaine and ſure ground may bee found out?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Papist.</speaker>
               <p>
                  <hi>Then a better and more ſure way is that, which by the faithfull Paſtors of the Church is decreed in a generall Councell, which can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not erre.</hi>
               </p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Protestant.</speaker>
               <p n="17">
                  <hi>17</hi> Indéed, I muſt confeſſe, it is a ſure way to build our faith vpon thoſe Councels which cannot erre: But how ſhal we be aſſured that they cannot erre?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Papiſt.</speaker>
               <p>
                  <hi>We are aſſured by the Scriptures, That the Church cannot erre; as is euident by theſe places following.</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Mat. 18.20.</note> 
                  <hi>Our Sauiour Chriſt ſaith, That when two or three are gathered toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther in his name, that he will be in the midſt. And,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Ioh. 16, 13.</note> 
                  <hi>he promiſeth to ſend, vnto his Church, the holy Ghoſt, which ſhall leade them into all trueth.</hi>
                  <note place="margin">1. Tim. 3.</note> 
                  <hi>And S. <hi>Paul</hi> calles it the Pillar and ground of trueth. Vpon which places, and many other, which for breuity I omit; wee conclude, that the Church cannot erre: which, to ſpeake as the Schoolemen doe, we
<pb n="37" facs="tcp:20283:31"/> call the Church repreſentatiue; becauſe the whole Church is there repreſented in a ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall Councell.</hi>
               </p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Proteſtant.</speaker>
               <p n="18">
                  <hi>18</hi> Take héede what you doe: Will you bring the Church (contrary to the iudgement of many learned Papiſts, mentioned in the preface of this booke) to take her authority from the Scriptures, and to be tried by them, whether it may erre? If you doe, it will be the vtter ruine and deſtruction of your Religion: for the Scriptures will conuince the Councel of <hi>Conſtance</hi> of error; in taking away the cup from the Laitie, contrary to S. <hi>Pauls</hi> expreſſe commandement, ſaying,<note place="margin">1. Cor. 11.</note> 
                  <hi>Let a man examine himſelfe, and ſo let him eate of this bread, and drinke of this cup.</hi> And contrary to the Inſtitu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion and commaundement of Chriſt himſelfe, ſaying, <hi>Drinke you all of this.</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Mat. 26.27.</note> And Saint <hi>Iohn</hi> witneſſeth, that our Sauiour Chriſt ſaith,<note place="margin">Iohn 6.53.</note> 
                  <hi>Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cept yee eate the fleſh of the ſonne of man, and drinke his blood, you haue no life in you:</hi> and ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny other teſtimonies which I omit. It wil con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uince the Councell of <hi>Nice</hi> of error, in decrée<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing for the worſhip of Images, contrary to the ſecond commandement. But what ſhall I néede to deſcend to particularities; it will con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uince your late Councell of <hi>Trent,</hi> and all o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther
<pb n="38" facs="tcp:20283:32"/> Councels; in all thoſe points of doctrine, wherein you varie from vs: if any Papiſt dare vndertake to bring the controuerſies be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>twéene vs, to that triall.</p>
               <p>And ſurely, ſince they will ſeeme to bring Scriptures, to prooue the authoritie of the church; and, that the church cannot erre: I ſée no reaſon why they ſhould refuſe to make them iudge of all differences betwéene vs. But I maruell they vrge theſe places of Scripture, to prooue that the church repre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſentatiue cannot erre: ſéeing they are not a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble to ſhew, that any one ancient Father hath ſo vnderſtood them: or, that the whole church is repreſented in a generall Councell. Name one Father that is ancient, and not counter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feit, for your credit ſake, that hath interpre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted theſe places of Scripture, or any other in that caſe, as you doe. If you cannot, the world may iuſtly holde you for wranglers, and a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>buſers, both of Scriptures and Fathers. But let vs a little examine the force of thoſe Scriptures, which if they were all granted, make nothing againſt vs, if they bee rightly vnderſtood. The firſt is, When two or thrée are gathered together &amp;c. This place is as pregnant for two or thrée faithfull men, aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſembled in Chriſts name, as to a Nationall
<pb n="39" facs="tcp:20283:32"/> or a Prouinciall Councell: Neither doeth it giue any greater priuiledge to a Generall Councell, than it doeth vnto them;<note place="margin">Bellar. li. 1. de Conc. ca. 12.</note> though it bee alleaged by <hi>Bellarmine,</hi> as the ground for the authoriſing of Councels. All which promiſe notwithſtanding, your ſelues grant, That both Nationall and Prouinciall Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cels may erre.</p>
               <p>The next place is the ſixtéenth of <hi>Iohn,</hi> where the holy Ghoſt is promiſed to the A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſtles, to leade them into all trueth: which ſpirit of trueth is promiſed to the church, and to euery particular member thereof, for whome our Sauiour Chriſt prayeth, ſaying, <hi>Sanctifie them in thy trueth, thy worde is trueth.</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Ioh. 17.17.19, 20.</note> And againe, <hi>I pray not for theſe alone, but for them alſo that ſhall beleeue in mee through their worde.</hi> But what maketh this for ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nerall Councels, more then the whole church, or euery faithfull member thereof? For al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>though this prooueth, that the holy Ghoſt ſhall euer remayne with the church, and with euery true member of the ſame: yet muſt wee not hereof conclude, (though it bee as pregnant for euery faithfull particular man, as for the whole) That either euery mem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber of Chriſt, or euerie Paſtor that is the A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſtles ſucceſſour, cannot erre: Neither
<pb n="40" facs="tcp:20283:33"/> is this to be reſtrained to generall Councels, or to the Pope: neither muſt wee thinke, that any viſible Church may challenge all priui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledges, that the Apoſtles had, as neceſſary to the conuerſion of the world.<note place="margin">Rhem. Teſt. Iohn 16.</note> But your Rhe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſts will tell you, that to teach all trueth, and to preſerue in trueth, and from error, the holy Ghoſt is promiſed and performed, onely to the Church, and the choice gouernour and gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall Councels. Vpon which the Papiſts con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clude, that if the Church cannot erre, the go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uernours of the church cannot erre. Is not this ſubſtantiall reaſoning? The whole church cannot erre; <hi>Ergo,</hi> the Paſtors and preachers cannot erre. Deale plainely and directly; Do you hereby conclude that all Paſtors cannot erre: or that no Paſtor can erre? For to ſay, that no Paſtor can erre, were apparant mad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe, and to ſay that all Paſtors cannot erre, ſtands you in no ſtead: neither is this a good argument, The whole Church cannot erre; that is, all and euery faithfull cannot erre: <hi>Er<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>go,</hi> all Paſtors cannot erre. This is no kind of conſequent: for ſome of the faithfull may be di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rected to the trueth, and they no Paſtors nor preachers; and many preachers may be pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerued from error, and they no Biſhops; and many Biſhops may kept in the faith, and they
<pb n="41" facs="tcp:20283:33"/> not aſſembled: And a great number of thoſe that be aſſembled, may be righty affected, and yet not the moſt part of them. And the grea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter ſide may be well diſpoſed, and yet not the Biſhop of <hi>Rome;</hi> without whoſe confirmati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on you hold no Councell lawfull. And there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore this argument is very childiſh, The whole Church cannot erre: <hi>Ergo,</hi> Generall Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cels cannot erre; and ſpecially the Pope: (of whom wee ſhall ſpeake more particularly hereafter) neither hath the holy Ghoſt filled with the vnmeaſurable abundance of grace, any but Chriſt:<note place="margin">Iohn 3.34 Iohn 1.16.</note> for God giueth not the ſpirit by meaſure to him; of whoſe fulneſſe wee all receiue. And it may well bee gathered from the Scriptures,<note place="margin">2. Cor. 10.13 Eph. 4.7.</note> that though the holy Ghoſt be giuen to the Elect, yet hee hath giuen it by meaſure, as I may ſay with Saint <hi>Paul:</hi> not to this end, that they may not erre, but that they may not erre to death. For what thing ſoeuer is receiued of another, it is receiued ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to the capacitie of that which recei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ueth it.</p>
               <p>The laſt is the <hi>1. Tim. 3.15.</hi> The Church is the pillar and ground of trueth, therefore it cannot erre. If this argument were granted, would it follow hereupon, that general Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cels could not erre? but this is ſufficiently re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>futed
<pb n="42" facs="tcp:20283:34"/> before. And you knowe that <hi>Peter</hi> was a pillar of trueth, and yet hee erred and was reprooued by Saint <hi>Paul:</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Gal. 2.</note> yea, your Diuines of <hi>Paris,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Articuli Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſienſes.</note> but lately reſolued, that <hi>Peter</hi> er<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red in faith when <hi>Paul</hi> reprooued him. And the very drift and ſcope of the place ſheweth, That <hi>Timothie</hi> is not ſent by Saint <hi>Paul</hi> to the church, to learne his duety, but to the Scripture. Theſe things write I vnto thée, (ſayth hee) hoping to come ſhortly; but if I tarie long, that thou mayeſt knowe how thou oughteſt to behaue thy ſelfe in the houſe of God, which is the church of the liuing GOD, the pillar and ground of trueth.</p>
               <p>This church then, which <hi>Timothie</hi> was conuerſant in, is the church of <hi>Epheſus,</hi> called by S <hi>Paul,</hi> The pillar and ground of trueth: But this church of <hi>Epheſus</hi> hath condemned the doctrine of the Popes ſupremacie;<note place="margin">Conc. Flor. Seſſ. vlt. Chalcocon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dylas de Reb. Turc. lib. 6.</note> to which other churches of the Eaſt haue likewiſe con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deſcended. Therefore, if that be true ſtill, which the Church teacheth, becauſe S. <hi>Paul</hi> calleth it the pillar and ground of trueth; then the do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrine of the Popes ſupremacie is wicked, and Papiſtrie is hereſie: yea euen this church, notwithſtanding it was called the pillar and ground of trueth, is now left deſolate to <hi>Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>homets</hi> wicked impietie.</p>
               <pb n="43" facs="tcp:20283:34"/>
               <p>But let vs ſée by ſome few teſtimonies of the Fathers, how they haue expounded this place, and whether they haue applied it to generall Councels as the Papiſts do, and not rather to the whole Church conſiſting of the faithfull, as the Proteſtants vnderſtand it.</p>
               <p>S. <hi>Auguſt.</hi> ſaith,<note place="margin">Aug. in Pſal 47. in pr<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ef</note> We may not vnderſtand the ſecond of the Sabbath, to be any other than the Church of Chriſt, yet the Church of Chriſt in the Saints; the church of Chriſt in thoſe that are not ouercome with the tentations of this wicked world: for they are worthy the name of firmament. Therfore the church of Chriſt is called the firmament, in thoſe that are firme, which is, ſaith hee, the Church of the liuing God, the pillar and firmament of trueth.<note place="margin">Aug. de Bap li. 7. cap: 3 Tom. 6.</note> The like ſaying hath S. <hi>Auguſtine</hi> in many other places, but ſpecially where he writeth againſt the Donatiſts.</p>
               <p>Saint <hi>Chryſoſtome</hi> expoundeth this place of the verity it ſelfe,<note place="margin">Chryſ. Ho<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> 11, in 1. Tim. 3.</note> and not of the Paſtors or Councels, as the Papiſts do: For (ſayth he) the verity of the church is both the pillar and the firmament. And if you will ſée that the Fathers haue vnderſtood the church, as the Proteſtants do; reade S. <hi>Augu.</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Enchirid. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> Laurent. ca<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> 56.</note> expounding the Articles of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Créed, where he ſaith that the Church is here to be taken for the whole, &amp; not
<pb n="44" facs="tcp:20283:35"/> for that part onely, which is a ſtranger vpon earth.</p>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">Aug. in Pſal. 137.</note>Againe, he ſaith, There is a Church be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neath, there is a Church aboue, the Church beneath in all the faithfull, &amp;c.</p>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">Ibid. Pſal. 90. Conc. 2.</note>Likewiſe, the whole church euery where diffuſed is the body of Chriſt, and hee is the head of it: Not onely the faithfull which are now, but alſo they that were before vs, from the beginning of the world, and they that ſhall be after vs, to the ende of the world, doe all pertaine to this bodie. The church is the bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>die of Chriſt, not the church which is here or there, but which is here and euery where, tho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rowout the world, &amp;c. And often times in his writings he affirmeth the Catholike church to conſiſt of all the predeſtinate,<note place="margin">De ciuitat. Dei, li. 21. ca. 25. de Bapt. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>i. 6. ca. 3. In Iohn Tract. 45.</note> which are the members of Chriſts myſticall bodie, and that no wicked men perteine vnto it, but on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly the good, holy and iuſt. But to conclude this point, with one whom you haue euer reputed your owne.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſelmus <hi>ſuper hunc locum,</hi>
                  </hi> ſaith, The houſe in which God dwelleth, is the whole congre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gation of the faithfull; who are to be taught diuerſly: and the ſame Church is in the per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fect, a pillar; that is, ſublime, ſtreight, incon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuſſible, ſupporting and lifting vp the yonger
<pb n="45" facs="tcp:20283:35"/> ſort: and in the ſame perfect, it is the firma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of trueth, becauſe both by words and examples it confirmeth, in the hearts of the weake, the veritie of faith and Gods comman<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dements. Thus you ſée the Church is by theſe teſtimonies vnderſtood to be the congregati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of the faithfull, and not generall Councels, or Pope. And it is truely gathered out of theſe words of <hi>Anſelmus;</hi> which are to be taught, that the church conſiſteth aſwell of the Laity as the Cleargie. Now if you will ſee how the church may be knowen, <hi>Chryſoſtome</hi> ſaith,<note place="margin">Hom. in Mat. 49,</note> Before it might be ſhewed many waies, which was the church of Chriſt; But nowe it is no way to be knowen, but onely by the Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures. S. <hi>Auguſtine</hi> ſaith, (as we may true<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly ſay of the Papiſts) Let the Donatiſts (ſaith he) ſhew their church,<note place="margin">De vnitat. eccleſ. ca. 16.</note> not in the rumors and ſpeaches of the men of <hi>Africa,</hi> nor in the Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cels of their Biſhops, nor in their diſcourſes of any writer whoſoeuer, nor in ſignes and miracles that may be forged; but in the pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcript of the law, in the predictions of the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phets, in the verſes of the Pſalmes, in the voices of the ſhepheard himſelfe, in the prea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chings and workes of the Euangeliſt, that is in all the Canonicall authorities of the ſacred Scriptures. And binding himſelfe to the ſame
<pb n="46" facs="tcp:20283:36"/> condition, he addeth, But whether they hold the Church,<note place="margin">Ibidem.</note> let them ſhew no otherwiſe than by the Canonical books of the holy ſcriptures, becauſe wee our ſelues doe not ſay, wee muſt therefore bee beléeued, for that wee are in the church of Chriſt; or elſe for that <hi>Optatus, Am<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>broſe,</hi> and infinite other Biſhops of our com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>munion haue commended the church which we hold; or becauſe our Church hath béen publi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhed in the Councels of our <hi>Collegues.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">Chryſoſt. in Mat. Hom. 16.</note>
                  <hi>Chryſoſtome</hi> ſayth, Euen ſo touching this new Ieruſalem which is the Church, they that were ſpiritual Chriſtian men, leauing the bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dily church, which the wicked by violence had inuaded, departed out fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> them. Or as <hi>S. Iohn</hi> expoundeth it, they rather departed out fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> vs: for hee ſéemeth not (indeed) to depart from the church, that bodily departeth, but he that ſpiri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tually leaueth the foundations of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Eccleſiaſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cal truth. We haue departed fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> them in body; they haue departed from vs in mind: we from them in place; they from vs by faith: we haue left with them y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> foundations of the wals; they with vs the foundations of the ſcriptures: we are departed fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> them in the ſight of man; they are departed fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> vs in the iudgement of God. But now after y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> the ſpirituall church is come forth, y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> bodily church is left forſaken: that is to
<pb n="47" facs="tcp:20283:36"/> ſay, fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the people that ſéemed to be a chriſtian people, &amp; was not; this people is gone forth, that ſéemed not outwardly, but was ſo indéed: not<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>withſtanding as we haue ſaid before, they are rather departed from vs, than we from them. Now let y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> indifferent Reader iudge by <hi>Chry<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoſtomes</hi> iudgement, whether the Papiſts or we, by this deſcription may be trulieſt reputed the true church: for I thinke it is euident to all, that they haue the foundations of the wals, and we y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> foundations of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Scriptures, which they ſo blaſphemouſly ſpeak of: we are departed fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> them in the ſight of man; but they fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> vs in the ſight of God: &amp; who they were that ſéemed to be a chriſtian people, and were not; let that be tried by the Scriptures. And, if you wil know what authority y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Fathers giue to the church, <hi>S. Aug.</hi> ſaith,<note place="margin">Cont. Creſc<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> li. 2. ca. 21. Idem oper. imperf. in Mat. Ho. 49</note> The church may not preferre her ſelfe before Chriſt; neither may we beleeue the true churches themſelues, vnles they ſay &amp; do thoſe things y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> are conſonant to the ſcriptures.</p>
               <p>The church may not preferre her ſelf before Chriſt,<note place="margin">Idem contr<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> Creſcon. li 2 cap. 21.</note> for ſo much as hee alwaies iudgeth rightly; &amp; eccleſiaſtical Iudges, as being but men, are often deceiued. Many be the teſtimo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nies that might be brought to this purpoſe: but to procéed, we make the ſame iuſt exceptions a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt general Councels, y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> we did againſt the Fathers.</p>
               <pb n="48" facs="tcp:20283:37"/>
               <p>Firſt, we will prooue that they are contrary one to another.</p>
               <p>Secondly, that they haue erred.</p>
               <p>And laſtly, that they are reiected by the Papiſts.</p>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">Canon 59.</note>The firſt Exception I prooue thus; (for I wil be brief) The Councel of <hi>Laodicea,</hi> (though a prouinciall Councell,<note place="margin">Conſtant. in Trullo, Can. 2.</note> yet allowed by a ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nerall Councel of <hi>Conſtantinople</hi>) did ſet down the ſame Canon of the Scriptures, which both the old church had, and our church doth holde; and commandeth, <hi>Ne aliqui praeterea legantur, &amp; in auctoritatem recipiantur. <hi>That none be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſides be read, and receiued into authoritie.</hi>
                  </hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">Canon. 47. Seſſ. 3.</note>The third Councel of <hi>Carthage</hi> which ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in the Councel of <hi>Trent</hi> ſubſcribeth to, did adde the bookes of the <hi>Maccabees,</hi> and the reſt of the Apocrypha, to the olde Canon, contrary to the ſayd Councels of <hi>Laodicea</hi> and <hi>Conſtanti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nople.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">Can. 6.</note>The Councel of <hi>Nice</hi> appointed boundes and limits, aſwell for the Biſhop of <hi>Romes</hi> iu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſdiction, as for other Biſhops: contrary to which the Councell of <hi>Lateran</hi> gaue the So<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uereignty of ordinary power,<note place="margin">Can. 5. apud Innocent. 3.</note> to the church of <hi>Rome,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Conc. Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>tant. as it is extant, Nice 2. Act. 6. Tom. 6.</note> ouer all Churches.</p>
               <p>The Councel of <hi>Constantinople</hi> condemned the ſetting vp of Images: contrary to which
<pb n="49" facs="tcp:20283:37"/> The Councell of <hi>Nice,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Aen. Sylu. de Conc. Ba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſil. contr. Flor. &amp; Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rar. Conc. Conſtant. Seſſ. 4. &amp; 5.</note> accurſeth thoſe that worſhip not holy images. I will inlarge this part no further, though I could ſhewe, that ſome Councels haue decréed, That the Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cell is aboue the Pope: ſome that the Pope is aboue the Councel.</p>
               <p>The next is thus prooued: Firſt, this is an infallible rule, That Councels decréeing things contrary (as is inſtanced in theſe few examples before) It muſt of neceſſitie follow, that the one of them muſt erre: yet wil I prooue it by ſome more particulars.</p>
               <p>The ſecond Councel of <hi>Nice,</hi> decréed,<note place="margin">Act. 5.</note> That Angels and mens ſoules are bodily &amp; circum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcriptible: and yet this Councel, notwithſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding this groſſe error, was confirmed by the Councell held at <hi>Constantinople;</hi> which Pope <hi>Agatho</hi> hath allowed for a generall Councel.</p>
               <p>In the Councell of <hi>Neoceſaria</hi> confirmed by <hi>Leo</hi> the <hi>4.</hi> ſecond mariage is forbidden.<note place="margin">Canon 7.</note> The Canon ſaith, he is commanded to enioyne pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nance for ſecond mariage.</p>
               <p>The Councel of <hi>Toletan</hi> ſaith,<note place="margin">Tolet. 1. Can. 17.</note> He that hath not a wife, but in ſtead of his wife, a concubine, is not for this cauſe to be repelled the commu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nion. This Councell was confirmed by <hi>Leo,</hi> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>s it may appeare, <hi>Canon 21.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>In the ſixt generall Councel,<note place="margin">Can. 72.</note> the mariages
<pb n="50" facs="tcp:20283:38"/> betwixt Catholikes and Heretikes are iudged to be voide. Now whether theſe be groſſe and manifeſt errors, I referre it to the cenſure of any indifferent Reader. But theſe abſur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dities they are forced to giue way to, or elſe to ouerthrowe that maine pillar of Popery, <hi>That the Church cannot erre.</hi> The laſt part which I promiſed to ſhewe, is; <hi>That Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cels are reiected by the Papiſts.</hi> This is proo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued, for that many things are reiected by them in both the ſaid Exceptions: But I will in<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſtance ſome few more.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Andradius</hi> the defender of the <hi>Tridentine</hi> Councell, in his firſt booke, reiecteth the Coun<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>cell of <hi>Chalcedon,</hi> one of thoſe firſt foure Coun<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>cels (which <hi>Gregorie</hi> profeſſeth to receiue, as the holy Goſpels) ſaying, <hi>This Councell er<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red, in that it did raſhly, and without reaſon ordaine; That the Church of <hi>Conſtantinople,</hi> ſhould be aboue the Church of <hi>Alexandria</hi> and <hi>Antioch.</hi>
                  </hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">Conc. Chal. de Laicis, ca. 20. Praefat. in li, de pont.</note>
                  <hi>Bellarmine</hi> ſaith, <hi>That in the Councell of <hi>Chalcedon,</hi> there is ſomthing good, and ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing euill,</hi> and that we may receiue the one, and refuſe the other. And in another place he diſpenſeth with himſelfe to reproue, in the ſam<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> manner, the Councell of <hi>Conſtantinople,</hi> for hauing attempted ſomewhat, that did not
<pb n="51" facs="tcp:20283:38"/> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>leaſe the Church of <hi>Rome.</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Bellar. de Conc. &amp; ec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cleſ. li, 10. ca. 60.70. Pighi. Hier. eccleſ. li. 6. cap. 4. &amp; 5. &amp; 7.</note> And he reiecteth wholly ſeuen general Councels. Reade like<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe what <hi>Pighius</hi> hath written of purpoſe <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>o diſcredit the ſixt and ſeuenth Synodes. And <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>e impugneth the Councel of <hi>Constance</hi> and <hi>Baſil.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Now though we haue prooued the thrée par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>icularities propoſed, wherein our lawful and <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>ſt Exceptio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s againſt Councels are euident: <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>et let vs ſée whether our aſſertio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> in this point <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>e iuſtified both by the Fathers, and chiefe and <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>earned Papiſts.</p>
               <p>Saint <hi>Auguſtine</hi> ſayth, <hi>That generall Councels are often amended, the former by <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>he later:</hi> and if our aduerſaries obiect, That <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>hey are amended but not from errors; What <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>éede amending where no fault is? The con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>itions, which S. <hi>Auguſtine</hi> repeateth in the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>rſt, indureth to the laſt, <hi>Si quid fortè à verita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>e deuiatum est, <hi>If in ought they ſwarne from <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>he trueth.</hi>
                  </hi> And it is manifeſt by the drift of <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>he place, writing againſt the Donatiſts,<note place="margin">Epiſt. 7<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap> Iubai.</note> that <hi>maintained the authority</hi> of the Councel hol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>en by S. <hi>Cyprian</hi> againſt the trueth, that hée ſpeaketh manifeſtly of <hi>Correction of errors,</hi> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>nd not of things indifferent, as the Papiſts <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>loſe to maintaine their error; <hi>That generall Councels cannot erre.</hi>
               </p>
               <pb n="52" facs="tcp:20283:39"/>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">In Epiſt. ad procopi.</note>The <hi>Arrians</hi> preuailed ſo by Councels, that it made <hi>Gregorie Nazianzen,</hi> to de<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſpaire, that euer any good would bee done by Councels</p>
               <p>Saint <hi>Auguſtine</hi> rehearſing two Epiſco<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pall iudgements,<note place="margin">Epiſt. 16.7.</note> that paſſed againſt the Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>natiſts, in the Councels at <hi>Rome</hi> and <hi>Arle,</hi> he ſheweth how Councels might bind vs: But, (ſaith he) let theſe be counted the iudgements of men, and let it be ſaid, They might either de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiue, or be deceiued, and perhaps corrupted.</p>
               <p>Saint <hi>Auguſtine</hi> hauing ſhewed, that th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> Councell of <hi>Ariminum,</hi> being deceiued by the ſubtilty of a fewe, decréed againſt the Coun<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>cel of <hi>Nice,</hi> which had decréed againſt the <hi>Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rian</hi> Heretikes,<note place="margin">Cont. Maxi. li. 3. ca. 14.</note> concludeth thus againſt <hi>Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ximinus;</hi> But now, neither ought I to produc<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> the Councell of <hi>Nice,</hi> nor you the Councell o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <hi>Ariminum,</hi> for a preiudice: for neither am I bound to the authoritie of this, nor you to th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> authoritie of that. Thus you ſée he confeſſeth that his aduerſarie was not tied to the autho<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ritie of the great <hi>Nicen</hi> Councel: comparabl<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> to the which no Councel was euer yet. Yea, S <hi>Hillarie</hi> was nothing afraid to be condemne<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> in many Councels.<note place="margin">Hillar. cont. Auxent. &amp; Arrian.</note> Now let him gather wha<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> Councels he will againſt me (ſaith he) and o<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>penly proſcribe me for an Heretike, as he had
<pb n="53" facs="tcp:20283:39"/> often done. The <hi>Arrians</hi> in <hi>26</hi> yéers,<note place="margin">Euſeb. li. 7. cap. 5.</note> gathered &amp; framed ſundry Councels for their purpoſe at <hi>Tyrus, Ieruſalem, Philippi, Sirmium, Ariminum,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Sozom. li. 4. ca. 9.</note> 
                  <hi>Selucia, Conſtantinople,</hi> and two at <hi>Antiochia.</hi> In the Councell of <hi>Millan,</hi> aboue thrée hun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dred of the Weſt Biſhops conſented, that <hi>A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thanaſius</hi> ſhould bee thruſt from his Biſhop<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ricke. There was but fiue againſt thrée hun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dred, that openly and plainely withſtood it. And <hi>Leo</hi> writeth of the famous Councell of <hi>Chalcedon, Tanquam refutari nequeat quod illi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>citè voluerit multitudo;</hi>
                  <note place="margin">In Epiſt. 52. ad Anatho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lium.</note> 
                  <hi>As though that might not be refuted, which a multitude hath vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lawfully decreed.</hi> Yea,<note place="margin">Panor. de E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lect. &amp; electi poteſtate, c. ſignificaſti.</note> your owne men haue béen of the ſame opinion with vs. <hi>Panormi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tane,</hi> the beſt of your Canoniſts; yea, a reue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rend Archbiſhop, and a renowmed Cardinall ſaith, A Councel may erre, as otherwiſe, a Councel hath erred about mariage to be con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tracted betwéene the Rauiſher, &amp; the Rauiſhed: and the ſaying of <hi>Hierome,</hi> as being of the ſounder opinion, was after preferred, before the Statute of the Councel. And the argu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment which Papiſts make, That the church ſhould faile in faith, if Councels ſhould erre, he reiecteth as friuolous, ſaying;<note place="margin">Panor. ibid.</note> It hindereth vs little, if it be ſaid, that a Councel cannot erre, becauſe Chriſt prayed for his Church, that it
<pb n="54" facs="tcp:20283:40"/> ſhould not faile. For though a generall Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cell repreſent the whole vniuerſall Church, yet to ſpeake trueth, the vniuerſall Church is not there preciſely, but by repreſentation; becauſe the vniuerſall Church conſiſteth of all the faithfull. <hi>And this is the Church which cannot erre, &amp;c.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">Pighius Hie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ra<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>. eccl. li. 6. ca. 4. &amp; 5.</note>
                  <hi>Pighius</hi> ſaith, it is certaine, <hi>that Councels are not the vniuerſall Church. In none of all the generall Councels ſhall you find, the fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers to haue arrogated thus much to them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelues, as to ſay they repreſented the Catho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>like Church; beſides theſe two laſt Councels of <hi>Conſtance,</hi> and <hi>Baſil,</hi> which we now im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pugne.</hi> And that <hi>General Councels may erre,</hi> he ſayth,<note place="margin">Li. 6. ca. 13.</note> 
                  <hi>It is certaine, that not onely theſe Councels (of <hi>Conſtance</hi> and <hi>Baſil</hi>) which we now diſproue, haue ſhamefully &amp; abſurdly erred, but alſo many others.</hi> And againe, <hi>We find that General Councels, euen of holy Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers, haue erred in decrees of faith: for ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ample of General Councels; The Councell of <hi>Ariminum,</hi> vniuerſall no doubt, and alſo the ſecond Councel of <hi>Epheſus,</hi> and that like<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe vniuerſall: Theſe I ſay are witneſſes, That euen general Councels, and thoſe law<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fully gathered may erre.</hi> The Biſhops that were preſent at <hi>Epheſus,</hi> commplained after
<pb n="55" facs="tcp:20283:40"/> in the Councell of <hi>Chalcedon,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Chalced. Conc. Act. 1.</note> that they were <hi>threatned</hi> and <hi>forced.</hi> Now if Biſhops may be forced, they may likewiſe bee circumuen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted, as they were in the Councel of <hi>Ariminum;</hi> or deceiued in opinion, as they were in the Councels of <hi>Carthage, Constance,</hi> and <hi>Baſill,</hi> by the confeſſion of learned Papiſtes them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelues. And if they may by all theſe wayes bee peruerted when they are aſſembled, <hi>Ergo,</hi> they may make both an erronious &amp; an iniuri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous concluſion. Wherefore, ſince it appeares euidently by this little that hath béene ſayd, <hi>That Generall Councels are no infallible rule, to build our faith on:</hi> What muſt wee then doe, to finde out a ſure Ground, where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>upon to ground our Religion?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Papiſt.</speaker>
               <p>
                  <hi>The laſt, and onely meanes, without all exception, is the Pope; whoſe faith cannot faile, neither can he erre iudicially. So that whether with the Councels, or without the Councels, <hi>That which he determineth and tea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cheth is a certaine trueth: That which hee con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demneth is a manifeſt Error.</hi>
                  </hi>
               </p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Proteſtant.</speaker>
               <p n="19">
                  <hi>19</hi> This aunſwere doeth manifeſt to all that are not wilfully blinde, that what
<pb n="56" facs="tcp:20283:41"/> brags ſoeuer you make of Fathers and Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cels, (who, as <hi>Campian</hi> boaſted in his tenne Reaſons, were al as ſure on your ſide, as Pope <hi>Gregory</hi> the thirtéenth) that yet yet the Pope is the man, vpon whom you ground your Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion: neither eſtéeming Fathers, Councels, or the learned of your owne ſide, further than they may ſtand and concurre with the Popes good pleaſure; which by this little Tract may euidently be deduced: For firſt, you ground your Religion on the Word; the Word on the Fathers; the Fathers on Councels; and the Councels on the Pope: So that in all the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trouerſies betwéene vs and you, we muſt ſtand to the cenſure of your Pope, who muſt be both Iudge and partie. And if he giue iudgement on our ſide I will neuer truſt him. But to o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerthrowe this pillar of Popery thorowly, I will prooue, that the Pope hath erred iudicial<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly:<note place="margin">
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>h<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>. Teſt. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>uk 22. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ect. 11.</note> For albeit they confeſſe, that the Pope may be an Heretike, yea, that <hi>Liberius</hi> the Pope might yéeld in perſecution; <hi>Marcellinus</hi> the Pope, for feare, might commit idolatrie; <hi>Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>norius</hi> the Pope might fal to hereſie, and more than all this, that ſome <hi>Iudas</hi> might créepe in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the office, as their Rhemiſts confeſſe: yet they diſtinguiſh betwéene the perſon and the office. And as their laſt ſhift and refuge ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing
<pb n="57" facs="tcp:20283:41"/> béen driuen by force of reaſon and exam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ples, to acknowledge thus much, They now inſiſt vpon this laſt anchor, as their laſt hope to auoide ſhipwracke, That the Pope cannot erre iudicially; that is, in their Conſiſtories, Courts, Councels, decrées, deliberations, or conſultations kept for deciſion and determina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of ſuch controuerſies, doubts, or Queſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons of faith, as ſhall be propoſed to them. Now what wrangling and ſhifting is this, to aſke for the place where, and the time when, the Pope decréed for error? For if he may erre at home, he may likewiſe erre abroad. If the Pope be an Heretike in his chamber, hee cannot bee a Catholike in his Conſiſtorie. And if the Pope may beléeue, defend, and preach an error, what néede we care whether his ſentence, be concluſiue, or perſwaſiue, definitiue or inter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>locutorie. And if you thinke that this idle di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtinction, can frée your Pope from his errors, becauſe thy haue not been definitiuely pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nounced in their publike Conſiſtories: wee could name infinite Biſhops and churches that haue not erred in this preciſe maner: For how can you prooue that euer the Biſhops of <hi>Yorke</hi> or <hi>Durham</hi> in <hi>England,</hi> of <hi>Poycters</hi> or <hi>Lions</hi> in <hi>France,</hi> of <hi>Valeria</hi> or <hi>Corduba</hi> in <hi>Spaine,</hi> of <hi>Ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uenna</hi> or <hi>Rhegium</hi> in <hi>Italy,</hi> of <hi>Corinth</hi> or <hi>Athens</hi>
                  <pb facs="tcp:20283:42"/> in <hi>Greece,</hi> of <hi>Miletus</hi> or <hi>Sardis</hi> in <hi>Aſia,</hi> gaue definitiue ſentence againſt the faith, in their publike Conſiſtories? Infinite others might be obiected, againſt whom it could neuer bee proued, that they haue erred in this kind: and therfore this cannot but be a ſtrong Bulwark wheron you depend &amp; boaſt, <hi>That it cannot be prooued, that the Biſhop of <hi>Rome</hi> hath erred, iudicially, or definitiuely.</hi> For if Popes haue erred in writing and teaching, they were as right Heretikes as euer were <hi>Arrius, Sabel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lius, Neſtorius, Eutiches,</hi> and ſuch like; which neuer gaue <hi>Definitiue ſentence againſt the faith, in Courts and Conſiſtories,</hi> but onely taught or wrote, againſt the trueth. But this new Popery was not then, nor many yéeres after found out; though the quaint Ieſuits, haue of late refined their late Poperie, to giue a colour to the Popes priuiledge.</p>
               <p>And albeit this were ſufficient, yet will I briefly procéede and prooue, that the Pope hath erred Definitiuely or Iudicially; as his De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cretals which are Definitiue ſentences ſhall euidently prooue.</p>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">In Chronic. Supputat. Romanor. po<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t. de Reg. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>tal. li. 6.</note>Firſt <hi>Sigebert, Martinus Polonus,</hi> and <hi>Si<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gonius</hi> doe witneſſe that Pope <hi>Stephen</hi> the <hi>6.</hi> decréed in a Councel, <hi>That they who were ordained Biſhops by Pope <hi>Formoſus,</hi> were
<pb facs="tcp:20283:42"/> not ordained lawfully, becauſe the man was wicked by whome they were ordained.</hi> And hee did not onely depriue, and vnordaine them who were ordeined by <hi>Formoſus,</hi> but he de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>créed too, as <hi>Sigebert</hi> noteth,<note place="margin">Ordinatio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes eius om<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>nes irrita<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> eſſe debere decernit.</note> 
                  <hi>That all the or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dainings of <hi>Formoſus,</hi> ought to be void:</hi> And this,<note n="*" place="margin">Pag 42. 7<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> Concil Ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen An. Do 898. Sigon. de Reg. Ita<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> li. 6.</note> Maſter <hi>Hart</hi> againſt Doctor <hi>Raynolds</hi> confeſſeth to be an error in faith. And <hi>Iohn</hi> the ninth in the Councel of <hi>Rauenna,</hi> condem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned <hi>Stephen</hi> and his Councell, and therein their new ordainings are forbidden, and mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ched with new Baptizings.</p>
               <p>Pope <hi>Coeleſtine</hi> the third did ſet forth a de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crée, that, <hi>when of married perſons, one fal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leth into hereſie, the marriage is diſſolued; and the Catholike partie is free to marrie a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gaine:</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Mat. 19.9.</note> flat againſt the Scriptures.</p>
               <p>And <hi>Alfonſus,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Alfon. à Ca<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſtro aduer. Haereſ. li. 1. ca. 4.</note> a famous patron of the Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pacie, doeth ſhewe, that he defined it. <hi>For, that Pope <hi>Coelestine</hi> did erre</hi> (ſaith <hi>Alfon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſus) about the marriage of the faithfull, of whome one falleth into Hereſie, It is ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nifeſt to all men: Neither was this errour of <hi>Coelestine</hi> ſuch, as ought to bee imputed to negligence alone; That wee may ſay he erred as a priuate man, and not as a Pope, who in defining of any ſerious matter, ſhould aske counſel of learned men.</hi> For this
<pb n="60" facs="tcp:20283:43"/> definition of <hi>Coeleſtine</hi> was extant in the olde Decretals, which I my ſelfe haue ſéene and read.<note place="margin">Super quart. decretal. c. quanto de <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>iuortijs. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> Ide<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſiqui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dem de co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                     <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>erſ. infid. c. audabilem. Gratia diſt. 9. c. in <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>omi. § <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>drian in 4: <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ent. de con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>irma. ca. vlt. Gerſon &amp; Almain Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>iſie<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſes The<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>logi. Decret. li 4. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>e diuort. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>uanto. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> Ibid. prae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deceſſor. Decretal. li. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>. de de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>o<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſa duoru<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> 
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap> licet prae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter.</note> And this is confirmed by Cardinal <hi>Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtienſis,</hi> who noteth the very paragraph of the Chapter, in the which it was, and ſpeaketh of it as a Decretall. And that the Pope may erre in iudgement of faith, <hi>Gratian, Adrian, Gerſon,</hi> and <hi>Almaine,</hi> the Diuines of <hi>Paris</hi> affirme. <hi>Innocentius</hi> the third, when he deci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded the cauſe, confeſſed, that one of his prede<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſors had decréed otherwiſe; which, ſaith the Gloze, was <hi>Coeleſtinus:</hi> whoſe reſolution was in the old Decretals, and it was euill that <hi>Coe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſtinus</hi> ſayd.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Alexander</hi> the third, in a matter of great importance, ſayd, <hi>Quamuis aliter à quibuſdam praedeceſſoribus nostris ſit aliquando iudicatum. <hi>Though ſome of our predeceſſors haue here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tofore otherwiſe giuen iudgement.</hi>
                  </hi> And if you obiect (for you will euer find ſome ſhift) that theſe were matters of mariage, and not of faith: as though the ſeuering of thoſe, whome God hath ioyned, did not touch the faith.</p>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>e conſe. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>iſtin. 2. Ego Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ren.</note>
                  <hi>Nicolaus</hi> the ſecond, in a Councell of <hi>114.</hi> Biſhops, appointed <hi>Berengarius</hi> to confeſſe, That the very body of Chriſt is in trueth, and ſenſually broken, and bruiſed in pieces with the téeth of the faithfull. And this confeſſion the
<pb n="61" facs="tcp:20283:43"/> Pope receiued, allowed, and ſent to the Bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhops of <hi>Italy, Germany,</hi> and <hi>France,</hi> as Catho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>like; which your owne Gloze ſaith,<note place="margin">Ibid. c. den<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tibus.</note> is a grea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter hereſie than euer <hi>Berengarius</hi> held, vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſſe you vnderſtand this of the outwarde formes of Bread and Wine, and not of the bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy of Chriſt.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Honorius</hi> the Pope did hold and teach the <hi>Monothelites</hi> hereſie,<note place="margin">1. Tim. 3 16 Luk. 22.42</note> who (whereas Chriſt is made our Sauiour and Redéemer, by that he doeth conſiſt of two natures, God and man; and as of two natures, ſo of two willes agrée<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able to the natures) they ſay that Chriſt hath but one will onely, and by conſequent but one nature. The ſixt general Councel hath hand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led the cauſe of the <hi>Monotholite</hi> heretikes, in <hi>18.</hi> actions, as they are tearmed. In the firſt action, the <hi>8.</hi> and the <hi>11.</hi> the heretikes alleage in their owne defence, that Pope <hi>Honorius</hi> taught as they do. In the <hi>12.</hi> &amp; <hi>13.</hi> his writings are examined, his hereſie diſcouered, himſelfe condemned and curſed. In the <hi>16. 17,</hi> &amp; <hi>18.</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Honor. ha<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>
                     <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>retico An<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>thema.</note> the ſentence which was giuen againſt him, and the curſe are repeated often, againe and againe with acclamation of the Councel: yea, the prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cipal point of his Decrées,<note place="margin">Vid: Rayn<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> ver. Hart <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> diu. 2. pag 293.</note> ſet forth to teach the Church, was the <hi>Monothelites</hi> hereſie: this is confirmed by chiefe Papiſts.</p>
               <pb n="62" facs="tcp:20283:44"/>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">Abbas Vrſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>erg. Ann. 1080. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ciculus <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>er ſciendar. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>n vita &amp; <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>eſt. Hilde<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>randi.</note>Pope <hi>Gregory</hi> the <hi>7.</hi> was condemned by the Biſhops of <hi>France</hi> and <hi>Germany,</hi> as the an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cient diſciple of the Heretike <hi>Berengarius,</hi> and ſwaruing from the true faith: And in ſpeciall words; <hi>This is <hi>Hildebrands</hi> Decree, in which hee erred from the Catholike doctrine and faith.</hi> Now let the indifferent Reader iudge betwéene you and vs, whether the Pope be a competent iudge. But how may it appeare, that to him is committed ſo great a charge, and that his ſentence is ſo abſolute, <hi>that all authorities of Scripture, Fathers, and Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cels, muſt ſubmit themſelues to his Cenſure?</hi>
               </p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Papiſt.</speaker>
               <p>
                  <hi>The abſolute authority of his Holineſſe is prooued by many places of Scripture; as, <hi>Thou art</hi> Peter,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Mat. 16.18.</note> 
                  <hi>and vpon this Rocke will I build my Church: <hi>and,</hi> the gates of hell ſhall not pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uaile against it:</hi>
                  <note place="margin">
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>uk. 22.32.</note> 
                  <hi>and, <hi>I haue prayed for thee</hi> Pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, <hi>that thy faith faile not:</hi> and, <hi>Thou being con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerted, ſtrengthen thy brethren:</hi> and, Feede my ſheepe:</hi>
                  <note place="margin">
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>oh. 21.17</note> 
                  <hi>Feede my lambes. <hi>And many other places of Scriptures, Fathers, and Councels doe conferre this ſpeciall priuiledge vpon</hi> Peter <hi>and</hi> Peters <hi>Succeſſours: By which means, all Controuerſies whatſoeuer may be determined.</hi>
                  </hi>
               </p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <pb n="63" facs="tcp:20283:44"/>
               <speaker>Protestant.</speaker>
               <p>This is ſtrange Diuinitie, and ſtranger Logicke: Chriſt ſayd, Thou art <hi>Peter,</hi> &amp; vpon this Rocke will I build my Church. <hi>Ergo,</hi> the Church is builded onely vpon <hi>Peter</hi> and the Pope. The gates of hell ſhall neuer preuaile againſt the Church. <hi>Ergo, <hi>Peter</hi>
                  </hi> and the Pope. are the Church, againſt which the gates of hell ſhall not preuaile. I haue prayed for thée <hi>Peter,</hi> that thy faith faile not: <hi>Ergo,</hi> whatſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>euer is determined by the Pope is not ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iect to error. And Chriſt ſayd to <hi>Peter,</hi> Feede my ſhéepe. <hi>Ergo,</hi> hée made him ſupreame head of the Apoſtles: Or thus, Chriſt did charge <hi>Peter</hi> to féede his ſhéepe: But the Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtles were ſhéepe of Chriſt; <hi>Ergo,</hi> hee had the charge of féeding them alſo, and ſo had ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolute authority. Nowe to make you ſée the folly of this manner of reaſoning, obſerue this argument, and you ſhall by that meanes eaſily diſcerne the weakeneſſe of your owne reaſon; Chriſt did charge his Apoſtles to preach the Goſpel to euery creature: But <hi>Pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter</hi> was a creature; <hi>Ergo,</hi> they had charge of preaching to him alſo. And this muſt néedes ouerſway your reaſon, if a man would play with words: For Chriſt ſaid not to <hi>Peter,</hi> féede al my ſheep: but he ſaid to y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Apoſtles, preach to
<pb n="64" facs="tcp:20283:45"/> euery creature. And if theſe conſequents bée good, then is it an eaſie and a ſafe way to decide all differences, and wee might well haue ſpa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red all theſe paines: for it will neceſſarily fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low, that if the Pope cannot erre in any point of doctrine or diſcipline of the Church, then the Scriptures, Fathers, &amp; Councels, are ſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perfluous:<note place="margin">Act. 15.</note> Neither is that Gloze to any pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe, that the Rhemiſts make; That the va<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rious meanes of determination, triall, and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>claration of the trueth, is neceſſary for the recouery of Heretikes, and for the contentati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of the weake; who not alwaies giuing ouer to one mans determination, wil either yéeld to the iudgement of all the learned men, and Bl<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhops of all Nations, or elſe remaine deſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rate. For ſince there is ſo variable cenſures of Councels:<note place="margin">Aene. Sylu. de Concil. Baſil. contr. Flor. &amp; Fer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rar. in Conc. indict. Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cil. Conſt. Seſſ. 4. &amp;. 5.</note> ſome holding the Pope to bee aboue the Councell; and ſome holding the Councell to be aboue the Pope; If this point be ſoundly prooued, That <hi>Peters</hi> Sée hath ſo the aſſiſtance of the holy Ghoſt, that it cannot erre: all other cauſes of the neceſſitie of Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers, or learned Biſhops of all Nations, is ſuperfluous: for if the priuiledge of not erring belong to the Pope and his ſucceſſors; why is it made common to them, with the reſt of the Church? If it appertaine to the whole Church,
<pb n="65" facs="tcp:20283:45"/> why is it appropriated to the Pope? But why doe they bring Scriptures to prooue this ſpeci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>all <hi>priuiledge, to belong to the Pope:</hi> Séeing <hi>Canus</hi> and <hi>Bellarmine,</hi> two great <hi>Champi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons</hi> of the <hi>Romiſh Church</hi> doe both confeſſe, that <hi>It is not in the Scripture, but by Traditi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, that the Pope hath this ſupremacie.</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Locor. The<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>olo. li 6. c. 8.</note> Firſt <hi>Canus</hi> doth graunt, <hi>That it is not written in the Scriptures, that the Pope ſucceedeth <hi>Pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter</hi> in the ſupremacie.</hi> And <hi>Bellarmine</hi> the great Ieſuite ſayth, That whereas <hi>Canus</hi> thought, that the ſtories haue ſufficient ground to conuey <hi>Peters</hi> right vnto the Pope; becauſe they ſay, <hi>Peter <hi>ſet his chaire at</hi> Rome, <hi>&amp; there died:</hi>
                  </hi> yet ſayth he,<note place="margin">Controu. 4. q. 5. de pont. finitae. 26. Maij. An. 1578.</note> if learned men ſhall not al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low of that, <hi>Another ground may bee, that the Church receiued it, though not by Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, yet by Tradition.</hi> And to put the mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter out of controuerſie, he defineth, <hi>that indeed it is a Tradition, not of Chriſt,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Licet Ro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manos E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piſcopos Petro ſuc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cedere in ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cris libris no<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> habeatur Scriptum: ab Apoſto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lis tamen Eccleſiae quaſi per Manus Traditum eſt. Romanum pontificem eſſe Petri ſucceſſorem in pontifica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tu totius orbis habetur extraditione Apoſtolica: etri.</note> 
                  <hi>but of the A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſtles:</hi> and leſt we ſhould doubt of which of the Apoſtles, he nameth the man, <hi>Peter;</hi> euen <hi>a tradition of <hi>Peter.</hi>
                  </hi> And therefore if you will follow the iudgement of this learned Ieſuite, which you all receiue with ſo great applauſe, then renounce the vnlearned follies of your
<pb n="66" facs="tcp:20283:46"/> 
                  <hi>Rhemiſts</hi> and others, who violently wreſt the Scriptures, to prooue the <hi>Popes priuiledge.</hi> For when you vrge theſe places, <hi>Thou art <hi>Peter,</hi> and on this rocke, &amp;c.</hi> and, <hi>I haue pray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed for thee <hi>Peter;</hi>
                  </hi> and, <hi>Peter, <hi>feede my ſheepe;</hi>
                  </hi> You preſume much of the ſimplicitie of your hearers: otherwiſe you would neuer reaſon ſo abſurdly. For though <hi>Stapleton,</hi> and ſome others vpon the <hi>16.</hi> of <hi>Matth.</hi> by theſe words; <hi>Thou art Peter, &amp;c.</hi> alleage the firſt Popes of <hi>Rome,</hi> moſt holy martyrs, to prooue the <hi>Popes Supremacie,</hi> by the Scriptures: and do rec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kon vp <hi>Anacletus, Alexander the 1. Pius the 1. Victor, Zepherinus, Marcellus, Melchia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>des,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Locor. The<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>olo. li. 6. c. 8 Bellar. cont. 4. q. 5.</note> 
                  <hi>Iulius,</hi> and others; yet doeth <hi>Canus</hi> and <hi>Bellarmine</hi> prooue, that it is grounded on <hi>Tra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dition;</hi> and <hi>Canus</hi> doth cite for witneſſes ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of, the firſt Popes of <hi>Rome,</hi> moſt holy martyrs. And the ſame Popes which are alleaged by <hi>Canus,</hi> to prooue the Supremacie, to be an <hi>vnwritten trueth;</hi> the very ſame Popes are alleaged by <hi>Stapleto<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>,</hi> to proue, that, <hi>It is writ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten: euen Anacletus, Victor, Zepherinus, Marcellus, Melchiades &amp; Iulius:</hi> yea, the very ſame Epiſtles are alleaged by <hi>Stapleto<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>,</hi> which are alleaged by <hi>Canus.</hi> Now if they be rightly cited by <hi>Canus,</hi> how may we truſt <hi>Stapleto<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>?</hi> if rightly by <hi>Stapl.</hi> how may we truſt <hi>Canus?</hi> if
<pb n="67" facs="tcp:20283:46"/> rightly by both, what trim Popes are they, y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> with one breath do ſay, <hi>That the ſame thing is both written and vnwritten.</hi> But the Ieſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ite dealeth more warily: who ſéeing the dan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger of naming ſpeciall men and places, doeth ſhrowde himſelfe in the generall tearmes, <hi>of Councels, Popes, and Fathers.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Thus you ſée how the Lord doth ſheath the ſwords of the Madianites in their owne ſides.<note place="margin">Iudg. 7.22.</note> But let vs ſée how y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Fathers vnderſtood theſe Scriptures that are brought to priuiledge the <hi>Pope from erring,</hi> and ſet downe their ſayings at large, though we haue briefly before in the <hi>14.</hi> Queſtion, part <hi>3,</hi> vrged their authorities.<note place="margin">Aug. de ver. Domini ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cundu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> Mat. ſerm. 13.</note> S. <hi>Auguſtine</hi> expoundeth the firſt place thus; <hi>Thou art <hi>Peter,</hi>
                  </hi> (ſaith Chriſt) <hi>and vpon this Rocke, which thou haſt confeſſed, vpon this Rocke, which thou haſt acknowledged,</hi> by ſaying, <hi>Thou art Chriſt the Sonne of the li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing God, wil I build my Church; that is, vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on my ſelfe, the Sonne of the liuing God, will I build my Church; I wil build thee vpon me, not my ſelfe vpon thee.</hi> S. <hi>Hillary</hi> ſaith,<note place="margin">Hillar. de Trin. li. 30</note> 
                  <hi>This onely is the immoueable foundation, This onely is the happy rocke of faith, which was confeſſed by <hi>Peters</hi> mouth, Thou art the Son of the liuing God: Then vpo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> this rock of co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                     <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſsion, ſtandeth the building of the Church.</hi>
               </p>
               <pb n="68" facs="tcp:20283:47"/>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">Ambr. in 2. ca. epiſt. ad Ephe.</note>Saint <hi>Ambroſe</hi> ſaith, <hi>The Lord ſaith to <hi>Peter, Vpon this rocke will I build my Church;</hi> that is in this confeſſion of the Catholike faith. Faith therefore is the foundation of the Church: for it was not ſpoken of <hi>Peters</hi> fleſh, but of faith, <hi>That hell gates ſhould not pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uaile againſt it:</hi> but that confeſsion conque<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red hell.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">Chryſ. Hom. 55. in Mat.</note>
                  <hi>Chryſoſtome</hi> ſayth, <hi>Vpon this Rocke will I build my Church; <hi>that is, vpon this faith and confeſsion.</hi>
                  </hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">Bed. in ca. 21. Iohan.</note>
                  <hi>Bede</hi> likewiſe, <hi>Vpon this Rocke which thou haſt confeſſed, will I build my Church. That Rocke was Chriſt, vpon the which foundation, euen <hi>Peter</hi> himſelfe was to be builded.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">1. Cor. 3.</note>Theſe Fathers meane as Saint <hi>Paul</hi> doth, ſaying, <hi>Another foundation can no man lay, than that which is already layd, which is Ie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſus Chriſt.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Others there are of the Fathers, <hi>that ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plie this rocke to <hi>Peter;</hi>
                  </hi> but not as though he alone were the foundation, but including the reſt with him.<note place="margin">Hiero. lib. 1. aduer. Io<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uin.</note> As for example; Saint <hi>Hierom</hi> ſaith, <hi>Thou wilt ſay the Church is built on <hi>Peter:</hi> notwithſtanding the ſelfe ſame in an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>other place is done vpon al the Apoſtles, and they all receiue the Keyes of the kingdome
<pb n="69" facs="tcp:20283:47"/> of heauen, and the ſtedfaſtneſſe of the Church, is equally ſetled vpon them.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Origen</hi> ſayth, <hi>If onely vpon <hi>Peter,</hi>
                  </hi>
                  <note place="margin">Origen. in 16. Math. Tract. 1.</note> 
                  <hi>thou thinkeſt the whole Church to be built, what wilt thou ſay to <hi>Iohn,</hi> and euery of the Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtles? ſhall wee dare ſay, that againſt <hi>Peter</hi> onely, the gates of hell ſhall not preuaile? And that alſo vpon this Rocke I will builde my Church: For if this ſpeach, To thee will I giue the Keyes of the kingdome of heauen, be common to all; why then ſhould not all that which goeth before and followeth after, as ſpoken to <hi>Peter,</hi> be common to them all?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>The next place is, <hi>I haue prayed for thee <hi>Peter,</hi> &amp;c.</hi> What then? ſhall wee conclude hereof, that <hi>Peter <hi>and his ſucceſſours cannot fayle in any point of faith, wherein they giue definitiue ſentence;</hi>
                  </hi> and, <hi>that the Pope can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not erre iudicially?</hi> No, but hereby is meant a liuely Chriſtian faith, which is not our pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uate expoſition (as they commonly obiect a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt vs) but the iudgement of <hi>Auſtin,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Aug. de cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rep. &amp; gratia ca. 8. Chryſ. Hom. 83. in Mat. &amp; 72. in Iohn. Proſper de vocatione gent. c. 24. Theoph. in Luk. 22.</note> 
                  <hi>Chry<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoſtome, Proſper,</hi> and <hi>Theophilact;</hi> who all doe vnderſtand by <hi>faith</hi> in that place, <hi>a liuely Chriſtian faith,</hi> and ſay, <hi>That Chriſt prayed, that Peter might continue therein to the end:</hi> which grace, neither they nor any Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther ſayth, that all the Popes haue: Nay, your
<pb n="70" facs="tcp:20283:48"/> Doctors,<note place="margin">Turrec. in ſum, de ec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cle. ca. 12. Can. locor. Theo. li. 6. cap. 1. Bellar. cont. 4 par. 2. q. 1. In annot. Luk. 22. Bed. in Gal. 2 Theophil. in Luc. 23. Chryſoſt. in Mat. Ho. 83.</note> 
                  <hi>Turrecremata, Canus, Bellarmine,</hi> and your <hi>Rhemiſts</hi> confeſſe the contrary: <hi>As I</hi> (ſaith <hi>Bede,</hi> ſpeaking in the perſon of Chriſt) <hi>haue by prayers protected thy faith, leſt by temptation of Satan it ſhould haue failed: ſo thou alſo remember, to lift vp and co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>fort thy weake brethren, by example of thy repen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tance, leſt peraduenture they ſhould deſpaire of pardon.</hi> And our Sauiour Chriſt did by theſe wordes, put him in mind of his fall, to coole the heate of pride and vainglory, if I may ſo ſay with <hi>Theophilact</hi> and <hi>Chryſoſtome.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">Fulk. in Rhem. Teſt. in Luk 22. Sectin.</note>And S. <hi>Baſil</hi> citeth this text, to prooue, <hi>that we ought to pray for them, that are ſought in te<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ptations.</hi> In theſe words you ſée, are taught the duety of <hi>Peter,</hi> &amp; of euery Chriſtian man, in the like caſe; &amp; no prerogatiue either for <hi>Peter,</hi> or his ſucceſſors. And vpon that place, <hi>Feed my ſheepe,</hi> the Fathers build no prerogatiue of <hi>Pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter,</hi> but rather do interpret it of his loue &amp; duty; as S. <hi>Auguſtine,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Aug. 123. in Ioh Tract. Cyril. li. 12. ca. 46. in Ioh. Chryſoſt. in Ioh. Ho. 87.</note> 
                  <hi>Cyril,</hi> and <hi>Chryſoſtome</hi> doe expound y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> place; where, to a thréefold denial, is rendred a thréefold confeſſion, leſt his tongue ſhould be leſſe ſeruiceable to loue, than it was to feare. And there is a reaſon giuen according to the Scripture, why <hi>Peter</hi> ſhould loue more, becauſe he had offended more; for to who<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> more is remitted, he ought to loue more, as <hi>Cyril</hi>
                  <pb n="71" facs="tcp:20283:48"/> ſaith. So that out of the iudgement of theſe Fathers, <hi>Peters</hi> offence to be greater than the reſt, may better be proued, than any preroga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiue to <hi>Peter</hi> or the Pope:<note place="margin">Fulk. in Rhe. Teſt. in Ioh. 21, ſect. 4.</note> ſée their teſtimonies more largely ſet downe by D. <hi>Fulke</hi> againſt the Rhemiſts: yea, this point is ſo cléere, that it is confirmed by the teſtimonie of chiefe and learned Papiſts themſelues.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Alfonſus</hi> ſaith,<note place="margin">Alfonſ. li. 1. ca. 4, cauſ. 24. q.</note> 
                  <hi>Euery man may erre in faith, euen the Pope himſelfe:</hi> and the ſame is confeſſed, by the beſt of your ſide, both Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>noniſts and Diuines.<note place="margin">De Flect. C. Significaſt.</note>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Panormitane</hi> ſaith, <hi>A Councel may con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demne the Pope of Hereſie, as appeareth in in the 40. <hi>diſt. ca. Si Papa.</hi> where it is ſaide, That the Pope may be an Heretike, and iud<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged of Hereſie.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Alfonſus</hi> ſaith, <hi>The Pope may erre in faith:</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Alfonſ. li. 1. cap. 7.</note> 
                  <hi>as the truer opinion is, euen of them that fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uour the Popedome verie much, Amonge whome is <hi>Innocentius,</hi> the 4. of that name, Bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhop of <hi>Rome,</hi>
                  </hi> writing vpon the firſt Chap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter <hi>de trinitate.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Arboreus,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Theoſoph. li. 4, cap. 32.</note> 
                  <hi>a Doctor of <hi>Paris</hi> &amp; one of your chiefe Sorboniſtes</hi> ſaith, <hi>The Pope may erre in faith: And he ſeemeth to me to be in foule Error, that thinketh otherwiſe. Surely they but flatter the Biſhoppe of <hi>Rome,</hi> that make
<pb n="72" facs="tcp:20283:49"/> him free from falling into Hereſie and Schiſme.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Gerſon,</hi> the Chancellor of <hi>Paris</hi> ſaith, <hi>The Pope may ſwarue from the faith,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">
                     <p>Gerſon. in Tract. An liceat in cauſa fidei <hi>à</hi> pontifice appellare. Panor. apud Syl. de fide § 9.</p>
                     <p>Sylueſt. de eccleſi. § 4.</p>
                  </note> 
                  <hi>as well as an other Biſhop.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Panormitan</hi> ſayth, <hi>Thus muſt the Gloze be vnderſtood, which ſayth, that the Church cannot erre, is not the Pope, but the congre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gation of the faithfull; that is ſuch as holde firmely that doctrine, which S. <hi>Peter,</hi> with other people, taught.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>And the Popes owne Gloze vpon his Decrées, doth deſcribe the Church which can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not erre,<note place="margin">Can. 14. q. 1 Can. A recta in gloſſ.</note> 
                  <hi>to be the Congregation of the faith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full;</hi> ſaying, <hi>I aske thee, O Pope <hi>Lucie,</hi> of what Church thou vnderſta<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>deſt that, which thou telleſt vs in this place, to wit, That the Church cannot erre: for if thou vnderſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deſt it of the Pope himſelfe, it is very certaine that the Pope may erre. I anſwere therefore, that the Church is here taken for the congre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gation of the faithfull: and ſuch a Church cannot erre.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">Lyrain Mat. ca. 6.</note>
                  <hi>Lyra</hi> ſayth, <hi>Many Popes haue proued A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſtates.</hi> But what néede I to deſcend to par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticulars, to prooue that the Pope may not on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly erre in doctrine, but alſo be an heretike? ſince it is a ruled caſe by your Schoolemen and
<pb n="73" facs="tcp:20283:49"/> Canoniſtes: As,<note n="a" place="margin">in dial. p. 1. li. 6. ca. 1.</note> 
                  <hi>Occam,</hi>
                  <note n="b" place="margin">In ſumma. lib 5. Tit. de Haeret.</note> 
                  <hi>Hoſtienſis,</hi>
                  <note n="c" place="margin">Summa de eccleſ. li. 2. ca 93. &amp; 112.</note> 
                  <hi>Turrrecremata,</hi>
                  <note n="d" place="margin">De Schiſmat. pont.</note> 
                  <hi>Zabarella,</hi>
                  <note n="e" place="margin">De concord. Catho. li. 2. cap. 17.</note> 
                  <hi>Cu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſanus,</hi>
                  <note n="f" place="margin">Summa part. 3 Tit. 22, cap. 7.</note> 
                  <hi>Antoninus,</hi>
                  <note n="g" place="margin">Aduerſ. Haer. li. 1. ca. 2 &amp; 4.</note> 
                  <hi>Alfonſus,</hi>
                  <note n="h" place="margin">Locor. Theol. lib. 6, cap 8,</note> 
                  <hi>Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nus,</hi>
                  <note n="i" place="margin">De vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſib. Monar. li 7.</note> 
                  <hi>Sanders,</hi>
                  <note n="k" place="margin">Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tro. 4. p 2. qu. 1.</note> 
                  <hi>Bellarmine,</hi>
                  <note n="l" place="margin">Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>noniſt. in diſtinct. 40, ſi Papa Archid. &amp; Iohan. Andrae. in fidei de Haereti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cis in Sext. Caietan de au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thoritat. Pap. &amp; Conc. cap. 20. &amp; 23.</note> and o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers,<note n="m" place="margin">Diſt. 40. ſi Pa,</note> yea, the <hi>Canon lawe</hi> it ſelfe,<note n="n" place="margin">
                     <p>Synod. Roma. quint. ſub Syma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cho.</p>
                     <p>Math. Pariſ. in Henri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>co 3. ſub. Anno 1253.</p>
                     <p>Mathaei Chroni. in An. 1409.</p>
                  </note> yea, <hi>A Councel, a Romane Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cell confirmed by the Pope doe graunt it.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>But to conclude this point, where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in it may ſéeme, I haue béen too tedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous: Sixe hundred prelates, <hi>124.</hi> Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uines, and almoſt thrée hundred Law<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>yers, with the whole Colledge of Cardinals, in your generall Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cell of <hi>Piſa,</hi> depoſed two Popes, <hi>Gre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gory</hi> the <hi>12.</hi> and <hi>Benedict</hi> the <hi>13.</hi>
                  <note n="o" place="margin">Naucler. Chronogr. genera. 47. Anno 1409.</note> as <hi>Schiſmatikes and Heretikes.</hi> Your Councel of <hi>Conſtance,</hi> whereas you ſay were<note n="p" place="margin">Genebrard. li: 2. Chro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nograph. Anno 1414.</note> 
                  <hi>4. Patriarches, 29. Cardi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nals, 47. Archbiſhops, 270. Biſhops, 564. Abbots and Doctors;</hi> in all a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>boue <hi>900.</hi> depoſed the ſame <hi>Benedict</hi> (perſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſting in his Popedome notwithſtanding the former ſentence) as being <hi>Schiſmaticum &amp; Haereticum &amp;c. A Schiſmatike,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Conc. Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtant. Seſſ. 37</note> 
                  <hi>and an He<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>retike ſwaruing from the faith, and a wilfull notorious, &amp; manifeſt ſubuerter of the Arti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cle of our faith, One holy Catholike Church.</hi>
                  <pb n="74" facs="tcp:20283:50"/> Nowe, can there bee any doubt, that theſe Popes were neuer compriſed in that prayer, which Chriſt made for <hi>Peter?</hi> Or that hel gates haue not preuailed againſt them? <hi>When Pope <hi>Marcellinus</hi> did offer ſacrifice to idols,</hi> as ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peares in y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> 
                  <hi>Synueſſan</hi> Councel, <hi>Pope <hi>Liberius</hi> ſubſcribed to the Arrians,</hi> as is teſtified by S. <hi>Hier.</hi> &amp; confeſſed by <hi>Nicholaus Cuſanus,</hi> and <hi>Alfonſ. de Caſtro,</hi> both Papiſts, &amp; great ſchool<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men. Pope <hi>Sylueſter</hi> the <hi>2.</hi> was <hi>a Necroman<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cer &amp; a Co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>iurer, as <hi>Stella, Platina, Petrus Prae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſtrate<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſis, Nauclerus</hi> &amp; <hi>Antonius</hi> do witnes. And Pope <hi>Anaſtatius</hi> was a Neſtoria<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> Here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tike,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Li: 1. de Haer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ca<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> 4</note> as is witneſſed by <hi>Alfonſ. de Caſtro.</hi> And many ſuch inſtances might be prooued out of their owne ſtories. Thus you ſée, in what ſenſe ſoeuer y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Papiſts vnderſtand the Church, it is proued, That it may erre. Wherefore, are you not ſingular men, to abuſe both the ſcriptures, Councels, &amp; Fathers, yea, &amp; your ſilly ſeduced followers, with ſuch co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>cluſions? Are theſe good conſequents at <hi>Rhemes: <hi>Peter</hi>
                  </hi> was ſet ouer the Church, or made Paſtor of the Lords flocke: <hi>Ergo,</hi> none but <hi>Peter?</hi> Euen ſo may you reaſon with much more warrant from the ſcriptures, to proue the ſupremacie to be in <hi>Paul;</hi> For he ſaith,<note place="margin">1, Tim: 1.<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>
                  </note> 
                  <hi>The glorious Goſpel of the bleſſed God which is committed to me. <hi>Ergo,</hi> to none but
<pb n="75" facs="tcp:20283:50"/> 
                     <hi>Paul.</hi>
                  </hi> Yea, he ſaith,<note place="margin">2, Cor: 11, 26</note> 
                  <hi>The care of all Churches were co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mitted to him. <hi>Ergo,</hi> to none but him.</hi> This had béen a pregna<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t place for the Papiſts, if it had béen ſpoken of <hi>Peter;</hi> according to ſuch inferences as they make. And to vrge you a little further: It is your maner in the <hi>Rhemes Teſt.</hi> to ſay often, All the Fathers ſay this and this, and I knowe you bragge much of them, That you can prooue all the doctrine you hold, by them: I pray produce their ioint conſent to prooue, <hi>That all controuerſies are to be deter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mined by the Pope; Or that he cannot erre; Or, that he muſt ſummon Councels; Or that they are of no authority, vnles they be confir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med by the Pope.</hi> All this is <hi>Catholike do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrine</hi> with the Papiſts: and yet I thinke they cannot name any one Father that is ancient (and not counterfeit) to confirme thus much; or to auowe any of theſe points. Is it not ſtrange therefore, that you ſhould reiect the Scripture, which is the onely rule of faith, to build your Religion on ſuch vncertainties, as in this ſmall Tract hath béen declared and ſhewed? This, <hi>Gerſon,</hi> a learned Papiſt ſawe, and therefore hée ſayth,<note place="margin">Gerſ prim<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>l part. de exa. doctrin. con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiderat. 5.</note> 
                  <hi>That there is more credit to be giuen to one man, learned in the Scriptures, and hauing them of his ſide, than either to the Popes ſentence,
<pb n="76" facs="tcp:20283:51"/> or to the decrees of a generall Councel.</hi> This made Cardinal <hi>Caietane</hi> ſay,<note place="margin">In praef. co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                     <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment in libr. Moyſe.</note> 
                  <hi>That God hath not tied the expoſition of the Scriptures vnto the ſenſes of the Fathers: And that if he fall vpon a newe ſenſe agreeable to the Texte, though it goe againſt the ſtreame of the Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers, he doth aduiſe the reader not to miſlike it.</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Andrad. de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fenſi fidei Trid. li. 2.</note> This made <hi>Andradius</hi> the defender of the <hi>Tridentine</hi> Councel, to defend <hi>Caietan</hi> againſt <hi>Canus;</hi> ſaying, <hi>That experience forceth vs to confeſſe (vnleſſe we will bee vnthankfull to moſt excellent wits) that very many things in <hi>Moyſes</hi> and the Prophets, are in this our age, expounded more exactly, (through the diligence of learned men) than euer they were before.</hi> And concludeth, <hi>that the holy Ghoſt, the onely and faithfull interpreter of the Scriptures, would haue many things to be knowen to vs, which our anceſtors knew not. And hath wrought by meanes (vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>knowen to vs, knowen to him) that the Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers noted good and godly myſteries, out of very many places of the Scripture, where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of the right and naturall ſenſe, hath beene found out by the poſteritie.</hi> Thus you ſée, that if wee bee deceiued, <hi>Scriptures, Popes, Councels, Fathers, and learned and chiefe Papiſts</hi> haue deceiued vs, who haue taught
<pb n="77" facs="tcp:20283:51"/> the ſame trueth that wee defend.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Papist.</speaker>
               <p>
                  <hi>Well: What colours ſoeuer you bring, of Scriptures, Fathers, Councels, Popes, and learned men of our owne ſide, yet this is an vndoubted poſition, that vnleſſe you main<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine, that the Church cannot erre; and that thereby you vnderſtand the definitiue ſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tence of the Pope, you bereaue your ſelues of all meanes, to ſettle your ſelues in the vnity of faith: neither haue you any meanes to end controuerſies. For leauing euery man to his owne priuate expoſition, whiles one expoundeth the Scriptures one way, and an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>other another way, This ſenſe is plaine in the expoſition of the one: That ſenſe is con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tradicted by the opinion of the other; there can neuer be end of theſe differences. And therefore there muſt bee ſome Tribunall on earth, where trueth may bee found at all times, and of all men, that be willing to ſeeke for it: Otherwiſe there ſhould bee no ſtay for Religion, nor end of contention; euery man pretending his faith to bee trueth, and no man hauing authoritie to decide which is truth: which were moſt abſurd. And therfore ſince you muſt of neceſſitie yeeld to haue a Iudge for auoiding ſo great inconueniences:
<pb n="78" facs="tcp:20283:52"/> who can bee fitter than the Pope, and the Church?</hi>
               </p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Protestant.</speaker>
               <p>This is <hi>Redire ad vomitum;</hi> and for the auoi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding of a leſſe fault to fall into a greater: Since it is prooued, <hi>in euery ſenſe, where you haue taken the Church, That it may erre.</hi> And therefore how much better were it, that there ſhould be continuall diſagréement, about mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters of Religion, than to maintaine falſe do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrine. Saint <hi>Iude</hi> ſaith, <hi>It was needefull for me to write vnto you,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Iude ver. 3.</note> 
                  <hi>to exhort you, that you ſhould earnestly contend, for the faith which was once giuen vnto the Saints.</hi>
                  <note place="margin">1. Cor. 11.19</note> And Saint <hi>Paul</hi> ſaith, <hi>There muſt bee Sectes amongst you, that they that bee perfect may bee knowen.</hi> For as wee muſt reſpect <hi>Vnitie,</hi> ſo wee muſt take héede, that it bee <hi>Secundum Ieſum Chriſtum,</hi> According to Ieſus Chriſt, <hi>An vnitie in veri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie:</hi> For better a diuerſitie in vnitie, than an vnitie in Poperie. And therefore wee are commaunded,<note place="margin">1, Ioh. 4. 1, Theſſ. 5.</note> 
                  <hi>to trie the ſpirits, whether they be of God. Trie all things, and holde faſt that which is good.</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Epheſ. 5.</note> 
                  <hi>Bee not vnwiſe, but vnderſtand what the will of the Lord is. Bee renewed in your minde,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Rom. 12.</note> 
                  <hi>that you may diſcerne what the good and acceptable and perfect will of GOD is.</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Phi. 1.9.</note> 
                  <hi>This I pray, that your loue may abound
<pb n="79" facs="tcp:20283:52"/> yet more and more in knowledge and in all iudge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, that you may diſcerne the things that are beſt.</hi>
                  <note place="margin">1. Cor. 2.</note> 
                  <hi>Hee that is Spirituall diſcerneth all things.</hi> Theſe exhortations were not giuen by the Spirit of God in vaine; which of ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſitie muſt follow, if you debarre all Chriſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans (other than <hi>Clergie men</hi>) to be diſcerners of trueth. And it is euident by the Scriptures, that there is a limitation, howe farre the Biſhops and Cleargie, are to be obeyed, and what they are to teach. For S. <hi>Paul</hi> ſaith, <hi>Be yee followers of me, as I am of Chriſt.</hi>
                  <note place="margin">1, Cor. 7.</note> So that he requireth no more of the Corinthians, than to follow him as hee followeth Chriſt. And this made him ſo diligently to diſtinguiſh the precepts of Chriſt, from his owne Councels, <hi>To the married I commaund, not I, but the Lord: &amp; to the reſt I ſpeake &amp; not the Lord.</hi> And our Sauiour Chriſt, when he gaue com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſſion to his Apoſtles, He bids them,<note place="margin">Mat. 28.19, 20.</note> 
                  <hi>Goe teach all nations:</hi> but what? <hi>To obſerue all things whatſoeuer I haue commanded you.</hi> And there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore <hi>Chryſoſtome</hi> alleaging the wordes of Saint <hi>Paul;</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Chryſ. in 1. ca. 2, Epiſt. ad Tim. Hom. 2.</note> 
                  <hi>Obey your Ouerſeers or Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lates;</hi> doeth thus limite them: <hi>But if hee peruert anie poynt of faith, though hee be an Angell, obey him not.</hi> And ſtraight after, <hi>Wee muſt not obey <hi>Paul</hi> himſelfe,
<pb n="80" facs="tcp:20283:53"/> if he ſpeake any thing of his owne, or as a man; but we muſt obey) the Apoſtle bearing Chriſt about, that ſpeaketh in him. It is not lawfull</hi> (ſaith <hi>Tertullian) <hi>to deuiſe any thing of our ſelues,</hi>
                  </hi>
                  <note place="margin">Tertul. de praeſcrip. ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſ. Haeret.</note> 
                  <hi>nor to follow that which others haue deuiſed: wee haue the Apoſtles of the Lord for our Authors, who deuiſed nothing of their owne heads, but deliuered faithfully to the nations the doctrine which they recei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued of Chriſt. Therefore, though an Angel from heauen ſhould preach otherwiſe, wee ſhould count him accurſed.</hi>
                  <note n="*" place="margin">Chryſoſt. operis im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per. Ho. 20. in 7. ca. Mat.</note> 
                  <hi>Euery teacher is a ſeruant of the Law, becauſe hee may nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther adde of his owne ſenſe vnto the Lawe, nor according to his owne conceit take any thing from the Law, but preach that onely which is found in the Law.</hi> And theſe inſtru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctions both of Fathers and Scriptures, were to little purpoſe, if wee were not by them taught, how to eſchew the euill and followe the good. And ſurely if the <hi>Vicars Conſiſto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie</hi> and <hi>Seate,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">In Luc. 12.</note> were <hi>infallible,</hi> as the Rhemiſts affirme; what néede wee reſpect or ſtudie to knowe, the infinite Teſtimonies of Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures and Fathers, brought to this purpoſe? But this doeth not prooue that they are pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uiledged and exempted from <hi>Erring.</hi> For the Scriptures which were written for our in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtruction,
<pb n="81" facs="tcp:20283:53"/> doe plainely conuince, that both Prieſts and Prophets haue erred: For God by the Prophet <hi>Malachie</hi> deſcribeth what the Prieſts ſhould doe, and what they had done. <hi>The Prieſts lippes ſhould preſerue knowledge,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Mala. 2.</note> 
                  <hi>and they ſhould ſeeke the Law at his mouth, for he is the meſſenger of the Lord of hostes. But yee are gone out of the way (O ye Priests) ye haue cauſed many to fall by the Law, ye haue broken the coue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nant of <hi>Leui,</hi> ſaith the Lord of hostes.</hi> And this proud priuiledge, which the Popes now chal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lenge, was claimed by the wicked Prieſts in <hi>Ieremies</hi> time. <hi>Come,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Iere. 18, 1<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>.</note> (ſay they) <hi>let vs imagine ſome deuiſe againſt <hi>Ieremie:</hi> for the Law ſhal not periſh from the Prieſt; nor counſell from the wiſe, nor the word from the Prophet.</hi> But God aſſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reth them by his Prophet,<note place="margin">Ezech. 7.2<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>
                  </note> for their arrogant preſumption; <hi>That the Law ſhould periſh from the Prieſt, and counſell from the ancient.</hi> What groſſe idolatrie <hi>Vriah</hi> the Prieſt committed, to pleaſe King <hi>Ahaz,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">2, King. 16.10.11. Eſay <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>8.</note> the Scriptures will tell you And <hi>Eſay</hi> ſaith, <hi>The Priest and the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phet haue erred, they haue gone away, they faile in viſion, they ſtumble in iudgement.</hi> And wee knowe there haue béen many Biſhops, and thoſe orderly ſuccéeding, if you looke to their <hi>dignity,</hi> not to the <hi>doctrine,</hi> who haue béen <hi>he<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>retickes,</hi> as <hi>Berillus, Paulus, Samoſatinus,
<pb n="82" facs="tcp:20283:54"/> Photinus, Neſtorius, Dioſcorus, Petrus Apa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>meus, Sergius, Cyrus, Theodorus, Macarius,</hi> And many <hi>others,</hi> Canonically <hi>ſucceeding</hi> in <hi>Seates</hi> and <hi>Churches</hi> of no ſmall account. And if theſe fell into peſtilent hereſies; that which was often and eaſie then, is contingent and poſſible ſtill: And ſucceſſion which ſaued not them fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> erring, cannot defend our Popes from the like danger. And therefore are wee forewarned, and taught by the Scriptures, to beware and take héede of ſuch men: For S. <hi>Paul</hi> ſaith,<note place="margin">Act<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> 20.</note> 
                  <hi>Out of your ſelues ſhall ariſe men, ſpeaking peruerſe things, to drawe diſciples af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter them.</hi> And the Lord when hee ſaith, <hi>Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ware of falſe Prophets,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Mat. 7.</note> noteth, that there ſhall be Prophets by their calling, which ſhall be found falſe in their teaching: As Saint <hi>Peter</hi> alſo witneſſeth;<note place="margin">2, Pet. 2.</note> 
                  <hi>There were falſe Prophets a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mong the people</hi> (of the Iewes) <hi>euen as there ſhall bee falſe teachers amongst you.</hi> And to what purpoſe are theſe, with many other te<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtimonies? but to teach vs that we muſt diſtin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guiſh godly teachers, <hi>not by office,</hi> but by do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrine. And if there were not an abilitie in vs, in ſome ſort to diſcerne them, in vaine were we taught to beware of them: neither had the men of <hi>Berea</hi> béen ſo highly commended for the tri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>all of their Paſtors doctrine,<note place="margin">Acts 17.11</note> if it had either béen
<pb n="83" facs="tcp:20283:54"/> vnlawfull, or not their duety ſo to haue done. But it ſéemes the Papiſts inſiſt much vpon the outward quiet of their Church, holding out this <hi>Buggebeare, That the Church cannot erre:</hi> aſſuming therby to be lords of ſcriptures, Fathers, Councels, and all when they liſt: But what hereticall Church, may not haue the ſame quietneſſe vpon the ſame perſwaſion? and yet it preuailes in none, but thoſe that can be perſwaded; That this falſe priuiledge of not erring, belongs to the Church, taking the Church in the ſame ſenſe which the Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piſts in this Tract vnderſtand it; of Fathers Councels, and the Pope. And who knowes not, that notwithſtanding your late Councel of <hi>Trent,</hi> and diuers other Councels, and lear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned bookes of all ſides; That yet the contro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerſies are not ended, being indéede the <hi>ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer ending knotte of Religion:</hi> For though this perſwaſion, <hi>That the Church cannot erre,</hi> may ſometimes bréede an outwarde quietneſſe in the Church; yet it hath no force to eſtabliſh men in the vnitie of <hi>Trueth,</hi> ſince it may both deceiue, and bée deceiued, as is in this Treatiſe prooued: Nor to end con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trouerſies, becauſe all beléeue it not: nor to aboliſh hereſies, which many times it may fauour, as is euident by ſome fewe examples,
<pb n="84" facs="tcp:20283:55"/> both of Popes and Councels before alleaged. For further example, put the caſe; That ſome of the Church are perſwaded, according to Chriſts Inſtitution, and the practiſe of the Church of <hi>Corinth,</hi> that the Laitie are not to be robbed of the Cup, but are to receiue the <hi>Euchariſt</hi> in both kinds: and hereby call the priuiledge of the Churches not erring into Queſtion, how ſhall this be decided? Shall it be ſufficient for the Church or Pope to ſay I cannot erre? and for proofe thereof, to call all his Cardinals, Abbots and Biſhops to a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uow the ſame, though it be contrary both to Scriptures, Fathers, and the long continued practice of the Church of Chriſt: hauing ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer béene prohibited as vnlawfull, vntill the Councell of <hi>Conſtance,</hi> which was <hi>1400.</hi> yéeres after Chriſt. But Controuerſies may be ended, and hereſies aboliſhed, either by con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uincing thoſe out of the Scriptures, that main<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine them; as diuers heretikes were, before either Pope or Councell were thought of: Or by the authoritie of the Magiſtrate, comman<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding for trueth, and inioining their ſilence and obedience;<note place="margin">
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> Chro. 14.<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>, 3, 4, 5.</note> according to the examples of <hi>Aſa</hi> the King of <hi>Iudah;</hi> who commanded his peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple to doe according to the Law,<note place="margin">
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> Chro. 29.</note> &amp;c. And <hi>Eze<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chiah</hi> who reſtored the worſhip of God, and
<pb n="85" facs="tcp:20283:55"/> diuers other Kings in the old Teſtament,<note place="margin">2. Chro. 17<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> ver, 3, 4, 5, 8. &amp; ca. 19 ver. 4, 8, 9<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> 10, 11 &amp;c 33. v. 11, 12 13, 15. &amp; c<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> 34. v. 3, 4, 7, 29.30, 3<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> 32, 33. &amp; c<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> 35. v. 1, 2, 3 4.5, 6.</note> as <hi>Iehoſhaphat, Manaſſes, Ioſiah,</hi> and others, yea, <hi>Salomon</hi> did dedicate the Temple in his owne perſon and<note n="*" place="margin">1. King. 8. &amp; ca. 2. v. 3</note> caſt out <hi>Abiathar</hi> from be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing Prieſt vnto the Lord, and placed <hi>Zadok,</hi> in his roume. And Saint <hi>Auſtine</hi> in many places ſheweth, Kings are charged with Gods Law, in reſpect of commanding it to others. In the times of the Prophets (ſaith he) <hi>All the Kings, which in the people of God, did not forbid and ouerthrowe thoſe things,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Aug. Epi. 5</note> 
                  <hi>which were brought in againſt the comman<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dements of God, are blamed: and they that did prohibit, and ſubuert ſuch things, are praiſed aboue the reſt.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>And for that part of the obiection, that wee leaue euery man to his priuate expoſition, (which though therein wee are wrongfully charged by our aduerſaries) yet the trueth is; we challenge not to our ſelues (as the Papiſts do) the true interpretation of the Scriptures, as if they were appropriated vnto vs: But we ſubmit our ſelues, and our interpretations whatſoeuer (according to the Generall and receiued doctrine of the Fathers in that point) to be compared and tried by the Scriptures: Or (to auoide your cauelling) if you will, to the Church, which are men ſpeaking by the
<pb n="86" facs="tcp:20283:56"/> Scriptures. Neither is this part of the obie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction of ſo great weight or conſequence, as it may ſéeme at the firſt bluſh. For moſt of the differences betwéene vs and the Papiſts, are not touching the ſenſe of the Scripture; ſéeing it is confeſſed by learned Papiſts (as I haue prooued in the preface of this booke) that moſt of the doctrines wherein they vary from vs, are grounded on <hi>Tradition.</hi> And all men of reaſon know, that where ther is no Text, there néedes no Interpreter. All the danger there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore, lieth in the laſt part of the obiection; when mens corrupt affections, may take thoſe things for trueth which are not; and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iect thoſe which are: a thing impoſſible to bee preuented, ſince euery man vnderſtands ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to the capacitie and conceite whereof himſelfe is. And herein likewiſe is the do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrine of Chriſt verefied, as Saint <hi>Paul</hi> ſayth,<note place="margin">2. Cor. 4.3</note> 
                  <hi>If our Goſpell bee hidde, it is hidde to them that are lost: For no man can come vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to mee</hi> (ſayth Chriſt) <hi>except the Father which haue ſent me drawe him.</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Iohn 6.44.</note> 
                  <note place="margin">1. Cor. 3.4, 6</note> Yea, <hi>Paul <hi>may plant, and</hi> Apollo <hi>may water, but God must giue the increaſe.</hi>
                  </hi> For though the Sunne bée of moſt excellent brightneſſe, yet none can ſée it, but thoſe which haue eyes: euen ſo is it of the Scriptures, which as Saint <hi>Peter</hi> ſayth,
<pb n="87" facs="tcp:20283:56"/> 
                  <hi>They that are vnlearned and vnſtable,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">2. Pet. 3.16.</note> 
                  <hi>doe per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uert to their own damnation.</hi> But ſhal we leaue the <hi>Triall of the Scriptures (to which all the Fathers referre vs)</hi> either becauſe many per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uert them; or, for that the diuel alleaged them; or, for that it is common to all Heretikes to make challenge and boaſt of them? No: for all Heretikes haue béen (by the Scriptures rightly vnderſtood) confuted and confounded: yea, euen the deuill himſelfe,<note place="margin">Mat. 3.7.</note> as Chriſts owne example teacheth vs, was conuicted by the ſame weapon, wherewith hee thought to haue vanquiſhed our Sauiour. But to make this plaine by example, what Lawyer will of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fer to defend a badde cauſe, but hee will bring Lawe for his purpoſe: and ſhall this debarre or preiudice the other that pleades againſt him, That hée ſhall not by Lawe conuince the <hi>Errours,</hi> and <hi>Sophiſtries,</hi> or <hi>Quirkes</hi> and <hi>Quiddities</hi> which are brought againſt him? Nay, rather anie man of iudgement, (hauing heard both parties) will readily diſtinguiſh, and ſay; <hi>The one makes a a ſhewe of Lawe, but the other hath Lawe indeede.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>And euen thus it reſts in thoſe controuer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſies, that are betweene vs and the Papiſts, touching the <hi>Senſe of the Scripture onely:</hi>
                  <pb n="88" facs="tcp:20283:57"/> and not for thoſe differences which the main<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine by <hi>Tradition:</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Petr. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> Soto. adu. Brent. Caniſi. in ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>techi. ca. 5. Lindan in pan. li. 4. ca. 100. Pereſius par. 3. Rhe. Teſt. Gal. 2. ſect. 4</note> which by the iudgement of their owne men, as I haue already ſhewed, are the greater number. And albeit the <hi>Rhe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſts</hi> would inſinuate, <hi>That the controuerſies betweene vs are, whether the Iudge, or the Euidence bee of greater authority,</hi> yet that ſhift will not ſerue them: for all men of iudge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment knowe, that that is not the queſtion be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>twéene vs. But the difference is, whether the Iudge, or the Law bee of greater authoritie: where euery wiſe man will graunt, the Lawe to be ſupreame; whereunto the Iudge is to obey, and according to which to giue his ſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tence: or elſe by the Lawe, his erronious iudgement is to be reuerſed. Neither is there other <hi>Iudiciall authority in the Church,</hi> than in the common wealth: which is to determine controuerſies according to the Lawe, and the true meaning thereof. And if there be queſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of the <hi>Senſe of the Law, The Lawmakers</hi> minde is to be diſcuſſed by his wordes, and the circumſtances and occaſions of making the Lawe. And euen ſo the meaning of the <hi>Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture</hi> is to be taken onely out of the <hi>Scripture,</hi> as <hi>Clemens</hi> ſaith,<note place="margin">
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>. 37. ca. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>elatum.</note> 
                  <hi>You ought not to ſeeke a ſtrange and forraine ſenſe without the Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures, that you may confirme it by any means
<pb n="89" facs="tcp:20283:57"/> by the Scriptures: But ſenſe of trueth you muſt take out of the Scriptures themſelues.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Saint <hi>Auguſtine,</hi>
                  <note n="*" place="margin">Confeſſ. Aug. praef. ad lecto.</note> whoſe doctrine your ſelues doe acknowledge, <hi>to be grounded on the lawes, the maners, the iudgements of all the Catholike Church;</hi> whom you call, <hi>a wit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe of the ſincere trueth and Catholike Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion, ſuch a witneſſe as no exception can be made againſt:</hi> who aſſureth you as you ſay, <hi>not onely of his owne, but alſo of the com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon, the conſtant faith and confeſſion of the ancient Fathers and the Apoſtolike Church:</hi> This <hi>Auguſtine</hi> hath written foure bookes of <hi>Chriſtian doctrine,</hi> wherein he purpoſely in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>treateth howe men ſhould vnderſtand the <hi>Scripture,</hi> and expound it. The ſumme of all his Treatiſe doeth aime at this marke, That<note n="a" place="margin">Aug. de doct. Chriſt. li. 1. ca. 2.</note> 
                  <hi>the meaning of the Scripture muſt bee learned out of the Scripture by the conſide<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration of things and wordes in it: That</hi>
                  <note n="b" place="margin">Ca. 35.</note> 
                  <hi>the ende whereto,</hi>
                  <note n="c" place="margin">Ca. 37.</note> 
                  <hi>the matter whereof it is all written, bee marked in generall:</hi>
                  <note n="d" place="margin">Ca. 35. &amp; 40.</note> 
                  <hi>and all be vnderſtood according to that end and matter:</hi>
                  <note n="e" place="margin">Li. 2. ca. 8</note> 
                  <hi>that all bee read ouer and ouer:</hi>
                  <note n="f" place="margin">Ca. 9.</note> 
                  <hi>and thoſe things chiefly noted, which are ſet downe plainely, both precepts of life and rules of beleefe, becauſe that all things which concerne beliefe and life, are plainely written
<pb n="90" facs="tcp:20283:58"/> in it: That obſcure and darke ſpeaches be lightened and opened by the plaine and ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nifeſt: that to remoue the doubt of vncertaine ſentences, the cleare &amp; certain be followed: that</hi>
                  <note n="g" place="margin">Ca. 11.</note> 
                  <hi>recourſe be had vnto the Greeke and Hebrew copies, to cleare out of the fountains if the tranſlation be muddy: that</hi>
                  <note n="h" place="margin">Li. 3. ca. 2 &amp; 3.</note> 
                  <hi>doubtfull places bee expounded by the rule of faith which we are taught out of the plainer places of the Scripture: that</hi>
                  <note n="i" place="margin">Ca. 1.</note> 
                  <hi>all the circu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſtances of the text be weighed, what goeth before, what co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>meth after, the maner how,</hi>
                  <note n="k" place="margin">Ca. 10.</note> 
                  <hi>the cauſe why,</hi>
                  <note n="l" place="margin">Ca. 17.</note> 
                  <hi>the men to whom,</hi>
                  <note n="m" place="margin">Ca. 18.</note> 
                  <hi>the time when euery thing is ſaid: to be ſhort, that</hi>
                  <note n="n" place="margin">Ca. 27.</note> 
                  <hi>we ſeeke to know ſtil the will &amp; meaning of the Author, by who<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the holy Ghoſt hath ſpoke<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>: if we find it not, yet giue ſuch a ſenſe, as agreeth with the right faith, approued by ſome othe place of ſcripture:</hi>
                  <note n="o" place="margin">C. 18.</note> 
                  <hi>If a ſenſe be giue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, the vncertain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty wherof cannot be diſcuſſed, by certain &amp; ſure teſtimonies of ſcripture; it might be pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued by reaſon, but this cuſtom is dangerous; the ſafer way far is to walke by the ſcripture, the which (being ſhadowed with darke and borrowed words) when we mind to ſearch, let either that come out of it, which hath no doubt &amp; co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>trouerſie; or if it haue doubt, let it be determined by the ſame ſcripture, through witneſſes to be fou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d &amp; vſed thence wherſoe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer:
<pb n="91" facs="tcp:20283:58"/> that ſo (to conclude)</hi>
                  <note n="p" place="margin">Li. 4. ca. 3</note> 
                  <hi>all places of the ſcriptures, be expounded by the Scriptures, the which are canonical, as being the Canon, that is to ſay, the rule of godlines &amp; faith.</hi> All which rules we confidently imbrace. And we conſtantly affirme, that neither he, nor any o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther auncient Father, did euer attribute the expounding of the Scripture (for the true ſenſe therof) to any Pope or biſhop whatſoeuer. And although D. <hi>Stapl.</hi> except againſt theſe <hi>Rules</hi> of S. <hi>Auſtin,</hi> (which is common to all <hi>Papiſts by ſpecial priuiledge,</hi> when the <hi>Fathers</hi> make againſt them) as I haue already partly pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued; and ſhal appeare to any y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> for a clearer ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nifeſtatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> therof, wil take a view of their <hi>Index expurgator.</hi>) yet doth S. <hi>Auſtin</hi> iuſtifie himſelf,<note place="margin">De doctr. Chriſtia. li: 1 a Prolo.</note> ſaying, <hi>If they who know theſe precepts, can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not ſee the things which are obſcure &amp; darke in the ſcriptures of God, the fault is in them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelues not in the precepts: as if I ſhould point with my finger at a ſtarre, which they would gladly ſee; and their eye-ſight were ſo weake, that although they could ſee my finger, yet could they not ſee the ſtarre, at which I point: Let them</hi> (ſaith he) <hi>ceaſe to blame mee, and let them pray to God that hee will giue them eye-ſight.</hi> And to the ende I may giue ſome proofe of euery thing I affirme, and to giue a taſte of the <hi>vile practiſe</hi> of the <hi>Papiſts:</hi>
                  <pb n="92" facs="tcp:20283:59"/> It ſhall not be amiſſe to ſet downe their owne words, namely the iudgement of the <hi>Vniuer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſitie of <hi>Doway,</hi> approued by the Cenſors of the Councel of <hi>Trent,</hi> concerning the booke of <hi>Bertram,</hi>
                  </hi> according to the <hi>Decree of the Councel; the Title, <hi>Vt liber Bertram, &amp;c.</hi> How the booke of <hi>Bertram,</hi>
                  </hi>
                  <note place="margin">Index ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>purg. 8. pag. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>1.</note> 
                  <hi>Prieſt, of the Bodie and Blood of our Lord, being amended, may be<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> tolerated.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Although wee make no great account of this booke, &amp; therfore we would not greatly care, if either it were no where extant, or vt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terly loſt: yet ſeeing it hath been already of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>te<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>times reprinted, &amp; hath been read of moſt men, and being prohibited by name, hath been made knowen to all men: ſeeing alſo the heretikes do know of the prohibition thereof, by diuers Catalogues: and that he was a Catholike Prieſt, and a Monke of the Abbey of <hi>Corbey,</hi> and was welbeloued and reuerenced not ſo much of <hi>Carolus Magnus</hi> as of <hi>Carolus Caluus,</hi> and doth helpe the ſtory of that age: And ſeeing that in other ancient Catholike writers, wee beare very many er<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rors, and extenuate them, excuſe them, and very often times by deuiſing ſome pretie ſhift we denie them,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Excogitato Commento.</note> 
                  <hi>and do faine ſome com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>modious ſenſe vnto them, when they are op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſed
<pb n="93" facs="tcp:20283:59"/> aginſt vs in diſputation or in conflicts with the aduerſaries: wee do not ſee, why <hi>Bertram</hi> doeth not deſerue the ſame equity and diligent Recognition; leſt the Heretikes ſhould Iangle againſt vs, that wee burne vp and prohibite Antiquitie which maketh for them: and therfore it is no maruel that ſo few things ſeeme to make for them, when wee Catholikes do ſo vnreuerently hiſſe out, and deſtroy antiquitie, which but in ſhewe diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſenteth from vs. Moreouer we feare leaſt this booke, not onely by Heretikes, but alſo by vnruly Catholikes (by meanes of the prohi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bition thereof) may be read more greedily, alleaged more odiouſly, and doe more hurt being inhibited, than if it were permitted.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>And vpon theſe conſiderations they take or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der, and ſhew how this booke at the next prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting, ſhall be falſified by adding, putting out, changing of the <hi>Wordes</hi> and <hi>Sentences,</hi> and by peruerting the whole ſcope and meaning of the Author.</p>
               <p>The laſt part of the obiection is, that there muſt bee ſome <hi>Tribunall</hi> on earth, to iudge which is trueth: And in this Queſtion, they réele ſometime to the <hi>Church,</hi> and ſometime to the <hi>Pope,</hi> who they will haue to bee <hi>Iudge</hi> of trueth; and that the Church, which ſometime
<pb n="94" facs="tcp:20283:60"/> they intitle to the <hi>Pope,</hi> and ſometime to <hi>Ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nerall Councels,</hi> are to be iudge of the <hi>Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures.</hi> To this I anſwere, That abſolute <hi>Iudge of trueth</hi> can no man be; for <hi>God is truth,</hi> &amp; of God I truſt no man may be Iudge. The Sonne of God ſaith of himſelfe,<note place="margin">Iohn 14. 1. Iohn 5.</note> 
                  <hi>I am truth;</hi> and S. <hi>Iohn</hi> teſtifieth, <hi>The ſpirit is truth.</hi> Therefore ye can be no <hi>Iudges of trueth,</hi> vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>les you will be Iudges of God. And, <hi>the Father hath committed all iudgement to the Sonne;</hi> and, my iudgment,<note place="margin">Iohn 5. &amp; 8.</note> ſaith Chriſt, <hi>is Iuſt.</hi> Chriſt ſaith, <hi>My ſheep, heare my voice,</hi> They be no iudges of his voice, which is the Scriptures. A Iudge of the Law, is no obſeruer of the Law, as S. <hi>Iames</hi> inſinuateth: &amp; ſince the whole <hi>Church</hi> is bound to obey the Law of God,<note place="margin">Iam. ca. 4.</note> they be no iud<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges of the law. S. <hi>Auſtin</hi> ſaith, <hi>It is inferiour to vs,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Aug. in Pſa. Idem de ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ra religio. ca. 31.</note> 
                  <hi>whatſoeuer we be Iudges of.</hi> And again, <hi>The eternall Law of God, therefore, it is law<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful for cleane hearts to know; it is not lawfull for them to iudge.</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Idem co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>feſ li. 13. ca. 23.</note> And againe, <hi>Wee muſt not iudge of ſo high authoritie, neither of the booke which is thine, becauſe we ſubmit our vnderſtanding to it.</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Contr Creſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>con. li. 2, c. 31</note> And laſtly, <hi>To the Canons of the ſcripture pertaine certaine books of the Prophets and Apoſtles, the which in any caſe we may not dare to iudge.</hi> And this is y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> reaſon, There may be no iudge of <hi>Trueth,</hi> where no
<pb n="95" facs="tcp:20283:60"/> da<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ger of <hi>Error</hi> is. And <hi>S. Auſtin</hi> ſaith,<note place="margin">Idem epiſt. 19. ad Hier.</note> 
                  <hi>It is wic<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kednes to make a doubt</hi> (ſpeaking of the <hi>ſcrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures) whether there be any error in the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> or not.</hi> Therfore there may be no iudges of them, but y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> whole <hi>Church muſt be ſubiect to the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, &amp; with all humility beleeue them.</hi> And yet will y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piſts aſſume vnto themſelues, to be <hi>Iudges</hi> of the <hi>ſcriptures;</hi> &amp; appoint which ſhall be <hi>Cano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nical,</hi> &amp; which ſhalbe <hi>Apocrypha?</hi> A Iudge we grant muſt haue two things, before he be com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>petent, namely, ſkill to diſcerne, y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> he miſſe not the truth; &amp; power to command, that his iudge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment may take place. Now if he want either of theſe, he is no fit Iudge. And that y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Pope hath neither of theſe, thus I proue. For the firſt I haue proued he may erre, &amp; therfore no man is bound to his iudgment further tha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> it is agrée<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able to the truth. And to adde one proofe more, the Councel of <hi>Baſil</hi> ſaith, <hi>This priuiledge,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Conc. Baſil. epiſt. Syno. 8</note> 
                  <hi>not to erre, hath not been granted by a common, or perpetual law to any: not to the Angels, for many of them fell: not to our firſt parents, for they were deceiued: not vnto the chiefe Bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhops, for many of them are read to haue fallen into error and Hereſie.</hi> And as it is abſurd to referre the iudgement to one man: ſo is it alſo to intitle the church of <hi>Rome</hi> to be <hi>The Catho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>like Church;</hi> ſince their chiefe Schoolemen
<pb n="96" facs="tcp:20283:61"/> and lights of the <hi>Papiſts,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Petr. a Soto. contr. co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>feſſ. Wittenburg. ca. de Co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>cil. Alfo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſ. <hi>à</hi> Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtro aduer. Haer. li. 1. c. 8. Co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>f. Petric. cap. 24. &amp; contr. Bre<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t. li. 2. Diſput. adu. Luther. tom. 6. deauthori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tat. &amp; poteſt. vniuerſ. ec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cleſ. ca. 5. Ibid. ca. 1.</note> 
                  <hi>Sotus, Alfonſus, Hoſius</hi> and <hi>Verratus,</hi> doe witneſſe, <hi>that any particular Church may erre. But that the Church of <hi>Rome</hi> is a particular Church the ſame <hi>Verratus</hi> affirmeth, nor can the reſt de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>me it.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>And as he may erre, ſo hath he no power to command princes or others; but onely to pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe the commandements of God vnto them, as <hi>euery Biſhop muſt and may by vertue of his vocation.</hi> Further authority by violence to compell, or by corporall and external means to puniſh, no Prelate nor Pope hath by the Lawe of GOD: ſince that belongeth to the <hi>Sworde,</hi> which the <hi>Prince,</hi> and not the <hi>Pope</hi> beareth,<note place="margin">Rom. 13. 1. Pet. 2.</note> as Saint <hi>Paul</hi> witneſſeth, and alſo <hi>Peter:</hi> from whoſe right the Pope makes claime to this ſuperioritie. But me thinkes I ſtill heare them obiect, that all this while wee appoint not who ſhall bee <hi>Iudges,</hi> or at leaſt, <hi>Diſcerners of Truth:</hi> And to that we anſwer, Let him that maketh the claime vndertake the proofe; for we find no place nor perſon to whom the Sonne of God hath referred vs, for the right vnderſtanding of his will, but onely to himſelfe and the Scriptures. And that you may knowe this is not our <hi>priuate opinion,</hi> (a ſlander which you often obiect) learne what
<pb n="97" facs="tcp:20283:61"/> 
                  <hi>Optatus</hi> &amp; S. <hi>Aug.</hi> hath ſet downe in this caſe. <hi>Chriſt</hi> (ſaith <hi>Optat.) hath dealt with vs as an earthly father is wont with his children,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Lib. 5. coni. Permenia. Donat.</note> 
                  <hi>who fearing leſt they ſhould fall out after his de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceaſe, doth ſet down his Will in writing vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der witneſſes; &amp; if there ariſe debate among the brethren; they goe to the teſtament. Hee, whoſe worde muſt end our controuerſie is Chriſt: let his Will be ſought in his Teſtame<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t.</hi> Which reaſon of <hi>Optatus,</hi> S. <hi>Aug.</hi> vrging a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt the Donatiſts, as he doth often; <hi>We are brethren</hi> (ſaith he to them) <hi>why doe we ſtriue?</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Aug. in Pſal. 21. expoſi. 2</note> 
                  <hi>Our Father died not inteſtate: he made a Te<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtament, and ſo died. Men doe ſtriue about the goods of the dead, till the Teſtament be brought foorth: when that is brought, they yeeld to haue it opened and read: The Iudge doeth hearken, the Councellors be ſilent; the Crier bids peace; all the people is attentiue, that the words of the dead may be read and heard. He lieth void of life and feeling in his graue, and his words preuaile: Chriſt doth ſit in heauen; &amp; is his Teſtament gaineſayd? O<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pen it; let vs reade, we are brethren: why doe we ſtriue? let our mindes bee pacified: Our Father hath not left vs without a Teſtament. He that made the Teſtament is liuing for e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer. He doth heare our words, he doth know his owne word. Let vs reade: why doe wee
<pb n="98" facs="tcp:20283:62"/> ſtriue?</hi> Were not this a <hi>ſilly</hi> ſpeach of S. <hi>Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtin,</hi> if <hi>Traditions</hi> were to be receiued with e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quall <hi>Reuerence</hi> to the <hi>Scriptures?</hi> or that <hi>Councels</hi> or <hi>Popes</hi> had ſuch abſolute authori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie? But it ſéemes, S. <hi>Auſtin</hi> aſcribed more to this <hi>Teſtament,</hi> than to any <hi>Pope</hi> or <hi>Councel</hi> whatſoeuer. And to conclude this point: <hi>Op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tatus</hi> in the Queſtion of the <hi>Catholikes</hi> with the <hi>Donatiſts,</hi> whether one ſhould be twice baptiſed:<note place="margin">Li. 5. contr. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ermen. Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>at.</note> 
                  <hi>You</hi> (ſaith he) <hi>ſay it is lawfull: Wee ſay it it not lawfull. Betweene your (it is law<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full) and our (it is not lawfull) the peoples ſoules doe doubt and wauer. Let none be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leeue you nor vs, we are all contentious men. Iudges muſt be ſought for: if Chriſtians, they cannot be giuen of both ſides, for trueth is hindered by affections. A Iudge without muſt be ſought for. If a Panime: he cannot know the Chriſtian myſteries. If a Iew: he is an enemie to Chriſtia<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> baptiſme. No Iudge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment therefore of this matter can be found in earth: a Iudge in Heauen muſt bee ſought for. But why knocke wee at heauen, when here we haue the Teſtament of Chriſt in the Goſpel.</hi> Belike <hi>Optatus</hi> and S. <hi>Auſtin</hi> were not ſo wiſe in thoſe dayes, as our <hi>Ieſuites</hi> and <hi>Papiſts</hi> are now: for they could eaſily haue put doubts and <hi>ſcruples,</hi> touching the <hi>ſenſe</hi> of the
<pb n="99" facs="tcp:20283:62"/> 
                  <hi>Scriptures,</hi> and could <hi>skilfully</hi> haue inforced ſuch obiections as theſe, and in all doubts could eaſily haue aſſigned their Pope as an <hi>Abſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lute Iudge.</hi> But it is euident by the iudge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of theſe two Reuerend Fathers, that we can haue <hi>no fit Iudge on earth:</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Ioh. 12.</note> 
                  <hi>God muſt therefore iudge vs by his word;</hi> To which all the Fathers doe ſubmit themſelues and their writings, as is before prooued and alleaged. Yea, we are warranted by the <hi>Prophet Oſea, to iudge our Mother</hi> (as it is in the vulgar Tranſlation) <hi>and to contend with her that ſhe is not the ſpouſe of Chriſt:</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Hoſ. 2.</note> 
                  <hi>nor he her huſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>band: that ſhe may take away her fornicati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons and adulteries &amp;c.</hi> as it is more at large in the Text. Thus haue you ſéene briefly, <hi>A view of the weakneſſe of the Grounds</hi> wher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on the <hi>Papiſts</hi> build their <hi>Religion:</hi> which in a word is, <hi>The Popes good pleaſure.</hi> And notwithſtanding I haue in this ſmall <hi>Tract</hi> layd downe our iuſt <hi>Exceptions,</hi> both againſt <hi>Fathers</hi> and <hi>Councels:</hi> yet would I haue none raſhly to cenſure, that we reiect al the Fathers and Councels: for we imbrace them, as whole<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſome meanes, by which great light hath béene brought to the <hi>Church of God,</hi> both in the Expoſition of the Scriptures, and the aboliſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing and confuting of Hereſies. But wee re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iect
<pb n="100" facs="tcp:20283:63"/> with great reaſon y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> partiality that is now vſed in calling of Councels: which muſt now only be done by the Pope: &amp; of which he onely muſt be Preſident and Iudge: contrary to the order of the firſt <hi>4. Generall Councels, which Gregory profeſſeth to receiue as the 4. holy Goſpels:</hi> Neither is any thing of force that is now decréed in Councel, vnles it be confirmed by the Pope: though in the firſt <hi>4. Councels the Pope was neither Preſident by himſelfe nor his Legates:</hi> neither needed they his con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firmation Beſides, the whole order of Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cels are now inuerted by the Popes, contrary both to y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> inſtitution of the Apoſtles in the firſt Councel holden by them,<note place="margin">
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ct. 15.22, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>3.</note> and to all antiquity. For now none muſt haue determining voyces but the Biſhops: and they muſt ſweare, and take this oath before they ſit in Councel: the forme whereof thus followeth.<note place="margin">
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ecret. li. 2. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>r. 24. ca. 4.</note> 
                  <hi>I (R.N.) will be faithfull from henceforth to S. <hi>Peter,</hi> and to the holy Church of <hi>Rome,</hi> and to my lord (<hi>Boniface</hi> the Pope) &amp; to his ſucceſſors, cho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſen Canonically, and I will bee an helper to defend, againſt all the world, the Popedome, or papall ſuperioritie, and the rules of the ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly Fathers: So God mee helpe and the holy Goſpel.</hi> According to that deteſtable clauſe annexed to the <hi>Decrees of reformation in the
<pb n="101" facs="tcp:20283:63"/> Councel of <hi>Trent,</hi>
                  </hi>
                  <note place="margin">Seſ. 7. in prooe. &amp; Se<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> 25. de. Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>format. ca. vlt.</note> 
                  <hi>Salua ſemper in omnibus au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thoritate ſedis Apoſtolicae; <hi>Prouided alwayes, that the Popes authority be ſafe, and no way preiudiced.</hi>
                  </hi> So that ſtill he will alwaies haue a <hi>non obſtante,</hi> notwithſtanding any law to the contrary, to breake through all lawes, to doe what he liſt. But to conclude, wee acknow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge according to the Scriptures, <hi>That there are two ſorts of iudgements in the Church of God: The one priuate, and the other pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>like: priuate, to all the faithful and ſpirituall,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">1, Cor. 2.15 &amp; 10.15. Ioh. 4.1.</note> as God calleth them, <hi>who are willed to iudge of that which is taught, and to trie the Spirits whether they be of God. Publike, to the aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſsmbly of the Paſtors and Elders:</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Act. 15.6. 1. Cor. 14.</note> 
                  <hi>for of that which Prophets teach, let Prophets iudge: And the ſpirits of the Prophets, are ſubiect to the Prophets.</hi> In all which y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Scripture is the rule, by which y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Church muſt be directed: nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther hath ſhe other authority, than the miniſte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry of giuing iudgement: For the <hi>Soueraignty of iudgement</hi> muſt reſt on Gods word.<note place="margin">Mat. 22.10 Iam. 4.12.</note> 
                  <hi>For Chriſt is our only Doctor &amp; Lawgiuer.</hi> The Lord open your eyes, that you may ſée the Truth, and be thankefull to God.</p>
            </sp>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
      <back>
         <div type="abstract">
            <pb facs="tcp:20283:64"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:20283:64"/>
            <head>An Abſtract of the chiefe <hi>Points of this booke.</hi>
            </head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">F</seg>Irſt, That all the Fathers do with general conſent attribute all ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficiencie to the Scriptures: ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king them the Rule of faith, and the abſolute meanes to deter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mine all doubts and controuerſies; prefer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring them before the Church, and all other writings of men whatſoeuer: and further, that the Church is no otherwiſe to be ſhewed or knowen, but by the Canonicall Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures: and that themſelues, and their opini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, without the Scriptures, are not to bee beleeued, but reiected. <hi>See the Preface: and pag.</hi> 15. 16. 17. 18. 19. 45. 46. 47. 52.</p>
            <p n="2">2 That the Scriptures are to be expounded by the Scriptures: and that we are not tied for the expoſition thereof to any Father, Councell, or Pope. And that no Papiſt can ſhew the conſent of the Fathers, that the ſcriptures are to be expou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ded by any Father, Councell, or Pope. <hi>See pag.</hi> 88. 89. 90. 91.</p>
            <p n="3">
               <pb facs="tcp:20283:65"/>3 That the Fathers agree with vs, taking the greater part, in approouing thoſe Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures, which the Proteſtants doe, to be Cano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nicall, and in reiecting thoſe which we do for Apocrypha. <hi>See pag.</hi> 4. 5.</p>
            <p n="4">4 That the Fathers take the word Traditi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on ſometimes for the Scriptures; ſometimes for the Cuſtomes and Ceremonies of the Church: and the Papiſts, which vrge them for matter of doctrine vnwritten, and to bee of equall authoritie with the Scriptures, doe depraue the Fathers, making their doctrines contrary one to another, yea, contrary to themſelues. <hi>See the Preface.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="5">5 That chiefe Papiſts, and pillars of Pope<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry, haue confeſſed, that many and moſt of the doctrines wherein they varie from vs, are grounded vpon Traditions. And that it is extreame madneſſe to thinke, that the whole and entire body of Euangelical doctrine is to bee fetched out of the Apoſtolike writings, and out of that little Booke of the New Te<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtament. In which doctrine, they goe whol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly againſt the ſtreame of the Fathers, and alſo diſcouer their abuſing of the ſimplicity of their followers, when they make them be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leeue the greateſt difference betweene them and vs, is, touching the ſenſe of the Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures:
<pb facs="tcp:20283:65"/> whereas by this their confeſſion, this conſequent neceſſarily followeth; That where there is no Text, there needes no In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terpreter. <hi>See the Preface.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="6">6 That the Papiſts haue vttered open blaſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phemy, in their bookes againſt the Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures, in taxing them of inſufficiencie, in tearming them a Noſe of waxe, Inkie diui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nitie, dumbe Iudges, no better than Aeſops Fables, without the authority of the Church: That they take their authority from the Church; That ſometimes they are to bee expounded one way, ſometimes another; That the Scriptures muſt folow the Church, and not the Church the Scriptures: prefer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring the authoritie of the Church aboue and againſt the Scriptures. All which blaſphe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies are refuted, not onely by the direct texts of Scripture, but by the generall conſent of the Fathers. <hi>See the Preface.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="7">7 That the Papiſts vrge the credit of the Fathers, for the receiuing of Traditions: and though there be many Traditions, which by the Fathers teſtimony haue the ſame autho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritie to prooue them to be Apoſtolike, that the others haue: Yet the Papiſts receiue the one, and reiect the other. <hi>See pag.</hi> 12. 13.</p>
            <p n="8">8 That the Fathers haue held diuers er<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rors:
<pb facs="tcp:20283:66"/> vpon which it neceſſarily followeth: that if they might erre in one thing, they might erre in another: And that their iudge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments are often reiected by the Papiſts, and therefore may with as great reaſon be reie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cted by vs: and conſequently are no per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fite Rule to build our Religion on: which euen the Fathers themſelues confeſſe. <hi>See pag.</hi> 20. 21. 22 23. 16. 17.</p>
            <p n="9">9 That there be many Counterfeits, that haue vſurped the names of auncient Fathers: wherby it is hard to diſcerne when a true Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, and when a falſe ſpeakes. And though ſome of theſe Fathers be cenſured for coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terfeits, euen by the learned Papiſts them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelues, and their Vniuerſities: yet doe they alleage them againſt vs in many of their bookes, (eſpecially in the Rhemes Teſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment) to giue countenance to Popiſh errors. <hi>See pag.</hi> 23. 24. 25. 26. 27. 28. 29. 30. 31. 32. 33.</p>
            <p n="10">10 That the conſent of the Fathers cannot be ſhewed, (nay, ſcarce any ancient Father) that all controuerſies are to bee determined by the Pope: or, that hee cannot erre: or, that hee muſt ſummon Councels: or, that they are of no authoritie, vnleſſe they bee confirmed by the Pope. And yet are theſe doctrines held Catholike by the Papiſts, and
<pb facs="tcp:20283:66"/> reputed the chiefe pillars of Popery. <hi>See pag.</hi> 75.</p>
            <p n="11">11 That al thoſe places of Scripture, which are brought by the Papiſts, either to prooue <hi>the Popes prerogatiue;</hi> or, <hi>the authority of the Church;</hi> or, that <hi>the Church cannot erre,</hi> are by the Fathers (writing purpoſely vpon the ſame places) expounded according to the Proteſtants ſenſe giuen; and contrary to the ſenſe which the Papiſts giue. So farre are the Papiſts from proouing the generall conſent of the Fathers, in expounding theſe Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures, which they commonly obiect againſt vs, (as, <hi>Thou art</hi> Peter, <hi>and vpon this Rocke will I build my Church:</hi> and, <hi>the gates of hell ſhall not preuaile againſt it:</hi> Or, the promiſes of the holy Ghoſt to be ſent to the Church, to leade it into all trueth: Or, <hi>To thee will I giue the keyes of the kingdom of Heauen:</hi> Or, <hi>The Church is the pillar and ground of Trueth:</hi> Or, <hi>Tell the Church:</hi> Or, <hi>if hee heare not the Church, let him be to thee as an heathen, or as a Publicane:</hi> Or, <hi>whatſoeuer thou bindeſt in earth, ſhall be bound in heauen:</hi> Or, any other place of Scripture to the ſayd purpoſes) to bee on their ſide; as namely, that thoſe Texts ſhould be meant of the Pope, Generall Councell, or the Church of <hi>Rome. See pag.</hi> 66. 67. 68. 69. 70.</p>
            <p n="12">
               <pb facs="tcp:20283:67"/>12 That Generall Councels haue erred, haue beene contrary one to another, haue been reiected by the Papiſts themſelues; and ſo are no ſure Rule to build our faith on. <hi>See pag.</hi> 48. 49. 50. 51. 52. 53. 54. 55.</p>
            <p n="13">13 That the Popes, whom they would haue to be ſupreame Iudges in al Controuer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſies, haue erred iudicially; haue been here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tikes (as maintaining the hereſie of the Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nothelites; ſubſcribing to the Arrian here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſie; to the Neſtorian hereſie) haue offered ſacrifice to idoles, haue been Necromancers, and Coniurers. <hi>See pag.</hi> 58. 59. 60. 61. 62.</p>
            <p n="14">14 That the Pope can be no competent Iudge: and whereunto the Fathers referre vs. <hi>See pag.</hi> 93, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
            </p>
         </div>
         <div type="errata">
            <pb facs="tcp:20283:67"/>
            <p>LEt me requeſt thee, Courteous reader, to take no<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ice, that the Texts of Scripture, and teſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monies of the Fathers (cited by me in this Trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſe) ſhould all haue been ſet downe in a different letter, from the rest of the matter wherewith they are ranked; accordingly as you ſee performed in the Preface, and in the later halfe of the booke. Now, by meanes of my abſence, and want of di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rection giuen, in this point, it could not be diſcer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned by the Printer, howe farre the wordes of the Text and Teſtimonies (ſo to bee diſtinguiſhed) might reach. And therefore I cannot but free him from that blame; as likewiſe (<hi>2.</hi> or <hi>3.</hi> literal eſcapes only excepted) from imputation of any the faults hereunder ſpecified: ſome of them being commit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted, in my Copie; and the reſt, through difficulty and darknes of the hand, might eaſily be miſtaken.</p>
            <div type="part">
               <head>In the Text.</head>
               <p>Page 5. line 7. for, allured: reade allowed. pag. 8. l. 17. Trations, Traditions. p. 11, l. 19. Prieſts: proofe. p. 29. l. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>6. addeth: alleageth. p. 29. l. 17. tehimony: teſtimony p. 31. l. 2. for, 25: 15. p. 33. l. 7. fault: fable. p. 40. l. 9. ch<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ice: chiefe. p. 72. l. 8. cannot: which can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not. p. 89. l. 1. ſenſe: the ſenſe.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>In the Margent.</head>
               <p>
                  <hi>Pag.</hi> 7. for, De Bapt. c. 6. li. 1. reade, De Bapt. cont. Don. li. 3. <hi>pag.</hi> 7. prat. <hi>reade</hi> pont. <hi>pag.</hi> 8. 1. Theſ. 2. Theſ. <hi>pag.</hi> 12. 1. Pet. 2.18. 1. Pet. 1.18. <hi>pag.</hi> 20. Aug. in Frut. Aug. in Enar. <hi>pag.</hi> 14. de fulta: de falſa. <hi>pag.</hi> 35. li. 1. cap. 22. li 1. cap 23. <hi>pag.</hi> 36. Tim. Tit. <hi>pag.</hi> 52. Epiſt. 16, 7. Epiſt. 167. <hi>pag.</hi> 59. (againſt Pope <hi>Coeleſtine</hi>) C. laudab. de con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerſ. Infidel, <hi>is omitted.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
         </div>
      </back>
   </text>
</TEI>
