<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>The amourous fantasme a tragi-comedy. By Sr. William Lower knight.</title>
            <author>Quinault, Philippe, 1635-1688.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1659</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 149 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 49 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-04">2011-04 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A74717</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing Q215</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Thomason E2108_1</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R210061</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99868893</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99868893</idno>
            <idno type="VID">121249</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A74717)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 121249)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Thomason Tracts ; 241:E2108[1])</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>The amourous fantasme a tragi-comedy. By Sr. William Lower knight.</title>
                  <author>Quinault, Philippe, 1635-1688.</author>
                  <author>Lower, William, Sir, 1600?-1662.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[8], 9-96 p. : ill.  </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>imprinted by John Ramzey,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>Hage :</pubPlace>
                  <date>Anno 1660.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>With a preliminary engraved half-title.</note>
                  <note>A play by Philippe Quinault, translated by William Lower -- Cf. Greg.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the British Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2009-12</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-01</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-02</date>
            <label>Lauren Proux</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-02</date>
            <label>Lauren Proux</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-04</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:121249:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>
               <hi>THE</hi> AMOUROUS FANTASME, <hi>A</hi> TRAGI-COMEDY.</p>
            <p>By <hi>Sr. WILLIAM LOWER</hi> Knight.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Amico Roſa, Inimico Spinae.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>HAGE,</hi> Imprinted by JOHN RAMZEY, <hi>Anno</hi> 1660.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="frontispiece">
            <pb facs="tcp:121249:2"/>
            <p>
               <figure>
                  <head>THE AMOVROVS FANTASME TRAGI-COMEDY</head>
               </figure>
            </p>
            <pb facs="tcp:121249:2" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
               <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
            </gap>
         </div>
         <div type="dedication">
            <pb facs="tcp:121249:3"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:121249:3"/>
            <head>
               <hi>TO</hi> HER HIGHNESSE <hi>THE</hi> PRINCESSE ROYALL.</head>
            <opener>
               <salute>MADAM,</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>IN preſuming to dedicate this imperfect Peece to the moſt accomplish'd Princeſſe of the Earth, I confeſſe to shew much more ambition then diſcretion, more rashnes then ſolid reaſon and moderation; but ſeeing or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinarily that the greateſt Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons have the leaſt pride, and the moſt charity, I caſt my ſelfe wholy upon your clemency, and fly the teſt of your judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, which being ſo exact, would doubly condemne me, firſt in the deſigne it ſelfe, next in the conduct, and conſequen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ce of it, as being a compoſition
<pb facs="tcp:121249:4"/>weak, and unworthy of ſo high a Patronage. If it may ſerve to divert Your Highneſſe in ſome vacant hower when your ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lime thoughts are ſuſpended, I have the onely end I aime at, and shall glory in the honour and happines to introduce ſome thing with the New Yeere, which may give you the leaſt ſatisfaction: My conclu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion is a moſt humble petition for pardon, and a favourable cenſure of the bould ambition, which I have to entitle my ſelfe,</p>
            <closer>
               <salute>MADAM,</salute> 
               <signed>Your Highneſſe moſt humble, moſt obedient, and moſt Faith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full Servant <hi>WILLIAM LOWER.</hi>
               </signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="prologue">
            <pb facs="tcp:121249:4"/>
            <head>PROLOGUE To the Court.</head>
            <sp>
               <l>HA! what divine shapes ſtrike mine eyes, and make</l>
               <l>My tongue to faulter, and my limbs to shake,</l>
               <l>Through a reſpestfull awe and reverence,</l>
               <l>Which thus ſo ſtrongly ſeyſeth on my ſenſe?</l>
               <l>Theſe are no <hi>Fantaſmes,</hi> ſuch as we preſent,</l>
               <l>But true Divinities from Heaven ſent</l>
               <l>To grace our Earthly Theater; then <hi>I,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>Who cannot ſtand before ſuch Majeſty,</l>
               <l>Fall on my knee, and in this poſture pray</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>I</hi> may be heard to ſpeak before the Play:</l>
               <l>Madam, to you then, from whoſe beautious ſight</l>
               <l>Thoſe leſſer Starrs derive their borrowed light,</l>
               <l>Firſt <hi>I</hi> addreſſe me; and although I'm ſent</l>
               <l>From the proud Poet with a complement</l>
               <l>To let you know that he proteſts and ſaith</l>
               <l>His Sceanes will pleaſe, <hi>I</hi> cannot have that faith:</l>
               <l>He ſweares that he prepares a Peece ſo rich</l>
               <l>In high conceptions, that it will bewitch</l>
               <l>Your eyes and eares, a Banket that may pleaſe</l>
               <l>The Danity Pallats of the Deities:</l>
               <l>Vnheard of vanity! <hi>I</hi> cannot chuſe</l>
               <l>But undeceive you, know tis an abuſe,</l>
               <l>You'll meet with no feaſt here, ſince the chief dish</l>
               <l>Which he preſents, is neither flesh nor fish,</l>
               <l>But a meere <hi>Fantaſme,</hi> garnish'd like a coarſe,</l>
               <l>Larded, and ſerv'd up vvith ſome love diſcourſe,</l>
               <l>Vnſolid matter flourishes of vvitt,</l>
               <l>And airy fancies, in my judgment fit</l>
               <l>But for the publick Stage, not to appeare</l>
               <l>Within the verge of this illuſtrious Sphere,</l>
               <l>Where nothing but the quinteſcence of vvit</l>
               <l>Should dare to enter: humbly <hi>I</hi> ſubmit</l>
               <pb facs="tcp:121249:5"/>
               <l>To your tranſcendent judgment my adviſe,</l>
               <l>And wish it may be found more rash then wiſe,</l>
               <l>For daign t' applaud the Play, and I'm content</l>
               <l>To ſuffer for it any punishment,</l>
               <l>t' Appeaſe the Poett, whoſe rage will be hot</l>
               <l>Vpon my head, if you protect me not:</l>
               <l>Auſpitious Planets, rule this night, and shed</l>
               <l>Sweet influences on your board and bed.</l>
            </sp>
         </div>
         <div type="dramatis_personae">
            <head>ACTORS.</head>
            <list>
               <item>
                  <hi>CARLOS.</hi> Lover of Iſabella, and Friend to Fabritio.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>CLARINA.</hi> Woman to Iſabella.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>FABRITIO.</hi> Lover of Climene.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>CLIMENE.</hi> Miſtreſſe to Fabritio, and to the Duke.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>JACINTA.</hi> Woman to Climene.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>FERDINAND.</hi> Duke of Ferrara.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>VALERIO.</hi> Captaine of the Dukes Guards.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>ISABELLA.</hi> Siſter to Fabritio.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>ALPHONSO.</hi> Father to Fabritio and Iſabella.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>LICASTES.</hi> Servant to Alphonſo.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>CELIN.</hi> Servant to Carlos.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>GUARDS.</hi>
               </item>
            </list>
            <p>The Scene is at Ferrara.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="play">
            <pb n="9" facs="tcp:121249:5"/>
            <head>
               <hi>THE</hi> AMOUROUS FANTASME.</head>
            <head type="sub">
               <hi>A</hi> TRAGI-COMEDY.</head>
            <div n="1" type="act">
               <head>ACT<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>S PRIM<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>S.</head>
               <div n="1" type="scene">
                  <head>SCENA PRIMA.</head>
                  <stage>Carlos, Clarina, in a ſtreet.</stage>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Carlos.</speaker>
                     <l>ARt ſure of it, <hi>Clarina?</hi> is it poſſible</l>
                     <l>That <hi>Iſabella</hi> now is ſenſible</l>
                     <l>Of what I ſuffer for her, and reſents</l>
                     <l>In my behalfe the fire which her faire eyes</l>
                     <l>Have kindled in my heart?</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Clarina.</speaker>
                     <l>Sir, I aſſure you,</l>
                     <l>Tis an undoubted truth, which I receiv'd</l>
                     <l>From her owne mouth.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Carlos.</speaker>
                     <l>I'm much aſtonished</l>
                     <pb n="10" facs="tcp:121249:6"/>
                     <l>With a ſucceſſe ſo charming.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Clarina.</speaker>
                     <l>For my parte,</l>
                     <l>I wonder that you are aſtonish'd at it:</l>
                     <l>Is it ſo great a miracle, I pray you,</l>
                     <l>To ſee a Mayd to chaung? we have a mind</l>
                     <l>Alternatelie to turne love into hatred,</l>
                     <l>Or hatred into love, ſuch an effect</l>
                     <l>As this ſo common in our Sex, should not</l>
                     <l>Seeme ſtrang unto you: <hi>Iſabella.</hi> is</l>
                     <l>Of age ſufficient to feele the effect</l>
                     <l>Both of the fire she kindles, and o'th'evill</l>
                     <l>Which she procures; the end, Sir, of her coldnes</l>
                     <l>Should not ſurpriſe you: who gives love, can eaſilie</l>
                     <l>Take it againe; and when a young heart never</l>
                     <l>Hath loved any thing, at the firſt fire</l>
                     <l>That ſparkles, tis inflam'd; my Miſtreſſe is</l>
                     <l>At ſenſible as faire you will be happie,</l>
                     <l>If you are faithfull.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Carlos.</speaker>
                     <p>But com'ſt thou by her order?</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Clarina.</speaker>
                     <l>To ſpeak truelie,</l>
                     <l>She willed me to ſpeak as from my ſelfe;</l>
                     <l>But, Sir, your goodnes is a gage that makes me</l>
                     <l>To tell you all, tis by her expreſſe order</l>
                     <l>That I have uttered this ſecret to you</l>
                     <l>Of ſuch importance; but you muſt be ſilent</l>
                     <l>And diſcreet, if yov'll profit by the knowledge.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Carlos.</speaker>
                     <l>But may I not at leaſt acquaint her brother</l>
                     <l>With my good fortune? he is bound by friendship</l>
                     <l>To favour me, and I should doe him wrong</l>
                     <l>To diſguiſe any thing to him.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <pb n="11" facs="tcp:121249:6"/>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Clarina.</speaker>
                     <l>Oh! Sir,</l>
                     <l>That's it my Miſtreſſe, dreadeth, believe me,</l>
                     <l>Above all things: ſo farre you muſt be from</l>
                     <l>Acquainting him therewith, that you should feare</l>
                     <l>Leaſt he might have the leaſt ſuſpition of it:</l>
                     <l>Know you not yet that her inhumane Father,</l>
                     <l>Will not permit her to give you her hand,</l>
                     <l>That to uphould the ſplendour of his houſe,</l>
                     <l>He'll rayſe his Sonne unto his Daughtets coſt,</l>
                     <l>And, as tis often practiſ'd now a dayes)</l>
                     <l>Toſh one deſignes his goods, and to the other</l>
                     <l>A Monaſterie?</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Carlos.</speaker>
                     <l>I know well that her Father</l>
                     <l>Hath fuch a purpoſe, but though he be of</l>
                     <l>A nature ſo inhumane, ſure, her brother</l>
                     <l>Is not ſo barbarous: we are tyed together</l>
                     <l>By ſuch faire bonds of friendship, that I know</l>
                     <l>He'll mix his intereſts with mine.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Clarina.</speaker>
                     <l>If I</l>
                     <l>May frelie ſpeak my thoughts here, I muſt tel you</l>
                     <l>That intereſt can break the ſtrongeſt bonds,</l>
                     <l>That commonlie men better keep their wealth</l>
                     <l>Then their fidelitie, and that there is</l>
                     <l>No friend which they love equall with themſelves</l>
                     <l>Be ſure you truſt no perſon now a dayes,</l>
                     <l>Daunger ſtill followes too much conſidence:</l>
                     <l>The leſſe a good is knowne, the ſweeter tis:</l>
                     <l>Laſtly Sir, keepe your ſecretts to your ſelfe,</l>
                     <l>My Miſtreſſe doth deſire it.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Corlos.</speaker>
                     <l>Oh! <hi>Clarina,</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>It is ynough, there is no teaſon more</l>
                     <pb n="12" facs="tcp:121249:7"/>
                     <l>In this point to examine now, but I</l>
                     <l>Obey without diſpute; the name of Friend</l>
                     <l>Muſt yeild to that of Lover; but shall I</l>
                     <l>See our faire Miſtreſſe by thy meanes this evening?</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Clarina.</speaker>
                     <p>Sir, it is verie late.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Carlos.</speaker>
                     <l>I know thy skill.</l>
                     <l>And thou know'ſt — <stage>puts gould in her hand.</stage>
                     </l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Clarina.</speaker>
                     <l>Yes, your liberalities.</l>
                     <l>I'le goe t'advertiſe her, as you deſire,</l>
                     <l>And preſentlie returne, if you will ſtay,</l>
                     <l>Either to bring you up, or to perſuade her</l>
                     <l>To come downe to you. — <stage>Exit Clarina.</stage>
                     </l>
                  </sp>
                  <stage>Carlos alone.</stage>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Carlos.</speaker>
                     <l>Oh how ſweet it is</l>
                     <l>To molliſie a hard and cruell heart!</l>
                     <l>How charming is Love, when tis mutuall?</l>
                     <l>what high content, what extaſie of joy</l>
                     <l>Feels a poore captive in his troubles, when</l>
                     <l>The hand that tames him, helpes to beare his chaines?</l>
                     <l>A good gain'd eaſilie is not eſteem'd:</l>
                     <l>The more it coſts, the more tis pretious:</l>
                     <l>Although th' Horizon's covered with darknes,</l>
                     <l>I eaſilie diſcerne the dore to open;</l>
                     <l>Doubtles, tis <hi>Iſabella,</hi> I'le advaunce.</l>
                  </sp>
               </div>
               <div n="2" type="scene">
                  <head>SCENA SECUNDA.</head>
                  <stage>Carlos, Fabritio.</stage>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Carlos.</speaker>
                     <l>My happines is greater then I dar'd</l>
                     <pb n="13" facs="tcp:121249:7"/>
                     <l>To fancie is, I can't expreſſe unto you,</l>
                     <l>By what ſoe'r indeavour <hi>I</hi> can uſe,</l>
                     <l>The fullnss of my paſſion and my joy.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Fabritio.</speaker>
                     <l>Deare friend, I doe beſeech thee let us leave</l>
                     <l>Vaine complements, I know shy goodnes for me.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Carlos.</speaker>
                     <p>Good God! how I'm confounded! tis her brother <hi>Fabritio.</hi> — <stage>a ſide.</stage>
                     </p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Fabritio.</speaker>
                     <l>Thou knoweſt then, it ſeemes,</l>
                     <l>How highlie fortune is propitious to me,</l>
                     <l>My marsiage is concluded and agreed,</l>
                     <l>And thou com'ſt without doubt to wish me joy.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Carlos.</speaker>
                     <p>Friend —</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Fabritio.</speaker>
                     <l>I'm certaine, it is this that brings thee hether:</l>
                     <l>Thou wilt congratulate my happines.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Carlos.</speaker>
                     <l>How readie, and ingenious he is</l>
                     <l>To draw me out of trouble? — <stage>a ſide</stage>
                     </l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Fabritio.</speaker>
                     <p>Thou comes to take part in my ravishment.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Carlos.</speaker>
                     <p>Thou should'ſt doe me a great wrong, to judge otherwiſe.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Fabritio.</speaker>
                     <l>Know then that our deſires did jump together:</l>
                     <l>I was a going haſtilie unto thee</l>
                     <l>To tell thee the glad ne Wes, I did believe</l>
                     <l>Thou knew'ſt it not, and did not thinke to be</l>
                     <l>Prevented, I am highlie redevable</l>
                     <l>To thy rare friendship.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Carlos.</speaker>
                     <l>I doe nothing for thee</l>
                     <l>That is conſiderable, my intereſt</l>
                     <pb n="14" facs="tcp:121249:8"/>
                     <l>Alone bringeth me hither, and thou need'ſt not</l>
                     <l>To thanke me for it.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Fabritio.</speaker>
                     <l>How! what intereſt</l>
                     <l>Canſt thou have in this place?</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Carlos.</speaker>
                     <l>The ſame which friendship</l>
                     <l>Enjoyneth me to take in thy contents.</l>
                     <l>Betweene two faithfull friends, ſuch as we are,</l>
                     <l>Everie thing should be common, joy and happines</l>
                     <l>Poſſeſſeth both, when one of them enjoyes it.</l>
                     <l>Know when I beare a part in thy good fortune,</l>
                     <l>I more oblige my ſelfe then thee, and am</l>
                     <l>So well paid for my care and tendernes,</l>
                     <l>That there needs no addition of thanks.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Fabritio.</speaker>
                     <l>Know alſo of my part when Fortune doth</l>
                     <l>Conferre her favours on me, they are dubled</l>
                     <l>When <hi>Carlos</hi> shares therein, and would diminish</l>
                     <l>If he should not partake them; but who comes</l>
                     <l>So late forth of our houſe?</l>
                  </sp>
               </div>
               <div n="3" type="scene">
                  <head>SCENA TERTIA.</head>
                  <stage>Clarina, Fabritio, Carlos.</stage>
                  <stage>
                     <hi>Clarina addreſſing her ſelfe to</hi> Fabritio <hi>thinking to ſpeake to</hi> Carlos.</stage>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Clarina.</speaker>
                     <l>SIr, enter quicklie;</l>
                     <l>My Miſtreſſe <hi>Iſabella</hi> in her chamber</l>
                     <l>Expecteth you and will. —</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Fabritio.</speaker>
                     <p>How, what will she?</p>
                  </sp>
                  <pb n="15" facs="tcp:121249:8"/>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Clarina.</speaker>
                     <l>Misfortune! tis <hi>Fabritio,</hi> I muſt</l>
                     <l>Diſſemble. — <stage>a ſide.</stage>
                     </l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Fabritio.</speaker>
                     <p>Well, what will she, finish now.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Clarina.</speaker>
                     <l>Sir, she would ſpeak with you,</l>
                     <l>T'expreſſe the joy whereto her love engageth her</l>
                     <l>On the concluſion of your marriage.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Fabritio.</speaker>
                     <l>I know her tendernes, and what I owe her;</l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Carlos</hi> and I will ſee her preſentlie</l>
                     <l>To give her a good night.</l>
                  </sp>
               </div>
               <div n="4" type="scene">
                  <head>SCENA QUARTA.</head>
                  <stage>Climene, Iacinta, Carlos, Fabritio.</stage>
                  <stage>Climene <hi>comming out of her houſe.</hi>
                  </stage>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Climene.</speaker>
                     <l>IT is <hi>Fabritios</hi> voice this which I heare,</l>
                     <l>I cannot come forth in a fitter time.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Carlos.</speaker>
                     <l>I willinglie waite on you, your deſires</l>
                     <l>Are mine, you need not doubt them — <stage>to Fabritio.</stage>
                     </l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Fabritio.</speaker>
                     <p>Let us enter.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Carlos.</speaker>
                     <p>How this ſucceſſe favoureth my flame! — <stage>a ſide</stage>
                     </p>
                  </sp>
                  <stage>Fabritio <hi>ſtopped by</hi> Climeme.</stage>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Fabritio.</speaker>
                     <l>But who doth ſtop me? Heaven! it is a Woman,</l>
                     <l>It ſeemes she Would ſpeak with me <hi>Carlos</hi> ſtay.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Carlos.</speaker>
                     <p>I waite you heere.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <pb n="16" facs="tcp:121249:9"/>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Fabritio.</speaker>
                     <l>How comes it she withdrawes</l>
                     <l>When I advaunce?</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Carlos.</speaker>
                     <l>Withour doubt she hath ſomething</l>
                     <l>To ſpeak to you in private.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Fabritio.</speaker>
                     <l>In the hope</l>
                     <l>Wherein I am that I am he you ſeek,</l>
                     <l>Be not offended that I dare t'approach:</l>
                     <l>I've courage and civilitie ynough</l>
                     <l>T'eſteeme me fortunare if I could ſerve you:</l>
                     <l>T'engage me, Madame, to the offer which</l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>I</hi> make to uſe my utmoſt cares and paines</l>
                     <l>T'accomplish your deſires, it is ſufficient</l>
                     <l>That Heaven hath given you the advantage to be</l>
                     <l>Of that faire Sex unto which all owe homadge:</l>
                     <l>If I may notwithſtanding without giving you</l>
                     <l>The leaſt offence be honoured to knowe</l>
                     <l>Your name, you will encreaſe my Zeale in giving me</l>
                     <l>So faire a ſatisfaction.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Climene</speaker>
                     <l>Take it then,</l>
                     <l>My deare <hi>Fabritio,</hi> and know <hi>Climene.</hi>
                     </l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Fabritio.</speaker>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Climene,</hi> my faire Miſtreſſe, what occaſion</l>
                     <l>Could bring thee heere at ſuch an hower as this?</l>
                     <l>Thou doubleſt my feare and perturbation;</l>
                     <l>The more thy voice aſſureth me; the more</l>
                     <l>Vncertaine am I: and ſo farre am I</l>
                     <l>From comming forth of errour, that I enter</l>
                     <l>Into new Labyrinths, and doubts, I was</l>
                     <l>More happie when I knew thee leſſe; oh what</l>
                     <l>Deſigne haſt thou, I cannot comprehend it?</l>
                  </sp>
                  <pb n="17" facs="tcp:121249:9"/>
                  <stage>CLIMENE.</stage>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Climene.</speaker>
                     <l>Leave me to ſpeake, then, I will tell it thee.</l>
                     <l>I will not ſay what joy and happie tapture</l>
                     <l>Seiſed me when I underſtood the newes,</l>
                     <l>That by a joynt accord our friends and parents</l>
                     <l>At laſt had yeilded to our marriage;</l>
                     <l>My love, which thou shouldſt not forget, exemps me</l>
                     <l>To diſcourſe this unto thee, and enjoynes me</l>
                     <l>To a relation much more important,</l>
                     <l>And much leſſe pleaſing,</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Fabritio.</speaker>
                     <l>How! what thing is there</l>
                     <l>In nature that can trouble our repoſe,</l>
                     <l>Since as our hearts, our parents are agreed?</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Climene.</speaker>
                     <l>Tis of a longer date then from to day</l>
                     <l>That Love uſeth to mingle with his ſweets</l>
                     <l>Much bitternes, thoſe whom he flattereth</l>
                     <l>At firſt, are ſoldome happie, his deceit</l>
                     <l>Is equall to his blindnes, and like Fortune,</l>
                     <l>H'is conſtant onelie in inconſtancie:</l>
                     <l>This is a truth, which thou shalt but to ſenſibly</l>
                     <l>Conceive: one day which was the fatalleſt</l>
                     <l>Of all my life, wherein my father burthened</l>
                     <l>With age and ſicknes had the ſorrie honour</l>
                     <l>To be by the <hi>Duke</hi> of <hi>Ferrara</hi> viſſitted:</l>
                     <l>This Prince knew me in this extremity,</l>
                     <l>And thought to ſee ſome charmes upon my pale</l>
                     <l>And blubbered face, my ne eyes unluckily</l>
                     <l>Wept unto his, and from the ſources of</l>
                     <l>My teares his flame took birth,</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Fabritio.</speaker>
                     <l>Oh <hi>Climene,</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>I feare —</l>
                  </sp>
                  <pb n="18" facs="tcp:121249:10"/>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Climene.</speaker>
                     <l>That feare offends me; my heart wholie</l>
                     <l>Was thine, I gave it thee, and the <hi>Dukes</hi> paſſion</l>
                     <l>Stir'd up in me nothing but my averſion:</l>
                     <l>Though I conceal'd this fire, thou haſt no cauſe</l>
                     <l>To complaine at it, for before twas knowne,</l>
                     <l>I hop'd to quench it, and I ſcarce should yet</l>
                     <l>Reveile it to thee, if thy intereſt</l>
                     <l>Oblig'd me not to ſpeak: on the report</l>
                     <l>Which was ſpread of our marriage, the paſſion</l>
                     <l>Of the <hi>Duke</hi> was converted into rage;</l>
                     <l>He came unto me in his firſt tranſport,</l>
                     <l>Sware to me ſolemnelie that my choice was</l>
                     <l>The ſentence of thy death, that Love oppoſing</l>
                     <l>My punishment, he thought to doe more in</l>
                     <l>Deſtroying what I lov'd; and to the end</l>
                     <l>He might with the more rigour punish me,</l>
                     <l>He would even to the bottome of thy heart</l>
                     <l>Goe for to ſeek me: Laſtly knowing well</l>
                     <l>That his deſire is to aſſault my life</l>
                     <l>In threatening thine, conducted here by love,</l>
                     <l>And more by feare, I come to conjure thee</l>
                     <l>T'avoid his furie; fly hence, what ſoever</l>
                     <l>Care for me keeps thee back heere, and to ſave</l>
                     <l>My life, preſerve thine.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Fabritio.</speaker>
                     <l>This diſcourſe is cruel</l>
                     <l>As much as it appeareth ſweet: should you</l>
                     <l>Advice me to abſent me from your perſon?</l>
                     <l>Sure I should little know what tis to love,</l>
                     <l>T'obey you in this point: Come, come, ſay all,</l>
                     <l>Confeſſe your love is chang'd, that my remaines</l>
                     <l>Of hope muſt vanish, and that the Dukes flame</l>
                     <l>Hath dazled you, I ſee well that mine heere</l>
                     <l>Is troubleſom, that you abandon Love</l>
                     <l>To follow Fortune, and that poore Fabritio</l>
                     <l>With all his fetters pleaſeth your faire eyes</l>
                     <pb n="19" facs="tcp:121249:10"/>
                     <l>Leſſe then a crowned Captive: I condemne not</l>
                     <l>This ſignall rigour; you deprive me of</l>
                     <l>A happines whereof I was not worthy,</l>
                     <l>And in receaving of a Scepter offered</l>
                     <l>Vnto your beauties, you obtaine much leſſe</l>
                     <l>Then you deſerve. Raigne, nothing is dishonou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable,</l>
                     <l>To gaine a diademne; and as I love you</l>
                     <l>More then my ſelfe, I shal eſteem my death</l>
                     <l>A faire deſigne, if entering into</l>
                     <l>A tombe, I leave you in a throne,</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Climene.</speaker>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Fabritio,</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>Canſt thou love me, and ſpeak thus? reallie</l>
                     <l>Thou detract'ſt from my glorie in this thought</l>
                     <l>That I can be unfaithfull, bannish it,</l>
                     <l>It is thy enemie and mine; ſuſpition</l>
                     <l>Between us two should be a hideous monſter;</l>
                     <l>Canſt thou be ignorant with any juſtice,</l>
                     <l>That I love leſſe a ſcepter then Fabritio,</l>
                     <l>And find more joy in being captive with thee</l>
                     <l>To raigne over thy heart, then ore the univerſe?</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Fabritio.</speaker>
                     <l>It is ynough, Climene, my devout</l>
                     <l>And amourous ſoule, which ever muſt adore thee</l>
                     <l>Although thou should'ſt abuſe it, would believe thee:</l>
                     <l>And though a lye carries a ſwarthy face,</l>
                     <l>In iſſumg from thy mouth it would have char<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mes;</l>
                     <l>But how comes it to paſſe that when they ſweet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes</l>
                     <l>For my ſake flyes a crowne, thou doſt ordaine me</l>
                     <l>To depart, and to leave thee? how to leave thee.</l>
                     <l>And in a Rivalls power to! no, this remedie</l>
                     <l>Is worſe then the diſeaſe. Suffer my preſence,</l>
                     <l>Or ſuffer my deſpaire, what matter is it</l>
                     <pb n="20" facs="tcp:121249:11"/>
                     <l>Whether the <hi>Duke,</hi> or abſence kill <hi>Fabritio</hi>
                     </l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Climene.</speaker>
                     <l>When two inevitable dangers meet</l>
                     <l>To invade us at once, tis wiſedome ſtill</l>
                     <l>To think of the moſt preſſing, here thy ruine</l>
                     <l>Is certaine, being abſent, thou canſt live;</l>
                     <l>Conſider this, that to what punishment</l>
                     <l>Soer our love expoſeth thee, thou canſt not</l>
                     <l>Suffer but I muſt ſuffer too, nor dye,</l>
                     <l>But I muſt ceaſe to live, for know abſuredlie</l>
                     <l>My dayes shall finish with thy deſtiny;</l>
                     <l>When we are dead, the grave shall be a wittnes</l>
                     <l>Of our reunion? where I ſee thee not</l>
                     <l>No object pleaſeth me; if thou art yet</l>
                     <l>Incredulous of words and proteſtations,</l>
                     <l>At leaſt believe my teares.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Fabritio.</speaker>
                     <l>Oh open not</l>
                     <l>Thoſe pretious ſluces, keep that treaſure in;</l>
                     <l>Encreaſe not my affliction with thy griefe:</l>
                     <l>Not all the blood which tunneth in my veines</l>
                     <l>Is worth the leaſt drop of theſe liquid pearles,</l>
                     <l>The evills wherewith my life is thretened</l>
                     <l>Are too well payed with a ſingle teare.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Climene.</speaker>
                     <p>Oh leave thoſe vaine diſcourſes, and depart.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Fabritio.</speaker>
                     <p>Well, well, <hi>Climene,</hi> I muſt then obey.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Climene.</speaker>
                     <l>I have as much cauſe heere to be afflicted,</l>
                     <l>As ſatiſſied, I feare more thy departure</l>
                     <l>Then wish it, and I give my faith unto thee,</l>
                     <l>That thou shouldſt not depart, if I could keep thee</l>
                     <l>And expoſe but my ſelfe. Let's ſeparate;</l>
                     <l>But what! this fatall image robbeth me</l>
                     <l>Already of my ſtrength, ſpare me, I pray thee,</l>
                     <l>In parting hence the danger heere to dye</l>
                     <pb n="21" facs="tcp:121249:11"/>
                     <l>In bidding thee adiew. — <stage>Exit Climene.</stage>
                     </l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Fabritio.</speaker>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Climene</hi> flyes me;</l>
                     <l>O lamentable deſtinie!</l>
                  </sp>
               </div>
               <div n="5" type="scene">
                  <head>SCENA QUINTA.</head>
                  <stage>Carlos, Frabitio.</stage>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Carlos.</speaker>
                     <p>FRiend, comfort thee.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Fabritio.</speaker>
                     <l>I am inconſolable,</l>
                     <l>And muſt die, <hi>Carlos,</hi> ſince I muſt abſent me.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Carlos.</speaker>
                     <l>Thou shalt be happier, if thou wilt heare me,</l>
                     <l>I have a meanes that thou shalt not depart,</l>
                     <l>And yet, in ſafetie too, shalt ſee <hi>Climene,</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>Alone, and without trouble.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Fabritio.</speaker>
                     <l>To abuſe</l>
                     <l>Thy friend, is but an odd way, in my judgment,</l>
                     <l>T'aſſiſt him, tis to aggravate my evill,</l>
                     <l>And not to heale it: is there any art</l>
                     <l>To tender me inviſible?</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Carlos.</speaker>
                     <l>For once then</l>
                     <l>Believe that I will doe for thee a thing</l>
                     <l>Which ſeemes impoſſible, give me leave to ſpeak</l>
                     <l>And in a moment thou shalt loſe thy griefe,</l>
                     <l>And thy aſtonishment: Thou knoweſt well</l>
                     <l>That <hi>Italie</hi> hath for a certaine time</l>
                     <l>Bene troubled with two factions, whoſe partakers</l>
                     <l>In everie citie name themſelves a loud</l>
                     <l>The <hi>Guelps</hi> and <hi>Gibelins:</hi> on this occaſion</l>
                     <pb n="22" facs="tcp:121249:12"/>
                     <l>My Father and <hi>Climenes</hi> 'gainſt each other</l>
                     <l>Took an immortall hatred; through their credit</l>
                     <l>And their condition, each made himſelfe</l>
                     <l>Head of a faction; the <hi>Duke</hi> receiving</l>
                     <l>Advertiſement thereof, and apprehending.</l>
                     <l>The iſſue of this enmity, ſo ſtronglie</l>
                     <l>Conceived, made them both to be arreſted,</l>
                     <l>Not withont, reaſon, and confined them</l>
                     <l>As priſoners, each one to his owne houſe.</l>
                     <l>My Father who ſaw his pretenſion vaine,</l>
                     <l>Knowing his houſe was neere unto the others,</l>
                     <l>Had recourſe unto cunning, and believed</l>
                     <l>That everie thing was lawfull to deſtroy</l>
                     <l>The greateſt of his enemies; to work then</l>
                     <l>His ruine, and in private too, he caus'd</l>
                     <l>A cloſe Mine to be digg'd even underneath</l>
                     <l>His adverſaries garden; being finish'd,</l>
                     <l>My Father fell ſick, and ſoone after dyed;</l>
                     <l>I was, as thou knowſt by the right of birth</l>
                     <l>Heire of his goods, and not of his revenge;</l>
                     <l>But though I should now have a hatred for</l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Climene,</hi> I should ſacrifice it wholie</l>
                     <l>Vnto thy love; in opening this Mine,</l>
                     <l>Thou may'ſt, without being ſeen, have eaſie acceſſe</l>
                     <l>Vnto thy Miſtreſſe, and to execute it</l>
                     <l>Securelie, we will make all men believe</l>
                     <l>That thou art gone.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Frabitio.</speaker>
                     <l>How infinitlie am I</l>
                     <l>Indebted to thee? how shall I acquit me?</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Carlos.</speaker>
                     <l>My friendship is offended verie much</l>
                     <l>At theſe expreſſions of acknowledgments.</l>
                     <l>I'le to the <hi>Duke</hi> expreſſie t'underſtand</l>
                     <l>What his intentions are concerning thee.</l>
                     <l>Enter into my houſe. — <stage>Exit Carlos.</stage>
                     </l>
                  </sp>
                  <pb n="23" facs="tcp:121249:12"/>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Fabritio.</speaker>
                     <l>I'le goe t'impart</l>
                     <l>This ſecret to <hi>Climene.</hi> But what heare I?</l>
                  </sp>
               </div>
               <div n="6" type="scene">
                  <head>SCENA SEXTA.</head>
                  <stage>The Duke, Valerio, Fabritio. Iacinta, Guards.</stage>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Duke.</speaker>
                     <p>Doe that which I commaunded.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <stage>Valerio knocks, at the dore of Climenes houſe.</stage>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Fabritio.</speaker>
                     <l>Tis the Duke.</l>
                     <l>Rage overcomes my reaſon.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Duke.</speaker>
                     <l>What averſenes</l>
                     <l>Soe'r <hi>Climene</hi> hath unto my flame</l>
                     <l>Some little hope yet flattereth my ſoule,</l>
                     <l>I've gain'd her woman; who hath promiſed</l>
                     <l>This night to bring me ptivatelie into</l>
                     <l>Her chamber, the dore openeth, <hi>Iacinta!</hi>
                     </l>
                  </sp>
                  <stage>Iacinta <hi>comming from</hi> Climene.</stage>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Iacinta</speaker>
                     <l>Yes everie thing ſucceedeth to your wish,</l>
                     <l>My Miſtreſſe is deceiv'd and takes you for</l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Fabritie,</hi> she commanded me to open</l>
                     <l>Without delay, her order doth excuſe me</l>
                     <l>In letting you to enter, loſe no time;</l>
                     <l>But I heare her deſcend, ſpeake not a word,</l>
                     <l>Without doubt, she'll miſtake her ſelfe.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Duke,</speaker>
                     <l>We will</l>
                     <l>Be cleer'd therein, let us approach a little.</l>
                  </sp>
               </div>
               <div n="7" type="scene">
                  <pb n="24" facs="tcp:121249:13"/>
                  <head>SCENA SEPTIMA.</head>
                  <stage>The Duke, Climene, Fabritio, Iacinta, Valerio, Guards.</stage>
                  <stage>
                     <hi>Climene addreſſing her ſelfe to the</hi> Duke <hi>and thinking to ſpeake to</hi> Fabritio.</stage>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Climene.</speaker>
                     <p>WHar would'ſt thou, my deare Lover?</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Fabritio.</speaker>
                     <l>Ha, deare Lover!</l>
                     <l>Heavens! what is this I heare!</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Climene.</speaker>
                     <l>I have cauſe, reallie,</l>
                     <l>To complaine of thee, could'ſt thou not one night</l>
                     <l>At my requeſt refraine my companie?</l>
                     <l>Yet I excuſe thee upon this preſumption</l>
                     <l>That who loves well is little Maſter of</l>
                     <l>Himſelfe, and can't deny but my charm'd ſoule</l>
                     <l>Complaines heere but of being too much lov'd.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Fabritio.</speaker>
                     <p>May I believe this? Heaven! am I enchanted?</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Climene</speaker>
                     <l>Thou need'ſt not doubt this truth; when I would be</l>
                     <l>Angry againſt thee, ſuddenlie I check</l>
                     <l>My ſelfe, and when my mouth accuſeth thee,</l>
                     <l>My ſoule defends thee.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Duke.</speaker>
                     <p>Fortunate <hi>Fabritio</hi> — <stage>a ſide</stage>
                     </p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Fabritio.</speaker>
                     <p>O happie Rivall! — <stage>a ſide.</stage>
                     </p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Climene.</speaker>
                     <p>Thou doſt know my love.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <pb n="25" facs="tcp:121249:13"/>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>FABRITIO.</speaker>
                     <p>I knew it ill. — <stage>a ſide</stage>
                     </p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>CLIMENE.</speaker>
                     <l>What! anſweareſt thou nothing?</l>
                     <l>Doubts thou my flame, or fearſt thou that another</l>
                     <l>More pleaſing object drives thee from my ſoul?</l>
                     <l>What ever happens, reſt thy ſelfe aſſur'd</l>
                     <l>That my loue and my life shall have one courſe,</l>
                     <l>And that it is impoſſible for me</l>
                     <l>No more to love thee.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>DUKE.</speaker>
                     <p>How unhappie am I? — <stage>aſide.</stage>
                     </p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>FABRITIO.</speaker>
                     <p>How miſerable am I? — <stage>aſide.</stage>
                     </p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>CLIMENE.</speaker>
                     <l>What obligeth thee</l>
                     <l>To murmur ſtill thus to thy ſelfe? muſt I</l>
                     <l>Confirme my love unto thee by ſome oathes?</l>
                     <l>If my flame for thee make not all my glorie,</l>
                     <l>If thou alone poſſeſſeſt not my heart,</l>
                     <l>And all my thoughts, let —</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>FABRITIO.</speaker>
                     <l>Sweare not ingrate full and perfidious Woman,</l>
                     <l>It needeth' not, I doe believe thy words.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>DUKE.</speaker>
                     <l>Thy death shall ſoone follow thy inſolence:</l>
                     <l>My Guards.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <stage>Fabritio flying.</stage>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>FABRITIO.</speaker>
                     <p>It is in vaine to make reſiſtance.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <stage>Valerio and the Guards goe after Fabritio.</stage>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>DUKE.</speaker>
                     <p>Purſue, and kill him.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>IACINTA.</speaker>
                     <p>Alas! I'm dead with feare.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>CLIMENE,</speaker>
                     <p>I faint, I faint, <hi>Iacinta,</hi> hould me up.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <pb n="26" facs="tcp:121249:14"/>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Duke.</speaker>
                     <l>Let him dye, tis but juſt, too great a merit</l>
                     <l>Is often a great crime, in ruining</l>
                     <l>This Rivall, I may gaine what <hi>I</hi> deſire;</l>
                     <l>And if he perish not, my hope muſt perish:</l>
                     <l>Let's ſee if the ſucceſſe anſweareth my wish.</l>
                  </sp>
               </div>
               <div n="8" type="scene">
                  <head>SCENA OCTAVA.</head>
                  <stage>Valerio, The Duke, Iacinta, Guards.</stage>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Valerio.</speaker>
                     <l>OH, Sir, tis done, he's dead, in vaine he did</l>
                     <l>Indeavour to defend himſelfe, he fell</l>
                     <l>Peirc'd with a thouſand mortall ſtroaks, his ſoul</l>
                     <l>Found overtures ynough to ſallie forth</l>
                     <l>His bloody body, covered o'r with wounds</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Iacinta.</speaker>
                     <p>Oh! ſtay Sir. —</p>
                     <stage>Comming forth of Climenes houſe.</stage>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Duke.</speaker>
                     <l>Thy cares are ſuperfluous.</l>
                     <l>I am reveng'd, <hi>laciuta,</hi> and <hi>Fabritio</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>Is dead.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Iacinta.</speaker>
                     <l>Oh if you love <hi>Climene,</hi> enter not</l>
                     <l>Into the houſe, she's ſcarce recovered yet</l>
                     <l>Of a great faintnes which ſeif d'on her ſpirits.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Duke.</speaker>
                     <l>The blood which I have shed, will coſt her teares,</l>
                     <l>I will not goe, to add unto her griefes,</l>
                     <l>But retire me, a while, in the meane time,</l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Valerio,</hi> let it be your charge to goe</l>
                     <l>Vnto <hi>Fabritios</hi> Father, to acquaint him</l>
                     <l>With his ſonnes death, and further let him know</l>
                     <l>That for his rash and ſawcy inſolence,</l>
                     <l>He hath receav'd but a juſt recompenſe.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <trailer>The End of the firſt Act.</trailer>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div n="2" type="act">
               <pb n="27" facs="tcp:121249:14"/>
               <head>AGTVS SECVNDVS</head>
               <div n="1" type="scene">
                  <head>SCENA PRIMA.</head>
                  <stage>Iſabella, Clarina, In a Chamber.</stage>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Iſabella.</speaker>
                     <p>WHo enters there?</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Clarina.</speaker>
                     <l>Madame, it is <hi>Valerio,</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>Who from the Duke Diſcourſeth with your Father</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Iſabella.</speaker>
                     <p>What preſſing buſines might bring him here?</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Clarina.</speaker>
                     <p>To tell you, I should be a Propheteſſe.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Iſabella.</speaker>
                     <l>A meſſage at this hower's not ordinarie.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Clarina.</speaker>
                     <p>It doth appeare as ſtrang to me, as you.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Iſabella.</speaker>
                     <l>Let us expect the iſſue on't, and change</l>
                     <l>Diſcourſe,</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Clarina.</speaker>
                     <l>You faine would have me ſpeak of <hi>Carlos;</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>Madame, confeſſe it.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Iſabella.</speaker>
                     <l>I cannot deny</l>
                     <l>But I am pleaſed, when I heare him prayſ'd.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Clarina.</speaker>
                     <l>I should not be in my right ſenſe if <hi>I</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>Should ſpeake ill of him, he is a brave man,</l>
                     <l>And of a Liberall and obliging nature,</l>
                     <l>He merits much.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Iſabella.</speaker>
                     <l>But in what manner did he enrertaine</l>
                     <l>Th' intelligence thou gav'ſt him that my h<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                           <desc>••</desc>
                        </gap> our</l>
                     <pb n="28" facs="tcp:121249:15"/>
                     <l>Towards him was inclined to more ſweetnes,</l>
                     <l>And that my heart at laſt diſp of d it ſelfe.</l>
                     <l>To love him?</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>CLARINA.</speaker>
                     <l>With tranſports, and extaſies,</l>
                     <l>Which cannot be expreſſ'd.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>ISABELLA.</speaker>
                     <l>Haſt thou bene careful</l>
                     <l>To tell him cunninglie, according to</l>
                     <l>Thoſe rules I gave thee, that to doe him ſervice</l>
                     <l>Thou didſt betray thy Miſtreſſe, and gav'ſt him</l>
                     <l>That notice without my conſent?</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>CLARINA.</speaker>
                     <l>Yes, Madame</l>
                     <l>I tould him ſo, and verie handſomlie;</l>
                     <l>But your ſtrang love ſurpriſeth me, you feare</l>
                     <l>that he should know it, and yet tell it him:</l>
                     <l>If he leſſe knew it, would you be more pleaſ'd?</l>
                     <l>What humourous fancies are in Lovers ſpirits?</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>ISABELLA.</speaker>
                     <l>Though I love <hi>Carlos,</hi> (be it reaſon, or</l>
                     <l>Fancie that guides me) I believe I doe</l>
                     <l>My ſelfe wrong, when I doe juſtice to him;</l>
                     <l>The hashfulnes which Heaven hath put into</l>
                     <l>Our Sex, for bids us to be free in what</l>
                     <l>Concernes the point of love; nor muſt we think</l>
                     <l>any thing lawfull in relation to't:</l>
                     <l>And by that power, which I know not my ſelfe,</l>
                     <l>I cannot without blushing ſay, I love:</l>
                     <l>It ſeemeth that our eyes made to tame hearts,</l>
                     <l>When thoſe that were our captives doe become</l>
                     <l>Our conquerours, although they finde the dart</l>
                     <l>Lovely and charming that ſubjected us,</l>
                     <l>Cannot without ſome shame, behould this change</l>
                     <l>The art to deſpiſe love, my heart no longer</l>
                     <l>Can practiſe, but o Heaven! whom ſee I Carlos?</l>
                     <l>So late here in my chamber.</l>
                  </sp>
               </div>
               <div n="2" type="scene">
                  <pb n="29" facs="tcp:121249:15"/>
                  <head>SCENA SECUNDA.</head>
                  <stage>CARLOS, ISABELLA, CLARINA.</stage>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>CARLOS.</speaker>
                     <l>PArdon me</l>
                     <l>This bold intruſion, ſeeing the dore open,</l>
                     <l>I could not but lay hould of the occaſion;</l>
                     <l>And following my love, I thought I might</l>
                     <l>With out offending you with diſreſpect</l>
                     <l>Enter, to caſt my ſelfe at your faire feet.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>ISABELLA.</speaker>
                     <l>How fancie you that I can be ſo little</l>
                     <l>Reſpectfull of my honour, as to ſuffer</l>
                     <l>A viſſit from you without being offended?</l>
                     <l>No, Sir, your hope deceives you, and this libertie</l>
                     <l>You take, denoteth in you little love,</l>
                     <l>Or too much Vanitie: can I believe</l>
                     <l>You love me well, in giving to your ſelfe</l>
                     <l>A licence thus to make foule-mouth'd detraction</l>
                     <l>Inveigh againſt me, or can you imagine,</l>
                     <l>Without great follie in your ſelfe, that I</l>
                     <l>Can approve this deſigne ſo little modeſt,</l>
                     <l>And not b'offended at it?</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>CARLOS.</speaker>
                     <l>Though I can</l>
                     <l>Produce ſome reaſon here for my defence,</l>
                     <l>I hould me criminall, ſince I offend you,</l>
                     <l>And should but little profit to perſiſt</l>
                     <l>In the opinion of my innocence</l>
                     <l>When your faire mouth condemnes me,</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>ISABELLA.</speaker>
                     <l>I condemne you,</l>
                     <pb n="30" facs="tcp:121249:16"/>
                     <l>Tis very true, and for your punishment</l>
                     <l>I bannish you; you muſt goe forth.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Carlos.</speaker>
                     <l>I dare not</l>
                     <l>Appeale upon your ſentence, but retire;</l>
                     <l>I obey with regreet, but without murmur.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Iſabella.</speaker>
                     <l>How Sir, begone ſo ſoone, what motives pray you,</l>
                     <l>Induce you thereunto?</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Carlos.</speaker>
                     <l>Since you ordaine it</l>
                     <l>I muſt depart, tis fitt that I obey you.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Iſabella.</speaker>
                     <l>I should think, Carlos, that you obey here</l>
                     <l>Some what too quickly for a perfect Lover:</l>
                     <l>Believing that you lov'd me, I appear'd</l>
                     <l>Too proud, and ſcornefull: t'is an aſſtir'd maxime.</l>
                     <l>That one loves coldly what he quitteth eaſily;</l>
                     <l>Love is but il expreſſed by reſpects;</l>
                     <l>Who readilie obeyes, knowes not to love</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Carlos.</speaker>
                     <l>I am aſtonished at this diſcourſe;</l>
                     <l>Can you Complaine, I quit you, <hi>Iſabella,</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>When I obey you gainſt my ſentiment</l>
                     <l>When my love glittereth in my ſubmiſſion,</l>
                     <l>And when by a kinde heat, which is not common,</l>
                     <l>My happines diſpleaſeth me, when it</l>
                     <l>Offendeth you? What would you then have ſaid,</l>
                     <l>If ſeeking onelie my owne ſarisfaction,</l>
                     <l>I had preferred my deſires and wishes</l>
                     <l>Before yours? in what manner can? I pleaſe you,</l>
                     <l>If in obeying you, I anger you.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Iſab</speaker>
                     <l>You argue too well for a <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 span">
                           <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                        </gap> love.</l>
                     <l>VVhere love is ſtrong, reaſon <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                           <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                        </gap> impotent;</l>
                     <l>The one can't be eſtablish'd, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                           <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                        </gap> the other</l>
                     <pb n="31" facs="tcp:121249:16"/>
                     <l>Subſiſts; ſometimes a mayd would be reſiſted,</l>
                     <l>And obſtinatelie lov'd gainſt her conſent;</l>
                     <l>And as her cloſe deſires are verie ſeldome</l>
                     <l>Expreſſ'd, she often ſpeaketh with intent</l>
                     <l>To meet a contradiction, and to be</l>
                     <l>Enforced unto that which she deſires:</l>
                     <l>According to this maxime, poſſibly,</l>
                     <l>I have on this occaſion diſcours'd</l>
                     <l>Conrrarie to my ſentiment, and perhaps,</l>
                     <l>I should be ſo farre from believing me</l>
                     <l>Injur'd thereby, that you would have oblig'd me,</l>
                     <l>In not obeying me.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Carlos.</speaker>
                     <l>I'm rap'd in pleaſant wonder, if thoſe words</l>
                     <l>Aſtonish me, they charme me more; if I</l>
                     <l>Muſt ſtay to pleaſe you, nothing is more eaſie,</l>
                     <l>Then to content you fully in that point:</l>
                     <l>Seeing obedience is not pleaſing to you;</l>
                     <l>I will ſtay, Madame, and will not obey.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Iſabella.</speaker>
                     <l>It is too late; begone, my mind is chang'd;</l>
                     <l>Occaſion is loſt aſſoone as' paſſ'd;</l>
                     <l>You would have too much pride, and I ſhould have</l>
                     <l>Too little, if after ſuch a confeſſion</l>
                     <l>I should detaine you here.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Carlos.</speaker>
                     <l>This order is</l>
                     <l>Severe and rigourous.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Iſabella.</speaker>
                     <l>But it is juſt:</l>
                     <l>I love not alwaies to be disobey'd.</l>
                     <l>Follow <hi>Clarina,</hi> goe, and have a care</l>
                     <l>You be not ſeen. O Heaven! I heare my Father.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Clarina.</speaker>
                     <l>Alas! we are undone; perhaps, he doubted</l>
                     <pb n="32" facs="tcp:121249:17"/>
                     <l>Of your intelligence, enter forthwith</l>
                     <l>Into this cloſet.</l>
                  </sp>
               </div>
               <div n="3" type="scene">
                  <head>SCENA TERTIA.</head>
                  <stage>Alphonſo, Clarina, Iſabella.</stage>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>ALPHONSO.</speaker>
                     <p>Oh Daughter, daughter!</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>ISABELLA,</speaker>
                     <l>He appeareth furious. — <stage>a ſide.</stage>
                     </l>
                     <l>I read my ſad misfortune in his eyes.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>ALPHONSO</speaker>
                     <p>Can I live after ſuch high injuries?</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>ISABELLA.</speaker>
                     <p>What is the Matter, Sir?</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>ALPHONSO.</speaker>
                     <l>How! demandeſt thou?</l>
                     <l>Doſt thou not plainelie ſee in the exceſſe</l>
                     <l>Of my quick griefes, that I am burthered with</l>
                     <l>The greateſt of misfortunes?</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>ISABELLA.</speaker>
                     <l>What miffortune.</l>
                     <l>Oh! Father?</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>ALPHONSO.</speaker>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Iſabella, Iſabella,</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>I muſt no more be called by that name.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>ISABELLA,</speaker>
                     <p>I feign'd in vaine, tis beſt to confeſſe all.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>ALPHONSO.</speaker>
                     <p>O fatall chang. Heaven, who could'er have thought it?</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>ISABELLA.</speaker>
                     <p>Sir, I beſeech you, heare me</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>ALPHONSO.</speaker>
                     <l>What would'ſt thou</l>
                     <pb n="33" facs="tcp:121249:17"/>
                     <l>That I should heare, I know now but to well</l>
                     <l>What that love coſteth me which taketh pleaſure</l>
                     <l>In blood and teares, and hideth deadlie poiſons,</l>
                     <l>When it shewes flowers.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Iſabella.</speaker>
                     <p>I confeſſe —</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Alphonſo.</speaker>
                     <l>Oh how often.</l>
                     <l>Our expectations are deceiv'd, in'wishing</l>
                     <l>Children, we wish troubles, and punishments.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Iſab.</speaker>
                     <p>If his death</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Alph.</speaker>
                     <p>Yes, his death is certaine,</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Iſabella.</speaker>
                     <l>Suffer</l>
                     <l>That by my teares —</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Alphonſo.</speaker>
                     <p>Thou sheddeſt them in vaine.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Iſabella.</speaker>
                     <p>Father, revenge is eaſie.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Alphonſo.</speaker>
                     <l>But alas?</l>
                     <l>What should I enterpriſe againſt the Duke?</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Iſabella.</speaker>
                     <p>The Duke? What ſay you?</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Alphonſo.</speaker>
                     <l>Art thou ignorant,</l>
                     <l>That my ſonne by his order receiv'd death?</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Iſabella.</speaker>
                     <p>I know it not; oh miſerable deſtinie?</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Alphonſo.</speaker>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Valerio</hi> from him brought me the ſad newes,</l>
                     <l>And would enforce me to agree with him,</l>
                     <l>That he in killing him did not unjuſtly:</l>
                  </sp>
                  <pb n="34" facs="tcp:121249:18"/>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Iſabella.</speaker>
                     <l>What crueltie is this? waſt not ynough,</l>
                     <l>Through an unjuſt and barbarous conſtraint,</l>
                     <l>To forbid you a juſt revenge, but even</l>
                     <l>To complaine of the injurie?</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Alphonſo.</speaker>
                     <l>True, Daughter;</l>
                     <l>To punish yet my ſonne after his death,</l>
                     <l>They will I underſtand it, and not murmur:</l>
                     <l>It ſeemes they have a minde, that I should goe</l>
                     <l>To kiſſe the hand that murthets me, as being</l>
                     <l>Stained, and ſmoaking yet writh my ſonnes blood.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Iſabella.</speaker>
                     <l>But Sir, conſider in this ſad conjuncture,</l>
                     <l>That my deare Brothers body doth expect</l>
                     <l>Interment.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Alphonſo.</speaker>
                     <l>Yes, I have tooke care for that,</l>
                     <l>By order from me it is to be brought</l>
                     <l>To this apart ement.</l>
                  </sp>
               </div>
               <div n="4" type="scene">
                  <head>SCENA QUINTA.</head>
                  <stage>Licaſtes, Alpbonſo, Iſabella. Clarma.</stage>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Licaſles.</speaker>
                     <l>THe death, Sir, of your ſonne is but to certaine</l>
                     <l>W'ave brought his body into the next cha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ber.</l>
                     <l>Some little diſtance from this place we found it</l>
                     <l>Stript, and ſo much disfigured with wounds,</l>
                     <l>That we should not have judg'd it to be his,</l>
                     <l>If ſeeking carefully we had not found</l>
                     <l>His coate not farre of, and a little further</l>
                     <l>His hart: The thing which troubleth me moſt</l>
                     <l>In this miſfortune is, that having made</l>
                     <l>A fruitles ſearch all over for the reſt</l>
                     <pb n="35" facs="tcp:121249:18" rendition="simple:additions"/>
                     <l>Of his habillements, I could not finde</l>
                     <l>Any one of them, and can not imagine</l>
                     <l>Who should have tane them thence.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Alphonſo.</speaker>
                     <l>Vnhappie Sonne</l>
                     <l>Of an unfortunate Father!</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Licaſtes.</speaker>
                     <l>Sir, you may</l>
                     <l>From hence ſee this ſad object, if you pleaſe</l>
                     <l>To cauſe that curtaine to be drawn aſide.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Alphonſo.</speaker>
                     <l>Draw it, <hi>Licaſtes,</hi> let me ſee my ſorrow;</l>
                     <l>We would be private, everie one retire.</l>
                     <stage>The curtaine is drawne, and he ſets upon a bed a murthered body.</stage>
                     <l>I cannot in this Lamentable object</l>
                     <l>Diſcerne one ſeature of my Sonne, and ſcarce</l>
                     <l>Will my confuſion give me leave to know</l>
                     <l>Him whom I have begotten, lying thus</l>
                     <l>In ſuch a mangled condition.</l>
                     <l>Sonne, if it may be lawfull in the ſad</l>
                     <l>Eſtate wherein our miſeries have put us</l>
                     <l>For me to uſe that name ſometime ſo ſweet,</l>
                     <l>I muſt then ſay unto thee, that this ſpectacle</l>
                     <l>Makes me to feel thy wounds more ſenſibly</l>
                     <l>Then thou thy ſelfe didſt when thou didſt receive them:</l>
                     <l>Thy miſerable deſtinie and mine</l>
                     <l>Differs not much, the blood which thou shed'ſt is</l>
                     <l>The pureſt in my veines, the arme whoſe rigour</l>
                     <l>Haſted thy death, gave not the fatall ſtroak</l>
                     <l>Through thy heart, but it entered in my bowells:</l>
                     <l>And if we differ any thing in ſuch</l>
                     <l>A miſerable fortune, tis in this,</l>
                     <l>That I ſtill feel the preſſing evills, which thou</l>
                     <l>Suffereſt no more. Sources of my afflictions,</l>
                     <pb n="36" facs="tcp:121249:19"/>
                     <l>Deepe wounds, which appeare now but bloody mouths,</l>
                     <l>Whoſe ſilent accents ſeeme here to foliſſit</l>
                     <l>My arme to a reveng, know that a ſubject</l>
                     <l>Houlds not his Soveraignes fate betwene his ha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ds:</l>
                     <l>In vaine ye aske reveng' gainſt ſuch a blood;</l>
                     <l>Alas here I can offer you no other,</l>
                     <l>But what my heart makes to flow from mine eyes.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Iſabella.</speaker>
                     <p>The crueltie o'th' Duke, Sir, should be punish'd.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Alphonſo.</speaker>
                     <l>He is my Prince, although in my concernement</l>
                     <l>A tyrant, ſubjects deſtinies depend</l>
                     <l>Vpon their Soveraignes, a crime becomes</l>
                     <l>Iuſt in their hands; and if at any time</l>
                     <l>Thoſe earthlie Gods ought to be punished',</l>
                     <l>It muſt be by a thunder bolt from Heaven:</l>
                     <l>In this caſe I should make but vaine attempts.</l>
                     <l>If the Duke dye, shall my Sonne live againe?</l>
                     <l>But what chance brings <hi>Clarina</hi> here in ſuch</l>
                     <l>Diſtracted haſte?</l>
                  </sp>
               </div>
               <div n="5" type="scene">
                  <head>SCENA QUINTA.</head>
                  <stage>Clarina, Alphonſo, Iſabella.</stage>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Clarina.</speaker>
                     <p>Oh Signeur, oh Madame! —</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Alphonſo.</speaker>
                     <p>VVhat ayles thee, art thou mad?</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Clarina.</speaker>
                     <p>Oh, I have ſeene —</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Alphonſo.</speaker>
                     <p>What haſt thou ſeene that troubleth thee ſo much?</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Clarina.</speaker>
                     <p>I have ſeene, I have ſeene —</p>
                  </sp>
                  <pb n="37" facs="tcp:121249:19"/>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Alphonſo.</speaker>
                     <l>VVhat haſt thou ſeene?</l>
                     <l>Speake, I conjure thee.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Clarina.</speaker>
                     <l>Since then I muſt ſpeake it,</l>
                     <l>I've ſeene a dead man walke.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Alphonſo.</speaker>
                     <p>Th'aſt loſt thy reaſon.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Clarina.</speaker>
                     <l>Nothing's more true, that fearefull Fantaſme fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowes</l>
                     <l>My ſteps, I heare him, he purſues me; ſave me.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Iſabella.</speaker>
                     <p>It is my Brother —</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Alphonſo.</speaker>
                     <p>Straung! It is my Sonne.</p>
                  </sp>
               </div>
               <div n="6" type="scene">
                  <head>SCENA SEXTA.</head>
                  <stage>Alphonſo, Fabritio, Iſabella.</stage>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Alphonſo.</speaker>
                     <l>Sonne, is my ſoule ſure, or am I deceiv'd,</l>
                     <l>Is this but an illuſion which I ſee</l>
                     <l>But a vaine object formed by my fancy?</l>
                     <l>If ſo, finish my life heere with my errour?</l>
                     <l>Mayſt thou yet be i'th' number of the living?</l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Fabritio,</hi> iſt thy body that I ſee</l>
                     <l>Or iſt thy shadow? comeſt thou to fill me</l>
                     <l>With joy, or with affright? come ſatisfie me.</l>
                     <l>Let me embrace thee.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Fabritio.</speaker>
                     <l>I ſee the light, Sir, and I finde here charms,</l>
                     <l>Since you eſteeme my life at ſuch a rate</l>
                     <l>As to lament it loſt; not but as injur'd</l>
                     <l>By love and fortune, they should not doe to me</l>
                     <l>A favour to deprive me of the light;</l>
                     <pb n="38" facs="tcp:121249:20"/>
                     <l>But though they should oblige me very much,</l>
                     <l>In the condition wherein my ſoule</l>
                     <l>Is now, to quench my feirce flame with my blood,</l>
                     <l>And though my blood thus shed would make my fortune,</l>
                     <l>More ſweet, I would conſerve it, ſince tis yours.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Alphonſo.</speaker>
                     <l>How comes it that thou haſt ſo ſtrong a hatred</l>
                     <l>For life? thou canſt not doubt Climenes love;</l>
                     <l>The paſſion of the Duke alarumes thee</l>
                     <l>Too much; if thou lou'ſt much, thou art no leſſe</l>
                     <l>Belou'd.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Fabritio.</speaker>
                     <l>A faire appearance oftentimes</l>
                     <l>Beareth falſe wittnes, I aſſur'd my ſelfe</l>
                     <l>Too much of her ſidelitie, and though</l>
                     <l>I could doubt the report my ſenſes made me,</l>
                     <l>I have too ſure a teſtimonie of her</l>
                     <l>Perfidiouſnes, ſince her owne mouth confirm'd it:</l>
                     <l>She entertain'd in amourous diſcourſe</l>
                     <l>My happie Rivall with ſo paſſionate</l>
                     <l>An air, that I forgate both my reſpect</l>
                     <l>Vnto the <hi>Duke,</hi> and the care of my life,</l>
                     <l>In uttering my deſpight; the <hi>Duke</hi> poſſeſſ'd.</l>
                     <l>Strongly with love and hate, gave expreſſe order</l>
                     <l>Vnto his Guards to kill me; but I knowing</l>
                     <l>That my defence then was unprofitable,</l>
                     <l>Vnder a dark porch ſought my ſanctuarie,</l>
                     <l>Whilſt an unfortunate ſtranger walking that way</l>
                     <l>They took to apprehend me in the darke,</l>
                     <l>Was ſuddenlie environ'd with the Guards,</l>
                     <l>And peirced through with halbards, aſſoone as</l>
                     <l>Thoſe murtherers were gone, to draw my life</l>
                     <l>Out of ſuch hazards, and to make this errour</l>
                     <l>More probable, I took the bloodie cloaths</l>
                     <l>Of that deplorable body, and was readie</l>
                     <pb n="39" facs="tcp:121249:20"/>
                     <l>To leave it mine, having caſt his into</l>
                     <l>The current of the river, when a noyſe</l>
                     <l>Of voices croſſing my deſigne, I was</l>
                     <l>Conſtrain'd to leave that body naked and</l>
                     <l>Without life, to come ſpeedilie to you,</l>
                     <l>And to advertiſe you of this event.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Alphonſo.</speaker>
                     <l>I feare the iſſue of this bleſt ſuccſſe;</l>
                     <l>Know that the Duke boaſts of thy death alreadie,</l>
                     <l>He thinkes it juſt, which maketh me to judge</l>
                     <l>That thy preſerved life is ſtill in danger;</l>
                     <l>If thou deſireſt to obey thy Father,</l>
                     <l>Stay not a minute here, but ſeek thy ſafety</l>
                     <l>In ſudden abſence,</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Fabritio.</speaker>
                     <l>But What! muſt I leave</l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Climene?</hi>
                     </l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Alphonſo.</speaker>
                     <l>She hath left thee, her example</l>
                     <l>Shewes thee the way to infidelitie;</l>
                     <l>If to betray a perſon that doth love us</l>
                     <l>Be a baſe act, to love one that betrayes us.</l>
                     <l>Is no leſſe weaknes.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Fabritio.</speaker>
                     <l>I am ſtil a Lovet,</l>
                     <l>Though an abuſed Lover, and she hath.</l>
                     <l>More beautie then injuſtice, her crime puts</l>
                     <l>No fearful object in her eyes and countenance,</l>
                     <l>Although she ceaſe to love, she ceaſeth not</l>
                     <l>To be belov'd, and my heart charm'd by her,</l>
                     <l>Deceives it ſelfe, if it thinks to be able</l>
                     <l>To hate her, though she hath betrayed it.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Alphonſo.</speaker>
                     <l>I finde that abſence is the onelie remedie</l>
                     <l>For this diſeaſe, tis fitt thy paſſion yeild</l>
                     <l>To my deſires; fly through obedience,</l>
                     <pb n="40" facs="tcp:121249:21"/>
                     <l>Or through reſentment, oh aſſure thy ſafety</l>
                     <l>By thy remove, tis that which Ideſire.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Fabritio.</speaker>
                     <p>And which I feare.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Alphonſo.</speaker>
                     <p>That matters not.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Fabritio.</speaker>
                     <p>But Sir —</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Alphonſo.</speaker>
                     <l>But I command it thee: for feare to be</l>
                     <l>Perceiv'd, goe forth without attendance and</l>
                     <l>Without noyſe unto Carlos houſe, and there</l>
                     <l>Paſſe the reſt of the night; to morrow earlie</l>
                     <l>Before the day break, take the way to <hi>Florence,</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>VVhere I have many Frie<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ds that will defend thee.</l>
                     <l>In the meane time I'le ſend thee by a friend</l>
                     <l>A horſe and money for thy journey; haſte.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Fabritio.</speaker>
                     <p>My Siſter.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Alphonſo.</speaker>
                     <l>Add not to my miſerie</l>
                     <l>By ſad regretts: be gone, be gone; adiew;</l>
                     <l>Let me embrace thee, I deprive my ſelfe</l>
                     <l>Of my moſt deare ſupport, but though I loſe thee,</l>
                     <l>Tis with intent to ſave thee. — <stage>Exit Fabritio.</stage>
                     </l>
                  </sp>
               </div>
               <div n="7" type="scene">
                  <head>SCENA SEPTIMA.</head>
                  <stage>ALPHONSO, ISABELLA.</stage>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Iſabella.</speaker>
                     <l>By what crueltie</l>
                     <l>Banish you my deare Brother?</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Alphonſo.</speaker>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Iſabella,</hi>
                     </l>
                     <pb n="41" facs="tcp:121249:21"/>
                     <l>Thou ſpeakeſt like a Siſter, and I act</l>
                     <l>As Father, it is farre more pleaſing to me</l>
                     <l>To have an abſent Sonne, then none at all:</l>
                     <l>I will deceive the Duke by taking of</l>
                     <l>His unjuſt purſuit gainſt his life, when he</l>
                     <l>Shall fully underſtand his death: I will</l>
                     <l>To morrow that my houſe be all in mourning,</l>
                     <l>That this corps be interred for my Sonne;</l>
                     <l>And to the end that all <hi>Ferrara</hi> be</l>
                     <l>Deceived with the Duke, I'le honour it</l>
                     <l>VVith funerall pompe, this is a debt we owe.</l>
                     <l>Vnto a blood, whoſe loſſe hath conſerv'd ours,</l>
                     <l>Although we had no further uſe of it.</l>
                     <l>Laſtly —</l>
                  </sp>
               </div>
               <div n="8" type="scene">
                  <head>SCENA OCTAVO.</head>
                  <stage>Fabritio, Alphonſo, Iſabella.</stage>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Fabritio.</speaker>
                     <p>S<hi rend="sup">Ir</hi> —</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Alphonſo.</speaker>
                     <p>VVhat is it that troubles thee?</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Fabritio.</speaker>
                     <l>I met the Duke, Sir, at our dore, he follow'd</l>
                     <l>A torch, which might, perhaps, diſcover me,</l>
                     <l>I heare noiſe, he purſues me, oh receive him,</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Alphonſo.</speaker>
                     <l>O duty too unjuſt! cruel conſtraint!</l>
                     <l>Goe quicklie with thy Siſter <hi>Iſabella</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>Intothat cloſet.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Iſabella.</speaker>
                     <p>He goes to Carlos houſe, what shall I doe?</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Fabritio.</speaker>
                     <l>Come along with me, what should hinder you?</l>
                  </sp>
                  <pb n="42" facs="tcp:121249:22"/>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Iſabella.</speaker>
                     <l>I feare you should be ſeene, and there fore would</l>
                     <l>That the light might be put out in this place.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Fabritio.</speaker>
                     <p>I contradict not, les us enter then.</p>
                  </sp>
               </div>
               <div n="9" type="scene">
                  <head>SCENA NONA.</head>
                  <stage>Carlos <hi>comming out of the cloſet.</hi>
                  </stage>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Carlos.</speaker>
                     <l>They are both entered, I muſt quickly forth:</l>
                     <l>Fortune no longer ſeemeth to be contrarie</l>
                     <l>To my deſignes; the way is free; but what!</l>
                     <l>I heare the Fathers voice: oh how unhappie</l>
                     <l>Am I?</l>
                  </sp>
               </div>
               <div n="10" type="scene">
                  <head>SCENA DECIMA.</head>
                  <stage>The Duke, Valerio, Alphonſo, Carlos, Guards.</stage>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Duke.</speaker>
                     <l>
                        <hi>ALphonſo,</hi> I am not deceiv'd,</l>
                     <l>Your ſone is Living, I have ſeene him: having</l>
                     <l>Vnderſtood, that <hi>Climene</hi> in a ſoowne</l>
                     <l>Fainted, being carefull of ſo faire a life,</l>
                     <l>And guided by my love, I went unto</l>
                     <l>Her houſe, where happilie I ſaw your ſonne:</l>
                     <l>I know that she adores him, and dare ſay</l>
                     <l>That her diſeaſe wil Vanish, if he Lives:</l>
                     <l>Laſtly I wish it, and am come of purpoſe</l>
                     <l>To be informed cleerelie of this truth.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <stage>Alphonſo shewing the Duke the body which is upon the bed.</stage>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Alphonſo.</speaker>
                     <l>SIr, you may eaſilie be cleerd herin;</l>
                     <l>Behould my ſonne, judge if his loſſe be certaine:</l>
                     <pb n="43" facs="tcp:121249:22"/>
                     <l>You fear'd him living, doe not feare him dead.</l>
                     <l>See, his congealed blood fmoaks at your preſen<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                           <desc>••</desc>
                        </gap>
                     </l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Duke.</speaker>
                     <l>It is too much, I'm fullie ſatisfied</l>
                     <l>That he is dead; but what did <hi>Carlos</hi> heere</l>
                     <l>Without light?</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Carlos.</speaker>
                     <l>To ſecure my Friend, I muſt</l>
                     <l>Feign hand ſomlie — <stage>aſide,</stage>
                     </l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Duke.</speaker>
                     <p>He ſeemes to be aſtonish'd.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Carlos.</speaker>
                     <l>Sir, tis not without cauſe that I am ſo.</l>
                     <l>For comming here to underſtand the newes</l>
                     <l>of my deare Friend <hi>Fabritios</hi> deſtinie,</l>
                     <l>Aſſoone as I entered that open chamber,</l>
                     <l>His Ghoſt appear'd before me in a poſture</l>
                     <l>So dreadfull, that I tremble to thinke on't:</l>
                     <l>He had the figure of a fearefull <hi>Fantaſme,</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>His boſom was opened with a large wound,</l>
                     <l>His colour pale, and all his bod, bloodie.</l>
                     <l>He came towards me with a ſtaggering pace,</l>
                     <l>And darted forth a look though languishing</l>
                     <l>Yet feirce; a bleak, and black blood iſſued</l>
                     <l>Out of his mouth, and in his eyes grim death</l>
                     <l>Walked the round.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Duke.</speaker>
                     <l>I alſo ſaw juſt now</l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Fabritios</hi> shape, but much leſſe horrible,</l>
                     <l>Mc thought he was allve.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Carlos.</speaker>
                     <l>I dare engage</l>
                     <l>My credit, that your Highneſſe ſaw his shadow</l>
                     <l>Aſwell as I.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <pb n="44" facs="tcp:121249:23"/>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Duke.</speaker>
                     <l>Tis that which doth confound me.</l>
                     <l>I ſtill held for a fable what the vulgar</l>
                     <l>Report, of vaine ghoſtes, and could not imagine</l>
                     <l>That a ſpirit once departed from a body,</l>
                     <l>Should leave the dead to come among the living,</l>
                     <l>Ceaſe to be ſimple, and be viſible,</l>
                     <l>Having no more a body. Notwithſtanding</l>
                     <l>This ſucceſſ ſtattles me, I could not think it,</l>
                     <l>And now I cannot doubt it. But adiew,</l>
                     <l>I ſee your griefe encreaſeth by my preſence.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Alphonſo.</speaker>
                     <p>Sir, I waite on you.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Duke.</speaker>
                     <l>I know what is a Farher, and that nature</l>
                     <l>VVill not allow him to pay homadges</l>
                     <l>To him that lobbs him of a Sonne— <stage>Exit Duke.</stage>
                     </l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Alphonſo.</speaker>
                     <l>How highly —</l>
                     <l>Am I indebled to you for this favour? — <stage>To Carlos</stage>
                     </l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Carlos.</speaker>
                     <l>It is not great; twere requiſire <hi>Fabritio</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>Should inſtantlie betake him to my houſe,</l>
                     <l>From whence he may unſeene make his eſcape,</l>
                     <l>I'le goe unto the Duke now, to confirme him</l>
                     <l>Yet ſtronger in his errour. — <stage>Exit Carlos.</stage>
                     </l>
                  </sp>
               </div>
               <div n="11" type="scene">
                  <head>SCENA UNDECIMA.</head>
                  <stage>Alfonſo, Fabritio, Iſabella.</stage>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Alphonſo.</speaker>
                     <l>Goe, and chuſe</l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Florence</hi> to morrow for retraite.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <pb n="45" facs="tcp:121249:23"/>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Fabritio.</speaker>
                     <p>Sir —</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Alphonſo.</speaker>
                     <l>Let me</l>
                     <l>Receive no more replyes, doe what I bid thee,</l>
                     <l>All my deſires should be ſtrong lawes to thee,</l>
                     <l>A diew, let me give thee the laſt embrace.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Iſabella.</speaker>
                     <l>Sir, notwithſtanding all your care, I feare</l>
                     <l>My brother can't ſubmit himſelfe unto</l>
                     <l>This ſevere order; by his laſt diſcourſe</l>
                     <l>I comprehended too well that he loves</l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Climene</hi> ſtill after all her contempts,</l>
                     <l>And that his blinded ſoule is ſtill reſolv'd</l>
                     <l>To loſe all, rather then to loſe her ſight.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Alphonſo.</speaker>
                     <l>I will be ſatisfied heerin, and know</l>
                     <l>The meanes to doe it, faile not thou to morrow</l>
                     <l>Towards the evening to goe to Climene:</l>
                     <l>The evill, that hath ſurpriſed her, invites thee</l>
                     <l>Vnto this Duty; for my part, I wil</l>
                     <l>Make Carlos a viſſit at that time:</l>
                     <l>If my ſonne ſtayes, I doubt not but to ſinde him</l>
                     <l>In one or to ther houſe; but it is late,</l>
                     <l>Adiew, in humane Fortune give unto thee</l>
                     <l>As much reſt, as I have unquietnes,</l>
                     <l>And trouble at my heart. — <stage>Exit Alphonſo.</stage>
                     </l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Iſabella.</speaker>
                     <l>Las! mine doth bleed</l>
                     <l>With double griefe, though the firſt wound be hid,</l>
                  </sp>
                  <trailer>The End of the Second Act.</trailer>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div n="3" type="act">
               <pb n="46" facs="tcp:121249:24"/>
               <head>ACTVS TERTIVS,</head>
               <div n="1" type="scene">
                  <head>SCENA PRIMA.</head>
                  <stage>The Duke, Jacinta, in Climenes Garden.</stage>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Iacinta.</speaker>
                     <l>THis is the Garden, Sir, where preſently</l>
                     <l>My miſtreſſe comes to walke her melancholie:</l>
                     <l>The griefe she taketh for her Lovers loſſe.</l>
                     <l>And her decayed health diſtracts her judgment;</l>
                     <l>Although the danger of her maladie</l>
                     <l>Be great, she walkes, and would even fly herſelfe.</l>
                     <l>Be you aſſur'd her griefes will ſuddenlie</l>
                     <l>Conduct her here to weep her ſad misfortunes,</l>
                     <l>And you may ſee her without witneſſes,</l>
                     <l>And without trouble, if your Highnes pleaſe</l>
                     <l>To fetch a turne or two in this cloſe Alley.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Duke.</speaker>
                     <l>Thy care augments my trouble, not my hope;</l>
                     <l>I burne, and feare to ſee her equallie:</l>
                     <l>I burne to ſee her when I repreſent</l>
                     <l>Vnto my amourous ſoule a charming Image</l>
                     <l>With all its beauties, and I feare to ſee her,</l>
                     <l>When my ſad fancie repreſents unto me</l>
                     <l>The rigour of thoſe faire offended eyes:</l>
                     <l>Tis an undoubted truth, I feare to ſee</l>
                     <l>That faire afflicted one to reproach me</l>
                     <l>The evills wherin my flame hath plunged her,</l>
                     <l>To ſay that hatred is the onelie fruite</l>
                     <l>Of my addreſſes, and that with my Rivall</l>
                     <l>My ſpirit is deſtroy'd.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Iacinta.</speaker>
                     <l>Your Highneſſe, Sir</l>
                     <l>Should be prepar'd againſt the bloody taunts</l>
                     <pb n="47" facs="tcp:121249:24"/>
                     <l>Of a beblubbered Miſtreſſe: to ſpeak truelie,</l>
                     <l>And not to flatter you, I cannot ſee</l>
                     <l>The leaſt hope that she will be wrought to love you</l>
                     <l>By this ſweet way you take; I should adviſe you</l>
                     <l>Vnto another courſe, make uſe of force,</l>
                     <l>Where kindnes cannot work; ravish a good.</l>
                     <l>Which is denyed to you; take her hence,</l>
                     <l>Who is ſo foolish and ſo rigourous,</l>
                     <l>And force her to be happie gainſt her will.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Duke.</speaker>
                     <l>How, take her hence by force? oh no, I cannot</l>
                     <l>Conſent unto it, force can never be</l>
                     <l>Compatible with love, I would be lov'd</l>
                     <l>Without conſtraint, and cherish'd with out feare.</l>
                     <l>So farre would her diſdaine be by this meanes</l>
                     <l>From ceaſing, that it would take deeper roote,</l>
                     <l>As having juſter ground to propagate.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Iacinta.</speaker>
                     <l>Your reaſons are not altogeither lawfull;</l>
                     <l>Our Sex, Sir, hath ſtrang maximes, oftentimes</l>
                     <l>It feeles not what it doth expreſſe, and ſeldome</l>
                     <l>Loveth <hi>Deaths</hi> fatall wracks, after a fortune</l>
                     <l>Of ſuch a nature, love in womans heart</l>
                     <l>Turnes unto griefe, and that griefe vanisheth:</l>
                     <l>Her oaths and cries are of no conſequence,</l>
                     <l>Her paſſion dies, when th' object is no more.</l>
                     <l>Perhaps, <hi>Climene</hi> at this verie hower,</l>
                     <l>Feeles that ambition from loves ashes ſprings</l>
                     <l>Within her heart, and that she is prepar'd,</l>
                     <l>In ſpight of her juſt mourning to proferre</l>
                     <l>The glorious poſſeſſour of a throne</l>
                     <l>Before the ſad in habitant of a tomb.</l>
                     <l>And, poſſibly, wearied with her affliction,</l>
                     <l>She would be forced to embrace your love.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Duke.</speaker>
                     <l>To take her hence, and force her unto marriage,</l>
                     <pb n="48" facs="tcp:121249:25"/>
                     <l>Are the laſt meanes which I will try; before</l>
                     <l>I uſe towards her the leaſt violence,</l>
                     <l>I'le ſee her.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Iacinta.</speaker>
                     <p>Sir, she comes there.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Duke.</speaker>
                     <l>How she ſtudies,</l>
                     <l>And how her ſlow uncertaine paces ſpeak</l>
                     <l>The violent troubles of her ſpirit, her palenes</l>
                     <l>Depaints her griefe.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Climene.</speaker>
                     <l>Leave me alone, and paſſe</l>
                     <l>Into that alley.</l>
                  </sp>
               </div>
               <div n="2" type="scene">
                  <head>SCENA SECVNDA,</head>
                  <stage>Climéné, Jacinta, The Duke.</stage>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Iacinta.</speaker>
                     <p>Madame, —</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Climene.</speaker>
                     <l>Once againe</l>
                     <l>I ſay I will be private for a minute;</l>
                     <l>Retire, and leave me to my ſelfe.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Iacinta.</speaker>
                     <l>But if</l>
                     <l>The Duke. —</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Climene.</speaker>
                     <l>Be gone, and ſpeak no more of him,</l>
                     <l>His name is odious to me.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Duke.</speaker>
                     <l>How unfortunate</l>
                     <l>Am I?</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Iacinta.</speaker>
                     <l>I tould you, ſweetnes would doe nothing</l>
                     <l>Vpon that ſtubborne ſpirit.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <pb n="49" facs="tcp:121249:25"/>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Duke.</speaker>
                     <l>I will follow</l>
                     <l>Thy counſell, let us ſpeedilie goe forth.</l>
                     <l>My preſence would encreaſe her crueltie.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Iacinta.</speaker>
                     <l>For feare you should be ſeene, be pleas'd to ſtay</l>
                     <l>Till she goes in; till when I cannot hand ſonelie</l>
                     <l>Draw you from hence; in the meane time your Highnes</l>
                     <l>May in thoſe shadie walkes divert your ſadnes.</l>
                  </sp>
               </div>
               <div n="3" type="scene">
                  <head>SCENA TERTIA.</head>
                  <stage>Climene alone.</stage>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Stanzas.</speaker>
                     <l>
                        <hi>THou which they ſay canſt with facilitie</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Act what inclndes impoſſibilitie,</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Blind Guide, falſe Child which canſt have no pretence</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>At all unto the ſtate of innocence,</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Tyrant of hearts, Love, wich haſt boaſted ſtill</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>That Death ſubmitts unto thy power and will.</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Make her to know that the muades thy right</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>In robbing my</hi> Fabritio <hi>of the light</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>And cauſe him to returne againe, or give</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Me paſſeport the Shades where he doth live.</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>The ſweeteſt objects that now ſtrike mine eyes,</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Encreaſe the number of my miſeries,</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>The Suune tells me</hi> Fabritio's <hi>but a ſhade,</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>The Lillies at his loſſe look black and fade,</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Thoſe Roſe, Queen of the flowers, ſeemes to be</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Stain'd with my Lovers blood, and neepes with me.</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Deare Lover, thou ſad object of my cries,</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Whoſe image still dwells in my heart and eyes,</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Reproach me not that I live yet to mourne,</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>After thy ashes ſleep in their cold vrne,</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Death without doubt are now had joyned me</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>To thy ſad shadovv, if</hi> I <hi>could agree</hi>
                     </l>
                     <pb n="50" facs="tcp:121249:26"/>
                     <l>
                        <hi>That thou shouldſt dye within my heart, oh no</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>I cannot leave th'y adored Image goe.</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Thy cruell Rivall when he murthered thee</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>In his conceit, miſtook, and murthered me:</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>His furie was deceiv'd, not ſatis fied,</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>In cutting of thy dayes,</hi> Climene <hi>dyed,</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>The</hi> Duke <hi>betrayd his vowes, for I expire</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>In thy cold ashes, Thou liv<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap>ſt in my ſire.</hi>
                     </l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Climene.</speaker>
                     <l>What's that I ſay, Thou liveſt in my fire,</l>
                     <l>Thy living Image is carv'd in my ſoule;</l>
                     <l>But thoſe immortall characters, alas!</l>
                     <l>Which flatter me, are dead <hi>Fabritios.</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>Vnjuſt and rigorous fate, was't reaſonable,</l>
                     <l>That death should ſeaſe him ſo neere marriage?</l>
                     <l>But why diſpute I in ſuch great miſfortunes?</l>
                     <l>I'le ſuffer my ſad ſighes, forbid my teares,</l>
                     <l>And to enuenome my affliction,</l>
                     <l>I'le ceaſe complaint, nourish my ſorrow, and</l>
                     <l>By prudent cares for feare to weaken it,</l>
                     <l>I'le ſtrengthen it within, Ile ſignalize</l>
                     <l>My griefes by ſilence better then by ſpeech.</l>
                     <l>When one hath loſt all who complaines, receaves</l>
                     <l>A kinde of comfort, therefore I'le forbeare;</l>
                     <l>Yes, my deare Lover, to deplore thy death</l>
                     <l>In ſtronger termes then plaints and exclamations</l>
                     <l>But what! I heare a fearfull noyſe beneath me?</l>
                     <stage>a noiſe under the Stage.</stage>
                     <l>It ſeemeth that to joyne me to <hi>Fabritio</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>A ſudden thunder doth prepare itſelfe</l>
                     <l>To come forth from the center of the earth:</l>
                     <l>The noyſe redoubleth, and renued ſtroaks</l>
                     <l>Makes me believe that underneath my feet</l>
                     <l>They dig graves, I perceive the flowers to fall</l>
                     <l>The plants to be unrooted, the moſt ſetled</l>
                     <l>And firmeſt oakes to tremble; it is time</l>
                     <pb n="51" facs="tcp:121249:26"/>
                     <l>To fly hence, but I cannot, feare forbids me;</l>
                     <l>Heaven! the diſorder growes, and the earth cleaves</l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Fabritio</hi> comes forth thence, my ſtrengh failes here,</l>
                     <l>And I am almoſt dead with feare and weaknes.</l>
                  </sp>
               </div>
               <div n="4" type="scene">
                  <head>SCENA QVARTA.</head>
                  <stage>FABRITIO CLIMENE.</stage>
                  <stage>Fabritio <hi>comming out the Mine.</hi>
                  </stage>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Fabritio.</speaker>
                     <l>THanks unto <hi>Carlos,</hi> and in ſpight of deſtinie,</l>
                     <l>I hope to ſee <hi>Climene</hi> in this garden</l>
                     <l>But to conceale the meanes on't I muſt cover</l>
                     <l>Moſt carefullie the opening of the Mine:</l>
                     <l>Thoſe ſtones, and thoſe greene boughs will make the hole</l>
                     <l>Inviſible, I need but ſeek the ingratefull,</l>
                     <l>Before I vent my anger; I<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>le reproach her</l>
                     <l>With my paſſ'd ſervices, with her inconſtancie,</l>
                     <l>And her falſe oaths; for feare my death should give her,</l>
                     <l>Some ſatisfaction, and to th'end t'afflict her,</l>
                     <l>I will appeare unto her, and proteſt</l>
                     <l>That I will live yet to abhorre her; yonder</l>
                     <l>I ſee that faire Inconſtant; but alas!</l>
                     <l>I ſee her pale, cold, and in dying poſture;</l>
                     <l>At this ſad object which confoundeth me,</l>
                     <l>A tender pittie doth ſucceed my paſſion;</l>
                     <l>And if this pittie cauſ'd by her misfortune,</l>
                     <l>Is not yet love, tis ſomething, ſure, that's neere it,</l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Climene</hi> thou faire object of the flame</l>
                     <l>which riſeth up againe, when almoſt dead,</l>
                     <l>Caſt yet a languishing look upon <hi>Fabritio;</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>For all thy anger and inconſtancie,</l>
                     <l>I never ſought any reveng gainſt thee;</l>
                     <l>Returne, and if thou wilt not that I live,</l>
                     <l>At leaſt with one ſweet look honour my death:</l>
                     <l>I heare ſome comming, I muſt hide my ſelfe.</l>
                     <pb n="52" facs="tcp:121249:27"/>
                     <l>If I should goe into the Mine againe,</l>
                     <l>There's danger I might be ſurpriſ'd.</l>
                  </sp>
               </div>
               <div n="5" type="scene">
                  <head>SCENA QUINTA.</head>
                  <stage>The Duke, Climene.</stage>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Duke.</speaker>
                     <l>I have heard ſtroaks which troubled me much</l>
                     <l>The noiſe came from this ſide, let us advaunce</l>
                     <l>I ſee <hi>Climene,</hi> who fleepes; but alas,</l>
                     <l>Vnparalel'd misfortune! she is dead,</l>
                     <l>And underneath a thick vaile, her faire eyes</l>
                     <l>Are shut up never to be opened:</l>
                     <l>Tyrannick deſtinie, by what law is it</l>
                     <l>That ſuch a rare and exquiſite beautie hath</l>
                     <l>So tragicall a fate, and that the Star</l>
                     <l>Of my nativitie, which hath produc'd</l>
                     <l>My ſires, ſindes in its morne eternall night?</l>
                     <l>But I am in an errout; Maſter peece</l>
                     <l>Of all perfection, fate is innocent,</l>
                     <l>And I alone am guiltie, tis this arme,</l>
                     <l>This batharous arme that hath tane hence my Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtreſſe</l>
                     <l>In murthering my Rivall.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Climene.</speaker>
                     <p>Oh, alas!</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Duke.</speaker>
                     <l>She breathes, she breaths, and openeth her eyes</l>
                     <l>Love, be propitious to me.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Climene</speaker>
                     <l>Is it thee,</l>
                     <l>My deare <hi>Fabritio,</hi> Fantaſme of my ſonle,</l>
                     <l>Sweet Shadow of my Lover? what wilt thou?</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Duke.</speaker>
                     <p>Her griefe diſtracts her judgment.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Climene.</speaker>
                     <l>Commeſt thou to reproach me ſuddenlie,</l>
                     <l>That thou hadſt lived, if thou had'ſt not ſeene me,</l>
                     <l>And that the fire ſometime ſo faire, which kindled</l>
                     <pb n="53" facs="tcp:121249:27"/>
                     <l>Our hearts with mutuall love, ſerv'd but to light thee</l>
                     <l>To deſcend to the grave?</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Duke.</speaker>
                     <l>You are miſtaken,</l>
                     <l>Adoreable <hi>Climene.</hi>
                     </l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Climene.</speaker>
                     <l>Tell me then</l>
                     <l>The cauſe that brings thee, Com'ſt thou to ſoliſſit</l>
                     <l>My heart and arme a while yet to deferre</l>
                     <l>My death, unto the end to revenge thine!</l>
                     <l>Wil thou that this ha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d plung'd in the <hi>Dukes</hi> blood</l>
                     <l>Make my deſtruction juſt, and thine reveng'd</l>
                     <l>Speak ſpeak; he shall not long be in condition</l>
                     <l>To triumph in thy death, in the midſt of</l>
                     <l>His Court, and in the eyes of all <hi>Ferrara,</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>I'le peirce the boſom of that barbarous Prince.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Duke.</speaker>
                     <l>My heart feares but the ſtroales of your faire eyes,</l>
                     <l>Know me, and recollect your wandering ſenſes</l>
                     <l>The exceſſe of your ſorrow wrongs you much.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Climene.</speaker>
                     <p>Whom doe I ſee?</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Duke.</speaker>
                     <p>A Prince that loveth you.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Climene.</speaker>
                     <l>What fatall accident, what cruell deſtinie</l>
                     <l>Preſenteth me, in ſtead of my Lover,</l>
                     <l>His murtherer, Sir, you muſt pardon me</l>
                     <l>This langvage, as a perſon highly injur'd:</l>
                     <l>I can no mor reſpect you: is it poſſible,</l>
                     <l>You are not fullie ſatisfied yet</l>
                     <l>In barbarouſlie depriving me of him,</l>
                     <l>I lov'd more then my ſelfe, but you muſt come</l>
                     <l>To robb me of his Shadow?</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Duke.</speaker>
                     <l>This vaine shadow</l>
                     <l>You ſpeake of, is but an illuſion</l>
                     <pb n="54" facs="tcp:121249:28"/>
                     <l>Form'd by your feare and your affliction;</l>
                     <l>And when I've diſſipated from your fancie</l>
                     <l>This fatall image, you will finde that I</l>
                     <l>Have more advauntaged, then injur'd you.</l>
                     <l>For dead <hi>Fabritio,</hi> pleaſe you to remember,</l>
                     <l>That twas your intereſt made me punish him;</l>
                     <l>The inſolent diſcourſe which he held forth,</l>
                     <l>Carried me juſtlie to that violence:</l>
                     <l>If I had ſpar'd him, I had injur'd you,</l>
                     <l>And if I had done leſſe, I had leſſe lou'd.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Climene.</speaker>
                     <l>Brahis accompt then I'm indebted to you</l>
                     <l>For giving, me the greateſt of misfortunes,</l>
                     <l>In killing even before mine eyes the object</l>
                     <l>Which I adore, without whom the faire light</l>
                     <l>Is odious to me; you are much deceav'd</l>
                     <l>In your pretentions, you have gained nothing</l>
                     <l>In ruining a Rivall, and the art</l>
                     <l>Whicch you uſe to aſperſe his reputation,</l>
                     <l>Can't hinder him to live with in my ſoule:</l>
                     <l>Though this death which I feel livelie with in me</l>
                     <l>Had not expreſſ'd ſo much hate and contempt</l>
                     <l>As you shew love and tendernes, I should</l>
                     <l>Have loved him ſo much as I hate you.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Duke.</speaker>
                     <l>I condemne not your juſt tranſports, but beare them,</l>
                     <l>He was your Lover, though he was my Rivall;</l>
                     <l>And I repent my rage in that I wrong'd</l>
                     <l>Your charming Image, printed in his ſoule:</l>
                     <l>I know that Rivall, which was odious to me,</l>
                     <l>Pleaſed your faire eyes more then I, his merit</l>
                     <l>Was that which onelie rendered him guiltie:</l>
                     <l>I hated him for being too amiable;</l>
                     <l>But in that hate, I fully did expreſſe</l>
                     <l>My love to you in offering you a heart,</l>
                     <pb n="55" facs="tcp:121249:28"/>
                     <l>And with that heart a crowne. But I offend you,</l>
                     <l>Your looks ſpeak your diſdaine. not to provoke you,</l>
                     <l>I leave you, and hope yet, that you will one day</l>
                     <l>Have leſſe averſion for me.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Climene.</speaker>
                     <l>Time can never</l>
                     <l>Cure my diſeaſe, death onelie is its terme.</l>
                  </sp>
               </div>
               <div n="6" type="scene">
                  <head>SCENA SEXTA.</head>
                  <stage>Jacinta, Fabritio, Climene.</stage>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Fabritio.</speaker>
                     <l>I will approach, I ſee the Duke retire,</l>
                     <l>My trouble is paſſ'd; and <hi>Climene</hi> lives;</l>
                     <l>But, heaven: who cometh here againe to croſſe me,</l>
                  </sp>
                  <stage>
                     <hi>Iacinta</hi> to <hi>Climene.</hi>
                  </stage>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Iacinta.</speaker>
                     <p>The Funerall is comming.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Climene.</speaker>
                     <p>What, <hi>Fabritio's?</hi>
                     </p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Fabritio.</speaker>
                     <l>It is <hi>Iacinta,</hi> I need not for her</l>
                     <l>Keep a loofe of. — <stage>aſide.</stage>
                     </l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Iacinta.</speaker>
                     <l>Yes Madame, you may ſee</l>
                     <l>The coffin which encloſeth your dead Lover</l>
                     <l>From your Balcony at this very inſtant:</l>
                     <l>His Father, who intends to celebrate</l>
                     <l>His mourning, honoureth <hi>Fabritios</hi> death</l>
                     <l>With funerall pompe, and whilſt they carrie him</l>
                     <l>Vnto the Temple, you may, if you pleaſe,</l>
                     <l>See that unfortunate body paſſe.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Climene.</speaker>
                     <l>I will ſo,</l>
                     <l>It is my laſt deſire,</l>
                  </sp>
                  <pb n="56" facs="tcp:121249:29"/>
                  <stage>Fabritio, <hi>diſcovering himſelfe.</hi>
                  </stage>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Fabritio.</speaker>
                     <l>Enjoy it, Madame,</l>
                     <l>Behould heere the unfortunate <hi>Fabritio.</hi>
                     </l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Iacinta</speaker>
                     <l>Heaven! where shall I fly ſafely from this Fantaſme.</l>
                     <l>I dare not ſtay. — <stage>Iacinta <hi>flyes away.</hi>
                        </stage>
                     </l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Climene.</speaker>
                     <l>What! will <hi>Iacinta</hi> leave me?</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Iacinta.</speaker>
                     <p>I have no other Miſtreſſe now but feare.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <stage>Fabritin <hi>houlding</hi> Climene.</stage>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Fabritio.</speaker>
                     <l>Falſe and ingratefull Beautie, doe you fly me!</l>
                     <l>This makes your lightnes. To appeare too much:</l>
                     <l>If any juſtice yet raignes in your ſoule,</l>
                     <l>After you have betray'd me, give me leave</l>
                     <l>To complaine my misfortune.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Climene.</speaker>
                     <l>I betray you?</l>
                     <l>What doe I heare, Heavens! how aſtonish'd am I</l>
                     <l>At this ſo ſtrang event? if I may heere</l>
                     <l>Believe mine eyes, it is the living portrait</l>
                     <l>Of my <hi>Fabritio,</hi> but if I believe</l>
                     <l>His voice, it is but a deceitfull Fantaſme</l>
                     <l>Of ſuch a ſa'tfull Lover:</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Fabritio.</speaker>
                     <l>I am that verie Lover, who againſt</l>
                     <l>Your will could not, in loſing all his hope,</l>
                     <l>Loſe his life too <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap> yes, I live yet, Ingratefull,</l>
                     <l>And feare I live for you ſtill in deſpight</l>
                     <l>Of my juſt anger, I know not what power</l>
                     <l>Oppoſeth it in ſteed of murmurring,</l>
                     <l>I ſigh, and all the heat that reſts with me</l>
                     <l>Reſembles anger leſſe then love.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <pb n="57" facs="tcp:121249:29"/>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Climene.</speaker>
                     <l>Now I</l>
                     <l>Begin againe to know <hi>Fabritio;</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>His heart in ſpight of him doth ſecretlie</l>
                     <l>Render me juſtice; and when the falſe mouth</l>
                     <l>Condemnes me, it ſeemes reſolute in thought</l>
                     <l>That I am faithfull.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Fabritio.</speaker>
                     <l>Faithfull? oh it is</l>
                     <l>Vnto the Duke that this ſpeech is addreſſ'd</l>
                     <l>He onelie is to hope for all your love.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Climen.</speaker>
                     <p>Canſt thou impute thoſe baſe thoughts unto me?</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Fabritio.</speaker>
                     <l>They are truths, if I may believe your oathes;</l>
                     <l>I should doubt yet of this extreem misfortune,</l>
                     <l>If I had underſtood it from the mouth</l>
                     <l>Of any other but your ſelfe.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Climene.</speaker>
                     <l>An evill</l>
                     <l>When it is knowne, is eaſie to be cur'd;</l>
                     <l>I know thy errour, ceaſe to be abuſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>d;</l>
                     <l>If the laſt fatall evening I expreſſ'd</l>
                     <l>Find words unto the Duke, I did believe</l>
                     <l>That I diſcourſ'd to thee, and ſo upon</l>
                     <l>That faith all that I ſaid to him, was wholie</l>
                     <l>Intended unto thee<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>, thy onelie Image,</l>
                     <l>Which can poſſeſſe my heart, my memorie,</l>
                     <l>And all my ſenſes with ſo much renowne,</l>
                     <l>Was onelie guiltie in that fatall moment,</l>
                     <l>If but a little blindnes may be ſaid</l>
                     <l>To be a crime in Love.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Fabritio.</speaker>
                     <l>Vnto a Lover,</l>
                     <l>Whoſe ſoule reſignes it ſelfe unto ſuſpitions,</l>
                     <l>Any excuſe is good ynough, and paſſeth,</l>
                     <pb n="58" facs="tcp:121249:30" rendition="simple:additions"/>
                     <l>A lye that pleaſeth deceives pleaſantlie,</l>
                     <l>And everie thing is eaſilie believ'd,</l>
                     <l>Which is deſir'd; though all thy reaſons were</l>
                     <l>As falſe as faire, ſo ſweet it would be to me</l>
                     <l>To ſee my ſcares to end, and in my fancie</l>
                     <l>To flatter the affliction which thou</l>
                     <l>Might'ſt cauſe me, that thou wouldſt oblige me ſtronglie</l>
                     <l>To make <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                           <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                        </gap> yeild to be abus'd.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Climene.</speaker>
                     <l>Let thy heart be</l>
                     <l>Free from thoſe Low ſuſpitions; if thou wilt</l>
                     <l>Abſent thee, I am readie heere to follow thee;</l>
                     <l>I'le maneſeſt unto thee everie where</l>
                     <l>The clecrenes of my faith, be it to live,</l>
                     <l>Or dye with thee, let Heaven bleſſe, or deceive</l>
                     <l>Our expectations, I'le live ſatisfied,</l>
                     <l>Or dye content.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Fabritio.</speaker>
                     <p>What owe I —</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Climene.</speaker>
                     <l>Thou ow'ſt nothing;</l>
                     <l>Nothing of thanks, in following thy deſires,</l>
                     <l>I follow my owne ſentiments; but how</l>
                     <l>Wer't thou ſecur'd?</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Fabritio.</speaker>
                     <l>Fortune did favour me,</l>
                     <l>A ſtraunger paſſing that night perished</l>
                     <l>Inſtead of me, and this Mine gives me meanes</l>
                     <l>From <hi>Carlos</hi> houſe to enter into thine.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Climene.</speaker>
                     <l>Thou mayſt a while heere entertaine thy thoughts</l>
                     <l>In the meane I'le goe to fetch my lewells:</l>
                     <l>Paſſe underneath this arbor, I believe</l>
                     <l>I heare a noyſe; aſſoone as it is night,</l>
                     <l>I'le come to thee againe.</l>
                  </sp>
               </div>
               <div n="7" type="scene">
                  <pb n="59" facs="tcp:121249:30"/>
                  <head>SCENA SEPTIMA.</head>
                  <stage>Jacinta, Fabritio.</stage>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Fabritio.</speaker>
                     <l>IF I am not deceiv'd, heere comes <hi>Iacinta,</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Climene</hi> truſts her with her neereſt ſecrets:</l>
                     <l>Fortune, it ſeemes, to day in overie point</l>
                     <l>Will be ſweet to me, if I can oblige her</l>
                     <l>To goe away with us.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Iacinta.</speaker>
                     <l>Scarce freed yet</l>
                     <l>From my firſt feare, I tremblinglie returne</l>
                     <l>Vnto <hi>Climenes</hi> houſe: <hi>Fabritio</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>Was murthered through my meanes, and without doubt</l>
                     <l>He cometh to revenge himſelfe upon me</l>
                     <l>From th' other world: my ruine were inevitable</l>
                     <l>If I should meet that fearefull Ghoſt againe.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Fabritio.</speaker>
                     <p>Stay. —</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Iacinta.</speaker>
                     <l>Tis the Spirit, good God, I dye with feare!</l>
                     <l>Oh Genrle <hi>Fantaſme,</hi> have compaſſion of me;</l>
                     <l>I doe confeſſe my fault, and promiſe faithfullie</l>
                     <l>N'er to betray you, nor my Miſtreſſe more.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Fabritio.</speaker>
                     <l>Strang! but I muſt know more. Diſguiſe me no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing,</l>
                     <l>If thou doſt —</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Iacinta.</speaker>
                     <l>Touch me not then, I beſeech you,</l>
                     <l>And I will tell you all: tis true, I alwaies</l>
                     <l>Indeavoured to hurt you, that I ſtudyed</l>
                     <l>To ſerve the Duke in his amours againſt you,</l>
                     <l>And that indead I was cauſe of your death.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <pb n="60" facs="tcp:121249:31"/>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Fabritio.</speaker>
                     <p>Pernstious ſpirit. —</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Iacinta</speaker>
                     <l>Enter not into furie,</l>
                     <l>This is not all yet, lend your eare, I pray you,</l>
                     <l>I had forgot to tell you that the Duke.</l>
                     <l>By my adviſe this day hath ſix'd upon</l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Climenes</hi> rape, and that this verie evening</l>
                     <l>He will attempt this unjuſt enterpriſe,</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Fabritio.</speaker>
                     <p>Horrid perſidiouſnes!</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Iacinta.</speaker>
                     <l>I have tould all my faults, now may it pleaſe you</l>
                     <l>That I leave you in peace: for know that nothing</l>
                     <l>Is ſo unpleaſant to me as diſcourſe</l>
                     <l>With people of another World. If you</l>
                     <l>Were not dead, you would be ſo good unto me,</l>
                     <l>To grant me pardon upon my repentance.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Fabritio.</speaker>
                     <l>It would not ſuite well with a generous ſpirit</l>
                     <l>To punish a weake woman. Goe. —</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Iacinta.</speaker>
                     <l>Monſieur Fantaſme,</l>
                     <l>God will receive your ſoule. — <hi>Exit Iacinta.</hi>
                     </l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Fabritio.</speaker>
                     <l>The Duke this night</l>
                     <l>Intends, it ſeemes, to take away <hi>Climene,</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>Heaven, muſt my hope be yet againe deſtroy'd?</l>
                     <l>But my heart leaves it ſelfe to be aſſaulted</l>
                     <l>With a vaine ſeare, ſeeing I am belov'd,</l>
                     <l>What should I doubt; nothing is ſtrong ynough</l>
                     <l>To diſunite two hearts which love hath joyn'd,</l>
                     <l>This God doth miracles for thoſe that be</l>
                     <l>His ſaithfull Votaries, and ſuch are we.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <trailer>The End of the third Act.</trailer>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div n="4" type="act">
               <pb n="61" facs="tcp:121249:31"/>
               <head>ACTVS QVARTVS.</head>
               <div n="1" type="scene">
                  <head>SCENA PRIMA.</head>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Fabritio, alone.</speaker>
                     <l>BEhould the hower, wherein I hope to ſee</l>
                     <l>The Beautie which my ſoule loves and adores:</l>
                     <l>The Snnne alreadie having run his courſe,</l>
                     <l>Darteth no more heere but a feeble light:</l>
                     <l>With his laſt rayes he now adornes the Weſt</l>
                     <l>He ſetts with glorie, shines when he is loſt</l>
                     <l>And the fair remnants of his dying brightnes</l>
                     <l>Maketh his fall and loſſe illuſtrious,</l>
                     <l>Pardon, thou glorious Stat, whoſe ſplendour hurts me,</l>
                     <l>If my hope comes, when thy light vanisheth:</l>
                     <l>Ingenious Love, to hurt me more, aſſembles</l>
                     <l>That maſſe of Inſtre which ſo charmeth me</l>
                     <l>In faire Climenes eyes, and preſentlie</l>
                     <l>Her looks wil give me brightnes which ſurpaſſeth</l>
                     <l>That which thou takeſt from me: But she ſtayes,</l>
                     <l>Heaven. she neglects me, she appeareth not:</l>
                     <l>The Moone is well advaunc'd: and all my hope</l>
                     <l>Dyes with the day; this long delay denotes</l>
                     <l>A'fault of love: I heare one walk, and if</l>
                     <l>My eyes are faithfull witneſſes, I ſee</l>
                     <l>This miracle of Faire ones come at laſt.</l>
                  </sp>
               </div>
               <div n="2" type="scene">
                  <head>SCENA SECUNDA.</head>
                  <stage>Climene, Fabritio.</stage>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Climene.</speaker>
                     <p>
                        <hi>FAbritie</hi> —</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Fabritio.</speaker>
                     <l>Heere, faire ſubject of my flame.</l>
                     <l>Here's he, who is as ſaithfull as he's happle.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <pb n="62" facs="tcp:121249:32"/>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Climene.</speaker>
                     <l>I did not think to have bene ſo long abſent.</l>
                     <l>I feare that I have put thee to ſome trouble.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Fabritio.</speaker>
                     <l>Believe, indead, that to <hi>Fabritio</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>The leaſt remove of thy faire eyes is grievous,</l>
                     <l>I did expect thee ſooner, and to ſpeak</l>
                     <l>The truth reſolved to complaine unto thee,</l>
                     <l>Vpon this point; but to forget it quire,</l>
                     <l>It is ſufficient that I ſee thee now;</l>
                     <l>I have no power to complaine before thee,</l>
                     <l>The preſent pleaſure flattering my thought,</l>
                     <l>Takes wholie from me the remembrance</l>
                     <l>Of my paſſ'd trouble.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Climene.</speaker>
                     <l>Since love forceth thee</l>
                     <l>Not to accuſe me, the ſame paſſion</l>
                     <l>Obligeth me too to excuſe my ſelfe.</l>
                     <l>It was not the care of theſe Diamonds</l>
                     <l>Where with I'm loaden, which cauſed my ſtay,</l>
                     <l>It onelie was the care to take a time</l>
                     <l>Proper for our departure.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Fabritio.</speaker>
                     <l>Let's referre</l>
                     <l>The proſecution of this diſcourſe</l>
                     <l>Vnto another time, and think we now</l>
                     <l>To finish our deſignes, and t'haſte our ſlight;</l>
                     <l>I feare the ſtroaks yet of injurious chaunce,</l>
                     <l>She should be truſted leaſt, when she ſmiles moſt.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Climene</speaker>
                     <l>Let's haſte, I willinglie conſent unto it,</l>
                     <l>I feare leaſt that torch should diſcover thee,</l>
                     <l>Oh hide thee!</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Fabritio.</speaker>
                     <l>I will dye rather then hide me;</l>
                     <l>An outrage is intended to thy perſon.</l>
                     <l>I muſt prevent it, being advertiſed</l>
                     <pb n="63" facs="tcp:121249:32"/>
                     <l>That the Dukes readie by a barbarous order</l>
                     <l>To carrie thee away by violence.</l>
                  </sp>
               </div>
               <div n="3" type="scene">
                  <head>SCENA TERTIA.</head>
                  <stage>The Duke, Valerio, Climene, Fabritio, Guards.</stage>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Valerio.</speaker>
                     <p>SHe muſt be heere</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Duke.</speaker>
                     <l>I'le draw a ſide a little,</l>
                     <l>But ſo, that I'le heare all: Goe, ſpeake from me.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Fabritio.</speaker>
                     <l>What ſuffer thee to be tane hence by force,</l>
                     <l>And in my preſence?</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Climene.</speaker>
                     <l>No, if any Violence</l>
                     <l>Be offered, ſtep forth unto my ayd,</l>
                     <l>In the meane time hide thee, and make me not</l>
                     <l>To feare for any but my ſelfe; Valerio,</l>
                     <l>What ſeek you heere at ſuch an hower as this?</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Valerio.</speaker>
                     <l>I could not wish to meet a better object</l>
                     <l>Then your faire ſelfe, a coach neere hand attends you,</l>
                     <l>I muſt conduct you there, having for it</l>
                     <l>An expreſſe order.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Climene</speaker>
                     <l>How! from whom have you</l>
                     <l>This order?</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Valerio.</speaker>
                     <l>Madame, from the Duke my Maſter,</l>
                     <l>Whom everie one is bound here to acknowledge</l>
                     <l>For Soveraigne.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Climene.</speaker>
                     <l>Let him be n'er ſo Soveraigne,</l>
                     <l>Yet he muſt know that the free ſoule of <hi>Climene</hi>
                     </l>
                     <pb n="64" facs="tcp:121249:33"/>
                     <l>Is not within his power my heart depends</l>
                     <l>Vpon another, and ſay what he will,</l>
                     <l>That is no lawfull ſubject to his Empire.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Valerio.</speaker>
                     <p>Madam, I'm ſorrie — but I muſt obey,</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Climene.</speaker>
                     <l>What' thinketh he to make himſelfe belov'd.</l>
                     <l>As one makes himſelfe hated' Loſing libertie?</l>
                     <l>Believeth he that I should be ſo ſimple</l>
                     <l>To take ſo many marks of hatred for</l>
                     <l>Effects of love? what from his enmitie</l>
                     <l>Might I not feare, if when he loveth me,</l>
                     <l>He ſeeks to perſecute me?</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Valerio.</speaker>
                     <l>I am forc'd</l>
                     <l>Aſmuch as you are, but it is in vaine</l>
                     <l>For you to give your ſelfe o'r to complaints,</l>
                     <l>Follow me quicklie where I goe. —</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Duke.</speaker>
                     <l>Stay, ſtay;</l>
                     <l>Her beautie will not ſuffer any outrage</l>
                     <l>To be done to her perſon, in my preſence,</l>
                     <l>Or rather I have too much paſſion</l>
                     <l>To ſuffer that she should be injured.</l>
                     <l>Tis true that troubled much, and deſperate</l>
                     <l>At your contempt I was prepar'd to take you</l>
                     <l>Away by force, I did expect the iſſue,</l>
                     <l>And will confeſſe, Madame, that in my ſoule</l>
                     <l>Love vanquished reſpect; but preſentlie</l>
                     <l>At your firſt words love vanquish'd at its turne,</l>
                     <l>Yeilded unto reſpect: ceaſe, ceaſe to feare,</l>
                     <l>Thou charming wonder, the heate of that love</l>
                     <l>Soome what too violent: should your heart be</l>
                     <l>Hard as a rock, I onelie would imploy</l>
                     <l>Reſpect to touch it, there's more paſſion in me</l>
                     <l>Then hate in you: in all the places where</l>
                     <pb n="65" facs="tcp:121249:33"/>
                     <l>I reigne, you shall be Souveraigne, and I shall</l>
                     <l>Eſteeme me happie, not to give you lawes,</l>
                     <l>But to take them of you.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Climene.</speaker>
                     <l>I should give thanks</l>
                     <l>Vnto the Duke for ſuch a declaration</l>
                     <l>If I could flatter heere <hi>Fabritios</hi> enemie.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Duke.</speaker>
                     <l>Although his loſſe hath reaſon to oblige me,</l>
                     <l>Since it afflicts you, it afflicteth me;</l>
                     <l>But there runnes a report upon this point</l>
                     <l>Which terrifies me, tis that to your eyes</l>
                     <l>His <hi>Fantaſme</hi> doth appeare.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Climene.</speaker>
                     <l>There's nothing falſe</l>
                     <l>In this report, <hi>Fabritio</hi> ſince his death</l>
                     <l>Appear'd before mine eyes.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Duke.</speaker>
                     <l>To diſſipate</l>
                     <l>Obnoxious feares which might cauſe evill viſions</l>
                     <l>Within your fancie, ſome of my attendance</l>
                     <l>Shall preſentlie have order not to leave you,</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Climene.</speaker>
                     <p>Oh! Sir, this is not it which I demaund.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Duke.</speaker>
                     <l>Tis the leaſt duty I muſt render you:</l>
                     <l>Suffer them for to guard you.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Climene.</speaker>
                     <p>Sir, it needs not.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Duke.</speaker>
                     <l>Your quietnes concernes me, and I muſt</l>
                     <l>Take care of it.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Climene.</speaker>
                     <l>So farre you would be from obliging me</l>
                     <l>By this deſigne, that you would hurt me rather;</l>
                     <l>Of this care therefore I diſpenſe your Highnes.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <pb n="66" facs="tcp:121249:34"/>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Duke.</speaker>
                     <l>To condeſcend to your deſires heerein,</l>
                     <l>Were to betray you, the ſad viſion</l>
                     <l>Of a dead perſon doth encreaſe your griefes.</l>
                     <l>Permit —</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Climene.</speaker>
                     <l>No, Sir, command them not to follow;</l>
                     <l>The viſion doth pleaſe me, and I feare</l>
                     <l>To be deprived of its companie.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Duke.</speaker>
                     <l>This Spirit will alwaies diſtract your reaſon,</l>
                     <l>As long as you ſtay in the houſe alone.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Climene.</speaker>
                     <l>If but to chaung houſe will give you content,</l>
                     <l>I'le ſatisfie you, <hi>Carlos</hi> is my neighbour,</l>
                     <l>I will retire to him.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Duke.</speaker>
                     <l>If you ſix there,</l>
                     <l>I contradict it not, his mother is</l>
                     <l>A verie prudent Woman, and her counſells</l>
                     <l>Will be a great helpe to your timourous ſpirits,</l>
                     <l>Permit me to conduct you to her houſe.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Climene.</speaker>
                     <l>This prayer is a command, Sir.</l>
                     <l>I cannot</l>
                     <l>Refuſe to follow, him, eſpeciallie</l>
                     <l>Seeing <hi>Fabritio</hi> likewyſe hath deſigne</l>
                     <l>To goe there.</l>
                     <stage>Softly.</stage>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Fabritio.</speaker>
                     <l>What diſcourſe i'th'name of wonder</l>
                     <l>Might she have all this while there; but good God!</l>
                     <l>The Duke drawes her away, I'le ſuccour her.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Duke.</speaker>
                     <l>This <hi>Fantaſm's</hi> nothing elce but the effect</l>
                     <l>Of a ſad thought, the ſenſes are all hurt,</l>
                     <l>When the ſoule's troubled.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <pb n="67" facs="tcp:121249:34"/>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Fabritio.</speaker>
                     <p>I'le put out the light.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Duke.</speaker>
                     <l>Laſtly l' promiſe you that there's no <hi>Fantaſme,</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>Nor ever was; but what is that I ſee?</l>
                     <l>O prodegie! o Heaven! how am I troubled?</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Fabritio.</speaker>
                     <l>It is <hi>Fabritio,</hi> who is come to take</l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Climene</hi> from you.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Climene.</speaker>
                     <l>O <hi>Fabritio,</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>Vnto what danger comes thou to expoſe thee?</l>
                     <stage>— <hi>aſide.</hi>
                     </stage>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Fabritio.</speaker>
                     <p>
                        <hi>Climene,</hi> ſave thy ſelfe, or leave me perish.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Climene.</speaker>
                     <l>My life's in danger, when thou hazardeſt</l>
                     <l>Thy ſelfe. I doe withdraw now, follow me.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Duke.</speaker>
                     <l>Advance, Guards, I'le be cleered in this point,</l>
                     <l>Leave me not, I comand yee.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Fabritio.</speaker>
                     <l>She is gone.</l>
                     <l>I'le follow her.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Valerio.</speaker>
                     <l>Sir doubt not on't, it is</l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Fabrotio's</hi> shadow.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Duke.</speaker>
                     <p>No matter, I'le be ſatisfied therein.</p>
                  </sp>
               </div>
               <div n="4" type="scene">
                  <head>SCENA QUARTA.</head>
                  <stage>Carlos, Valerio, the Duke, attendance.</stage>
                  <stage>Carlos <hi>comming out of the Mine.</hi>
                  </stage>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Carlos.</speaker>
                     <l>I'le goe to ayd my friend, this noyſe doth make me</l>
                     <l>To judge that his life runnes ſome danger here.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <pb n="68" facs="tcp:121249:35"/>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Valerio.</speaker>
                     <l>It is impoſſible to take a <hi>Fantaſme;</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>Yet he is taken, and it is a ſenſible,</l>
                     <l>And ſolid body.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Duke.</speaker>
                     <l>Traitor, and the greateſt</l>
                     <l>Of all my enemies.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Carlos.</speaker>
                     <l>Oh Sir! what fault</l>
                     <l>Hath <hi>Carlos</hi> committed? never had you</l>
                     <l>A ſubject yet more faithfull.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Duke.</speaker>
                     <l>What is that?</l>
                     <l>Tis <hi>Carlos,</hi> ſtrange! this is a new ſurpriſe:</l>
                     <l>Heere all my arguments are vaine. Come you,</l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Carlos,</hi> to take <hi>Climene</hi> from my hands?</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Carlos.</speaker>
                     <l>I, Sir? by no meanes; the noiſe which I heard</l>
                     <l>Drew me unto this place to know the cauſe on't.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Duke.</speaker>
                     <p>Who came into this garden then to ſtop me?</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Carlos.</speaker>
                     <l>It was <hi>Vabritios</hi> shadow, can you doubt out?</l>
                     <l>We can give you a certaine teſtimonie</l>
                     <l>Thereof, as knowing well his voice and viſage.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Duke.</speaker>
                     <p>I obſerv'd them my ſelfe verie diſtinctlie.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Carlos.</speaker>
                     <p>Aſſure yee, Sir, it was <hi>Fabritios</hi> shadow.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Duke.</speaker>
                     <l>I'm ſtranglie troubled at this prodegie;</l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Climene</hi> was perſuaded by my reaſons</l>
                     <l>To quit this houſe, and I was bringing her</l>
                     <l>Vnto thyne, when that ſpirit came and parted us,</l>
                     <l>So that we have loſt each other in the darke.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <pb n="69" facs="tcp:121249:35"/>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Carlos.</speaker>
                     <p>This ſucceſſe, Sir, ſtrikes me with terrour too.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Duke.</speaker>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Carlos,</hi> we muſt finde out this charming Beautie,</l>
                     <l>And for her ſafetie bring her home to thee:</l>
                     <l>Seek thou of than ſide, the reſt follow.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Carlos.</speaker>
                     <l>Oh heaven! we are undone, the plotts diſcover'd:</l>
                     <l>If the <hi>Duke</hi> finde <hi>Fabritio,</hi> his ruine</l>
                     <l>Is certaine, but if in ſpight of the night</l>
                     <l>I'm not abus'd, I ſee a woman comming</l>
                     <l>Towards me.</l>
                  </sp>
               </div>
               <div n="5" type="scene">
                  <head>SCENA QUINTA.</head>
                  <stage>Carlos, Climene.</stage>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Climene.</speaker>
                     <p>
                        <hi>FAbritio,</hi> is it thee?</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Carlos.</speaker>
                     <p>No.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Climene.</speaker>
                     <p>Oh, my griefe!</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Carlos.</speaker>
                     <l>Although it be not he, at leaſt it is</l>
                     <l>His ſecond ſelfe, tis <hi>Carlos.</hi> —</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Climene.</speaker>
                     <l>Oh! deare Sir,</l>
                     <l>How miſetable am I?</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Carlos.</speaker>
                     <l>I know, Madame,</l>
                     <l>All your misfortune, having underſtood it.</l>
                     <l>From the <hi>Dukes</hi> mouth, who verie much in paſſio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>,</l>
                     <l>Seeketh you with no ordinarie care.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Climene.</speaker>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Fabritio's</hi> heere about, if he should be</l>
                     <l>Vnfortunatelie ſound, it were impoſſible</l>
                     <l>To ſave him afterward; Sir, if you love him,</l>
                     <pb n="70" facs="tcp:121249:36"/>
                     <l>Divert his daunger, overtake the Duke;</l>
                     <l>To draw him hence, tell him that I am readie</l>
                     <l>To come forth of this fatall place, and that</l>
                     <l>I've promiſed to ſtay here till you come,</l>
                     <l>To goe with you unto your houſe.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Carlos.</speaker>
                     <l>I fly;</l>
                     <l>In the meane time, find, if you can your Lover,</l>
                     <l>And tell him what hath happened, above all</l>
                     <l>faile not to be here preſentlie, your ſelfe.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Climene.</speaker>
                     <l>Fortune; I feare is not propitious</l>
                     <l>Ynough unto me, to permit me now</l>
                     <l>To finde <hi>Fabritio,</hi> with too much heat</l>
                     <l>Her anger doth purſue me, to conſent</l>
                     <l>That I shall have this happines, notwithſtanding</l>
                     <l>I heare a noiſe, perhaps Love favorable</l>
                     <l>To my chaſt flames, guideth my Lover here:</l>
                     <l>But what, they are two women; they have ſeene me,</l>
                     <l>Or I am much deceiv'd, I muſt be gone</l>
                     <l>To ſeek <hi>Fabritio,</hi> and to shun their preſence.</l>
                     <stage>Exit Climene.</stage>
                  </sp>
               </div>
               <div n="6" type="scene">
                  <head>SCENA SEXTA</head>
                  <stage>Iacinta, Iſabella.</stage>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Iacinta.</speaker>
                     <l>IT is my Miſtreſſe, Madame, approach bouldly,</l>
                     <l>And give me leave to goe immediatelie</l>
                     <l>Into the houſe, my conduct, and my cares</l>
                     <l>Are here ſuperfluous.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Iſabella.</speaker>
                     <l>Stay, she goes away,</l>
                     <l>And I ſee her no more, come, let us follow.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <pb n="71" facs="tcp:121249:36"/>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Iacinta.</speaker>
                     <l>Good God! if I should meet the ſpirit againe</l>
                     <l>Which I fo dread?</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Iſabella.</speaker>
                     <l>Thou knoweſt all theſe turnings,</l>
                     <l>And thou canſt guide me; Goe before.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Ianinta.</speaker>
                     <l>Who, I? defend me, God, from ſuch a rudenes,</l>
                     <l>I know my duty well, though a groſſe Girle,</l>
                     <l>Madame, you are to goe firſt, I'm to waite you</l>
                     <l>Oh if the ſpirit should come to punish me</l>
                     <l>For my late treaſon! — <stage>ſoftly</stage>
                     </l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Iſabella.</speaker>
                     <p>But thou trembleſt.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Iacinta.</speaker>
                     <p>Alas! there's reaſon for it.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Iſabella.</speaker>
                     <l>Stav here then,</l>
                     <l>I'le follow her without thee, ho, <hi>Climene!</hi>
                     </l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Iacinta.</speaker>
                     <l>She leaveth me alone, oh, I am loſt!</l>
                     <l>Madame, where runne you?</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Iſabella.</speaker>
                     <p>Doe not ſtay my ſtepps.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Iacinta.</speaker>
                     <l>Should you be n'er ſo angry, by your favour,</l>
                     <l>You shall not follow her.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Iſabella.</speaker>
                     <l>Thy importunitie</l>
                     <l>Is really, extreme, why doſt thou ſtop me?</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Iacinta.</speaker>
                     <l>Becauſe I love you, you would be in danger,</l>
                     <l>Should you goe on, your ſafetie's deare unto me,</l>
                     <l>And I'le take care on't.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Iſabella.</speaker>
                     <p>Leave me.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <pb n="72" facs="tcp:121249:37"/>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Iacinta.</speaker>
                     <l>No, I muſt not:</l>
                     <l>I'le tell you a ſtrang thing a fearefull Spiritt</l>
                     <l>Haunteth thoſe places,</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Iſabella</speaker>
                     <l>Iſt a waggish Spirit?</l>
                     <l>Hobgoblin, or a Robin, Good follow?</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Iacinta.</speaker>
                     <l>No, he's not pleaſant, rather on the contrarie,</l>
                     <l>It is an evill, and a miſchievous ſpirit.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Iſabella.</speaker>
                     <p>Who tould it thee?</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Iacinta.</speaker>
                     <l>Mine eyes, which did not lye.</l>
                     <l>And Iſ weare to you that I've twenty times</l>
                     <l>Seen it in ſeverall figures, ſometimes like</l>
                     <l>A man, and ſometimes like a ravenors beaſt,</l>
                     <l>And ſtill at everie bout miſchievoullie</l>
                     <l>Readie to break my neck.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Iſabella.</speaker>
                     <l>Climene then</l>
                     <l>Is not in ſafetie here.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Iacinta.</speaker>
                     <l>I know not that;</l>
                     <l>But I believe there is a league betweene them</l>
                     <l>They agree verie well: But ſee the ſpirit</l>
                     <l>In forme now of a Giant; Heaven protect me.</l>
                  </sp>
               </div>
               <div n="7" type="scene">
                  <pb n="73" facs="tcp:121249:37"/>
                  <head>SCENA SEPTIMA.</head>
                  <stage>Fabritio, Iacinta, Iſabella.</stage>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Fabritio.</speaker>
                     <l>IT is <hi>Iacinta,</hi> and <hi>Climene</hi> is</l>
                     <l>Without. doubt with het.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Iacinta.</speaker>
                     <l>It approacheth to us,</l>
                     <l>Oh let us fly, tis death to meete with it.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Iſabella.</speaker>
                     <p>It ſtopps at me, o Heaven, what feare have I?</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Fabritio.</speaker>
                     <p>Climene, ſtay, and heare me, I'm Fabritio.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Iſabella.</speaker>
                     <l>It is my brother, ſtrang ſurpriſe! I wil</l>
                     <l>Speak ſoft and conterfeit my voice to finde</l>
                     <l>What his deſigne is, — <stage>aſide.</stage>
                     </l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Fabritio.</speaker>
                     <l>The injurious Duke,</l>
                     <l>Fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> whom my cares would take thee, ſee keth thee</l>
                     <l>Without doubt at this inſtant, let us loſe</l>
                     <l>No time to shun his violence, but haſte we</l>
                     <l>To Carlos houſe: beſides, I feare my ſiſter,</l>
                     <l>For she at home this evening ſaid unto me,</l>
                     <l>That she would come to viſſit thee: if she</l>
                     <l>Should ſee me, preſentlie my Father, who</l>
                     <l>Thinks me alreadie farre of from this place,</l>
                     <l>Will underſtand the contrarie. This is not</l>
                     <l>To detract from my Siſter, she is good.</l>
                     <l>And verie innocent, but her fault is</l>
                     <l>She cannot hould her peace.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Iſabella.</speaker>
                     <l>Continue, Brother,</l>
                     <l>I'm much oblig'd unto you, pray, proceed.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <pb n="74" facs="tcp:121249:38"/>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Fabritio.</speaker>
                     <p>Misfortune! tis my Siſter <hi>Iſabella.</hi>
                     </p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Iſabella.</speaker>
                     <p>Purſue, good Brother.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Fabritio.</speaker>
                     <l>Las! I've ſaid too much,</l>
                     <l>Excuſe the feares and weaknes of a Lover?</l>
                     <l>If thy heart felt ſuch ſeiſures thou shouldſt know</l>
                     <l>That the God, who is Preſident of love,</l>
                     <l>Is but a timourous child, and trembles alwaies:</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Iſabella</speaker>
                     <l>I doe confeſſe, that I am ignorant</l>
                     <l>In maximes of this nature, and indead</l>
                     <l>Too innocent to underſtand them well:</l>
                     <l>Concerning your aboad, which I have learn'd</l>
                     <l>With ſome regrett, for being knowne to me</l>
                     <l>T'is not leſſe ſecret: I will make appeare</l>
                     <l>By ſilence and diſcretion, that I am</l>
                     <l>A better Siſter to you then you are a</l>
                     <l>Brother to me.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Fabritio.</speaker>
                     <l>Oh! Siſter, what ſweet ſentiments have you?</l>
                     <l>How shall I merit them?</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Iſabella.</speaker>
                     <l>I heare ſome body,</l>
                     <l>Brother, let us withdraw.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Fabritio.</speaker>
                     <l>I'le take your counſell; goe forth of this dwelling</l>
                     <l>To Carlos houſe, I'le follow you immediatelie.</l>
                  </sp>
               </div>
               <div n="8" type="scene">
                  <head>SCENA OCTAVA.</head>
                  <stage>The Duke, Carlos, Iſabella, attendance.</stage>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Carlos.</speaker>
                     <p>YOu ſee Climene ſtayes heere, as I ſaid,</p>
                  </sp>
                  <pb n="75" facs="tcp:121249:38"/>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Duke.</speaker>
                     <l>Conduct her! tis ynough, Im ſatisfi'd,</l>
                     <l>And will goe forth content.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Carlos.</speaker>
                     <l>Madame, tis Carlos,</l>
                     <l>Follow me without feare, ſpeake ſoft —</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Iſabella</speaker>
                     <l>Tis Carlos,</l>
                     <l>I'le follow him without conſtraint. — <stage>aſide.</stage>
                     </l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Duke.</speaker>
                     <l>Guards, waite upon <hi>Climene</hi> for this night,</l>
                     <l>My eyes muſt be deprived of the happines</l>
                     <l>To ſee her, my love urgeth me in vaine</l>
                     <l>To follow her, defer we till to morron</l>
                     <l>To render her a viſſit, the good which</l>
                     <l>I expect thence would be too dearelie bought</l>
                     <l>If it should coſt a trouble to <hi>Climene.</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>Depart we, and lets flatter us with hope</l>
                     <l>That we through perſeverance shall o'rcome,</l>
                     <l>And that there is no heart ſo hard by charme,</l>
                     <l>Which thoſe fires in my boſom cannot warme.</l>
                  </sp>
               </div>
               <div n="9" type="scene">
                  <head>SCENA NONA.</head>
                  <stage>Climene, Fabritio, The Duke.</stage>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Climene.</speaker>
                     <p>
                        <hi>FAbritio.</hi>
                     </p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Fabritio.</speaker>
                     <p>My <hi>Climene.</hi>
                     </p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Duke.</speaker>
                     <l>Heaven! what heare I?</l>
                     <l>My judgment is confounded heere; <hi>Climene</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>Is gone with <hi>Carlos,</hi> yet ſome ſecret charme</l>
                     <l>Which I can't comprehend, houldeth her heere</l>
                     <l>In conference with the shadow of the dead.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <pb n="76" facs="tcp:121249:39"/>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Climene.</speaker>
                     <l>Everie one is retir'd we are alone,</l>
                     <l>The <hi>Duke</hi> is alſo gone out of the garden:</l>
                     <l>Let's finish the deſigne we have in hand,</l>
                     <l>Let's preſſe it on, and fly we without feare</l>
                     <l>That Tyrants love, for whom I've ſo much horrour</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Duke.</speaker>
                     <l>In what a hideous gulfe of black deſpaire</l>
                     <l>Am I plunged by this prodegy? iſt a truth,</l>
                     <l>Or iſt a dreame?</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Fabritio.</speaker>
                     <l>Haſte we, but I'm afrayd</l>
                     <l>That in the dark we shall not finde the Mine.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Climene.</speaker>
                     <l>No matter we caan goe out of the garden</l>
                     <l>Another way, the key of the back dore</l>
                     <l>Which I have heere about me privately,</l>
                     <l>Will give us paſſage forth to <hi>Carlos</hi> houſe,</l>
                     <l>Where' gainſt the light returnes, I will be readie</l>
                     <l>T'embrace thy fortune, and to follow thee,</l>
                     <l>Goe where thou wilt.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Fabritio.</speaker>
                     <p>By what expreſſions. —</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Climene,</speaker>
                     <l>Tis ynough, make me no reply, but follow,</l>
                     <l>We Ioſe time,</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Duke.</speaker>
                     <l>There's no doubt of it, tis certaine,</l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Fabritio</hi> either dead of living ſteale</l>
                     <l>Away <hi>Climene;</hi> ha! I cannot ſuffer,</l>
                     <l>This outrage in my ſight: come, I'm reſolv'd</l>
                     <l>To loſe my ſelfe, or reſkue her; O Heavens!</l>
                     <stage>
                        <hi>The</hi> Duke <hi>running to ſuccour</hi> Climene, <hi>falles into the Mine.</hi>
                     </stage>
                  </sp>
                  <trailer>The End of the fourth Act.</trailer>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div n="5" type="act">
               <pb n="77" facs="tcp:121249:39"/>
               <head>ACTVS QVINTVS.</head>
               <div n="1" type="scene">
                  <head>SCENA PRIMA.</head>
                  <stage>Carlos, Iſabella.</stage>
                  <stage>In a hall of Carlos houſe.</stage>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Carlos.</speaker>
                     <l>WHom ſee I here? misfot tune! oh unluckie</l>
                     <l>Encounter! but, perhaps, I am deceiv'd,</l>
                     <l>Is it you, <hi>Iſabella?</hi>
                     </l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Iſabella.</speaker>
                     <l>Strang? What heare I?</l>
                     <l>Iſt poſſible that <hi>Carlos</hi> should not know me?</l>
                     <l>Are all my features ſuddenlie defaced?</l>
                     <l>No, they remaine yet, onelie I have cauſe</l>
                     <l>To thinke ahat they are raz'd out of thy memorie</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Carlos.</speaker>
                     <l>Oh, Madame, this ſuſpition is unjuſt,</l>
                     <l>I will upon this point tell you the truth</l>
                     <l>With all ſinceritic.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Iſabella.</speaker>
                     <l>Pray, What ſinceritie</l>
                     <l>Can one expect from you?</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Carlos.</speaker>
                     <l>Condemne me not</l>
                     <l>Before you heare me: I had a deſigne</l>
                     <l>Which prospered not, my intent was to bring</l>
                     <l>Another woman here, and I confeſſe</l>
                     <l>That I am ſorrie now to ſee you Madame.</l>
                     <l>In her place, your faire preſence is indead</l>
                     <l>A trouble at this time. But —</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Iſabella.</speaker>
                     <l>It ſufficeth,</l>
                     <l>Ingratefull, thy crime is acknowledged,</l>
                     <l>And more ſincerely then I could have thought</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Carlos.</speaker>
                     <p>Suffer me to expreſſe my ſelfe.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <pb n="78" facs="tcp:121249:40"/>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Iſabella.</speaker>
                     <l>It needs not,</l>
                     <l>What explication can be more cleer?</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Carlos.</speaker>
                     <p>Heare what remaines.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Iſabella.</speaker>
                     <l>No, I will heare no more,</l>
                     <l>All thy diſguiſements are ſuperfluous.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Carlos.</speaker>
                     <p>But know —</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Iſabella.</speaker>
                     <l>What should I know more? haſt thou not</l>
                     <l>Tould me that thy ſoule's fleeting, thou intende'ſt</l>
                     <l>To bring another Woman here, thou wilt</l>
                     <l>That I believe it, and I doe believe it.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Carlos.</speaker>
                     <p>I have not. —</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Iſabella.</speaker>
                     <l>True, thou haſt not any thing</l>
                     <l>For me but coldnes, and preſumption;</l>
                     <l>To ſee me in her place, thou ſayſt, th'art ſorrie,</l>
                     <l>And with an unjuſt paſſion thy ſalfe ſpirit</l>
                     <l>Carried away, goes from inconſtancie</l>
                     <l>To incivilitie.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Carlos.</speaker>
                     <p>Give me leave to ſpeake.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Iſabella.</speaker>
                     <l>What canſt thou ſay unto me?</l>
                     <l>That thou acknowledgeſt the Empire of</l>
                     <l>A Worthier object, that in vaine thy heart</l>
                     <l>Hath ſtood againſt her charmes, and that to gaine thee</l>
                     <l>I have too little beautie?</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Carlos.</speaker>
                     <l>Oh deceive not</l>
                     <pb n="79" facs="tcp:121249:40"/>
                     <l>Your ſelfe with ſo much art, and I beſeech you</l>
                     <l>Be leſſe unjuſt to my poore heart that loves you.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Iſabella.</speaker>
                     <l>In loſing ſuch a heart as thine, I shall</l>
                     <l>Loſe little, it is faithles, baſe, and treacherous,</l>
                     <l>And I pretend not any thing unto it;</l>
                     <l>Adiew.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Carlos</speaker>
                     <l>What without hearing me, oh ſtay,</l>
                     <l>I doe beſeech you, ſtay.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Iſabella.</speaker>
                     <l>My preſence here</l>
                     <l>Doth trouble you.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Carlos.</speaker>
                     <p>It is a reall truth.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Iſabella.</speaker>
                     <l>A reall truth,</l>
                     <l>Ingratefull?</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Carlos.</speaker>
                     <l>You shall not goe forth before</l>
                     <l>Y'ave heard me, ſuffer me upon this point</l>
                     <l>T'ex preſſe my thought.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Iſabella.</speaker>
                     <l>I should againe be troubled</l>
                     <l>With thy diſcourſe.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Carlos.</speaker>
                     <l>What I shall ſay unto you</l>
                     <l>Can eaſilie be verified.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Iſabella.</speaker>
                     <l>No, no,</l>
                     <l>I forbid thee to juſtifie thy ſelfe.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <pb n="80" facs="tcp:121249:41"/>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Carlos.</speaker>
                     <l>For the laſt time yet give me leave to ſay,</l>
                     <l>That it is you alone whom I adore,</l>
                     <l>That I am wholy yours.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Iſabella.</speaker>
                     <l>Well, let me ſee then,</l>
                     <l>If I have any power yet in thy ſoul.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Carlos</speaker>
                     <p>Madame, commaund, you shall be ſatiſfied.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Iſabella.</speaker>
                     <l>Say nothing more then to excuſe thy ſelfe,</l>
                     <l>And leave me to depart. this I command,</l>
                     <l>Obey me in this point.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Carlos.</speaker>
                     <l>For ſuch a perfect Lover as I am,</l>
                     <l>It is a crime t'obey too readilie.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Iſabella</speaker>
                     <l>No, no, I have ſome power upon thy ſpirit,</l>
                     <l>Shew thy reſpect by thy obedience,</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Carlos.</speaker>
                     <l>Love by reſpect is verie ill expreſſ'd,</l>
                     <l>Who can obey well, knoweth not to love,</l>
                     <l>This favourable councell, cruell Beautie,</l>
                     <l>Was given to Carlos.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Iſabella.</speaker>
                     <l>Yes to Carlos faithfull,</l>
                     <l>But this fatall adviſe, whereof thou doſt</l>
                     <l>Preſume ſo much, was never given vnto</l>
                     <l>Carlos inconſtant,</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Carlos.</speaker>
                     <p>Madame, what's my crime?</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Iſabella.</speaker>
                     <l>Ingratefull, I will tell it thee, tis true</l>
                     <l>I had for thee ſomething about my heart</l>
                     <l>That ſavoured of tendernes and that</l>
                     <l>I know not what began to differ little</l>
                     <pb n="81" facs="tcp:121249:41"/>
                     <l>From the toy called Love; at laſt I was</l>
                     <l>Tainted with that diſeaſe, when for my punishme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t</l>
                     <l>I knew my love produeed but thy hate;</l>
                     <l>True, thou feel'ſt it no more, now that thou ſeeſt</l>
                     <l>That I am touch'd; I become trouble ſome</l>
                     <l>To him that's deare to me; now that my flame</l>
                     <l>Appeares, thine is conſumed, and beginning</l>
                     <l>To love, I ceaſe to be belov'd. Belov'd?</l>
                     <l>what have I ſaid'? I learne by the effects,</l>
                     <l>That thou feigneſt alwaies, and did'ſt never love me</l>
                     <l>What canſt thou anſweare to excuſe thy ſelfe.</l>
                     <l>So juſt a reproach cannot but confound thee;</l>
                     <l>Thou ſtriv'ſt not more to juſtifie thy ſelfe,</l>
                     <l>Thy ſilence ſpeaks thee guilty and confounded.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Carlos.</speaker>
                     <l>This trouble which appeareth in my countenance</l>
                     <l>Proceeds from your injuſtice, not my crime.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Iſabella.</speaker>
                     <l>What have I ſaid here which thou canſt deny?</l>
                     <l>Defend thy ſelfe.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Carlos.</speaker>
                     <l>You have forbidden me</l>
                     <l>To juſtifie my ſelfe. I feare you would be</l>
                     <l>Offended ſtill with my diſcourſe.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Iſabella.</speaker>
                     <l>No, no</l>
                     <l>Speak, Carlos, now my anger's vanished;</l>
                     <l>Although thou shouldſt be falſe, and prove in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>conſtant.</l>
                     <l>In ſuch a high degree as to betray me,</l>
                     <l>I might co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>plaine thereof, but could not hate thee</l>
                     <l>And whatſoever change thy heart should make.</l>
                     <l>I should excuſe thee if thou didſt deſire it.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Carlos.</speaker>
                     <l>Vpon your faire hands for this ſweet expreſſion,</l>
                     <l>Let me imprint my joy, and my reſentment.</l>
                     <stage>He kiſſeth her hand.</stage>
                  </sp>
               </div>
               <div n="2" type="scene">
                  <pb n="82" facs="tcp:121249:42"/>
                  <head>SCENA SECUNDA.</head>
                  <stage>Alphonſo, Iſabella, Carloo.</stage>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Alphonſo.</speaker>
                     <p>WHat doe I ſee?</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Carlos.</speaker>
                     <l>But Madame, your ſuſpitions</l>
                     <l>Injute my love extremelie.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Iſabella.</speaker>
                     <l>My ſuſpitions</l>
                     <l>Give Carlos intimation that I love him.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Alphonſo.</speaker>
                     <p>You love him?</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Iſabella.</speaker>
                     <p>Heaven! what heare I?</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Carlos.</speaker>
                     <p>O hard Fortune!</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Iſabella.</speaker>
                     <l>I muſt diſpoſe my ſelfe to dye, he'll kill me — <stage>aſide</stage>
                     </l>
                     <l>Father.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Alphonſo.</speaker>
                     <l>Vnworthy object of my anger</l>
                     <l>In ſtly provoked, I'm thy enemie,</l>
                     <l>Call me no more thy Father: how! preſum'ſt thou</l>
                     <l>T'offend me in fo high degree as thus</l>
                     <l>Againſt the rules of reaſon and of honour</l>
                     <l>To come to Carlos at his houſe by night,</l>
                     <l>And in deſpiſing the Religious Cloyſter</l>
                     <l>Whereto I've deſtin'd thee, to give thy ſelfe</l>
                     <l>Over to baſe amours?</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Iſabella.</speaker>
                     <l>I doe beſeech you,</l>
                     <l>Heare me, graunt me that ſavour, will you, Sir</l>
                     <l>Refuſe me?</l>
                  </sp>
                  <pb n="83" facs="tcp:121249:42"/>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Alphonſo.</speaker>
                     <p>Yes, everie thing except death.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Carlos.</speaker>
                     <l>Heare equitic oppreſſed by my mouth,</l>
                     <l>If her flame be a crime, I m guilty onelie;</l>
                     <l>Yes if it be a fault, daigne to remember,</l>
                     <l>That I am the cauſe on't, and whom you ought</l>
                     <l>Onelie to punish, be more juſt without</l>
                     <l>Being more gentle, ſave the innocent.</l>
                     <l>And deſtroy the offender.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Iſabella.</speaker>
                     <l>No, againſt me</l>
                     <l>Bend all your furie, if it be a crime</l>
                     <l>To love, it is a vertue to be loved:</l>
                     <l>The tendernes which I reſent for Carlos</l>
                     <l>Denotes his merit, and ſetts forth my weaknes:</l>
                     <l>And if my paſſion be worthy death,</l>
                     <l>Carlos is free, and I alone am guilty.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Alphonſo.</speaker>
                     <p>Perfidious, thou shalt dye then.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Carlos</speaker>
                     <l>Oh, abandon</l>
                     <l>That thought.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Alphonſo.</speaker>
                     <l>Then Carlos with my honour take</l>
                     <l>Away my life, that is the onely way</l>
                     <l>To make her crime ſafe; nothing but my death</l>
                     <l>Can ſtop her punishment.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Carlos.</speaker>
                     <l>Feare nothing from me,</l>
                     <l>I have reſpect for you, and ſince I could not</l>
                     <l>Appeaſe your anger. I oppoſe no further</l>
                     <l>But rather preſſe you now that <hi>Iſabella</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>May perish</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Iſabella</speaker>
                     <l>How? doe you preſſe my deſtruction?</l>
                     <l>Oh now's the fatall moment, wherein I</l>
                     <pb n="84" facs="tcp:121249:43"/>
                     <l>Have juſt cauſe to complaine of deſtiniie</l>
                     <l>My heart is peirc'd with griefe to ſee you here</l>
                     <l>With ſuch injuſtice to become my judge,</l>
                     <l>And not my complice. I was well reſolv'd,</l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Carlos,</hi> to dye, and quarrell'd not with fate,</l>
                     <l>So long as I thought to expire for thee;</l>
                     <l>But I believed not in this adventure</l>
                     <l>That Love aſwell as Nature would betray me,</l>
                     <l>And that I should at laſt goe to the grave</l>
                     <l>Thus by a Fathers ſtroak, and Lovers ſentence.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Carlos.</speaker>
                     <l>Madame, I've ſayd but what I should have ſayd:</l>
                     <l>Once more I doe repeate it, ſince your daughter</l>
                     <l>Muſt dye, Sir, and I cannot hinder it,</l>
                     <l>Content your ſelfe to ſtrike, but pray miſtake not</l>
                     <l>The boſome, heere direct your ſtroaks, tis heere</l>
                     <l>That <hi>Iſabella's</hi> lodg'd, heere she is Miſtreſſe,</l>
                     <l>Heere she is criminall, heere you muſt aſſault her</l>
                     <l>To punish her, and in peircing my heart,</l>
                     <l>You cannot miſſe her.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Iſabella.</speaker>
                     <l>Oh, believe him not;</l>
                     <l>Turne your armes here.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <stage>Alphonſo aſide.</stage>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Alphonſo.</speaker>
                     <l>Readie to shed my blood,</l>
                     <l>I feel my teares flow, and my choler's cold:</l>
                     <l>I onelie by a ſudden ſtrange effect</l>
                     <l>Am vanquish'd in the fight, let us feigne yet,</l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Carlos,</hi> your cunning for a little time</l>
                     <l>Retards her Puniſhment, but fatisfy me</l>
                     <l>Vpon a thing that brought me heere, and wick</l>
                     <l>Doth trouble me extreemely tell me truelie,</l>
                     <l>Is my Sonne here, or no; if he be here,</l>
                     <l>His death is but too certaine.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Carlos.</speaker>
                     <l>I aſſure you,</l>
                     <pb n="85" facs="tcp:121249:43"/>
                     <l>He is not here, Sir.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Alphonſo.</speaker>
                     <l>Since you doe aſſure me,</l>
                     <l>I will not doubt it.</l>
                  </sp>
               </div>
               <div n="3" type="scene">
                  <head>SCENA TERTIA.</head>
                  <stage>Fabritio, Alphonſo, Climene, Carlos, Iſabella.</stage>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Fabritio.</speaker>
                     <l>WE are free at laſt</l>
                     <l>From the <hi>Dukes</hi> hands.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Alphonſo.</speaker>
                     <l>O Heaven! iſt poſſible?</l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Fabritio</hi> yet preſent him to mine eyes?</l>
                     <l>I gave, Sir, too much credit to your words. — <stage>to Carlos,</stage>
                     </l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Carlos.</speaker>
                     <p>He was not here, Sir, when I ſaid them to you,</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Alphonſo.</speaker>
                     <l>Thou blinded Sonne, through what ingratitude</l>
                     <l>Build'ſt thou thy pleaſures upon my diſquiet?</l>
                     <l>VVhat hath made thee deſpiſe a Fathers Will,</l>
                     <l>whom thou know'ſt cherisheth thy life ſo much</l>
                     <l>And why in violating all the rights</l>
                     <l>Of nature, doſt thou make ſo ſmall accompt</l>
                     <l>Of the light which thou oweſt me? Ingratefull?</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Fabritio.</speaker>
                     <l>The care, Sir, of my ſafetie troubleeh you</l>
                     <l>Too much, I doe not hate the light, but love is</l>
                     <l>Leſſe then <hi>Climene.</hi>
                     </l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Alphonſo.</speaker>
                     <l>I commanded thee</l>
                     <l>To quit this reſidence.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <pb n="86" facs="tcp:121249:44"/>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Fabritio.</speaker>
                     <l>But I receiv'd</l>
                     <l>Another order.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Alphonſo.</speaker>
                     <p>How! from whom?</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Fabritio.</speaker>
                     <p>From Love.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Alphonſo.</speaker>
                     <l>Love makes no lawes but for thoſe that will take 'em;</l>
                     <l>And reaſon now forbiddeth thee to embrace it</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Fabritio.</speaker>
                     <l>Oh reaſon, Sir, had left me, and I was</l>
                     <l>Too much enchained, to depart.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Alphonſo.</speaker>
                     <l>Canſt thou</l>
                     <l>Stay without shame, after an infidelitie?</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Fabritio.</speaker>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Climene</hi> is as conſtant as she's faire:</l>
                     <l>My ſpirit was ſtruck with an injuſt ſuſpition,</l>
                     <l>I'm diſabuſed, and she's readie heere</l>
                     <l>To follow me.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Alphonſo.</speaker>
                     <p>To follow thee?</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Climene.</speaker>
                     <l>Yes Sir,</l>
                     <l>To follow him, I have engag'd my ſelfe;</l>
                     <l>Though his condition be chang'd, I am not.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Alphonſo.</speaker>
                     <l>I alwaies doubted till this very moment.</l>
                     <l>Whether a woman could love conſtantly;</l>
                     <l>But if your love hath any reaſon with it,</l>
                     <l>Haſte you to goe out of his fatall cuntry.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Fabritio.</speaker>
                     <l>There's nothing that shall ſtop my ſtepps to mor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>row</l>
                     <l>Sir, I ſweare to you. —</l>
                  </sp>
                  <pb n="87" facs="tcp:121249:44"/>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Carlos.</speaker>
                     <p>Friend, thou shalt not ſweare.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Fabritio.</speaker>
                     <l>If you believe it not, I doe aſſure you,</l>
                     <l>You are in an extreme errour; who can ſtay us?</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Carlos.</speaker>
                     <p>Pehaps, It may be I.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Fabritio.</speaker>
                     <p>You?</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Carlos.</speaker>
                     <l>Yes, I will</l>
                     <l>Tell you a ſad adventure, which should be</l>
                     <l>Equallie grievous to us both; <hi>Climene</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>Is by a fatall chaunce committed to</l>
                     <l>My guard, and I'm reſponſible for her.</l>
                     <l>I've the Dukes order for it, and to add</l>
                     <l>To the misfortune, I thought to have taken</l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Climene,</hi> and I took your ſiſter for her.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Iſabella.</speaker>
                     <l>What! this was then the cauſe which troubled you</l>
                     <l>So much but now?</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Carlos.</speaker>
                     <l>You have but little reaſon</l>
                     <l>To doubt of it; but underſtand my trouble</l>
                     <l>In this extremitie, if <hi>Climene</hi> flyes,</l>
                     <l>I shall be forc'd to expoſe <hi>Iſabella</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>Inſtead of her to <hi>the</hi> Dukes paſſions:</l>
                     <l>I love her, and tis now no longer time</l>
                     <l>To diſguiſe my thoughts to you, Iudge, I pray you,</l>
                     <l>If in this daunger I ought to expoſe her.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Fabritio.</speaker>
                     <p>How great is our misfortune?</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Alphonſo.</speaker>
                     <l>Not ſo great</l>
                     <l>As it appeares unto you; to be free</l>
                     <l>Of all ſcare, get ye gone all foure togeither.</l>
                     <pb n="88" facs="tcp:121249:45"/>
                     <l>The Duke will be reduced afterward</l>
                     <l>To be appeas'd.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Carlos.</speaker>
                     <l>This is a moſt ſure way;</l>
                     <l>But whence proceeds this noiſe?</l>
                  </sp>
               </div>
               <div n="4" type="scene">
                  <head>SCENA QUARTA.</head>
                  <stage>
                     <hi>Celin, Alphonſo, Carlos, Fabritio, Climeno, Iſabella, Celin</hi> to <hi>Carlos.</hi>
                  </stage>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Colin.</speaker>
                     <l>Sir, diverſe men</l>
                     <l>Armed with halberds deſire ſpeech with you.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Carlos.</speaker>
                     <l>Tis the Duke and his Guards, ſure, their deſigne</l>
                     <l>Surpriſeth me.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Alphonſo.</speaker>
                     <l>I have loſt all my hope.</l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Carlos,</hi> aſſuredly my ſonne's diſcover'd.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Carlos</speaker>
                     <l>We will be preſently cleer'd on that point.</l>
                     <l>Without light let <hi>Fabritio</hi> ſtay heere,</l>
                     <l>And if he doubts that they are come to ſeek him</l>
                     <l>Behind this falſe wall he may hide himſelfe:</l>
                     <stage>He shewes them a wall which is turn'd upon a pivot of Iron.</stage>
                     <l>See, how it turnes; before his death my Father</l>
                     <l>Fearing the malice of his enemies,</l>
                     <l>Cauſed it to be made in ſecret for him,</l>
                     <l>And I know that there is no wit ſo ſubtle,</l>
                     <l>That can finde out <hi>Fabritio</hi> in this place.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Alphonſo.</speaker>
                     <p>To ſave thy life, doe this, Sonne, I conjure thee;</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Climene.</speaker>
                     <p>And I <hi>Climene</hi> pray thee.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <pb n="89" facs="tcp:121249:45"/>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Fabritio.</speaker>
                     <l>I obey</l>
                     <l>As ſonne, and I obey no leſſe as Lover.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Carlos.</speaker>
                     <p>Let's ceaſe diſcourſe, and goe forth preſently.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <stage>
                     <hi>Exeunt all but</hi> Fabritio.</stage>
                  <stage>Fabritio alone.</stage>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Fabritio.</speaker>
                     <l>Heaven! muſt I alwaies be diſtracted thus</l>
                     <l>Twixt feare and hope, and muſt ſo juſt a love</l>
                     <l>Have ſuch a rigid fortune? the Duke loves,</l>
                     <l>Or abhorres her, and I know that there's reaſon</l>
                     <l>To feare all things from him that hopeth nothing;</l>
                     <l>And that? bove all things it is daungerous</l>
                     <l>To be competitor with his Prince, and Rivall</l>
                     <l>Vnto his Maſter. But what<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap> heare I not</l>
                     <l>Some perſon walke, at if he would come to me?</l>
                  </sp>
               </div>
               <div n="5" type="scene">
                  <head>SCENA QUINTA.</head>
                  <stage>The Duke, Fabritio.</stage>
                  <stage>The Duke alone.</stage>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Duke.</speaker>
                     <l>I've paſſed through a ſtreight way, now I enter</l>
                     <l>Into a greater, yet am ſtill in doubt,</l>
                     <l>My hope's confounded, and my ſpirits dark,</l>
                     <l>Which should light me in theſe obſcurities?</l>
                     <l>Am I'mongſt mortalls? am I in ſome cave?</l>
                     <l>Am I upon the earth, or in is center?</l>
                     <l>Murthered <hi>Fabritio</hi> offereth himſelfe</l>
                     <l>To my remembrance, would Heaven punish me</l>
                     <l>For his unjuſt death? but I heare a noyſe,</l>
                     <l>Who's there?</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Fabritio.</speaker>
                     <p>
                        <hi>Fabritio.</hi>
                     </p>
                  </sp>
                  <pb n="90" facs="tcp:121249:46"/>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Duke.</speaker>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Fabritio!</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>Appeares his <hi>Fantaſme</hi> heere then for my punish<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment,</l>
                     <l>And am I ſunk downe into Hell alive</l>
                     <l>To ſuffer for the evills I've made him ſuffer?</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Fabritio.</speaker>
                     <l>I heare the <hi>Dukes</hi> voice, which I know full well.</l>
                     <l>Is it you then, Sir Duke?</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Duke.</speaker>
                     <l>Th' art not deceiv'd.</l>
                     <l>I am the authour of thy death, I will not</l>
                     <l>Say any thing unto thee for to ſave</l>
                     <l>My life, thou canſt without crime take it fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> him</l>
                     <l>Who hath tane thine from thee, all the feare which</l>
                     <l>Reſteth unto me in this ſad misfortune,</l>
                     <l>Proceedeth from my crime, not from my death;</l>
                     <l>And if now any griefe oppreſſeth me,</l>
                     <l>Tis not to dye, but to dye culpable.</l>
                     <stage>Fabritio aſide.</stage>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Fabritio.</speaker>
                     <l>He thinks me ſtill dead, I will profit by</l>
                     <l>This errour. — <stage>aſide.</stage>
                     </l>
                     <l>Duke, you have juſt cauſe to feare</l>
                     <l>My furie, your fate now is in my power,</l>
                     <l>Nothing can ſtop the courſe of my revenge;</l>
                     <l>I can now ſacrifice your blood to mine;</l>
                     <l>But, Sit, you are my Prince, and I le not doe it;</l>
                     <l>Injuſtice I abhorre, and notwithſtanding</l>
                     <l>My anger, I would rather ſuffer it</l>
                     <l>Then execute it.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Duke.</speaker>
                     <l>The mote thy reſpect</l>
                     <l>Appeares for me, the more unjuſt's thy death</l>
                     <l>And the more black my crime; by this, my fault</l>
                     <l>Becomes doubly condemnable, the leſſe</l>
                     <pb n="91" facs="tcp:121249:46"/>
                     <l>Sevete thou art in punishing me, the more</l>
                     <l>I'm worthy punishment. But if thy shadow</l>
                     <l>Pretendeth to reſpect me, what obligeth thee</l>
                     <l>To perſecute me thus in everie place?</l>
                     <l>How comes it that thou doſt conferre upon me</l>
                     <l>Imperfect favouts? why doſt thou purſue me?</l>
                     <l>What iſt thou doſt deſire?</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Fabritio.</speaker>
                     <l>Since you ordaine it</l>
                     <l>I'le ſpeake it then; know, Sir, that this your trou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble</l>
                     <l>Shall never ſee an end before you ceaſe,</l>
                     <l>To love <hi>Climene.</hi>
                     </l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Duke.</speaker>
                     <l>Ceaſe to love <hi>Climene?</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>Oh! that's too much preſumption, I may ceaſe</l>
                     <l>To live, but not to love her, to obtaine</l>
                     <l>Thy wishes, thou shouldſt ask a poſſible thing;</l>
                     <l>But I should have abus'd thee if I had</l>
                     <l>Flattered thy hope that I would ceaſe to love</l>
                     <l>That charming Beautie.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Fabritio.</speaker>
                     <l>To love in this manner</l>
                     <l>Is to love like a tyrant.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Duke.</speaker>
                     <l>Well, I know</l>
                     <l>That I love like a tyrant, but no matter:</l>
                     <l>Know alſo that. Love who gives Law to me,</l>
                     <l>Is yet a blinder tyrant farre then I:</l>
                     <l>To force me to love this ingratefull Miſtreſſe,</l>
                     <l>He hath to much ſtrength, and I soo much weak<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes</l>
                     <l>Onelie the hope that I can give thee is,</l>
                     <l>Never to ſee her more, yet ſtill to love her.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Fabritio.</speaker>
                     <l>He that can loſe the object, can loſe alſo</l>
                     <l>The flame, the heart houlds not what the eye is</l>
                     <pb n="92" facs="tcp:121249:47"/>
                     <l>Depriv'd of, Love from our will hath his power;</l>
                     <l>To ceaſe to love, there needs but the deſire:</l>
                     <l>To put out all your flames, quench all your hope,</l>
                     <l>And yeild <hi>Climene</hi> to my conſtancie.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Duke.</speaker>
                     <p>But if I should doe ſo, what's thy deſigne?</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Fabritio.</speaker>
                     <p>To marrie her.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Duke.</speaker>
                     <l>To marrie her? what! art thou</l>
                     <l>Not dead then?</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Fabritio.</speaker>
                     <p>What have I ſaid?</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Duke.</speaker>
                     <l>Thou shouldſt be</l>
                     <l>O'th' number of the living for this works;</l>
                     <l>Who cherisheth a body, muſt not be</l>
                     <l>A shadow. Speak, and believe that thy death</l>
                     <l>Hath coſt me teares.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Fabritio.</speaker>
                     <l>He feigneth for to knowe me,</l>
                     <l>And to deſtroy me afterward. — <stage>aſide.</stage>
                     </l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Duke.</speaker>
                     <l>He anſweareth not a word; Lets ſeek about.</l>
                     <l>But leaſt he should goe forth, 'tis requiſite</l>
                     <l>To keepe this porte: to know too where I am,</l>
                     <l>Tis beſt to make a noyſe; hola! who's there?</l>
                     <l>Some one come to me.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Fabritio.</speaker>
                     <l>Heaven! whereto am I</l>
                     <l>Reduc'd? but let me, ere they bring a light</l>
                     <l>Advaunce to wards the wall, and hide my ſelfe</l>
                     <l>Behind it.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Duke.</speaker>
                     <l>I'le be cleered in this doubt,</l>
                     <l>Heere comes a light.</l>
                  </sp>
               </div>
               <div n="6" type="scene">
                  <pb n="93" facs="tcp:121249:47"/>
                  <head>SCENA SEXTA.</head>
                  <stage>The Duke, Carlos, Alphonſo, Valerio, Climene, Iſabella, Guards.</stage>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Climene.</speaker>
                     <p>DOe we not ſee the Duke?</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Duke.</speaker>
                     <p>See I againe my Miſtreſſe?</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Valerio.</speaker>
                     <l>Oh! we ſought</l>
                     <l>Your Highneſſe everie where.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Duke.</speaker>
                     <l>Is this enchantment?</l>
                     <l>Where am I?</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Carlos.</speaker>
                     <p>In my houſe.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Duke.</speaker>
                     <p>But where is he?</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Alphonſo.</speaker>
                     <p>Who, Sir?</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Duke.</speaker>
                     <p>Your Sonne.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Alphonſo.</speaker>
                     <l>My Sonne.</l>
                     <l>Your Highnes is abus'd.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Duke.</speaker>
                     <l>I've ſpeaken with him;</l>
                     <l>Vſe no deceit towards me.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Alphonſo.</speaker>
                     <p>Thoſe are viſions.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Duke.</speaker>
                     <l>They are truths, but he can't come forth, ſeek ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>refully</l>
                     <l>On everie ſide.</l>
                     <pb n="94" facs="tcp:121249:48"/>
                     <stage>Alphonſo <hi>ſpeaking to</hi> Carlos.</stage>
                     <l>Oh <hi>Carlos</hi> how I feare!</l>
                     <stage>Carlos <hi>addresſing himſelfe to</hi> Alphonſo.</stage>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Carlos.</speaker>
                     <p>I ſay, be not afraid.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Valerio.</speaker>
                     <p>Sir, I've ſeene nothing.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Duke.</speaker>
                     <l>Heaven! what new prodegie is this? Iudge all</l>
                     <l>If I have reaſon to believe my ſelfe</l>
                     <l>Enchanted: I went forth the garden, thinking</l>
                     <l>To ſee before mine eyes <hi>Fabritios</hi> Ghoſt,</l>
                     <l>When ſuddenlie I fell into a precipice;</l>
                     <l>And paſſing through places which I know not,</l>
                     <l>Arriv'd heere, where to encreaſe the horrour</l>
                     <l>Of my ſad ſoule, his shadow once againe</l>
                     <l>Appear'd before me, ſpake long time unto me,</l>
                     <l>And uſ'd perſuaſions to make me ceaſe</l>
                     <l>To love <hi>Climene,</hi> and to yeild her to him.</l>
                     <l>This diſcourſe gave me much incertaintie</l>
                     <l>Of his condition; I doubted if</l>
                     <l>He was dead; but ſurpriſed and amaz'd</l>
                     <l>By this ſucceſſe, I need no more to doubt it.</l>
                     <l>Would that it plaſed Heaven he were alive,</l>
                     <l>I should be free then of that ſad remorſe</l>
                     <l>Which wounds my conſcience, I would doe him juſtice,</l>
                     <l>And banishing my fires, would ſatiſfie</l>
                     <l>My ſelfe in rendering him happy.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Alphonſo.</speaker>
                     <l>Sir,</l>
                     <l>It is an eaſie generoſity</l>
                     <l>To lament, an oppreſſed enemie</l>
                     <l>That is no longer to be fear'd, you think</l>
                     <l>My ſonne dead, and on that accompt, bewaile him,</l>
                     <l>But if he were alive indead, you would</l>
                     <l>Be leſſe humane.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <pb n="95" facs="tcp:121249:48"/>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Duke.</speaker>
                     <l>I would not break my word.</l>
                     <l>By Heaven, by faire <hi>Climene,</hi> by all nature,</l>
                     <l>I ſweare to you <hi>Alphonſo,</hi> that if now</l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Fabritio</hi> yet alive should by a miracle.</l>
                     <l>Appeare before mine eyes, ſo farre would I</l>
                     <l>Be from oppoſing ſtill his juſt deſires</l>
                     <l>That I would willing lie reſigne unto him.</l>
                     <l>That Beautie ſo belou'd and Cherished.</l>
                  </sp>
               </div>
               <div n="7" type="scene">
                  <head>SCENA SEPTIMA.</head>
                  <stage>Fabritio, The Duke, Alphonſo, Carlos, Climeno, Iſabella, Valorio, Guards.</stage>
                  <stage>Fabritio <hi>comming forth from behind the falſe wall.</hi>
                  </stage>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Fabritio.</speaker>
                     <l>Behould me living then, moſt generous Prince,</l>
                     <l>Feep your word and your oath, and make me happie.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Duke.</speaker>
                     <p>Is this a <hi>Fantaſme?</hi> Heaven!</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Alphonſo.</speaker>
                     <l>Shake of your feare.</l>
                     <l>It is <hi>Fabritio</hi> living, and his death</l>
                     <l>Is but a feigned thing.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Fabritio.</speaker>
                     <l>Sir, at your feete</l>
                     <l>I humbly doe expect the bleſt effect</l>
                     <l>Of what you promiſed.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Duke.</speaker>
                     <l>I'le keepe my word,</l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Climene's</hi> yours.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Alphonſo.</speaker>
                     <l>Sir, favour my poore familie</l>
                     <l>In everie point, givs <hi>Carlos</hi> too in marriage</l>
                     <l>Vnto my daughter, and approve with me</l>
                     <l>Their innocent deſires,</l>
                  </sp>
                  <pb n="96" facs="tcp:121249:49"/>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Carlos.</speaker>
                     <l>I humble crave</l>
                     <l>That favour from your Highneſſe</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Duke.</speaker>
                     <l>I conſent to't;</l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Carlos,</hi> enjoy your wish, although I am</l>
                     <l>Deceived by your artifice; but loſing</l>
                     <l>My Miſtreſſe, I loſe my injuſtice too:</l>
                     <l>In not betraying me, you did betray</l>
                     <l>My glorie, who commands ill, should be ill</l>
                     <l>Obey'd', unjuſt deſignes may juſtly be</l>
                     <l>Deſtroy'd: Come follow me, and whilſt your joyes</l>
                     <l>Are making readie, rell me by what Art</l>
                     <l>The Amourous <hi>Fantaſme</hi> plaid his ſubtle part.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <trailer>The End of the fifth and laſt Act.</trailer>
               </div>
            </div>
         </div>
         <div type="epilogue">
            <head>EPILOGUE to the Court.</head>
            <sp>
               <l>LEt me Star gaze a while, and calculate</l>
               <l>Thoſe Heavens, to know our fortune, or our fate</l>
               <l>Before I dare to ſpeak; I cannot ſee</l>
               <l>One cloud appeare that should diſcourage me;</l>
               <l>Tis a good omen: Faire Queen of this night,</l>
               <l>Not Cynthia, but a Goddeſſe far more bright,</l>
               <l>To you I kneel. From him, whoſe glory is</l>
               <l>To offer you a pleaſing Sacrifice,</l>
               <l>I meane th' ambitious Poet I am come,</l>
               <l>Humbly to begg a favourable doome</l>
               <l>Vpon his <hi>Fantaſme,</hi> who although he be</l>
               <l>At the full point of his felicity</l>
               <l>A perfect body now, yet if you frowne</l>
               <l>Vpon his action, and ſo cry him downe,</l>
               <l>No more a feigned <hi>Fantaſme</hi> to be made,</l>
               <l>He dyes indead, and flyes into a shade.</l>
            </sp>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
