<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>The rebellion of Naples or the tragedy of Massenello· commonly so called: but rightly Tomaso Aniello di Malfa Generall of the Neopolitans. Written by a gentleman who was an eye-witnes where this was really acted upon that bloudy stage, the streets of Naples. Anno Domini MDCXLVII.</title>
            <author>T. B.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1649</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 160 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 44 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2012-10">2012-10 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A76435</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing B199</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Thomason E1358_2</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R12266</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99859247</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99859247</idno>
            <idno type="VID">111318</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A76435)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 111318)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Thomason Tracts ; 179:E1358[2])</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>The rebellion of Naples or the tragedy of Massenello· commonly so called: but rightly Tomaso Aniello di Malfa Generall of the Neopolitans. Written by a gentleman who was an eye-witnes where this was really acted upon that bloudy stage, the streets of Naples. Anno Domini MDCXLVII.</title>
                  <author>T. B.</author>
                  <author>M., engraver.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[8], 77, [3] p., folded plate   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>for J.G. &amp; G.B at Furnivals-Inne Gate in Holborne,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>Printed at London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>MDCIL. [1649]</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Dedication signed: T.B.</note>
                  <note>Frontispiece signed: M. sculp.</note>
                  <note>Most running titles read: The rebellion of Naples, or, The tragedie of Massenello.</note>
                  <note>The last leaf is blank.</note>
                  <note>Annotation on Thomason copy: "July 12.".</note>
                  <note>Reproductions of the originals in the Henry E. Huntington Library and Art Gallery (Early English books) and in the British Library (Thomason Tracts).</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Masaniello, 1620-1647 --  Drama --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Naples (Italy) --  History --  17th century --  Drama --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2011-09</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-09</date>
            <label>Apex CoVantage</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-11</date>
            <label>Jayanthi Reddy</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-11</date>
            <label>Jayanthi Reddy</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-05</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:111318:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p> THE Rebellion of NAPLES, OR THE TRAGEDY OF MASSENELLO.</p>
            <p>Commonly ſo called: But Rightly TOMASO ANIELLO DI MALFA <hi>Generall of the</hi> Neopolitans.</p>
            <p>WRITTEN By a Gentleman who was an eye-witnes where this was really Acted upon that bloudy Stage, the ſtreets of NAPLES.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anno Domini MDC XL VII.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Nec labore, nec judicio, nec magnanimitate, nec in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>telligentia: ſed jungantur &amp; tunc maxima obtineantur.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Printed at <hi>London</hi> for <hi>J. G.</hi> &amp; <hi>G. B</hi> at <hi>Furnivals-Inne Gate</hi> in <hi>Holborne, MDC II.</hi>
            </p>
         </div>
         <div type="frontispiece">
            <pb facs="tcp:111318:2"/>
            <p>
               <figure>
                  <figDesc>depiction of a man holding a baton and speaking, in front of imagery of a battlefield.</figDesc>
                  <q>Acchiappato il peste viala rete</q>
                  <q>
                     <lg>
                        <l>The Fiſ is caught, the Net is under foot,</l>
                        <l>Whil'st Fool's cry Shal I, Shall I, these goe to't.</l>
                        <l>The silly Fiſ, whil'st left but the least water,</l>
                        <l>And can see through the Net, think it no matter</l>
                        <l>But Sacrifice to' th' Net, where in they'v caught:</l>
                        <l>Burne Incence to the Drag, that thus has wrought</l>
                        <l>All their Destruction: Neither doe they dread,</l>
                        <l>The Divine Vengeance that is or'e their head.</l>
                        <l>And ne're will think themselves meet Fiſh to fry,</l>
                        <l>Till great TOMASO, draws, the CY<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 span">
                              <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                           </gap>
                        </l>
                     </lg>
                  </q>
               </figure>
            </p>
            <pb facs="tcp:111318:2" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
               <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
            </gap>
            <pb facs="tcp:111318:3"/>
         </div>
         <div type="dedication">
            <pb facs="tcp:111318:3"/>
            <head>TO <hi>The Right Worſhipfull his Honoured Kins-man,</hi> John Caeſar <hi>of</hi> Hyde hall, <hi>in the County of</hi> Hert<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ford, <hi>Eſquire.</hi>
            </head>
            <opener>
               <salute>Sir,</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>Here are many reaſons wherefore I ſhould dedicate this Tragedy to your ſelfe: and let great <hi>Tomaſo,</hi> fall at no other feet then yours: The one is, I attained to the obſervation of all the particulars at your charge; and reaſon it is, that I ſhould tender to none other but your ſelf, the fruites which grew upon the fien that was grafted upon your ſtocke. So that my writings, and <hi>Tomaſoes</hi> fall, are both tributes which belong to <hi>Caeſar.</hi> The moſt famous Poets that ever had a being,
<pb facs="tcp:111318:4"/> were never ſo wel pleaſed with their grea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſt Patrons, as I am with mine: they who had the beſt, had onely <hi>Caeſars,</hi> to be Judges of their Poems excellence: but I have <hi>Caeſar</hi> not onely to be my Judge, but a witneſſe alſo of the truth of what I write: nor can I fear the cenſure of any inferiors, after that I have made my appeale to <hi>Cae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſar.</hi> Sir, there is another reaſon which is occaſioned by the remembrance of an <hi>I<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>talian</hi> Proverbe.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Reſpetto ſon le ballie di charetza,</hi> Reſpect is the nurſer of friendſhip. Sir, wee have been Comrades together through divers Countries, we have been joynt-purchaſers of many favours, and honours; and fellow-ſufferers of as many miſeries: wee have waded hand in hand together, through the greateſt dangers, and (guided onely by ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſity) fording through deepe and run<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning rivers of calamities we were carried down the ſtream into an ocean of perplex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ities, out of which we were at laſt caſt up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on an Iſland, which upon our arrivall wee ſoon found to be our own. Such Paſſages
<pb facs="tcp:111318:4"/> as theſe, as they could not be otherwiſe then mutual obligations to one another of the higheſt nature, ſo they could be no leſſe then the higheſt motives to the grea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſt love. Now to foſter up this iſſue of travaile, to a full proportion of reſpect, whereby this friendſhip ſhould be main<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tained, I thought good to preſerve it from ſuch an oblivion, as theſe thin paper walls will give me leave, and to Dedicate both my ſelfe and it to be always ready at your commands, who am,</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>Couſen, <hi>Your moſt faithfull Servant,</hi> T. B.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="to_the_reader">
            <pb facs="tcp:111318:5"/>
            <head>To the Reader.</head>
            <p>THough this Tragedy (for the exiſtent part there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of, and ſetting the liberty which Poets uſe to aſſume to themſelves aſide, as their birth-right by the lawes of Poetry) be true, and reall, and a worke both begun and finiſhed in a ſtrange Country, and by a ſtranger to theſe proceedings, yet I am perſwaded that there are ſome, who will not beleeve otherwiſe, but that I uſe Duck policy in my writing, who hiding her head under the water, diſcovers her own nakednes. <hi>Caput inter nubila condit.</hi> Saith another, I warrant you this man drives at notable and remarkable paſſages of State, if we could underſtand him. And though <hi>Naples</hi> be the Scene, yet he plaſters his bills upon the walls and gates of <hi>London.</hi> Truly I know a pick-lock can do no harme to the doore where there is no key to any locke: and if there be any thing in my booke which points at the preſent condition of our affairs, I aſſure you the times are buſie with me, and not I with the times. Types muſt agree with their antitypes, like a paire of Inden<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures, which being compared together ſeem one and the ſame, ſo if you take the whole ſubſtance of this Trage<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy and compare it with our tranſactions, you will finde that the ſame pen-knife never went between them, if there be any thing therefore that contents you, fare wel; But if ye cry rost-meate where there is no dinner, you ſhal have knotted bulruſhes for your Sallet.</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>Your Servant. T. B.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="list_of_actors">
            <pb facs="tcp:111318:5"/>
            <head>The names of the ſeverall Actors.</head>
            <list>
               <item>D. <hi>Di Arcas</hi> Vice Roy of Naples.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Antonio</hi> Sonne to the Vice Roy.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Cardinall Filomerino</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Duke di Mattaloone.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>rſino</hi> Lord Chamberlaine.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Montalto</hi> Lord Controller.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Maſſenello</hi> the Generall.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Genuino</hi> Secretary to <hi>Maſſenello.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Lord Treaſurer,</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Father Antony</hi> the Hermite.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Eletto di popolo.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Peron</hi> Captaine of the Bandites.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Don Peppe</hi> Brother to the Duke.</item>
               <item>Sig. <hi>Burlameo</hi> an Ingineir, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
               </item>
            </list>
            <list>
               <head>The names of the Women Actors.</head>
               <item>
                  <hi>Mariamma</hi> Mother to the Generall.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Agatha</hi> Wife to the Generall.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Flora</hi> Eldeſt daughter to the Generall by a former wife.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>rſula</hi> Youngeſt daughter by this wife.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Bonella</hi> an old woman flatterer.</item>
            </list>
         </div>
         <div type="prologue">
            <pb facs="tcp:111318:6"/>
            <head>Prologue.</head>
            <l>COurt'ous ſpectators, you muſt know that he</l>
            <l>Who is the writer of this Tragedy.</l>
            <l>Was actor and ſpectator in't: who means,</l>
            <l>Here to preſent it into <hi>Acts</hi> and Scaenes:</l>
            <l>If you are pleas'd with truth, the ſtorie's true,</l>
            <l>And if with novelties, the ſubject's new,</l>
            <l>If wonders do delight ye: on this Stage</l>
            <l>Acted's the greateſt wonder of our age.</l>
            <l>Or if you'r pleas'd with ſeaſonable things,</l>
            <l>Here's fightings 'twixt the people and their Kings.</l>
            <l>Or if ſad melancholy hath you ſent</l>
            <l>Hither for paſtime, here is merriment.</l>
            <l>And if truth, wonder, novelties, mirth, ſeaſon</l>
            <l>Do not content you, ſirs, you have no reaſon.</l>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="play">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:111318:6"/>
            <head>THE REBELLION OF NAPLES.</head>
            <div n="1" type="act">
               <head>ACTUS I.</head>
               <div n="1" type="scene">
                  <head>SCENA I.</head>
                  <stage>
                     <hi>Enter Father</hi> Anthony, <hi>the Prophetick Eremite, all hairy, and a deaths head under his arm; he fals a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſleep upon his ſtaffe, awakes and ſpeaks.</hi>
                  </stage>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Fa: Ant.</speaker>
                     <p>
                        <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg> Shall not be able to get into any Cell: ſuch another fit of drow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſineſſe fell upon me, when I ſaw the Viſion of the Sun, which the moſt Catholique King wears for his Creſt, run back ſo many de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>grees—then was I—as I am now—ready to drop down with heavineſſe: he that cannot hold up any longer, muſt needs lie down.</p>
                     <stage>
                        <pb n="2" facs="tcp:111318:7"/> He lies down, laying his head upon his deaths head, and ſleeps, whil'ſt the Vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion is appearing Muſick plaies, and this Song, as a Chorus, is ſinging all the while.</stage>
                  </sp>
                  <lg>
                     <head>SONG.</head>
                     <l>This is the ſtate of Kingly Glory,</l>
                     <l>Kings they are but tranſitory:</l>
                     <l>Beggars they aſcend the Throne,</l>
                     <l>Vengeance light on every one.</l>
                     <l>They w'had all things at their beck,</l>
                     <l>Here they ride, and break their neck.</l>
                     <l>Riſe, O King, and nere relent,</l>
                     <l>Here's a Throne from Heaven ſent;</l>
                     <l>With a Scepter, Crown and Ball;</l>
                     <l>Longeſt Liver muſt take all.</l>
                     <l>Abundant riches ſhall ſhow'r down:</l>
                     <l>Then go fetch another Crown.</l>
                  </lg>
                  <stage>Whil'ſt this Song is in ſinging, there appears a Viſion of little Boyes: One whereof, King-like, in War-like ſtate, aſcends the Throne; after that, a Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pany of Beggar-boyes pull down the King, throwing him to the ground, ſnatch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing away his Crown, Globe and Scepter, who lies in a trance; the Beggar-boyes all in cluſters get up into, and upon the Throne: The Throne breaks, it thun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders and lightens, and they all run away. After that, melodious muſick; the King riſes up, ſtands dejectedly, whil'ſt a Throne deſcends from above, with a Crown, Globe and Scepter in it; he aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſaies
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:111318:7"/> the Crown, and ſettles it upon his head; he takes the Globe and Scepter in his hands, and ſeats himſelf in the Throne: It rains firſt wheat, and then gold upon his head; he aſcends up, and vaniſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth.</stage>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Fa. Ant.</speaker>
                     <stage>rouſes himſelf, &amp; ſpeaks</stage>
                     <p>
                        <hi>Poſt tempeſtatem tranquillitas,</hi> After a ſtorm comes a calm; firſt, famine and fury; then, plenty and riches. This was not revealed un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to me, but for ſome uſe that <hi>I</hi> ſhould make thereof: What though <hi>Spain</hi> contemn my warnings, it may be <hi>Naples</hi> will not: if <hi>I</hi> can do any good, then—ſo: if not—ſo, ſo.</p>
                     <stage>Exit.</stage>
                  </sp>
               </div>
               <div n="2" type="scene">
                  <head>SCEN. II.</head>
                  <stage>Enter <hi>Maſſenello</hi> and <hi>Genuino.</hi>
                  </stage>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Gen.</speaker>
                     <p>I've given you inſtructions; which if you follow, the Town's ours.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Maſſ.</speaker>
                     <p>Worthy Patron, this bulk and veſſel of mine, ſhall ſtrike, or hoize up ſail, or tack about, agreeable to the wind of your words; and ſteer accordingly, and imploy all her Oares, to further what you breathe. Provided al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>waies, that what you adviſe, be ſtill for the good of the Republique. O the dear people of God, the too too much abuſed people, they ſhall never want my pains and beſt endeavours to do them good.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Gen.</speaker>
                     <p>About it then, Talk is but talk, 'tis mony buyes land; wit commands money; diſcretion governs wit; expedition is the life of action, but delaies are dangerous.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Maſſ.</speaker>
                     <p>About, ſay you? why I'l run or flie</p>
                     <p>To ſerve the <hi>Popolo,</hi> I'l live, I'l die.</p>
                     <stage>Exit Maſſ.</stage>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Gen.</speaker>
                     <p>So: if my Engin holds, I'l batter the lofty
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:111318:8"/> Tower, that ſo much threatens depopulations; and level the high wals of Government, with the earth they ſtood upon: The Axe is already laid to the root of that aſpiring Tree, that us'd ſuch droppings on thoſe under-ſuccours, that they could neither riſe, nor grow, and ſpreads her flouriſhing leaves at ſuch a breadth, that her head cannot perceive the ſtroaks ſhe now re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceives, even at her root, till down ſhe fals, that all her Royall Branches lye like ſprey upon the ground: I've found a fit ſubject for to work upon: the man is bold and reſolute, active and quick of apprehen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion; and prodegies run ſtill along with his expreſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons: The ſeverall opinions which the world conceives of the ſimplicity of this poor Fiſher-man, ſhall ſerve for light and ayeriall corks, whil'ſt the profound and weighty principles, wherewith <hi>I</hi> have inſtructed him, ſhall ſerve for ſo many leads and plummers to that net, that ſhall take whole draughts of Politicians; that ſhall drive them from ſwimming in their deeps, and force them to ſuch exigents, that the moſt contemptible and mean hands, ſhall take them in their ſhallows: and well ye have deſerv'd it, ye ear-wigs to Kings; you that think the Sacred Unction not ſufficient to anoynt your King, except it mingled with the peoples tears.</p>
                     <p>'Tis you that crown the Royall Temples with Thorns inſtead of Gold, and put Reeds into their hands inſteed of Scepters: It is you that have brought the people from feeding on the food that was ordain'd by God, to live on fruit ordain'd by you: And yet not reſting there, you have put Exciſe on that: And worſe then Catterpil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lars, who only were devourers of the fruit upon their trees; ye'have crept into the poor man's baſket, and eat a third part of every apple out of the childrens hands: And when I withſtood theſe impoſitions, as my place and duty bound me, with all the preſſing arguments of pity and compaſſion: As if my words were charms,
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:111318:8"/> they ſtopt their ears, like Adders; and I, for my piety and good advice, was ſent to <hi>Spain,</hi> upon an honourable Embaſſie, to carry <hi>Beleropho</hi> his Letters: which lodg'd me in the dungeon; ſo that 500 leagues, and more, I was forc'd to carry mine own priſon, and a Letter, whoſe lines were all as ſtrong as Irons. But now I'm here ready to act the ſweeteſt of all ſins, revenge: Nor will I let it fall like rain upon them, or diſtill my fury drop by drop, but I will pour my anger forth.</p>
                     <p>For all is now at ſtake; the Die is caſt:</p>
                     <p>I'expect my chance; the Rubicon is paſt.</p>
                     <stage>Exit Gen.</stage>
                  </sp>
               </div>
               <div n="3" type="scene">
                  <head>SCEN. III.</head>
                  <stage>A noyſe within, crying, Down with the Exciſe, no Exciſe, no Exciſe, &amp;c.</stage>
                  <stage>Enter <hi>Maſſenello,</hi> with the rabble rout, with canes in their hands.</stage>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Om<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes.</speaker>
                     <p>One and all, one and all, one and all, &amp;c.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Maſſ.</speaker>
                     <p>My Maſters, now we are full-bodied, let us chuſe a Head, otherwiſe we ſhall be ſubject to confuſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on; and no man knows what to do, or whom to obey.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Omnes.</speaker>
                     <p>A <hi>Maſſenello,</hi> A <hi>Maſſenello,</hi> A <hi>Maſſenello, &amp;c.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <stage>They hoyſe him up upon mens ſhoulders, and proclaim,</stage>
                     <p>
                        <hi>Tomaſo Amello di Malfa,</hi> Generall of the <hi>Neopolitanes.</hi>
                     </p>
                  </sp>
                  <stage>Enter the <hi>Eletto di popolo.</hi>
                  </stage>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Eletto.</speaker>
                     <p>What means this Tumult? Wherfore are theſe ſtirs? For what's this inſurrection? How occaſioned is this commotion? My Maſters, if from the Exciſe, that is on fruit your diſcontents ariſe, I'l undertake
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:111318:9"/> to eaſe all your grievances, ſatisfie all your deſires: Let me ſuffer, let my Wife and Children be ſacrifices for the peoples good, if I procure not this good unto the peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple: Let my houſe, and all within it, ſuffer in the juſt flames of your high inſenſments, if I do not procure you all the contentment that your hearts can wiſh: Only be ſatisfied for the preſent, till ſatisfaction for the future may be had; which may be no leſſe welcome unto you, then peaceable unto all.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Maſſ.</speaker>
                     <p>
                        <hi>Don Eletto di popolo,</hi> In anſwer to your grave and learned ſpeech; you muſt know, that the horſe now knows his own ſtrength, and is beholding to you for his underſtanding, and will not anſwer your ſwitch and ſpur ſo readily as he was wont: they will not take it at your hands, nor at your heels, as heretofore; they will not be rid off their legs, nor out of wind, by every hot ſpur; Apes muſt not think to ride fierce Maſtiffs, and box them into conformity, now the muzzle's off.</p>
                     <p>Sir, in a word, our preſſures were intolerable; and when the Aſſe's back is broke, it is time to take off the burthen. Our reſolution's this; We will not have the leſſer rule the greater ſtrength, nor the fewer rule the multitude, nor one rule all; and that's our reſoluti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Eletto.</speaker>
                     <p>Noble Sir—</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Maſſ.</speaker>
                     <p>Noble Fool: do'ſt thou think to catch <hi>Tomaſo</hi> with thy courtly tearms?</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Omnes.</speaker>
                     <p>He prates, he prates, we have had enough of this, prating, we will have no more prating.</p>
                     <stage>They uſe violence to him.</stage>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Maſſ.</speaker>
                     <p>
                        <hi>Andiamo.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>
                        <hi>Viva Maſſenello, vi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap>a, viva, Maſſenello</hi>
                     </p>
                     <stage>
                        <hi>
                           <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ſing violence to the</hi> Eletto de popolo.</stage>
                     <stage>Exeunt.</stage>
                  </sp>
               </div>
               <div n="4" type="scene">
                  <pb n="7" facs="tcp:111318:9"/>
                  <head>SCEN. IV.</head>
                  <stage>Enter <hi>Vice-Roy</hi> of <hi>Naples, Lord Treaſurer, Lord Cham<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>berlain, Lord Controuler.</hi> Attendants.</stage>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Vice-Roy.</speaker>
                     <p>MY Lord, I pray you let me peruſe the Letter over again—muſt? the command is perem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ptory: I would to God, that when they ſend ſuch muſty Letters out of <hi>Spain,</hi> for ſuch large ſums after ſums of mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ney, they would be pleaſed to direct us waies how we muſt come by them.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Lord Treaſ.</speaker>
                     <p>And't pleaſe your Majeſtie, the Exciſe that's laid on fruit, brings money in apace, and the tax is ſure and conſtant; and a ſum of money that will ſtrike a great ſtroke into the ſum that is demanded, may be advanced out of that, if it ſo like your Majeſtie.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Vice-Roy.</speaker>
                     <p>How great ſums of money out of that? Poor people! how they ſhrink under the burthen we are ſorc'd to lay upon them: And having laid Exciſe on all things upon earth, on fire, in water, the people fly to ſee what immunities there are in air, and ſeek for pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viledges in the tops of trees; and how they may make free meals upon their fruit: but cruelty hath caſt up ſuch a trench, whoſe quick-ſets are now grown ſo high, that they have now (even) enclos'd the com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon air.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Mont.</speaker>
                     <p>Good your Majeſtie, be not pleas'd to aggravate too much the hardneſſe either of your own, or their con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dition; no Kingdom wherein the people in their ſeverall degrees live more happily, then in this flouriſhing King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom of NAPLES, and under your Government: Whereon it ſtands, like a Mountain, firm upon its baſis. Are not the Laws duly executed? Do not the No<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bility live in a moſt ſplendid and glorious equipage? The Gentry in a moſt illuſtrious and ſeemly deco<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rum? But as for this ſame <hi>Popolo,</hi> this <hi>profanum vul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gus,</hi>
                        <pb n="8" facs="tcp:111318:10"/> this <hi>bellua mortuorum capitum,</hi> theſe Bores, Peſants and Commons, Goodmen and Gaffers, their backs were made for burthens, and their hands for labour: How will you make your ſauces, if you will not ſqueez your Oran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges? Or Wine, if you will not preſſe the Grape? How ſhall the King of <hi>Spain's</hi> Souldiers eat bread, if you will not tread the Corn out of the ſtraw? Nature never in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tended, that the Aſſe ſhould be ſtall-fed: nor did you e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver hear of ſuch creatures pampered up, till they were provender-prickt—</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>
                        <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>rſino.</speaker>
                     <p>Come, come my Lord Controuler, this is not well to pick thanks from ſome one or two, you draw upon your head the curſes of a multitude; and to pleaſe ſome one, you care not though you diſpleaſe all: but we have too many ſuch now adaies, it would be better if it were otherwiſe.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Mont.</speaker>
                     <p>Lord Chamberlain, I envy not your Lordſhip's popularity, which I never eſteemed otherwiſe then a ſea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther in a fool's cap.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>
                        <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>rſino.</speaker>
                     <p>My Lord, you ſaid too much; if you do not underſtand your ſelf, I do; if you have forgotten in whoſe preſence you are, I have not: However, this I ſhall be bold to tell your Lordſhip, though it be in the Kings hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring, though you have put the Aſſe upon the people, you ſhall not put the fool on me. Had we alwaies day, we had need of no other Favours, but the Suns: but ſeeing we have as many nights, we ſtand in need of ſmaller lights; that favour doth not alwaies laſt.</p>
                     <l>And 'gainſt the favour ſets, which light debars;</l>
                     <l>I'l think of being beholding to the ſtars.</l>
                     <stage>Exit L. Chamberl.</stage>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Mont.</speaker>
                     <p>Good night to your Lordſhip.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Vice-Roy.</speaker>
                     <p>My Lord, you did not well: I do not like theſe janglings, they bode miſchief, they portend no good:
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:111318:10"/> my mind preſages evil; and theſe quarrellings are a bad Omen, and put me in mind of a ſcurvy dream I dream't laſt night. Methought I was in <hi>Spain,</hi> hunting the <hi>Tauro;</hi> and whil'ſt I was ready for the encounter, the furious beaſt made at me with more heads then had <hi>Briarius</hi> hands; and methought looking how, and where to charge, ſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding near unto a Poplar tree, the wind blew the falling leaves ſo thick into my face, that I could neither ſee, nor breath; ſo that the furious beaſt bare me to the ground: whereupon I awak't, and found my ſelf in the jaws both of danger and diſhonour.</p>
                     <stage>Enter <hi>
                           <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>rſino</hi> puffing and blowing, with the <hi>Eletto di popolo.</hi>
                     </stage>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Vice-Roy.</speaker>
                     <p>The news, my Lord? Heaven defend us; their looks ſpeak nothing but diſtraction and horrour: ſpeak out, my Lord, what's the matter?</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>
                        <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>rſ.</speaker>
                     <p>I met with the <hi>Eletto di popolo;</hi> here, let him tell his own tale.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Eletto.</speaker>
                     <p>O Sir, all the City is riſen, commotions are in every part thereof, and the inſurrection grows higher and higher.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>V. Roy.</speaker>
                     <p>Now my dream is out: ſilence: go ſpeedily, and from me, aſſure them of all the ſatisfaction can be given them.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Eletto.</speaker>
                     <p>I have done it already.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>V. Roy.</speaker>
                     <p>You did not do it from me?</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Eletto.</speaker>
                     <p>I have, my Leige.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>V. Roy.</speaker>
                     <p>Do it again.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Eletto.</speaker>
                     <p>I have engaged my life, the lives of my Wife and Children, and all <hi>I</hi> have, and they will not hear a word: they ſay, you have broken your promiſe with them ſo oft, that they will not believe a word you ſay, or what is ſaid in your behalf.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>V. Roy.</speaker>
                     <p>Away, make haſt, run, fly, tell them, ſwear, proteſt, call God to witneſſe, that I intend it, and
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:111318:11"/> that you know my intentions to be ſuch, as will give them ſatisfaction, not only in this, but in more then they deſire.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Eletto.</speaker>
                     <p>I'l go; but God bleſſe me, for I fear Hel's broke looſe.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>
                        <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>rſ.</speaker>
                     <p>Now, my Lord, Sunſhine: how goes the day by your Clock?</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Mont.</speaker>
                     <p>Marry <hi>I</hi> think it is almoſt upon the ſtroke of twelve.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>
                        <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>rſ.</speaker>
                     <p>You ſhall hear it ſtrike one by and by.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Mont.</speaker>
                     <p>One and twenty, with all my heart, and we may but ſtrike a faſt as they. Sir. what will you do? Will you, that I gather ſtrength? and we will cruſh this Cocka<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trice in the egge, and deſtroy the Monſter, whil'ſt the Dam is in her labour: I'l be the Midwife that ſhall welcom it by peice meals into the world.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>
                        <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>rſ.</speaker>
                     <p>The King is wiſer, or I could wiſh he were.</p>
                     <stage>Exit L. Chamb.</stage>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>V. Roy.</speaker>
                     <p>My Lord, It is not long ſince your Lordſhip told me, that the Kingdoms Government ſtood firm, as doth a Mountain, on its Ballance; but now it can be compared to no Mountain, except <hi>Veſuvias,</hi> whoſe flames do run a head, whoſe big ſwollen breaſt vomits out ſulphurs more prodigious then that: NAPLES was then pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerv'd from that eruption, by a contrary wind; and ſo it muſt be now too, what you breath, or others may be plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed to think, as a preſent remedy, <hi>Nec vult panthera do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mari,</hi> the people will not, like a Town-top, fall aſleep with ſcourging: I have ſeen an unruly horſe, when all harſh means could not prevail, ſtand ſtill with ſtroking: I'l try that way; when I grant them all, they can aſk no more.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Mont.</speaker>
                     <p>Sir, they will not be ſatisfied with all you grant, except you will grant your ſelf to be no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>V. Roy.</speaker>
                     <p>I'l warrant you; I have ſent unto them, and you
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:111318:11"/> ſhall hear they will be ſatisfied: they are men, and men have reaſon, and reaſon will tell them when they are well.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Mont.</speaker>
                     <p>I tell you, Sir, they are men, and men of reaſon, yet injur'd men; and there are Devils amongſt thoſe men; who laying hold upon the peoples former diſcon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tents, ſow ſuch fears and jealouſies in the hearts of the people, that nothing ſhall ſatisfie, till they have brought their Deviliſh, and ſo long hatch'd deſign, to ſome effect<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
                     </p>
                     <stage>Enter <hi>L. Chamberlain.</hi>
                     </stage>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>
                        <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>rſ.</speaker>
                     <p>O Sir, the people are all mad, and both their mad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe and themſelves increaſe: they would not hear the <hi>Eletto di popolo,</hi> but offered violence to his perſon: ſo that he is hardly eſcap'd, if he be eſcap'd at all, and they are all marching towards the Palace.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>V. Roy.</speaker>
                     <p>Go, give command the Palace be well guarded: What a tempeſt is here all upon the ſud<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>den?</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Mont.</speaker>
                     <p>O, are you advis'd of that now? pray God it be n't too late.</p>
                     <stage>Exit L. Contr.</stage>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>V. Roy.</speaker>
                     <p>O thou Angel guardian! lead me by the hand, through this Wilderneſſe of wild beaſts and maſes, whoſe intricate, and ſo difficult windings, are never to be found out, but by the higheſt providence, and your aſſiſtance, keep my ſenſes from diſtraction, and let no fear out my reaſon from its proper office.</p>
                     <stage>Enter <hi>L. Contr.</hi>
                     </stage>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Mont.</speaker>
                     <p>O Sir, you are betray'd by your own Guard, who moſt cowardly and traiterouſly, upon the ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proach of the rabble, have put out all their matches, and turn'd the muzzles of their muſkets downwards, and ſtood like ſo many ſenſleſſe ſtatues, as if every ſoul had ſuffered an Eclypſe, whil'ſt the rout entred the
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:111318:12"/> gates; and poſſeſt themſelves of the Palace.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>V. Roy.</speaker>
                     <p>Baſe mungrel curs: have they taught their muſket-barrels to ſubmit to Canes? and have their chines of beef bred no better ſpirits in the bloud within their veins, then to give way to apple-feeders? Dumb dogs! could they neither bark, nor bite?</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Mont.</speaker>
                     <p>Sir, it is no time to expoſtulate, but to ſave your ſelf.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>V. Roy.</speaker>
                     <p>Save my ſelf: from whom? From Apple-parings? From men whoſe veins are fil'd with nothing but the juice of Plums? Shall the Scepter ſubmit to a compa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny of Reeds? I, I, be gon, be gon; ſee how the wind blows chaffe away: though none ſtood to me, I ſhould think my ſelf as ſtrongly armed as <hi>Jove,</hi> that holds thun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der enough in one hand, to frighten a world of men.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>L. Contr.</speaker>
                     <p>Sir, What do you mean? Your Friends have all left you, you are alone.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>V. Roy.</speaker>
                     <p>No, thou art here, my Friend <hi>Mon<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                              <desc>••</desc>
                           </gap>lto;</hi> they were never Friends of mine; for Friends would never leave me thus. O adverſitie! thou touchſtone of mens hearts; I ſee thou art good for ſomething; forſaken of all; power is fallen to the ground, and no advice remains to help it up: experience, you are come too late to tell me, that,</p>
                     <p>That Prince his Throne is ſtaid up but in parts,</p>
                     <p>That i'n't ſupported by the peoples hearts.</p>
                     <stage>Exit V. Roy.</stage>
                  </sp>
                  <stage>
                     <hi>Maſſenello,</hi> and the rout, ruſh in; <hi>Mont.</hi> draws, and hinders them from purſuing the Vice-Roy.</stage>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Mont.</speaker>
                     <p>Stand: what would you have?</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Maſſ.</speaker>
                     <p>Silkworm: put up thy Sword: offer but to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiſt us in the leaſt degree, or to diſobey us but in a tittle, and thou hadſt as good eat thunder, or engage lightning within thy boſom, inſtead of air: Where's the Vice-King?</p>
                     <pb n="13" facs="tcp:111318:12"/>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Mont.</speaker>
                     <p>I do not know; or if I did, <hi>I</hi> would not tel you.</p>
                     <stage>
                        <hi>Maſſenello</hi> ſtrikes at him, and he makes his way through them all.</stage>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Maſſe.</speaker>
                     <p>Divide your ſelves, and ſearch the King there, whil'ſt we ſearch here.</p>
                     <stage>They go out at ſeverall dores, and the firſt party finds him, and drags him upon the Stage.</stage>
                     <p n="1">1. Hold; let's bring him to the <hi>Mercato;</hi> and what we do, do there in the ſight of all the people.</p>
                     <p n="2">2. Will it pleaſe your Majeſtie to give me leave to take you by the coller?</p>
                     <p n="3">3. And I to take you by the locks?</p>
                     <p n="4">4. Come along, Jackanapes with a Whim-wham.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Omnes.</speaker>
                     <p>
                        <hi>Viva il popolo, viva, viva, &amp;c.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <stage>The Vice-Roy putting his hands into his pockets, takes out hands full of chi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>keens, and throws them up into the air; the people fall a ſcrabling for the gold, whil'ſt the King eſcapes.</stage>
                     <stage>Enter <hi>Maſſenello,</hi> and the other party.</stage>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Maſſ.</speaker>
                     <p>What's the matter?</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Omnes.</speaker>
                     <p>We have found him, we have found him, here he is.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Maſſ.</speaker>
                     <p>Where? Where is he? Where is the Vice-Roy? What's become of him? Have you loſt him? Who had him? No man ſpeak? What's that you were ſcuffling for? Chikeens? How came they to be thrown amongſt you?</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Omnes.</speaker>
                     <p>The King threw them.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Maſſ.</speaker>
                     <p>
                        <hi>Capitra!</hi> Was there ever known ſuch fools, to graſp at ſhadows, and to loſe the ſubſtance thus? You all ſhew your ſelves to be what you are, and not men like<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly to go through with ſuch a work. <hi>I</hi> hope you ſee your er<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rour now: and that it may be ſo no more, ſeeing you have
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:111318:13"/> made me your Generall, I pronounce it death, hence<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forth, for any man to keep or preſerve any thing, that is the eſtate of any Delinquent whatſoever, be they Chariots or Horſes, Pearls or precious Stones, Cloths of Gold or Silver, but let them all burn, and let Delinquents Hou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes be fuell for Delinquents goods; that all the World may know, we have not enterpris'd this buſineſſe to enrich our ſelves, but to vindicate the common liberty: Death and damnation be his lot, that dares tranſgreſſe a tittle of that which I command.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <l>That all the World may know our equitie,</l>
                  <l>Were he ten thouſand Brothers, he ſhould die.</l>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Omnes.</speaker>
                     <p>
                        <hi>Viva, viva, viva, &amp;c.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <stage>Exeunt omnes.</stage>
                  </sp>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div n="2" type="act">
               <head>ACT. II.</head>
               <div n="1" type="scene">
                  <head>SCEN. I.</head>
                  <stage>Enter <hi>Duke di Mattaloon,</hi> and Captain of the Caſtle, at ſeverall dores.</stage>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Duke Mat.</speaker>
                     <p>WHere's the Captain of the Caſtle?</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Capt.</speaker>
                     <p>Here.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Mat.</speaker>
                     <p>Make haſt, and call the Souldiers together, man your Wals, draw up your Bridges, load your Cannon, charge your Muſkets, light your Matches, beat your Drums, call to the Parade, Hel's broke looſe, and the Devil leads the dance: O, I fear me, the Vice<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>Roy hath ſuffered already in this tumult.</p>
                     <stage>Enter <hi>L. Contr.</hi>
                     </stage>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>L. Cont.</speaker>
                     <p>No, hee's ſafe as yet, though ſeiz'd upon by the rudeſt hands, at a dead lift: the Vice-Roy turn'd Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jurer, caſt a golden apparition before their eies, and ſo eſcaped their clutches.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>D. Mat.</speaker>
                     <p>How Conjurer? What golden apparition? Prethee do not trifle with us now: Where's the King? What's become of him?</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <pb n="15" facs="tcp:111318:13"/>
                     <speaker>L. Cont.</speaker>
                     <p>He is ſafely hous'd in the next Convent, where, if you ſend (preſently) but the ſmalleſt guard, to prevent the worſt; they knowing not what is become of him, you may eaſily conduct him to this Caſtle.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Mat.</speaker>
                     <p>Captain, make all the haſt you can, with what Guard is next at hand, and guard the Vice-Roy hi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Capt.</speaker>
                     <p>It ſhall be done.</p>
                     <stage>Enter <hi>Vice-Roy,</hi> in a Friers habit.</stage>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Vice Roy.</speaker>
                     <p>
                        <hi>Q<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>em queritis adſum?</hi>
                     </p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Mat.</speaker>
                     <p>My Lord the King, welcom, as is <hi>Eli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zeum,</hi> to a new come ſoul: how ſcap'd your Majeſtie?</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>V. Roy.</speaker>
                     <p>As a bird out of the ſnare, or as a brand out of the fire, engag'd by the hairs, both of my head and beard, hands laid hold upon my coller, and no part of my body unſeas'd on.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Mat.</speaker>
                     <p>Strange outrage! and unheard of inſolence! how got you looſe?</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>V. Roy.</speaker>
                     <p>
                        <hi>I</hi> ſhowr'd down gold upon their heads, which loos'd their hands: ſo that whil'ſt they were ſcrambling for the money, I eſcaped to the next Convent, and ſo hither: This is the habit of Father <hi>Anthony,</hi> that holy man, whom I found there; having purpoſely left the Woods to fore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>warn me of this miſchief, but happened to come in the very action, followed me into the Convent, bad me be of good comfort; told me, that all ſhould have a happy en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding; would not let me ſtay for any convoy, but put his habit upon me, wherewith I paſſed (unſuſpected) through the thickeſt of them: This, I am ſure, is well, and the other courſe might not have been ſo fortunate.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Mat.</speaker>
                     <p>Happy day, and a good preſage of future happi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe, and proſperous ſucceſſe.</p>
                     <stage>Enter <hi>Card: Filomarino.</hi>
                     </stage>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Card:</speaker>
                     <p>Sir, I am over-joyed to ſee you here, and alive:
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:111318:14"/> but I wiſh that <hi>I</hi> could ſay, ſafe, and out of danger; for the place neither aſſures the one, nor makes you ſafe from t'other: I have been viewing the proviſions and Ammunition of the Caſtle, and <hi>I</hi> find neither Am<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>munition for a daies fight, nor proviſion for a months continuance.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>V. Roy.</speaker>
                     <p>Captain of the Caſtle: how do you anſwer this?</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Capt.</speaker>
                     <p>Sir, I can ſooner give to your Majeſtie an anſwer, then a remedy. Sir, beſides my often ſolicitations of thoſe whom it did concern; here are my Copies of Petitions to your Majeſtie for both, after months upon months de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>laies; here are my aſſignments for ſo much bullet, pouder, corn and beef, wine and oyl; here are the Copies of Or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders to the contrary; ſo much of this and that for <hi>Spain;</hi> ſo much proviſion and ammunition for the <hi>Gallies;</hi> ſo ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny quarters of wheat to be ſent to <hi>Genoa,</hi> to make mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ney; ſum <hi>totalis,</hi> nothing for me. Sir, if any of all theſe things had grown within the Caſtle, I would have been an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwerable for the want thereof: but ſince they do not, but muſt be otherwiſe had, I doing my endeavour, and all would not do, I hope your Majeſtie will hold me excuſed, and lay the blame on thoſe who worthily deſerve it.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>V. Roy.</speaker>
                     <l>O miſerable ſtate of Princes! When</l>
                     <l>They'r forc'd to ſee with th'eies of other men.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Card.</speaker>
                     <p>This is no time to think of what is paſt, but how we may help our ſelves out of the preſent plunge we are in: they are our Maſters now, and there is no wreſtling without hands.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>V. Roy.</speaker>
                     <p>Lord Duke, you are a man in ſome favour with the people, and may happily do good ſervice at this time; it would be very acceptable, if you could do any thing to appeaſe this uproar.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Mad.</speaker>
                     <p>Sir, I underſtand, that nothing wil ſatisfie them now, but the priviledges granted unto them by the
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:111318:14"/> Emperour <hi>Ferdinand,</hi> and ratified by <hi>Carolo quinto.</hi>
                     </p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Card.</speaker>
                     <p>You may make them believe priviledges of leſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſer moment, to be the ſame; and 'tis all one to them.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Mat.</speaker>
                     <p>Lord Card: If I ſhould demand the ſame privi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledges which they require, interpretation might make me guilty of a crime as black as theirs: And if <hi>I</hi> ſhould go about to delude them with priviledges, which are not the ſame, and they find it out, I ſhould run my ſelf upon the fury of a multitude.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Card.</speaker>
                     <p>My Maſters, we have nothing left us now, but every man a head; which that he may keep upon his ſhoulders, he muſt make uſe of his brains; for ought that I can hear, they carry their buſineſſe warily; their pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceedings ſpeak order and method; contrivement go along with their deſign: Believe it, the progreſſe they have made already, diſcovers a head, above a vulgar capacity; and the beaſt, as he goes along, ſhews, though many heads, yet one above the reſt, by whom all are directed: So that Monarchy it ſelf is oppoſed by that of its own nature; and we muſt play with them now at their own Weapons.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <l>And where the Lyon's ſkin doth fail,</l>
                  <l>Wee'l piece it with the Foxes tail.</l>
                  <p>My Lord Duke, you have a wild Brother, <hi>Don Peppe di Caraffa,</hi> who we hear is very great with <hi>Peroon,</hi> Captain of the <hi>Bandittoes;</hi> ſo that by your means, he, and all his Aſſociates, may be drawn to our part, and every one of thoſe is worth a hundred door-keepers: And what do ye lack? Let us call them in: yet ſo, as they firſt offer their ſervice unto the people, and ſo poſſeſſe themſelves of the heart of the City: then ſhall you go with theſe pretended priviledges; and if they take, the buſineſſe is ended: if not, you have ſo many ſervants at your elbow, ready to defend you, and to bring you off.</p>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>V. Roy</speaker>
                     <p>Excellently well advis'd: we thank you for your good advice.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <pb n="2" facs="tcp:111318:15"/>
                     <speaker>Mat.</speaker>
                     <p>'Twas ſpoke like a Cardinall, and they are the men now adaies, who have ingroſſed the exaltations of Kingdoms to themſelves, and have appropriated thoſe re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nowned acts unto their own order.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Card:</speaker>
                     <p>Let the Queen be taught to act her part too, and to go to <hi>Maſſenello</hi>'s Mother, Wife and Daughters, and col<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>logue and cog with them.</p>
                     <p>To ſtoop to our neceſſities, is Wiſdom ſed:</p>
                     <p>For when the Sun courts Dunghils, there are Serpents bred.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>V. Roy.</speaker>
                     <p>Come, let's about it then, and leave no ſtone unturn'd, where under may be found our look'd for ſafety: truly they were much to blame,</p>
                     <p>Who put us thus to play the after game.</p>
                     <stage>Exeunt.</stage>
                  </sp>
               </div>
               <div n="2" type="scene">
                  <head>SCEN. II.</head>
                  <stage>Enter <hi>Maſſanello, Gen: Mariamma, Agatha, Flora</hi> and <hi>
                        <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>rſula.</hi>
                  </stage>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Gen.</speaker>
                     <p>SIR, I muſt tell you here, in the preſence of your Mother, your Wife, and Daughters here likewiſe, that you are much to be blamed; you have committed more goods and monies-worth unto the fire, out of meer vain-glory and oſtentation, then would have made you the wealthieſt man in the whole Kingdom of NAPLES, and ſo conſequently the wiſeſt, the greateſt, the beſt, the nobleſt of all the <hi>Neopolitans:</hi> for wherein is wiſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom moſt exerciſed? Then, in the gaining of that which hath the unqueſtionable command of all things, and that's money: ſo far I'm right. 2. For greatneſſe: Who is great (I pray) but he that hath the world at will? And who's that? but he that hath money at command. Now for goodneſſe: <hi>
                           <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nde derivatur</hi> goodneſſe? Goodneſſe, <hi>quaſi</hi> a neſt of goods: get but that, and ye are good e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nough. And Laſtly, for Nobility: What is Nobility, but ancient riches? Get good ſtore of old gold, it's no mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter whoſe 'tis, and ſearch for bags that have not ſeen
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:111318:15"/> the Sun this many a day, and then you have ancient riches, and ſo conſequently nobility. Sir, I beſeech you to take the advice of him by whoſe direction you have proſpered hitherto: do not ſo vainly reject and conſume that, which is only able to preſerve you from oblivion; Palms and Laurels wither in the hands, and on the heads of thoſe who wear them, but riches imbalms a Worthies memory more precious then any ſtatues of braſſe or marble; and give him a more laſting fame then a memory that's preſerv'd from oblivion by thin paper-wals.</p>
                     <p>Were I in your condition, the firſt thing Iw'd do, ſhould be to build my ſelf a houſe, for the honour of my name: then I would ſo feather my neſt, that <hi>Jupiters</hi> own Bird, who builds his neſt in the Sun, ſhould not think it a diſparagement to ſeek alliance with one of my Chikeens.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Maſſ.</speaker>
                     <p>
                        <hi>Genuino,</hi> thou haſt converted me, henceforth I will be covetous, high minded, glorious and haughty: and hearken to what I ſhall ſay, in order to my converſion. <hi>Genuino,</hi> the City is rich, we have the power in our hands, why ſhould we not have the riches? The Citizens begin to thruſt their thumbs under their girdles, and to make pauſes at our demands, and ſome of them begin to look aſquint already upon our actions: Haſt thou not obſerv'd it, <hi>Genuino? Genuino,</hi> thou haſt ſpoken wiſely, money is all in all, and that's the thing we aim at; money is the ſinews of War, and the life-bloud to action: let us ſuck this bloud, and cut theſe ſinews, leſt they ſtand upon their tearms with us: It is requiſite that ſo ſtrong a body ſhou'd be thus enfeebled, when we know not how long they will take our part: let us but get a world of money, and we care not for the World. <hi>Pecunia</hi> is the Queen Regent of the Worlds Empire, whoſe divall juſſements being ſo ſlenderly regarded, hath been the only cauſe, why none hath hitherto attained to the Quinteſſentiall and fift Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>narchy. And therfore Dame Nature was wiſely provi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dent,
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:111318:16"/> in hiding with her greateſt care, this thing Omni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>potent, in the very bowels of the earth; like a carefull Mother, who hides her knives out of her childrens way, till they know how to uſe them: But we are men, and know full well how to be our own carvers: Let us pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vide our ſelves with theſe neceſſaries, and none ſhall live, but ſuch as are beholding to us for doles of meat, and ſhives of bread: Money will ranſom Kings, and make Crowns to pawn their Jewels: Therfore good <hi>Genuino,</hi> let us have money enough, the City has it: we have the City, and why ſhould we be without it?</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Gen.</speaker>
                     <p>Softly, great <hi>Tomaſo,</hi> you are too apt a Scholar; all that you have ſaid is truth, and muſt be executed: yet ſo, as that they may ſeem to enjoy what we are Maſters of: Let them be your Caſh-keepers, and you ſhall command whatſoever they have, as readily, as if they were your Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vants: Now you have made your ſelf their Conquerour, you muſt not plunder the City, nor take all away at once; for if you do not leave a neſt-egge behind you, the hens will lay no more: What's theirs by providence, muſt be ours with prudence: We will make them give, or we will uſe them, as the old Wives uſe their cakes, when they are grown dry, put them under ground.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Maſſ.</speaker>
                     <p>
                        <hi>Genuino,</hi> thou ſaiſt well; of all Nations, ſools have the leaſt wit; and of all wiſe men, thou art one for my money.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Mariam.</speaker>
                     <p>Sir, you were pleas'd to talk of alliance even now; I forgot to tell you, that the Vice-Queen was here, and ſaid, that her eldeſt Son ſhould many one of your Daughters, if you will be friends with him.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Maſſ.</speaker>
                     <p>A pox conſound her for an Hypocrite; ſhe came to abuſe us, to flout and jeer us: a likely mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Gen.</speaker>
                     <p>Not ſo, carry your buſineſſe handſomly, and he ſhall be glad to ſeek it: Where, in all the Royall Palace, is there a prettier Moppet then this ſame? A wittier
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:111318:16"/> thing? I tell you, Sir, ſhe is a Bed-fellow for a Prince, and a Companion for his betters.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>
                        <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>rſula.</speaker>
                     <p>What ſhe? marry come up; a bliſter on the tongue that ſpake it.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Agatha.</speaker>
                     <p>What ſay you to this girl? She's black, but lovely: If you can force him to any, you may compell him to accept of this; if he may chuſe, hee'l chuſe nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Maſſ.</speaker>
                     <p>I may do ſo, but I may chuſe: if you ſhackle Princes, you muſt have golden bonds, not ruſtie iron.</p>
                     <p>Come <hi>Genuino,</hi> wee'l go and adviſe about the premiſes, leave fooliſh Women to themſelves.</p>
                     <stage>Ex. Maſſ. Gen.</stage>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>
                        <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>rſula.</speaker>
                     <p>Am I but ruſtie iron? I think my ſelf to be as good mettal as her ſelf: 'Twas a roguiſh ſpeech.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Mariam.</speaker>
                     <p>O Child, remember he is your Father.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>
                        <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>rſula.</speaker>
                     <p>My Father? What of that? Let him uſe me like a Child, I am no ruſty piece.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Agatha.</speaker>
                     <p>As ruſty as thou art, he ſhall thee, or none: let them conſult out, as they pleaſe, 'tis your fine face that is the cauſe of all this ſtir.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Flora.</speaker>
                     <p>Mother, I never thought it fine; but as it is, God beſtowed it, and I hope you will not make Gods gifts my fault.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Agatha.</speaker>
                     <p>Go, go, you're a prating baggage.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Flora.</speaker>
                     <p>Good Mother, do not build your diſcontents upon imaginations ſo improbable, and unlikely.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Agath.</speaker>
                     <p>Improbable to thee, vile Wretch! but not to her.</p>
                     <stage>Enter <hi>Maſſenello</hi> and <hi>Genuino.</hi>
                     </stage>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Gen.</speaker>
                     <p>I tell you, Sir, you muſt not do things raſhly; take advice: Where have you a King? But ſuch a one is his right hand: Be adviſed, Sir, Gods themſelves did ſit in Councel.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Maſſ.</speaker>
                     <p>I tell thee man, thou ſhalt be my right hand,
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:111318:17"/> and my right foot, and my right eie, and my right ear, and my right, right, right, any thing, if thou wilt be quiet: thou ſhalt be my chief Secretary, and Councellour of State; you ſhall be a Queen Mother, you a Queen; and thou, my little Chuck, the new Infanta of <hi>Neapolis.</hi> I fear nothing, but that I ſhall want Children, and Kindred, ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther then honours and preferments to confer upon them.</p>
                     <stage>Enter a Meſſenger in haſt.</stage>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Meſſ.</speaker>
                     <p>Sir, they all expect you in the <hi>Mercato,</hi> nothing can be done untill you come.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Gen.</speaker>
                     <p>You may be ſure of that: Who dares act any thing without you? You are the ſoul that gives life to the body politique, and the main Engin from whom the wheel of fortune borrows its motion.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Maſſ.</speaker>
                     <p>'Tis well done of you, thus to let us underſtand our ſelf.</p>
                     <stage>Ex. Maſſ. Gen.</stage>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Mariam.</speaker>
                     <p>I remember, when he was but a boy, many a time and oft, when he came home from fiſhing, he would commend the policy of the Herring, that could make themſelves Kings, by their multitudes, notwithſtanding the greatneſſe of the Whale, and other Fiſhes: and when I was with Child with him, I dream'd that <hi>I</hi> was delivered of a ſon, who as ſoon as ever he was born, could ſtand up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on his head.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Agatha.</speaker>
                     <p>Mother, I can eaſily interpret that dream for you; the King is the Head of the People, my Huſband ſhall pull down the King, and bring him under his foot, and ſo ſtand upon his Head.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>
                        <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>rſula.</speaker>
                     <p>'Tis very likely to be true: a very pretty in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terr retation.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Flora.</speaker>
                     <p>I, but Siſter, this ſhould have been done as ſoon as he was born: for ſo my Grandmother dream'd.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <pb n="7" facs="tcp:111318:17"/>
                     <speaker>
                        <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>rſula.</speaker>
                     <p>Goodly, goodly: how you come in with your five eggs a penny, and four of them rotten? The riſing of the people was the big ſwoln belly, that contain'd the bully lad, that ſhould do ſuch feats: and my Father is not two daies old, ſince he was ſo born.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Flora.</speaker>
                     <p>I, but Siſter, my Grandmother ſaies, ſhe dream'd how that my Father, as ſoon as he was born, ſhould ſtand upon his head; if he ſtood upon his head, then his feet muſt be uppermoſt: how could he tread the King (then) under foot, when he ſtood upon his head?</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>
                        <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>rſula.</speaker>
                     <p>Why, that may very well be, too—</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Flora.</speaker>
                     <p>I, juſt as you took ſhipping to go for <hi>Turkie,</hi> ſo I lent you my horſe, and you went to <hi>Rome.</hi>
                     </p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Agatha.</speaker>
                     <p>Vile Baggage! ſhe's alwaies croſſing her Siſter, and chopping of Logick with her; I'l chop you:
<stage>Strikes her.</stage> Take that for your labour.</p>
                     <stage>Exeunt Mar. Agatha, <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>rſula. manet Flora.</stage>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Flora.</speaker>
                     <p>How ſhall I do, to let my Mother in law, and my Siſter know, I have no ſuch ambition, as they think in me, and have themſelves? I would I could as well clear their boſoms from thoſe ſuſpicions, as well as I can my own from ſuch vain hopes: they are all fir'd with that, which warms not me: My Grandmother is high-minded; my Father higher; my Mother higheſt; my Siſter high<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eſt of all.</p>
                     <p>And ſince there's no degree in height for me, I'l ſtick unto my old humilitie.</p>
                     <stage>Exit Flora.</stage>
                     <stage>Enter Major, Aldermen, &amp;c. at one dore: <hi>Maſſ.</hi> at another: <hi>Gen.</hi> and others.</stage>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Major.</speaker>
                     <p>An't pleaſe your Excellence, here is a Catalogue of the Delinquents names.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Maſſ.</speaker>
                     <p>Have you taken examinations duly and truly? for
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:111318:18"/> I will do nothing but juſtice, all thoſe (let me ſee your pen) before whoſe name you find this mark.</p>
                     <stage>He makes a dumb ſign, with his finger ſawing his throat.</stage>
                     <p>You underſtand me, the words out; and ſee that there be Commiſſioners appointed to take an Inventory of their goods, and be accomprable to us therfore.</p>
                     <stage>Enter a Meſſenger, and ſpeaks ſoftly and haſtily to <hi>Genuino.</hi>
                     </stage>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Gen.</speaker>
                     <p>Sir, The Bandits are come faithfully, and accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding unto promiſe: <hi>Peroon,</hi> their Chieftain; and <hi>Don Peppe di Caraffa,</hi> Brother to the Duke of <hi>Mattal.</hi> deſire audience.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Maſſ.</speaker>
                     <p>Bring them in, they're welcom:</p>
                     <stage>Exit Gen.</stage>
                     <p>Theſe are Blades indeed, that, if occaſion ſerve, will ſhew my Gallants School-play.</p>
                     <stage>Enter <hi>Gen.</hi> with <hi>Peroon, Don Peppe,</hi> and <hi>Bandits.</hi>
                     </stage>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Peroon.</speaker>
                     <p>To the thrice worthy, <hi>Tomaſo Amello di Malfa,</hi> Generall of the <hi>Neopolitans,</hi> are we come to offer our ſervice.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Don. Pep.</speaker>
                     <p>And our lives to be ſacrificed in the defence of the moſt worthy <hi>Tomaſo,</hi> and the <hi>Popolo.</hi>
                     </p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Maſſ.</speaker>
                     <p>We accept your offer, and appoint your guard to our own perſon.</p>
                     <stage>
                        <hi>Peroon</hi> and <hi>Peppe</hi> make ſour faces upon <hi>Maſſenello.</hi>
                     </stage>
                     <p>Trumpets ſound.</p>
                     <p>What noyſe is that? Go know the cauſe.</p>
                     <stage>Exit Gen.</stage>
                     <p>I am not yet well acquainted with the language of Trum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pers.</p>
                     <stage>Enter <hi>Gen.</hi>
                     </stage>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Gen.</speaker>
                     <p>The Duke of <hi>Mattaloon</hi> deſires audience and ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mittance to your Excellence.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <pb n="25" facs="tcp:111318:18"/>
                     <speaker>Maſſ.</speaker>
                     <p>Let him have his will, and wee'l have ours.</p>
                     <stage>Aſide.</stage>
                     <stage>Enter Duke <hi>di Mattaloon,</hi> with Attendants.</stage>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Mat.</speaker>
                     <p>Peace to this people, and happineſſe to <hi>Tomaſo</hi> their Generall, as in the body naturall, ſo in the politique; there are cauſes which turn the beſt bloud into corrupti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on; and againſt tumeſcency there are medicines to be uſed to keep the ſwelling down, and to hinder the corrupt humours from gathering to a head: if the ef<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fects may ceaſe by taking away their cauſes, I have brought you cure: behold all your deſires are granted, here's what you aſk.</p>
                     <stage>He gives <hi>Maſſenello</hi> the pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tended priviledges.</stage>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Maſſ</speaker>
                     <p>Peruſe them <hi>Gen:</hi> they did well to ſend your grace with them: for as nothing could have ſatisfied the people, but that which you have brought; ſo nothing could have been more ſatisfactory, then that they ſhould be brought by you; a man whom the people alwaies had a good opinion of.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Gen.</speaker>
                     <p>Sir, hold, I pray, your commendations are too ſoon beſtowed; theſe Writings are all counterſeit, and not the priviledges of <hi>Carolo quinto;</hi> upon my life they are.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Maſſ</speaker>
                     <p>Hah? Counterſeit? My Lord, you have forſei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted your honour, and your honeſty together; and what is more, our good opinion of you; and are indeed no better then a Traitor to your Country.</p>
                     <stage>The people ſhoulder the Duke up and down, and begin to be outragious; the Duke all the while applyes himſelf to <hi>ſpeaks. Peroon.</hi>
                     </stage>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Mat.</speaker>
                     <p>Sir—Sir—Sir<hi>—Peroo—Peppe—</hi>can ye endure this inſolence to be done to my perſon?</p>
                     <stage>
                        <hi>Peroon</hi> gives fire at <hi>Maſſ:</hi> and his Carbine would not off.</stage>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <pb n="10" facs="tcp:111318:19"/>
                     <speaker>Maſſ.</speaker>
                     <p>If that will not off, this will.</p>
                     <stage>
                        <hi>He kils</hi> Pero <hi>with Sword.</hi>
                     </stage>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Don. Pep.</speaker>
                     <p>Guard the Duke, give the ſign to the Caſtle for ſallying out ſpeedily.</p>
                     <stage>
                        <hi>Ex.</hi> Don. Pep. <hi>with Mat.</hi> and <hi>Banditte.</hi>
                     </stage>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Maſſ.</speaker>
                     <p>And I'l regard ye, ye fine, politick, neat, faceti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous traitors: give the word there: bid them all make ready: on my ſoul, <hi>Mat.</hi> they ſhall carry thee marching over this full body of reſolves; but I will intercept thy paſſage, which ſhall be as difficult for thee or them to do, as to march over <hi>Veſuvias</hi> head. Drums beat aloud and call, our men together; if we ſtand, we ſtand; &amp; if we fal, we fall.</p>
                     <stage>Exit.</stage>
                     <stage>A battail without, Drums and Trumpets ſound the charge, Cannon and Muſket go off, as in hard fight: Bandits paſſe over the ſtage by ones, and by couples, bleeding and led. Two Bandits drop down dead upon the Stage, one after another, the firſt crying out, <hi>Ploudy Trai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tor! could I but die tearing thy fleſh with my teeth, I ſhould die contentedly; but now, I'm fain to die only with my mouth full of wiſhes.</hi>
                     </stage>
                     <stage>He dies</stage>
                     <stage>The ſecond, <hi>A Kingdom for another life to loſe, in ventring at</hi> Tomaſoes <hi>head; but I muſt give out, I've loſt all.</hi>
                     </stage>
                     <stage>He dies</stage>
                     <stage>Then enters a brave Italian banditted Captain, having loſt his arm, and ſpeaks theſe dying words, <hi>Though I was right and nobly born, yet I muſt die the death of the Baſtard Sea-Ea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gle, cal'd,</hi> Halietus, <hi>who ſeizing ſometimes on ſo big a Fiſh, that not being able to heave it out of the water, is by it drowned under the waves. I ſeiz'd not on the Fiſh, but on the Fiſherman him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf: I had once hold of him, but he was too heavy for me; I loſt that arm, and now this life.</hi>
                     </stage>
                     <stage>He dies</stage>
                     <stage>
                        <pb n="11" facs="tcp:111318:19"/> Then enters a poor Spaniard Bandit, with a half pike in his hand, he reels and ſtaggers up and down, at laſt he drops, and ſpeaks, <hi>I was born well, I liv'd honourably, but I fell ſcurvily; I will ſee if I can riſe up, that I may fall better; it may be, ſome ſaw me fall, not commendably.</hi> He riſes and charges his pike, and ſaies, <hi>This pike I won from a Neopolitan, and fall, thus, with my own Trophie in my hand.</hi>
                     </stage>
                     <stage>He dies</stage>
                     <stage>Then marches <hi>Matteloon</hi> haſtily over the Stage, bids, <hi>Call off my Brother, ſound the retreat, all's well. Don Peppe</hi> marches after him, but is ſhot through the back, as he was bringing up the rear; fals, his men keep on; and <hi>Peppe</hi> riſeth up, upon <hi>Maſſenello</hi>'s approach.</stage>
                     <stage>Enter <hi>Maſſ.</hi>
                     </stage>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Maſſ.</speaker>
                     <p>Where's this Villain?</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Don Pep.</speaker>
                     <p>Hold dog, I am <hi>Don Peppe.</hi>
                     </p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Maſſ.</speaker>
                     <p>Thou art the man I look'd for.</p>
                     <stage>runs him through,</stage>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Don Pep</speaker>
                     <p>Dogſtar where under <hi>I</hi> was born! What? Did the fates ordain me to be no better then a Sprat or Whi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting, to be thus taken by a Fiſherman? Yet high and migh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty Prince, <hi>Tomaſo,</hi> you muſt caſt your net into the Sea once more; the Fiſh you look'd for, is not caught:</p>
                     <p>And though I die, the fight this comfort gives, That by my bloud and death, my Brother lives</p>
                     <stage>he dies</stage>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Maſſ.</speaker>
                     <p>To give thee thy due, <hi>Peppo,</hi> thou wer't a brave Fellow, and 'tis pity but that thou hadſt been an honeſt man: In all my life <hi>I</hi> never heard of a braver piece of ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vice: And to deal plainly, I was aſhamed of the odds, ſeeing they have done their work: They fought like De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vils, or like men weary of living; they reach'd him into the Caſtle, as if it had been with a hand ſtretch'd through a Cloud; and they did it with ſo much eaſe, as if ſo many Sun-beams had made their way through a contrary wind. When they made a ſtand, they ſtood like a ſtretch'd out
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:111318:20"/> Rock againſt an Ocean, bidding defiance to all its Waves: And when they made their way through us, they paſs'd like a fierce wind over the heads of corn; then wheel'd about, like a Whirlwind, which rais'd not duſt, but a ſmoke ſo big bellied wi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>h fire and thunder, as with the blind thereof they conveyed this <hi>Mattaloon</hi> ſafe into the Caſtle; whil'ſt ſome few and inconſiderable (O had we known it) made good the rear with a ſtand of fifteen naked breaſts, againſt the power of NAPLES, untill cal'd off by order: then made their retreat as orderly, leaving a Bar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ricado between them and us, only of the ſmoke of pou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der; which with much difficulty, my fellow Cits and Chits got over, but too late to gain any thing, ſave only the ſight of theſe brave men who did this act. Only here <hi>Don Peppe</hi> lies, who rather fell into, then by my hands; and, curſed be the rage, and madneſſe, mingled with my ſhame, that coloured my ſword with any of his bloud: But <hi>I</hi> think <hi>I</hi> rather put him out of pain, then rid of his life: Yes, 'twas ſo, mortally ſhot through the back.
<stage>He views him.</stage> Well <hi>Peppe,</hi> though thou wert mine Enemy, yet <hi>I</hi> will erect thee a Monument: Death diſcharges all enmity, and hadſt thou liv'd, <hi>I</hi> had doubted the ſucceſſe: But</p>
                     <l>As for the reſt, I make but even a ſcoff:</l>
                     <l>The body's ſoon diſſected, when the head is off.</l>
                     <stage>Exeunt.</stage>
                  </sp>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div n="3" type="act">
               <pb n="29" facs="tcp:111318:20"/>
               <head>ACT. III.</head>
               <div n="1" type="scene">
                  <head>SCEN. I.</head>
                  <stage>Enter <hi>Vice-Roy, Card: Mat:</hi> Capt: of the Caſtle, with Attendants.</stage>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Card:</speaker>
                     <p>
                        <hi>HAc non ſucceſſit alia aggrediemur via:</hi> we muſt tack about again, and take another compaſſe, before we can arrive at our wiſhed point.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Mat.</speaker>
                     <p>Wiſhed point, do ye call it? The Devil himſelf would never wiſh for ſuch a point, as I was like to find: the Devil a point was I likely to arrive at, but the point of death: if you have not better points then theſe, I will not give three pence a dozen for all the Poynts in your ſhop.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>V. Roy.</speaker>
                     <p>My Lord, it doth not become Nobility to ſeem frighted into ſo much choler: we admir'd your va<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lour, took notice of your ſervice, and were about to give you thanks, had you not anticipated thoſe thoughts which we were about to give breath unto.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Mat.</speaker>
                     <p>When a man hath eſcap'd hanging, I hope your Majeſtie will give a man leave to be merry after it; I made but a little bold with the Cardinal's language, but I am ſure the Cardinall (a pox on his Rhetorick) had like to have been very bold with me: neither do I repent it, ſince your Majeſtie doth command me to be ſerious.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>V. Roy.</speaker>
                     <p>If it be ſo, my Lord, I am willingly miſtaken.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Card.</speaker>
                     <p>If it were not ſo, I ſhould willingly have given way to any paſſion my Lord ſhould pleaſe to have been in; for looſers ſhould have leave to ſpeak, and I'm ſure he hath loſt a Brother, whom we all ſhall miſſe as ſoon as he.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Mat.</speaker>
                     <p>Could Heavens decree have been ſo ſatisfied, mine ſhould have paid the ranſom for his life; but let us fall to conſiderations, how we may preſerve the lives that are left more conſiderable.</p>
                     <pb n="14" facs="tcp:111318:21"/>
                     <p> Lord Cardinall, 'tis you muſt beat your brains, that muſt be the anvil whereon all our ſafeties muſt be wrought.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Card.</speaker>
                     <p>My Maſters, we cannot expect otherwiſe then ſpeedily to be beſeiged: if ſo, we muſt expect ſpeedily to be brought to the ſeverall exigents of famine, and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſperateneſſe, with their Attendants, ruine and deſtructi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on. A Caſtle without ammunition and proviſion, is like a Carcaſſe that hath neither life nor ſoul; nay, like a Sche<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leton, that hath neither fleſh nor bloud; therfore theſe muſt be had: And for the effecting whereof, this is my advice; Let there be Letters deviſed to this purpoſe, that the French are upon the Sea with a great Fleet, and that their deſign is againſt NAPLES.</p>
                     <p>Theſe Letters muſt be ſo ordered, as that they may be intercepted by the way: then if this take, and we find them ſenſible of the danger, you ſhall intreat <hi>Maſſenello</hi> to accept the office of Generall of all the Forces to be rais'd in the defence of the whole Kingdom. And to make this offer appear the more reall, we will call upon all our loving Citizens to arm themſelves (for the honour and ſafety of their Country) with what arms and ammunition they have need of, out of the Magazine; which is no more but what we can neither injoy our ſelves, nor hin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der them of: ſo ſhall we render our ſelves voyd of all ſuſpicion; then ſhall we call upon them, as an act of the higheſt neceſſity, to proviſion and ammunition the Caſtle: Then ſend for <hi>Don John</hi> of <hi>Auſtria</hi> to come unto our re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcue: ſo ſhall we furniſh our ſelves with what is wanting; and by a fear of others, lull them into ſuch ſecurity of us, that we may at leiſure work all our ends both by Sea and Land, and ſo gain time, which is only able to reſtore us.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>V. Roy.</speaker>
                     <p>Your eminence ſpeaks good advice.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Card.</speaker>
                     <p>This is not all, the Queen ſhall go on with her old inſtructions, bear him in hand, with the marriage of
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:111318:21"/> his Daughter; aſſure them all exciſe to be taken off: pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſe <hi>Maſſ.</hi> that a ſtately Monument ſhall be erected in the <hi>Mercato,</hi> containing all the articles of agreement between you and him, and hereby add ſuch fuell to his proud fire;</p>
                     <l>That this deteſtable, and ſo accurſt</l>
                     <l>Toad ſwels, and with his own poyſon burſts.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>V. Roy.</speaker>
                     <p>Lord Card. Your advice is ſo good and ſeaſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nable, that it needs no debate, but execution; let it be done ſpeedily, and uſe our authority therein as ſhall be requiſite.</p>
                     <l>—Come, let us riſe,</l>
                     <l>And reduce words to actions, then we're wiſe.</l>
                     <stage>Exeunt omnes.</stage>
                     <stage>Enter <hi>Bonella,</hi> erecting ſeverall Chairs of State.</stage>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Bonell.</speaker>
                     <p>Where are you? haw!</p>
                     <stage>Enter <hi>Mariam: Agath: Flora, <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>rſula.</hi>
                     </stage>
                     <p>Come, ſit you down there, and you there, and you ſhall ſit there: by the faith of my body you muſt take ſtate upon you now: you muſt not think to do as you have done heretofore: and is it not time you ſhould? Hath not your Son all? Hath not your Huſband all? Hath not your and your Father all? Doth not the King, and the Lords, and all the Evil Councellours, hide themſelves out of his ſight? And doth not he command and rule all the people? Is not all at his diſpoſing? If he bids take off a hundred heads, they muſt loſe them: What ſhall I ſay more? In a word, he is all in all.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Mar.</speaker>
                     <p>Nay, I am ſure all this is true.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Agath.</speaker>
                     <p>Then all is well.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>
                        <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>rſula.</speaker>
                     <p>All the better.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Flora.</speaker>
                     <p>And I muſt have my all too. All is but vanity.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>
                        <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>rſula.</speaker>
                     <p>That was but a vain ſpeech, Siſter.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Flora.</speaker>
                     <p>I have another all for you, then: All is not gold that gliſters.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <pb n="32" facs="tcp:111318:22"/>
                     <speaker>Agath.</speaker>
                     <p>This girl is alwaies croſſing of her Siſter: Vile Wretch!</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Bonell.</speaker>
                     <p>Peace: how you two are alwaies rangling and jangling: What? can't you agree when you have all be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tween you? You ſhould rather agree, and plot, and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trive how you may get a ſhare in the Government; ſure he will not refuſe to hear his Mother ſpeak, I <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>row; and he is a very unkind Huſband, that will communicate his ſecrets unto his own Wife, and ſhew all that he has unto the Wife that is in his boſom. Have not great Kingdoms been excellently governed by Women? And do you think that the Popedom it ſelf could be ſo well ordered, if <hi>Don Olympia,</hi> like a good Huſwife, did not keep the Keys? Come, come, if I were as you, I would ſee what becomes of all the Money, and all the Land, and all the Houſes, and all the Houſhold-ſtuff, that is confiſcated; I would ſee, which way it went, and how it was diſpoſed, and to what end and uſes, that I would.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Mar.</speaker>
                     <p>Indeed I could wiſh, that my Son would be rul'd a little.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Ag.</speaker>
                     <p>Mother, he muſt, and ſhall: What not hear his neareſt and deareſt Friend ſpeak? And when 'tis for his own good? Who ſhould he hear?</p>
                     <stage>Enter <hi>Maſſ.</hi> and <hi>Gen.</hi> with Attendants.</stage>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Maſs.</speaker>
                     <p>Mother, your pardon a little: Wife I pray ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuſe me, I am very buſy.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Gen.</speaker>
                     <p>What would you peruſe—</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Maſs.</speaker>
                     <p>No, no, you know I have done with the Land and Houſes; I would ſee what ſums of money were ceas'd on to your uſe.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Gen.</speaker>
                     <p>O here it is.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Maſs.</speaker>
                     <p>Read it.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Gen.</speaker>
                     <p>
                        <hi>Imprimis,</hi> Found in the <hi>Duk di Mat:</hi> his houſe, 60000 Spaniſh Piſtols.</p>
                     <p>
                        <hi>Item,</hi> in his <hi>Villa,</hi> 40000 Crowns.</p>
                     <p>
                        <hi>Item,</hi> in <hi>Don Peppe</hi> his houſe—</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <pb n="33" facs="tcp:111318:22"/>
                     <speaker>Maſſ:</speaker>
                     <p>
                        <hi>Don Diego Devil!</hi> how many millions is there in all? What? do you talk to me of Crowns and Piſtols? Do you think that I have leiſure to hear you prate of Crowns and Piſtols?</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Gen.</speaker>
                     <p>Sir, there is eleven Millions in all.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Maſſ.</speaker>
                     <p>So then, eleven Millions, that's ſomething to the purpoſe, wee'l divide it all amongſt our ſelves; but I've given order that 200 houſes be pul'd down already in the Mercato, for the building of my ſelf a Palace; and I allow four Millions out of this money towards the work; I com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mand you ſee there be Workmen enough provided, that it may be built this Summer.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Gen.</speaker>
                     <p>I pray, will you ſpeak to him? He talks ſo extra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vagantly, and doth ſuch ſtrange things, that I begin to fear him extremely: beſides, he hath not ſlept a wink this four or five nights together.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Mar.</speaker>
                     <p>Dear Son, I pray you, will you be rul'd?</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Maſſ.</speaker>
                     <p>How? rul'd by a Woman? Mother, I'l tell you a ſtory, the glory of the Engliſh Nation and Sex: the Lady <hi>Ward</hi> was in hot purſuit of a new order of the Je<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſuiteſſes, to be granted to her, and her Siſternity, by the laſt Pope; which not obtaining in his daies, ſhe renews her ſuit at the entrance of this preſent Pope into his reign; ſhe makes her addreſſes, fortifies her deſires with the moſt ſpecious arguments; the Pope ſends all his Cardi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nals and Camarers out of the preſence, pretends to truſt her with the greateſt ſecret in the world, ſuch a one, as he would truſt no man withal: whereupon his Holineſſe riſes up, and fetches a little box, which he delivers unto her, deſiring her but to keep it three daies, and then to bring it unto him again; giving her a ſtrict command, not to open it: ſhe carries it home, her Siſters were impatient of being kept ignorant of what was therein contained; ſhe pleads his commands to the contrary, they urge their Warrants of a Non-diſcovery:
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:111318:23"/> aſſuring her (undoubtedly) that whatſoever were in it, they would be ſure to lay it up again, and wrap it as it was before; ſhe yeilds to their temptations; the box is opened, nothing therin but a ſtrange kind of fly, which got away, and could never be recovered, nor the like thereof: The time is come, when the box muſt be reſtored; not coming, ſhe is ſent for; ſent for; comes; there was the box, but no fly; confuſion of face, and diſtracted looks, was all her anſwer: Whereupon the Pope ſpake unto the Lady, as followeth, <hi>Madam, Now you ſee your own errour, and the frailty of all your Sex together: you deſire, amongſt the reſt of your requeſts, that you would have me grant unto your Order, and to your Sex,</hi> viz: <hi>the power of hearing Confeſſions: So,</hi> ſaith he, <hi>I ſhall commit the affairs and ſecrets of the Chriſtian World, to a thing, cal'd Woman; who from firſt to the laſt, could never let alone ſo much as an Apple upon a Tree, or a Bee in a Box, but they muſt be med<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling, though it were to ſave or confound the whole World: Therfore, Mother,</hi> I <hi>pray keep your rules to your ſelf, for I do not mean to be rul'd by any of you all.</hi>
                     </p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Agatha.</speaker>
                     <p>What, not by me, who am the Wife in your boſom?</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Maſſ.</speaker>
                     <p>No forſooth: What? hear a rib prate?</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Agatha.</speaker>
                     <p>O Lord! I would I had my old Huſband a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gain.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Maſſ.</speaker>
                     <p>Why hadſt thou ever any Huſband before?</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Agatha.</speaker>
                     <p>I mean, I would I had my Huſband now of the old faſhion, if honours have ſo chang'd his manners, that I muſt not ſpeak to him.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Maſſ.</speaker>
                     <p>I tell thee, Wife, when I was in caſe to do ſo, thou know'ſt I did it; I made thee privy, heretofore, to all the ſecret windings and turnings of my Net; and when the buſineſſe was any thing intricate, you know I alwaies cal'd you forth to unfold the myſterie, I cal'd you ever and anon to dilate the buſineſſe, and <hi>I</hi> alwaies took your ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vice about the repairing and mending the breaches of that
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:111318:23"/> our Commonwealth; you had the fing'ring and ordering, not only of the light corks, but alſo of the moſt weighty plummets of our State; I acquainted you from day to day, how many priſoners I had taken, <hi>viz.</hi> ſo many Sprats, ſo many Whitings, ſo many Gudgeons, ſo many this, ſo many that, I with-held nothing from your knowledge; but now the hand of providence hath cal'd me to hold the Scales of Juſtice; now, to be Preſident of a Councel of State; by and by, Preſident of a Councel of War: Do you think Women are ſit Creatures to be conſulted with? Muſt the affairs of State hang upon an apron-ſtring? Look to your diſhes, and ſee that your rooms be well ſwept, and never think to teach <hi>Tomaſo</hi> what he hath to do.</p>
                     <stage>Enter a Servingman.</stage>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Ser.</speaker>
                     <p>Moſt excellent Sir, there's ſeverall poor Citizens without, who beg admittance, and pray that you would do them juſtice.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Maſſ.</speaker>
                     <p>Let them have admittance: O, I do love that work alife; I am never well but when I am doing juſtice; they ſhall have juſtice to a hairs bredth.</p>
                     <stage>Enter Citizens, with l<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>ttle loaves of bread.</stage>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Citiz.</speaker>
                     <p>Moſt excellent, and thrice worthy <hi>Tomaſo,</hi> we are come to complain of the great injury we ſuffer by the moſt unconſcionable Bakers; who contrary to all right and honeſty, have preſum'd to bake ſuch loaves as theſe, as little as when the Exciſe was on foot; and want one quarter of their weight, according to the al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowance.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Maſſ.</speaker>
                     <p>Do you know the Bakers names?</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Cit.</speaker>
                     <p>Yes, here they be.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Maſſ.</speaker>
                     <p>Carry theſe men (you I ſay) unto their own Ovens mouths, and let their Ovens be heated red hot, and put them in, and there let them be bak'd themſelves;
<pb n="36" facs="tcp:111318:24"/> which will be a terrour to all Bakers, how they bake light bread<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
                     </p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Cit.</speaker>
                     <p>How long ſhall they remain there?</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Maſſ.</speaker>
                     <p>No longer, but untill you fee them all over of a cruſt, and their eies look like parch'd plumbs upon a plumb cake, and then it's time to take them forth.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Cit.</speaker>
                     <p>It ſhall be done.</p>
                     <stage>Ezeunt Cit:</stage>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Maſſ.</speaker>
                     <p>I think I have done juſtice pretty well.</p>
                     <stage>Enter Servingman.</stage>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Ser.</speaker>
                     <p>And if it pleaſe your Excellence, there are more Citizens without, deſiring audience.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Maſſ.</speaker>
                     <p>Some others, I warrant you, come for juſtice: bring them in.</p>
                     <stage>Enter Citizens.</stage>
                     <p>How novv, good fellows, what would you have with me?</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Cit.</speaker>
                     <p>We are come for juſtice to your Excellence.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Maſſ.</speaker>
                     <p>Marry, and you ſhall have it, with all my heart, as freely, and with as good a will, as ever I came from School.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Cit.</speaker>
                     <p>Sir, here's a liſt of certain Butchers, who refuſe to ſell meat otherwiſe then at the ſame rates they did, whil'ſt the Exciſe was up.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Maſſ.</speaker>
                     <p>Carry theſe men unto their own ſlaughter-houſes, and there let them be knock'd on the head, as they knock down their Oxen; and let their throats be cut, as they us'd their Calves.</p>
                     <stage>Ex. Cit.</stage>
                     <p>I think I ſhall do ſuch juſtice, e're it be long, that all the World ſhall admire me.</p>
                     <stage>Enter Servingman.</stage>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Ser.</speaker>
                     <p>Sir, there are more Citizens without, with a Petition to your Excellence.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Maſſ.</speaker>
                     <p>Let them come in: O, I am in my Kingdom now! O, how God-like it is, to rule and ſway! I could be
<pb n="37" facs="tcp:111318:24"/> contented to forſake meat, drink and ſleep, ſo that I might be doing of juſtice.</p>
                     <stage>Enter Citizen, and deliver a Petition.</stage>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Maſſ.</speaker>
                     <p>
                        <hi>Genuino,</hi> read it.</p>
                     <stage>He read<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>,</stage>
                     <stage>
                        <hi>The humble Petition of</hi> 200 <hi>poor Citizens, living in the Mercate.</hi>
                     </stage>
                     <p>
                        <hi>Humbly ſheweth,</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>THat whereas your ſaid Oratours were ſeated and poſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeſſed of good and ſubſtantiall houſes, and dwelling places, in and about the Mercato; and that by direction from your Highneſſe, the ſaid houſes, to the number of 200 are ordered to be pul'd down, to give way to the building of your Excellencie's Palace.</p>
                     <p>Now, foraſmuch as your Excellencie's ſaid Oratours are utterly deprived of places of abode:</p>
                     <p>They humbly pray, that your Excellency will be pleaſed to take the premiſſes into conſideration, and either to give ſatisfaction to the ſaid Inhabitants, for their ſaid dwelling houſes, or elſe to provide ſome other places of abode, whereby they may be diſpoſed of otherwiſe.</p>
                     <stage>And your Oratours ſhall pray, &amp;c.</stage>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Maſſ.</speaker>
                     <p>So I will, and that preſently: let them be all ſent to the Gallies, and there let them make their abode: What? When the foot of <hi>Italus</hi> his leg was in the grave, I took it by the ſmall, and reach'd it out again: When an Ocean of calamities had overwhelm'd the Land, I made that Sea run back, and keep its channel: and do you now grudge me a place to build my houſe in? Ungratefull Monſters! you ſhall ſoon know, what puniſhments are belonging to ſo great a ſin.</p>
                     <stage>Cit: kneel.</stage>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Cit.</speaker>
                     <p>Your pardon, gracious Sir, we acknowledge our fault, and are heartily contented that your will ſhould
<pb n="38" facs="tcp:111318:25"/> be fulfilled; now we underſtand our ſelves, and do hum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bly beg your pardon.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Maſſ.</speaker>
                     <l>Lie down flat upon your bellies then: ſo,</l>
                     <l>Now you may riſe up again, and go.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Cit.</speaker>
                     <p>Call you this the libertie of the Subject? and the property of what is ours?</p>
                     <p>I would we had our old Government and Gover<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nours.</p>
                     <stage>Exeunt Cit:</stage>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Maſſ.</speaker>
                     <p>I am not only good at juſtice, but I can be as good at mercy, if I pleaſe.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Gen.</speaker>
                     <p>Sir, Did you not perceive how they muttered forth their diſcontents at the preſent Government and Governours?</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Maſſ.</speaker>
                     <p>I did, my <hi>Genuino;</hi> but they ſhall find me of the nature of the Cock, that crows over the ſame dunghill, whoſe unnaturall heat gave him ſo untimely and prepo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſterous production: Their hands have rear'd me up, but I ſhall not be ſo eaſily diſſolv'd, as are their bears of ſnow, which their hands have made unſhap'd, and melted to a ſhapeleſſe lump, with the leaſt ſhower of rain: <hi>Tomaſo</hi> is more hard and laſting then braſſe or marble; not to be reduc'd to nothing, by the greateſt ſhowers of tears, that poſſibly can fall from the peoples eies. Theſe Citizens, if they abound with ſuch bad humours, as I ſee they do, <hi>I</hi>'l purge them, even to the excoriation of their guts, and make them to commend my doings, as men uſe to praiſe the biting Muſtard with tears in their eies. I'l be their Oracle my ſelf, and mean to confine all truths to my own mouth: <hi>I</hi>'l be their <hi>Coloſſus,</hi> all their Ships ſhall ſail between my legs, and their money ſhall all run between my fingers: I am not what I am for nought.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Gen.</speaker>
                     <p>Brave <hi>Tomaſo,</hi> how like thy ſelf thou ſpeakeſt, pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vender pricking hath made them caſt their firſt Rider; and they will caſt you too, if you do not hold them to hard meat.</p>
                     <pb n="39" facs="tcp:111318:25"/>
                     <p> The corruption of eſtates is the generation of Souldiers; whil'ſt you drive away their trade, you drive on your own: and what injury is it to them, to be firſt made beggars, and then to be paid with their own coyn?</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Maſſ.</speaker>
                     <p>Excellently well adviſed, my good Genius! How excellently thou ſpeakeſt!</p>
                     <stage>Enter Servingman.</stage>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Ser.</speaker>
                     <p>Sir, The Major and Aldermen are at the dore to wait upon you to the Mercato.</p>
                     <stage>Ser. whiſpers.</stage>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Maſſ.</speaker>
                     <p>'Tis well then, I ſhall have juſtice buſineſſe e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nough to laſt me all this day; and I'l lay it on, let whoſe will take it off. Daughter, anon the Prince will viſit you, ſee that you are fit to entertain him in every re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpect.</p>
                     <stage>Ex. Maſſ. Gen.</stage>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Mariam.</speaker>
                     <p>Truly my Son is ſtrangely altered of late, he is not the ſame man he was wont to be.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Agath.</speaker>
                     <p>Not ſuffered to ſpeak to him, deſpis'd and jeer'd at every word; you huſſee, can talk with him in private, and have whole hours diſcourſe together, when his Mother and his Wife, <hi>I</hi> and his Daughter too, as good as you, are not thought worthy to ſpeak to him.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Flora.</speaker>
                     <p>He is my Father; and what I do, is but in or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der to that obedience, which I owe to him; I cannot be juſtly accuſed of any intruſion upon his privacies, and for the common ſubject of his Diſcourſe, it is as unpleaſing unto me as to your ſelf.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Agatha.</speaker>
                     <p>Hang you lyar, I don't believe you.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>
                        <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>rſula.</speaker>
                     <p>It is a very likely thing; for when my Father cals her to his privy Chamber, O how ſhe trips it along as ſhe goes! How her colour riſes! How ſhe ſtarts up when ſhe is cal'd! And makes ſuch haſt! I would not
<pb n="40" facs="tcp:111318:26"/> be guilty of ſuch diſſimulation for the World.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Flora.</speaker>
                     <p>I would not be guilty of ſo much cruelty for ten Worlds.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Agatha.</speaker>
                     <p>What cruelty, you ſtinking baggage?</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Flora.</speaker>
                     <p>Not to believe a body, when one ſpeaks truth: to chide a body for that, which one cannot help: to envy me, for anothers ambition: and, in a word, to make my duty to my Father, a diſpleaſure to my Mother.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Agatha.</speaker>
                     <p>Vile Harlot! I'l make that face, the make bate of this divided family, as homely and deformed, as wounds and ſcars can make it. So, now let the Prince come and viſit you, and tell me how he likes you.</p>
                     <stage>She ſtabs her in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the face.</stage>
                     <stage>Enter <hi>Maſſ.</hi> with the <hi>Prince.</hi>
                     </stage>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Maſſ.</speaker>
                     <p>Where's my Daughter? Where's <hi>Flora?</hi> I will ſhew you a rare flower indeed.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Prince.</speaker>
                     <p>It ſeems, there was a battail fought in the field, where this flower grew, and too much bloud fell to her ſhare.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Maſſ.</speaker>
                     <p>Fury, this was thy doings.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Agath.</speaker>
                     <p>Hands off: what and if it were?</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Maſſ.</speaker>
                     <p>Then thus I'd uſe her that did it.</p>
                     <stage>He breaks her neck between his hands.</stage>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Flora.</speaker>
                     <p>O me! Father, what have you done? It had been better mine eies had been ſtab'd out of my head, then left me to behold an act ſo barbarous.</p>
                     <l>O, Father; you have plaid a Butchers part:</l>
                     <l>She ſtab'd my face, you ſtrike me to the heart.</l>
                     <stage>She offers to go away.</stage>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Prince.</speaker>
                     <p>Stay, gentle Virgin; let me hear how this buſineſſe is, before you go; pray let me hear how 'twas, for it concerns me now; I came to be your Servant, and to elect you for my Miſtris.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <pb n="41" facs="tcp:111318:26"/>
                     <speaker>Flora.</speaker>
                     <p>O Sir, I am altogether unworthy to be your Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtris, or your Miſtriſſes ſervant; it is enough, that I am your Martyr: wherfore I humbly beg you pardon, Sir;—for I</p>
                     <p>Have bloud to ſtench, and alſo tears to dry.</p>
                     <stage>Exit.</stage>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Prince.</speaker>
                     <p>A lovelier face I never ſaw: But, is ſhe thus amiable, when ſhe wants thoſe compound ornaments of bloud and tears?</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Maſſ.</speaker>
                     <p>Sir, you did but ſee the Sun behind a Cloud, or the Moon in an Eclypſe, when you beheld my Daughter how: I tell thee Prince, thou ſhalt ſee her when her face is waſh'd; and, if the ſcars have not too much disfigured her, you'l ſay, you ſaw a Queen, if beauty has domini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Prince.</speaker>
                     <p>She talk'd of being my Martyr, as if ſhe had received thoſe wounds for my ſake: how was that?</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Maſſ.</speaker>
                     <p>She did ſo; and 'twas thus: <hi>Flora</hi> is my Daugh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter by a former Wife, that Blackamore mine by this: This envious Woman, envying the happineſſe that your affections might throw upon that other Daughter, inten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded the ruin of her face, to make way for your addreſſes to this foul Dowdye: when, alack,</p>
                     <p>Her outſid's not ſo ſwarthy, as her inſid's black.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Prince.</speaker>
                     <p>She's my Martyr then indeed; methought ſhe look'd very prettily, when the bloud and tears ran races down her cheeks; and methought they did no more disfigure her, then ſtreamers of red and white do miſbecome the goodlieſt ſhip; and methought ſhe carried a great deal of modeſtie and humilitie, both in her ſpeech and countenance.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Maſſ.</speaker>
                     <p>Sir, ſhe is ſo full of humilitie, that I proteſt un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to you, I could never get her to open an ear, or to leak into her the leaſt thought of what is now. I could ne'r make her believe it: Father, ſaith ſhe, forbear this
<pb n="42" facs="tcp:111318:27"/> vain diſcourſe; 'tis juſt ſuch another likely matter; as if you could make me believe, that you could turn the Horſes of the Sun into your Cow paſture.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Prince.</speaker>
                     <p>Extreme witty! I ſhall be in love with this girl, I ſee.</p>
                     <p>Whatſoever my Father and you</p>
                     <l>Do, let you and I agree; you go about</l>
                     <l>Your buſineſſe; I'l go ſeek my Miſtris out.</l>
                     <stage>Exeunt.</stage>
                     <stage>Enter <hi>Major, Alder: Maſſ: Gen.</hi>
                     </stage>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Major.</speaker>
                     <p>Moſt excellent Sir, we have intelligence, and it comes ſeverall waies, and from very good hands: but one eſpecially amongſt the reſt, to whom we give moſt credit, is, a Letter to the Vice-Roy, which we intercepted, thin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king it to have contained matters of other conſequence; which aſſure us, that the French are upon the Seas with a mighty Fleet, and they ſay, their deſign is, for NA<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>PLES: Sir, we thought fit to acquaint you with the buſineſſe.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Maſſ.</speaker>
                     <p>Moſt excellent Sir, have you provided the mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ney for the Army, I ſent unto you for? I think fit to ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quaint you alſo with this buſineſſe.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Major.</speaker>
                     <p>Sir, the money is moſt willingly ready, and moſt readily willing they were all to pay it.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Maſſ.</speaker>
                     <p>Then moſt readily willing, and moſt willingly ready I am, that you ſhould on to your other buſineſſe.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Major.</speaker>
                     <p>Sir, I have ſpoken the buſineſſe already, it is concerning the French.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Maſſ.</speaker>
                     <p>What a pox do we care for the French? or the French with a pox? I would they were here, I long to be doing, now I have command and men enough.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Major.</speaker>
                     <p>I, but Sir, we are at odds among our ſelves, and 'tis to be feared—</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Maſſ.</speaker>
                     <p>I tell thee, Major, I'l be friends with the Devil, and ſalute his Dam, before the French ſhall have any thing to do here: and becauſe they are ſo forward, wee'l begin with them firſt: Go, and ſee that the heads of all
<pb n="43" facs="tcp:111318:27"/> the French men within NAPLES, be cut off (ſpee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dily Go without any more ado, they ſhall have juſtice, I warrant you; juſtice hath not been executed a great while, and now it takes its courſe: O how pleaſant a thing it is!</p>
                     <stage>Exeunt two Alder:</stage>
                     <p>Sound Trumpet.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Gen.</speaker>
                     <p>Hark Sir! a parley from the Caſtle.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Major.</speaker>
                     <p>Upon my life, it is about this buſineſſe.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Maſſ.</speaker>
                     <p>It comes very ſeaſonably and welcom; let ſome know who it is that deſires to treat with us.</p>
                     <stage>Exit Gen.</stage>
                     <p>If the King grants what we aſk, then 'tis likely we ſhall do—what we pleaſe, ſo ſomething may be done.</p>
                     <stage>Enter <hi>Gen.</hi>
                     </stage>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Gen.</speaker>
                     <p>It is Card: <hi>Filomarino,</hi> who humbly deſires to mediate between the King and the people.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Maſſ.</speaker>
                     <p>Bring him in; I never ſpoke with a Cardinall yet, but I believe I ſhall be hard enough for him.</p>
                     <stage>Enter Card: <hi>Filomarino.</hi>
                     </stage>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Card.</speaker>
                     <p>I am ſent by the King, unto the moſt excellent <hi>Tomaſo,</hi> and to the reſt of the moſt faithfull <hi>Neopolitan</hi> people, to acquaint them with what great dangers we are all in, by reaſon of a ſuddain and unexpected invaſion by the French, which is like to find us in all the confuſions and diſtractions, that are able to give them the greateſt advantage, and us the moſt unavoydable ruin that can be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fall a Nation, deſtinated to deſtruction: Wherfore, in regard we may, perchance, want this very time, which we beſtow in words, to imploy upon more neceſſary actions, he deſires the moſt excellent <hi>Tomaſo</hi> in the firſt place: ſecondly, all his loving people, that they will open their ears to peace, and accept of all that ever he can do, or grant, in purſuance thereof; and that every man that wants arms, or ammunition, will ſpeedily repair unto
<pb n="44" facs="tcp:111318:28"/> the Magazine, and there furniſh themſelves with what is wanting: then the moſt excellent, and thrice valiant <hi>To<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maſo,</hi> is deſired, by his Majeſtie, and the whole Councel, to admit of the conduct of theſe men againſt the enemy; an act of oblivion to paſſe, and all to be well.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Maſſ:</speaker>
                     <p>Card: What is it that the King will do?</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Card:</speaker>
                     <p>What is it that you would have him do?</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Maſs:</speaker>
                     <p>Take off all Exciſe, all, all, all, all, &amp;c.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Card.</speaker>
                     <p>It ſhall be done: I'l undertake it.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Maſſ:</speaker>
                     <p>And an oath never to ſet any up again.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Card:</speaker>
                     <p>Not only ſo, but I will tell you more: there ſhall be an everlaſting Monument of Marble ſet up in the Mercato, containing the articles of Agreement between the moſt excellent <hi>Tomaſo,</hi> on the one part; and the Vice-King, on the other.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Maſſ:</speaker>
                     <p>Now you ſay ſomething, Card: this is ſomething to the purpoſe; but there is ſomething behind, which muſt be done—or elſe, though all the French in <hi>France</hi> ſhould fly in the air, like ſo many Crows into the Land; or come by water in ſholes, like Herrings, yet will I not hear of peace, or believe a word you ſay.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Card:</speaker>
                     <p>Sir, theſe hands of mine ſhall bind them both together, but not a word of priviledges.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Maſs:</speaker>
                     <p>Not one word, but mum: Let the Monument be ſpeedily erected, and the Agreement ſworn unto; for Card: vve muſt have no delaies, for they are dangerous.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Card:</speaker>
                     <p>We will go preſently to the Vice-Roy, and have him confirm what is agreed upon: in the interim, your ſervant preſents you with this, as a little pledge of great good will, and this.</p>
                     <stage>He preſents <hi>Maſs:</hi> with a ſuit and cloak of gold, and a chain of gold.</stage>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Maſs,</speaker>
                     <p>Think you, that chains, or cloths of gold, can add? or the want of ſuch poor toyes, diminiſh from <hi>To<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maſo</hi>'s worth? He's very barren of juſt merit, that bor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rows reſpect from the earths garbage: No, Card: I tell
<pb n="45" facs="tcp:111318:28"/> thee plainly, I think my ſelf no more diſparaged by theſe cloaths, then the Sun thinks himſelf diſgrac'd by Clouds.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Card:</speaker>
                     <p>The moſt excellent <hi>Tomaſo</hi> ſpeaks admirably: I muſt confeſſe, the richeſt apparel ſets him out but mean<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, who alwaies goes ſo clothed with renown, and can put on new wonders every day: But Sir, I have known thoſe, who would value pins, and rings of ruſhes, when they proceed from a heart that truly honours them: ſuch is mine: ſuch is my Preſent: ſuch may your acceptance be, and it will be the greateſt obligation wherewith I ever was obliged.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Maſs:</speaker>
                     <p>Well, I'l wear them for your ſake, Card: you and I muſt be better acquainted; thou art an honeſt man, and ſpeak'ſt truth, I love ſuch an one: but hark you in your ear—</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Card:</speaker>
                     <p>Yes, yes.</p>
                     <stage>Maſs: whi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpers.</stage>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Card:</speaker>
                     <p>I, I, leave that to me.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Maſs:</speaker>
                     <p>Come, let us go then, wy this is excellent; no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing but aſk and have: a brave World, if it will hold.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Card:</speaker>
                     <p>
                        <hi>O tempora! O mores!</hi>
                     </p>
                     <stage>Exeunt omnes.</stage>
                  </sp>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div n="4" type="act">
               <head>ACT. IV.</head>
               <div n="1" type="scene">
                  <head>SCEN. I.</head>
                  <stage>Enter <hi>Prince,</hi> with <hi>Flora</hi> in his hand, with patches on her face.</stage>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Prince.</speaker>
                     <p>I Tell thee, ſweeteſt, envy has done thee a cour<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſie, to make thee look ten times lovelyer then thou didſt before. I proteſt, as it is my chiefeſt delight to look upon thee, ſo it will be my chiefeſt hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pineſſe to enjoy thee.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Flora.</speaker>
                     <p>Sir, as it would be an over-high preſumpti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on in me, to believe all you ſay: ſo to ſay, I do
<pb n="46" facs="tcp:111318:29"/> not believe you were in civilitie, though but to a Gen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tleman, but to my Prince it is rebellion: you ſay, you love me; nay, you proteſt you do, and ſwear it too; I, and that in an honourable way; 'tis a Princes word, a Princes proteſtation; 'tis a Prince that ſwears, if any thing can diſtill into my faith, the leaſt dram of beliefe out of theſe profeſſions of yours, it muſt be this; That it is as poſſible for me, Natures ruff caſt, Envies ruin, Poverties child, to appear acceptable in your eies, as it is poſſible for ſo good a Prince as you, to ſwear and vow otherwiſe then what your heart directs you.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Prince.</speaker>
                     <p>Deareſt Love, neceſſitie requires your ſpeedy aſſent; and for my love, which you ſeem ſo much to doubt of, reſt you ſatisfied.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Flora.</speaker>
                     <p>O Sir, that word, Neceſſity, is that which wounds my heart; for indeed it is neceſſity that ſends you unto me; there being as little merit in me to invite you, as love has reaſon to bring you hither.
<stage>She weeps.</stage> O Sir, I beſeech you, have pity upon me, and let me not be thrown into Paradiſe over the Wall, where my entrance ſhall be my ruine; or flung into your arms, or forc'd into your bed, for then I ſhall fall no welcomer then dirt, upon your cheeks; and ſhew in your arms no otherwiſe then reeds and ruſhes, which a ſinking man is glad for to imbrace, to ſave his life. O, rather then ſo, moſt Princely Sir, I beg this favour;
<stage>She kneels.</stage> I will be contented, that it may be ſo contriv'd, that to ſatisfie my Father's high ambition, it may be given out, that we are married; and ſo ordered, that there may be no doubt made thereof, untill all be ſetled: then ſhall the moſt excellent Prince chuſe him out a Wife, amongſt the race of Kings, that may be worthy of him; and bleſſe me with the happineſſe (only) of waiting upon her: for I had rather fall to my old contentment, of ſitting alone by the Sea ſhore, mending my Fathers nets; where I could
<pb n="47" facs="tcp:111318:29"/> fancy the pebles to be my Subjects, and the Waves my Courtiers, then to ſit with you upon a Throne, where I am not as well ſeated by your liking, as guarded by your love.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Prince.</speaker>
                     <p>How prettily ſhe pleads againſt her ſelf! and how forcibly ſhe attracts honour, by flying it! Come, <hi>Flora,</hi> thou art mine.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Flora.</speaker>
                     <p>Remember your ſelf, and know who I am; I am a Fiſhers Daughter.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Prince.</speaker>
                     <stage>Starts &amp; turns a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſide.</stage>
                     <p>A Fiſhers Daughter is no good ſound: Why did ſhe trouble my ears with it? Let me ſee; why it is impoſſible that hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mane nature can be ſo much above it ſelf, as is the nature of the Gods above humanitie: and yet we know, that the Gods themſelves have been ſutors unto that which we call, Woman; and if I make choyce of her, none can ſay, I have transform'd my ſelf into a Beaſt, a Bird, or into a thing that is inanimate, as have the Gods.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Flora.</speaker>
                     <p>O, how my trembling heart expects the event of this ſole conflict!</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Prince.</speaker>
                     <p>Thus it is Reſolv'd upon the Queſtion, if you will have it ſo, Neceſſity ſhall marry the Fiſhers Daugh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter: but I'l have thee; thee, not by conſtraint, but by affection; not by compulſion, but by free choyce; not to be the <hi>Jone</hi> make-peace of our Land, but as one who beſt deſerves my love, and merits me.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Flora.</speaker>
                     <p>Can there be a diſtinction then, between me, and the Fiſhers Daughter?</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Prince.</speaker>
                     <p>Yes, <hi>Flora,</hi> ſuch a one as the Sun makes between a vapour and an exhalation; which being one and the ſame thing, whil'ſt it cleaves unto the earth, is but a fog: but being exhal'd and drawn up nearer towards the Sun, it appears as glorious as it ſelf.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <pb n="48" facs="tcp:111318:30"/>
                     <speaker>Flora.</speaker>
                     <p>Great Prince, whoſe laſting fame is ſuch, that flatteries can neither hurt, nor hyperboles reach, if I were good at either: with what faces will the honourable Women look, when they ſhall ſee ſuch a one as I, as your Bride, delivered into holy hands, to be made yours?</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Prince.</speaker>
                     <p>With ſuch like faces of wonder and amaze<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, as the houſhold Gods did look, when mortals were exalted above their nature, and had their conſtellations in the higheſt Firmament, glob'd by the breaths of all the Gods, whil'ſt they were tied to reſidence in taberna<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cles made with hands, and yet durſt neither envy nor complain.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Flora.</speaker>
                     <p>Sir, You ſpeak ſuch high language, that I am afraid you exerciſe Rhetorick, rather then Love.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Prince.</speaker>
                     <p>I here engage my honour, as deeply, as the moſt unfeigned heart can direct a tongue how to oblige it, that I rather want language to expreſſe my love, then am either vain, or diſſembling, in any thing of all which I profeſſe.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Flora.</speaker>
                     <p>Why then, Sir, I can anſwer you no more, but in this language— <hi>weeps</hi> —Speak, ſpeak apace, my beſt Ora<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tours; ſpeak out and tell him the news from whence you're come; hee's good, and may, perchance, give credit—</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Prince.</speaker>
                     <p>Hold up, celeſtiall ſhowers, you'l drown a little World: the precious diſtillations are in value next to penitentiall tears, wherewith the gods oft drink themſelves to ſuch a height of kindneſſe, that they forget that they are juſt—Weep upon my boſome, and make the ſoyl fruitfull in the increaſe of that, vvhich thine ovvn iuſt me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit hath there ſovvn vvith a full hand: What! doth ſhee ſink under the burthen of her
<stage>She ſounds.</stage>
                        <pb n="49" facs="tcp:111318:30"/> owne joyes, <hi>Flora,</hi> my <hi>Flora,</hi> cannot my voyce recall thee ſooner then waters, my affections are above their heate <hi>Flora,</hi> my deareſt, dear <hi>Flora,</hi> where haſt thou been? what doſt thou meane to do?</p>
                     <stage>She comes to her ſelfe and finds her armes about his necke.</stage>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Flo:</speaker>
                     <p>Sir you may ſee my ſenſes were all fled, when mine armes preſumed to imbrace that Sun it ſhould adore, they are of too baſe mettall to make a chaine for that necke.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Prin:</speaker>
                     <p>Object that fond objection no more <hi>(I</hi> charge you) I conſider thee now as thy fathers daughter, as thy Fathers Daughter now, I ſay; who at this time ſtands the abſoluteſt of Monarchs, and commands all, me, Kings, and Vice-Kings, and the greateſt Princes, nor doe I think otherwiſe then that the Fates prodigiouſly rais'd him up to this greatneſſe to make thee my equall, I am not a Secretary of their State, nor privy Councellour to their wills, but whatſoever their Decrees are, I take it ſo, and ſo take thee.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Flo:</speaker>
                     <p>Well then, I'le tell you what I will doe for you, I will bee faithfull to you, I will never offend you, I will alwayes love you, when I am with you, I will bee a ſervant ready to obſerve and put in execution all your deſires, and when I am out of your ſight, whereſoever I am, I wil ſpend my time in ſtudying how I may next pleaſe you when I come into your preſence: when you ride from home, I will get up upon the wings of prayer, and will importune Heaven that no bad influence from their Stars may hurt you: I will ſo charme the earth with the often falling of my tears, that no noiſome vapor ſhall ariſe to prejudice my love, and when you go into the wars I will have fervency enough in prayer (lawfully) to make you ſhotfree. When my Love ſhall charge his enemies the
<pb n="50" facs="tcp:111318:31"/> mouthes of their Guns ſhall loſe their voices, and their bullets when they come near my Lord, ſhall forget their meſſage, Ile ſo prevail with—</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Prince.</speaker>
                     <p>Away, Away, thou little fool, thou: tis the pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rieſt little fond thing that ever I ſaw, what doſt thou doe, nothing but weep, <hi>ſhe weeps:</hi> Ile d<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>y up your rears for you: Come, <hi>he kiſſes her.</hi> Will that doe it? the earneſt of my hearts union: the ſeale of all that ever I have ſaid or promiſed; the aſſurance of what we are now going a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bout, without more delayes.</p>
                     <p>Let each man envy, what the gods ſhall praiſe.</p>
                     <stage>Ex<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>unt.</stage>
                  </sp>
               </div>
               <div n="2" type="scene">
                  <head>SCENA II.</head>
                  <stage>
                     <hi>Enter</hi> Vice Roy, Card. Prince, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
                  </stage>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Vice Roy.</speaker>
                     <p>How do you like your Miſtris, Sirrah?</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Prince.</speaker>
                     <p>Well Sir.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Vice Roy</speaker>
                     <p>Not very well I beleeve.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Prince.</speaker>
                     <p>Yes very well.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Vice Roy.</speaker>
                     <p>Truly?</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Prince.</speaker>
                     <p>Truly I doe.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Card.</speaker>
                     <p>You are not taken with her?</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Prince.</speaker>
                     <p>So much taken with her, that Ile take her, and bleſſe the fates which threw me headlong into ſo great happineſſe.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Vice Roy.</speaker>
                     <p>The boye's in love upon my life.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Prince</speaker>
                     <p>Sir, Ile tell you, I went unto her as if it had been ſome miſerable Ward forc<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>d by his Tyrant Guardian to a peece of ſome deformity, and to be ſacrificed to ſome ſoul beaſt, to preſerve a faire eſtate; but when <hi>I</hi> came into her preſence, I found the world could not parallel her for beauty, when I c<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>nvers'd with her; I ſaw ſhe was match<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſſe for wit, behaviour, language, or any thing, that
<pb n="51" facs="tcp:111318:31"/> might compleat or adorne the moſt accompliſhed of all her ſex: nor ſhall all the riches in the world invite me for to ſeek another Miſtris; rather then the meaneſſe of her condition, ſhould be thought a conſideration why I ſhould not have her, I would deſcend to her capacity and tu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>n fiſherman. Nor lyes it in the power of art or force of argument to wean me from her.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Vice Roy.</speaker>
                     <p>Good Son, we are all glad ſhe likes you ſo wel, we were all afraid we ſhould be faine to uſe both art and argument, to draw on your affections. But Indeed I have heard many commend her for a pretty girle.</p>
                     <stage>
                        <hi>Enter</hi> Servingman.</stage>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Ser.</speaker>
                     <p>Sir, <hi>Maſſenello</hi> is comming towards the Pallace.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Card.</speaker>
                     <p>I'le goe and bring him in.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Vice Roy.</speaker>
                     <p>By all means. Son, remember you aske y<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>ur father bleſſing when he comes in.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Prince.</speaker>
                     <p>Sir, I ſhall aske him for a bleſſing, and the greateſt bleſſing: that any man alive can give me.</p>
                     <stage>
                        <hi>Enter</hi> Maſſenello <hi>taking the right hand of the</hi> Card. <hi>all in gold. Attendants.</hi>
                     </stage>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>V. Roy,</speaker>
                     <p>
                        <hi>Tomaſo</hi> is welcome to us very oppor<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>unely, for my ſonne was (even) upon your entrance in a high en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>comion of your daughter: truly in a word hee's over head and ears in love with her, and I am glad to ſee it.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Maſſ.</speaker>
                     <p>
                        <hi>Vice Roy,</hi> you have reaſon for what you ſay: and I hope there is no love loſt; my daughter loves him as well, and though I ſay it, ſhe is a match for the beſt Prince in Europe.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>V. Roy.</speaker>
                     <p>I make no doubt of it.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Maſſ.</speaker>
                     <p>But I have not heard your Son ſpeake, yet, con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerning her, let me hear how you like her from your own month.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <pb n="52" facs="tcp:111318:32"/>
                     <speaker>Prince.</speaker>
                     <p>Sir, I like her as a new come ſoule likes Elyſium, and with the ſame affection that the moſt ambitious man likes ſitting in a throne crown'd with his owne hearts deſires.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Maſſ.</speaker>
                     <p>Why then young man thou'rt happy, when will you marry her?</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Prince.</speaker>
                     <p>When will the hunger-ſtarv'd wretch eat meat? or the thirſty ſoule quench his flames? or the man that is a cold come near the fire; but as ſoon as ere he can.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Maſſ.</speaker>
                     <p>Why then to morrow is the day, how ſayes the Vice King.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>V. Roy.</speaker>
                     <p>With all my heart, the ſooner, the better.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Card.</speaker>
                     <p>Come then we will to the <hi>Archive ſcovato,</hi> and there you both ſhall ſolemnly ſweare before the high Alter to performe all the Articles which are agreed upon between you both, in the behalfe of the new made hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pier <hi>Neopolitans,</hi> and by this the Monument contayning the articles agreed upon, is erected in the <hi>Mercato,</hi> and from the Cathedrall, the <hi>Cavalcato</hi> in the greateſt pompe, ſhall bring you both as paires coupled in the ſame de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſires of procuring your Countries good, and there before all the people, you ſhall conſecrate the Monument with your preſence; and let them all ſee how in your peaceable intentions you both meet in parrallels like <hi>Apollo's</hi> twins, and from thence unto the performance of thoſe nuptiall rates which ſhall make the peace between you ever<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>laſting.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Maſſ.</speaker>
                     <p>The <hi>Card.</hi> is a good man, he ſpeaks well, but when ſhall this be done, <hi>Card.</hi>
                     </p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Card.</speaker>
                     <l>Come one thing firſt, another at the heels,</l>
                     <l>When all's concluded action runs on wheels.</l>
                     <stage>Exeunt.</stage>
                  </sp>
               </div>
               <div n="3" type="scene">
                  <pb n="53" facs="tcp:111318:32"/>
                  <head>SCENA III.</head>
                  <stage>Enter people running over the Stage after French men, they take one.</stage>
                  <p>1. HAh <hi>Mounſier,</hi> have we taken you, off with his head.</p>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Mounſ.</speaker>
                     <p>O <hi>pardon a moy</hi> ie <hi>vous ſom pric.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>2. <hi>Mounſier</hi> don't be afraid, we won't hurt your locks, wee'l onely cut off your head.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Mounſ.</speaker>
                     <p>Vat have I done to you Gentilmen, mort dien?</p>
                     <p>3 Take heed of his Miſtris favours there.</p>
                     <stage>They cut off his head.</stage>
                     <stage>Enter people with two more for French-men, but one of them is an Engliſh-man.</stage>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Omnes.</speaker>
                     <p>More ſacks to the Mill, here's a couple of <hi>Mounſiers</hi> more, they are cutting off, I know not how ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny <hi>Mounſ.</hi> heads every where.</p>
                     <stage>One cut off.</stage>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Engliſh.</speaker>
                     <p>Swounds, I am an Engliſh-man, Engliſh man, Engliſh man, Engleterra, Engleterra.</p>
                     <p>2. He cries Engleterra, Engleterra, and the Rogue ſpeaks French.</p>
                     <p>3. You don't know, it may be Engliſh for ought you know.</p>
                     <p n="1">1. A pox confound him, he's a French-man, you may know him by his points hanging at the wrong end of his breeches.</p>
                     <p n="2">2. Away with him then, off with it, off with it, cut off his head, let it be cut off, though there were no more heads in England.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Engliſh.</speaker>
                     <p>Damn me, and ram me, and ſinke me, I am an Engliſh-man; what a devill doe you meane to dee with me, I am an Engliſh man, I tell you, what won't you
<pb n="54" facs="tcp:111318:33"/> beleeve a body when a body tells you the right: Sounds I am an Engliſh-man; hell confound you all for a com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pany of Arſe-wormes, Turky-drivers, and Goat mongers; what a devill would you have? won't you beleeve a body with a pox?</p>
                     <p n="3">3. Piſh, piſh, you may ſee he is a French-man by his locks and favours, and by his garniſhed cotpeece.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Omnes.</speaker>
                     <p>Away with him, away him, cut off his head.</p>
                     <stage>He makes reſiſtance.</stage>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Engliſh.</speaker>
                     <p>What a pox are you, are all ſtarke mad? is there never a wiſe man amongſt you, that underſtands Engliſh.</p>
                     <stage>They uſe violence to him, he raves.</stage>
                     <p>A plague confound you all, a devills dogs couples, hags and furies light upon you, for a company of hog dogs, and cow-dogs, and vinegar-bottles.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Omnes.</speaker>
                     <p>If he will not be ordered, hold up his head, and cut his throat.</p>
                     <stage>They hold him by the nape of the neck, he ſpits in their face like a Cat, at laſt cryes Boh, and frights them; in which interim, comes two Engliſh Merchants by and ſpeaks.</stage>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Merch.</speaker>
                     <p>Hold Gentlemen, hold I pray you, he is an Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſh-man, we know him.</p>
                     <p>3. You came in a very good time, or elſe you had ſound your Country-man ſhorter by the head.</p>
                     <stage>
                        <hi>Exeunt</hi> people.</stage>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Engliſh.</speaker>
                     <p>Shorter by the head ke they? hearlikins; I was never in ſuch a feare in all my life: a pox on them for a company of block-heads, they could not underſtand ſenſe, nor heare reaſon; a company of cuckoldly curs, take my head off: 'Tis more then they could do, or elſe it had not been on now.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Merch.</speaker>
                     <p>You are well enough ſerv'd, you muſt be in the French-faſhion forſooth, with your <hi>all a mode de France,</hi> with your locks, favours, and <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>ibbans.</p>
                     <stage>
                        <pb n="55" facs="tcp:111318:33"/> He cuts them off, and throws them away.</stage>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Engliſh.</speaker>
                     <p>Got by it: nay what had I like to have loſt by it? for I am ſure I had like to have loſt my head by it which is more then ever I ſhould have got by them as long as I had liv'd; but if they ever find me with your <hi>all a mode, de France,</hi> as you call it, I'le give them leave, not onely to cut off my head, but to make a devill of me when they have done, pray change cloaks, and hats with me.</p>
                     <stage>The Merchants charge cloaths with him, and were likely to loſe their heads by the miſtate.</stage>
                     <stage>Enter a Citizen with a French mans head in one hand, and his faulchion in t'other.</stage>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Engliſh.</speaker>
                     <p>Doe you heare friend; what's the price of your Cods-head?</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Cit</speaker>
                     <p>You ſee what it is, 'tis a French mans head.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Engliſh.</speaker>
                     <p>I pray let me have it, I will give thee mony for it.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Cit.</speaker>
                     <p>What mony will you give me?</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Engliſh.</speaker>
                     <p>What mony will you aske?</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Cit.</speaker>
                     <p>A French Crowne.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Engliſh.</speaker>
                     <p>What ſhall I crowne him now his head's off, hee'l be little the better for that.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Cit.</speaker>
                     <p>You ſhall have it for halfe a Crowne.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Engliſh.</speaker>
                     <p>What ſhall I give thee for that ſword?</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Cit.</speaker>
                     <p>Yours.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Engliſh.</speaker>
                     <p>Thou ſhalt, for this is an <hi>all a mode de France</hi> too, I'le endure um no more.</p>
                     <stage>He changes his brave Sword for a ruſty Semiter, paſſes two French-men over the Stage, and taking the Engliſh-man for an Italian, are in great fear.</stage>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <pb n="56" facs="tcp:111318:34"/>
                     <speaker>Eng.</speaker>
                     <p>Fee fo fum, hoh what are you French men?</p>
                     <p n="1">1. <hi>French,</hi> Mercy, Mercy, Mercy, Mercy: Making pitti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full faces.</p>
                     <stage>He kneeles, and the Engliſh man layes his ſword over the firſt French mans head and ſays,</stage>
                     <p>
                        <hi>Eng.</hi> Riſe up Sir <hi>Chriſtopher Boon-grace.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p n="2">2 <hi>French,</hi> A Sir, you be de good Engliſhman, mee can ſpreake little Engliſh, me have been one, two, three times in London, ſpare you me I pre.</p>
                     <stage>Hec takes him up by the chinne.</stage>
                     <p>
                        <hi>Engliſh,</hi> Come thou ſhalt ſee London the fourth time You muſt not bee ſo fearefull, had I been ſo tame as you, whereas now I am a cutter off of heads, I might have cari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed mine own head thus.</p>
                     <stage>Enter Citizens paſſing the Stage.</stage>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Citiz.</speaker>
                     <p>Who have you there?</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Eng.</speaker>
                     <p>They are Engliſh Gentleman of my acquaintance.</p>
                     <stage>Exeunt omnes, French hugging the Engliſh.</stage>
                  </sp>
               </div>
               <div n="4" type="scene">
                  <head>SCENA. IV.</head>
                  <stage>
                     <hi>Enter a guard with attendants,</hi> V. Roy. Maſſ: <hi>On his right hand the</hi> Card: <hi>on his left hand under the ſame Canopie into the Mereato a monument of counterfeit marble, with articles inſcrib<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed behind a curtaine, The Curtaine drawn Trumpets ſound,</hi>
                  </stage>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Card.</speaker>
                     <p>BEhold the hierogliphiks of our peace and happi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes, the landskipp of a joyful Country, the Map of a world of good that is derived unto us by this days hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pineſſe, a monument which gives the beſt characters of the moſt wiſe King, and the moſt invincible <hi>Tomaſo,</hi> here is the originall, peruſe it and ſee if they agree not.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>V. Roy.</speaker>
                     <p>They agree to a word.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <pb n="57" facs="tcp:111318:34"/>
                     <speaker>Maſſ.</speaker>
                     <p>Tis well, but is't not pitty that the winde ſhould blow upon it? or that the rayne ſhould fall upon ſo faire a peece? or that the Sun ſhould fade any of its coulours? or that bold and forward hands ſhould ſully any of its pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cious ſtones? or that time it ſelfe, ſhould eate, this, with the reſt of things?</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Card.</speaker>
                     <p>Moſt excellent Sir, I have given directions for a ſafeguard of Iron, whoſe bars ſhall be ſo high and ſharpe, that not any ſhal be able to behold it, otherwiſe then at their due diſtance.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Maſſ.</speaker>
                     <p>But Card: have you made any proviſion againſt Winde and Weather? that time it ſelfe may never fill her paunch with ſuch bits, as are too great dainties for ſuch a common feeder.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Card.</speaker>
                     <p>What the moſt excellent <hi>Tomaſo</hi> ſhall think fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther fit to the preſervation of that which preſerves ſo great fame, wee ſhall bee glad admirers of, but for my owne particular, I have given no further directions concern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing it.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Maſſ.</speaker>
                     <p>Then I ſhall, where's <hi>Sig. Burlameo.</hi>
                     </p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>V. Roy.</speaker>
                     <p>It was nobly reſolved on.</p>
                     <stage>Enter Sig. Burlameo.</stage>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Maſſ.</speaker>
                     <p>
                        <hi>Burlameo</hi> I will have thee poſt to Egypt (hah doeſt thou ſtare upon me?) and there take patterne of the big<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geſt Piramis that's there, and make me a ſhelter over this monument fifty cubits higher than the higheſt of all Egypts Piramides, and that ſhall be a Penthouſe to keep it from the rain, ſo that that greedigut Time ſhal find it the hardeſt bone to picke, that to feed upon it, it ſhall looſen the old teeth of aged time, that they ſhall drop out faſter than theſe ſtones ſhall fall, and at laſt finde it meate of ſo hard dige<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtion that time it ſelf ſhall take ſo great a ſurfeit that it ſhall ceaſe to be.</p>
                     <p>And dying yeeld unto eternity.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <pb n="58" facs="tcp:111318:35"/>
                     <speaker>Omnes.</speaker>
                     <p>Ah <hi>Maſſenello,</hi> ah <hi>Maſſenello,</hi> ah <hi>Maſſenello.</hi>
                     </p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Card</speaker>
                     <p>This is enough to make him ſtarke mad, lets fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low h<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>s humour.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Burla.</speaker>
                     <p>S<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap> I heare you, and having taken meaſure of your mind, Il<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap> f<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                           <desc>••</desc>
                        </gap> i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap> to a haire,</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Card.</speaker>
                     <p>When the d<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>vill's blinde, your reſolutions are like your ſelfe, great and glorious.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>V. Roy.</speaker>
                     <p>This age is happy that hath produc'd a man fit for ſo high and mighty undertakings.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Maſſ.</speaker>
                     <p>Now nothing's left undone, but that which muſt be done, the marriage.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>V. Roy.</speaker>
                     <l>That ſhall be don, to morrow is the day.</l>
                     <l>That <hi>Hymeneus</hi> askes us leave to play.</l>
                     <stage>Exeunt.</stage>
                  </sp>
               </div>
               <div n="5" type="scene">
                  <head>SCENA: V.</head>
                  <stage>Enter Vrſula and Bonella.</stage>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Vrſula,</speaker>
                     <p>Is the Pothecary comming? prethee go and fetch him to me, and ſtay you without.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Bon</speaker>
                     <p>I'le fetch him preſently Madam,</p>
                     <stage>Ex Bonella.</stage>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Vrſ</speaker>
                     <p>My Mothers death I will revenge on her who was the cauſe of it, b<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>ſides ten thouſand hazards I will run, before Ile ſuffer her to prince it over me, that face which age could neither blemiſh nor years decay ſhall looke as pale as death can make it. I'd rather dye my ſelfe then ſhe ſhould live to be ſo much above me, and thought worthy of ſo high eſtate whilſt I neglected, ſtand like a forelorne hope periſhing for want of ſeconds, and why? becauſe I am blacke and ſhee<hi>'s</hi> faire, marry muff: I thinke my penny as good as her's.</p>
                     <l>Pepper is blaeke and hath a good ſmacke,</l>
                     <l>And every man will it buy:</l>
                     <l>When Snow it is white, and lies in the dike</l>
                     <l>And every man let's it lye.</l>
                     <stage>
                        <pb n="59" facs="tcp:111318:35"/> Enter Pothecary.</stage>
                     <p>Honeſt Pothecary I ſent for thee to doe me a pleaſure, I am ſo troubled with Rats in my chamber that I cannot be quiet for them, I pray thee teach me a way how I may de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtroy them.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Pot.</speaker>
                     <p>Madam I will fetch you ſome Rats-baine imme<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diately.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Vrſu.</speaker>
                     <p>No, no, That's but a ſcurvy weak poyſon, they'l take it and live ſo long after it, that they'le creep hehind the Wainſcot and get into holes, and there lye and ſtinke, able to poiſon any living ſoule, I would have a quick diſpatch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing poyſon that ſhall worke preſently upon them that they ſhall not ſtir from the place.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Pot.</speaker>
                     <p>Mad: I warrant you, Ile fetch you ſuch a poyſon as ſhall do the feate.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Vrſula</speaker>
                     <p>Why well ſaid honeſt fellow: here's for thy paines.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Pot.</speaker>
                     <p>I thanke you Maddam, I never was ſo rewarded for killing of Rats, I pray God ſhee puts it to no worſe uſe, but why ſhould I ſuſpect any thing, ſhee payes mee liberally.</p>
                     <stage>
                        <hi>Enter Prince with</hi> Flora <hi>in his hand.</hi>
                     </stage>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Flora,</speaker>
                     <p>My Lord, though I am not worthy to indent with you, or ingage you to the leaſt promiſe, yet I may be in ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pacity of begging a favour at your hands:</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Prince,</speaker>
                     <p>What is it? and command what lyes within my power.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Flo.</speaker>
                     <p>Here is my only ſiſter, pleaſe you to take notice of her, and let her bee within your thoughts to make her happy.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Prince</speaker>
                     <p>As happy ſhall ſhee bee as induſtry it ſelfe can find out wayes to make her ſo-</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Vrſula.</speaker>
                     <p>I thanke you Sir: I pray Siſter keepe your hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pineſſe
<pb n="60" facs="tcp:111318:36"/> to your ſelfe, I doe not deſire to be made happy by you.</p>
                     <stage>
                        <hi>Enter</hi> Pothecary.</stage>
                     <p>
                        <hi>She flings out of the roome, and takes the</hi> Pot. <hi>with her, re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mains in occulto.</hi>
                     </p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Prince.</speaker>
                     <p>What an unmannerly ſiſter is this of thine.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Flora.</speaker>
                     <p>Sir, It may be ſhe cannot brook this happineſſe, wherewith you'r pleas'd to crowne me, and the more I ſeek to pleaſe her, the worſe ſhe is.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Prince.</speaker>
                     <p>She's angry that ſhe's ſo blacke, and thou ſo faire.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Flora.</speaker>
                     <p>Not ſo my Lord, but it may be ſhe is angry that a Prince of ſo great judgement ſhould be ſo much decei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved in his choice, as is able to verefie the proverb how that love is blinde.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Prince.</speaker>
                     <l>That love is blinde indeed that doth not ſee</l>
                     <l>Cauſes ſufficient for loving thee.</l>
                     <l>Love is not blinde becauſe he hath no eyes,</l>
                     <l>But cauſe he's guided by loves ſympath<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>es.</l>
                     <l>Love ſees, and ſeeing loves but yet in part;</l>
                     <l>But he loves throughly that doth love by heart.</l>
                     <p>But I'le tell thee my deareſt dear, thy ſiſter is mad that I am not a Sutor unto her, and I had as live be a Sutor unto the ſhades of night, and imbrace a moon-calfe as to be l<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>nckt to ſuch deformity.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Flora.</speaker>
                     <p>Not ſo an't pleaſe your highneſſe, ſhades oft<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinies are ſought for, when the brighteſt Sun-beames are eſchewed; and though a black one pleaſe not you, ſhe may be pleaſing in anothers eye.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Prince.</speaker>
                     <p>Come, come, I know and ſee her conditions to be as foule as is her viſage, which is the index of her minde; 'tis thy goodneſſe to ſay otherwiſe.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Flora.</speaker>
                     <p>Well Sir, I that am ſo happy in your affections, have the leſſe reaſon to be troubled at your diſ-affection to any elſe but indeed I muſt intreat you to love my ſiſter, though.</p>
                     <pb n="61" facs="tcp:111318:36"/>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Prince.</speaker>
                     <p>Well then, to morrow when ſhe is my ſiſter, I'le begin to love her, becauſe ſhe is my ſiſter, though there be as much difference between thee and her, as be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tween night and day.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Flora.</speaker>
                     <p>Now your highneſſe is pleas'd to ſpeake of nights and dayes, when I thinke how that there is no day to come, onely one night to paſſe, before you make me beleeve, I ſhall be your wife; my joyes begin to be orewhelm'd with feares, and ſadneſſe takes poſſeſſion of my heart, and outs thoſe wonted lively apprehenſions of the happineſſe I heretofore conceived of being yours: ſurely my heart hath onely room for you to caſt anchor there, and ſo poſſeſſe me of ſome hope, but not to bring the Sovereigne of a Sea of bliſſe, laden with the riches of your love into ſo poor a harbour.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Prince.</speaker>
                     <p>Humility is the crowne of all other vertues, and thou crowneſt humility, with ſuch a becomingneſſe, that ſhee is true humility no where but in thee; and it deſerves an exaltation, which it ſhall ſoon finde.</p>
                     <stage>Exeunt omnes. Manet Urſula.</stage>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Urſula.</speaker>
                     <l>O how I burn to be reveng'd: my malice (it is true)</l>
                     <l>Was firſt to one; now, in tha<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap> one, to two.</l>
                     <stage>Exit.</stage>
                  </sp>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div n="5" type="act">
               <head>ACTUS V.</head>
               <div n="1" type="scene">
                  <head>SCENA I.</head>
                  <p>Maſſenello <hi>ſteals in the night time unto his Monument to adore it, clad in his night Gow<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>e.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Maſſ.</speaker>
                     <p>THus in the night of ſecreſie have I ſtolne time from ſleep, that I might ſacrifice with uncontrolled devotion, unto the Idea of my minde <hi>[He adores it.]</hi> Tis a faire peece. They were fools who thought to make <hi>Babels</hi> Tower reach heaven by building of it high. Approaches made to heaven, doe
<pb n="62" facs="tcp:111318:37"/> not conſiſt in degrees of height, nor are ſteps, and rounds of ſtaires, and ladders wayes to climbe up thither, heaven is every where where men, God-like behave themſelves.</p>
                     <l>Fools were all the Wiſemen ſeven;</l>
                     <l>This is it that reaches heaven.</l>
                     <p>Come wee'l be thought men no more; I begin to be im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mortall the ſymptomes of mortallity begin to leave me, ſleep: that dull and ſenceleſſe block-head, begins to know his diſtance; and to thinke himſelfe no fit com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>panion for us, hunger and thirſt, begin to ſtand aloofe, and not to ruſh ſo boldly into our preſence as they were wont. I will ſhake off them too, and then mortallity good night.</p>
                     <p>
                        <hi>Alexander</hi> was an Aſſe, he would be deified, but never deſerv'd it: he went with an Army of drunken Grecians, and ſo ſtumbled upon a victory; but did he overcome a warlike Nation with a company of boyes and canes? did he frighten a company of daring Spaniards into their re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>treat, and ruin with the ruffling of a company of blew aprons? he that will become a Deity, muſt not reſt himſelfe contented with the attributes of High and Mighty, but he muſt be wonderfull: And now I think on <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>, I will goe and bethinke my ſelfe (how I may teach the people how to flye, that things call'd walls, and towers, flanckers, and counter-ſcarfes, palliſadoes, and ſtockadoes, fitter to keep hogs and dogs from entrance, then men indued with ſo rare a thing as is a ſoule, ſurely this invention was leſt for me to bring into the world; I'le make them as good keep out the wind, the light, the common ayre, as keep out me; and ſo I'le conquer all the world, and not like foole <hi>Alexander,</hi> lye downe and cry, becauſe there be no more worlds to conquer. I'le goe and be merry with the gods, drinke their wine, ſing cat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches with the angells, hunt the Devill, run races with the horſes of the Sun, hob-naile my ſhoos with a couple of old Moons, and ſo drinke a pot at every one of the ce<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſtiall
<pb n="63" facs="tcp:111318:37"/> ſignes. It is decreed, nor ſhall thy fort, O <hi>Rome</hi> reſiſt my vow.</p>
                     <stage>Exit furens.</stage>
                  </sp>
               </div>
               <div n="2" type="scene">
                  <head>SCENA II.</head>
                  <stage>
                     <hi>Enter</hi> Mariamma <hi>and</hi> Urſula, Mar. <hi>ſets downe a cawdle, and</hi> Urſula <hi>ſteals an opportunity to drop her poyſon into it,</hi> Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riam. <hi>calls her grandchild</hi> Flora.</stage>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Mar.</speaker>
                     <p>DAughter, the Prince hath ſent you word that he is comming to fetch you to Church, eat this be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore you go, becauſe ſtate nuptiall ceremonies are very tedious.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Flora.</speaker>
                     <p>Grandmother, I humbly thanke you: but I am ſo ſtrait lac'd that I cannot get any thing down.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Mar.</speaker>
                     <p>Come, come, you ſhall; there's a fine trick in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deed, you may chance wiſh you had.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Urſula.</speaker>
                     <p>I, and repent it too, I'le aſſure you.</p>
                     <stage>She takes, and eats part of it.</stage>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Flora.</speaker>
                     <p>I doe not like it: there is ſomething in it, that hath not a good taſte—O I begin to feel it work, Grandmother I'm poiſoned.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Mar.</speaker>
                     <p>How poyſon<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>d? nay child I'le aſſure you there's nothing in't but what is good; for I am ſure I put all the ingredien<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>s in't my ſelfe: you ſhall ſee me eat of it.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Urſula.</speaker>
                     <p>Mother don't, you don't know what may be.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Mar.</speaker>
                     <p>Don't: I'm ſure there<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>s nothing in't but good.</p>
                     <stage>The Grandmother eats of it.</stage>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Flora.</speaker>
                     <p>O my ſenſes begin to fail me, and this poyſonous drug begins to worke upon my vitalls.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Mar.</speaker>
                     <p>Curſed caitiffe, what haſt thou done, poyſoned thy Grandmother and thy ſiſter.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Urſula.</speaker>
                     <p>
                        <hi>I</hi> told you that you ſhould not eat of it, and yet you would.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Mar.</speaker>
                     <p>Why then thou confeſſeſt the murther.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <pb n="64" facs="tcp:111318:38"/>
                     <speaker>Urſula.</speaker>
                     <p>I doe, but not of you, you might have chus'd, now let us ſee in what fine pompe ſhe'l go unto her wed<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding.</p>
                     <stage>
                        <hi>Enter</hi> Prince <hi>with attendants.</hi>
                     </stage>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Mariam.</speaker>
                     <p>Here's the murthereſſe lay hold on her.</p>
                     <stage>She is laid hold on.</stage>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Prince.</speaker>
                     <p>What's the matter?</p>
                     <stage>[Flying upon her]</stage>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Mar.</speaker>
                     <p>Poyſoned, and I too by that infernall hag.</p>
                     <stage>She falls down.</stage>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Prince.</speaker>
                     <p>Furies light upon her, O my dear <hi>Flora,</hi> run, and without there is a Padua Doctor, bid him come hi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther quickly, quickly, quickly. O my deare <hi>Flora,</hi> ſhe breaths, ſhe's alive, ſhe's warme. O helpe, helpe, helpe, for the Lords ſake.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <stage>
                     <hi>Enter</hi> Doctor.</stage>
                  <p>Now Doctor ſhew your skill, and be renown'd for ever<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>more.</p>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Doctor.</speaker>
                     <p>Sir, I have an antidote that if it hath not too much wrought upon the vitals, it will recover her; how<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever, it will fetch her to her ſenſes againe for a while.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <stage>He puts it into her mouth.</stage>
                  <p>So it will diſſolve of it ſelfe, hold her up.</p>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Prince.</speaker>
                     <p>She begins to looke up already.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Flora.</speaker>
                     <p>Doſt thou know me? O I will puniſh that black devill with a hundred tortures.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Flora.</speaker>
                     <p>No my dear Lord, let not my ſiſter be put unto any tortures for my ſake; for I forgive her with all my heart, and thanke God that he hath given me ſo much ſenſe be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore I dye, as to make it my laſt requeſt to you, that you would do ſo too. I was once entring into the fineſt place that ever was ſeen; ſuch fine flowers, ſuch rare muſicke, ſuch glorious creatures! and the door was open
<pb n="65" facs="tcp:111318:38"/> for me, and all, and my thought ſome body pull'd me back and told me that one would ſpeak withme? was it you.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Prince;</speaker>
                     <p>Deare heart it was I, would you not willingly if it lay in your power, forbeare that place a while for my ſake?</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Flora</speaker>
                     <p>Though you are the fineſt man in the world, yet you are not ſo fine as any there, but I pray don't you doe any thing to my Siſter, don't diſgrace her.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Prince,</speaker>
                     <p>She hath poiſoned her Grandmother too, here ſhe lyes.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Flora;</speaker>
                     <p>I am ſorry for it, why would you uſe ſo much di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligence to recall me, and extend no charity to her.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Doctor.</speaker>
                     <p>Sir, it doth her hurt to talke ſo much, a little ſleep will doe her good, if any thing, and gentle muſicke would be requiſite if it may be had;</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Prince,</speaker>
                     <p>Yes, call for the muſick that was appointed for our nuptiall feaſt, and let them change their note, to ſad Eligies. Carry that <hi>Cerberus</hi> bitch out of my ſight, and let her be cut into a thouſand peeces, and caſt to dogges.</p>
                     <stage>aſide.</stage>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Vrſula,</speaker>
                     <l>I ſtand your fury, ſwell untill thou burſt,</l>
                     <l>I am beforehand with you, do your worſt.</l>
                     <stage>Muſicke plays, A ſong. ſhe ſleeps, he weeps,</stage>
                     <l>O <hi>Yee Gentle powers above,</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>What are you your ſelves but love?</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Pitty lovers in diſtreſſe,</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Helpe us, helpe us more or leſſe;</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>And we'l ſing you, your due praiſe;</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>If not yeares, yet give us dayes.</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>If you will not grant theſe things,</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Doe but give my ſpirit wings.</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>And ſee how glad my ſoule within</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Will be to leape out of her skin</hi>
                     </l>
                     <pb n="66" facs="tcp:111318:39"/>
                     <l> 
                        <hi>In life or death I care not whither;</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>So we two may be together.</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>If I ha'nt deſerv'd ſuch grace,</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Give me leave to buy a place,</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>To be where ſhe'le be by your doome,</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>I'le give a Kingdome for a roome.</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Crown and Scepter, Throne and Ball</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Let me have her, and take all.</hi>
                     </l>
                     <p>
                        <hi>She awakes, the muſicke ceaſeth.</hi>
                     </p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Flora</speaker>
                     <p>O Sir I muſt bid you farewell,</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Prince,</speaker>
                     <p>Stay a little my deareſt <hi>Flora,</hi> I will marry thee in ſpight of death, that when I meet thee in another world I may claime thee as one that was ſometimes mine. Prieſt do your office: ſtay a while, go fetch the murdereſſe, that I may doe it in ſpight of envy.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Servingman,</speaker>
                     <p>Sir ſhe is dead.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Prince,</speaker>
                     <p>Bring her in dead.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Serving.</speaker>
                     <p>Sir She is cut in peeces.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Prince,</speaker>
                     <p>Bring in the peeces.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Servirg.</speaker>
                     <p>Sir they were throwne to the dogges, and the dogs have eaten them.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Prince,</speaker>
                     <p>Let me have the dogs brought in, for by all thats ſacred.<hi>—Flora makes ſignes to ſpeak with him.</hi>
                     </p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Omnes,</speaker>
                     <p>Sir ſhe would ſpeake with you, ſhe feels her ſelf departing.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Prince,</speaker>
                     <p>What would my deareſt have with me.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Flora,</speaker>
                     <p>O Sir, I feele my ſelfe now going to the place from whence you called me backe, doe ſo no more for cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity ſake, I gladly would have lived yours I muſt confeſſe, but I am happier in this, that it thus lies in my power to expreſſe a fitter tribute of my love to you, rather thus to die your Martyr, then to live your wife, like <hi>Icarus I</hi> fly'd,</p>
                     <p>And ſoard too high, fell downe and di'd.</p>
                     <stage>Exit Vita.</stage>
                     <stage>
                        <pb n="67" facs="tcp:111318:39"/> Enter Maſſenello furiens.</stage>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Maſſ.</speaker>
                     <p>Where are theſe fooles that will, and won't bee married: why don't ye come away, they all ſtay for you?</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Prince,</speaker>
                     <p>O Sir, your devill daughter hath forbid the Banes.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Maſſ.</speaker>
                     <p>What's here to doe, my mother and my daughter dead? who durſt do this? that death himſelfe (had I for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bid him) durſt not do it.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Prince</speaker>
                     <p>Your owne daughter, poiſoned your own mother, and her owne Siſter.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Maſſ.</speaker>
                     <p>Where is ſhe, ſhe ſhall have juſtice.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Prince,</speaker>
                     <p>That is done already.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Maſſ.</speaker>
                     <p>How, juſtice done already, are you turn'd juſticia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry? I thought there had been no more Juſtices but my ſelfe.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Prince,</speaker>
                     <p>I thought according to the Articles of our agree<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, you were to become a private man, and to have no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing to do with juſtice buſineſſe.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Maſs.</speaker>
                     <p>I tell thee thou Prince of Darkeneſſe, I am immor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tall.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Prince,</speaker>
                     <p>I will not diſpute with you in that argument, on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly give me leave to take away this relique, that I may pay the tribute of mine eyes thereto, and performe the laſt kind office of a lover, in ſeeing her honourably interred.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Maſſ.</speaker>
                     <p>Why didſt thou love her truly? wouldeſt thou have been married to her?</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Prince,</speaker>
                     <p>Would you be wedded to your wil.—</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Maſſ.</speaker>
                     <p>Nay, if thou loveſt her but halfe ſo well, take her and much good do thee with her.</p>
                     <stage>
                        <hi>Exeunt omnes with the Corps. Manet</hi> Maſſ.</stage>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Maſſ.</speaker>
                     <p>My mother dead, my wife dead, my daughter dead, al dead? why now I ſtand by my ſelf like the popular ſtar, fixt in his ſeate, and all the heavens of great and little ones do move about me. Me thinks that preſumptuous boy began to talke of articles, doe they thinke that Ile be confin'd to articles, the ſun may be confin'd within its tropickes, the
<pb n="68" facs="tcp:111318:40"/> Sea may be confin'd within its bounds, the earth may be confin'd in a circle: but <hi>Tomaſo,</hi> cannot, will not bee confin'd: Ile therefore goe, and preſently confound, that preſumptuous monument that dares confine <hi>Tomaſo</hi> with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in any tearmes, had it root fixt in the very center, I would pluck it up: or did the articke and antarticke poles, ſtrike through it as ſtayes to hold it up, I'de caſt it downe, I'le have my words law, my will reaſon, my pleaſures obſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved, and my commands obeyed, I do not like this <hi>hoc nihil indeclinabile,</hi> i'de have <hi>ut ſunt Divorum, Mars, Baccus, Apollo, Virorum,</hi> O I love to be like one of theſe thundring gods, I'le tell you what, I'le begin a new world, and if men wo'nt follow me it is no matter, it is but to teach foxes how to ſpeake, they have cunning and ſubtlety enough, Lyons have ſtrength, and valour, horſes courage, dogs di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligence, and faithfullneſſe. It is but teaching theſe the uſe of reaſon, and we will bid defiance to all mankind: and what is this to one that is immortal: but firſt I muſt down with this confining monument. I go about it.</p>
                     <stage>Exit.</stage>
                  </sp>
               </div>
               <div n="3" type="scene">
                  <head>SCENA III.</head>
                  <stage>Enter V: <hi>Roy: Pr: Card: Cap: of the Caſtle, Mat: Lo: Cha<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>: Lo: Con: &amp;c.</hi>
                  </stage>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>V: <hi>Roy:</hi>
                     </speaker>
                     <p>WEE are all reſolved to honor that faire body parted from as faire a ſoule, with as great ſolemnity as if ſhee were my owne daughter, or my owne ſonnes wife.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Pr:</speaker>
                     <p>O Sir, the honour of thoſe rich jewells which were ingaged within this breaſt that's now turned to earth; can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not be let downe, or an inventory taken of halfe the good<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap> ſhe had there laid up in ſtore, were all men in the worl<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap> regiſters, the world paper, and the Ocean incke, The pens would ſcrawle the paper, and the paper drink That Inckie Ocean up: the worke unfiniſh'd lye: And a thouſand pities call for new ſupply.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <pb n="69" facs="tcp:111318:40"/>
                     <speaker>Card.</speaker>
                     <p>We all contribute ſorrow to your ſufferings, and pray we may not ſuffer too much with you.</p>
                     <stage>Great knocking without.</stage>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>V. <hi>Roy:</hi>
                     </speaker>
                     <p>Goe know the reaſon of this noyſe, <stage>Exit. Lo. Con.</stage> I pray that all be well, the fellow was mad e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nough before, and it may be this will make him ten times worſe.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Card:</speaker>
                     <p>I 'tis no matter, and if he be; if <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>he people be not all mad.</p>
                     <stage>
                        <hi>Enter</hi> Lo. Con. <hi>with</hi> Bakers, Brewers, Butchers, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
                     </stage>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Lo. Con.</speaker>
                     <p>I have brought you a great many of diſconten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted people, who ſeem to be as much diſpleaſed with the times as we; I thinke we ſhall be very good company together.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>V. <hi>Roy.</hi>
                     </speaker>
                     <p>Friends ſpeake your mindes freely, we give you leave.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Bakers.</speaker>
                     <p>Then Sir know; this <hi>Tomaſo</hi> is mad: ſtark mad: he runs up and downe the ſtreets, ſtriking every man, that comes in his way; has thrown downe the Articles, will ſtand to nothing, breeds confuſion, and turnes all topſie turvy.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>V. <hi>Roy.</hi>
                     </speaker>
                     <p>This is the Idoll which ye firſt ſet up, and then ador'd, now ye know the difference, betwixt a golden Scepter, and an iron rod.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Butch.</speaker>
                     <p>I but a pox confound him, he made us beleeve ſuch ſtrange ſtories, and we ſee n<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>thing performed, where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore we are come unto you in the behalfe of the reſt of our fellow Citizens to make our grievance knowne, and to crave your aſſiſtance for our redreſſe.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>V <hi>Roy.</hi>
                     </speaker>
                     <p>Alas how can I helpe you!</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Butch.</speaker>
                     <p>Nay Sir, we'l helpe you: and our ſelves too, and you'l but give us leave.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Card.</speaker>
                     <p>My Maſters, it was your own fault that brought you to this, and it muſt be your owne vertue to bring y<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>u
<pb n="70" facs="tcp:111318:41"/> out of it againe; he is of your owne making, and now you would faine be rid of him if you knew how.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Butch.</speaker>
                     <p>Yes we know how to be rid of him, and you'l give us leave.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>V. <hi>Roy.</hi>
                     </speaker>
                     <p>How.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Bakers.</speaker>
                     <p>Wee'l ſerve him as he ſerv'd us.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Butch.</speaker>
                     <p>No, as he ſerv'd us.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Omnes.</speaker>
                     <p>Ha, Ha, He.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>V. <hi>Roy.</hi>
                     </speaker>
                     <p>About it then if you have the hearts.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Butch.</speaker>
                     <p>I tell you Sir he is as dead already to my think<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing as a doore nayle.</p>
                     <stage>
                        <hi>Exeunt</hi> Bakers, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
                     </stage>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Card.</speaker>
                     <p>In the interim by all means let the Secretary be ſent for, as about ſome earneſt buſineſſe, leſt he prevent the plot, and when 'ti done, that we may be ſure of him.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>V. <hi>Roy.</hi>
                     </speaker>
                     <p>My Lord, I pray will you take the pains.</p>
                     <stage>Ex. Lo Con.</stage>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Card.</speaker>
                     <p>This is that which I was ſpeaking unto you of, we muſt lay hold upon the preſent diſguſt of the people, and make it ſerve our turnes, theſe joyned together with the <hi>Morcato</hi> men, will make a good luſty party.</p>
                     <stage>
                        <hi>Eut</hi> Lo. Con. <hi>with</hi> Gen.</stage>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Lo. Con.</speaker>
                     <p>Here is the Secretary, I met him comming to your Highneſſe.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>V <hi>Roy.</hi>
                     </speaker>
                     <p>What is your pleaſure Mr. Secretary?</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Gen.</speaker>
                     <p>Sir I am ſent unto you in the behalfe of the people, who heare how that there is a great reſort of Ci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tizens unto the Caſtle, and thoſe m<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>n of no good report.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>V. <hi>Roy.</hi>
                     </speaker>
                     <p>And what then? what of that? what would you have?</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Gen.</speaker>
                     <p>They would know their buſineſſe, and would not have you thus to countenance them; and further, they would have you leave the Caſtle, and remaine with them for their ſecurity.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <pb n="71" facs="tcp:111318:41"/>
                     <speaker>Card.</speaker>
                     <p>What people is that which you are come from? they were people that were here, and of more loyalty and underſtanding then the people that have ſent you hither. Your Maſter's mad already, and you are little better.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Gen.</speaker>
                     <p>Well <hi>Card.</hi> ere it be long you ſhall think your ſelfe the maddeſt of the three.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Card.</speaker>
                     <p>This villain muſt not goe alive out of the Caſtle, if he doe, hee'l ſpoyle the plot and us.</p>
                     <stage>Card. whiſpers.</stage>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Gen.</speaker>
                     <p>Sir, I deſire your ſpeedy anſwer.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>V. <hi>Roy.</hi>
                     </speaker>
                     <p>Our anſwer is your diſmiſſion; you may be gone.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Gen.</speaker>
                     <p>Is that all?</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Card.</speaker>
                     <p>Thou ſawcie peece of inſolence, dareſt thou con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſt with Majeſty, be gone.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Gen.</speaker>
                     <p>I go—but—remember this</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Card:</speaker>
                     <p>Let the fool go, hee'l be met with, I warrant you.</p>
                     <stage>Exeunt omnos.</stage>
                     <stage>
                        <hi>Enter</hi> Capt: <hi>with a</hi> Guard.</stage>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Capt:</speaker>
                     <p>Doe ye knew the man?</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Guard:</speaker>
                     <p>Yes, here he comes.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Cap:</speaker>
                     <p>That's he.</p>
                     <stage>
                        <hi>Enter</hi> Gennino.</stage>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Gen.</speaker>
                     <p>Open the gate there, let downe the bridge.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Guard.</speaker>
                     <p>What are you? I will not open the gate, I have no order for it.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Gen.</speaker>
                     <p>Well you ſhall rue it ere it be long.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Guard.</speaker>
                     <p>Doe you threaten the Kings guard? take that:</p>
                     <stage>kills him.</stage>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Gen.</speaker>
                     <p>O I am kill'd.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Guard.</speaker>
                     <p>It makes no matter, you ſhould have a better tongue in your head then.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Gen.</speaker>
                     <l>'Twas not my tongue that made me thus depart,</l>
                     <l>But 'twas this vile, and baſe, and treacherous heart.</l>
                     <stage>Ex. vita. Exeunt omnes.</stage>
                  </sp>
               </div>
               <div n="4" type="scene">
                  <pb n="72" facs="tcp:111318:42"/>
                  <head>SCENA IV.</head>
                  <stage>
                     <hi>Enter</hi> Maſſ. <hi>into the</hi> Mercato <hi>looking wildly; all the people about him, after a long pauſe, he ſpeaks.</hi>
                  </stage>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Maſſ.</speaker>
                     <p>WOnders! wonders! without all bounds and meaſures. Death and <hi>Cupid</hi> quartered together laſt night in the ſame room: <hi>Venus</hi> call'd up her boy betimes, time call'd death, preſent employment was for both: the more haſte, the worſe ſpeed: death groping for his quiver in the morning, laid his hand upon <hi>Cupids,</hi> and h<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>s eyes being out of his head, takes the boyes quiver for his owne: <hi>Cupid</hi> as blinde as he, took the deadly quiver in his hand, and dreſſing himſelfe in the morn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, in ordering his wings, diſorders ſome of his feathers in bruſing them againſt deaths head, <hi>Venus</hi> having in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>telligence that her ſon had got ſuch a chamber-fellow, to prevent miſtakings brings in the light of nature; <hi>Cu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pid</hi> whoſe feathers were not right, reaches and ſtretches out his wings, flutters, and claps them too and againe, and blowes out the candle: goe then as you are, ſaid <hi>Venus</hi> to <hi>Cu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap>id,</hi> Time ſaid the like to Death; both never reſted from journying till they came to my very doore, being come there, they both ſtrove for priority; Death ſaid, he ſcorn'd to give place to <hi>Cupid,</hi> becauſe he was but a boy; and the boy anſwered him as prettily againe, that he ſcorn'd to be beholding to him, and ſo flew in at the window: By this unfortunate miſtake, death who intended to ſtrike me, ſlew my daughter; and <hi>Cupid</hi> that would have play'd his part with <hi>Flora,</hi> over-acts his part with me: Here I have it, here I burne. I cannot ſay I ſwim in love, but I am over head and eares: But where ſhall I entertaine my Miſtris? I will have all this great City contriv<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>d into one houſe, and the inha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bitants ſhall leave being Citizens, and become officers;
<pb n="73" facs="tcp:111318:42"/> its no matter for their liberties, ſo they be my ſervants, for that ſhal be their greateſt freedom. Ile have my houſe well furniſh'd with Taxes and Rates, and hung about with Sequeſtrations: For I muſt tell you, Sirs, I am be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come immortall, and will make ye all Kings; but ye muſt be rul'd by me, for ye ſhall ſee me flye in the ayre, walke upon the water, run through the fire, hang up the terreſtiall globe, upon one of the Celeſtiall poles, and it ſhall ſo hang by the ſecret invention, that all Sum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mer long it ſhall ſwing towards the North, in Winter towards the Southerne clime: ſo that both Summers heat, and Winters cold ſhall be no more, but a ſweet temper all the yeare: nothing but Spring and Autome, pleaſure and profit, ſhall ye have. This is the golden age the Poets propheſied of. I tell you what, they never ſprinkled holy water over <hi>Veſuvias</hi> head; for if they had, it would have quenched its flames. To morrow I am to be married to <hi>Don Olympia.</hi> I bid you to my wedding. The triple Crowne's mine owne already; and me-thinks I heare the keys jingling in my pocket.—</p>
                     <p n="1">1. <hi>Peo.</hi> He talks extravagantly.</p>
                     <p n="2">2. <hi>Peo.</hi> Hee's wild me-thinks.</p>
                     <p n="3">3. <hi>Peo.</hi> Stark mad.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Bakers.</speaker>
                     <p>Come downe.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Butchers.</speaker>
                     <p>Come downe I ſay.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Maſſ.</speaker>
                     <p>Come downe, why ſo I will come downe; Time is to loſe his fore-top, and <hi>Cupid</hi> is to be whipt; what would you have?</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Butch.</speaker>
                     <p>Your head:</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Maſſ.</speaker>
                     <p>Take it.</p>
                     <stage>
                        <hi>He thruſts out his head, and they cut off a falſe head made of a bladder fill'd with bloud.</hi> Exeunt <hi>with his body.</hi>
                     </stage>
                  </sp>
               </div>
               <div n="5" type="scene">
                  <pb n="74" facs="tcp:111318:43"/>
                  <head>SCENA V.</head>
                  <p>
                     <hi>A Solemne funerall of</hi> Maſſ. <hi>in warlike manner paſſes over the Stage,</hi> Maſſ. <hi>open fac'd after the manner of the Italians lyes carri<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>d upon a Beere, he makes croſſes, bleſſing the people with a counterf<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>it right hand, that is directed by a Fryer who ſtands under the Beer; the people cry out wonderfull, wonderfull, he bleſses us, he was a Saint, and dyed our Martyr; this was but a trick of the royall party, who ſhall know that there are a hundred</hi> Maſſenelloes <hi>more in</hi> Naples.</p>
                  <stage>
                     <hi>Enter the funerall of</hi> Flora <hi>meeting them; the Prince chieſe mourner, the prophetick Hermite on his right hand, with all his friends, and attendants.</hi>
                  </stage>
                  <stage>
                     <hi>Maior</hi> ſpeaks.</stage>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Maior.</speaker>
                     <p>HEre they are, here they be, let's fall upon them, while we may, we have loſt too many ſuch op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>portunities; make ready my Maſters.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Pr. advances.</speaker>
                     <p>Gentlemen, what doe you meane?</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Maior.</speaker>
                     <p>We meane to let you know, what tis to murther</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Maſ.</speaker>
                     <p>whoſe ſelfe alone was worth you all; 'twas but their hands that acted what your heads contriv'd, for which you ſhall ſoon ſuffer.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Pr.</speaker>
                     <p>Let but theſe your executioners go with me to the grave, that I may but lay, my deareſt Saint to reſt in peace, and then do what you pleaſe; and for mine own part, if I aske you life, let me not live; for as her death did give my ſorrows life, ſo my death will eaſe my paine, and end my ſorrow.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Omnes.</speaker>
                     <p>He bleſſes us againe: O holy Saint!</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Maior.</speaker>
                     <p>This was a Saint, not call'd a Saint, but as you ſee confirmed by wonder, and the hand of miracle.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Hermit.</speaker>
                     <p>By the hand of an impoſtor. If you will be undeceived, you may look under the Beere, and you ſhall finde a Jugler playing the <hi>Hocus Pocus</hi> with you.</p>
                     <stage>
                        <pb n="75" facs="tcp:111318:43"/> 
                        <hi>He holds up the cloath and ſhewes the people a Fryer underneath with his juggling in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtruments, and</hi> Maſſenelloes <hi>falſe arme diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>covered.</hi>
                     </stage>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Her.</speaker>
                     <p>If neither the lawes of God, nor the lawes of na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, or the Land, nor the rule of reaſon, yet let experience beare ſome ſway, let palpable demonſtrations worke upon you, what do you doe with eyes and eares, if you will not believe their intelligence? do you not ſee your ſelves couſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ened? Do you not ſee your ſelves puppet plaid into a new war? O return therfore to your old obedience, &amp; your hearts cannot deſire more than your Prince will give you, what is paſt ſhall be forgotten, and forgiven, 'tis the falſe Cler<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gy (my deare Citizens) who have contributed the fuel, laid it together, ſet live coales under it, and then have been the bellowes to all thoſe combuſtions, as if all miſcheifes had been but ſo many exaltations of their braines, ſet on fire by the continuall motions and agitations of their tongues, witneſſe this incendiary, O returne, returne! unto your Prince, whoſe armes were alwayes open to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive you into his boſome, whenſoever you ſhould make it, though but your laſt refuge.</p>
                     <stage>
                        <hi>The people cry a King, a King, a King, fall upon the Fryer, and beat him to death, throw down the body of</hi> Maſſenello, <hi>ſaying, his lou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſie duſt ſhal not be carried into the ſepulchers of Kings.</hi>
                     </stage>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>V. <hi>Roy</hi>
                     </speaker>
                     <p>Wel then good people, ſince 'tis ſo with you, you and the children that are yet unborne ſhall have juſtcauſe to ſay this was a happy day, and ye ſhal ſoon find the differ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence between a ſuppoſitious and a natural parent: Al things ſhall be ſo forgot as if they had not been, And perchance</p>
                     <p>We'le laugh our follies out of countenance.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Omnes,</speaker>
                     <p>
                        <hi>Vita il Re di Spaine, vita, vita, vita.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <stage>Exeunt Omnes ſhouldring and affronting the Mayor.</stage>
                     <stage>
                        <pb n="76" facs="tcp:111318:44"/> 
                        <hi>Enter a</hi> Herauld at armes <hi>with Trumpetors on each ſide of him.</hi>
                     </stage>
                     <p>
                        <hi>Trumpets ſound, Heraulds proclaime.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>To all perſons of what degrees and qualities ſoever, is proclaimed a generall pardon by the moſt—</p>
                     <stage>[Maſſenello <hi>r<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap>vives, and ſtarts up, ſpeakes.]</hi>
                     </stage>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Maſſ.</speaker>
                     <p>Ha, whoſe that, that talkes of a general pardon? the word revives me, and hath brought me my ſoul again, and hath faſtened once more unto this clog.</p>
                     <p>Your pardon, and Ile ſpeake the Epilogue.</p>
                  </sp>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div type="epilogue">
               <head>Epilogue.</head>
               <lg>
                  <l>LEt Kings beware how they provoke</l>
                  <l>Their Subjects with too hard a Yoke,</l>
                  <l>For when all's done, it will not doe,</l>
                  <l>You ſee they breake the Yoke in two:</l>
                  <l>Let Subjects no rebellion move</l>
                  <l>On ſuch pretences leaſt it prove,</l>
                  <l>As ſad a thing, (which God forbid)</l>
                  <l>And fatall as to us it did.</l>
                  <l>Much blood ſpilt, great battails won,</l>
                  <l>Our treaſure ſpent, and nothing done.</l>
                  <l>Leaſt fooles the wiſe ones do deride,</l>
                  <l>Gentles foot it, beggars ride,</l>
                  <l>Lazy Lubbers get the riches,</l>
                  <l>Women preach and weare the britches,</l>
                  <l>Leſt vengeance fall as did on me</l>
                  <l>Vndone; and my poſterity,</l>
                  <l>Help'd and ſuccour'd from all parts</l>
                  <l>Supported by the peoples hearts.</l>
                  <pb n="77" facs="tcp:111318:44"/>
                  <l> Riches, honours made me glad:</l>
                  <l>Pride and glory made me mad,</l>
                  <l>Madneſſe made me do ſuch things</l>
                  <l>The people wiſh'd they had their Kings</l>
                  <l>The King aſſures them acts of grace,</l>
                  <l>Here they leave me in the place.</l>
                  <l>And like <hi>Acteon</hi> ('t may be ſe'd)</l>
                  <l>By my owne dogges I'me worried.</l>
                  <l>Fond men be rul'd, play not with Kings,</l>
                  <l>With Lyons clawes, nor Serpents ſtings.</l>
                  <l>For Rebellion, and treaſon;</l>
                  <l>Rots your name, and outs your reaſon,</l>
                  <l>Could all the traytors that are dead,</l>
                  <l>But riſe—they'd ſay—as I have ſed.</l>
               </lg>
            </div>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
