<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>The Ghost or The woman wears the breeches. A comedy written in the year MDCXL.</title>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1653</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 122 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 26 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2013-12">2013-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A85968</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing G641</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Thomason E710_8</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R202207</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99862582</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99862582</idno>
            <idno type="VID">114745</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A85968)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 114745)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Thomason Tracts ; 109:E710[8])</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>The Ghost or The woman wears the breeches. A comedy written in the year MDCXL.</title>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[4], 46, [2] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed by William Bentley for Thomas Heath dwelling in Russel street in Covent-garden near the piazza.,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London, :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1653.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>In verse.</note>
                  <note>The last leaf is blank.</note>
                  <note>Annotation on Thomason copy: "August".</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the British Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>English drama --  17th century.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2012-09</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-09</date>
            <label>Apex CoVantage</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-11</date>
            <label>Susie Lorand</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-11</date>
            <label>Susie Lorand</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-02</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:114745:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>THE GHOST OR The Woman wears the Breeches.</p>
            <p>A COMEDY Written in the Year MDCXL.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON,</hi> Printed by <hi>William Bentley</hi> for <hi>Thomas Heath</hi> dwelling in <hi>Ruſſel ſtreet</hi> in <hi>Covent-garden</hi> near the <hi>Piazza.</hi> 1653.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="dramatis_personae">
            <pb facs="tcp:114745:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:114745:2"/>
            <head>Dramata Perſonarum.</head>
            <list>
               <item>Frier.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Gentlemen of</hi> France.
<list>
                     <item>Rogat</item>
                     <item>Senio</item>
                  </list>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Sons to</hi> Rogat.
<list>
                     <item>Octavian</item>
                     <item>Dauphine</item>
                  </list>
               </item>
               <item>Babilas <hi>Son to</hi> Senio.</item>
               <item>Philarchus <hi>a rich Citizen and <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ſurer.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Gentlemen of</hi> France, <hi>Suitors to</hi> Aurelia.
<list>
                     <item>Pinnario</item>
                     <item>Procus</item>
                     <item>Valerio</item>
                  </list>
               </item>
               <item>Aurelia <hi>Daughter to</hi> Senio.</item>
               <item>Erotia a <hi>Bawd.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Cunicula <hi>her Enginier.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Engin <hi>Servant to</hi> Aurelia.</item>
               <item>Boy and Servant.</item>
            </list>
            <p>The Scene PARIS.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="prologue">
            <pb facs="tcp:114745:3"/>
            <head>PROLOGUE.</head>
            <lg>
               <l>ALl Legions broke from Hell, all Fiends to day</l>
               <l>Task'd for to work on earth, and to obey</l>
               <l>Goetian <hi>ſpells, what ſtarrs foretell the event</hi>
               </l>
               <l>Of hidden things, and future detriment,</l>
               <l>Earthquakes that ſhake us to believe and fear,</l>
               <l>Or more portentous ſpectacles ith' Air,</l>
               <l>All Circles drawn, Charms writ in Virgin-parchment</l>
               <l>Are here all turn'd to comfits and ſweet Marchpent.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>You are welcoome Gallants to a merry Ghoſt,</l>
               <l>You know a playing one, his ſign's on the poste,</l>
               <l>Rais'd by a waggiſh Scholar in the Town,</l>
               <l>Onely to affright a Citizens Breeches down:</l>
               <l>And give you all a caution on your lives,</l>
               <l>To get ſtrong Points, but weak and gentle Wives.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>But if I linger, I ſhall be acceſſary</l>
               <l>To a murther here; and yet in faith I'm ſorry;</l>
               <l>For 'bout thoſe Breeches I have much to ſay;</l>
               <l>Sit ſtill, and merrily feed on the Play;</l>
               <l>'Tis City-chear, and ſtead of Wine pray laugh,</l>
               <l>And with your money we your healths will quaff.</l>
            </lg>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="play">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:114745:3"/>
            <head>The Ghoſt.</head>
            <div n="1" type="act">
               <head>Actus primus. Scaena prima.</head>
               <stage>Enter <hi>Octavian</hi> and <hi>Babilas,</hi> they fight. <hi>Octavian</hi> falls, then <hi>exit Babilas.</hi>
               </stage>
               <stage>Enter <hi>Frier.</hi>
               </stage>
               <lg>
                  <l>
                     <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>He early ſtar hath chear'd the chanting Cock</l>
                  <l>And taught his wings to be the Countrey Clock,</l>
                  <l>The chirping Birds ſalute him with their notes,</l>
                  <l>Tuning his welcome in their warbling throats,</l>
                  <l>The gloing Marigold with other flowers</l>
                  <l>Prepare their ſcents to dreſs the ſun-freſh Bowers:</l>
                  <l>The windes ſoft whiſtlings bluſter 'gainſt the Trees,</l>
                  <l>Saluting <hi>Titan</hi> with the humming Bees;</l>
                  <l>All theſe adore thy beauty, I alone</l>
                  <l>Admire thee but for meditation.</l>
                  <stage>
                     <hi>Spies</hi> Octavian's <hi>body.</hi>
                  </stage>
                  <l>Hah! has the Moon to night wept bloudy tears?</l>
                  <l>A wounded man! Saints ſhield me from all fears.</l>
                  <l>Who is't? Diſguiſed too? I know the cauſe</l>
                  <l>For dread of the Edict and our ſtrict Laws</l>
                  <l>'Gainſt Duels now proclam'd. My charity</l>
                  <l>Shall give his body burial by me.</l>
                  <l>Raſh men when on falſe honour wings they fly</l>
                  <stage>
                     <hi>Exit with</hi> Octavian's <hi>body.</hi>
                  </stage>
                  <l>Out-glide their path, and thus to ruine hie.</l>
               </lg>
               <stage>Enter <hi>Pinnario</hi> and <hi>Procus.</hi>
               </stage>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Pin.</speaker>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Procus</hi> well met thou art going to the Wedding:</l>
                  <l>Give me thy hand, thou art bobb'd as well as I.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Pro.</speaker>
                  <l>Yes faith, thank <hi>Cupid</hi> and my own neglect.</l>
                  <l>Since I have left Coaches, and poudring of my hair,</l>
                  <pb n="2" facs="tcp:114745:4"/>
                  <l> And took delight to trace the populous ſtreets</l>
                  <l>In my huge Boots, red Cloak, and my long Sword:</l>
                  <l>She never lookt on me, Pox on all</l>
                  <l>Baſe affectation and practiſing big looks,</l>
                  <l>'Tas quite undone me, and thruſt my Miſtriſſes eys out</l>
                  <stage>
                     <hi>Enter</hi> Valerio.</stage>
                  <l>Here's t'other Fiſher that has miſt the Eel too.</l>
                  <l>Good day <hi>Valerio.</hi>
                  </l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Val.</speaker>
                  <l>Like to the transform'd <hi>Procus.</hi>
                  </l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Pin.</speaker>
                  <l>That's no where but in's looks, now truſt me Sir.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Pro.</speaker>
                  <l>Well, this <hi>Octavian</hi> has cozen'd all o'us:</l>
                  <l>Prithee let's ſtudy ſomething for revenge.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Pin.</speaker>
                  <l>But not ith' military way.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Pro.</speaker>
                  <p>O fie, hang it.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Val.</speaker>
                  <p>A baudy ſong, and <hi>Procus</hi> ſhall bear the burthen.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Pin.</speaker>
                  <l>Faith, now you talk of a baudy ſong, my Rivals,</l>
                  <l>What think you of a Randevous to night</l>
                  <l>At fat <hi>Erotia's</hi> the Curtezans.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Pro.</speaker>
                  <l>How ſoon my thoughts are back on by the Devil.</l>
                  <l>Why I was muſing what to do to cool me,</l>
                  <l>For my conceit of happineſs in <hi>Aurelia</hi>—</l>
                  <l>Well, thank my temper, and the Edict come forth</l>
                  <l>'Gainſt Duels, blith <hi>Pinnerio,</hi> thou hadſt elſe;</l>
                  <l>For being Rival to my luſt and Miſtris,</l>
                  <l>Been earth by this. But to the Whore agen.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Pin.</speaker>
                  <l>I thought thy anger would end in ſuch a trifle.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Val.</speaker>
                  <l>But is ſhe cheap and tractable my Lads.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Pro.</speaker>
                  <l>Troth that's a queſtion too. Who has any money?</l>
                  <l>Pox on lac'd handkerchiefs, and amorous Rings,</l>
                  <l>They have begger'd me.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Pin.</speaker>
                  <l>And broke thy very Purſe-ſtrings,</l>
                  <l>With hiring paltry Poets to make their Poſes.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Pro.</speaker>
                  <l>Still Fiend doſt vex me?</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Pin.</speaker>
                  <l>O the Wench, the Wench.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Pro.</speaker>
                  <l>I prethee pardon me, I had forgot the Doxy.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Pin.</speaker>
                  <l>Faith, then Ile tell you, for money, Gentlemen,</l>
                  <l>Ile give my word and promiſe for your credits.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Pro.</speaker>
                  <l>O my dear Idol.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Val.</speaker>
                  <l>Nay pox hinder him.</l>
                  <pb n="3" facs="tcp:114745:4"/>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Pin.</speaker>
                  <l>Then my Blades—but you ſhall keep it ſecret.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Pro.</speaker>
                  <l>May we turn Eunuchs if we do not, and never</l>
                  <l>Piſs when people look on us for modeſty.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Pin.</speaker>
                  <l>Why then a Maid, a Virgin, a freſh Roſe,</l>
                  <l>A ſticking <hi>Paracelſa.</hi>
                  </l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Pro.</speaker>
                  <l>Who who, nay who?</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Pin.</speaker>
                  <l>Quiſh like a Codling <hi>Procus</hi> in thy arms.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Pro.</speaker>
                  <l>Nay, nay, dear Idol, prithee who is it?</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Val.</speaker>
                  <l>Piſh, thou art ſo tyrannical, <hi>Pinnario.</hi>
                  </l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Pin.</speaker>
                  <l>Marry, a Fox-glove Lads of my preſenting:</l>
                  <l>A handſom Laſs that wanted means and money;</l>
                  <l>Whom I commiſerating did prefer</l>
                  <l>To <hi>Erotias</hi> handling, and I know by this</l>
                  <l>Is taught to tumble with dexterity,</l>
                  <stage>
                     <hi>Enter</hi> Philarchus <hi>and his Servant.</hi>
                  </stage>
                  <l>Look, look, our other Rival, old <hi>Philarchus.</hi>
                  </l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Phi.</speaker>
                  <l>Stint, ſtint your pace, you Raſcal, you Plodd on</l>
                  <l>As if I went to my <hi>Aurelia's</hi> bed.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Pro.</speaker>
                  <l>Vengeance oth' ſtone, and weather-beating Collick,</l>
                  <l>Before ſhe cheated the old Sponge, hee'd wriggle,</l>
                  <l>And throw his Gout-bound Legs a mile before us;</l>
                  <l>Nay, kiſs his rough Lips ſmooth upon her hands</l>
                  <l>Ere we could overtake him. Slight can't you ſee?</l>
                  <stage>Juſtles him.</stage>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Phi.</speaker>
                  <l>Catarrhs conſume thee, juſtle an old man.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Val.</speaker>
                  <l>An old man, and going to be married?</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Pin.</speaker>
                  <l>Aged, and get a Maidenhead to night?</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Phi.</speaker>
                  <l>I muſt give way, there is no ſtriving here.</l>
                  <stage>Enter Frier.</stage>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Pin.</speaker>
                  <l>The Frier! what makes he here?</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Fr.</speaker>
                  <l>To all good morrow.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Pro.</speaker>
                  <l>Dee hear my Ghoſtly Father, may I diſpence,</l>
                  <stage>Aſide to the Frier.</stage>
                  <l>And for all my yeſternights Confeſſion</l>
                  <l>Stew out that heat <hi>Aurelia's</hi> love hath kindled.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Fr.</speaker>
                  <l>What means my Son?</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Pro.</speaker>
                  <l>A wench, a wench, my Father.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Fr.</speaker>
                  <l>Away.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Pro.</speaker>
                  <l>Why good Father?</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Fr.</speaker>
                  <l>O poor <hi>Octavian!</hi>
                  </l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Pro.</speaker>
                  <l>Why, what of him? he is not married yet!</l>
                  <l>We that were his Rivals mean to preſent him</l>
                  <l>With a Song.</l>
                  <pb n="4" facs="tcp:114745:5"/>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Fr.</speaker>
                  <l>Alas, alas, he's ſlain.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Om.</speaker>
                  <l>Who, who?</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Pro.</speaker>
                  <l>Mum, mum, good Frier, mum, ſay nothing.</l>
                  <l>Pox of all whores and meetings. Sweet <hi>Aurelia.</hi>
                  </l>
                  <stage>Exit.</stage>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Phi.</speaker>
                  <l>Father, you ſigh, who is't I pray is ſlain?</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Fr.</speaker>
                  <l>The Bridegroom Sir, and by <hi>Aurelia's</hi> brother.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Val.</speaker>
                  <l>My dear friend <hi>Babilas,</hi> who told you this.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Ser.</speaker>
                  <l>I Sir, who ſaw young <hi>Babilas</hi> this morning</l>
                  <l>With frowning looks come to my Maſters Chamber,</l>
                  <l>And call him forth, ſince when I never ſaw him.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Val.</speaker>
                  <l>Where found the Frier <hi>Octovian?</hi>
                  </l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Fr.</speaker>
                  <l>Walking abroad</l>
                  <l>To taſte the ſweetneſs of the mornings air,</l>
                  <l>Hard by my Cell I found his breathleſs body.</l>
                  <l>I took him up, and from him now am come</l>
                  <l>To acquaint his father with the heavy news.</l>
                  <stage>Benedicite.</stage>
                  <stage>
                     <hi>Exit</hi> Frier.</stage>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Pin.</speaker>
                  <l>Nay then <hi>Aurelia,</hi> have at thee once agen.</l>
                  <stage>Exit.</stage>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Val.</speaker>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Valerio</hi> thou art unhappy to thy friend,</l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Babilas</hi> coveting his ſiſter for me</l>
                  <l>Thought to make way by young <hi>Octavians</hi> death,</l>
                  <l>Which he has now perform'd. What ſhall I do?</l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Aurelia</hi> for her brothers ſake will hate me,</l>
                  <l>She knows he lov'd me dearly. Well, Ile in too,</l>
                  <l>And win <hi>Aurelia,</hi> or finde out <hi>Babilas.</hi>
                  </l>
                  <stage>Exit.</stage>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Phi.</speaker>
                  <l>Hold, hold my ſides, O I ſhall burſt, hold, hold.</l>
                  <l>O conſtant thrift, that never leaves that man</l>
                  <l>Who honours thee. <hi>Aurelia's</hi> father's mine,</l>
                  <l>He always wiſht his daughter to my bed;</l>
                  <l>And though her amorous tears prevail'd with him</l>
                  <l>For young <hi>Octavian,</hi> yet when he hears he's dead,</l>
                  <l>He will replant me in <hi>Aurelia's</hi> heart.</l>
                  <l>Yes, jeer and flout me my young Rivals, do,</l>
                  <l>You'l finde at laſt, th' old Fox has cozen'd you.</l>
                  <stage>Exit.</stage>
               </sp>
               <stage>Enter <hi>Senio, Procus, Pinnario, Valerio.</hi>
               </stage>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Omnes.</speaker>
                  <l>Nay <hi>Senio,</hi> noble <hi>Senio,</hi> let me finde favour.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Senio.</speaker>
                  <l>This rudeneſs Gentlemen becomes you not,</l>
                  <l>Pray give me leave that my Indulgency.</l>
                  <pb facs="tcp:114745:5"/>
                  <l> May chuſe one for my Daughter, not your claimours.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Pro.</speaker>
                  <l>If I am not the handſom'ſt Ile be hang'</l>
                  <l>And lik'ſt <hi>Octavian</hi> Pox o' my oregrown Boots.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Pin.</speaker>
                  <l>Nay, ſhe is mine that's certain, I heard her ſwear once.</l>
                  <l>Next to <hi>Octavian</hi> ſhe admired me.</l>
                  <stage>
                     <hi>Enter</hi> Philarchus.</stage>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Phi.</speaker>
                  <l>Many fair years crown the moſt honour'd <hi>Senio.</hi>
                  </l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Sen.</speaker>
                  <l>Moſt Grave <hi>Philarchus.</hi> I, here's a man indeed!</l>
                  <l>Who wears ſobriety upon his looks.</l>
                  <l>Whom thrift has worm'd ſo well, that he will laſt</l>
                  <l>When all theſe Graſhoppers are ſhrunk to nothing,</l>
                  <l>I wiſh <hi>Aurelia</hi> his, and none but his.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Phi.</speaker>
                  <l>I am ſorry for your ſadneſs.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Sen.</speaker>
                  <l>I <hi>Philarchus.</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>This 'tis to love for handſomneſs and honour:</l>
                  <l>Had ſhe choſe you, ſhe might have ſmil'd, not wept.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Phi.</speaker>
                  <l>That yet may be perform'd if you conſent.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Sen:</speaker>
                  <l>She is to full of grief and will not hear.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Phi.</speaker>
                  <l>Shee'l not deny her Father for duty ſake.</l>
                  <l>Beſides, behold how many gaping Wolves</l>
                  <l>Grin with falſe hopes of her retired favour,</l>
                  <l>Whom if ſhe has, ſhe's begger'd and undone,</l>
                  <l>I am ſure, and can in the rough Winters want,</l>
                  <l>Pave all my path with Gold. Your Wedding dinner</l>
                  <l>Is now prepar'd, and a full Table met.</l>
                  <l>Coſin, not all our expectations:</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Sen.</speaker>
                  <l>Enough, I am reſolved. My noble friends,</l>
                  <l>I do perceive you all do emulate</l>
                  <l>Each others fortune. Speak, are you content</l>
                  <l>To let me chuſe a Bridegroom for my Daughter.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Omnes.</speaker>
                  <l>And hear it with delight and willingneſs.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Sen.</speaker>
                  <l>Then before all theſe, as witneſs of my gift,</l>
                  <l>I here conſent and freely do give up</l>
                  <l>My Daughter to the thrifty Grave <hi>Philarchus.</hi>
                  </l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Val.</speaker>
                  <l>Philarchus.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Pin.</speaker>
                  <l>That humming Drone.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Pro.</speaker>
                  <l>That rotten Medler.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Sen.</speaker>
                  <l>Nay Gallants, repine not, 'twas your conſent,</l>
                  <l>Nor ſhall yea yet diſcourteouſly return</l>
                  <pb n="6" facs="tcp:114745:6"/>
                  <l> Without ſome recompence; we therefore both</l>
                  <l>Intreat your company would honour as</l>
                  <l>At the Wedding dinner, which I intend this day.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Phi.</speaker>
                  <l>Shall we expect you</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Om.</speaker>
                  <l>Yes with all our hearts.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Pro.</speaker>
                  <l>Theſe damned Boots, <hi>Aurelia</hi> had been mine elſe.</l>
                  <stage>Exeunt.</stage>
               </sp>
               <stage>Enter <hi>Fryer, Rogat, Senio, Aurelia, Engin.</hi>
               </stage>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Fr.</speaker>
                  <l>What comfort Daughter, come, you muſt forget</l>
                  <l>Old grief, and dreſs your Maiden ſmiles agen</l>
                  <l>In Amorous bluſhes, to embrace <hi>Philarchus</hi>
                  </l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Aur.</speaker>
                  <l>Is he the man then?</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Fr.</speaker>
                  <l>Such is your Fathers pleaſure.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Aur.</speaker>
                  <l>You Frier contracted me and my <hi>Octavian.</hi>
                  </l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Fr.</speaker>
                  <l>Yes, that all theſe can witneſs, I did contract ye.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Sen.</speaker>
                  <l>But now ſweet Girl, my onely joy and comfort</l>
                  <l>(Since <hi>Babilas</hi> is gone) thou art alone</l>
                  <l>My ſtaff to lean on in my drooping age,</l>
                  <l>Oh do not ſlide away and make me fall</l>
                  <l>In grief as well as years, but give conſent.—</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Aur.</speaker>
                  <l>To marry old <hi>Philarchus,</hi> I conſent</l>
                  <l>And would 'twere done to night, within this hour.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Rog.</speaker>
                  <l>Can you ſo ſoon forget my loſt <hi>Octavian,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>And bury all your love in's grave with him?</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Sen.</speaker>
                  <l>Sir, you muſt pardon me, you are too buſie!</l>
                  <l>Your Son is dead, and your intereſt loſt there:</l>
                  <l>She's ſtill my Daughter, and ſhall proſecute</l>
                  <l>What I command, or elſe diſclaim her Father.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Rog.</speaker>
                  <l>Forgive me Sir, my grief alas did move me,</l>
                  <l>My grief for two loſt Sons.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Pro.</speaker>
                  <l>Two Sons! why my friend, and the mad Rogue <hi>Dauphine,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>Your young heir now, is not departed too?</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Rog.</speaker>
                  <l>He is indeed departed, for when he heard</l>
                  <l>Of my <hi>Octavians</hi> death, and by whoſe hand,</l>
                  <l>This day he left my houſe, and vows to ſearch</l>
                  <l>The flying <hi>Babilas</hi> throughout the world,</l>
                  <l>In the revenge of his unhappy brother.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Pin.</speaker>
                  <l>Good fortune after him, 'tis a valiant witty Rogue:</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Sen.</speaker>
                  <l>Hah, whoſe that ſtalks and figures on the ground</l>
                  <pb n="7" facs="tcp:114745:6"/>
                  <l> As if he conjur'd and invok'd the ſpirits?</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Aur.</speaker>
                  <l>Pray be not angry on my wedding day Sir,</l>
                  <l>It is my ſervant, preferr'd by a noble friend,</l>
                  <l>And with ſuch commendations and applauſe,</l>
                  <l>That I muſt begg you'd pleaſe to entertain him.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Sen.</speaker>
                  <l>Well I conſent, come hither. What's thy name?</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>En.</speaker>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Engin,</hi> Sir,</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Sen.</speaker>
                  <l>For water or for fire?</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>En.</speaker>
                  <l>When you command for both.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Sen.</speaker>
                  <l>Diſcreetly anſwered.</l>
                  <l>A new device comes in my head. Heark <hi>Engin.</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>Some few hours hence meet me ith' Gallerie,</l>
                  <l>I have ſome Items to acquaint thee with.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>En.</speaker>
                  <l>With duty and obſervance Ile attend you.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Sen.</speaker>
                  <l>Ha's a good thriving promiſing face believe me:</l>
                  <l>You'l not be wanting.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Rog.</speaker>
                  <l>You muſt excuſe me Sir,</l>
                  <l>My dead Sons body is to morrow interr'd,</l>
                  <l>I muſt contrive a little Ceremony.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Sen.</speaker>
                  <l>We may remember you in a Bowl of Wine.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Rog.</speaker>
                  <l>With my true thanks.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Sen.</speaker>
                  <l>And our Confeſſour.—</l>
                  <l>Come my <hi>Aurelia.</hi> Honourable <hi>Rogat.</hi>
                  </l>
                  <stage>Exeunt.</stage>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Frier.</speaker>
                  <l>Thus the world goes hurrying on</l>
                  <l>Till wonders come ne're thought upon.</l>
                  <l>He who ſleeps to night, ere day</l>
                  <l>Death inrobes with weeds of clay,</l>
                  <l>'Tis a ſteddy tottering ſtate</l>
                  <l>Propt with Love and ſhook with hate.</l>
                  <l>Like that I now am muſing on to be</l>
                  <l>Relator of a joyfull Tragedy.</l>
                  <stage>Exit.</stage>
               </sp>
            </div>
            <div n="2" type="act">
               <head>Actus ſecundus, Scaena prima.</head>
               <stage>Enter <hi>Senio, Philarchus, Engin.</hi>
               </stage>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Sen.</speaker>
                  <l>For look thee Engin, ſhould her coy denial</l>
                  <l>Be once reſiſted by thy diligence,</l>
                  <pb n="8" facs="tcp:114745:7"/>
                  <l> And old <hi>Philarchus</hi> aided by thy power.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Phi.</speaker>
                  <l>She fears if ſhe conſent not willingly,</l>
                  <l>Wee'l force her to my bed.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Sen.</speaker>
                  <l>You hit me right,</l>
                  <l>But I will not drown your ſweet inſuing pleaſures</l>
                  <l>With more ſuppoſed fears. <hi>Engin</hi> the light</l>
                  <l>A long night and a happy to my Son.</l>
                  <stage>Exit.</stage>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Phi.</speaker>
                  <l>Could I but blow away theſe humble Bees,</l>
                  <l>Time ſhould deferr my wiſht delights no longer.</l>
                  <l>Oh, theſe court Blazers buz about my ears</l>
                  <l>And kill my heart, with poiſon'd jealouſie.</l>
                  <l>Nay by this light wee'l wait you to your Chamber.</l>
                  <stage>Within.</stage>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Phi.</speaker>
                  <l>Hoida, a morris dance, and ſhe the jeſter.</l>
               </sp>
               <stage>Enter <hi>Pinnario, Procus, Valerio, Aurelia.</hi>
               </stage>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Pin.</speaker>
                  <l>Thank you for that, not ſee you in your Chamber:</l>
                  <l>Yes, and there leave you with a kiſs ſweet Bride.</l>
                  <l>Doſt here if thou lov'ſt me, kick him out o'th bed</l>
                  <l>And wriggle into his breeches.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Aur.</speaker>
                  <l>You are merry Sir.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Pro.</speaker>
                  <l>Then <hi>Venus</hi> may'ſt thou rule thy crooked Vulcan,</l>
                  <l>And let a Childe of <hi>Mars</hi> rewhet this ſword,</l>
                  <l>Upon thy ſmooth and Alabaſter breaſt.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Phi.</speaker>
                  <l>My good gay friends, is it not ſleeping times.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Pin.</speaker>
                  <l>Not yet with you theſe two hours Sir, I take it.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Pro.</speaker>
                  <l>Two hours, has this drie weather-beaten Kix</l>
                  <l>Subſtance and ſtrength to ſuck this Sugar Cane</l>
                  <l>Two hours, two minutes, and thoſe coughing ones.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Phi.</speaker>
                  <l>And yet theſe wrinckles put down your ſmooth faces.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Pin.</speaker>
                  <l>Thank the dim eyes that made the election.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>En.</speaker>
                  <l>Gentlemen, pray remember where you are,</l>
                  <l>And who you ſpeak to: 'tis <hi>Auralia's</hi> husband:</l>
                  <l>A Grave experience, thrifty Citizen;</l>
                  <l>And one that (by your favours) ſhe is pleas'd</l>
                  <l>Without compulſion to ſmile upon.</l>
                  <l>Since you are caſt off, 'tis indiſcreetly done</l>
                  <l>(In my opinion) to laugh at your own ſhame.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Pro.</speaker>
                  <l>What ſword-man have we here?</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Pin.</speaker>
                  <l>His Poet man,</l>
                  <pb n="9" facs="tcp:114745:7"/>
                  <l> That made his Verſes when he was a Suitor.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>En.</speaker>
                  <l>So, jear on.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Pin.</speaker>
                  <l>And to night is hir'd,</l>
                  <l>To reade the Hiſtory of <hi>Palmerin,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>Valiant <hi>Pariſmus</hi> and his lov'd <hi>Laurana,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>To ſtir up mettle in this crumbling fleſh.</l>
                  <l>What price my Geegaw, my Lute-ſtring baſe and treble.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>En.</speaker>
                  <l>Yes, my good Beagles, I have a Baſe hangs here</l>
                  <stage>draws.</stage>
                  <l>Shall ſing a deep note in your wanton blouds.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Au.</speaker>
                  <l>Let um abuſe thy Maſter! to um <hi>Engin.</hi>
                  </l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Val.</speaker>
                  <l>She againſt us too?</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Pro.</speaker>
                  <l>That Devil then be with her.</l>
                  <stage>Exeunt Pin. Pro. Val.</stage>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Phi.</speaker>
                  <l>VVhat recompence ſhall I reward thee with,</l>
                  <l>My beſt beſt <hi>Engin,</hi> ſaviour of my life,</l>
                  <l>Ineſtimable Jewel, bright <hi>Aurelia.</hi>
                  </l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>En.</speaker>
                  <l>Let me undreſs you Sir, the night grows late.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Phi.</speaker>
                  <l>That's my good <hi>Engin,</hi> untruſs me, prithee untruſs me.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Au.</speaker>
                  <l>And truſs agen, and make a Capon of him.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Phi.</speaker>
                  <l>How's that <hi>Aurelia?</hi> Be near me, prithee <hi>Engin.</hi>
                  </l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Au.</speaker>
                  <l>VVhat, is't the faſhion with you Citizens</l>
                  <l>To have your man to help the Bride to bed,</l>
                  <l>I muſt have Maids, and will have, ere I ſtir</l>
                  <l>Or move a finger to undreſs my ſelf.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Phi.</speaker>
                  <l>Have patience but to night, thou ſhalt hereafter.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Au.</speaker>
                  <l>Poyſon to night had fitter been apply'd:</l>
                  <l>Come hither and kiſs me. His breath not perfum'd neither.</l>
                  <stage>kiſſes him.</stage>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>En.</speaker>
                  <l>You ſhould have remembred kiſſing Comfits, Sir;</l>
                  <l>An old mans breath to a Virgin is unſavoury.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Au.</speaker>
                  <l>Some Perfumes there, I ſhall be ſtifled elſe.</l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Engin,</hi> what ſeeſt thou in his mouth? Look <hi>Engin.</hi>
                  </l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>En.</speaker>
                  <l>I, Madam, what ſhould I ſee? I ſee nothing.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Au.</speaker>
                  <l>He has borrow'd ſure a Cheek-pouch of ſome Monkey,</l>
                  <l>And ſtuft it full with Bonds and intereſt money;</l>
                  <l>Look how he chews the cud upon um now;</l>
                  <l>A pair of Horns would fit the Monſter well.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Phi.</speaker>
                  <l>Nay, prithee Sweet, forbear theſe idle words,</l>
                  <l>And be more ſerious with him who loves thee.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Au.</speaker>
                  <l>More ſottiſh and lie weltring with a Booby:</l>
                  <pb n="10" facs="tcp:114745:8"/>
                  <l> What dry skind monſter would the Bore beget?</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>En.</speaker>
                  <l>Let your wife get the ſupremacy at firſt,</l>
                  <l>Do, and be ever after in obedience</l>
                  <l>Tide at her Girdle with a ſilken ſtring.</l>
                  <l>Slight, to her Sir, and ſince ſheel not to bed,</l>
                  <l>Let her know that you can do it up as well.</l>
                  <l>To her luſtily, imbrace her, down with her.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Phi.</speaker>
                  <l>Help me then <hi>Engin.</hi>
                  </l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>En.</speaker>
                  <l>How, two againſt one woman,</l>
                  <l>Dare you aſſume the name of Husband, Sir,</l>
                  <l>And not compell her to obedience?</l>
                  <l>Come, you are a man Sir, ſhew her that you are ſo.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Au.</speaker>
                  <l>Shew him a Baſon to receive his Rheum,</l>
                  <l>And not my Lips; Are they Receptacles</l>
                  <l>To dry rank ſpittle, or drive away hoarſe coughs,</l>
                  <l>To diſſolve Burs, or whiten yellow teeth,</l>
                  <l>To exhauſt flegm, or conſume Catharrs,</l>
                  <l>Expell the ſtone, or remedy the ſcurvy.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Phi.</speaker>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Engin,</hi> where art thou, wilt not help me <hi>Engin?</hi>
                  </l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Au.</speaker>
                  <l>Remove the Palſie, or ſettle ſhaking Agues,</l>
                  <l>Unbend crookt bones, ſuck moiſture from ſore eys.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Phi.</speaker>
                  <l>Why Raſcal <hi>Engin,</hi> wilt not help me <hi>Engin?</hi>
                  </l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>En.</speaker>
                  <l>Troth Sir, ſhe ſpeaks but reaſon now me thinks,</l>
                  <l>And ſhews you a clear mirrour to behold</l>
                  <l>Your own deformities, and her abuſes.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Phi.</speaker>
                  <l>Why ſhe has converted him too. O my Temples.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>En.</speaker>
                  <l>Soft Sir, you are not toucht yet to the quick,</l>
                  <l>Untruſs him Miſtriſs, that we may ſee the wound.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Phi.</speaker>
                  <l>O Villain, Miſcreant, wilt thou betray me?</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>En.</speaker>
                  <l>Las, I but honour her for your ſake Maſter,</l>
                  <l>You ſhall finde me able and active in your ſervice,</l>
                  <l>And without grunting get you luſty boys.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Phi.</speaker>
                  <l>I am betraid.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Au.</speaker>
                  <l>O beaſt, beraid, lets ſearch him.</l>
                  <l>Sirrah help me, or I vow nere to kiſs thee more.</l>
                  <stage>
                     <hi>They pull off</hi> Phi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>larchus <hi>his breeches</hi>
                  </stage>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>En.</speaker>
                  <l>I muſt obey your wife for your credit Sir.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Au.</speaker>
                  <l>Upon my wedding-day, Ile teach you manners.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>En.</speaker>
                  <l>Theſe breeches would fit you Miſtris paſſing well.</l>
                  <pb n="11" facs="tcp:114745:8"/>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Au.</speaker>
                  <l>Nay I will wear um, and he ſhall conſent to it,</l>
                  <l>Ile ſtifle him with um elſe, Sirrah dee yield?</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Phi.</speaker>
                  <l>To what, to what, moſt dreadfull wife, pray name it?</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>En.</speaker>
                  <l>To let <hi>Aurelia</hi> be your ſole Commandreſs,</l>
                  <l>Have the preheminence in all affairs,</l>
                  <l>To ſmile on all, kiſs ſome, and dote on many,</l>
                  <l>To love, or lie with any, and not to grumble,</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Phi.</speaker>
                  <l>I do, I do.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Au.</speaker>
                  <l>Swear, ſwear, thou breechleſs Booby.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Phi.</speaker>
                  <l>By my loſt hopes.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Fn.</speaker>
                  <l>Out with your Paper Miſtris,</l>
                  <l>And write this down, you remember what he has ſaid.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Au.</speaker>
                  <l>Yes, and ſhall call him to a ſtrict account</l>
                  <stage>
                     <hi>She writes &amp; ſits aſtride o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver</hi> Philarchus</stage>
                  <l>To ſee't perform'd on <hi>Engin.</hi>
                  </l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>En.</speaker>
                  <l>To give her licence</l>
                  <l>On all occaſions lawfull or unlawfull,</l>
                  <l>To ranſack all your Coffers, and poſſeſs</l>
                  <l>Your Treaſure for her uſe and maintenance.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Phi.</speaker>
                  <l>Releaſe me and to all I do conſent.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>En.</speaker>
                  <l>The man does melt, forgive him Amazon.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Au.</speaker>
                  <l>His hand and he is free. Youl not renounce this?</l>
                  <stage>He ſets to his hand.</stage>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Phi.</speaker>
                  <l>My Religion ſooner.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Au.</speaker>
                  <l>Kiſs then and be obſervant:</l>
                  <l>Reply no word of thanks, I hate thy voice</l>
                  <l>Worſe than the howling of a hungry Wolf.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>En.</speaker>
                  <l>VVhere will it pleaſe you he ſhall lie to night?</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Au.</speaker>
                  <l>Here take my ſhield and then Ile tell thee.</l>
                  <stage>
                     <hi>She gives</hi> Engin <hi>the breeches and he puts them on a Pole, and car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries them before her.</hi>
                  </stage>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Phi.</speaker>
                  <l>O <hi>Engin, Engin,</hi> wilt thou ſerve me ſo?</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>En.</speaker>
                  <l>Where ſhe is pleaſd to place me I muſt raiſe</l>
                  <l>The houſe, nay you out of your bed to night</l>
                  <l>If ſhe commands me.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Au.</speaker>
                  <l>Why, the withdrawing Room.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>En.</speaker>
                  <l>'Tis too far from your call and from your eye:</l>
                  <l>Say you ſhould want the Chamber-pot ith' night,</l>
                  <l>Hee'd not be ready to do his duty to you:</l>
                  <l>I think your Cloſet fitter, Amazon.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Au.</speaker>
                  <l>There ſhield-bearer I have him under lock.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Phi.</speaker>
                  <l>Amazon and ſhield-bearer, this is fine.</l>
                  <pb n="12" facs="tcp:114745:9"/>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Au.</speaker>
                  <l>Dee grumble Tetworm?</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Phi.</speaker>
                  <l>Not I Amazon.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>En.</speaker>
                  <l>Spend not your breath on ſuch a water-bubble, Come Sir into the Cloſet, youl along Sir.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Phi.</speaker>
                  <l>Was ever man ſo cozen'd by an <hi>Engin.</hi>
                  </l>
                  <stage>Exeunt.</stage>
               </sp>
               <stage>Enter <hi>Valerio</hi> reading a Letter.</stage>
               <sp>
                  <stage>reades</stage>
                  <floatingText type="letter" xml:lang="eng">
                     <body>
                        <p>
                           <hi>In my abſence (dear</hi> Valerio) <hi>be preſent with my ſister, woo her, ſhe's thine by conqueſt, and</hi> Octavian's <hi>bloud by my hand let out, hath to thee reſign'd her. If thou poſſeſſeſt what I hope thou doſt, ſend me word to</hi> Orleans, <hi>where in a diſguize I live undiſcovered.</hi>
                        </p>
                        <closer>
                           <signed>Thine BABILAS.</signed>
                        </closer>
                     </body>
                  </floatingText>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Val.</speaker>
                  <l>If obſcur'd there, then why not here as well?</l>
                  <l>The ſtrictneſs of the Edict hath power with them</l>
                  <l>As well as us, I want thee <hi>Babylas,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>And I will have thee, or refuſe thy friendſhip.</l>
               </sp>
               <stage>
                  <hi>Enter</hi> Pinnario <hi>and</hi> Procus.</stage>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Pin.</speaker>
                  <l>Piſh, what a ſtudying now <hi>Valerio?</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>Prithee put up and go along with us.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Val.</speaker>
                  <l>VVhether, to th' Tavern?</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Pro.</speaker>
                  <l>To th' Tavern, penſive Raſcal,</l>
                  <l>No, to the Down-a-down, the plump wench,</l>
                  <l>The quick ey'd Laſs <hi>Pinnario</hi> told us of.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Val.</speaker>
                  <l>VVhat in thy red Mantle and thoſe cloak-bag Boots?</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Pro.</speaker>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Pinnario</hi> if thou lov'ſt me talk not on her</l>
                  <l>Till I have mangled this VVhoreſons tongue.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Pin.</speaker>
                  <l>VVhat, thou wilt not fight?</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Pro.</speaker>
                  <l>Yes, by this light will I.</l>
                  <l>I have commended my attire, praiſd my trappings,</l>
                  <l>Yet never had good luck in um ſince I wore um,</l>
                  <l>Sure theyl do ſomething when I have fought for um;</l>
                  <l>Come Sir, you that ride in Coaches, and contemn</l>
                  <l>Your foot-companions, Ile ope your boſom for you.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Val.</speaker>
                  <l>The Boot thou meanſt, why what an aſs art thou</l>
                  <l>To quarrel thus with thy friend, thy wenching friend?</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Pro.</speaker>
                  <l>VVhy, there's the vice weakens virtue in the ſtomach,</l>
                  <l>VVith what a whimſie that wench comes round my head,</l>
                  <l>And ſtupefies and dulls my active ſpirits;</l>
                  <l>Give me thy hand; thou'lt to her with us then.</l>
                  <pb n="13" facs="tcp:114745:9"/>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Val.</speaker>
                  <l>And from her too, ſo you'l put off your Boots firſt.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Pro.</speaker>
                  <l>Agen that word, <hi>Pinnario</hi> let me go.</l>
                  <stage>draws.</stage>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Val.</speaker>
                  <l>Ile give thee another pair.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Pro.</speaker>
                  <l>Gifts may mollifie.</l>
                  <stage>Enter <hi>Servant.</hi>
                  </stage>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Val.</speaker>
                  <l>Within there. Sirrah, fetch this Gentleman</l>
                  <l>My Velvet Cloak, and a pair of walking Boots.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Pin.</speaker>
                  <l>Then maiſt thou court her in a Method <hi>Procus,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>And let her all that while rip out the lining:</l>
                  <l>'Tis none of thine, Alas! thou needſt not care:</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Pro.</speaker>
                  <l>Maſs, and well remembred, let me ſee, not a farthing.</l>
                  <stage>Feels his pockets.</stage>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Pin.</speaker>
                  <l>—No matter, here's Apparel, Money, and credit.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Val.</speaker>
                  <l>Here, here, I theſe, theſe Boots will fit thee, come.</l>
                  <stage>Ent. <hi>ſervant.</hi>
                  </stage>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Pro.</speaker>
                  <l>Faith, I think they'l ne'er fit you agen.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Ser.</speaker>
                  <l>What ſhall I do with theſe hides, pray Sir.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Pro.</speaker>
                  <l>What hides, pray, Sir.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Ser.</speaker>
                  <l>I cry you mercy Sir. I mean your Boots.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Pro.</speaker>
                  <l>Why, hide 'um any where,</l>
                  <l>Drown 'um or anything, ſo I ne'er ſee 'um.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Ser.</speaker>
                  <l>I thank you Sir, I ſhall diſpoſe of them.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Pro.</speaker>
                  <l>I prithee do.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Pin.</speaker>
                  <l>Come Gallants, ſhall we go.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Pro.</speaker>
                  <l>But do'e hear, by this hand Ile take the Wall,</l>
                  <l>Ile make that bargain for my new Boots ſake.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Val.</speaker>
                  <l>Fy, how this <hi>Procus</hi> ſtill forgets himſelf,</l>
                  <l>And the old cuſtomary way he uſed.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Pin.</speaker>
                  <l>'Tis his red Mantle his led him to this errour</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Val.</speaker>
                  <l>Thou haſt forgot them, there are ſuch things as Coaches,</l>
                  <l>Hang the Wall and Kennel, they'l exempt from both.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Pro.</speaker>
                  <l>This 'tis to have a drabbing humour, oh theſe damn'd Queans.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Pin.</speaker>
                  <l>Come, come, we dally blades, 'tis very late.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Val.</speaker>
                  <l>We go <hi>Pinnario.</hi> Stay I had forgot.</l>
                  <l>Boy, here take my Keys and fetch me ſome guilt ſhillings.</l>
                  <l>A cheating way my Rogues that I have invented</l>
                  <l>To entice and coſen my night play-fellows.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Pin.</speaker>
                  <l>Excellent.</l>
                  <stage>Gives them guilt ſhillings.</stage>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Val.</speaker>
                  <l>Your hands, there's ſix a piece. My Coach there?</l>
                  <stage>Exeunt.</stage>
                  <pb n="14" facs="tcp:114745:10"/>
                  <stage>Enter <hi>Philarchus.</hi>
                  </stage>
                  <stage>As ſtealing out o' th' Cloſet.</stage>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Phi.</speaker>
                  <l>Softly, ſoftly, thus far I am crept unheard:</l>
                  <l>If I but once eſcape your tallons Rooks</l>
                  <l>Ile waſh, and rub, and ſcrub you too for this.</l>
                  <l>Firſt, (let me ſee) Ile call her Father hither,</l>
                  <l>Then raiſe the Citie, all <hi>France</hi> too if I could:</l>
                  <l>Then to the Frier, hee'l make 'um confeſs all.—</l>
                  <l>Oh, I ſhall cough, I am undon, oh, oh,</l>
                  <l>This bur will choak me if I hoakt not up.</l>
                  <stage>Engin <hi>looks out of his bed.</hi>
                  </stage>
                  <l>Hum, hum, uh, uh, uh.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>En.</speaker>
                  <l>'Tis he, <hi>Philarchus.</hi>
                  </l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Phi.</speaker>
                  <l>Uh, uh, uh, uh.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>En.</speaker>
                  <l>Ile riſe and terrifie him on a ſuddain,</l>
                  <l>This ſheet will dreſs me rarely like a Ghoſt.</l>
                  <stage>He enters like a Ghoſt.</stage>
                  <l>Whoſe that diſturbs this ſilent Room with coughs,</l>
                  <l>Or dares break ope his barred doors to walk,</l>
                  <stage>Philarchus <hi>trembles.</hi>
                  </stage>
                  <l>And trace the path of the departed Spirits?</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Phi.</speaker>
                  <l>The Devil haunts her too, what ſhall I do?</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>En.</speaker>
                  <l>Be ſilent and to bed, and never more</l>
                  <l>Diſturb the pleaſures of this ſleeping pair.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Phi.</speaker>
                  <l>Oh no, I will not, what's thy name good Devil?</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>En.</speaker>
                  <l>I am the ſpirit of ſlain <hi>Octavian,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>Oh, I could tear thee in pieces, to think that thou</l>
                  <l>Durſt think on that <hi>Aurelia</hi> with luſt</l>
                  <l>Which was once mine, continue thy obedience,</l>
                  <l>For if thou doſt betray her, I will haunt thee,</l>
                  <l>And with pale apparitions vex thy ſoul.</l>
                  <l>Depart to bed, thy cold hug, not <hi>Aurelia.</hi>
                  </l>
                  <stage>Exit Ghoſt.</stage>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Phi.</speaker>
                  <l>Good Devil I am gone, how ſhall I do</l>
                  <l>I have forgot my way, befriend me darkneſs,</l>
                  <stage>
                     <hi>He gropes in the dark, and goes to</hi> Aurelias <hi>bed in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtead of his own.</hi>
                  </stage>
                  <l>This way the cloſet lies I think. Uh, uh.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Au.</speaker>
                  <l>Who's there, <hi>Philarchus.</hi>
                  </l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Phi.</speaker>
                  <l>Uh, uh, uh, uh.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Au.</speaker>
                  <l>Oh, that my ſhield-bearer could hear me now,</l>
                  <l>Ide make him eaſe the tickling of your throat,</l>
                  <l>His bed is not ſo far, but he may hear me.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Phi.</speaker>
                  <l>Curſed miſtake.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Au.</speaker>
                  <l>Hoh ſhield-bearer awake.</l>
                  <pb n="15" facs="tcp:114745:10"/>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>En.</speaker>
                  <l>What ails my Amaſon.</l>
                  <stage>Within<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
                  </stage>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Au.</speaker>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Philarchus</hi> here.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>En.</speaker>
                  <l>How's that <hi>Philarchus,</hi> nay, then put on the breeches.</l>
                  <stage>Within.</stage>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Au.</speaker>
                  <l>Sirrah what make you here, confeſs, confeſs?</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>En.</speaker>
                  <l>Conjure up the Ghoſt, hee'l reveal all he intended.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Phi.</speaker>
                  <l>Oh, oh my heart the Ghoſt, dear wife forbear.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Au.</speaker>
                  <l>He calls me wife, call him up ſhield-bearer.</l>
                  <stage>Enter Engin <hi>with the breeches on a Pole.</hi>
                  </stage>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Phi.</speaker>
                  <l>Oh I ſhall ſhakes to powder, I confeſs all.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>En.</speaker>
                  <l>Without premeditation quickly, come.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Phi.</speaker>
                  <l>I meant this night to ſteal away and leave you,</l>
                  <l>Then raiſe old <hi>Senio,</hi> the <hi>Erier, Rogat,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>And to conduct 'um hither to be witneſs.—</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>En.</speaker>
                  <l>Of what, ſpeak villain?</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Phi.</speaker>
                  <l>Of my impriſonment and—</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Au.</speaker>
                  <l>Oh Dotard betray his Lady and Empreſs, the breeches.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>En.</speaker>
                  <l>Here <hi>Amazon.</hi>
                  </l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Phi.</speaker>
                  <l>Dear Imperiours wife take heed.</l>
                  <stage>She attempts to put on the breeches.</stage>
                  <l>If you do wear 'um you are quite undone,</l>
                  <l>Las, I was cur'd of the dry ſcab laſt moon.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Au.</speaker>
                  <l>Well, hang 'um on the pole agen, but heark you,</l>
                  <l>If you agen conjecture any eſcape,</l>
                  <l>Or let your frowns diſcover inward anger;</l>
                  <l>Ile hang 'um here, here on thy horns deviſer.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Phi.</speaker>
                  <l>Oh miſery, of a handſom wife, my forehead.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Au.</speaker>
                  <l>Well Ile to ſleep agen, watch you the Ferret.</l>
                  <stage>Exit.</stage>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Phi.</speaker>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Engin,</hi> come hither.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>En.</speaker>
                  <l>Your will Sir, what's your will.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Phi.</speaker>
                  <l>Haſt thou indeed: lain with my wife to night</l>
                  <l>And don the feat for me? Nay, Shield-bearer.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>En.</speaker>
                  <l>Speak ſoftly Sir, if my Amaſon ſhould hear you,</l>
                  <l>You are loſt for ever.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Phi.</speaker>
                  <l>Why, what's the matter?</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>En.</speaker>
                  <l>Softly, you heard us ſtrugling in the night.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Phi.</speaker>
                  <l>Oh yes, the bed did reel againſt my forehead.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>En.</speaker>
                  <l>Well you may think I am falſe, but 'tis well you ſpoke not.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Phi.</speaker>
                  <l>Why, what, what projects, honeſt <hi>Engine</hi> tell me?</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>En.</speaker>
                  <l>Why, ſome fears ſhe had that you'd diſcover us,</l>
                  <l>Which made her even this night intend to gueld you,</l>
                  <pb n="16" facs="tcp:114745:11"/>
                  <l> And then to ſwear ſhe found you impotent,</l>
                  <l>I uſed what exhortations I could</l>
                  <l>In pitie to your members, and at laſt prevail'd</l>
                  <l>Something <hi>Octavians</hi> Ghoſt has told her ſince:</l>
                  <l>You had beſt take heed Sir, for he tells her all things.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Phi.</speaker>
                  <l>The Devils Cuckold, die, die <hi>Philarchus.</hi>
                  </l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>En.</speaker>
                  <l>Oh the ſweet kiſſes ſhe hung upon my lips,</l>
                  <l>When I had put <hi>Philarchus</hi> from her thoughts.</l>
                  <l>That barren piece of Earth where furrows are plow'd,</l>
                  <l>That ſtubble fit for nothing but to burn.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Phi.</speaker>
                  <l>So, now I am going the way of thriving Citizens.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>En.</speaker>
                  <l>Then with a thouſand paſſages of Love tricks.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Phi.</speaker>
                  <l>No more, no more, my luſt begins to boil.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>En.</speaker>
                  <l>Why, I can help you Sir to cool't agen,</l>
                  <l>So you'l not grumble at what we poſſeſs.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Phi.</speaker>
                  <l>One boon, and all is thine, my wife and all.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>En.</speaker>
                  <l>On that condition any thing, come tell me.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Phi.</speaker>
                  <l>Beauty has wrought ſo on my flexid nature,</l>
                  <l>And ſo increaſed the flame I would ſuppreſs.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>En.</speaker>
                  <l>Oh, you'd evacuate, is that all Sir,</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Phi.</speaker>
                  <l>Some ſimple harmleſs wench, thou knowſt 'um all</l>
                  <l>Though of thy inſtruction, I ſhall not weaken her much.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>En.</speaker>
                  <l>Why now <hi>Philarchus</hi> ſpeaks himſelf a man,</l>
                  <l>And will conform himſelf unto the times,</l>
                  <l>His vizard is fallen off, and he's become</l>
                  <l>A ſmooth young ſtriker, active, full of ſpirit,</l>
                  <l>His knees grow ſtraight, his ſtaff with fury flies him</l>
                  <l>For fear of being arreign'd for killing thoſe</l>
                  <l>His fatall hand ſhall threaten, his ſhoulders ſhrink</l>
                  <l>Into his marrowy back, his eys fill up.—</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Phi.</speaker>
                  <l>No more good <hi>Engin,</hi> I am worſe than Goat already,</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>En.</speaker>
                  <l>Then for his wiſdom an <hi>Iſocrates.</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>He knows his wife (ſince ſhe is young and handſom)</l>
                  <l>Muſt have her longings, but then hee'l have his too:</l>
                  <l>And whilſt ſhe ſports at home, hee'l rut abroad:</l>
                  <l>For ſhould he ſay his wife does Cuckold him,</l>
                  <l>The Town would jear him into age agen:</l>
                  <l>Beſides: the proofs and confirmations,</l>
                  <pb n="17" facs="tcp:114745:11"/>
                  <l> The Lawyers Fees, with the Attorneys bribes,</l>
                  <l>Would rip his bags up, ſhoal away his Gold,</l>
                  <l>Undo his thrift, and cancel all his Bonds.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Phi.</speaker>
                  <l>True, <hi>Engin,</hi> true. VVhy, thou ſhalt have a ſtipend</l>
                  <l>From all rich Citizens to be maintain'd;</l>
                  <l>That I ſhould ſtudy to accuſe thee <hi>Engin,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>VVho thus haſt ſav'd my honour and eſtate.</l>
                  <l>Get me but wenches, and I vow nere more</l>
                  <l>To think upon <hi>Aurelia</hi> but as thine.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>En.</speaker>
                  <l>For ſhould you mutter the diſgrace is yours.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Pin.</speaker>
                  <l>Thou haſt inſtructed elegantly before.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>En.</speaker>
                  <l>As ſoon as day expect one in the Cloſet;</l>
                  <l>Your wife with men, and why not you with women?</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Phi.</speaker>
                  <l>Ile bite thy ear thou Raſcal, I will bite it.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>En.</speaker>
                  <l>Youl ſpoil your better bit Sir. Softly, ſoftly.</l>
                  <stage>Exit Phi.</stage>
                  <l>My mouth waters at your bed. <hi>Aurelia,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>Pox on theſe tempting curteſies. O that I could</l>
                  <l>Un-gentleman my ſelf and break my truſt:</l>
                  <l>But ſhould I do ſo? Inceſt and faith together</l>
                  <l>VVould lie ſo heavy on me, 'twould make me hang</l>
                  <l>An-arſe, and then like hunting of the Hare</l>
                  <l>VVith un-breath'd Dogs, 'twill be but petty ſport.</l>
                  <stage>Exit Engin.</stage>
               </sp>
               <stage>Enter <hi>Rogat</hi> and <hi>Frier.</hi>
               </stage>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Ro.</speaker>
                  <l>VVere't poſſible I could wiſh all were preſent.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Fr.</speaker>
                  <l>It will be requiſit, but how which way?</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Ro.</speaker>
                  <l>The way muſt be my invitation</l>
                  <l>To my ſons funeral. How thinks my Father?</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Fr.</speaker>
                  <l>I think it reaſonable, but then prepare</l>
                  <l>VVhat ornaments are fitting for the Hearſe;</l>
                  <l>VVe muſt uſe order in this undertaking;</l>
                  <l>About it noble <hi>Rogat,</hi> the ſun begins</l>
                  <l>To ſhew his rays and you have much to do.</l>
                  <stage>Exit Rogat.</stage>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Frier.</speaker>
                  <l>Prepare we for Confeſſion,</l>
                  <l>And our ſouls abſolution,</l>
                  <l>VVhat a world of horrid acts,</l>
                  <l>Heinous crimes, and bloudy facts,</l>
                  <l>VVhiſpering evils, ſecret thoughts,</l>
                  <l>Inward fears, and outward faults,</l>
                  <pb n="18" facs="tcp:114745:12"/>
                  <l> Big-mouth'd oaths, invented Lyes,</l>
                  <l>Bitter Curſes, envious Cries,</l>
                  <l>Shall this mornings night produce,</l>
                  <l>VVhileſt I pardon Heavens abuſe.</l>
                  <l>But ſome Delinquents will ſo blindly run,</l>
                  <l>They'l knock their brains out 'gainſt Confeſſion.</l>
               </sp>
            </div>
            <div n="3" type="act">
               <head>Actus tertius.</head>
               <stage>Enter <hi>Erotia</hi> and <hi>Cunicula.</hi>
               </stage>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Er.</speaker>
                  <l>Cunicula.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Cu.</speaker>
                  <l>My Patroneſs.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Er.</speaker>
                  <l>When jumbled you laſt <hi>Cunicula?</hi>
                  </l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Cu.</speaker>
                  <l>Not ſince the Ides of <hi>March.</hi>
                  </l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Er.</speaker>
                  <l>A <hi>Roman</hi> was it not?</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Cu.</speaker>
                  <l>Yes, Patroneſs.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Er.</speaker>
                  <l>I thought ſo by the language he has left thee.</l>
                  <l>Let me ſee, how many practiſings have you had now?</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Cu.</speaker>
                  <l>Some half a ſcore.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Er.</speaker>
                  <l>Well ſaid, thou ſcor'ſt um up:</l>
                  <l>Juſt of thy years did I begin this trade:</l>
                  <l>Ah, what diſcourſe my beauty bred ith' ſtreets!</l>
                  <l>One ſaid I was handſom, t'other proper, witty a third:</l>
                  <l>Then the fine Broaths I daily had ſent to me,</l>
                  <l>Potato-paſties, and luſty marrow-pies:</l>
                  <l>And then ith' morning Pickled Oiſters brought</l>
                  <l>To give my Muſcadel and Eggs a reliſh:</l>
                  <l>Then my preſenters arm'd with Piſtolets,</l>
                  <l>Would drop down ſhowres of bounty on my lap:</l>
                  <l>And then, Ah, ah, when I was young</l>
                  <l>The novelty was ſuch a thing, Ah, ah.</l>
                  <l>Now I am old, and cuſtom has deceiv'd me.</l>
                  <l>Thou art ſtill <hi>Cunicula</hi> full of juice and beauty,</l>
                  <l>Rejoyce and hug thy time, thou wilt be one day,</l>
                  <l>To my grief I ſpeak it, like thy Patroneſs?</l>
                  <stage>Knock.</stage>
                  <l>One knocks, a Booty I hope, look out <hi>Cunicula.</hi>
                  </l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Cu.</speaker>
                  <l>O Patroneſs, ſilk Cloaks and ſilver Lace,</l>
                  <l>A Coach-full on um.</l>
                  <pb n="19" facs="tcp:114745:12"/>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Er.</speaker>
                  <l>In and prepare your ſelf.</l>
                  <l>Some youngſter I hope that has bought new cloaths,</l>
                  <l>And comes to ſaye um here, weel make a-fire,</l>
                  <stage>Knock again</stage>
                  <l>Which ſhall both air your ſuit, and melt your Gold:</l>
                  <l>Soon enough, ſoon enough, with what force</l>
                  <l>And eagerneſs they thruſt in, but go out</l>
                  <stage>Knock ſtill</stage>
                  <l>As tame as ſheep. Why what's the matter there?</l>
                  <l>Will you knock down my doors you ſawcy Jacks?</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Pin.</speaker>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Erotia,</hi> ſweet <hi>Erotia</hi> let us in.</l>
                  <stage>Within.</stage>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Er.</speaker>
                  <l>Let ye in, who are ye, I am no ſuch woman,</l>
                  <l>Would you ſhould know it I.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Pin.</speaker>
                  <l>'Tis <hi>Pinnario.</hi>
                  </l>
                  <stage>Enter Pin. Pro Val.</stage>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Er.</speaker>
                  <l>My Benefactor, you muſt not be denide.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Pin.</speaker>
                  <l>Why how now Souce, what ſhut the door upon us?</l>
                  <l>Have you not learn'd my call nor knock yet?</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Er.</speaker>
                  <l>Sweet Sir,</l>
                  <l>I muſt adhere, I know your knock within,</l>
                  <l>Though, without, my age has dull'd my ears too much.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Pin.</speaker>
                  <l>Well, for my ſatisfaction ſalute theſe Gallants.</l>
                  <stage>They kiſs</stage>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Er.</speaker>
                  <l>Sir, as I take it, I have kiſt thoſe lips before,</l>
                  <l>And yet me thinks I have fogotten where.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Pro.</speaker>
                  <l>Familiar friends already: I knew when once</l>
                  <l>I had defide my Boots, red Cloak and Sword:</l>
                  <l>I ſhould be ador'd. I feel my back a breaking.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Er.</speaker>
                  <l>Nor have I loſt your memory delightfull Sir.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Val.</speaker>
                  <l>No, if thou hadſt, thou hadſt loſt the ſweeteſt pleaſure</l>
                  <l>Ere ſlept with thee tough Bombaſt.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Er.</speaker>
                  <l>Ah, dee remember,</l>
                  <l>Juſt this time four year, I, 'tis thereabouts,</l>
                  <l>The Catches we two ſung in the back Room,</l>
                  <l>And how you laugh'd at me, when I ſaid, you had forgot</l>
                  <l>To hold your Minnum-prick out. Ah you are a wagg.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Pin.</speaker>
                  <l>But heark thee Souce, where's my preferr'd Damſell:</l>
                  <l>I have brought theſe Gallants here to ſee her (Bombaſt)</l>
                  <l>And to applaud my choice and care of her.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Er.</speaker>
                  <l>So, ſo, youl never leave this open dealing:</l>
                  <stage>Enter Cun.</stage>
                  <l>Why <hi>Cu?</hi> why <hi>Cuni?</hi> why <hi>Cunicula?</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>Thou inſatiate Fawn, why doſt thou ſtay ſo long?</l>
                  <pb n="20" facs="tcp:114745:13"/>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Pin.</speaker>
                  <l>Morrow Fondling, morrow ſweet young Fondling:</l>
                  <l>Well, be a good wench, and let Souce indue thee;</l>
                  <l>Thou haſt found a Patron will not let thee ſink.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Cu.</speaker>
                  <l>But dive a little into your Comrades pockets.</l>
                  <stage>Aſide </stage>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Pro.</speaker>
                  <l>Sweet Nightingale your Servant, then your Lips.</l>
                  <stage>Salutes her.</stage>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Val.</speaker>
                  <l>That liberty muſt none of us be barr'd of.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Pro.</speaker>
                  <l>Heart, a brave Laſs, what a chop ſhe has given my Lips,</l>
                  <l>And made their anguiſh fire my heart with love?</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Pin.</speaker>
                  <l>What think you Blades, how do you like my choice?</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Pro.</speaker>
                  <l>Prithee ſtand out oth' light man, <hi>Cuni,</hi> Kether,</l>
                  <l>I would I were your Hays, Ide hamper yee;</l>
                  <l>If I have a face to ſpeak to this old ſtew'd meat</l>
                  <l>I am a ſnow-ball, and that I am far from at this time.</l>
                  <l>Ile fee the Tar-box: Beautifull <hi>Erotia.</hi>
                  </l>
                  <stage>Cunicula <hi>picks</hi> Procus <hi>his pockets.</hi>
                  </stage>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Pin.</speaker>
                  <l>Smitten, ſmitten, on my honour, ſee they are at it</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Val.</speaker>
                  <l>Why what an impudence my Cloak has lent him.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Pro.</speaker>
                  <l>Hah, let me ſee t'other pocket:</l>
                  <l>Vaniſht, all vaniſht, at ſuch a time too.</l>
                  <l>Nay, if money be loft to buy virginity,</l>
                  <l>The devil and charity fly with't.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Er.</speaker>
                  <l>Nay Sir,</l>
                  <l>Your golden Coin and my Patient is yours?</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Pro.</speaker>
                  <l>Miſchief, a little patience, and thou ſhalt hav't.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Pin.</speaker>
                  <l>How now Cock-maſter? what cow'd already?</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Pro.</speaker>
                  <l>Yes faith, and bow'd too. Doſt hear <hi>Valerio?</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>Thou muſt needs contribute four or five pieces more.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Val.</speaker>
                  <l>How?</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Pro.</speaker>
                  <l>Nay, prithee be not angry, faith thou muſt.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Val.</speaker>
                  <l>Why your gilt ſhillings?</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Pro.</speaker>
                  <l>Loſt, <hi>Valerio,</hi> loſt.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Val.</speaker>
                  <l>Nay, loſe the cauſe, and loſe the effect for me.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Pro.</speaker>
                  <l>Logick at wenching diſputations, abſurd.</l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Pinnario,</hi> thou haſt a noble bounteous nature.</l>
                  <l>Faith, I have prevail'd to hug thy fondling there,</l>
                  <l>And onely want ſome cuſtomary duties.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Pin.</speaker>
                  <l>Away thou Truant, out with thy cozening Doits.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Pro.</speaker>
                  <l>Las, they are all periſht.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Pin.</speaker>
                  <l>Periſht, how, which way?</l>
                  <pb n="21" facs="tcp:114745:13"/>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Pro.</speaker>
                  <l>Shall I tell thee this <hi>Valerio's</hi> a Quackſalver,</l>
                  <l>Hang him out ſide, there's nought but dregs within.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Pin.</speaker>
                  <l>Why, what's the matter?</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Pro.</speaker>
                  <l>Has mixt ſome hungry poyſon</l>
                  <l>With's deceitfull Gold, and it has eat through our pockets.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Pin.</speaker>
                  <l>How? let me ſee; why, th'art deceiv'd mad <hi>Procus,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>Look you, he's mine ſtill. Thou wilt not Cheater?</l>
                  <stage>Procus <hi>ſnatches</hi> Pinnario's <hi>money.</hi>
                  </stage>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Pro.</speaker>
                  <l>By this Gold but I will. Here, here, <hi>Erotia,</hi> here</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Er.</speaker>
                  <l>Here's but three Sir, my bargain was for ſix.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Pro.</speaker>
                  <l>Pox on my clutches could not ſcrabble all.</l>
                  <stage>Knocks.</stage>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Pin.</speaker>
                  <l>Heark Souce, one knocks there I think.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>En.</speaker>
                  <l>Within there.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Er.</speaker>
                  <l>What intruders that?</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>En.</speaker>
                  <l>Ide ſpeak with the Lady.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Er.</speaker>
                  <l>Here's none ſo worſhipfull.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>En.</speaker>
                  <l>With the Governeſs.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Cu.</speaker>
                  <l>Govern your tongue, Ile waſh your manners elſe.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Pin.</speaker>
                  <l>Well ſaid, <hi>Cuni.</hi>
                  </l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Pro.</speaker>
                  <l>Nay, prithee hear me <hi>Cuni.</hi>
                  </l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Cu.</speaker>
                  <l>No, not a ſyllable without the other three.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Er.</speaker>
                  <l>'Tis <hi>Aurelia's</hi> Bobadil, her waiting Favourite.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Pin.</speaker>
                  <l>Who, <hi>Engin,</hi> let's admit him and be reveng'd.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Pro.</speaker>
                  <l>The Rogue that braund us in his Miſtriſſes Chamber.</l>
                  <l>Doſt hear <hi>Valerio,</hi> a man without offence</l>
                  <l>To your pluſh Cloak, may try his skill a little.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Val.</speaker>
                  <l>And tire it too. What makes the <hi>Cerberus</hi> here?</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Er.</speaker>
                  <l>What ſhall I ſay to him?</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Val.</speaker>
                  <l>Let him in firſt.</l>
                  <stage>Exit Erotia.</stage>
                  <l>By that time weel invent his entertainment.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Pro.</speaker>
                  <l>Shall's drill his eys out?</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Pin.</speaker>
                  <l>Or make an Eunuch of him.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Pro.</speaker>
                  <l>And ſwear we found him up to th' ears with Souce.</l>
                  <stage>
                     <hi>Enter</hi> Ero<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tia <hi>with</hi> Engin.</stage>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Er.</speaker>
                  <l>Sir, this liberality commands my houſe,</l>
                  <l>What's here pray call your own.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>En.</speaker>
                  <l>Defend me craft,</l>
                  <l>My enemies in rank againſt me. Then <hi>Philarchus</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>Some of your muſty coin muſt buy um off.</l>
                  <stage>
                     <hi>Gives</hi> Erot. <hi>money.</hi>
                  </stage>
                  <l>Here, but remove theſe ſilken toys a while.</l>
                  <pb n="22" facs="tcp:114745:14"/>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Om.</speaker>
                  <l>A Pander, a Pander, a Pander.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>En.</speaker>
                  <l>Your meaning Gallants?</l>
                  <stage>Draws</stage>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Val.</speaker>
                  <l>Firſt your chaſtiſement Sir, and weel obey you.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Pro.</speaker>
                  <l>Sirrah, you <hi>Janus</hi> with your double face,</l>
                  <l>That ſrowns on us, but ſmiles upon <hi>Aurelia,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>We ſmell your cunning, Fox, and we will hunt you,</l>
                  <l>Till we have worried out your ſubtlety.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>En.</speaker>
                  <l>Sir, the good news I bring deſerves not this:</l>
                  <l>Have I ſtretcht out my ey-ſtrings for your ſearch,</l>
                  <l>Survey'd each ſtreet, each alley about the City,</l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>To</hi> finde you and the brave <hi>Pinnario</hi> out,</l>
                  <l>And do you thus requite my diligence?</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Pin.</speaker>
                  <l>Why, the fellow's made ſure, what buſineſs haſt with me?</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>En.</speaker>
                  <l>What ſhall I ſay? Now, now befriend me wits:</l>
                  <stage>Aſide.</stage>
                  <l>Sir, the Actors in my buſineſs are more than my ſelf,</l>
                  <l>And one that loves ye Sir.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Pro.</speaker>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Aurelia</hi> may be.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>En.</speaker>
                  <l>Happy inſtruction. Sir, your ear in private.</l>
                  <stage>Engin <hi>whispers with</hi> Pinnario <hi>and</hi> Procus</stage>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Pin.</speaker>
                  <l>How?</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>En.</speaker>
                  <l>If I do lie, act on me what you threaten.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Pin.</speaker>
                  <l>But why muſt <hi>Procus</hi> be my companion?</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>En.</speaker>
                  <l>Why Sir, <hi>Philarchus</hi> has done ill it ſeems,</l>
                  <l>All curſes plague him for't, for but for you Sir</l>
                  <l>She'd die oth' longings.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Pin.</speaker>
                  <l>Why, why what's the matter man?</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>En.</speaker>
                  <l>The hoary Ram nere lay with her laſt night,</l>
                  <l>Onely lent her his Breeches to keep her warm,</l>
                  <l>And poor Heart what with expectation</l>
                  <l>And angry affliction, ſhe's grown ſo fiery</l>
                  <l>That ſhe's impoſſible to be quencht by one.</l>
                  <l>Heark you. There's work enough for you both</l>
                  <l>Theſe ſix weeks, though you turn your bloud to marrow.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Pin.</speaker>
                  <l>Souce, come, I have given thee many a Piſtol,</l>
                  <l>Lend me ſome Gold to reward this truſty Servant,</l>
                  <l>This faithfull honeſt fellow, or ſtay, <hi>Valerio</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>Prithee let's give him thy Cloak <hi>Procus</hi> has.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Pro.</speaker>
                  <l>How Sir, my Cloak?</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Val.</speaker>
                  <l>But hear you Gentlemen, pray what's the news?</l>
                  <pb n="23" facs="tcp:114745:14"/>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>En.</speaker>
                  <l>Is this your friend Sir?</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Pin.</speaker>
                  <l>I <hi>Engin,</hi> an honeſt <hi>Hector,</hi> ſhall he along too?</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>En.</speaker>
                  <l>Yes to his Grave when I can ſingle him.</l>
                  <stage>Aſide.</stage>
                  <l>Sir, with your pardon, I have news for you too,</l>
                  <l>And that will make your heart ſwell high with joy,</l>
                  <l>Ile but diſpatch theſe firſt, and then attend you.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Pro.</speaker>
                  <l>How were we cozen'd in this honeſt <hi>Engin?</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>We thought thee our greateſt Enemy alive.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>En.</speaker>
                  <l>Who Sir, I? truth defend me, but ſtay a while,</l>
                  <l>I had forgot that, you muſt ſhift Gentlemen,</l>
                  <l>And put on womens cloaths, my Maſter elſe</l>
                  <l>(At whoſe name I tremble, he has ſo beaten me.)</l>
                  <l>Will be ſuſpitious to your undoing:</l>
                  <l>Some old caſt Gowns would ſecure all.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Pin.</speaker>
                  <l>But heark thee <hi>Engin,</hi> where ſhall we finde <hi>Aurelia?</hi>
                  </l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>En.</speaker>
                  <l>Why in her Cloſet:</l>
                  <l>Knock thus, you hear, ſheel open preſently.</l>
                  <l>Perhaps I may be there before you change,</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Pro.</speaker>
                  <l>Here <hi>Engin,</hi> take my Cloak, I give it thee:</l>
                  <l>Now are my arms at liberty to hold up my Coats.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>En.</speaker>
                  <l>Why is your appetite ſo ſlender Gallants?</l>
                  <l>Can you demur ſo long?</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Pin.</speaker>
                  <l>Away, away. <hi>Engin</hi> thou art ſo faithfull.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Pro.</speaker>
                  <l>Buy, <hi>Valerio,</hi> buy.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Val.</speaker>
                  <l>Youl ſup with me to night?</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Pin.</speaker>
                  <l>We cannot promiſe.</l>
                  <stage>Exeunt Pinnario &amp; Procus.</stage>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>En.</speaker>
                  <l>So, now for you <hi>Valerio. Erotia</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>I have ſome private buſineſs with this Monſieur</l>
                  <l>Pray expect us in another Room a while.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Er.</speaker>
                  <l>Libidinous thoughts be with you. Come <hi>Cunicula.</hi>
                  </l>
                  <stage>Exeunt Erotia &amp; Cunicula.</stage>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Val.</speaker>
                  <l>Now <hi>Engin,</hi> what's for me to execute</l>
                  <l>About <hi>Aurelia,</hi> prithee let it be.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>En.</speaker>
                  <l>I have no other buſineſs than hers, Sir.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Val.</speaker>
                  <l>What, ſhe expects me ſome where privately?</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>En.</speaker>
                  <l>So, ſo, hee'l make the quarrel himſelf anon.</l>
                  <stage>Aſide</stage>
                  <l>Sir, my fair Miſtris, (ſo far have I prevail'd)—</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Val.</speaker>
                  <l>She has ſent thee to bring me to her? Hah!</l>
                  <l>I do conceive, but doſt hear me Sirrah?</l>
                  <pb n="24" facs="tcp:114745:15"/>
                  <l> What, is ſhe active and nimble in her dealing?</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>En.</speaker>
                  <l>How Sir?</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Val.</speaker>
                  <l>Piſh come, thou art ſo modeſt now:</l>
                  <l>Faith, when didſt hug her laſt? I know thou haſt don't:</l>
                  <l>Here's none but friends man.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>En.</speaker>
                  <l>Yes, a deadly foe,</l>
                  <stage>Strikes him.</stage>
                  <l>And to raiſe courage in you firſt: take that.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Val.</speaker>
                  <l>Why, villain <hi>Engin?</hi>
                  </l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>En.</speaker>
                  <l>My Miſtris a whore, draw and defend your ſelf.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Val.</speaker>
                  <l>Art thou ſo treacherous?</l>
                  <stage>Draws.</stage>
                  <l>Thy blow baſe Groom has forfeited thy life.</l>
                  <stage>Valerio falls.</stage>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>En.</speaker>
                  <l>Your propheſie proves falſe Sir.</l>
                  <stage>Enter Erotia.</stage>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Er.</speaker>
                  <l>Murder, murder.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>En.</speaker>
                  <l>Whore, open but thy jaws agen, Ile ſplit um,</l>
                  <l>Reply not, but hearken and obey me, if thou mutter'ſt</l>
                  <l>Ile carve thy skin into Eſcutcheons for his Hearſe.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Er.</speaker>
                  <l>By all my fears, and all that's good I will not.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>En.</speaker>
                  <l>Let this confirm you, which if you proſecute</l>
                  <stage>Engin <hi>gives her more money.</hi>
                  </stage>
                  <l>With fortunate ſucceſs ſhall ſtill flow to you.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Er.</speaker>
                  <l>Why this is a fee to make us fire the City.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>En.</speaker>
                  <l>If he be loſt uſe all care for his concealment,</l>
                  <l>Then with your fair Diſciple here, be ſure</l>
                  <l>You meet me at <hi>Aurelia's</hi> houſe this night.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Er.</speaker>
                  <l>The hour.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>En.</speaker>
                  <l>About ſix, I muſt not ſtay, farewell.</l>
                  <stage>Exit</stage>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Val.</speaker>
                  <l>Oh.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Er.</speaker>
                  <l>Fetch ſome ſtrong water, quick <hi>Cunicula,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>There may be hope of life. How do you Sir?</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Val.</speaker>
                  <l>Who's there? <hi>Erotia.</hi>
                  </l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Er.</speaker>
                  <l>Yes.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Val.</speaker>
                  <l>Then I have dreamt.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Cu.</speaker>
                  <l>Here's the water Miſtris.</l>
                  <stage>He drinks</stage>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Er.</speaker>
                  <l>So, ſo, take comfort 'las how weak he is?</l>
                  <l>Fetch the back-water by my bed-ſide, <hi>Cuni,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>That will make him ſpring agen, though his heart were dead.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Val.</speaker>
                  <l>Foil'd by a Villain, my unlucky fate.</l>
                  <stage>Exeunt.</stage>
                  <pb n="25" facs="tcp:114745:15"/>
               </sp>
               <stage>Enter <hi>Procus</hi> and <hi>Pinnario</hi> in womens Cloaths.</stage>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Pro.</speaker>
                  <l>Slight what a mincing gate theſe Coats have taught me?</l>
                  <l>Theſe ſhe-comrades muſt needs be nimble-thigh'd,</l>
                  <l>They practice it in walking ſo.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Pin.</speaker>
                  <l>What's here, the Sign oth' Breeches?</l>
                  <stage>
                     <hi>They ſpy the Breeches upon the pole ſtand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing at</hi> Aurelia's <hi>chamber-door.</hi>
                  </stage>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Pro.</speaker>
                  <l>I conceive it</l>
                  <l>'Tis where <hi>Philarchus</hi> keeps his Centinel,</l>
                  <l>We muſt avoid that path, there's Hell at end on't.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Pin.</speaker>
                  <stage>
                     <hi>Enter</hi> Engin.</stage>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Engin</hi> moſt opportunely come, doſt hear</l>
                  <l>Where, where's the Cloſet? but direct us, then</l>
                  <l>Let us alone to raiſe the Hare and hunt her.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>En.</speaker>
                  <l>Yes, you ſhall hunt, and hang for hunting falſe.</l>
                  <stage>Aſide.</stage>
                  <l>You ſpeak too loud, what mean you Gentlemen?</l>
                  <l>A Lion rampant does inhabit there:</l>
                  <l>Behold the Enſign of his deſperate wrath:</l>
                  <stage>points to the Breeches</stage>
                  <l>The leaſt ſuſpition of your preſence here</l>
                  <l>Blows us to nothing.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Pro.</speaker>
                  <l>Why, is he then ſo valiant?</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>En.</speaker>
                  <l>A very <hi>Hercules,</hi> Ile tell you Sir,</l>
                  <l>One blow of his has ſo benumm'd this arm</l>
                  <l>I muſt deſpair of life in't for theſe two days,</l>
                  <l>But I ſhall do you wrong, Knock there and enter.</l>
                  <stage>Exit.</stage>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Pro.</speaker>
                  <l>Now could I leap through the door, but for <hi>Philarchus</hi>
                  </l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Pin.</speaker>
                  <l>Open fair <hi>Danae</hi> theſe golden Gates</l>
                  <stage>They knock at the Cloſet door.</stage>
                  <l>And ſhroud delight within thy pleaſant arms.</l>
               </sp>
               <stage>
                  <hi>Enter</hi> Phil.</stage>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Phi.</speaker>
                  <l>Thy <hi>Mars</hi> bright <hi>Venus</hi> does obey thy call.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Ambo.</speaker>
                  <l>Philarchus.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Phi.</speaker>
                  <l>Yes, <hi>Philarchus</hi> can ſpeak Lines</l>
                  <l>Provok't by Lechery. A brace of Turtles!</l>
                  <l>This <hi>Engin</hi> exceeds thy duty, come ye Puttocks.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Pin.</speaker>
                  <l>Why <hi>Procus</hi> we are abus'd, a trick upon us.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Pro.</speaker>
                  <l>Speak lower, if the purblind Aſs will needs</l>
                  <l>Take us for whores, and ſo beguile himſelf,</l>
                  <l>Let us not croſs his humour.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Pin.</speaker>
                  <l>A match, be confident.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Phi.</speaker>
                  <l>Theſe Harlots have ſuch inticing delays.</l>
                  <l>I muſt defer no longer. Come kiſs me both of ye.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Pro.</speaker>
                  <l>Pox o' your briſtles, how they bore my Lips.</l>
                  <pb n="26" facs="tcp:114745:16"/>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Phi.</speaker>
                  <l>Nay, now we have begun, no fumbling till we have ended.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Pin.</speaker>
                  <l>Nay, good Sir, youl diſgrace your ſelf with us.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Phi.</speaker>
                  <l>I, ſo you all ſay when you want a greaſing.</l>
                  <l>I will endure no longer—</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Pro.</speaker>
                  <l>But you muſt.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Phi.</speaker>
                  <l>Too loud, my wife will hear. I muſt ye Queans;</l>
                  <l>Get ye in to th' Cloſet, go.</l>
                  <stage>
                     <hi>Enter</hi> Aur. <hi>and</hi> Engin.</stage>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Pin.</speaker>
                  <l>Wee'l be no priſoners.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>En.</speaker>
                  <l>Quench him now whileſt he's hot, he'l hiſs agen.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Au.</speaker>
                  <l>Ye Vagabonds, ye Harlots, out ye Strumpets.</l>
                  <stage>Beats them.</stage>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Phi.</speaker>
                  <l>My wife <hi>Aurelia,</hi> O my endleſs ſhame!</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>En.</speaker>
                  <l>Good Sir bear up, would I could help you Sir.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Au.</speaker>
                  <l>A Conſtable, fetch me a Conſtable:</l>
                  <l>Ile have theſe Queans whipt round about the Town.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Pin.</speaker>
                  <l>Why—</l>
                  <stage>Aſide to the Gen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tlemen.</stage>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>En.</speaker>
                  <l>For your own credits diſcover not your ſelves</l>
                  <l>Should my Maſter ſee your breeches hee'd run mad.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Au.</speaker>
                  <l>Fetch me a Conſtable, I ſay, why go'ſt not?</l>
                  <l>Sirrah for your part Ile have your boiſterous—</l>
                  <stage>
                     <hi>Enter</hi> Engin.</stage>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Phi.</speaker>
                  <l>Stomach or any thing pull'd down, dreadfull wife,</l>
                  <l>I do confeſs and humbly ask thy pardon.</l>
                  <stage>
                     <hi>Enter</hi> Engin.</stage>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Au.</speaker>
                  <l>So, is he come?</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>En.</speaker>
                  <l>Yes, thoſe you thought not on. The <hi>Frier</hi> and <hi>Rogat.</hi>
                  </l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Phi.</speaker>
                  <l>My fit, my fit.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Pro.</speaker>
                  <l>What will become of us <hi>Pinnario?</hi>
                  </l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Pin.</speaker>
                  <l>Become of us, why let's unmask our ſelves.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Au.</speaker>
                  <l>Peace Gentlemen, conceal, it was my plot:</l>
                  <l>But vex <hi>Philarchus</hi> for my ſake this night,</l>
                  <l>And then I am yours.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Pro.</speaker>
                  <l>Excellent rare wit!</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Au.</speaker>
                  <l>Dee tremble Sir, there's remedy on coming.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Phi.</speaker>
                  <l>I hear um coming. Dear Amazon, on my knees</l>
                  <l>I beg concealment but for this offence,</l>
                  <l>With my hired lewd ones here, and I vow hereafter,</l>
                  <l>Never to croſs thee in the leaſt attempt.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>En.</speaker>
                  <l>Madam, have mercy on his vanquiſht Gaſcoyns.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Au.</speaker>
                  <l>Shall I then pity thee? O thou vile—</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Phil.</speaker>
                  <l>No more, I will confeſs my ſelf all baſe,</l>
                  <pb n="27" facs="tcp:114745:16"/>
                  <l> So youl betray us not.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Au.</speaker>
                  <l>In, to my Cloſet.</l>
                  <l>What now, Ile take a care for theſe. Farewell.</l>
                  <stage>Exeunt.</stage>
               </sp>
               <stage>Enter <hi>Rogat, Frier, Engin.</hi>
               </stage>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>En.</speaker>
                  <l>Sir, ſome occaſions have call'd my Maſter forth,</l>
                  <l>My Miſtris though will much rejoyce to ſee you.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Ro.</speaker>
                  <l>But we may ſee <hi>Aurelia</hi> then.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>En.</speaker>
                  <l>Yes Sir, there lies your way, if you pleaſe to enter.</l>
                  <stage>Exeunt.</stage>
               </sp>
               <stage>Enter <hi>Pinnario, Procus, Engin.</hi>
               </stage>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>En.</speaker>
                  <l>For look you Gentlemen it was her policy;</l>
                  <l>For had not ſhe devis'd ſome ſuddain terrour</l>
                  <l>To affright <hi>Philarchus,</hi> his jealouſie</l>
                  <l>Had interrupted all, but now our plot is ſure,</l>
                  <l>He dares not now divulge it though he know it,</l>
                  <l>Leaſt he betray what he would act with you;</l>
                  <l>But I am glad you ſhirk away ſo handſomly.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Pin.</speaker>
                  <l>'Twas time I think. When ſhall we hear from thee?</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>En.</speaker>
                  <l>I askt not that oth' <hi>Frier.</hi> About Supper-time.</l>
                  <stage>Aſide.</stage>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Pro.</speaker>
                  <l>Thou know'ſt <hi>Valerio's</hi> Lodging.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>En.</speaker>
                  <l>Why dee ask?</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Pin.</speaker>
                  <l>We ſup with him to night.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>En.</speaker>
                  <l>Ile wait upon you there.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Pin.</speaker>
                  <l>Nay thou ſhalt, in faith, in faith thou ſhalt.</l>
                  <stage>Gives him money. </stage>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>En.</speaker>
                  <l>This way to pleaſe you.</l>
                  <stage>Exeunt.</stage>
               </sp>
               <stage>Enter <hi>Rogat</hi> and <hi>Frier.</hi>
               </stage>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Ro.</speaker>
                  <l>'Tis doubtleſs ſo, for had his death been certain</l>
                  <l>The Law by this time had ſurprized <hi>Engin.</hi>
                  </l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Fr.</speaker>
                  <l>The Houſe ſets forth no memory of ſorrow</l>
                  <l>As I paſt by, fear not but he's recovered.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Ro.</speaker>
                  <l>Fie <hi>Engin,</hi> venture all our hopes thus raſhly.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Fr.</speaker>
                  <l>Well Son, we muſt not flag in the laſt ſcene,</l>
                  <l>When enterprizes moſt need aid and action</l>
                  <l>What has been further caſt by me within,</l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Aurelia</hi> will inform you. Night haſtens on,</l>
                  <l>Away to the proſecution.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Ro.</speaker>
                  <l>Ile to <hi>Senio.</hi>
                  </l>
                  <stage>
                     <hi>Exit</hi> Rogat.</stage>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Fr.</speaker>
                  <l>Thus our weather-beaten Bark</l>
                  <l>Arrives at the Haven in the dark,</l>
                  <pb n="28" facs="tcp:114745:17"/>
                  <l> Hoping there to be redreſt</l>
                  <l>Of the ſtorms which her oppreſt,</l>
                  <l>And now ſmiles to think upon</l>
                  <l>Horrours ſhe hath undergone,</l>
                  <l>So we to night expect a happy reſt</l>
                  <l>In deaths cold womb, or in <hi>Aurelia's</hi> breaſt.</l>
                  <stage>Exit.</stage>
               </sp>
            </div>
            <div n="4" type="act">
               <head>Actus quartus. Scaena prima.</head>
               <stage>Enter <hi>Aurelia</hi> and <hi>Engin,</hi> met by <hi>Erotia</hi> and <hi>Cunicula.</hi>
               </stage>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Er.</speaker>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Cupid</hi> defend me, what tempting Enſign's that?</l>
                  <stage>She ſpies the Breeches hang<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing on the pole and wonders at them.</stage>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>En.</speaker>
                  <l>Pox on my Enſign, how does <hi>Valerio?</hi>
                  </l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Er.</speaker>
                  <l>View thoſe exalted hams, <hi>Cunicula.</hi>
                  </l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Au.</speaker>
                  <l>Hell on theſe Breeches, how does <hi>Valerio?</hi>
                  </l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>En.</speaker>
                  <l>She muſt be humour'd. Ile tell the myſtery.</l>
                  <l>My Maſter to terrefie this his young wife</l>
                  <stage>She ſtill wonders.</stage>
                  <l>Commands me ſtill to bear this ſhield before her.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Er.</speaker>
                  <l>O wicked provocation! Out upon it!</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>En.</speaker>
                  <l>Now wilt thou tell us how <hi>Valerio</hi> does?</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Er.</speaker>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Valerio,</hi> never better in his life;</l>
                  <l>'Twas onely loſs of bloud, his wounds were ſlight;</l>
                  <l>He ſups with me to night, and now ſent word</l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>To Pinnario</hi> and <hi>Procus</hi> to be his Gueſts.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Au.</speaker>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Engin</hi> give her one of <hi>Philarchus</hi> bags.</l>
                  <l>I may believe thee?</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Er.</speaker>
                  <l>By the reward <hi>I</hi> hope for.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Au.</speaker>
                  <l>So, give it her.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>En.</speaker>
                  <l>But on condition,</l>
                  <l>To aid and help us with your pretty Servant.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Er.</speaker>
                  <l>Though we lie by it a fortnight.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>En.</speaker>
                  <l>My Miſtris will inſtruct you. Ile to th' Frier.</l>
                  <stage>Exeunt.</stage>
               </sp>
               <stage>Enter <hi>Valerio</hi> and <hi>Babilas.</hi>
               </stage>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Val.</speaker>
                  <l>My <hi>Babilas,</hi> no more, for thy fruition</l>
                  <l>Has brought a Balſom to reſtore my health.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Ba.</speaker>
                  <l>O my <hi>Valerio,</hi> were my ſiſter thine</l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>I</hi> could with willingneſs contemn the world</l>
                  <l>And this Diſguize tane off, publiſh my ſelf</l>
                  <l>To the rigorous Laws, but when <hi>Valerio</hi>
                  </l>
                  <pb n="29" facs="tcp:114745:17"/>
                  <l> Wants <hi>Babilas</hi> to aſſociate his Deſigns,</l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>I</hi> am not my ſelf, till <hi>I</hi> have proſecuted</l>
                  <l>The leaſt of his intents.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Val.</speaker>
                  <l>Thou art my boſom,</l>
                  <l>No thought lies there but what thy fancy breeds:</l>
                  <l>Then prithee adviſe me if thou canſt, my friend,</l>
                  <l>VVhich way <hi>I</hi> might wipe off this foul diſgrace</l>
                  <l>This baſe Groom gave me?</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Ba.</speaker>
                  <l>You muſt not be too raſh,</l>
                  <l>VVhat we reſolve muſt ſilently be done,</l>
                  <l>Nor think <hi>Valerio</hi> to ſhare alone in this.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Val.</speaker>
                  <l>Not for my Reputation <hi>Babilas.</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>That were unequal odds againſt one man.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Ba.</speaker>
                  <l>VVere his birth equal to us <hi>I</hi> confeſs it,</l>
                  <l>It were a Cowards act, but to a Peaſant</l>
                  <l>What puniſhment too great can be inflicted?</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Val.</speaker>
                  <l>Thou haſt clear'd my doubts, then let's conſult a while.</l>
                  <stage>Enter Servant.</stage>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Ser.</speaker>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Pinnario</hi> Sir and <hi>Procus</hi> are without.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Ba.</speaker>
                  <l>Let me withdraw.</l>
                  <stage>
                     <hi>Enter</hi> Pin. <hi>and</hi> Pro.</stage>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Val.</speaker>
                  <l>By no means <hi>Babilas.</hi>
                  </l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Pin.</speaker>
                  <l>Pox on your conſtancy, and why here to night?</l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Procus</hi> has worn his Boots out to the welts</l>
                  <l>With ſeeking you.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Pro.</speaker>
                  <l>And my heels too I think.</l>
                  <l>Hah, what <hi>Switzers</hi> beard is that?</l>
                  <stage>
                     <hi>points at</hi> Babilas.</stage>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Pin.</speaker>
                  <l>Who is't <hi>Valerio?</hi>
                  </l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Val.</speaker>
                  <l>A worthy friend of mine, prithee ſalute him.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Pin.</speaker>
                  <l>Thy friend and we not know him. Noble Sir,</l>
                  <l>I ſhall be proud to be eſteem'd your ſervant.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Pro.</speaker>
                  <l>And I to kiſs your hands.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Ba.</speaker>
                  <l>You honour me too much, and did my—</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Val.</speaker>
                  <l>Nay, prithee no complements,</l>
                  <l>'Twill hinder our diſcourſe and ſpoil our mirth:</l>
                  <l>Come honeſt Rogues ſit down. Boy, ſome Tobacco.</l>
                  <l>And now <hi>Pinnario</hi> tell me, how doſt like her?</l>
                  <stage>
                     <hi>Aſide to</hi> Pinnario.</stage>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Pin.</speaker>
                  <l>Like, who?</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Val.</speaker>
                  <l>I muſt deviſe ſome way to know</l>
                  <stage>Aſide.</stage>
                  <l>Where they have been, you think I know nothing.</l>
                  <pb n="30" facs="tcp:114745:18"/>
                  <l> Why, what ſtaid <hi>Engin</hi> here but to relate</l>
                  <l>What you were ventring for. What, to thy friend?</l>
                  <l>Slight, were I guilty of my fathers death</l>
                  <l>I would not hide it from my familiar friend.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Pin.</speaker>
                  <l>Why, thou ſhalt know, <hi>Valerio</hi> is my friend,</l>
                  <l>'Tis but a womans credit loſt at moſt,</l>
                  <l>If thou ſhould'ſt blab, walk by, Ile tell thee all.</l>
                  <stage>Val. <hi>&amp;</hi> Pin. <hi>whisper whilest</hi> Babilas <hi>&amp;</hi> Pro. <hi>take Tobacco.</hi>
                  </stage>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Ba.</speaker>
                  <l>Sir, will you taſte of this Tobacco?</l>
                  <l>Right <hi>Spaniſh</hi> I aſſure you.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Pro.</speaker>
                  <l>I love the weed</l>
                  <l>For the bold Nations ſake, I have heard um ſay,</l>
                  <l>You may believe a <hi>Spaniard</hi> on his word</l>
                  <l>Before an <hi>Engliſhman</hi> on forty oaths.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Ba.</speaker>
                  <l>Amongſt my many Travails, 'twas my fortune</l>
                  <l>To touch upon that preaching Iſland.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Pro.</speaker>
                  <l>England?</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Ba.</speaker>
                  <l>'Twas call'd ſo Sir, till another eat it up.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Pro.</speaker>
                  <l>What Country, Sir?</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Ba.</speaker>
                  <l>They call it <hi>Scotland</hi> Sir.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Pro.</speaker>
                  <l>Miraculous. A hungry Countrey ſure.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Ba.</speaker>
                  <l>Troth Sir, good ſtore of ſtones and long thorn'd buſhes.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Pro.</speaker>
                  <l>The people too devour'd?</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Ba.</speaker>
                  <l>Moſt on um Sir,</l>
                  <l>Some few who clapt hands with the Enemy</l>
                  <l>Are ſav'd, who for a badg of their conformity</l>
                  <l>Unto the Victors will, ſharpened their ears,</l>
                  <l>And ſtead of hair, glew'd on their heads the briſtles</l>
                  <l>Of naſty Swine.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Pro.</speaker>
                  <l>Why there's my Logick prov'd now,</l>
                  <l>I remember in my laſt ſchool diſputation,</l>
                  <l>They laught at me for ſaying, <hi>Homo est aſinus rationalis.</hi>
                  </l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Pin.</speaker>
                  <l>Incredible by <hi>Engin,</hi> he durſt not do't.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Val.</speaker>
                  <l>He dares not cheat as ſoon, or be a Pander,</l>
                  <l>But I am glad you ſcapt ſo well, if he does ſo—</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Pin.</speaker>
                  <l>Nay come thou muſt not cheriſh anger <hi>Val,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>I dare proclame (what ever mov'd him to't)</l>
                  <l>Him true and faithfull.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Val.</speaker>
                  <l>The event will ſhew it.</l>
                  <stage>
                     <hi>Enter</hi> Er. <hi>&amp; Cun.</hi>
                  </stage>
                  <pb n="31" facs="tcp:114745:18"/>
                  <l> What my fat Hoſteſs where haſt thou been puffing.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Pro.</speaker>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Erotia</hi> and her Servant.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Er.</speaker>
                  <l>Pray pardon.</l>
                  <l>Sir, I have buſineſs with you, lend your ear.</l>
                  <stage>
                     <hi>to</hi> Pin.</stage>
               </sp>
               <stage>Erot. <hi>whispers with</hi> Pin. <hi>and</hi> Proc.</stage>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Pin.</speaker>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Procus</hi> a word.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Ba.</speaker>
                  <l>What means this whiſpering?</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Val.</speaker>
                  <l>A bargain for <hi>Cunicula,</hi> my life on't.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Pro.</speaker>
                  <l>Excellent <hi>Engin.</hi>
                  </l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Pin.</speaker>
                  <l>At the Friers Cell.</l>
                  <l>And the pretence <hi>Octavian's</hi> funeral.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Er.</speaker>
                  <l>The better cloak to hide your Enterprize:</l>
                  <l>For ſhould you be ſuſpected, pretending that—</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Val.</speaker>
                  <l>Piſh, prithee defer this jugling ſport a while,</l>
                  <l>And let's to ſupper, drink hard, and then</l>
                  <l>Pox o'the world: we are fit for any Exploit.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Cun.</speaker>
                  <l>Sir, ſupper waits you.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Val.</speaker>
                  <l>We come <hi>Cunicula</hi>
                  </l>
                  <stage>
                     <hi>Exeunt</hi> Pro. Val. Erot.</stage>
               </sp>
               <stage>
                  <hi>Manet Valerio</hi> and <hi>Pinnario.</hi>
               </stage>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Val.</speaker>
                  <l>Hang me, thou ſhalt profeſs thy ſelf my foe,</l>
                  <l>But I will know it.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Pin.</speaker>
                  <l>Prithee I muſt not tell thee.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Val.</speaker>
                  <l>Ile tell thee thou art a Coward by this light then,</l>
                  <l>Forſwear thy company—why, haſt drank <hi>Lethe?</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>That th'aſt forgotten what th'aſt promiſt me?</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Pin.</speaker>
                  <l>Wilt thou be ſilent?</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Val.</speaker>
                  <l>As <hi>Octavian's</hi> murther'd Ghoſt.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Pin.</speaker>
                  <l>Why then thy hand, thou ſhalt along with us.</l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Aurelia's</hi> but for a night, thou art mine for ever.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Val.</speaker>
                  <l>Nobly reſolv'd.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Pin.</speaker>
                  <l>And ſo weel proſecute.</l>
                  <stage>Exeunt.</stage>
               </sp>
               <stage>Enter <hi>Rogat</hi> and <hi>Senio.</hi>
               </stage>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Ro.</speaker>
                  <l>Sir, what I utter: grant us but your preſence,</l>
                  <l>Ile pawn my honour ſhall be manifeſt.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Sen.</speaker>
                  <l>Shall I believe <hi>Philarchus,</hi> whoſe account</l>
                  <l>Hath ſtretcht above the reach of common men,</l>
                  <l>Whoſe Character is known about the City,</l>
                  <l>To be full of faith and awfull gravity.</l>
                  <l>Shall I believe I ſay, that this this man</l>
                  <pb n="32" facs="tcp:114745:19"/>
                  <l> Would dim the luſtre of his dear Repute</l>
                  <l>By ſuch an act as this 'twere ſin to credit it.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Ro.</speaker>
                  <l>Sir, if my zeal to you hath rais'd your temper,</l>
                  <l>You muſt not look now for a rough reply</l>
                  <l>From him whoſe grief is rais'd above his anger,</l>
                  <l>Yet this ith' midſt of my extrem'ſt diſtraction,</l>
                  <l>Which for <hi>Aurelia's</hi> ſake I intimate.</l>
                  <l>Be pleas'd to night to grace <hi>Octavian's</hi> Hearſe</l>
                  <l>At the Friers Cell, where if I prove not this</l>
                  <l>Let me be held a Traitour. Think on't. Farewell.</l>
                  <stage>
                     <hi>Exit</hi> Rog.</stage>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Sen.</speaker>
                  <l>To all this worlds content if this prove true.</l>
                  <stage>
                     <hi>Exit</hi> Sen.</stage>
               </sp>
               <stage>Enter <hi>Philarchus</hi> as in the Cloſet.</stage>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Phi.</speaker>
                  <l>Fire, fire, where is't? O that my Gold would turn</l>
                  <l>To kindled fuel, or my rotten Bonds</l>
                  <l>Engender flame to burn themſelves to aſhes,</l>
                  <l>And thaw my frozen joynts. <hi>I</hi> quake for cold</l>
                  <l>Horn'd and ſterv'd too, this 'tis for age to dote</l>
                  <stage>
                     <hi>Enter</hi> Engin.</stage>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>En.</speaker>
                  <l>Heaven bleſs my Maſter, your Ague ſtill upon you.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Phi.</speaker>
                  <l>O <hi>Engin,</hi> art thou come, lend me thy hand.</l>
                  <l>Have <hi>I</hi> it? tell me, for <hi>I</hi> have loſt my feeling.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>En.</speaker>
                  <l>Why, you have forgot the Lecture that <hi>I</hi> read you!</l>
                  <l>Nay then <hi>I</hi> ſee all labours loſt on you.</l>
                  <l>What tremble at a ſudden interruption?</l>
                  <l>VVhy, who'd have thought your wife had been ſo near?</l>
                  <l>'Twas a meer chance, for my pains deſpair not</l>
                  <l>That way has fail'd, but <hi>I</hi> have now invented</l>
                  <l>So ſure a plot, ſo certain a ſoundation—</l>
                  <l>VVhy do you ſtart at that ſhould make you glad?</l>
                  <l>VVhy, this me thinks ſhould raiſe and rally up</l>
                  <l>Your blaſted ſpirits, and like an angry Ram</l>
                  <l>Make you retreat to run with greater force.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Phi.</speaker>
                  <l>Fa la la, la la fa, la la la, fa la.</l>
                  <stage>Dances.</stage>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>En.</speaker>
                  <l>Stampt like <hi>Bucephalus,</hi> agen, agen Sir.</l>
                  <l>O lechery in age what Monſter art thou?</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Phi.</speaker>
                  <l>Come lovely <hi>Phillis,</hi> ſince that thy will is—</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>En.</speaker>
                  <l>So does the ſhadow hurt the tender Graſs</l>
                  <l>Or mornings dew ſuppreſs the opening flowers,</l>
                  <l>As does the nimble feet of young <hi>Philarchus</hi>
                  </l>
                  <stage>
                     <hi>He dances whilest</hi> Engin <hi>talks.</hi>
                  </stage>
                  <pb n="33" facs="tcp:114745:19"/>
                  <l> Imprint their weight upon the fruitfull earth.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Phi.</speaker>
                  <l>I could now caper ore the Moon me thinks.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>En.</speaker>
                  <l>Over an earthly Moon, (be rul'd by me)</l>
                  <l>And you ſhall preſently.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Phi.</speaker>
                  <l>How? where? which way?</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>En.</speaker>
                  <l>How he inchants himſelf within the nooz?</l>
                  <stage>Aſide.</stage>
                  <l>Such is my care and diligence to ſerve you,</l>
                  <l>Forgetfull of my ſelf and all the world,</l>
                  <l>So I may purchaſe your high prized favour.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Phi.</speaker>
                  <l>My favour <hi>Engin.</hi>
                  </l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>En.</speaker>
                  <l>'Tis that I onely aim at:</l>
                  <l>And to give fire and level at my ends,</l>
                  <l>Hear Sir the cunningſt plot wit ere found out:</l>
                  <l>This night, this night, this happy pleaſant night</l>
                  <l>You are to meet at the holy Friers Cell,</l>
                  <l>The rareſt Pidgeon, comfortableſt Dove—</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Phi.</speaker>
                  <l>But what affairs ſhall I pretend my <hi>Engin?</hi>
                  </l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>En.</speaker>
                  <l>Why, your wife with <hi>Senio</hi> your father in law,</l>
                  <l>Are both invited to <hi>Octavian's</hi> funeral:</l>
                  <l>Set out with them, 'twill be a good excuſe;</l>
                  <l>And once being there, by me you ſhall beled</l>
                  <l>Where you ſhall finde—</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Phi.</speaker>
                  <l>Such paſtime, ſuch delight.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>En.</speaker>
                  <l>Wolf, how the meer conceit makes his Chaps mumble?</l>
                  <l>Why are you idle Sir? by this they are going.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Phi.</speaker>
                  <l>But for thy reward, nay, in faith thou ſhalt.</l>
                  <stage>Gives him money,</stage>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>En.</speaker>
                  <l>I have batter'd yet the Rock, if I do ſplit.</l>
                  <stage>Exeunt.</stage>
               </sp>
               <stage>Enter <hi>Rogat</hi> and <hi>Frier.</hi>
               </stage>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Fr.</speaker>
                  <l>Yet I think it not unfit ſince all's prepar'd,</l>
                  <l>If you do make a ſecond invitation.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Ro.</speaker>
                  <l>Doubtleſs he'l come.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Fr.</speaker>
                  <l>We muſt be certain, <hi>Rogat.</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>If <hi>Senio</hi> fail our enterprize is loſt:</l>
                  <l>A minutes complement and they are ours.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Ro.</speaker>
                  <l>Since you will have it ſo I am content.</l>
                  <stage>
                     <hi>Exit</hi> Rog.</stage>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Fr.</speaker>
                  <l>Thus the wounds which bleeding were</l>
                  <l>Are now ſtopping by my care.</l>
                  <l>'Tis the glory of the Frier</l>
                  <pb n="34" facs="tcp:114745:20"/>
                  <l> To be <hi>Chorus</hi> in this Quire,</l>
                  <l>Where our ſorrows are divorcing,</l>
                  <l>And no envy reinforcing.</l>
                  <l>Thus innocence at laſt ſhall wear the Crown,</l>
                  <l>When vice its ſelf with her own hands plucks down.</l>
               </sp>
            </div>
            <div n="5" type="act">
               <head>Actus quintus. Scaena prima.</head>
               <stage>Enter <hi>Pinnario, Procus, Babilas, Valerio, Engin,</hi> as in the Friers Cell.</stage>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>En.</speaker>
                  <l>Can it be poſſible that you ſhould thus</l>
                  <l>Oppoſe my ſervice and delude your ſelf.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Pin.</speaker>
                  <l>What means the fellow?</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>En.</speaker>
                  <l>What does <hi>Valerio</hi> here?</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Pin.</speaker>
                  <l>Why, he comes to tell thee he has forgot thy fault,</l>
                  <l>Upon condition to be partner with us.</l>
                  <l>His friend to his honeſt friend a Travailer,</l>
                  <l>'Las he'l do nothing but keep councel, he.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>En.</speaker>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Babilas</hi> I muſt then conclude their ſtay.</l>
                  <stage>Aſide.</stage>
                  <l>I have it, excellent. How am I bound</l>
                  <l>And twice rewarded for this favour Sir?</l>
                  <l>But mediate for me Sir, Ile fit you all.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Pin.</speaker>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Valerio</hi> a word.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>En.</speaker>
                  <l>Good Sir be earneſt.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Pin.</speaker>
                  <l>By all our friendſhip, and familiar love,</l>
                  <l>By valour, honour, faith and loyalty,</l>
                  <l>Forget, forgive, and here again receive</l>
                  <l>This truſty fellow.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>En.</speaker>
                  <l>Sir, upon my knees.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Val.</speaker>
                  <l>Upon condition I may participate</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>En.</speaker>
                  <l>I have another Sir, on purpoſe for you.</l>
                  <l>Equal in all things to <hi>Pinnario's.</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>And ſee how it happens; two and two.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Val.</speaker>
                  <l>Good <hi>Engin?</hi>
                  </l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>En.</speaker>
                  <l>Sir, for the cauſe of my affront, but ſtay</l>
                  <l>Till I have praefac'd this ſmall ſatisfaction</l>
                  <l>And I will ſhew you—</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Val.</speaker>
                  <l>Hang all Repetitions,</l>
                  <pb n="35" facs="tcp:114745:20"/>
                  <l>'Twas a meer dream, thou never wrong'ſt me <hi>Engin.</hi>
                  </l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>En.</speaker>
                  <l>Concupiſcence, what Cowards are thy ſlaves?</l>
                  <stage>
                     <hi>They go out and enter agen as being led by</hi> Engin <hi>in the dark Cave.</hi>
                  </stage>
                  <l>Gentlemen follow ſoftly: not a word.</l>
                  <l>So, here ſtay you Sir with your noble friend,</l>
                  <l>But ſtir not for fear of loſing, the Cave is wide</l>
                  <l>And dark: when you hear this inchanting melody,</l>
                  <l>Come <hi>Cloris</hi> hie we to to the Bower—</l>
                  <stage>
                     <hi>Speaking to</hi> Vale<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rio <hi>and</hi> Bab.</stage>
                  <l>That's the word to know your wench by.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Val.</speaker>
                  <l>Come <hi>Cloris</hi> hie we—</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>En.</speaker>
                  <l>And then you have her.</l>
                  <l>Your wench ſhall finde you out, you need not ſtir.</l>
                  <stage>
                     <hi>Speaking to</hi> Pin. <hi>and</hi> Pro.</stage>
                  <l>When you have done I will conduct you forth,</l>
                  <l>But ſtir not till then, for <hi>Octavian's</hi> Hearſe lies near,</l>
                  <l>If you ſhould ſtumble at it, you are loſt.</l>
                  <l>Mum not a word. Now comes your turn <hi>Philarchus.</hi>
                  </l>
                  <stage>Exit.</stage>
               </sp>
               <stage>Enter <hi>Rogat, Senio, Philarchus, Aurelia.</hi>
               </stage>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Ro.</speaker>
                  <l>Firſt Sir, I bid you welcome to my grief</l>
                  <l>Then to the unfolding of the ſtrangeſt plot</l>
                  <l>The wicked ere invented, or Hell produc't.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Sen.</speaker>
                  <l>Sir, you amaze me with wonder, and yet ſtill</l>
                  <stage>
                     <hi>Enter</hi> Engin</stage>
                  <l>Draw or't a curtain to interpoſe the knowledg.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Ro.</speaker>
                  <l>Pleaſe you to enter, it ſoon ſhall be withdrawn.</l>
                  <stage>
                     <hi>Ex.</hi> Rog. Sen. Au.</stage>
               </sp>
               <stage>Manet Engin, Philarchus.</stage>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Phi.</speaker>
                  <l>Now <hi>Engin,</hi> now, now are we left alone.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>En.</speaker>
                  <l>Follow then ſoftly, Ile finde you company.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Phi.</speaker>
                  <l>If I do not bore her, then cozen me agen.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>En.</speaker>
                  <l>I will ſo Sir.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Phi.</speaker>
                  <l>How <hi>Engin,</hi> Coſin me?</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>En.</speaker>
                  <l>I will go Sir, I ſaid.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Phi.</speaker>
                  <l>I cry thee mercy.</l>
                  <stage>
                     <hi>They go out and</hi> Engin <hi>leads him in again by the hand as into the dark Cave.</hi>
                  </stage>
                  <l>At his mercy now indeed. I hope ſhe brings</l>
                  <l>Full ſparkling ey-balls and a ſhining brow,</l>
                  <l>I ſcarce ſhall grope her elſe; ſo thick's the darkneſs.</l>
                  <l>But why may not this <hi>Engin</hi> here have an Engin</l>
                  <l>Subtilly prepar'd to waſh my appetite</l>
                  <stage>Rogat <hi>&amp;</hi> Senio <hi>heark<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>en behinde the Arras.</hi>
                  </stage>
                  <l>Piſh, I am diffident, it cannot be</l>
                  <l>He means as plainly as I am full of wrinkles.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Sen.</speaker>
                  <l>Miraculous, this cannot be <hi>Philarchus.</hi>
                  </l>
                  <stage>Behinde the Arras.</stage>
                  <pb n="36" facs="tcp:114745:21"/>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Ro.</speaker>
                  <l>The end proves that, pray interrupt him not.</l>
                  <stage>
                     <hi>Exit</hi> Eng. <hi>and enter</hi> Fr. <hi>in his room, and brings with him</hi> Er. <hi>diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guis'd like</hi> Au. <hi>Here the Frier counterfeits</hi> Eng. <hi>voice.</hi>
                  </stage>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Fr.</speaker>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Philarchus,</hi> Maſter, Maſter.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Phi.</speaker>
                  <l>Here, here.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Fr.</speaker>
                  <l>Take here then your Taſſel gentle.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Phi.</speaker>
                  <l>Yes faith Ile warrant thee, &amp; make her ſtoop too.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Fr.</speaker>
                  <l>You may be louder, Sir.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Phi.</speaker>
                  <l>But the old men.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Fr.</speaker>
                  <l>In the <hi>Friers</hi> Chappel, far enough from you.</l>
                  <l>Sir, ſtrike on opportunity while ſhe's here;</l>
                  <l>You may trail many a night for ſuch a ſcent.</l>
                  <l>Well, my old Maſter expects me.</l>
                  <stage>He makes as if he went out, but ſtays.</stage>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Phi.</speaker>
                  <l>My own own <hi>Engin,</hi> all the wealth I have:</l>
                  <l>Come my young Parſley-bed, come prithee kiſs me.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Ro.</speaker>
                  <l>Now Sir it works.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Sen.</speaker>
                  <l>The Devil, 'tis the Devil:</l>
                  <l>My Daughter's wedded to a ramping Fiend.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Ro.</speaker>
                  <l>Youl juſtle all aſide, peace and attend.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Phi.</speaker>
                  <l>Well ſaid my nimble Doe: what thinks my wench?</l>
                  <l>If to ſtretch my pleaſures to a large extent,</l>
                  <l>My Nightingale would warble forth a ſong.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Fr.</speaker>
                  <l>You muſt humour him, ſing, ſing any thing.</l>
                  <stage>
                     <hi>Enter</hi> Eng. <hi>with a dark Lanthorn &amp; a ſheet, and lies down in</hi> Octav. <hi>coffin.</hi>
                  </stage>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>En.</speaker>
                  <l>So, now to the cold Grave to riſe agen</l>
                  <l>Eternally inrob'd with peacefull bliſs.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Er.</speaker>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Come</hi> Cloris, <hi>hie we to the Bower.</hi>
                  </l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Val.</speaker>
                  <l>My ſweet Decoy, I come, I come delight.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Fr.</speaker>
                  <l>Miſchief upon him, he'l interrupt our ſport.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Val.</speaker>
                  <l>Who's here, <hi>Pinnario?</hi>
                  </l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Fr.</speaker>
                  <l>I, pox on't I.</l>
                  <stage>The Frier counterfeits Pin. <hi>his voice.</hi>
                  </stage>
                  <l>Hinder me juſt in action, is this fair play?</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Val.</speaker>
                  <l>Rail at the darkneſs prithee, and not at me.</l>
                  <stage>
                     <hi>All this while</hi> Phil. <hi>hears them talk in the Cave &amp; trembles at it.</hi>
                  </stage>
                  <l>Who'd think your Quean ſhould learn my Turtles note?</l>
                  <l>'Tis helliſh dark, would I could finde my place agen</l>
                  <l>Prithee whiſtle <hi>Babilas</hi> that I may finde thee out.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Sen.</speaker>
                  <l>Hah, <hi>Babilas,</hi> my ſon a whore-maſter!</l>
                  <stage>
                     <hi>Enter</hi> Cun. <hi>diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guiz'd like</hi> Au. <hi>ſhe goes to</hi> Pin.</stage>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Ro.</speaker>
                  <l>But patience Sir, all will be known anon.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Pin.</speaker>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Aurelia</hi> welcome, come weel make no words.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Phi.</speaker>
                  <l>O what an Ague ſhakes my unſavoury tongue?</l>
                  <l>And 'gainſt my will makes me confeſs my ſelf</l>
                  <pb n="37" facs="tcp:114745:21"/>
                  <l> A Knave, a Rogue, a moſt inceſtuous Villain.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Sen.</speaker>
                  <l>Say you ſo, ſay you ſo. <hi>Aurelia</hi> my wrong'd childe.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Phi.</speaker>
                  <l>Valerio, Pinnario, Babilas.</l>
                  <l>Here too skulks ſome body <hi>Valerio</hi> talkt to;</l>
                  <l>Welcome wives pounces, <hi>Engins</hi> ſtaff and ſhield.</l>
                  <l>So you would thump me from this den of Devils.</l>
               </sp>
               <stage>Eng. <hi>from the coffin in a ſheet.</hi>
               </stage>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>En.</speaker>
                  <l>That, thats my Cue. In me <hi>Octavians</hi> Ghoſt</l>
                  <l>The Devils do ſalute thee, and have ſent—</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Phi.</speaker>
                  <l>Oh oh oh.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>En.</speaker>
                  <l>The hungry ſword that devourd his youthful bloud</l>
                  <l>To entertain thy putrefied intrails.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Fr.</speaker>
                  <l>Hah, <hi>Octavians</hi> Ghoſt!</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Ba.</speaker>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Octavians</hi> Ghoſt!</l>
                  <stage>They are all frighted.</stage>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Cu.</speaker>
                  <l>A Ghoſt!</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Pro.</speaker>
                  <l>Nay, the Devil ſhall part us ere we let thee go.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Fr.</speaker>
                  <l>How's this? My Cave the beaten Road of Luſt?</l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Philarchus</hi> and his Trull?</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Phi.</speaker>
                  <l>O Father, Father.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Fr.</speaker>
                  <l>Pinnario, Procus, Valerio, Babilas?</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Om.</speaker>
                  <l>We'l all confeſs, good good Father forgive us,</l>
                  <l>And by your art remove this fearfull Ghoſt.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Fr.</speaker>
                  <l>Say you ſo too.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Phi.</speaker>
                  <l>All that I ever did</l>
                  <l>Since my day of birth; O oh my chattering teeth,</l>
                  <l>My quaking bowels, O.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Fr.</speaker>
                  <l>Then ſtand apart;</l>
                  <stage>Speaks to the Ghost.</stage>
                  <l>Brother of earth, and ſhadow of frail fleſh,</l>
                  <l>By my holy Order I command thee ſpeak,</l>
                  <l>What crimes on earth remit thy pains in Hell?</l>
                  <l>And gives thee licence, like <hi>Octavians</hi> Ghoſt</l>
                  <l>To trace the upper Region of us Mortals?</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>En.</speaker>
                  <l>Let me firſt ſuck away this old mans ſoul,</l>
                  <l>And Ile obey thee, or with my fiery eys</l>
                  <l>Flaſh him to aſhes.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Phi.</speaker>
                  <l>O Father, Frier, Father.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Fr.</speaker>
                  <l>Speak, ſpeak, or I will ſink thy troubled Ghoſt</l>
                  <l>Unſatisfied into the cold earths womb.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>En.</speaker>
                  <l>Let him confeſs then all the injuries,</l>
                  <pb n="38" facs="tcp:114745:22"/>
                  <l> The wrongs, the miſeries, afflictions,</l>
                  <l>Abuſes, terrours, fears, threats, and diſgraces,</l>
                  <l>He ere did think, act, or intend to <hi>Aurelia;</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>Next let the knees of <hi>Babilas</hi> my foe</l>
                  <l>Bend at my feet, and there forgiveneſs ask,</l>
                  <l>To appeaſe my wrathfull ſpirit.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Ba.</speaker>
                  <l>I do, I do.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>En.</speaker>
                  <l>Aurelia now ith' arms of brave <hi>Pinnario,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>I do bequeath as his.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Pin.</speaker>
                  <l>Bear witneſs, Father.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>En.</speaker>
                  <l>He'l not confeſs. Let me foam Brimſtone on him.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Phi.</speaker>
                  <l>O yes, good Devil, confeſs, Ile confeſs all.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>En.</speaker>
                  <l>My time is ſhort, be brief.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Phi.</speaker>
                  <l>Briefer than words.</l>
                  <l>Where's <hi>Engin,</hi> O that <hi>Engin,</hi> he has a Paper</l>
                  <l>Fill'd with my wrongs committed to <hi>Aurelia,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>Which have been many, vile, notorious,</l>
                  <l>To the defiling of her name and bed.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>En.</speaker>
                  <l>My nimble Ghoſt hath fetcht the paper already.</l>
                  <stage>Shews a paper.</stage>
                  <l>Is all this true? Swear, ſwear, thou worſe than damn'd.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Phi.</speaker>
                  <l>By my preſent fears, by the mercy that I hope for</l>
                  <stage>
                     <hi>Ent.</hi> Ro. Sen.</stage>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>En.</speaker>
                  <l>I come you houling Furies, make me way.</l>
                  <stage>Exit.</stage>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Ro.</speaker>
                  <l>And we ſupply your room, nay you may enter,</l>
                  <l>The Ghoſt is vaniſht.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Sen.</speaker>
                  <l>Shame of Gravity.</l>
                  <stage>
                     <hi>To</hi> Phil.</stage>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Phi.</speaker>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Rogat</hi> and <hi>Senio?</hi> Infamy, diſgrace:</l>
                  <l>Sir, make me not a ſhame to all the world;</l>
                  <l>I will repair the ruines I have made</l>
                  <l>With the beſt ſatisfaction of my life.</l>
                  <l>Dear wife (if I may call thee ſo) on my knees</l>
                  <l>I do intreat thy mediation.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Fr.</speaker>
                  <l>But I good Son,</l>
                  <l>Muſt not forget the appeaſing of the Ghoſt.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Phi.</speaker>
                  <l>What means my Father ſtill to talk of Ghoſts?</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Fr.</speaker>
                  <l>Yes, and his Ghoſt, till fair <hi>Aurelia</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>Be made <hi>Pinnario's</hi> will ever haunt thee.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Phi.</speaker>
                  <l>I do reſign and freely give her up.</l>
                  <stage>
                     <hi>Enter</hi> Au. <hi>and</hi> Eng.</stage>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Pin.</speaker>
                  <l>Marry, and I will keep her. Ah ſweet Miſtris.</l>
                  <pb n="39" facs="tcp:114745:22"/>
                  <l> I knew I ſhould arrive at laſt though long.</l>
                  <stage>
                     <hi>Enter</hi> Eng. <hi>with</hi> Au. Pin. <hi>ſtares to ſee</hi> Au. <hi>with</hi> En. <hi>pulls off her veil.</hi>
                  </stage>
                  <l>But where's this <hi>Engin,</hi> this diſſembling Rogue?</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>En.</speaker>
                  <l>Here Sir, why ſtare you? you call'd me, did you not?</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Pin.</speaker>
                  <l>Damn'd lying ſpirit, <hi>Aurelia</hi> with <hi>Engin?</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>What Snail hid in her ſlimy ſhell have I got?</l>
                  <l>Cunicula.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Cu.</speaker>
                  <l>Your own Sir, fleſh and bone.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Pin.</speaker>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Procus, Valerio,</hi> my conſtant friends,</l>
                  <l>Shall we ſtill flatter and beguile our ſelves</l>
                  <l>With this baſe Varlets ſaucineſs and pride,</l>
                  <l>So many evidences of our ſhame</l>
                  <l>As here are preſent: if we murder him,</l>
                  <l>Will ſay he merited that puniſhment:</l>
                  <l>Draw then, and on him.</l>
                  <stage>
                     <hi>They draw.</hi> Eng. <hi>pulls off his diſguize.</hi>
                  </stage>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Pro.</speaker>
                  <l>Raſcal we'l mark your Carkaſe.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Dauph.</speaker>
                  <l>Why, Gentlemen, this rudeneſs is below</l>
                  <l>A Commons mutiny, or Sailers muſter.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Om.</speaker>
                  <l>Dauphine!</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Pro.</speaker>
                  <l>Were't thou the Ghoſt and thing that cheated us?</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Dau.</speaker>
                  <l>Thank this white ſheet and this diſguiſe, I was;</l>
                  <l>Nay, tremble not, I am no Ghoſt, <hi>Philarchus,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>Give you joy young Sir, and your fat wife <hi>Erotia.</hi>
                  </l>
                  <stage>Er. <hi>unveiled.</hi>
                  </stage>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Om.</speaker>
                  <l>Erotia!</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Sen.</speaker>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Philarchus</hi> with a Bawd.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Phi.</speaker>
                  <l>Where ſhall I look? That I were blinde and deaf.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Ro.</speaker>
                  <l>Nay, all appears not yet, for that the world</l>
                  <l>May teſtifie how much <hi>Dauphine</hi> preferr'd</l>
                  <l>His brothers life before my fair Eſtate.</l>
                  <l>By <hi>Dauphines</hi> help behold <hi>Octavian</hi> ſafe.</l>
                  <stage>
                     <hi>Enter</hi> Oct.</stage>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Om.</speaker>
                  <l>Octavian!</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Ro.</speaker>
                  <l>It is my Son alive, in health and luſty.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Pro.</speaker>
                  <l>By my great Boots as greatly joy to ſee thee.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Om.</speaker>
                  <l>So do we all.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Oct.</speaker>
                  <l>To all my humbleſt thanks.</l>
                  <l>And Gentlemen I ſoon will ſatisfie</l>
                  <l>Your longing expectation, give me firſt leave</l>
                  <l>To acquit my wrong'd <hi>Aurelia</hi> of this man.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Phi.</speaker>
                  <l>Now, now, I am ſlicing for the Devils breakfaſt.</l>
                  <pb n="40" facs="tcp:114745:23"/>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Oct.</speaker>
                  <l>See here with his own hand regiſtred</l>
                  <l>All the devices, plots, conſpiracies,</l>
                  <l>To <hi>Aurelia</hi> offer'd.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Sen.</speaker>
                  <l>Ile reade them preſently—</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Oct.</speaker>
                  <l>Stay Sir, <hi>Aurelia</hi> now is mine agen,</l>
                  <l>I muſt not ſow diſtaſt with my ſpringing joys:</l>
                  <l>Let him but vow to obey this one command,</l>
                  <l>And thus his faults are torn.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Phi.</speaker>
                  <l>I do proteſt.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Oct.</speaker>
                  <l>Then I command and charge you to receive</l>
                  <l>This equal wife into your feeble arms;</l>
                  <l>Cheriſh, imbrace her, and both live honeſtly.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Phi.</speaker>
                  <l>Marry a whore.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Oct.</speaker>
                  <l>Then Ile proclame all.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Phi.</speaker>
                  <l>Hold noble juſt <hi>Octavian, I</hi> obey you.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Er.</speaker>
                  <l>And me to Giblets, Ile chip you into Mommocks elſe.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Phi.</speaker>
                  <l>So, ſo, <hi>Aurelia's</hi> cruelty in her too.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Dau.</speaker>
                  <l>Heark brother, pauſe a little; <hi>I</hi> have now</l>
                  <l>A happy occaſion to advance my fortune:</l>
                  <l>You know <hi>I</hi> have but a ſmall Annuity,</l>
                  <l>But all had been mine, had <hi>I</hi> not ſav'd your life,</l>
                  <l>By acting <hi>Engin</hi> for you.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Oct.</speaker>
                  <l>Thou haſt ſo nobly freed me from my fears</l>
                  <l>That <hi>I</hi> am onely poor in thanking thee,</l>
                  <l>Command what ere thou wilt.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Dau.</speaker>
                  <l>Heark then. You ſee <hi>Philarchus</hi> is ſo frighted</l>
                  <l>So aſham'd, and fearfull of what you may diſcover,</l>
                  <l>That he'l do any thing ſo you be ſecret.</l>
                  <l>Faith, add one more command, and let it be</l>
                  <l>To ſettle on me two hundred pounds a year,</l>
                  <l>And then th'aſt nobly recompenc'd thy brother;</l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>I</hi> have a Bond here of twenty thouſand pound</l>
                  <l>Ready ingroſt to tie him to his promiſe.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Oct.</speaker>
                  <l>'Tis done, Ile warrant thee. Stay <hi>I</hi> recant,</l>
                  <l>Shall <hi>I</hi> be good to thee, conceal thy faults,</l>
                  <l>Marry thee to a fit wife, and all this</l>
                  <l>To thee my Enemy, yet reap no benefit?</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Phi.</speaker>
                  <l>What a poor doting fool can give, receive.</l>
                  <pb n="41" facs="tcp:114745:23"/>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Oct.</speaker>
                  <l>Then on my brother <hi>Dauphine</hi> engage to ſettle</l>
                  <l>Two hundred pounds a year, no words, but preſently</l>
                  <l>Seal to perform it, elſe by my revenge—</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Phi.</speaker>
                  <l>No big words, if you have mercy, what ſhall <hi>I</hi> do?</l>
                  <l>Two hundred pound, though dearer than my bloud,</l>
                  <l>Yet cheap enough to ſave my Reputation.</l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>I</hi> do conſent, give me the Bond, Ile ſeal.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Dau.</speaker>
                  <l>Father and Gentlemen your hands to witneſs.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Rog.</speaker>
                  <l>To what my ſon?</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Dau.</speaker>
                  <l>A trifling thing call'd two hundred pounds a year</l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Philarchus</hi> here is bound to ſettle on me.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Ro.</speaker>
                  <l>How's that? My hand and bleſſing too.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Pro.</speaker>
                  <l>A lucky Rogue, and yet wears no great Boots.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Phi.</speaker>
                  <l>I deliver you this as my Act and Deed.</l>
                  <stage>Seals.</stage>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Dau.</speaker>
                  <l>Why, ſo, this is a bleſſed end of Uſury,</l>
                  <l>To purchaſe Land to beſtow on younger brothers.</l>
                  <l>May all rich Citizens obſerve thy charity.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Sen.</speaker>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Octavian</hi> as I rejoyce to ſee</l>
                  <l>Thy forgotten duſt reſume a ſhape agen,</l>
                  <l>So I lament the deprivation</l>
                  <l>Of <hi>Aurelia</hi> from thee and all men elſe.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Oct.</speaker>
                  <l>How's this?</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Sen.</speaker>
                  <l>Alas, ſhe's married to <hi>Philarchus.</hi>
                  </l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Fr.</speaker>
                  <l>Hold <hi>Senio,</hi> and hear the <hi>Frier</hi> ſpeak,</l>
                  <l>And from his words gather the union</l>
                  <l>Of theſe ſo long divorced pair of Lovers.</l>
                  <l>Walking abroad to taſte the morning ſweetneſs</l>
                  <l>A goary track of bloud made me a path</l>
                  <l>To the unwelcome place, where wounds lay gaſping</l>
                  <l>Of a ſlain body, ghaſtly, ſtiff, diſguiz'd</l>
                  <l>For fear of the Edict then new proclam'd:</l>
                  <l>I rais'd his body with my aged arms,</l>
                  <l>Bore him to be interr'd within my Cell,</l>
                  <l>But ſearching his wounds, and pulling off his Vizard,</l>
                  <l>(With pale fear daunted) I beheld his face,</l>
                  <l>Which me thought was colour'd with ſome hope of life;</l>
                  <l>In ſhort ſuch bounty Heaven lent my pains,</l>
                  <l>That with my Art I ſoon recall'd again.</l>
                  <pb n="42" facs="tcp:114745:24"/>
                  <l> His ſhrinking ſpirits. But he whoſe onely life</l>
                  <l>Was hid and cheriſht in <hi>Aurelia's</hi> boſom</l>
                  <l>Burſts out loud cries for his <hi>Aurelia,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>And that he fear'd, if's death were but ſuſpected</l>
                  <l>Her father then would force her to <hi>Philarchus:</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>All comforts I adminiſtred were loathſom,</l>
                  <l>Unleſs Ide ſweeten them with his <hi>Aurelia:</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>I found this grief was deſperate, which made me</l>
                  <l>Send in all haſte to <hi>Rogat</hi> and <hi>Aurelia,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>And to be certain, and add joy to health,</l>
                  <l>(And with conſent of <hi>Rogat</hi> and <hi>Aurelia,)</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>By my holy Order made them Man and Wife.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Se.</speaker>
                  <l>But why ſo long did you conceal the Marriage?</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Fr.</speaker>
                  <l>Hearing <hi>Philarchus</hi> was the ſelected man,</l>
                  <l>And doubting leaſt <hi>Octavians</hi> wounds might prove</l>
                  <l>Still mortal, and that <hi>Senio</hi> would not hazard</l>
                  <l>(On that account) his daughter to <hi>Octavian,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>And that <hi>Philarchus</hi> Gold and ſolid outſide</l>
                  <l>Should tempt and cozen you, grave <hi>Senio,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>To give your daughter up to him ſhe hated,</l>
                  <l>And on a fathers curſe wed whom ſhe abhorr'd.</l>
                  <l>(Aſham'd to ſee an old man dote in love)</l>
                  <l>'Twas our invention, <hi>Dauphine</hi> thus diſguiz'd</l>
                  <l>Should fright and terrefie <hi>Philarchus,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>Unto a true confeſſion of himſelf.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Se.</speaker>
                  <l>Why, then you married <hi>Aurelia</hi> and <hi>Octavian?</hi>
                  </l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Fr.</speaker>
                  <l>I did.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Se.</speaker>
                  <l>And your pretence of <hi>Dauphines</hi> hot purſuit</l>
                  <l>In ſearch of <hi>Babilas,</hi> was but ſuppos'd,</l>
                  <l>That ſo he might act <hi>Engin</hi> unſuſpected.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Ro.</speaker>
                  <l>It was indeed.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Se.</speaker>
                  <l>My bleſſing, my bleſſing on you both.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Oct.</speaker>
                  <l>Now may I call thee twice mine bright <hi>Aurelia.</hi>
                  </l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Fr.</speaker>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Pinnario</hi> though young <hi>Octavians</hi> friend,</l>
                  <l>You have done ill, and groſly have betraid</l>
                  <l>In this poor wench even innocence it ſelf,</l>
                  <l>It will agree with our conformity,</l>
                  <l>If you create <hi>Cunicula</hi> your wife.</l>
                  <pb n="43" facs="tcp:114745:24"/>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Pin.</speaker>
                  <l>Troth now I am up, and for <hi>Octavians</hi> ſake:</l>
                  <l>Doſt hear <hi>Cunicula,</hi> after variety</l>
                  <l>Of bed-fellows, will one content thee? Ha?</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Cun.</speaker>
                  <l>Yes, and my prayers for this converſion.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Fr.</speaker>
                  <l>How is my Cell bleſt?</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Pro.</speaker>
                  <l>Nay, ſince all's loſt, Ile to my Boots agen.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Oct.</speaker>
                  <l>Now to you <hi>Babilas,</hi> whoſe fortune 'twas</l>
                  <l>To glory in my conqueſt, let me tell thee,</l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Dauphine</hi> has fetcht mine honour back again</l>
                  <l>From thy friends boſom, and if you repine</l>
                  <l>Again, I dare thee to a ſecond fight.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Ba.</speaker>
                  <l>No more contention unleſs it be in friendſhip:</l>
                  <l>Happy <hi>Octavian</hi> I beg thy love and pardon.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Oct.</speaker>
                  <l>Thou haſt um back. Henceforth for ever friends.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Val.</speaker>
                  <l>Was <hi>Babilas</hi> the cauſe then of our quarrel?</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Dau.</speaker>
                  <l>He was.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Ba.</speaker>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Valerio</hi> and <hi>Dauphine</hi> then agree too.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Fr.</speaker>
                  <l>Ile mediate betwixt um: give me your hands,</l>
                  <l>Becauſe in my opinion all are quit,</l>
                  <l>For what <hi>Octavian</hi> loſt by <hi>Babilas</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>In <hi>Valerio's</hi> bloud was recompenc'd by <hi>Dauphine,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>What <hi>Valerio</hi> ſuffer'd was before maintain'd</l>
                  <l>By the hand of <hi>Babilas.</hi> By the love and honour</l>
                  <l>For which you fought for, I command you:</l>
                  <l>Receive each others friendſhips to your boſoms.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Dau.</speaker>
                  <l>With my ſouls beſt power.</l>
                  <stage>Embrace.</stage>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Val.</speaker>
                  <l>With joy and gladneſs.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Dau.</speaker>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Pinnario</hi> and <hi>Procus</hi> I ask your pardon.</l>
                  <l>'Twas for my brothers Miſtris I us'd you thus.</l>
                  <l>When you have a Miſtris each of you command,</l>
                  <l>Both of us how or in what form you pleaſe.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Pro.</speaker>
                  <l>And by my great Boots thou wilt act it rarely.</l>
                  <l>Well. Since 'twas for a handſom Laſs, <hi>Dauphine,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>And on condition of the like aſſiſtance</l>
                  <l>For me, when I ſhall need thee. Let's embrace.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Pin.</speaker>
                  <l>On the ſame terms then let us all embrace.</l>
                  <stage>Here all imbrace.</stage>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Om.</speaker>
                  <l>For ever real, hearty and true Friends.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Se.</speaker>
                  <l>To make this union ſtronger, let me entreat</l>
                  <pb n="44" facs="tcp:114745:25"/>
                  <l> You all would honour my poor houſe this night,</l>
                  <l>And taſte a ſupper ſeaſon'd with your welcom.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Omnes.</speaker>
                  <l>We all conſent.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Frier.</speaker>
                  <l>Take then thy fair one in thy arms,</l>
                  <l>And Saints protect ye from all harms;</l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Pinnario</hi> with <hi>Cuniculu,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Philarchus</hi> with <hi>Erotia,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Valerio, Babilas,</hi> and <hi>Procus,</hi> they</l>
                  <l>Shall be the Bridemen of this day;</l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Dauphine</hi> with his new purchaſe then</l>
                  <l>The rare alms of a Citizen;</l>
                  <l>Wiſe <hi>Rogat</hi> with grave <hi>Senio,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>And laſt my ſelf the <hi>Frier</hi> too.</l>
                  <l>All to my Chappel then away</l>
                  <l>To thoſe delights which ſhew the day.</l>
                  <l>Thus flouriſh ſhall the juſt, and ſtill increaſe,</l>
                  <l>Till death them crown with everlaſting peace.</l>
                  <stage>Exeunt omnes.</stage>
               </sp>
            </div>
         </div>
         <div type="epilogue">
            <pb n="45" facs="tcp:114745:25"/>
            <head>EPILOGUE.</head>
            <lg>
               <l>TIs done without <hi>Amen,</hi> or ſuperstition,</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Popes</hi> Bull, or the Committees inquiſition:</l>
               <l>What think ye now of Plays? Abominable:</l>
               <l>Or is't 'cauſe you want wit to unfold a Fable,</l>
               <l>Pick out the Allegory, drive the ſenſe</l>
               <l>Where the Plot aims it: that your benevolence</l>
               <l>Should clap us, and our mouths up. Confeſs, confeſs;</l>
               <l>You would be ſomething, and 'gainst Plays you preſs,</l>
               <l>To be prickt down as States-men, not becauſe</l>
               <l>You do conceive um hurtfull, but will make Laws,</l>
               <l>To undo the Gallants pastime of the Land:</l>
               <l>Beats down becauſe you cannot understand.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Slow Readers, look upon the <hi>Roman</hi> State,</l>
               <l>Whoſe high built frame the ſtars durst emulate,</l>
               <l>And look as far as they. Ask <hi>Livie</hi> there,</l>
               <l>How many worthies grac'd her Theatre:</l>
               <l>They whoſe civility hath nurst us all;</l>
               <l>Thought um moſt holy, ſtil'd um Tragical,</l>
               <l>From their Gods Sacrifices. And must we,</l>
               <l>Whoſe polliſh'd Scene purg'd from obſcenity</l>
               <l>By Poets flaming fancies, whoſe bright rays</l>
               <l>Conſume ſcurrility, and fix the Bays</l>
               <pb n="46" facs="tcp:114745:26"/>
               <l> With us to fan profaneſs, drive away</l>
               <l>Light chaff, that in pure colours, Scenes display.</l>
               <l>When plots work high with contradictions fill'd,</l>
               <l>Amazing you, how are they reconcil'd?</l>
               <l>Muſt we I ſay be cenſur'd? Why 'tis your nature</l>
               <l>To gaze at new things, adore the faſhions altar.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>No, more reſiſt your own opinions. We</l>
               <l>Will dreſs our Scenes with various novelty,</l>
               <l>And teach you wit enough for eighteen pence</l>
               <l>Above the reach of the Common Councils ſenſe.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Try and perſever, if you finde this true,</l>
               <l>Silence your errours, and we are quit with you.</l>
            </lg>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
