<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>The walks of Islington and Hogsdon, with the humours of Woodstreet-compter. A comedy, as it was publikely acted 19. days together, with extraordinary applause. Never printed before. Written by Tho. Jordan, Gent.</title>
            <author>Jordan, Thomas, 1612?-1685?</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1657</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 165 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 32 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-12">2011-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A87372</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing J1071</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Thomason E910_5</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R202056</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99862476</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99862476</idno>
            <idno type="VID">114636</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A87372)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 114636)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Thomason Tracts ; 137:E910[5])</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>The walks of Islington and Hogsdon, with the humours of Woodstreet-compter. A comedy, as it was publikely acted 19. days together, with extraordinary applause. Never printed before. Written by Tho. Jordan, Gent.</title>
                  <author>Jordan, Thomas, 1612?-1685?</author>
                  <author>R. C.</author>
                  <author>Cheyney, Richard, attributed name.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[64] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>printed by Tho. Wilson at the sign of the Three-Foxes in Long-lane,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1657.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Includes commendatory verses signed: R. C. in Art. Magist. [i.e. R. Cheyney, to whom the work is dedicated?--cf. Pforzheimer Catalogue].</note>
                  <note>Signatures: [A]⁴ B-H⁴.</note>
                  <note>Annotation on Thomason copy: "May 7".</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the British Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2011-01</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-01</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-03</date>
            <label>Ali Jakobson</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-03</date>
            <label>Ali Jakobson</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-06</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:114636:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>THE WALKS OF <hi>ISLINGTON</hi> and <hi>HOGSDON,</hi> WITH <hi>The Humours of Woodſtreet-Compter.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>A Comedy, As it was publikely Acted 19. days toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, with extraordinary Applauſe.</p>
            <p>Never Printed before.</p>
            <p>Written by <hi>Tho. Jordan,</hi> Gent.</p>
            <q>Carpere vel noli noſtra, vel ede tua, <bibl>
                  <hi>Mart. Epig.</hi>
               </bibl>
            </q>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON:</hi> Printed by <hi>Tho. Wilſon</hi> at the ſign of the Three-Foxes in Long-lane. 1657.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="dedication">
            <pb facs="tcp:114636:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:114636:2"/>
            <head>TO The true Lover of Ingenuitie, <hi>The much Honoured, RICHARD CHEYNEY,</hi> of <hi>Hackney,</hi> Eſquire.</head>
            <opener>
               <salute>SIR,</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg>N thoſe jocund dayes, when ingenious Spirits were not daunted to behold the Phyſiognomy of their Minds and Man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ners in the Mirrour of a Dramatick-Poem, this Comedy gained the ſucceſs of a good Cenſure, and received more Acceptation then I thought it merited: Yet ſince the importunacy of Friends hath prevailed with me (in this tempeſtuous ſeaſon) to print it; Prudence hath well inſtructed me to ſhrowd it under the undoubted ſafety of your Protection; becauſe I am aſſured that the glittering influence of your bright Approbation, will, as the riſing Sun doth gild all Trees he looks upon, ſet ſuch a luſtre on theſe Leaves, that Time armed with En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vie ſhall never extinguiſh; ſuch lawful confidence hath he aſſumed that wiſheth your everlaſting proſperity, and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſireth no other temporal Title, then to be found in the Liſt, though the leaſt of,</p>
            <closer>
               <salute>SIR,</salute>
               <signed>Your greateſt Honcurers, THO. JORDAN.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="dramatis_personae">
            <pb facs="tcp:114636:3"/>
            <head>Dramatis Perſonae.</head>
            <list>
               <item>
                  <hi>Mercurio,</hi> a Lover of <hi>Splendora.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Flylove,</hi> A Humoriſt, Lover to <hi>Bellaflora.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Rivers.</hi> Love and brother to <hi>Mrs. Trimwel.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Wildblood.</hi> A Companion to <hi>Flylove,</hi> and nephew to <hi>Bella.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Sir Reverence Lamard,</hi> Brother to <hi>Splendora,</hi> diſguis'd like a Frenchman.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Mr. Nice,</hi> Father to <hi>Splendora.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Pimpwel,</hi> A creature to the young Gallants.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Mr. Trimwel,</hi> An old jealou Citizen.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Mr. Hemlock,</hi> A cheating Vintner.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Six Fidlers. Three Keepers.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Two Serjeants.</hi> The one of them <hi>Tripes.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Drawers.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Six priſoners.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Old Jones,</hi> A Cobler.</item>
            </list>
            <list>
               <head>Women.</head>
               <item>
                  <hi>Splendora,</hi> The Miſtreſs to <hi>Mercurio.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Bellaflora,</hi> The Love to <hi>Flylove..</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Mrs. Trimwel,</hi> A Citizens wife, and ſiſter to <hi>Rivers.</hi> Miſtris of the Kings-head at <hi>Hogsdon.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Mrs. Hemlock,</hi> A Vintners wife.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Mrs. Light,</hi> A Whore.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Drowzy,</hi> A Kitchin-wench.</item>
            </list>
         </div>
         <div type="encomium">
            <pb facs="tcp:114636:3"/>
            <head>To his much deſerving Friend Mr. <hi>Thomas Jordan,</hi> on his excellent Comedy, entituled, <hi>The Walks of Iſlington and Hogsdon, With the Humours of</hi> Woodſtreet-Compter.</head>
            <l>HOw have I task'd my ſelf that now muſt clear</l>
            <l>A debt that's due almoſt this twenty year?</l>
            <l>And, by your large improvements ſince, do finde</l>
            <l>You much before, and my ſelf caſt behinde,</l>
            <l>In ſuch a weak condition, who can</l>
            <l>Expect full payment from a Bankerupt man?</l>
            <l>Yet know no empty ſhaddows had the Art,</l>
            <l>To catch my prayſes, but your known deſart;</l>
            <l>Though love obligeth love, the nobler tye</l>
            <l>Of worth by knowledge is mere faſt and high;</l>
            <l>With Poetry you have Muſick, and as ſoon</l>
            <l>As you have made the Song, you ſet the Tune;</l>
            <l>Where both in meaſure ſo exactly dance,</l>
            <l>Numbers court Numbers, Ayrs do Words advance;</l>
            <l>Had I but room, I could declare how clean</l>
            <l>Your Fancy wrought, which did adorn your Scaene</l>
            <l>In ſeveral Plots, and Plays, this here exprest,</l>
            <l>Will ſpeak the noble Linage of the reſt.</l>
            <l>Theſe <hi>Walks</hi> 'twixt <hi>Iſlington</hi> and <hi>Hogsdon</hi> will,</l>
            <l>(Like thoſe 'twixt <hi>Tempe</hi> and <hi>Parnaſſus</hi> Hill)</l>
            <l>Show how the Muſes in their ſportfull rage,</l>
            <l>Set all the Town a Walking to your Stage,</l>
            <l>With ſo much Wit, and Art, and Judgement lay'd,</l>
            <l>That nineteen days together they were play'd.</l>
            <l>Now by the bounty of the Preſs we be</l>
            <l>Poſſeſs'd of that which we before did ſee,</l>
            <l>Not pleaſing onely nineteen times read o're,</l>
            <l>But nineteen Ages, or till Time's no more.</l>
            <byline>R. C. in Art. Magiſt.</byline>
         </div>
         <div type="prologue">
            <pb facs="tcp:114636:4"/>
            <head>The Prologue.</head>
            <l>THe Author (as late cuſtome hath thought fit)</l>
            <l>Makes me the <hi>Prologue</hi> to his wandring Wit;</l>
            <l>The Gate into his <hi>Walks,</hi> through which you may</l>
            <l>Behold a petty proſpect of the Play;</l>
            <l>
               <hi>A Play of Walks,</hi> or you may pleaſe to rank it,</l>
            <l>With that which Ladies love, <hi>A running Banquet:</hi>
            </l>
            <l>And, though the Scoene be <hi>Iſlington,</hi> we ſwear,</l>
            <l>We will not blow ye up with Bottle Bear;</l>
            <l>Cram ye with Cream and Fools, which ſweetly pleaſe</l>
            <l>Ladies of Fortune and young Prentices,</l>
            <l>Who (when the Superviſors come to find 'um)</l>
            <l>Quake like the Cuſtard which they leave behind 'um.</l>
            <l>Yet to exalt your ſpleen, he hath invented,</l>
            <l>Perſons that you'l all know when they'r preſented;</l>
            <l>Nay they ſhall know themſelvs, and that is more,</l>
            <l>It may be then you ever knew before.</l>
            <l>We'l ſhew you things not taken out of Hiſt'ries,</l>
            <l>A loyal Lover, and a grateful Miſtriſs,</l>
            <l>A futile Frenchman (acted to the life)</l>
            <l>A jealous husband and a jocund wife,</l>
            <l>That kiſſeth, danceth, tipples like a Tench,</l>
            <l>A Chamber-Gallant and a Kitchin-wench;</l>
            <l>A jovial Cobler (or a Quibler rather)</l>
            <l>A Catchpole that arreſted his own father;</l>
            <l>A crew of Ranters to the Gaole committed,</l>
            <l>A dead man rais'd, a Uſurer out-witted,</l>
            <l>A Priſon-Pimp diſcover'd and detected,</l>
            <l>The <hi>Compter</hi> character'd, the <hi>Hole</hi> diſſected.</l>
            <l>Here my Commiſſion ends, leſt I betray</l>
            <l>The Plot, and ſhew the Clock-work of the I lay:</l>
            <l>Your liking will (like to the Suns bright rays)</l>
            <l>Lighten the Gaole, and plant theſe <hi>Walks</hi> with Bays,</l>
            <l>Where you will finde ſome Flowers as well as ſtalks,</l>
            <l>Then lend's your hands, we'l lead you to the <hi>Walks,</hi>
            </l>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="play">
            <pb facs="tcp:114636:4"/>
            <head>The Walks of <hi>Iſlington</hi> and <hi>Hogsdon,</hi> &amp;c.</head>
            <div n="1" type="act">
               <head>Actus primus, Scoena prima.</head>
               <stage>Enter as at the Sarazens-head in Iſlington; Jack Wildblood, Frank Rivers, and Stephen Flylove; to them Tavern-Boyes.</stage>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Wildblood.</speaker>
                  <p>BOy Drawer.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Rivers.</speaker>
                  <p>Drawer, Sirrah.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Within.</speaker>
                  <p>By and by, anon, anon Sir.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Wildbl.</speaker>
                  <l>Why thou <hi>Parte-per-villain,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>Drawer and Tapſter,</l>
                  <l>Are you ſo taken up with your Holy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>day Gheſts,</l>
                  <l>A Gentleman can have no attendance?</l>
                  <stage>Enter Drawer.</stage>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Drawer.</speaker>
                  <p>Attendance? Yes Sir, What Wine will it pleaſe you to drink?</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Rivers.</speaker>
                  <p>That is, which of three ſorts will ye drink, Sack, White, or Claret.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Draw.</speaker>
                  <p>Nay (with your favour Sir) we have more va<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riety then thoſe.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>lylove.</speaker>
                  <p>Well then Sir, without farther diſputation, bring White Wine, and let it be right.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Drawer.</speaker>
                  <p>I ſhall Sir.</p>
               </sp>
               <stage>Exit Drawer.</stage>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Wild.</speaker>
                  <p>Well <hi>Frank,</hi> and how doth thy little Miſtris?</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Rivers.</speaker>
                  <p>What little Miſtris?</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Wild.</speaker>
                  <p>Why ſhe that is the rareſt, the faireſt that ever was Maid, <hi>Jack Trimwel</hi> the Chyrurgeons wife.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Rivers.</speaker>
                  <p>Mum, not a word, our plots are almoſt diſcovered, I have kept ſome villains company that have betray'd me to the jealous Coxcomb (her husband) ſhe'l be here preſently.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <pb facs="tcp:114636:5"/>
                  <speaker>Wild.</speaker>
                  <p>Who haſt ſent?</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Rivers.</speaker>
                  <p>My old Mercury, <hi>Alexander Pimpwel.</hi>
                  </p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Fly.</speaker>
                  <l>Look, you can no ſooner talk of <hi>Pimpwel,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>But the Drawer comes; ſirrah, have you any</l>
                  <stage>Ent. Drawer with Wine.</stage>
                  <l>Whores in the houſe?</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Drawer.</speaker>
                  <p>I cannot tell Sir, I'le ask the Fidlers.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Fly.</speaker>
                  <p>Hark you ſirrah, have you any females in the houſe?</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Draw.</speaker>
                  <p>Yes Sir, there's half a ſcore in ſeveral rooms.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Fly.</speaker>
                  <l>Why you rogue, do you doubt whether there be</l>
                  <l>Any whores in the houſe then?</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Rivers.</speaker>
                  <p>Why thou rebel to Chaſtity, doſt thou conceive the ſtock of Females vertue is ſo extreamly waſted, that in ſo ſmall a number as they are, the moſt part muſt be vitious?</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Fly.</speaker>
                  <p>I, I vow if there were but two there, though my Mother were one.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Wild.</speaker>
                  <p>And thy Aunt tother.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Fly.</speaker>
                  <p>I mean ſo, the other ſhould be one of my Aunts.</p>
               </sp>
               <stage>Enter Alexander Pimpwel and Mrs. Trimwel.</stage>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Rivers.</speaker>
                  <p>Little <hi>Betty,</hi> your humble ſervant.</p>
                  <stage>Riv. ſalutes her.</stage>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Mrs. Trim.</speaker>
                  <p>But hark you <hi>Frank,</hi> what Gentlemen are theſe?</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Riv.</speaker>
                  <p>Friends of mine, moſt dear and intimate, ſalute them.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Mrs. Trim.</speaker>
                  <p>Oh, y' are a pretty Gentleman to ſend for me into company.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Wild.</speaker>
                  <p>Lady your humble ſervant.</p>
                  <stage>He kiſſeth.</stage>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Flyl.</speaker>
                  <p>Turn to me hony, and give me a kiſs.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Mrs. Trim.</speaker>
                  <p>Turn to you Sir, which part? my face is to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards you already.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Fly.</speaker>
                  <p>By the Cherry-lip of <hi>Venus,</hi> you are wondrous witty, Lady.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Mrs. Trim.</speaker>
                  <p>I am glad Sir you ſo apprehend it.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Fly.</speaker>
                  <p>'Tis not my apprehenſion can mend it.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Rivers.</speaker>
                  <p>Is ſhe not wondrous fair?</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Fly.</speaker>
                  <l>I dare not tell you,</l>
                  <l>For ſhould I grow ſo paſſionate in praiſe</l>
                  <l>As her worth merits, I might juſtly fear</l>
                  <l>Your fondneſs of her would ſuſpect my friendſhip;</l>
                  <l>For in this age Experience makes it common,</l>
                  <l>He needs muſt love that doth but praiſe a woman.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <pb facs="tcp:114636:5"/>
                  <speaker>Rivers.</speaker>
                  <l>You wrong my friendſhip to ſuppoſe I doubt you.</l>
                  <l>It were an injury to her and you;</l>
                  <l>The baſe ſuſpect from neither is exempted,</l>
                  <l>To think that you ſhould tempt, or ſhe be tempted.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Wild.</speaker>
                  <l>You are full of Noble confidence, I think ſhe</l>
                  <l>Loves you well.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Rivers.</speaker>
                  <l>Or ſhe doth well diſſemble,</l>
                  <l>But here's the wo, what bondage is he in,</l>
                  <l>That lives in love, when all his love is ſin?</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Mrs. Trim.</speaker>
                  <l>Gentlemen, doth my coming cauſe this diviſion among you?</l>
                  <l>Such ſeperation in ſo few a number hath been unuſuall.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Wild.</speaker>
                  <l>Your coming Lady rather makes an unitie,</l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Frank Rivers</hi> I'le begin a round to thy Miſtris.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Rivers.</speaker>
                  <p>Let it come.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Fly.</speaker>
                  <p>I vow I'le pledg't a brimmer:</p>
                  <stage>
                     <hi>Sings.</hi>
                     <l>
                        <hi>My Miſtris hath a Roſie Check</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>her eye-brows they are Jetty,</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Then drink off a brimmer</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>to he that doth</hi> —</l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>For tis a Health to</hi> Betty.</l>
                  </stage>
               </sp>
               <stage>Enter Drawer.</stage>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Draw:</speaker>
                  <p>Mr. <hi>Flylove</hi> is your name I pray Sir.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Fly.</speaker>
                  <p>Yes, ſo they ſay Sir.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Draw.</speaker>
                  <p>There's a woman without would ſpeak with you.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Fly.</speaker>
                  <p>Prethee what manner of piece is it?</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Draw.</speaker>
                  <l>A good homely creature Sir, ſome ſervant I believe,</l>
                  <l>A Maid-ſervant I dare ſwear ſhe is not,</l>
                  <l>For her noſe and belly do almoſt meet.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Fly.</speaker>
                  <p>A ſtrange creature, either ſhe hath a ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry <stage>aſide.</stage> long noſe, or a terrible great belly, and now I talk of a great belly, I pray Heaven it be not the Kitchin-wench I was dabling with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>all once, when drink and a fooliſh humor poſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeſt me (I heard ſhe was with Child) if it be, <stage>Exit Drawer.</stage> I am undone for ever, ſtay I'le go out to her.</p>
                  <stage>Ent. Drowzy.</stage>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <pb facs="tcp:114636:6"/>
                  <speaker>Drowzy.</speaker>
                  <p>No Sir, ſhe I come in to you.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Fly.</speaker>
                  <p>Prethee honeſt <hi>Drowzy.</hi>
                  </p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Drow.</speaker>
                  <p>Honeſt <hi>Drowzy</hi> I, I was honeſt <hi>Drowzy</hi> before I knew you.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Fly.</speaker>
                  <l>Nay but prethee <hi>Drowzy</hi> that was once honeſt,</l>
                  <l>Let me ſpeak with thee in private.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Drow.</speaker>
                  <p>No Sir, you have ſpoken too much in private with me already, <hi>Ecce ſigne,</hi> and Jle ſpeak to you here Sir; for all your fine Laſs there in the ſilk, I might have been as fine as ſhe, and yaw had kept your word.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Wild.</speaker>
                  <p>How now <hi>Stephen,</hi> what's the matter?</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Drow.</speaker>
                  <l>What's that to yaw ſir,</l>
                  <l>Pray meddle with your own buſineſs.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Fly.</speaker>
                  <p>Prethee be gone <hi>Jack,</hi> 'tis an honeſt Laſs comes with an errand to me.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Drow.</speaker>
                  <p>An arrant, what arrant am I, I come to ſpeak to you Sir, and to have ſatisfaction for the wrong you have done me, ye ſhall nere carry it to heaven nor to hell.</p>
               </sp>
               <stage>Enter Drawer.</stage>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Fly.</speaker>
                  <l>What the Devil ſhall I do, Drawer?</l>
                  <l>Prethee what haſt thou brought me here, a mad wench?</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Drow.</speaker>
                  <p>What would you have ſirrah?</p>
                  <stage>Gives the Boy a box oth' eare.</stage>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Draw.</speaker>
                  <l>A pox o' your greaſie fingers,</l>
                  <l>An you were not with Child —</l>
                  <l>— If ſhe be mad, I pray Sir do you tame her.</l>
               </sp>
               <stage>Exit.</stage>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Rivers.</speaker>
                  <p>How now <hi>Stephen,</hi> what's the buſineſs?</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Drow.</speaker>
                  <p>What care yaw ſir, you may go to yawr Gentlewo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man in the long locks again.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Mrs. Trim.</speaker>
                  <p>What is the woman mad?</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Drow.</speaker>
                  <p>Mad! no ſhe's as wel in her wits as you are, though ſhe is not ſo fine forſooth.</p>
                  <stage>Enter Pimpw.</stage>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Pimpw.</speaker>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Mrs. Trimwell,</hi> as I live your Husband's here.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Mrs. Trim.</speaker>
                  <p>Marry Heaven defend.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Pimpw.</speaker>
                  <p>He's coming up ſtayrs.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Mrs. Trim.</speaker>
                  <p>What will become on's.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Pimpw.</speaker>
                  <p>There's but one way, and thats this, here is a door goes down another pair of ſtayrs, whilſt he comes up, do you
<pb facs="tcp:114636:6"/>run down, you may eaſily eſcape unſeen by the back-ſide of <hi>Iſlington.</hi> Let me alone here.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Fly.</speaker>
                  <p>I, I, come let's go, I think the devil haunts us to day.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Drow.</speaker>
                  <l>Pray whither go yaw ſir,</l>
                  <l>I ha' more to ſay to you then ſo.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Fly.</speaker>
                  <p>Prethee honeſt <hi>Pimpwel</hi> keep this mad wench from me, and do you pay the reckning, you know our old rendezvouz.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Pimpw.</speaker>
                  <p>Well, well, let me alone.</p>
                  <stage>
                     <hi>Exeunt Wildblood Mrs. Trim.</hi> &amp; <hi>Flylove, manent Pimpw. with Drowzy.</hi>
                  </stage>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Drow.</speaker>
                  <p>Keep me back! ſirrah Ile ſet all my fingers in your eyes, if you keep me back, though your name be <hi>Pimpw.</hi> you ſhal not keep the door at this time.</p>
                  <stage>They both ſtrive. Enter Trimwel.</stage>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Trimw.</speaker>
                  <p>How now what's the matter? vaniſhed, ha all vaniſhed, only one rogue and a dirty whore, what are you, what are you, pray turn about?</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Drow.</speaker>
                  <p>Dirty whore, you lye like a baſe rogue, I am as honeſt a woman as thy wife, what come you for?</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Trim.</speaker>
                  <p>As honeſt as my wife, I, I, it may be ſo good Por<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pus, I ſpeak not to you, pray Sir where is all your company gone, where's my wife.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Pimpw.</speaker>
                  <p>Your wife Sir.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Trim.</speaker>
                  <p>My wife Sir, I my wife Sir.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Drow.</speaker>
                  <p>Doſt thou call me Porpus, you may be aſhamed to liken a woman to a beaſt, I am as like a Chriſtian as thou art, or any of thy kin, my father was as honeſt a man as any in <hi>Warwickshire,</hi> and his daughter ſhall not be made a fool yet as.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Trim.</speaker>
                  <p>Wher's my wife? what ſecret holes have you?</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Pimpw.</speaker>
                  <p>What do you ask me for your wife Sir, I know her not, nor you?</p>
                  <stage>Enter Drawer.</stage>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Draw.</speaker>
                  <p>Anon, anon Sir, by and by, did you call? how now what's become of the company was here, who payes the Reckoning?</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Trim.</speaker>
                  <p>Hey day, what have they left their Reckoning to pay, they were in mighty haſt it ſeems?</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Drow.</speaker>
                  <p>Was the woman in the black Guown yawr woife Sir?</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Trim.</speaker>
                  <p>Yes, which way went they?</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <pb facs="tcp:114636:7"/>
                  <speaker>Drow.</speaker>
                  <l>Marry 3. Gentlemen carried her down them ſtayrs,</l>
                  <l>You were beſt make haſte after 'um, or they'l</l>
                  <l>Make you a Coock old afore you come, and then</l>
                  <l>You'l loſe the ſport.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Trim.</speaker>
                  <l>He follow preſently, I gueſs where to find them.</l>
                  <l>If I cannot overtake them.</l>
               </sp>
               <stage>Exit Trim.</stage>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Drow.</speaker>
                  <l>By the maſſe Ile follow too, for my Gentleman</l>
                  <l>Is amongſt them; Ile teach him to turne</l>
                  <l>Up wenches bellies, and give them no ſartifaction.</l>
               </sp>
               <stage>Exit Drow.</stage>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Pimp.</speaker>
                  <p>Well you have your reckoning Drawer.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Draw.</speaker>
                  <l>To a farthing Sir, if you'l ſtay Sir, Ile give</l>
                  <l>You one pinte, becauſe you ſhall remember the</l>
                  <l>Sarazens head in <hi>Iſlington.</hi>
                  </l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Pimp.</speaker>
                  <l>I cannot ſtay now, I faith ſirrah, but next time</l>
                  <l>I come this way.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Draw.</speaker>
                  <p>Well Sir, you are welcome, by and by, I come, I come.</p>
               </sp>
               <stage>Exit Draw.</stage>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Pimpw.</speaker>
                  <p>So, ſo, a bad ſhift's better then none; oh the rage his head is filld with for his wife, and the belly full of vexa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion ſhe has to find Mr. <hi>Flylove.</hi> Pox of all fooles, <hi>I</hi> wonder what mad folly poſſes'd him to lye with this dirty, greaſy kichen-wench, was his appetite ſo ſharp ſet, that he muſt needs be lapping in the Dripping-pan? well, Ile follow them; <hi>I</hi> know their old haunt (the Kings-head at <hi>Hogſdown</hi>) Jealouſie hath many eyes, <hi>I</hi> muſt prevent the ſearcher: If all my plots hit right, Ile make the Cuckolds horns hang in his light.</p>
               </sp>
               <stage>Exit.</stage>
               <stage>Actus primus, Scaena ſecunda.</stage>
               <stage>Enter <hi>Marcurio</hi> and <hi>Splendora.</hi>
               </stage>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Mercu.</speaker>
                  <l>My fair <hi>Splendora,</hi> though my fortunes are,</l>
                  <l>Humble as he that ownes them; yet <hi>I</hi> can</l>
                  <l>
                     <pb facs="tcp:114636:7"/>Love thee with holy ardencie; devoutly</l>
                  <l>As zealous men in prayer do their Saints,</l>
                  <l>Or Votaries their Goddeſs.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Splend.</speaker>
                  <l>I know you want not wit to coyn a paſſion,</l>
                  <l>And pray (with all <hi>Mercurio</hi>) conceive,</l>
                  <l>I know how many ſymtoms of true love,</l>
                  <l>A Paraſite (in ſervice to his Mrs.)</l>
                  <l>Can uſe to gain his end; 'tis not a ſigh,</l>
                  <l>Diſſembled ſorrow in a far ſtraind tear,</l>
                  <l>The folded Arms; Encomiums compos'd,</l>
                  <l>With many interjections, nor the trick,</l>
                  <l>Of praiſing what ſhe's pleaſed with, can move me</l>
                  <l>To the leaſt faith, he whoſe ſlow tongue ſpeaks leaſt,</l>
                  <l>In Love or ſorrow oftentimes means beſt.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Merc.</speaker>
                  <l>I am ſorry you ſhould think I doubt your knowlege</l>
                  <l>I know you have a ſoul as full of Raies,</l>
                  <l>As <hi>Delphean Phaebus</hi> in oraculous glory;</l>
                  <l>You have divinity enough to ſee,</l>
                  <l>The pureſt love from niceſt flattery,</l>
                  <l>Or I ſhould ne'r affect you, tis my thought,</l>
                  <l>That ſhe whom flattery can purchaſe to me,</l>
                  <l>By one more ſubtil may be flattered fro me.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Splend.</speaker>
                  <l>You give a large account of your pure thoughts,</l>
                  <l>And I beleeve thee with ſuch confidence,</l>
                  <l>As to not do't, were hereſie; There</l>
                  <l>Reſign thee all the intreſt I hold dear,</l>
                  <l>In this weak frame.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Merc.</speaker>
                  <l>That ſhall contain us both,</l>
                  <l>Our hearts ſhall be one individuall eſſence,</l>
                  <l>To which we'l frame like paſſions, like affections,</l>
                  <l>By this divineſt Metomorphoſis,</l>
                  <l>The Gods (well pleas'd) ſhall terminate our lives,</l>
                  <l>Both at one Expiration in good age,</l>
                  <l>Seaſon'd and fit for glory, more Divine,</l>
                  <l>Where in one or be our unity ſhall ſhine.</l>
                  <stage>Ent. Mr. Nice.</stage>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Nice.</speaker>
                  <l>Who's here (undone) <hi>Mercurio</hi> and my daughter</l>
                  <l>Embracing? Changes Kiſſes? I ſhall part you.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <pb facs="tcp:114636:8"/>
                  <speaker>Splend.</speaker>
                  <p>My Father.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Nice.</speaker>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Splendora,</hi> your Mother calls you.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Splend.</speaker>
                  <l>I am ſorry Sir I have ſuch faulty ears, as not</l>
                  <l>To hear till your love pleaſe to tell me,</l>
                  <l>I attend her.</l>
               </sp>
               <stage>Exit Splend.</stage>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Nice.</speaker>
                  <p>Sir tis to you that I direct my ſpeech.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Merc.</speaker>
                  <p>I ſhall attend Sir what your ſpeech directs.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Nice.</speaker>
                  <l>To this intent I frame it, whats the cauſe</l>
                  <l>You make it all the buſineſs of your time</l>
                  <l>In viſits to my houſe? though uninvited,</l>
                  <l>I do not ſay you'r an unwelcome gueſt,</l>
                  <l>But till I know the motive of your coming,</l>
                  <l>I ſhall be cautious in your entertainment.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Merc.</speaker>
                  <l>Your words do bear a ſtrange ſuſpect in them,</l>
                  <l>And this to me, the Son of him that was</l>
                  <l>Once your beſt friend; whoſe love hath made you rich,</l>
                  <l>The manner's ſomewhat ſtrange.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Nice.</speaker>
                  <l>I ſhall be plainer,</l>
                  <l>I diſaffect your neerneſs with my daughter,</l>
                  <stage>Splend. ſtands within the Arras.</stage>
                  <l>I have beheld looſe kiſſes fond embraces,</l>
                  <l>Her ſighes to eccho yours, ſuch wantonneſs</l>
                  <l>As may not fit a pair of ſingle creatures,</l>
                  <l>Much leſſe you two, conſidering the diſtance.</l>
                  <l>Sir to be brief, I do ſuſpect you love her.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Merc.</speaker>
                  <p>Oh nere ſuſpect ſo Sir, you may be ſure on't.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Splend.</speaker>
                  <p>Why this is honeſt truth, fine right down dealing.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Nice.</speaker>
                  <p>And ſhe loves you.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Merc.</speaker>
                  <p>I hope ſhe will in time Sir.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Nice.</speaker>
                  <p>Tis well Sir, lend me your eare.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Merc.</speaker>
                  <p>Your pleaſure.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Splend.</speaker>
                  <l>I fear this whiſpering portends no good,</l>
                  <l>Here's pen and paper, Ile appoint our meeting,</l>
                  <l>Though we ſhall miſſe that ceremonious way,</l>
                  <l>Of lovely parting we were wont to have,</l>
                  <l>Ile find occaſion to deliver this.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Nice.</speaker>
                  <p>Nay which is more, you are a riotous man.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Splend.</speaker>
                  <p>
                     <hi>My deare Mercurio.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <stage>She writes.</stage>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Nice.</speaker>
                  <l>And let me tell you Sir, my Child and wealth,</l>
                  <l>
                     <pb facs="tcp:114636:8"/>Shall not be both expoſ'd to your profuſeneſs</l>
                  <l>Therefore (by my admoniſhment) pray leave her.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Splend.</speaker>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Meete me to morrow.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <stage>Writes agen.</stage>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Merc.</speaker>
                  <p>Sir did you ever love?</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Nice.</speaker>
                  <p>Yes.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Merc.</speaker>
                  <p>But did you e're affect a Virgin truly?</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Nice.</speaker>
                  <p>As man can do.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Merc.</speaker>
                  <p>When.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Splend.</speaker>
                  <p>
                     <hi>To morrow in the afternoon.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <stage>Writes agen.</stage>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Nice.</speaker>
                  <l>When time and love had made me capable</l>
                  <l>Of woman and her vertues.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Splend.</speaker>
                  <p>
                     <hi>In the green long walk by Newington.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <stage>Writes.</stage>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Merc.</speaker>
                  <l>Was not her preſence all your heaven on earth,</l>
                  <l>And then her abſence brought ſuch ſickly thoughts,</l>
                  <l>No novelty could mitigate.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Nice.</speaker>
                  <p>Very true.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Merc.</speaker>
                  <l>With that affection I eſteem your daughter.</l>
                  <l>Juſt ſuch a heaven her bleſt ſociety,</l>
                  <l>And ſuch a hell her abſence, had we not</l>
                  <l>By ſome diviner inſpiration,</l>
                  <l>A little proſpect to eternity,</l>
                  <l>I ſhould believe all joyes of ſoul were her:</l>
                  <l>The moſt indulgent Mothers never lov'd,</l>
                  <l>Their fair ligitimate Babes with ſuch a fondneſs,</l>
                  <l>As I do your <hi>Splendora.</hi>
                  </l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Nice.</speaker>
                  <p>You are very bountifull in your expreſſion.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Merc.</speaker>
                  <l>Too niggardly, her goodneſs merits more</l>
                  <l>Then I have worth to know, or tongue to utter;</l>
                  <l>I think her vertues all are infinite,</l>
                  <l>And not to be examin'd, I have ſearcht,</l>
                  <l>With moſt ingenious and induſtrious boldneſs,</l>
                  <l>To take the height of her perfection,</l>
                  <l>But forc'd with admiration to retire,</l>
                  <l>For ſtill as I drew neer her ſoul flew higher.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Splend.</speaker>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Your conſtant heart Splendora.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <stage>Writes agen.</stage>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Nice.</speaker>
                  <l>You have expreſt her merit and your love,</l>
                  <l>And had you an eſtate equall to either,</l>
                  <l>With worldly providence and care to uſe it,</l>
                  <l>
                     <pb facs="tcp:114636:9"/>
                     <hi>I</hi> ſhould eſteem your motion, as you are;</l>
                  <l>Your polyte phraſes cannot work on me,</l>
                  <l>Nor ſhall they on my daughter, whoſe obedience</l>
                  <l>Muſt be conformable to my diſpoſe.</l>
                  <stage>Enter Splend</stage>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Splend.</speaker>
                  <p>Did you call Sir.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Nice.</speaker>
                  <l>No,</l>
                  <l>But ſince your diligence hath got ſuch wings,</l>
                  <l>Stay and take leave of your kind viſitant,</l>
                  <l>And be not tedious.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Splend.</speaker>
                  <p>Well Sir.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Nice.</speaker>
                  <l>I have ſome buſines may concern your good,</l>
                  <l>Which you cannot conceive.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Splend.</speaker>
                  <l>
                     <hi>I</hi> do believe you.</l>
                  <l>You ſee my dear <hi>Mercurio,</hi> how adverſe</l>
                  <stage>Softly.</stage>
                  <l>My Father is, time's ſhort, read that, farewell,</l>
                  <l>We'l meet agen.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Merc.</speaker>
                  <p>This parting is my hell.</p>
               </sp>
               <stage>Exit Merc.</stage>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Servant.</speaker>
                  <p>Sir the French Knight is come,</p>
                  <stage>Enter a ſervant.</stage>
                  <stage>Sir <hi>Reverenee Lamard.</hi>
                  </stage>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Nice.</speaker>
                  <p>Wait on him in.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Ser.</speaker>
                  <p>
                     <hi>I</hi> ſhall Sir.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Splend.</speaker>
                  <p>Oh, my torment!</p>
                  <stage>Enter Sir Reverence and Wildfire his Page.</stage>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Nice.</speaker>
                  <p>Noble Sir <hi>Reverence,</hi> your humble ſervant.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Sir Rev.</speaker>
                  <l>Tres humble Serviture Monſieur.</l>
                  <l>A voſtre Serviture Madam.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Nice.</speaker>
                  <l>Sir you too ſeldome grace us with your viſits,</l>
                  <l>Although our country cuſtome cannot yield,</l>
                  <l>That fair and ceremonious entertainment</l>
                  <l>You French men uſe; believe me you are welcome.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Sir Rev.</speaker>
                  <l>Gramercie Monſieur de mon ceuir,</l>
                  <l>Vat you name de Madam your dater a.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Nice.</speaker>
                  <p>We call her Sir <hi>Splendora.</hi>
                  </p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Sir Rev.</speaker>
                  <p>Spent whora?</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Nice.</speaker>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Splen do ra.</hi>
                  </p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Sir Rev.</speaker>
                  <p>Split whore a.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Nice.</speaker>
                  <p>The name is ſome what hard Sir.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Sir Rev.</speaker>
                  <p>Begar ſo it is, Split, Split, Split whore a.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <pb facs="tcp:114636:9"/>
                  <speaker>Nice.</speaker>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Splen.</hi>
                  </p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Sir Rev.</speaker>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Splen.</hi>
                  </p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Nice.</speaker>
                  <p>Do.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Sir Rev.</speaker>
                  <p>Do.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Nice.</speaker>
                  <p>
                     <hi>ra.</hi>
                  </p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Sir Rev.</speaker>
                  <p>
                     <hi>ra.</hi>
                  </p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Nice.</speaker>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Splen do ra.</hi>
                  </p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Sir. Rev.</speaker>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Splen do ra.</hi>
                  </p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Nice.</speaker>
                  <p>Right Sir.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Sir Rev.</speaker>
                  <p>Madam <hi>Splen do ra,</hi> will you give Sir <hi>Reverence,</hi> Leave to kiſſe beſhide your ſheeke.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Splend.</speaker>
                  <p>Let it be but of one ſide <hi>I</hi> beſeech you Sir, <hi>I</hi> have lately been troubled with the Tooth-ake.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Nice.</speaker>
                  <p>Ile leave you ſir to opportunity.</p>
                  <stage>Riſes.</stage>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Sir Rev.</speaker>
                  <p>Gramercie Monſeir, voſtre ſerviteur.</p>
                  <stage>Vildfier.</stage>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Wild.</speaker>
                  <p>At your backe Monſeir.</p>
               </sp>
               <stage>Exit Nice.</stage>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Sir Rev.</speaker>
                  <p>Allo allo.</p>
                  <stage>and wild.</stage>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Wild.</speaker>
                  <p>
                     <hi>I</hi> am gon Sir.</p>
               </sp>
               <stage>Exit.</stage>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Sir Rev.</speaker>
                  <p>Madam your fadra ſay to me he would have me take you for my wife, my Lady, my Madam, my Madam <hi>Lamard;</hi>
                  </p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Splend.</speaker>
                  <p>Did my father bid you put me in hope of theſe phantaſticke titles?</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Sir Rev.</speaker>
                  <p>Fantaſie, begar be brave title to be wife to Sir <hi>Reverence Lamard.</hi>
                  </p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Splend.</speaker>
                  <p>To be your wife Sir <hi>Reverence?</hi>
                  </p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Sir Rev.</speaker>
                  <p>Awee, and Sir <hi>Reverence</hi> to be your husband.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Splend.</speaker>
                  <l>I thank you Sir.</l>
                  <l>I hope that uinon will happy prove;</l>
                  <l>Where Sir <hi>Reverence</hi> is the beginning of love,</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Sir Rev.</speaker>
                  <p>Begar dat was right, me love you out of all cry, You ſhall be a Lady, when we have marry, wee'l go to <hi>Parry,</hi> begar was de brave City of the World, me will have you dreſſe like de Frenſh Madam, and ride in your Carroſh, begar dis Engliſh Dreſſe is noting; 'tis not a le mode <hi>France,</hi> den me vill ſhew you de brave Pallace of de King, you never ſee ſuch ſtate in your life, Oh brava, brava; and den.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Splend.</speaker>
                  <l>Pray ſtay there Sir.</l>
                  <l>I wonder that a Knight of your vaſt wealth,</l>
                  <l>In your owne Country could not find a faire one,</l>
                  <l>Worthy to meet your merrit; I may doubt</l>
                  <l>You are not what you would have me conceive,</l>
                  <l>Or my too credulous father is inform'd,</l>
                  <l>
                     <pb facs="tcp:114636:10"/>And did your judgment, ſympathize with mine,</l>
                  <l>I would not wiſh you to adventure marriage,</l>
                  <l>With any Lady of another Nation,</l>
                  <l>There is a fitneſs to be found in love,</l>
                  <l>Which very far tranſcends wealth wit or beauty,</l>
                  <l>By him that keeps me for a better end,</l>
                  <l>I would not be your Miſtris, could you give,</l>
                  <l>All <hi>Paris,</hi> for Joynture; The truth is I am engaged.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Sir Rev.</speaker>
                  <p>Begar den you ſhall be no Lady.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Splend.</speaker>
                  <p>I ſhall be contented with my fortune.</p>
                  <stage>
                     <hi>Enter to them</hi> Nice <hi>and</hi> Wildfire.</stage>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Nice.</speaker>
                  <p>How is't Sir <hi>Reverence,</hi> what is my daughter plyant,</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Sir Rev.</speaker>
                  <p>Begar your dauter ſay ſhe will no have me, if I Shall give all <hi>Pary</hi> for a zhoynture.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Nice.</speaker>
                  <l>You muſt give Virgins licenſe to be Nice,</l>
                  <l>Things eaſily purchaſed are not valuable,</l>
                  <l>Is it their own worth or their ſcarcity,</l>
                  <l>That ſets ſo high a price on Jewells think you.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Sir Rev.</speaker>
                  <p>Begar your dauter be fooliſh to ſlight me, She bid me love de frenſh Lady, begar ſo me can.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Nice.</speaker>
                  <p>I hope ſhe hath not angerd you Sir <hi>Reverence.</hi>
                  </p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Sir Rev.</speaker>
                  <p>Begar is vill know me can have de brave Lady in <hi>France.</hi>
                  </p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Nice.</speaker>
                  <p>I do not queſtion't Sir, ſhe is too peeviſh.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Sir Re.</speaker>
                  <l>Begar me have ſcorn a Counteſſe in <hi>France,</hi> and</l>
                  <l>Have had two three love letter from a Douſheſſe,</l>
                  <l>Since I came to <hi>Englant,</hi> your dauter no know</l>
                  <l>Vat J am, ſhe be foole beggar — <hi>Vildfire.</hi>
                  </l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Wild.</speaker>
                  <p>Monſieur.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Sir Re.</speaker>
                  <p>Donne moy me manteau.</p>
                  <stage>Gives him his Cloake.</stage>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Wild.</speaker>
                  <p>Awy Monſieur voſtre ſervice.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Nice.</speaker>
                  <p>I hope you will not leave us ſo Sir.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Sir Re.</speaker>
                  <p>Begar me vill ſtay no longer your dauter a ſcorn my love.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Nice.</speaker>
                  <p>Be not ſo diſcontented good Sir <hi>Rev.</hi> all ſhall be to your wiſh, I have prepar'd a courſe banquet for you Sir <hi>Rev.</hi>
                  </p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Sir Rev.</speaker>
                  <p>She ſcorn a my love.</p>
               </sp>
               <stage>Ex. omnes, manet Splend.</stage>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Splend.</speaker>
                  <l>This fool it ſeems is noted to be rich,</l>
                  <l>
                     <pb facs="tcp:114636:10"/>What's that to me? In dignity a Knight,</l>
                  <l>A Knight Sir Reverence, then he is of <hi>France,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>The onely man of faſhion (from whoſe Countrey</l>
                  <l>All things are acceptable, no diſeaſe excepted)</l>
                  <l>Let him go ſeek a choiſe in his own Nation,</l>
                  <l>French feats grow ſtale, I'le have ſome newer faſhion;</l>
                  <l>I'le learn to love for worth, not one whoſe flaſhes</l>
                  <l>Blaze much, and are at one time flame and aſhes,</l>
                  <l>Give me a man whoſe love is built upon</l>
                  <l>Eternal vertue and perfection,</l>
                  <l>Who loves for mental worth, not outward ſhow,</l>
                  <l>And ſuch a one is my <hi>Mercurio.</hi>
                  </l>
               </sp>
            </div>
            <div n="2" type="act">
               <head>Actus ſecundus, Scaena prima.</head>
               <stage>Enter Drowzy and Trimwel.</stage>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Trimw.</speaker>
                  <p>Art ſure thou ſawſt them go this way?</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Drow.</speaker>
                  <p>Sure, yes ſure enough, I'm ſure they croſs'd this field, went o're that ſtile, and I am much deceived if I did not ſee <hi>Pimpwel</hi> peep out of yonder Tavern window.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Trimw.</speaker>
                  <l>That's the Kings-head I know't,</l>
                  <l>Oh for ſome queint diſguiſe,</l>
                  <l>My jealouſie hath yet no occular proof,</l>
                  <l>Theſe two years have I wandred in this maze,</l>
                  <l>And ſtill been blinded by her ſublil ſleights?</l>
                  <l>That <hi>Rivers</hi> is the man I moſt ſuſpect,</l>
                  <l>And yet I dare not think he wrongs my bed,</l>
                  <l>The very thought bred in a jealous breaſt,</l>
                  <l>Is proof enough, and then were he defenc'd</l>
                  <l>With Devils I would end him;</l>
                  <l>Oh! we vain men covet moſt to ſee</l>
                  <l>What we would not, my eyes can take no reſt;</l>
                  <l>How many Moonſhine nights and Summer evenings,</l>
                  <l>In various ſhapes have I walkt out to find her,</l>
                  <l>But never could?</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <pb facs="tcp:114636:11"/>
                  <speaker>Drow.</speaker>
                  <p>Would I had never ſeen the face of Mr. <hi>Flylove.</hi>
                  </p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Trim.</speaker>
                  <l>Thou haſt even got, thy belly full of miſchief too,</l>
                  <l>But prethe do not cry out i'th fields, though I'm</l>
                  <l>A Surgeon, I ſhall make but a mad midwife,</l>
                  <l>Thou hadſt better repare to the City, and quietly,</l>
                  <l>For a month hire the next Cage is to be let, you</l>
                  <l>May buy a bed in Smith-feild, they come to Town,</l>
                  <l>In Cart-loads.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Drow.</speaker>
                  <l>No Sir, I know you'l lend me a room for one month,</l>
                  <l>I'le enquier for your houſe when I come to <hi>London,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>How farr do you live from Cuckolds haven.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Trim.</speaker>
                  <p>A pox on you for a whore, you have wit enough to jeer though you had not to keep your Maiden-head.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Drow.</speaker>
                  <l>I pray Sir, is it not your black bird that ſings,</l>
                  <l>J cannot keep my wife at home, my wife at home.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Trim.</speaker>
                  <p>Out you greazy kitchen whore.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Drow.</speaker>
                  <p>Why thou foole, is not better to have ſuch a Greazy piece as I am, then to have a curious fine wife, and cannot come neer her.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Trimwel.</speaker>
                  <l>The whore ſayes true, how now who comes here,</l>
                  <l>Muſitians very good, I have a plot,</l>
                  <l>Come into my head, which by theſe fidlers,</l>
                  <stage>
                     <hi>Enter</hi> 5. <hi>or</hi> 6. <hi>Fidlers.</hi>
                  </stage>
                  <l>Meanes I'le put in practiſe, hark you,</l>
                  <l>Honeſt Fidlers (Muſitians I ſhould call you)</l>
                  <l>I am a little Muſicall my ſelf, Gentlemen</l>
                  <l>Whither Croud you ſo faſt.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Fidlers.</speaker>
                  <p>Sir we are ſent for to play to Mr. <hi>Rivers</hi> at the Kings-head.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Trim.</speaker>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Frank Rivers.</hi>
                  </p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Fid.</speaker>
                  <p>The ſame Sir.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Trim.</speaker>
                  <p>Who playes the Citterne.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Boy.</speaker>
                  <p>That do I Sir.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Trim.</speaker>
                  <p>Very good, I have a plot that ſhall get you double the mony you expect.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Fid.</speaker>
                  <p>How is that I pray Sir.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Trim.</speaker>
                  <p>Why look, <hi>Franke Rivers</hi> is my only Companion, I would now ſteale upon him in the middle of's mirth diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guiſed like one of you, I have a falſe beard in my pocket, I'le carry the Baſe, counterfeit to be blind, and that boy ſhall lead me, and in the concluſion he ſhall pay you for the jeſt.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <pb facs="tcp:114636:11"/>
                  <speaker>Fid.</speaker>
                  <p>With all our hearts Sir.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Trim.</speaker>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Drowzy</hi> what will you do?</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Drow.</speaker>
                  <p>Ile even home to <hi>London,</hi> but if you ſee Mr. <hi>Flyloeve</hi> tell him I'le ſerve him ſuch a trick as he ſaw in's life time, I'le warrant him.</p>
               </sp>
               <stage>Exit.</stage>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Trim.</speaker>
                  <p>Farewell good <hi>Drowzy.</hi> Come Gentlemen let's a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bout this buſineſs; Aha wife, yfaith I ſhall over-reach you now.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Sings.</speaker>
                  <l>
                     <hi>I have been a Fidler theſe fifteen year,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>And never was put in the Stocks before,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>If an good fellow will give me ſome Beer,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>I'le Fiddle and fuddle, and ner'e give o're.</hi>
                  </l>
               </sp>
               <stage>Exit.</stage>
               <stage>Actus ſecundus, Scaena prima.</stage>
               <stage>Enter Rivers, Wildblood, Flylove, Mrs. Bellaflora, and Mrs. Trimwell.</stage>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Fly.</speaker>
                  <p>Fair Lady you are welcome, I ſhoul ſalute you by your name if I knew it.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Bella.</speaker>
                  <p>My name is <hi>Mary Fair-chaſte.</hi>
                  </p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Fly.</speaker>
                  <p>Fair and chaſt too, impoſſible; it is a Paradox to me.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Bella.</speaker>
                  <p>Is it ſuch wonder to be fair and chaſte Sir?</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Fly.</speaker>
                  <p>No, no, 'tis no ſuch wonder, A fair Cabinet ſhould contain a fair Jewel; but ſince we have had poyſon in guilt bowls, killing Perfumes in rich Gloves, Hereſie in religious exact habit, and Treaſon in the well-ſeeming gravity of State, we put ſmall truſt in form; but what do I trouble you with theſe things, let's drink, ſing, dance, and be merry boyes;</p>
                  <l>
                     <hi>We come to be merry,</hi> &amp;c. <stage>Sings.</stage>
                  </l>
               </sp>
               <p>Gentlemen, what ſhall we do for anoyſe of Vagrants, I have a dancing deſire to exerciſe my heels.</p>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Wild.</speaker>
                  <p>I have ſent for Muſick, but we want a woman.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Fly.</speaker>
                  <p>Its impoſſible; Drawer.</p>
                  <stage>Ent. Draw.</stage>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Draw.</speaker>
                  <p>Did you call Sir?</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Fly.</speaker>
                  <p>Intreat your Miſtris hither.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <pb facs="tcp:114636:12"/>
                  <speaker>Draw.</speaker>
                  <p>I ſhal Sir, ſhe prevents my ſervice, ſhe's here already.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Fly.</speaker>
                  <p>How doth my Madona? my Belladoſſa? my <hi>Ent. Mrs.</hi> Sommer ſinner, the Connteſſe of <hi>Hogſdowne.</hi>
                  </p>
               </sp>
               <stage>Exit Drawer.</stage>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Mrs.</speaker>
                  <p>You give me many ſtiles Mr. <hi>Flylove.</hi>
                  </p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Fly.</speaker>
                  <p>I have come over as many more ſtiles to behold thee my Queen of the Kings-head. Hark you; what rate holds womens fleſh? in breif haſt thou ever a peice of Impenitence, that will be ſociable, and will deſire, only her pleaſure for her paines, if ſhe can dance well, wee'l bear with any im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perfection elſe; thou ſhalt not loſe all; wee'l ſeem to want the knowledg of thy over-reckoning, and pay thee. You know we are noe Cittizens, that (to eaſe our bodies and pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerve our pockets) keep a due Accompt of every quart and paper, by unbuttoning our doublets; or doubt our own me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mories by calling many reckonings at one ſitting.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Mrs.</speaker>
                  <p>You are very merry Mr. <hi>Flylove,</hi> but as I am a vertu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous ſinner, you could never have choſe a time to have found me ſo unprovided in a whole ſummer, there is but one wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man in the houſe, and ſhe is with a French man, yet I believe his greateſt buſineſs is over, if you will allow of his company you may have hers, nor will he be any interruption to you, for call what you will he'l pay freely, and be as merry as you will give him leave.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Fly.</speaker>
                  <p>Have they paid all?</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Mrs.</speaker>
                  <p>They are now calling.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Fly.</speaker>
                  <p>Prethe entice them in.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Mrs.</speaker>
                  <p>No twill become you better, he may conceive I have ſome end of mine own in't; your way of invitation will in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tice him, the ſociety of an Engliſh Gentleman, is his only ambition.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Fly.</speaker>
                  <p>Very well; I'le invite him.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Rivers.</speaker>
                  <p>Whither go you <hi>Stephen?</hi>
                  </p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Bella.</speaker>
                  <p>Sir I'le take my leave of you.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Fly.</speaker>
                  <p>By no means Lady, I'le return preſently, <hi>aſide. Jack Wildblood</hi> prethee entertain this Lady in my abſence, ſhe's modeſt, &amp; thou art civil; but if you make your ſeeming civility a bawd to abuſe me, look to your ſelf.</p>
               </sp>
               <stage>
                  <hi>Ex. Fly.</hi> &amp; <hi>Mrs.</hi>
               </stage>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Wild.</speaker>
                  <p>Well, well, pray follow your humor; Lady you are not merry.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <pb facs="tcp:114636:12"/>
                  <speaker>Bella.</speaker>
                  <p>Is the Gentleman your friend gone?</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Wild.</speaker>
                  <p>Some private occaſion, he'l be here ſuddenly.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Bella.</speaker>
                  <p>I cannot ſtay Sir.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Pimp.</speaker>
                  <p>Mr. <hi>Rivers;</hi> what is Mr. <hi>Flylove</hi> gone?</p>
                  <stage>Enter Pimpw.</stage>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Wild.</speaker>
                  <p>where's the Muſick?</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Pimp.</speaker>
                  <p>I have been as far as <hi>Redcroſſe-ſtreet</hi> for them, they were playing to a company of Cittizens at the Queens-head, but they told me they would make all the neceſſary expedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion they could poſſible, and attend you in <hi>Hogsdon</hi> here at the Kings-head.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Rivers.</speaker>
                  <p>Nay, I'le ſay that for thee, thou art the happieſt Purveyor for Wine, Wenches and Muſick, that ever was aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiſtant to the increaſe of ſinners.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Pimpw.</speaker>
                  <p>Who ſhould I meet withall coming from thence, through the Fortune-Playhouſe yard, but old <hi>Jones</hi> the Cobl.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Wild.</speaker>
                  <p>Thou ſhouldſt have brought him hither.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Pimp.</speaker>
                  <p>I thought you would have Wiſh'd ſo, and I have brought him.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Rivers.</speaker>
                  <p>A Cobler; what is he?</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Wild.</speaker>
                  <p>What is he? why the rareſt humoriſt of a Cobler, that ever was tranſlated into merry company, his wit is jeering, tart in all ſuch jeaſts, nor will he ſpare the proudeſt he in pluſh. And ſpeaking in a moſt compoſed ſtrain, with countnance grave, no man can take exceptions, but may ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe it ignorance, not wit; You cannot chuſe but know him, that is he that owed fourty ſhillings to an Allderman, to pay 12. pence by the week, when he did exact Coblers law, and made his worſhipful creditor give him two pots at every payment.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Riv.</speaker>
                  <p>Yes, yes, I have heard of him.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Pimp.</speaker>
                  <p>Then now you ſhall ſee him, here comes the man in Perſon; welcome Mr. <hi>Jones.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <stage>Enter Jones.</stage>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Jones.</speaker>
                  <p>Thank you good Mr. <hi>Allexander,</hi> I'le make bold to ſalute theſe worthy Gentlemen, noble Mr. <hi>Wildblood,</hi> I take it.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Wild.</speaker>
                  <p>The very ſame Mr. <hi>Jones,</hi> and how did Mr. <hi>Alexander,</hi> and you meet.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Jones.</speaker>
                  <p>Honeſt Mr. <hi>Pimpwell</hi> (here) was walking I believe
<pb facs="tcp:114636:13"/>about his accaſions, I ſaw 2. or 3. Gentlemen with him, and introth becauſe I was in my workydaie Clothes, I was aſhamed to ſpeak with him, but I thank him good Gen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tleman, he call'd me to him, and told me I ſhould ſee ſome worthy Gentlemen of my acquaintance.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Wild.</speaker>
                  <p>Here Mr. <hi>Jones,</hi> I'le drink to you and to your wife, do you remember ſince you put her i'th cage?</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Jones.</speaker>
                  <p>I pray Sir how long is't ſince we <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ere merry at the Sargeons head in <hi>Iſlington,</hi> where we drank Sack ſo long till all our mony was gone, but introth I think I brought but a groat with me; we came off from the reckoning though prety handſomly, but good Gentleman you were forc'd to leave your ſilver Seal behinde, but I think you redeemed it again in a little while.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Rivers.</speaker>
                  <p>Ha, ha, ha, there he hath met you <hi>Jack.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <stage>Enter Flylove, Sir Reverence, Lamard, and Mrs. Light.</stage>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Fly.</speaker>
                  <p>Gentlemen I preſume to invite this worthy Gentle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man and his Lady, I pray be courteous to them.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Wild.</speaker>
                  <p>Noble Sir, a friend of yours can never come unwel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come where we are; my ſervice Sir attends you.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Sir Re.</speaker>
                  <p>Monſieur your tres nmble umble vaſſale.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Rivers.</speaker>
                  <p>Sir according to our downright Engliſh Comple<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment you are welcome.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>
                     <hi>Sir</hi> R.</speaker>
                  <p>Awee Monſieur, begar me tanke you heartely dere be Engliſh Complement for you agen, vat velow's dat?</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Wild.</speaker>
                  <p>A very honeſt man Sir, and Beadle of the pariſh.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>
                     <hi>Sir</hi> R.</speaker>
                  <p>A beadle, begar he be no forboon company, my Madam can no endure a beadle.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Jones.</speaker>
                  <p>Alack good Gentlewoman; no Sir, I am no beadle I can aſſure you, though the Gentleman pleaſes to jeaſt.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>
                     <hi>Sir</hi> R.</speaker>
                  <p>Begar you look as like a rogua as a beadle.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Jones.</speaker>
                  <p>Alack, I believe Monſieur you have heard the ill newes lately come forth you are ſo angry of the ſudden.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>
                     <hi>Sir</hi> R.</speaker>
                  <p>Begar me have hear no ill news.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Jones.</speaker>
                  <p>then I'le tell you Sir, the ſad report goes that moſt of the Engliſh Gentlemen in <hi>France</hi> muſt return to England agen, I am ſorry for't.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>
                     <hi>Sir</hi> R.</speaker>
                  <p>Begar vas nothing but lies; how how vat is here, Fiddles? Madam ſall we dance?</p>
               </sp>
               <stage>
                  <pb facs="tcp:114636:13"/>
                  <hi>Enter Muſitians, amongſt them, Trimwel diſguiſed like an old blind Fidler, and led in by a boy.</hi>
               </stage>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Wild.</speaker>
                  <p>Well done, you are honeſt Raſcalls, every man take his ſtool, ſtrike up couragiouſly, and be ſure have a ſpeciall care he that plays oth' baſe Violin ſleep not, we are no colls you know, you muſt not flam us.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Riv.</speaker>
                  <p>Come Gentlemen ſhall we try our footing, here am I.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Fly.</speaker>
                  <p>And here am I.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Wild.</speaker>
                  <p>And if this Gentleman pleaſe, here I'le be.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Sir Rev.</speaker>
                  <p>Vould all mine heart Monſieur.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Bella.</speaker>
                  <p>I cannot dance believe me Sir.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Fly.</speaker>
                  <p>Nor I, we'l onely practiſe.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Mrs. Light.</speaker>
                  <p>Excuſe me Sir, indeed I cannot dance.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Wild.</speaker>
                  <p>Excuſe me Sir, indeed <hi>I</hi> cannot dance? You ſhall not dance excuſe me then, that Country trip is old, we'l have ſome novelty.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Riv.</speaker>
                  <p>Are you perfect in the tune I gave you laſt to practiſe.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Fidlers.</speaker>
                  <p>Very perfect Sir.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Rivers.</speaker>
                  <p>Let me hear it.</p>
                  <stage>They play the tune once over.</stage>
                  <stage>They dance the tune once over, then enter into a figure with, the beginning of the firſt ſtrain, Pimpwel and the Mrs. betwixt every change two perſons drink till it comes round, and Pimpw. diſcovers trimw. in the Dance, and at the end of ſeveral Changes he de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clares his diſcovery.</stage>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Pimpw.</speaker>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Mrs. Trimwel</hi> do you obſerve that old fellow that plays oth' Baſe.</p>
                  <stage>firſt Change. Wildb. and his Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtris drink.</stage>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Mrs. Trimw.</speaker>
                  <p>Well, what of that?</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Pimpw.</speaker>
                  <p>By my life 'tis your Husband.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Mrs. Trim.</speaker>
                  <p>My Husband?</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Pimpw.</speaker>
                  <p>Take no notice.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Wild.</speaker>
                  <p>Come t'other Change.</p>
                  <stage>
                     <hi>They dance, at the end of the next Change</hi> Flyl. <hi>and his Mrs. drink.</hi>
                  </stage>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Fly.</speaker>
                  <p>Lady my ſervice to you.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Bella.</speaker>
                  <p>Pray let it be your love Sir, Twill make the Health much ſweeter.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Rivers.</speaker>
                  <p>Thou mak'ſt me wonder.</p>
                  <stage>At the end of the next Change Mrs. Trim. and Rives drink.</stage>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Mrs. Trim.</speaker>
                  <p>As I live 'tis true.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Rivers.</speaker>
                  <p>What? he that plays the Baſe?</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Fly.</speaker>
                  <p>Come to the next.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <pb facs="tcp:114636:14"/>
                  <speaker>Trim.</speaker>
                  <p>Here is ſtrange humours in this <stage>This laſt Change Pimpw. and the Miſtris drink.</stage> Dance, how they drink and whiſper, as if they had capering minds as well as bodies; Hey! I how my wife trips it, when ſhe comes home ſhe was with one Aunt or other; She's no Tavern-dan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cing company, no, no; Oh my bleſt diſguiſe.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Pimw.</speaker>
                  <p>Oh your Bulls-head, we'l take a courſe to order you, you blind puppy, becauſe you wink you think no bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy can ſee you; Come the tother Change, and conclude.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Sir Rev.</speaker>
                  <p>Begar vas moſe brave, my <stage>They dance the laſt Change of all.</stage> Lady dance al lemode like our Frenſh Madam.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Jones.</speaker>
                  <p>Introth Mr. <hi>Flylove</hi> you dance very well, but that you ſtraddle ſo much, but if you take it in time that may be altered; Oh Mr. <hi>Flylove</hi> you have a little gone awry, but mum for that.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Fly.</speaker>
                  <p>Well ſaid Mr. <hi>Jones,</hi> do you remember one night when you caſt Anchor ith' kennel, and call'd to the Goldfinder for a Coach, who mounted you in his Chariot, and drew you to the River <hi>Acharon</hi> at the back-ſide of <hi>Iſlington.</hi>
                  </p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Jones.</speaker>
                  <p>Oh! Mr. <hi>Flylove</hi> you are an ingenious Gentleman, I have heard high commendations of you by a Neighbours daughter a friend of mine.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Fly.</speaker>
                  <p>Prethee who's that?</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Jones.</speaker>
                  <p>'Tis a very good natur'd Laſs, if ſhe knew you were here, ſhe would have a quart of Wine at your ſervice.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Fly.</speaker>
                  <p>Do I know her?</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Jones.</speaker>
                  <p>Do you know her? Do I know <hi>Jone</hi> my wife? Do not you know <hi>Alice Drowzy?</hi>
                  </p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Fly.</speaker>
                  <p>Pox on you hold your tongue, this dirty whore hants me in a thouſand ſhapes, I muſt throw her out of my memory. Come Gentlemen ſhall we have another Dance?</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Rivers.</speaker>
                  <p>Come Gentlemen t'other Dance.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Sir Rev.</speaker>
                  <p>I come, me like de Dance better den Song.</p>
                  <stage>
                     <hi>They all dance to a ſprightly Ayr, but in the fourth
<pb facs="tcp:114636:14"/>Change they all dance off from the Stage into the Tyring<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>houſe, where they remain till the tune it plaid once over; then they dance all in again, and come to their ſeverall Figures, and continue dancing the tune once more over; then they dance in and out again as before; At the laſt they Dance quite away from the houſe, leaving the Fidlers to play to the Monſieur, Mr.</hi> Jones, <hi>and themſelvs; having played an unreaſonable while, they deſiſt, and the Mon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſieur ſpeaks.</hi>
                  </stage>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Sir Rev.</speaker>
                  <p>Hold, hold good Monſieur Minikin, for begar dey have dance avay wid my Ladce; Rogue, Drawer. <hi>Ent. Draw.</hi>
                  </p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Draw.</speaker>
                  <p>Anon, anon Sir.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Sir Rev.</speaker>
                  <p>Fere be de Zhentlemen and de Ladce.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Draw.</speaker>
                  <p>They have taken Coach Sir, and are at <hi>London</hi> by this time.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Fidlers.</speaker>
                  <p>How? how?</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Sir Rev.</speaker>
                  <p>Begar me never ſaw ſuſh a frisk in my life; Vas dis de skip de Angleteire?</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Drawer.</speaker>
                  <p>I was bid to deliver this Note to him that plays on the Baſe?</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Trim.</speaker>
                  <p>To me? give me't.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Draw.</speaker>
                  <p>Yes, they ſay your ill fidling made them all dance quite away, they would have ſtaid longer elſe.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Trim.</speaker>
                  <p>The Devils have unridled me; what's here?</p>
                  <stage>Trim. reads.</stage>
                  <l>
                     <hi>The Woodcock when his head is hid,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Thinks his body is unſpid;</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Fool when thou comeſt next to find us,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Bring ſome better trick to blind us;</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Pay the reckning, or you'l finde,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>There's a worſer plot behinde.</hi>
                  </l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Jones.</speaker>
                  <p>What have you there Sir, a Bill of Exchange?</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Trim.</speaker>
                  <p>Pox on your Cobling jeaſts, <stage>Trimwell pulls off his grey beard.</stage> you quibling Coxcombe I am undone for ever.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <pb facs="tcp:114636:15"/>
                  <speaker>Sir Rev.</speaker>
                  <p>Begar de Fidler be mad, he tear his hair off.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Jones.</speaker>
                  <p>Who's this? My old acquaintance Mr. <hi>Trimwel.</hi>
                  </p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Trimw.</speaker>
                  <p>Hang up your old acquaintance, do not trouble me, who would have thought that through this diſguiſe their careleſs eyes ſhould thus diſcover me, but I'le follow them as cloſe as Death doth ſin.</p>
                  <stage>Offers to go off.</stage>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Draw.</speaker>
                  <p>Sir you muſt pay the Reckoning firſt.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Trim.</speaker>
                  <p>Shall I.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Draw.</speaker>
                  <p>Before you part, it is your device hath made us loſe the beſt Gueſts that come to our houſe.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Trim.</speaker>
                  <p>How much is it?</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Draw.</speaker>
                  <p>One pound thirteen and nine pence.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Trim.</speaker>
                  <p>Here's the French Knight, one of their company that call'd it in, let him diſcharge it.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Sir Rev.</speaker>
                  <p>Diſharge it, begar my Lady <stage>The Frenchman feels in's pockets.</stage> have left me noting to diſharge, ſhe got all my mony and my Waſh.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Jones.</speaker>
                  <p>Gentlemen, I'le go pay my part at the bar.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Draw.</speaker>
                  <p>Your part, what's that?</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Jones.</speaker>
                  <p>A three-pence, a good three-pence, a Spaniſh 3. d. and ſo farewell to you both good Gent.</p>
               </sp>
               <stage>Ex. Jones.</stage>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Trim.</speaker>
                  <p>Well, there's your mony Drawer, I muſt confeſs I drank for't.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Fidlers.</speaker>
                  <p>Who ſhall pay us Sir?</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Trim.</speaker>
                  <p>The Devil pay't, ſhall I be made a But for every knave to ſhoot at.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Fidlers.</speaker>
                  <p>Sir, you are the cauſe that we have not only loſt this mony, but our credit with the Gentlemen, if we had known you had been a Trapan, you ſhould ne'r have been admitted into our company; you had other pretences.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Trim.</speaker>
                  <p>Well, ſince 'twas my plot, I am like to pay for't, there's a French crown among you, pray get you from me. Sir, you are a ſtranger, and therefore I <stage>Exeunt Fidlers.</stage> have nothing more to ſay to you, but to deſire your abſence.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Sir Rev.</speaker>
                  <p>Mee bee glad mee come off ſo, farewel Monſieur Bo-peep.</p>
               </sp>
               <stage>Exit Sir Rev.</stage>
               <stage>Trimwel ſolus.</stage>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Trim.</speaker>
                  <l>The juſt cauſe of my fears I now perceive,</l>
                  <l>
                     <pb facs="tcp:114636:15"/>As evident as day-light; in this Dance</l>
                  <l>There is compos'd all that her wanton heart</l>
                  <l>Can give, or he can covet, I muſt now</l>
                  <l>Turn all my love to loathing; Sweet Revenge</l>
                  <l>I am thy faithful Votary, I will ſtill</l>
                  <l>Purſue their foot-ſteps, and with wary eyes,</l>
                  <l>Watch their Adulterous Conſpiracies:</l>
                  <l>Now I have thought upon't, if they defend</l>
                  <l>Their perſons from this plot I now intend,</l>
                  <l>I will disband my reaſon, and reſign</l>
                  <l>My Intellectuals, or what elſe is mine:</l>
                  <l>Look to it Gallants, the next time you view me,</l>
                  <l>I'le make you curſe the time that e're you knew me.</l>
               </sp>
            </div>
            <div n="3" type="act">
               <head>Actus tertius,</head>
               <div n="1" type="scene">
                  <head>Scaena prima.</head>
                  <stage>Enter Mercurio and Splendora.</stage>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Mercu.</speaker>
                     <l>Time and our fitter opportunity,</l>
                     <l>The pleaſant entertainment of our love</l>
                     <l>Hath almoſt waſted; 'tis an hour neer night,</l>
                     <l>And we can tread no farther then to'th place</l>
                     <l>Thy Father hath expell'd me, we muſt part,</l>
                     <l>But urg'd to't with much more unwillingneſs,</l>
                     <l>Then heat from life, when ſouls and bodies ſeperate.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Splend.</speaker>
                     <l>Thou ſhalt not leave me yet, I'le plant my love</l>
                     <l>Above my fear, it is a nobler paſſion,</l>
                     <l>Nor ſhall my fathers frown have more command</l>
                     <l>On my affection, then thy brow, made ſmooth</l>
                     <l>By thy own love, credit me gentle youth,</l>
                     <l>Thou haſt next rule in this weak manſion</l>
                     <l>To him that built it.</l>
                     <stage>Ent. Nice. Sir Rev. Trimwel and two Serjeants.</stage>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Nice.</speaker>
                     <p>That's he.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>1. <hi>Ser.</hi>
                     </speaker>
                     <p>We know him Sir.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Nice.</speaker>
                     <p>Perform your task then.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>2. <hi>Ser.</hi>
                     </speaker>
                     <p>I'le warrant you.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Sir Rev.</speaker>
                     <p>Begar me have waſh him hither, now me ſall be revenge.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Nice.</speaker>
                     <p>Stay not for bayl, I'le double your reward.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <pb facs="tcp:114636:16"/>
                     <speaker>1. <hi>Ser.</hi>
                     </speaker>
                     <p>You are a kind Gentleman: Sir we arreſt you by the name of <hi>Mercurio.</hi>
                     </p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Merc.</speaker>
                     <p>Arreſt me Sir, who hath employ'd you for this Action? At whoſe ſuit is't?</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>2. <hi>Ser.</hi>
                     </speaker>
                     <p>At the Suit of Mr. <hi>Nice,</hi> a very honeſt Gentleman I can aſſure you.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Merc.</speaker>
                     <p>You gueſs that by his bounty for your baſeneſs: What is the ſum?</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>1. <hi>Ser.</hi>
                     </speaker>
                     <p>Twenty pounds upon bond, if you have ſpeciall Bayl, produce it preſently, we cannot ſtay.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Merc.</speaker>
                     <p>Why is your time ſo precious that is ſpent to ruine man-kind, be not pray ſo haſty, where is the Gentleman?</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>2. <hi>Ser.</hi>
                     </speaker>
                     <p>He is not far Sir.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Nice.</speaker>
                     <p>What is your wil with me.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Merc.</speaker>
                     <p>Longer time for payment of your debt.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Nice.</speaker>
                     <p>I may forbear no longer, Sir you know the mony hath been due theſe 14. weeks, it is in vain to think you can urge me to an agreement, but my preſent ſum.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Splend.</speaker>
                     <p>But not, I intreat that mercy Sir.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Nice.</speaker>
                     <p>Fond Girl ask mercy for your diſodedience, I have appear'd too temperate with you, and ſhown too much in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dulgence; 'tis your cauſe that makes him ſuffer.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Splend.</speaker>
                     <l>And 'tis his abuſe</l>
                     <l>Will make me periſh; Oh remember Sir</l>
                     <l>You had a wife, my Mother, whoſe dear duſt</l>
                     <l>With low and humble reverence I kiſs:</l>
                     <l>Had you been ſeiz'd between two Tygers thus,</l>
                     <l>Would't not have mov'd her, made her plyant knees</l>
                     <l>Grow toth' dull earth, till the deaf Creditor,</l>
                     <l>(By importunacy more then compunction)</l>
                     <l>Had ſeal'd a truce 'twixt him and's undone Debtor.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Nice.</speaker>
                     <l>Your ſuperſtitious knees in vain are bent</l>
                     <l>For this bad cauſe, Laws Moral and Divine,</l>
                     <l>Have ſtill provided that each man ſhall claim</l>
                     <l>What is his right, I but exact mine own.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Splend.</speaker>
                     <l>What can you call your own, that you may ſpare,</l>
                     <l>Whilſt ſtill the cryes of widdows, injur'd Orphans</l>
                     <l>Beat at the ears of pitty; had this man</l>
                     <l>(Trapt in the ſnares of Canibals) his own</l>
                     <l>
                        <pb facs="tcp:114636:16"/>The fair inheritance his birthright claims,</l>
                     <l>(Heaven pardon them that have it) I believe</l>
                     <l>You need not rack his body for your owne.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Nice.</speaker>
                     <p>Your zeal makes you forget your ſelf.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Splend.</speaker>
                     <l>My ſorrow is too bold indeed, to ſee</l>
                     <l>Such pregnant hopes thus blaſted in the bloom</l>
                     <l>Of teeming growth, nipt in the ſpringing bud</l>
                     <l>Of ſpreading youth; to ſee mans ſpan contracted,</l>
                     <l>Sent to the grave e're yet he can conceive</l>
                     <l>The end of his Creation, 'cauſe his Cheſts</l>
                     <l>Want coyn, not to ſupply, but cram anothers:</l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Joves</hi> great impreſſion ſuffers this decay,</l>
                     <l>For want of <hi>Caeſar<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap>
                        </hi> Image ſtampt in Clay.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Nice.</speaker>
                     <p>I'le hear no more.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Splend.</speaker>
                     <l>A little pray Sir,</l>
                     <l>He that's ſo indigent to want the means</l>
                     <l>Of rendring your right, whilſt he enjoys</l>
                     <l>His fair and open freedom; Can you believe,</l>
                     <l>That being cloſe pent up with Iron barrs,</l>
                     <l>Stone walls and Jaylors hearts,</l>
                     <l>Where every cowardly Creditor treads down,</l>
                     <l>The o'rethrown Debtor with a doubled ſum,</l>
                     <l>That ſtands bayl-proof; is that a time to ſatisfie,</l>
                     <l>Unleſs he had the Elixor to convert</l>
                     <l>The Iron grates to Gold, or (which is beſt)</l>
                     <l>To nothing.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Nice.</speaker>
                     <p>Officers what ſtay you for?</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>1. <hi>Ser.</hi>
                     </speaker>
                     <p>Come will you go Sir.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Splend.</speaker>
                     <l>How diligent in cruelty you are:</l>
                     <l>Have you the heart to think this good old man</l>
                     <l>(That knows the ſcales unto Eternity</l>
                     <l>Are pitty, mercy, love (the beſt Religion)</l>
                     <l>Fear of oppreſſion) will commit his youth</l>
                     <l>To your ungentle uſage?</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>2. <hi>Ser.</hi>
                     </speaker>
                     <p>Pray be not mov'd with us, your father may re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leaſe him.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Splend.</speaker>
                     <l>Look Sir, the Officers grow merciful,</l>
                     <l>And ſeem to bear no part in his undoing;</l>
                     <l>Shall men that ſtudy nought but cruelty,</l>
                     <l>Out-doe you in an act of gentleneſs?</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <pb facs="tcp:114636:17"/>
                     <speaker>Nice.</speaker>
                     <p>Officers, I'le leave him to your charge, take Bayle at your peril.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <stage>Exit Nice.</stage>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Splend.</speaker>
                     <p>
                        <hi>Sir Reverence,</hi> will you be bayl for him, you are good for nothing elſe.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Sir Rev.</speaker>
                     <p>Begar me be no bayl.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <stage>Exit Sir Rev.</stage>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Splend.</speaker>
                     <p>There's a day for thee when no bayl ſhalbe taken; Shall I ſpeak one word with your Priſoner?</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>1. <hi>Ser.</hi>
                     </speaker>
                     <p>Two if you pleaſe.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Trim.</speaker>
                     <p>Hark you Mr. <hi>Tripes,</hi> I ſhal find you at the Compter gate.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>2. <hi>Ser.</hi>
                     </speaker>
                     <p>Without fail.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Trim.</speaker>
                     <p>I have another miſchievous imployment for you.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>1. <hi>Ser.</hi>
                     </speaker>
                     <p>We ſhall endeavour to perform it Sir.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Trim.</speaker>
                     <p>Oh Sir, I know you to be deſerving men; there's money, enter an Action againſt <hi>Stephen Flylove</hi> at the ſuit of <hi>Alice Drowzy</hi> in an Action of aſſault and battery committed upon the belly of the ſaid <hi>Alice</hi> laſt <hi>May,</hi> the Planets being <hi>Venus</hi> and <hi>Mars</hi> Rampant, and the Sign <hi>Virgo.</hi>
                     </p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>2. <hi>Ser.</hi>
                     </speaker>
                     <p>I apprehend you Sir.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Trim.</speaker>
                     <p>Apprehend me Sir, for what? you are deceived, you muſt apprehend Mr. <hi>Flylove.</hi>
                     </p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>2. <hi>Ser.</hi>
                     </speaker>
                     <p>I underſtand you Sir.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Trim.</speaker>
                     <p>Farewel my underſtanding Serjeant,</p>
                  </sp>
                  <stage>Exit.</stage>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Merc.</speaker>
                     <p>Come we muſt part.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Splend.</speaker>
                     <p>I'l come and viſit thee.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Merc.</speaker>
                     <p>Thy ſight in priſon is my liberty.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <stage>Ex. ſeveral ways.</stage>
               </div>
               <div n="2" type="scene">
                  <head>Act. <hi>3.</hi> Scaen. <hi>2.</hi>
                  </head>
                  <stage>Enter Stephen Flylove and Bellaflora.</stage>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Fly.</speaker>
                     <p>Can you conceit why I have ſingled you thus from the company.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Bella.</speaker>
                     <p>No, pray inſtruct me Sir.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Fly.</speaker>
                     <p>The inſtructions are too eaſie to be good, ſince you appear ſo innocently modeſt; I'le be your amorous School<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maſter for once.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Bella.</speaker>
                     <p>You'l teach me no ill Doctrine.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Fly.</speaker>
                     <p>No, no, prethee obſerve me, be but capable, and I'le warrant thee an apt Scholler.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Bella.</speaker>
                     <p>Well-Sir, ſo far as I perceive it's good, I'le learn.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Fly.</speaker>
                     <p>I'le ſhew you the Lovers Alphabet, be obſervant then, and be not ſqueamiſh, but do as I direct you; When a Gentle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man and's Lady do meet, <hi>A.</hi> the firſt letter is A ſalutation.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Bella.</speaker>
                     <p>The word begins with S.</p>
                     <stage>They ſalute.</stage>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <pb facs="tcp:114636:17"/>
                     <speaker>Fly.</speaker>
                     <p>No matter for the word, give me the ſence, B. the next letter, lend me your fair hand.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Bella.</speaker>
                     <p>Very good Sir.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Fly.</speaker>
                     <p>'Tis in a very good hand indeed; nay I'le ſhew you more tricks by and by, it is ſo very fair that I muſt kiſs it, there's a letter gone that ſtands for C.I confeſs C. may ſtand for another buſineſs, and ſitter for the letter, but a kiſs ſhall ſerve at this time.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Bella.</speaker>
                     <p>On I pray Sir.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Fly.</speaker>
                     <p>Nay, I ſhall come on faſt enough, I warrant you. D. ſhall joyn both our hands, now do we look as if we were wreſtling, which of us both ſhould give the firſt kiſs.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Bella.</speaker>
                     <p>You make your own conſtruction Sir.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Fly.</speaker>
                     <p>I, I, no matter, it's nere the worſe for that.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Bella.</speaker>
                     <p>Proceed Sir.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Fly.</speaker>
                     <p>Stay, ſtay, let's pauſe a little, you'l forget it agen elſe, E. is embrace me, there I have hit you to a letter.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Bella.</speaker>
                     <p>You come neer me now Sir.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Fly.</speaker>
                     <p>I ſhall come neerer yet, for F. I'le ſtroak your cheek.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Bella.</speaker>
                     <p>F. ſtands for flattery.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Fly.</speaker>
                     <p>Not at this time fair one, if you will tye me punctu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ally to a better F. ſtands for Faith or Friendſhip.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Bella.</speaker>
                     <p>That is the trueſt uſe on't.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Fly.</speaker>
                     <p>Well, it ſhall go ſo then. G. is a Gift.</p>
                     <stage>Gives her a Ribbon.</stage>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Bella.</speaker>
                     <p>I'le wear it.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Fly.</speaker>
                     <p>Let me ſee you.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Bella.</speaker>
                     <p>Firſt make an end.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Fly.</speaker>
                     <p>H. ſtands for Hug me t' you.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Bella.</speaker>
                     <p>I have heard of a Wine call'd by that name Sir.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Fly.</speaker>
                     <p>Were it Nectar it could not be ſweeter then this.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Bella.</speaker>
                     <p>It ſeems your favour and my embrace do want no acceptation.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Fly.</speaker>
                     <p>I. ſtands for you, and K. ſtanding for kiſs, is I kiſs you. By the breath of <hi>Venus</hi> y'have a pleaſant lip.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Bella.</speaker>
                     <p>I'm glad it pleaſeth you; to the next letter.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Fly.</speaker>
                     <p>L. is another kiſs, it ſtands for Love.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Bella.</speaker>
                     <p>L. may be luſt, but it ſhould be Love.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Fly.</speaker>
                     <p>I, I, it may ſtand for both by fits. M. ſtands for <hi>Mary.</hi>
                     </p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Bella.</speaker>
                     <p>So it may for Marry.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <pb facs="tcp:114636:18"/>
                     <speaker>Fly.</speaker>
                     <p>Remember R. ſtands for repent, but I am far enough off from that. N, is the next letter, N. ſtands for ne're be good, you ſhall learn O. Q. P. V. in private, that is the full prick or concluſion of the Lovers Alphabet.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Bella.</speaker>
                     <l>Take heed, be not too haſty.</l>
                     <l>Some that would ſeem more nice then vertuous.</l>
                     <l>Who uſe a bluſh, or modeſt baſhfulneſs,</l>
                     <l>To vail their knowledge of ill propoſitions,</l>
                     <l>(Such as I'm ſure pou make, though y'have a trick</l>
                     <l>To ſmooth it o're with your methodick wantonneſs)</l>
                     <l>Would be aſham'd to tell you your ill meaning,</l>
                     <l>But I will not.</l>
                     <l>L. in your Alphabet doth ſtand for luſt,</l>
                     <l>And be not fool'd with ſuch a vanity,</l>
                     <l>To think becauſe you are a handſome man,</l>
                     <l>Or I ſo eaſie won to your ſociety,</l>
                     <l>That I will do an act may hold proportion</l>
                     <l>With any baſeneſs; if you can love truly,</l>
                     <l>Without a glance to any vild reſpect,</l>
                     <l>Reveal it, I was never ſo ill bred</l>
                     <l>To give diſcourteous anſwers.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Fly.</speaker>
                     <l>Love, and love truly, are not you married?</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Bella.</speaker>
                     <l>I am not now Sir.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Fly.</speaker>
                     <l>A widdow and ſo cautious, I'le try another ways;</l>
                     <l>Have I taken up an Angle inſtead of a <hi>Bona Roba?</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>Yes I can love thee, and can love thee truly, and heartily,</l>
                     <l>He ſwear ſo if thou'lt have me.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Bell.</speaker>
                     <p>Let me but hear you Sir, I'le ſwear as much.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Fly.</speaker>
                     <p>Wilt thou, faith ſtay a little.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Bell.</speaker>
                     <p>What do you pauſe on't Sir?</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Fly.</speaker>
                     <p>No, no, I'm ready enough to ſwear, I am loath to caſt away too big an oath, and I'm afraid a ſmal one wil not ſuffice her.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Bell.</speaker>
                     <p>Come I'le propoſe the Oath.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Fly.</speaker>
                     <p>With all my heart.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Bell.</speaker>
                     <p>By tho<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>e diviner powers that govern Contracts, Swear to be true to me.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Fly.</speaker>
                     <p>By all thoſe ſacred powers I kiſs the book, &amp; ever wil obſerve it, come ſhal we walk a ſide now: <hi>Kiſſes her.</hi> Whoſe here?</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <pb facs="tcp:114636:18"/>
                     <speaker>Bell.</speaker>
                     <p>I am glad you are prevented; How vainly men in their raſh heat will ſwear to what they ne'r intend.</p>
                     <stage>Enter Riv. Wild. and Mrs. Trimwel.</stage>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Wild.</speaker>
                     <p>How now <hi>Stephen,</hi> what do you flye from your Colours?</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Fly.</speaker>
                     <p>No Sir, I flye to my Colours, red and white, I'm a right Engliſh-man<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
                     </p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Riv.</speaker>
                     <p>Where's <hi>Pimpwel</hi> gone?</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Fly.</speaker>
                     <p>I ſent him for more Money.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Wild.</speaker>
                     <p>But that Heaven ordained al things for a good end, a man might ſwear that <hi>Pimpwel</hi> was created for a Pimp: how cunningly he found her husband out, &amp; how ſuddenly the rogue contriv'd that quick eſcape; I will have him put in the Almanack next to the Gunpowder-Treaſon.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Rivers.</speaker>
                     <p>Or <hi>Gowries</hi> Conſpiracy; In what a ſtammering caſe now is my French-man; and now I think upon him, I have ſeen a face as right like that in <hi>Parris.</hi>
                     </p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Wild.</speaker>
                     <p>Faith ſo have I.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Mrs. Trim.</speaker>
                     <p>Were you e'r in France Mr. <hi>Rivers?</hi>
                     </p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>River.</speaker>
                     <p>Yes Sweetheart.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Mrs. Trim.</speaker>
                     <p>I have had a brother there theſe 14. years, and have not heard-from him.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Riv.</speaker>
                     <p>What part of <hi>France?</hi>
                     </p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Mrs. Trim.</speaker>
                     <p>
                        <hi>Paris.</hi>
                     </p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Wild.</speaker>
                     <p>What was his name?</p>
                  </sp>
                  <stage>Enter Pimp</stage>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Mrs. Trim.</speaker>
                     <p>
                        <hi>Brooks.</hi>
                     </p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Wild.</speaker>
                     <p>I never heard of him.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Fly.</speaker>
                     <p>Haſt thou brought the mony.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Pimp.</speaker>
                     <p>Ther's. 5. l.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Fly.</speaker>
                     <p>Go and beſpeak ſupper at the <hi>John of Jeruſalem.</hi>
                     </p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Pim.</speaker>
                     <p>I fear it's too late.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Fly.</speaker>
                     <p>What's a clock?</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Pim.</speaker>
                     <p>Paſt 9.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Fly.</speaker>
                     <p>No matter; Lady you ſhall not leave me.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Bell.</speaker>
                     <p>Indeed I cannot ſtay, to morrow where you pleaſe I'le keep an hour with you.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Fly.</speaker>
                     <p>we'l drink a pint &amp; talk on't</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Pimpw.</speaker>
                     <p>I'le tell you news, The French Knight's arreſted at the ſuit of Mr. <hi>Bonaventure</hi> an Engliſh Merchant for 6000. pound, is gone to priſon, no bayl will be taken.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Fly.</speaker>
                     <p>I'm ſorry for't; go, prethee make haſte.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Pimpw.</speaker>
                     <p>I am gone.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <stage>Exit Pimpw. Enter Porter.</stage>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Port.</speaker>
                     <p>Gentlemen, my buſineſs is to one Mr. <hi>Elylove,</hi> Can you direct me to him?</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Fly.</speaker>
                     <p>What is your buſineſs Porter?</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Port.</speaker>
                     <p>I pray read that Letter Sir, I received it from a young Gentleman.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <pb facs="tcp:114636:19"/>
                     <speaker>Fly.</speaker>
                     <p>Gentleman! I hope it is no news from <hi>Drowzy.</hi> To my friend <hi>Stephen Flylove;</hi> I'le try what your inſide ſayes; Ha, come with all ſpeed, Gentlemen I have ſad news for you, <hi>Mercurio</hi> is arreſted.</p>
                     <stage>Reads the Superſcription.</stage>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Wild.</speaker>
                     <p>Arreſted!</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Riv.</speaker>
                     <p>What devil did the deed?</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Fly.</speaker>
                     <p>
                        <hi>Nice</hi> the rich Merchant, 'tis but 20. l.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Riv.</speaker>
                     <p>But 20. l. alas poor Gentleman, he can as wel diſcharge 1000.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Fly.</speaker>
                     <p>He hath writ to ſpeak with me, he is not yet in priſon.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Wild.</speaker>
                     <p>Where is he?</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Fly.</speaker>
                     <p>At the Harrow-Tavern in Little <hi>Woodſtreet.</hi>
                     </p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Wild.</speaker>
                     <p>Come we'l all go, perhaps they'l take our Bayl.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Riv.</speaker>
                     <p>No hang them, theſe Citizens will take none but Free men; We'l make a tryal though.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Wild.</speaker>
                     <p>I would <hi>Pimywel</hi> were here agen, I am ſorry you appointed a Supper.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Fly.</speaker>
                     <p>No matter, we ſhall know ſome end on't ſuddenly.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Riv.</speaker>
                     <p>Let us defer no time, at the Harrow-Tavern ſay you.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Bella.</speaker>
                     <p>Sir I muſt take my leave of you at next turning.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Fly.</speaker>
                     <p>Well, meet me at the <hi>Jeruſalem</hi>-Tavern, but be ſure you fail not.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Bella.</speaker>
                     <p>Your injunction ſhall be obſerved?</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Fly.</speaker>
                     <p>I'le leave a Glove at bar.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <stage>Exeunt.</stage>
               </div>
               <div n="3" type="scene">
                  <head>Act. <hi>3.</hi> Scaen. <hi>3.</hi>
                  </head>
                  <stage>Enter Mr. Hemlock, Mrs. Hemlock, Trimwel, Mace &amp; Trip<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>s.</stage>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Trim.</speaker>
                     <p>Mrs. <hi>Hemlock</hi> if you and your husband do not aſſiſt me in this plot of dexterious miſchief (ſiniſter I ſhould call it) I ſhal be diſgraced beyond remedy; I have now met with an opportunity ſo pleaſing, ſo fit, ſo apt to entertain my pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe, an hour where only <hi>Saturn</hi> is predominant, ſhall ſo jerk my light-heel'd Gallants, and the politick little Gypſie my wife, <hi>Flylove</hi> is the pin that muſt ſet all the other wheels a going, which pin this honeſt blade my old acquaintance <hi>Tripes</hi> ſhall turn, Mr. <hi>Mace</hi> I know your part is not the leaſt in thiſ revengeful conſpiracy, be ſure you uſe him roughly that it may cauſe a quarrel, and young <hi>Rivers</hi> will take fire at the leaſt ſpark.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Tripes.</speaker>
                     <p>If ſcurvy uſage will make them quarrel they ſhal not want it, I hope <hi>Tripes</hi> is not to learn to uſe a man ſcur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vily,
<pb facs="tcp:114636:19"/>I'm ſure I have practiz'd theſe 20. years, and there's ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver a one that ever I arreſted yet can give me a good word; The Players brought me oth' Stage once I thank them in a Play call'd the <hi>Roaring Girle,</hi> or <hi>The Catchpole,</hi> he was a pret<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty fellow that acted me, but he came ſhort of the rogueries I have done.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Mrs. Hem.</speaker>
                     <p>You have ſent a Porter.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Trim.</speaker>
                     <p>I ſaw him deliver the Letter.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Mrs. Hem.</speaker>
                     <p>'Tis very well, 'cauſe this is a large room, you ſhall retire into a leſs, I'le ſhew them up ſtayrs, and pretend that <hi>Mercurio</hi> and the Serjeants are gone into the City to ſee ſome friend of his for bayl, and will be here preſently, which to countenance you ſhall leave your pint pot half full of wine, your empty foul pipes and the candle, and when I ſhall give the watch-word you may enter.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Trimwel.</speaker>
                     <p>And now you talk of the watch-word, is the Watch ſet at <hi>Cripplegate?</hi>
                     </p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Mrs. Hem.</speaker>
                     <p>And hath been this half hour.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Trim.</speaker>
                     <p>If there be but the leaſt diſturbance, let your boy be ready to call the Watch up; can he frame a lye hanſomly before the Juſtice next morning, I know the Watch will do their parts, only they have one fault, which is to charge every offender with one way of aſſault, that muſt be avoided.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Mrs. Hem.</speaker>
                     <p>I warrant you for the boy <hi>Ned.</hi>
                     </p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Boy.</speaker>
                     <p>Anon, anon Sir, Did you call Mr.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Mrs. Hem.</speaker>
                     <p>Yes Sir.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Trim.</speaker>
                     <p>Is thy name Villanous?</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Boy.</speaker>
                     <p>No Sir, 'tis a nick-name my Mr. hath given me.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Trim.</speaker>
                     <p>But thou muſt now deſerve it, can you if need be, abuſe. I mean accuſe a Gentleman before a Juſtice of peace, to do a courtefie for a friend of your Maſters?</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Boy.</speaker>
                     <p>Of what degree muſt the fault be?</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Trim.</speaker>
                     <p>Of what degree? a learned boy, oh my dainty pick<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pocket, he hath faults at's fingers ends, the devil hath given us ſuch equal gifts; let me hear your degrees my fine villain.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Trim.</speaker>
                     <p>Time runs away, let me hear ſom of them preſently.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Boy.</speaker>
                     <p>Why ſir, I can accuſe him for picking of your kocket calling you ſon of a whore Rogue, Knave, Cheat, ſtriking of you with a ſword, with a ſtaff, with a pot, a Candleſtick, or ſtab'd you with a Tobacco-pipe, or — are you married?</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Trim.</speaker>
                     <p>Yes Sir.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <pb facs="tcp:114636:20"/>
                     <speaker>Boy.</speaker>
                     <p>Then if you will Sir, I'le ſwear I ſaw him lye with your wife.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Trim.</speaker>
                     <p>No, no, hang you, I'le have thee ſwear to nothing that appears like truth, you ſhall find cauſe enough to ſwear I'le warrant you, and ſo we ſhall have all.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Tripes.</speaker>
                     <p>I ſhould know this boy, a pretty ingenious Lad; Doſt thou not know me, <hi>Jack?</hi>
                     </p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Boy.</speaker>
                     <p>My name's <hi>Richard Philpot,</hi> I was born in Turnbal-ſtreet</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Tripes.</speaker>
                     <p>'Tis true, 'tis true, doſt not know me <hi>Dick Filpot?</hi>
                     </p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Boy.</speaker>
                     <p>No truly Sir.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Tripes.</speaker>
                     <p>How doth thy father, is thy mother living ſtill?</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Boy.</speaker>
                     <p>No Sir, ſhe's dead; did you know her Sir?</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Tripes.</speaker>
                     <p>Did I know her, I a dozen years before I knew thee, why thou art now, let me ſee, 1641. thou art now ſome 14. years of age <hi>Dick.</hi>
                     </p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Boy.</speaker>
                     <p>I am almoſt 15. Sir.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Tripes.</speaker>
                     <p>I think thou wantſt half a year on't.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Boy.</speaker>
                     <p>No Sir, I want but a quarter.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Tripes.</speaker>
                     <p>I, thereabouts, didſt never hear thy father ſpeak of me <hi>Dick.</hi>
                     </p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Boy.</speaker>
                     <p>No indeed Sir.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Tripes.</speaker>
                     <p>I am thy Godfather.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Boy.</speaker>
                     <p>Are you Sir?</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Tripes.</speaker>
                     <p>Am I quotha, who would have thought to have ſeen this boy here; do thy duty, I ſhal find ſomthing for thee.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Boy.</speaker>
                     <p>Pray Godfather give me your bleſſing.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Tripes.</speaker>
                     <p>Good boy, thou art no Browniſt, I ſee thou canſt kneel to thy Godfather for a gift, ſo can ſom of them too for thy hopes, but y faith boy <hi>I</hi> cannot part with mony at this time, thou ſhalt have my bleſſing.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Omnes.</speaker>
                     <p>Ha, ha, ha.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Boy.</speaker>
                     <p>A pox of your bleſſing, I thought how wel you were my Godfather; had it not been for the hopes of your mony I'le have ſeen you hang'd e'r I'le have beleeved you, I know where my Godfathers are, though I'de have ſatisfied your humor for your mony.</p>
                     <stage>Within. Boy, Drawer, Drawer.</stage>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Trim.</speaker>
                     <p>Boy look to your charge, they are come.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Boy.</speaker>
                     <p>By and by, anon, anon Sir.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <stage>Exit boy.</stage>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Mrs. Hem.</speaker>
                     <p>Go all of you into that room.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Mr. Hem.</speaker>
                     <p>The watch-words ſhall be, I <hi>wonder he ſtayes ſo long.</hi>
                     </p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Mr. <hi>Trim.</hi>
                     </speaker>
                     <p>I would not have you ſeen.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <stage>Exeunt Serj. and Trimwel.</stage>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Trim.</speaker>
                     <p>No, I'le warrant you.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <pb facs="tcp:114636:20"/>
                     <speaker>Mrs. Hem.</speaker>
                     <p>You are very welcom Gent.</p>
                     <stage>
                        <hi>Ent. Wild. Fly. Riv.</hi> &amp; <hi>Mrs. Trim.</hi>
                     </stage>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Wild.</speaker>
                     <p>Are you the Maſter of the houſe?</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Mr. Hem.</speaker>
                     <p>Yes Sir, for want of a better.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Wild.</speaker>
                     <p>It may be ſo; what ſhall I call your name?</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Mr. Hem.</speaker>
                     <p>My name is <hi>Hemlock</hi> Sir.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Fly.</speaker>
                     <p>Thou art half hang'd, thou haſt an ill name <hi>Hemlock</hi> and a Vintner, bleſs me from thy wine; did there not a couple of Serjeants bring in a Gentleman even now?</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Mr. H.</speaker>
                     <p>Yes Sir, are you the Gentleman he ſent for?</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Fly.</speaker>
                     <p>Where is he?</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Mr. H.</speaker>
                     <p>He and the Serjeants are gone into <hi>Cheapſide</hi> to a friend of his that he hopes will bayl him, they'l be here pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſently, this is his room.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Fly.</speaker>
                     <p>Why would not that friend come hither?</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Mrs. H.</speaker>
                     <p>He was in bed Sir.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Fly.</speaker>
                     <p>A poor excuſe, that man will ſcarce be bayl, that will not have his bed to ſave his friend.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Mr.</speaker>
                     <p>I hope Sir you will do him ſome good, he's a pretty Gentleman, 'tis pitty he ſhould ſuffer.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Fly.</speaker>
                     <p>It is indeed, hath he paid the reckning.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Mr.</speaker>
                     <p>No Sir.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Fly.</speaker>
                     <p>How long hath he been gone?</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Mr.</speaker>
                     <p>Half an hour Sir, I wonder he ſtays ſo long.</p>
                     <stage>Enter Serjeants.</stage>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Wild.</speaker>
                     <p>How now, who are theſe?</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Tripes.</speaker>
                     <p>Is your name Mr. <hi>Flylove?</hi>
                     </p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Fly.</speaker>
                     <p>Yes Sir.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Tripes.</speaker>
                     <p>I arreſt you at the ſuit of <hi>Alice Drowzy.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <stage>
                        <hi>Riv. draws, offers to run at the Serj. and the</hi> Mr. <hi>oth' houſe comming between, he is hurt ith' arm, then coms in the miſtris.</hi>
                     </stage>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Riv.</speaker>
                     <p>Arreſt my friend?</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Wild.</speaker>
                     <p>Then let me ſuffer too.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Mr. H.</speaker>
                     <p>Murder, murder, murder, go run and call the Watch, my hus<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>band's kill'd.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Conſtable.</speaker>
                     <p>Beat down their weapons, I charge you in the Kings name to keep his peace.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Riv.</speaker>
                     <p>The Kings peace we will keep.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Conſt.</speaker>
                     <p>Or we ſhall force you.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Riv.</speaker>
                     <p>Did nothing urge me to't but your force, I ſhould not fear to break it.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Conſt.</speaker>
                     <p>Sir you have kill'd the Maſter of the houſe.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Riv.</speaker>
                     <p>I'm very ſorry for't Sir.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Conſt.</speaker>
                     <p>That is no ſatisfaction.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <pb facs="tcp:114636:21"/>
                     <speaker>Riv.</speaker>
                     <p>He is a man I meant no hurt to; Sir do you ſend for Chyrurgeon to night, I'le ſend you one to morrow, I gueſs the danger of the wound; Come Sir, where will you con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duct us?</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Conſt.</speaker>
                     <p>To the next priſon.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Wild.</speaker>
                     <p>Oh that's the Compter.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Riv.</speaker>
                     <p>Come then we'l altogether and make a merry night, no queſtion but we ſhall come off to morrow; I pray Mr. Conſtable will you come for us betimes.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Conſt.</speaker>
                     <p>You ſhall have all the favour I can do you, I am ſorry for this chance.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Fly.</speaker>
                     <p>Faith ſo am I.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <stage>Exeunt.</stage>
                  <stage>Ent. Trimw.</stage>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Trim.</speaker>
                     <lg>
                        <l>And I am ſorry too but cannot cry,</l>
                        <l>Now Is my plot made perfect, all the wheels</l>
                        <l>Are in a general motion, I muſt follow, I ſhall</l>
                        <l>Never think they are in priſon, till I ſee them</l>
                        <l>Within the Compter-gates.</l>
                     </lg>
                     <lg>
                        <l>My ſinging Gallants your mad miſdemeanor,</l>
                        <l>Shall bring you now to ſing the Compter tenor.</l>
                     </lg>
                  </sp>
                  <stage>Exit.</stage>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div n="4" type="act">
               <head>Actus quartus,</head>
               <div n="1" type="scene">
                  <head>Scaena prima.</head>
                  <stage>Enter as in the Compter Wildblood, Rivers, Flylove, Mrs. Trimwel and Keeper.</stage>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Wild.</speaker>
                     <l>Blood of the <hi>Rivers,</hi> thou beginſt to droop,</l>
                     <l>Thy ſoul ſeems not ſo active as it was:</l>
                     <l>Where be thoſe capering pieces of pure flaſh,</l>
                     <l>That made the genius of the place grow Comick?</l>
                     <l>By the wanton memory of <hi>Chaucer</hi> I could turn Poet,</l>
                     <l>And write in as Heathen Engliſh; and as bawdy;</l>
                     <l>I'le not to bed to night.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Rivers.</speaker>
                     <p>Nor I by <hi>Jove.</hi>
                     </p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Fly.</speaker>
                     <p>By <hi>Jupiter</hi> nor I, ſhall we be jovial; why ſhould we not; conceive this place a Tavern, one place may ſerve for two uſes; ſome conceive it the habitation of the ſorrowful, and our free ſpirits ſhall convert it to a Paradiſe of delight; Pray Sir what hour of the night is't.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Keeper.</speaker>
                     <p>Paſt twelve Sir.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <pb facs="tcp:114636:21"/>
                     <speaker>Fly.</speaker>
                     <p>It is an age to morning:</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Frank Rivers,</speaker>
                     <p>prethee cheer up the woman, ſhe droope.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Riv.</speaker>
                     <p>Doſt thou want reſt?</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Mrs. Trim.</speaker>
                     <p>Yes Sir, far more then ſleep.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Riv.</speaker>
                     <l>Thy mind's diſquiet then, prethee be cheerful,</l>
                     <l>Sorrows are momentary as well as joyes;</l>
                     <l>Were I ith' bottome of the Ocean,</l>
                     <l>I'd bear my head up, till my own weight ſunk me.</l>
                     <l>Sir, can we have ſome Wine.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Keep.</speaker>
                     <p>I'le ring the Bell for you, they are up at the Fea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers-Tavern; they lye at a ſafe Guard, they' I have their money before-hand.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Fly.</speaker>
                     <p>With all my heart, we ſhall not be miſ-reckoned then, here's money for a pottle of Canary, the night is ſomewhat cold, and Sack is ſprightly.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Keep.</speaker>
                     <p>
                        <hi>Hugh, Hugh.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <stage>Enter Drawer at the window.</stage>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Hugh.</speaker>
                     <p>What a Hugh and cry you make, I have ſtayed up theſe two nights, you are all mad I think, will you not go to bed to night.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Wild.</speaker>
                     <p>Prethee honeſt <hi>Hugh</hi> (if thy name be ſo) fill us one pottle of Canary, let's have clean pipes and Tobacco.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Hugh.</speaker>
                     <p>Where's your money?</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Riv.</speaker>
                     <p>At hand, at hand, my midnight Drawer.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Hugh.</speaker>
                     <p>Who's that, Mr. <hi>Rivers?</hi>
                     </p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Riv.</speaker>
                     <p>I, doſt know me?</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Hugh.</speaker>
                     <p>Do I Sir, I fill'd you many a gallon of Wine at the Bear upon <hi>Fleet-bridge.</hi>
                     </p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Riv.</speaker>
                     <p>Oh, th'art an honeſt blade, I know thee, prethee fill me good Wine.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Hugh.</speaker>
                     <p>The beſt in the Sellar.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <stage>Exit.</stage>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Wil.</speaker>
                     <p>Hark you ſir, is there not a French knight in the houſ?</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Keep.</speaker>
                     <p>His name is <hi>Sir Reverence Lamard,</hi> he lies two ſtories higher to the ſtreet.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Riv.</speaker>
                     <p>A lamentable ſtory! can you not invite him down?</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Keep.</speaker>
                     <p>I'le try Sir.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Riv.</speaker>
                     <p>Th'art an honeſt Keeper.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Fly.</speaker>
                     <p>Theſe Keepers have been rumor'd to be churliſh; I like this fellows humour very well.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Wild.</speaker>
                     <p>Oh what a crew of Wine-Leaches ſhal we have ſtick upon us to morrow morning for our Garniſh, we are of the Maſter-ſide, your half-crowns a piece Gentlemen, I know the order, I have commenc'd in this Colledge before now.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <pb facs="tcp:114636:22"/>
                     <speaker>Hugh.</speaker>
                     <p>A pottle of Canary in the Compter, ſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                           <desc>••</desc>
                        </gap>re.</p>
                     <stage>Enter Drawer with Wine.</stage>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Fly.</speaker>
                     <p>In the Compter you rogue; Sir can't you ſhew us a better room.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Hugh.</speaker>
                     <p>It is too late Sir, pray be civill, and keep your own room:</p>
                  </sp>
                  <stage>Exit Drawer.</stage>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Fly.</speaker>
                     <p>Is this the end of our travail? Here s a Health to our good deliverance.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Wild.</speaker>
                     <p>By the blood of <hi>Bacchus</hi> I'le pledge thee.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Fly.</speaker>
                     <p>Come I'le begin a mad Health, and let every man have his fancie.</p>
                     <lg>
                        <l>
                           <hi>Here's a curſt to all thoſe</hi>
                        </l>
                        <l>
                           <hi>That are Priſ'ners foes,</hi>
                        </l>
                        <l>
                           <hi>And the Coward that goes</hi>
                        </l>
                        <l>
                           <hi>To undoe men for blows,</hi>
                        </l>
                        <l>
                           <hi>Who doth baſely expoſe</hi>
                        </l>
                        <l>
                           <hi>Their bodies to throwes,</hi>
                        </l>
                        <l>
                           <hi>In a Priſon where growes</hi>
                        </l>
                        <l>
                           <hi>Infection to th' noſe,</hi>
                        </l>
                        <l>
                           <hi>And from top to the toes</hi>
                        </l>
                        <l>
                           <hi>Are tormented with woes,</hi>
                        </l>
                        <l>
                           <hi>Till, be it ſpoke under the Roſe,</hi>
                        </l>
                        <l>
                           <hi>They'r meat for the Crowes;</hi>
                        </l>
                        <l>
                           <hi>Confuſion to thoſe</hi>
                        </l>
                        <l>
                           <hi>In Meeter and Proſe.</hi>
                        </l>
                     </lg>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Wild.</speaker>
                     <p>Pray drink off your cup, and we'l all keep the cloſe, here comes my white Knight in his Lawn ſleeves, now if a Quaker ſaw him he would take his ſhirt for a Surpleſs, and condemn it for a Babyloniſh Garment, or in good ſooth and verily a wicked and ſuperſtitious remnant of that foul ſlaps the whore of Babylon.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Sir Rev.</speaker>
                     <p>Begar dat whore of Babylon be one of me Aunts.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Riv.</speaker>
                     <p>Monſieur you ſee we are come to bear you company, you ſhall not engroſs the priſon to your ſelf.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Sir Rev.</speaker>
                     <p>Me tank you for noting, you can no give me de ſheat now as you have fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> (vat do you cal de fader of de pig)</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Fly.</speaker>
                     <p>The father of the Pig; a Hog.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>
                        <hi>Sir</hi> R.</speaker>
                     <p>Hog, hog, hog, as you gave me de ſheat at <hi>Hogdown.</hi>
                     </p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Riv.</speaker>
                     <p>Wel forget it, there was no hurt meant, on my cre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dit, there was another cauſe you muſt not know.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <pb facs="tcp:114636:22"/>
                     <speaker>Sir R.</speaker>
                     <p>Begar but me do know already, you carry away de Surzhons viſe, begar he be horn-mad.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Wild.</speaker>
                     <p>How came you to know this? would he reveal it?</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Sir R.</speaker>
                     <p>Yes begar and more to, 'twas he dat make <hi>Drowzy</hi> de Kiſhin-wenſh to arreſt Monſieur <hi>Flylove.</hi>
                     </p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Riv.</speaker>
                     <p>The devil at laſt is even with us.</p>
                     <stage>A ſhowt in the Hole.</stage>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Within.</speaker>
                     <p>Room for my Lord Judge.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Fly.</speaker>
                     <p>How now what's the matter?</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Keep.</speaker>
                     <p>This noiſe is ith' Kings Ward; 'tis term'd the Hole.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Fly.</speaker>
                     <p>But are they allow'd to be ſo lowd there.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Keep.</speaker>
                     <l>We cannot check a Cuſtome they have us'd,</l>
                     <l>Which is when a new Priſoner firſt comes in,</l>
                     <l>They have a Scaene of mirth, where one is Judge,</l>
                     <l>And ſits a tryal upon life and death.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Fly.</speaker>
                     <p>May we not ſee them Sir.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Keep.</speaker>
                     <p>I have no priviledg to open Wards at this late hour oth' night, left ſome combuſtion happen amongſt the priſoners, which my ſtrength will be too weak to pacifie.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Riv.</speaker>
                     <p>My life for yours no danger Sir.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Keep.</speaker>
                     <p>Ye appear honeſt Gentlemen, and I'le truſt ye.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Riv.</speaker>
                     <p>Thank you Sir; come Monſieur wil you walk down.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Sir R.</speaker>
                     <p>Zhentlem me vill vait on you to morrow, but me mus com to bed; but me have anoder plot in my head begar.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Fly.</speaker>
                     <p>Wel Monſieur good night<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> take reſt, and ſleep ſecure.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Sir R.</speaker>
                     <p>Awee Monſieur tres humble ſerviteur.</p>
                  </sp>
               </div>
               <div n="2" type="scene">
                  <head>Act. <hi>4.</hi> Scaen. <hi>2.</hi>
                  </head>
                  <stage>Enter as in the Hole Wildfire, Lord Lowſ-proof, Steward Rentfree Conſtable-Lazy, and Chamberlain-Jaylbird.</stage>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Rent.</speaker>
                     <p>What is your name my friend?</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Lowſ.</speaker>
                     <p>You muſt tell the Steward your name, you will be the ſooner entred a member of the Sheriffs-Basket, there is (my friend) a ſtrange miracle in our living, we never want meat yet keep continual faſt; and yet all that faſt, you may ſee by our Clothes we are looſe enough; we live in imita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of the Owls, we ſleep ith' day time, and revel all the night: Some beds we have for Gentlemen of quality, as my ſelf being the Lord, <hi>Steward Rentfree, Conſtable Lazy,</hi> and <hi>Chamberlain Jaylbird.</hi>
                     </p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <pb facs="tcp:114636:23"/>
                     <speaker>Wildf.</speaker>
                     <p>Gentlemen, I was a Page to a Knight that was a priſoner in this houſe <hi>Sir Rev. Lamard,</hi> my name is <hi>Wildfire.</hi>
                     </p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Lowſ.</speaker>
                     <p>Prethee ſtand farther off, thou wilt melt me elſe.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Jayl.</speaker>
                     <p>My Lord begins to hiſs.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Lowſ.</speaker>
                     <p>Gentlemen of the Kings Ward let us conſult upon the buſineſs, 'tis for the good of the Hole, and of the whole Houſe; let us for once be wiſer and honeſter then e'r we have been, there may come much miſchief by this <hi>Wildfire,</hi> if he ſtay long he will conſume us, and every creeping thing a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bout us, our beds being all ſtraw is very combuſtible; the very blowing on's noſe blows a bed up.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Rent.</speaker>
                     <p>There's a Bug upon your Honours doublet.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Lowſ.</speaker>
                     <p>Is there but one, give it <hi>Wildfire,</hi> he is fit for no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing but to receive my Moabites in reverſion, they may live upon him like ſo many Salamanders; I will petition to morrow for the diſcharge of <hi>Wildfire,</hi> he ſhall not ſtay with us, we muſt have <hi>Wildfire</hi> put out, 'tis pity ſuch a ſpark ſhould be in the Compter.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <stage>Enter Keeper, Flylove, Rivers, Wildblood, Mrs. Trimw.</stage>
                  <p>Stand aſide, here comes the Gentlemen Rats, it is moſt fit I give them the firſt ſalutation; Gentlemen you are moſt un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>happily incountred.</p>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Fly.</speaker>
                     <p>I do moſt unfortunately thank you Sir, we come to ſee your Revels, are they ended? are you my Lord?</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Lazy.</speaker>
                     <p>Yes Sir, he's my Lord.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Fly.</speaker>
                     <p>Well Gentlemen we make bold to viſit you, and (to be the better welcome) we have brought with us each man a bottle of Canary; who's that knocks?</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Keep.</speaker>
                     <p>'Tis ſomebody at the Compter-gate, ſome more Rats I believe.</p>
                     <stage>knocking at the Compter-gate.</stage>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Wild.</speaker>
                     <p>Bring them hither of what degree ſoever.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <stage>Exit Keeper and Lowzy.</stage>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Lazy.</speaker>
                     <p>I, I, Hole 'um, Hole 'um; Rat, tat, tat, this is the City-Mouſ-trap; here do we lye at a ſure ward, revel all night, and breath defiance to the Watch and the Conſtable; we have ſuffered under the terrour of Authority, and now we have got the Law in our own hands.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Lowzy.</speaker>
                     <p>A Rat, a Rat, a Rat.</p>
                     <stage>Enter Lowzy.</stage>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <pb facs="tcp:114636:23"/>
                     <speaker>Riv.</speaker>
                     <p>What are they, Citizens or Gentlemen?</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Low.</speaker>
                     <p>No, no, they are neither Citizens nor Gentlemen, and yet they are a company for Lords, they are muſicall Rats, ſinging Rats, men that are come to keep time in the Compter; they are crowding in, therefore you that mean to expreſs your activity, prepare and be in readineſs, a man in priſon may eaſily do his ſink-a-pace.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <stage>Enter Keeper and the Muſicians.</stage>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Fly.</speaker>
                     <p>Theſe are the Blades that were with us at <hi>Hogsdon;</hi> this was ſome preciſe Conſtable, ſome brother oth' Family, that ſent the Muſicians to priſon, or elſe ſome joviall Hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mouriſt that had a mind the priſoners ſhould be merry to night; well my Maſters, ſince you are here, ſtrike up cou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ragiouſly, here be Gentlemen have a mind to diſcover their footing, you ſhall not loſe your labour, I'le pay your Fees in the morning.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Fidlers.</speaker>
                     <p>We thank you noble Mr. <hi>Flylove.</hi>
                     </p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Low.</speaker>
                     <p>Gentlemen, throw of your bottomleſs pantoffles, and let's to't, here's Sack to cherriſh us when we have fini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhed.</p>
                     <stage>They Dance an Antick.</stage>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Wildb.</speaker>
                     <p>Gentlemen, we thank you, when we'r at liberty, we'l ſend you ſomething worth your eſtimation, in the mean time drink that.</p>
                     <stage>Gives them money.</stage>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Fly.</speaker>
                     <p>I come, let's go, I do not like the fume of this cloſe room; how fare you Mrs. <hi>Trimwel?</hi>
                     </p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Mrs. Trim.</speaker>
                     <p>Well Sir, but that the ſcent is ſomewhat noy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſome, the room above, from whence we came, is ſweeter.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Riv.</speaker>
                     <p>Come, we'l go up agen then.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Fly.</speaker>
                     <p>I, I, let's go, god-night good friends.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Omnes.</speaker>
                     <p>We thank you Gentlemen, we'l drink your healths to morrow morning.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Riv.</speaker>
                     <p>In the morning Muſick we'l keep our words with you, but I ſhall talk with you for the trick you put upon me at <hi>Hogsdon.</hi>
                     </p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Fidlers.</speaker>
                     <p>It was no fault of ours indeed Mr. <hi>Rivers,</hi> we'l mak't appear to morrow.</p>
                     <stage>Exeunt Rivers, Mrs. Trim. Wildblood and Flylove.</stage>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Riv.</speaker>
                     <p>Well, well, good night.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Omnes.</speaker>
                     <p>Good night to you all Gentlemen.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <pb facs="tcp:114636:24"/>
                     <speaker>Lowſ.</speaker>
                     <p>Come my Maſters we that were Dancers will make an equal diviſion of the Gentlemans bounty, here is ten ſhillings, and we are ſix on's.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Ren.</speaker>
                     <p n="12">12. d. a piece, &amp; the reſt in drink among the priſners</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Lowſ.</speaker>
                     <p>I like the motion well my equal Steward, here is ſome Sack left, that we'l drink with the Muſitians, and ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuſe their Garniſh in the morning.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Omnes.</speaker>
                     <p>Agreed, agreed.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Lowſ.</speaker>
                     <p>Let us conſult farther in our with-drawing room: How now Chamberlain cannot you leave your old trade? muſt you be filching? wouldſt thou undo a poor Common<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wealth at one pull thou unconſcionable thief, but I am too ſubtil for you ſirrah, you can't deceive me; The devil take me if my Angel leave me.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Rent.</speaker>
                     <p>Nobly ſpoke my Lord; room for my Lord there.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <stage>Enter above with a long rope Sir Rev. Lamard.</stage>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Sir Rev.</speaker>
                     <p>'Tis very light, begar me ſall be diſcover; now if my ſtring do ſlip, down goes <hi>Sir Reverence</hi> upon ſome Waſh-mans head, and begar dat vill bewray all; I can ſee no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting but de Fiddles in de Priſon; if I ſall break my neck in ſundra for my liberty, begar my adverſary make dice of my bones, but I ſall couzen him, for my bone crumble to aſhes: So, ſo, vas very faſt, and ſo faſt, as me can, me vill down; Begar me tink it be ſomewhat ſtrange dat me mus come to be ſave by de Rope, but if I be taken, for ought I know I ſall be hang in de Rope. I care not me ſall <stage>He ſlides down and reſteth on the Fea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers Tavern.</stage> ventre for all dat, as good be hang as live in priſon: Begar here comes ſom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>body vith light, me ſall be taken, dere <stage>Ent. Pimpw. drunk with a Torch in his hand.</stage> be no vay to ſcape, and me canot clime up agen: Oh Diabolo vat ſall become of me, de vindow be ſhut, me can no creep into de Tavern, and I ſall not be taken for Zhorge a horſ-back, as me ſaw once in de Play; begar dis man be drunk, I ſee by his ſtagger.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Pimpw.</speaker>
                     <p>A ſawcy Conſtable to queſtion my lodging, can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not a man go home to his houſe in peace? Is it not ſuffici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ent that I can carry my ſelf to the Compter, but I muſt be beholding to an enigmatical Conſtable, and his miſchievous
<pb facs="tcp:114636:24"/>Watch; a man can no ſooner come neer them, but who goes there? come before the Conſtable; Come afore a Cuckold, Oh ſuch a rogue would be hang'd; Let me ſee, where am I? this is <hi>Woodſtreet,</hi> whereabouts is the Feathers-Tavern.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Sir Rev.</speaker>
                     <p>A pox for you, you be too neer de Feder-Tavern already, and begar now I ſee him, dis fellow be priſoner in de Compter, but I have an invention he ſall no ſpy me, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gar me vill creep into dis Buſh, and ven he be gone me ſall go down courageo.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Pimpw.</speaker>
                     <p>This is the Compter where many a man lies with a heavy heart, I have been a priſoner this two or three years, yet I walk abroad at my leaſure, and am as drunk as a devil for my pleaſure.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Sir Rev.</speaker>
                     <p>Begar me have extream need to make vater, I ſall piſh my breeſh, Oh Diabolo I ſall be found, begar me can ſtay no longra, me ſall burſe.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Pimpw.</speaker>
                     <p>I will knock up this rogue <hi>Hugh</hi> at the Feathers; <hi>Hugh, Hugh,</hi> you rogue riſe, my name's <hi>Pimpwel,</hi> you ſleepy rogue riſe and let me in, muſt I wait upon you with a pox to you. Nouns what's that?</p>
                     <stage>Sir Rev. piſſeth upon him.</stage>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Sir Rev.</speaker>
                     <p>Begar now I be undon in a piſſing vhile.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Pimpw.</speaker>
                     <p>You ſon of a Batchelor, do you throw your Piſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pots upon my head, if I could finde ſtones I'de break your windows, but ſince I cannot, I will even make bold to ſet fire of your Buſh, then throw your water and ſpare not.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Sir Rev.</speaker>
                     <p>Oh Mordieu, me ſall be burn in de Buſh, or be hang in de Rope, I vould I were in me ſhamber agen.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Pimpw.</speaker>
                     <p>What's here, a Rope? ſome pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoner <stage>Pimpw. ſpieth the rope.</stage> has made an eſcape out of the Maſters-ſide; there's money for ſomebody to pay, I'le in and call the Turn-key, a priſoner eſcap't, a priſoner, a priſoner.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Within.</speaker>
                     <p>From whence?</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Pimpw.</speaker>
                     <p>A private chamber in the Maſters-ſide.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Within.</speaker>
                     <p>A priſoner, a priſoner.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Pimpw.</speaker>
                     <p>Look, look, here's the Rope.</p>
                     <stage>
                        <hi>Ent.</hi> 2. <hi>or</hi> 3. <hi>Keepers.</hi>
                     </stage>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Keep.</speaker>
                     <p>Run up to the Maſters-ſide, ſee if the French Knight be in's Chamber, his Action is 6000. l. we are all undone if he eſcape away.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <stage>
                     <hi>Exit</hi> 2. <hi>Keepers.</hi>
                  </stage>
                  <sp>
                     <pb facs="tcp:114636:25"/>
                     <speaker>Pimpw.</speaker>
                     <p>I, I, we are all undone, if he be gone here's Rope enough for us all.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>3. <hi>Keep.</hi>
                     </speaker>
                     <p>Pox on you for a drunken rogue, wher haſt bin?</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Pimpw.</speaker>
                     <p>Drinking wine in bowls boys, I am almoſt drunk, but what ſhal we do for the priſoner, ſhall I run after him?</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>3. Keep.</speaker>
                     <p>Which way is he gone?</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Pim.</speaker>
                     <p>The Lord knows.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>2. <hi>Keep.</hi>
                     </speaker>
                     <p>Hallowgh?</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>1. <hi>Keep.</hi>
                     </speaker>
                     <p>What ſay you?</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>2. <hi>Keep.</hi>
                     </speaker>
                     <p>The French Knight is eſcaped, you muſt make ſwift purſuit, he cannot be gone far.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>1. <hi>Keep.</hi>
                     </speaker>
                     <p>Pluck up the Rope; look well toth' Gate, <hi>Pimp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wel</hi> run you to <hi>Cripplegate,</hi> you to ſome other Watches, and all the way you run, cry out a priſoner.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <stage>Exit.</stage>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>3. <hi>Keep.</hi>
                     </speaker>
                     <p>A priſoner, a priſoner.</p>
                     <stage>Ex. keep. ſeveral ways.</stage>
                  </sp>
                  <stage>
                     <hi>Sir</hi> Reverence <hi>comes out of the Buſh.</hi>
                  </stage>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Sir Rev.</speaker>
                     <p>Oh the great pox run with you all, vat a fear have dey put me in, begar me vill not ſtay, 'tis very light, I ſee no paſſenger, dis vas de braveſt time: So, now me are down, futra for Keeper; begar me can no ſhuſe but laugh, how dey run-away from me to find me; Oh me brave buſh! Fiſh vay ſall me take to be ſafe, me mus come no neer <hi>Crip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plegate,</hi> nor <hi>Sheapſide,</hi> I ſall take ſome udder vay, the devil is in me if I come agen; Farewell good Compter, I am not loath to part from you: I remember two line of an Engliſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man dat vent from de Priſon, dey var des:</p>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Dis Houſe mus be let at a miſerable rate,</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>For I ha' left my Shambra, any man may ha't.</hi>
                     </l>
                     <p>Farewel Comptera.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <stage>Exit.</stage>
                  <stage>Enter Splendora and a Keeper.</stage>
                  <stage>Mercurio?</stage>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Splend.</speaker>
                     <p>Can you direct me to the hapleſs lodging of yong</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Keep.</speaker>
                     <p>He lies ith' Maſters-ſide, he is a Gentleman whoſe miſery works much compaſſion in each Officer, I would my power could ſave him.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Splend.</speaker>
                     <l>Thank you Sir?</l>
                     <l>Such worthy wiſhes in ſuch men as you,</l>
                     <l>Who bear a function of that cruel nature,</l>
                     <l>Being ſo rare, appears moſt excellent;</l>
                     <l>Pray tell me Sir, how doth he take his ſufferings?</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <pb facs="tcp:114636:25"/>
                     <speaker>Keep.</speaker>
                     <l>I think he is in love; he's often heard</l>
                     <l>To ſigh a Ladies name, and ſing ſad Sonnets</l>
                     <l>In diſſolving paſſion,</l>
                     <l>Such as might melt the Tyger-cruelty</l>
                     <l>Of men turn'd Tyrants; thus much I obſerve,</l>
                     <l>The priſon doth not fright him from his reſt,</l>
                     <l>Like his divorce from her whoſe name he ſighs ſo;</l>
                     <l>I'le call him if you pleaſe, yet 'tis ſomewhat early.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Splend.</speaker>
                     <l>Sir, I give thanks</l>
                     <l>Unto your loving diligence, and with your leave,</l>
                     <l>I ſhall conceive it but a friendly Office,</l>
                     <l>To ſpare his labour, and walk up to him.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <stage>Exit Splend.</stage>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Keep.</speaker>
                     <p>Thoſe ſtayrs direct you, turn on your left hand.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <stage>Enter to the Keeper Bellaflora.</stage>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Bella.</speaker>
                     <p>Are you the Keeper Sir?</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Keep.</speaker>
                     <l>I turn the key, my Office is as much</l>
                     <l>To let men out as in; I take no pride,</l>
                     <l>To ſtand 'twixt men and freedome, ſuck a Keeper</l>
                     <l>I am, and would be thought.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Bella.</speaker>
                     <p>Heaven be thy Keeper, and grant thy place cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rupt thee not; pray Sir, was there not brought in amongſt other Gentlemen, a priſoner late laſt night, call'd Mr. <hi>Flylove?</hi>
                     </p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Keep.</speaker>
                     <p>Yes Lady.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Bella.</speaker>
                     <p>How could I ſpeak a word in private with him? the buſineſs which I have concerns his freedome.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Keep.</speaker>
                     <p>I ſhall be glad to call him, — Mr. <hi>Flylove.</hi>
                     </p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Priſoners within.</speaker>
                     <p>Mr. <hi>Flylove,</hi> Mr. <hi>Flylove.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <stage>Ent. Flylove.</stage>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Fly.</speaker>
                     <p>What a noiſe you make, I'm become a man of cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling now; who is't would ſpeak with me Sir.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Keep.</speaker>
                     <p>Here's a fair Lady, I'le leave you to your oppor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tunity.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <stage>Exit Keeper.</stage>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Fly.</speaker>
                     <p>Gramercy honeſt Keeper: How now, who's this? How my blood ſtartles in me on the ſudden?</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Bella.</speaker>
                     <p>What, do I fright you Sir? I come to ſee and com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fort you with my beſt love to file your Fetters off.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Fly.</speaker>
                     <l>Such charitable language, and ſuch face</l>
                     <l>Had beauteous <hi>Bellaflora,</hi> to whoſe ſoul</l>
                     <l>
                        <pb facs="tcp:114636:26"/>Mine was contracted, but my breach of vow,</l>
                     <l>Joyn'd with the infamy of this Ioath'd action,</l>
                     <l>So lately done, hath ſent her far from me;</l>
                     <l>This is the pleaſant widdow we met at <hi>Hogsdon,</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>I remember now;</l>
                     <l>But ſee how guilt will fool a man, I was</l>
                     <l>Admiring how you thought to finde me here.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Bella.</speaker>
                     <l>Some other time I'le tell you, if I may</l>
                     <l>(Without the breach of modeſt manners) ask you</l>
                     <l>What is the cauſe of your impriſonment?</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Fly.</speaker>
                     <p>What a queſtion's that? I'le lye ith' Compter all my life time, e're I make known the cauſe that laid me here, a toy, a trifle, for nothing but diſputing with the Conſtable, here's <hi>Jack, Wildblood</hi> and <hi>Frank Rivers</hi> in the houſe (three merry boys be we) here's the woman too, will you go ſee them.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Bella.</speaker>
                     <p>No Sir, but if the cauſe of your reſtraint from freedom be of that eaſie value, you'l be gone within an hour.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Fly.</speaker>
                     <p>I, I, within this hour at the fartheſt.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Bell.</speaker>
                     <l>Poor man, how thou deceiv'ſt me and thy ſelf,</l>
                     <stage>aſide</stage>
                     <l>I as much bluſh to let him underſtand</l>
                     <l>I know the cauſe of his affliction,</l>
                     <l>As he doth to reveal it; if you pleaſe</l>
                     <l>I'le ſtay till you go off.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Fly.</speaker>
                     <p>You may ſtay this twelve-month for ought <stage>aſide</stage> I know; I muſt put her off, to ſay the plain truth Lady I have an Action entred againſt me ſince I came in.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Bella.</speaker>
                     <p>You need not let that fright you, I have ſo much skill, although a very unexperienc'd woman to tell you, whilſt you are under the command of any Juſtice for the breach oth' peace, you are not lyable to any Action.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Fly.</speaker>
                     <p>She ſays true, where the Devil got you ſo much law?</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Bella.</speaker>
                     <p>Come, come, I know the cauſe that keeps you here.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Fly.</speaker>
                     <p>How! I am ſorry for that.</p>
                     <stage>aſide.</stage>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Bell.</speaker>
                     <p>Is't not a womans Action?</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Fly.</speaker>
                     <p>A womans Action.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Bell.</speaker>
                     <p>I have hit the mark, and I could name the party.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Fly.</speaker>
                     <p>Lady I'le take my leave, I'm call'd above.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Bella.</speaker>
                     <l>Indeed you are not Sir, pray ſtay a little,</l>
                     <l>I know you think the fact you have committed,</l>
                     <l>
                        <pb facs="tcp:114636:26"/>To be of that vile nature, that you bluſh</l>
                     <l>To tell or think I know it; you the leſs</l>
                     <l>Stand in my condemnation for the ill,</l>
                     <l>Becauſe 'twas acted on ſo much deformity,</l>
                     <l>It makes me think ſome Witchcraft, drink, or madneſs</l>
                     <l>Poſſeſt you at that time; they being remov'd,</l>
                     <l>Your penitence brings back your raviſht worth,</l>
                     <l>And you are man agen, but the nice winner</l>
                     <l>Of every fair one's a judicious ſinner,</l>
                     <l>And in that judgement multiplies each fact,</l>
                     <l>And findes his Tragedy in the laſt Act.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Fly.</speaker>
                     <p>This circumſtance confirms your knowledge of it, And I am ſorry.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Bell.</speaker>
                     <p>That I know't.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Fly.</speaker>
                     <p>Tis true.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Bella.</speaker>
                     <l>But if you pleaſe't ſhan't be the worſe for you,</l>
                     <l>Would I were beautiful enough to pleaſe you,</l>
                     <l>Or had a mind that you might think ſo fair,</l>
                     <l>To merit your beſt wiſhes in the bliſs</l>
                     <l>Of ſacred Wedlock, you ſhould then be ſure</l>
                     <l>To ſhake this bondage off.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Fly.</speaker>
                     <l>Pray let me pauſe.</l>
                     <l>My former raſhneſs may take licenſe for't;</l>
                     <l>I am in priſon, and the Law exacts</l>
                     <l>My body for a year; I could produce</l>
                     <l>Such bayl as is ſufficient for my freedom,</l>
                     <l>But I will periſh e'r I reveal my ſcandall;</l>
                     <l>This woman's fair, and hath a face ſo like</l>
                     <l>To one, whoſe memory I owe my being,</l>
                     <l>I know not what to anſwer; Then agen</l>
                     <l>'Tis for my freedom, from a bondage which</l>
                     <l>May ruine ſoul and body; I'm reſolv'd,</l>
                     <l>If <hi>Bellaflora</hi> knew it, ſo would ſhe,</l>
                     <l>And pardon all, which works my Liberty.</l>
                     <l>You do not ask me this to try me, do you?</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Bella.</speaker>
                     <p>No by thoſe joys I wiſh for.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Fly.</speaker>
                     <l>Nor tell me of my fact, or of your friendſhip,</l>
                     <l>At every angry occaſion,</l>
                     <l>Which the beſt married pair ſeldome avoid.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Bella.</speaker>
                     <l>May all my life be made of diſcontents,</l>
                     <l>And they in old age kill me, if I do:</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <pb facs="tcp:114636:27"/>
                     <speaker>Fly.</speaker>
                     <lg>
                        <l>How neer ſhe comes to <hi>Bellaflora</hi> ſtill,</l>
                        <l>In all her noble actions; If I could</l>
                        <l>Believe the Pythagorean axioms true,</l>
                        <l>Of tranſmigrated ſpirits, did the Grave</l>
                        <l>Contain my <hi>Bellaflora,</hi> I ſhould think</l>
                        <l>This frame contain'd her ſoul, the Gods would ſure</l>
                        <l>Conſume me, if this Contract I now make</l>
                        <l>And ſeal, this vertuous woman were not lawful:</l>
                     </lg>
                     <lg>
                        <l>By all the joys eternal, by the hopes</l>
                        <l>I have to live a life that's long and bleſt,</l>
                        <l>To ſee a numerous iſſue fairly bred</l>
                        <l>In all their actions, ſhewing ſtill the minds</l>
                        <l>Of their long ſleeping Anceſtors, I'le bee</l>
                        <l>Thy husband, love, and life, I'le marry thee.</l>
                     </lg>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Bella.</speaker>
                     <p>This day.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Fly.</speaker>
                     <p>This very day.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Within.</speaker>
                     <p>
                        <hi>Stephen Flylove,</hi> the Conſtable's come.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Keep.</speaker>
                     <p>Sir, the Conſtable waits for you.</p>
                     <stage>Ent. keeper.</stage>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Bella.</speaker>
                     <p>Delay not, ith' mean time I'le bayle you here, Remember Sir.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Fly.</speaker>
                     <p>I doe.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Bella.</speaker>
                     <p>Adieu my dear.</p>
                  </sp>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div n="5" type="act">
               <head>Actus quintus,</head>
               <div n="1" type="scene">
                  <head>Scaena prima.</head>
                  <stage>Enter Flyl. Bellafl. Rivers, Mrs. Trimwel and Wildblood.</stage>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Wild.</speaker>
                     <l>W<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>lcome to liberty my Cavaliers,</l>
                     <l>The gawdy portalIs of the red-cheekt morn,</l>
                     <l>Stand wide to entertain you, and delight</l>
                     <l>Your ſickned ſences with the bright diſplay</l>
                     <l>Of glittering Phoebus.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Rivers.</speaker>
                     <p>Your genius ſoars too high, you'l melt his wings.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Wild.</speaker>
                     <l>I am aiery as <hi>Philetus</hi> when he tripp'd</l>
                     <l>Over the ears of Corn, and ne'r bent head;</l>
                     <l>I could out-run <hi>Atlanta.</hi>
                     </l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Rivers.</speaker>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Atlanta?</hi> within theſe two hours a Cripple could</l>
                     <l>out-run thee, and give thee five in the fifteen:</l>
                     <l>But <hi>Stephen,</hi> why ſo ſtupid? rowſe thy ſpirit;</l>
                     <l>Can Liberty diſcomfort, or the exchange</l>
                     <l>
                        <pb facs="tcp:114636:27"/>Of grates for fragrant fields diſmay thee thus.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Fly.</speaker>
                     <p>Faith I am dull, and I ha' reaſon for't.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Wild.</speaker>
                     <p>What is the melancholly matter prethee?</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Fly.</speaker>
                     <p>That which will move you all when I ſhall ſpeak; <hi>Mercurio's</hi> dead.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Rivers.</speaker>
                     <p>Dead!</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Wild.</speaker>
                     <p>He was well laſt night.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Fly.</speaker>
                     <p>He dy'd this morning.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Wild.</speaker>
                     <p>Oh my poor loſt friend!</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Rivers.</speaker>
                     <p>His cruel Creditor is paid; Oh my <hi>Mercurio!</hi>
                     </p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Fly.</speaker>
                     <l>I knew 'twould dull you all as well as I,</l>
                     <l>This day his Funeral is, I hope you'l be</l>
                     <l>The ſad ſpectators of his Obſequies,</l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Raynard</hi> the Keeper will inſtruct you when,</l>
                     <l>And tell you more, pray go and leave me here,</l>
                     <l>I have a ſadneſs that concerns not you,</l>
                     <l>I'le put it off and meet ye.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Riv.</speaker>
                     <p>Good morrow <hi>Stephen.</hi>
                     </p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Wild.</speaker>
                     <p>Farewel friend.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Mrs. Trim.</speaker>
                     <p>Good morrow Mr. <hi>Flyl.</hi>
                     </p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Fly.</speaker>
                     <p>Your humble ſervant; Laday what ſtay you for?</p>
                     <stage>Exe.</stage>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Bella.</speaker>
                     <p>Where would you have me be?</p>
                     <stage>Riv. Wild. Mrs. T.</stage>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Fly.</speaker>
                     <p>Where you pleaſe; I can't command your being.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Bella.</speaker>
                     <l>What means my Love?</l>
                     <l>Your ſpeech betrays ſome diſcontent in you.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Fly.</speaker>
                     <p>Yes, I'm troubled, Oh my ſweet <hi>Bellaflora!</hi>
                     </p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Bella.</speaker>
                     <p>Who do you ſigh for Sir?</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Fly.</speaker>
                     <p>A friend, a friend, an honeſt friend of mine.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Bella.</speaker>
                     <p>This is a time to baniſh diſcontents.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Fly.</speaker>
                     <p>No, no, to increaſe them.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Bell.</speaker>
                     <p>It is an hour was made to conſecrate our holy contract</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Fly.</speaker>
                     <p>Why I, I told you ſo.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Bell.</speaker>
                     <p>Will you not marry me.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Fly.</speaker>
                     <l>I will not break my faith to <hi>Bellaflora</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>To gain a Queen, a Goddeſs.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Bella.</speaker>
                     <p>Then you have plighted faith unto another.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Fly.</speaker>
                     <p>Yes cunning temptreſs I have.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Bell.</speaker>
                     <l>Why do you blemiſh my well-meaning heart,</l>
                     <l>With ſuch a title?</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Fly.</speaker>
                     <l>Could your ſecurer ſubtilty preſume</l>
                     <l>On no deceit but this? Had you propos'd</l>
                     <l>Out of ſome Magazine of rarities,</l>
                     <l>Gold, Silver, Jewels, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>hough they were as precious</l>
                     <l>As <hi>Erephile's</hi> Bracelet (which ſhe ſold</l>
                     <l>
                        <pb facs="tcp:114636:28"/>Her dear affecting husband for) I had</l>
                     <l>Eſteem'd them all as nothing, but weak I</l>
                     <l>Too fond of (what I now curſe) Liberty,</l>
                     <l>Muſt ſell my peace, my life, and much I fear</l>
                     <l>My bliſs eternal.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Bella.</speaker>
                     <l>Oh you Angels, where</l>
                     <l>Lives there a faithful man, why did you make</l>
                     <l>This ſolemn Contract to me.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Fly.</speaker>
                     <l>'Twas a bad proteſtation, and the breach</l>
                     <l>Is better then performance, yet becauſe</l>
                     <l>You ſhall not ſay I cheated favours from you,</l>
                     <l>Reſign me to my priſon, where I'le live,</l>
                     <l>Onely with thinking of my <hi>Bellaflora,</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>Her very name ſhall purifie the ayre,</l>
                     <l>And make a dungeon grow as fragrant,</l>
                     <l>As Meadow Flowers in triumphant <hi>June.</hi>
                     </l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Bella.</speaker>
                     <l>Thou common man that doſt two contracts break,</l>
                     <l>I have ſo much to ſay, I cannot ſpeak.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <stage>Exit Bellaflora.</stage>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Fly.</speaker>
                     <l>Like men for Robberies that loſe their breath,</l>
                     <l>I leave the priſon to embrace my death.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <stage>Exit Flylove.</stage>
                  <stage>Enter Rivers and Mrs. Trimwel,</stage>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Mrs. Trim.</speaker>
                     <p>You are very wanton <hi>Frank.</hi>
                     </p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Rivers.</speaker>
                     <l>Now I have got thee ſingle, ſhall we try</l>
                     <l>An amorous duell for a boy now, I'm all fire,</l>
                     <l>And could perform an act 'bove <hi>Hercules;</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>Glue thy red lips to mine, and let us prove,</l>
                     <l>The jocund pleaſure of the billing Dove.</l>
                     <stage>They kiſs.</stage>
                     <l>Agen, once more, you do not do it heartily,</l>
                     <l>We'l make a numeration from a kiſs,</l>
                     <l>Shall poſe Arithmatick.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Mrs. Trim.</speaker>
                     <p>You'l tell of this.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Riv.</speaker>
                     <p>Steal, and reveal; he's a bold thief indeed.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Mrs. Trim.</speaker>
                     <l>There are too many ſuch.</l>
                     <l>They cannot have a favour, — ſuch a one.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Rivers.</speaker>
                     <p>I, ſuch a one.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Mrs. Trim.</speaker>
                     <l>As you imagine, but they muſt reveal it,</l>
                     <l>As if it were a ſecond ſporf to tell it.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Rivers.</speaker>
                     <l>They glory in their actions, and would prove</l>
                     <l>How much they merit by their Ladies love;</l>
                     <l>This I diſdain.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <pb facs="tcp:114636:28"/>
                     <speaker>Mrs. Trim.</speaker>
                     <p>Do ye uſe to talk in your ſleep, you'l tell it to your bed-fellow.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Riv.</speaker>
                     <p>You are too jealous of me.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Mrs. Trim.</speaker>
                     <l>Come then, I'le try thee; kiſs me,</l>
                     <l>That's the firſt peal to bed, but I won't truſt ye.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Rivers.</speaker>
                     <p>Why do you mock me thus?</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Mrs. Trim.</speaker>
                     <l>The cauſe being ſo great, I may be doubtful,</l>
                     <l>You'l have another Love, then out goes all,</l>
                     <l>But uſe your will.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Rivers.</speaker>
                     <p>To do thy will a pleaſure, ſhall we be private.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Mrs. Trim.</speaker>
                     <p>As private as you pleaſe.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Rivers.</speaker>
                     <p>Such privacie beſt pleaſeth.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Mrs. Trim.</speaker>
                     <p>Come let's away then.</p>
                     <stage>They offer to off.</stage>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Rivers.</speaker>
                     <p>Stay (upon better thought) I have <stage>Riv. returns.</stage> No ſuch deſire to't.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Mrs. Trim.</speaker>
                     <p>How?</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Riv.</speaker>
                     <p>Prethee be not angry, I am very loath to go to hell ſo eaſily.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Mrs. Trim.</speaker>
                     <p>What pretty change is this?</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Riv.</speaker>
                     <p>I would it pleas'd you, pray ſatisfie one thought and I am for you.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Mrs. Trim.</speaker>
                     <p>Willingly.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Riv.</speaker>
                     <p>And truly.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Mrs. Trim.</speaker>
                     <p>By my life I will.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Riv.</speaker>
                     <l>Did never ſilken Gallant with queint words,</l>
                     <l>A fair proportion'd body, and ſmooth chin,</l>
                     <l>Such as you women like, tempt you to this,</l>
                     <l>This feat, before I mov'd you.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Mrs. Trim.</speaker>
                     <p>Never.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Riv.</speaker>
                     <p>Never, prethee bethink thy ſelf, you doubt me ſtill.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Mrs. Trim.</speaker>
                     <p>But you ſuſpect me more, I vow never.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Riv.</speaker>
                     <l>How fain would I believe thee, if thou ſwear'ſt true,</l>
                     <l>Thou'rt fitter far for Heaven then this act,</l>
                     <l>Which thou ſhalt ne'r be guilty of for me;</l>
                     <l>What pitty 'tis to take fair new blancht Lawn,</l>
                     <l>And ſprinkle ink on't; let not your husbands doubts,</l>
                     <l>Bred by your frequent abſence, and ſuch howers</l>
                     <l>Civility ne'r warranted, urge you</l>
                     <l>To acts that cauſe his ſhame, and your own ſhame.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Mrs. Trim.</speaker>
                     <p>Whats' your intent for this.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Riv.</speaker>
                     <l>I'le tel you.</l>
                     <l>The guilty giddy people, who conceive</l>
                     <l>All acts more vile then they appear,</l>
                     <l>Have ſpred an infamy upon us both,</l>
                     <l>Which if unquell'd, in time will fix a ſtain,</l>
                     <l>
                        <pb facs="tcp:114636:29"/>(though cauſleſs) which no Rethorick can charm</l>
                     <l>To alteration; thus in brief I'le do,</l>
                     <l>By a moſt queint invention I have thought,</l>
                     <l>I ſhall return you to your husband, who</l>
                     <l>Shall with his love, not jealouſie, embrace you,</l>
                     <l>And to the bold ears of the rumorous world,</l>
                     <l>Declare his errour, and your innocence.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Mrs. Trim.</speaker>
                     <l>A very modeſt way to do me miſchief,</l>
                     <l>I thank you for your love, your honeſt love.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Rivers.</speaker>
                     <p>That you'l confeſs hereafter, will you go?</p>
                  </sp>
                  <stage>Exit</stage>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Mrs. Trim.</speaker>
                     <l>Yes Sir, I'le wait on you;</l>
                     <l>Am I betray'd by tricks? a Letter op'd,</l>
                     <l>The ſecret read, and then ſeal'd up agen?</l>
                     <l>Inquiſitive fool, thy dear experience ſhall</l>
                     <l>Inſtruct thee, what a fate he undergoes,</l>
                     <l>That turns the fierce ſtream of a womans love:</l>
                     <l>I could be leſs impatient had he ſpoke</l>
                     <l>From knowledge of my guilt, then know my will,</l>
                     <l>And afterwards diſcloſe me; well I'le diſguiſe my anger,</l>
                     <l>And frame a fierce revenge ſhall make thee tremble,</l>
                     <l>Women act miſchief ſure when they diſſemble.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <stage>Exit.</stage>
               </div>
               <div n="2" type="scene">
                  <head>
                     <hi>Act.</hi> 3. <hi>Scaen.</hi> 2.</head>
                  <stage>Enter Mr. Nice and Splendora.</stage>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Nice.</speaker>
                     <p>Is the French Knight in priſon, what is his debt?</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Splen.</speaker>
                     <p>Six thouſand pound they ſay Sir.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Nice.</speaker>
                     <l>Tis a great ſum I have been wrong enform'd,</l>
                     <l>'Twas credibly reported on the Change,</l>
                     <l>He had a free eſtate, his Traffick great,</l>
                     <l>A moſt unqueſtion'd credit; and doth all</l>
                     <l>Conclude in this, they did not mean me well</l>
                     <l>That tempted my belief thus.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Splend.</speaker>
                     <p>Shall my ſuit have gracious hearing yet Sir?</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Nice.</speaker>
                     <l>What for <hi>Mercurio?</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>Becauſe I was ſo neer to be deceiv'd,</l>
                     <l>With the feign'd riches of a Bankerupt,</l>
                     <l>Would you betray your ſelf to certain beggery.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Splen.</speaker>
                     <l>Will you be pleas'd to free him from his bondage?</l>
                     <l>It is reported he is ſick, that place</l>
                     <l>Will kill him, where is then your ſatisfaction?</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <pb facs="tcp:114636:29"/>
                     <speaker>Nice.</speaker>
                     <l>He cannot want a friend for twenty pound,</l>
                     <l>I will not loſe my money, I'le take time,</l>
                     <l>If he can fit me with ſecurity.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Splen.</speaker>
                     <p>Alas he is not able.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <stage>Enter Mercurio on a Hearſe, four Bearers (as Mourners) Wild. Riv. Flyl. Mrs. Trim. Raynard, Pimpwel. They ſet the Coffin before Nice, and Flylove makes an Oration.</stage>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Nice.</speaker>
                     <l>What are theſe; heark you friend, whoſe body's this?</l>
                     <l>And whither carry you it?</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Fly.</speaker>
                     <l>Here Sir our journey ends,</l>
                     <l>It is the body of deceas'd <hi>Mercurio,</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>A priſoner at your ſuit, who dyed this morning,</l>
                     <l>And thus according to an ancient cuſtome,</l>
                     <l>We bear him to you (all that's left)</l>
                     <l>His bones to make you ſatisfaction,</l>
                     <l>Becauſe his poverty enforc'd him (living)</l>
                     <l>To keep your right from you; withall, our form</l>
                     <l>Is to deliver to the Creditor,</l>
                     <l>At whoſe peculiar ſuit the debtor dyes,— A bale of Dice.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Nice.</speaker>
                     <p>Strange cuſtom; Heaven! now it doth amaze me.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Fly.</speaker>
                     <l>I have a little ſpeech that muſt excuſe</l>
                     <l>The expences of a bought Oration, which concerns</l>
                     <l>His miſerable end, and cauſe of it, and I have done.</l>
                     <stage>She ſowns.</stage>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Splen.</speaker>
                     <p>Oh my <hi>Mercurio.</hi>
                     </p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Riv.</speaker>
                     <p>Look to the Lady.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Fly.</speaker>
                     <l>When he came in he wanted all that makes</l>
                     <l>Man in this Age ſubſtantial (Friends and Coyn)</l>
                     <l>Which want was ſoon attended with theſe, neglect &amp; hunger</l>
                     <l>But then the perturbations of his minde,</l>
                     <l>His ſighing ſilence onely could declare,</l>
                     <l>As if they were too vaſt for elocution;</l>
                     <l>Great griefs are tongue-ty'd, there's no clamour rear'd,</l>
                     <l>So deepeſt waters crawl along unheard.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Nice.</speaker>
                     <l>Moſt reverend piece of ſorrow, whoſe wet eyes</l>
                     <l>Drop, as they would command another Spring,</l>
                     <l>To raiſe the body from its earthly ruine,</l>
                     <l>To heat and life agen; what friendſhip had you with him?</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Fly.</speaker>
                     <l>Sir, I am one,</l>
                     <l>That wiſh I had ſuch neerneſs to his vertue,</l>
                     <l>As to his blood; a poor unhappy Kinſman.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <pb facs="tcp:114636:30"/>
                     <speaker>Nice.</speaker>
                     <l>There's ſo much Magick in your ſorrow Sir,</l>
                     <l>All my attentions charm'd.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Fly.</speaker>
                     <l>Like men who are neer drowning, catch weak hold</l>
                     <l>On broken boords, on ſedge, or any thing</l>
                     <l>Diſaſtrous chance betrays to the wild waves,</l>
                     <l>He ſends for me that could but grieve his ſight,</l>
                     <l>With the wet ſorrow in my eyes for him:</l>
                     <l>Inſtead of Chambers hung with Tapeſtry,</l>
                     <l>Arras, and Attick pictures, the dark walls</l>
                     <l>Are eaſly beautifi'd with Chalk and Cole,</l>
                     <l>According to the melancholly fancy</l>
                     <l>Of the ſad Priſoners, where the numerous beds</l>
                     <l>Shew like ſo many Graves in a Churchyard,</l>
                     <l>With the men riſing out: No Canopies</l>
                     <l>But what the charitable Spider wove,</l>
                     <l>To ſave their always watching eyes from danger,</l>
                     <l>For they'r un-us'd to ſleep.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Nice.</speaker>
                     <p>Alas poor men.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Fly.</speaker>
                     <l>In ſuch a ſtate as this my kinſman lay,</l>
                     <l>My poor, poor kinſman.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Nice.</speaker>
                     <p>Thou weep'ſt too faſt old man, I ſhal not overtake thee.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Fly.</speaker>
                     <l>I figh'd, ſate down by him, and did obſerve</l>
                     <l>The manner of his Chamber-mates, and one</l>
                     <l>Belov'd above the reſt, as it appear'd,</l>
                     <l>Was cheriſht with a friend that happy day,</l>
                     <l>Who ſaid he came to ſee him, could not ſtay,</l>
                     <l>Although ſome Meſſenger fix times had been</l>
                     <l>To fetch him, but in vain, was ne'r within</l>
                     <l>After he heard the buſineſs, though his eare</l>
                     <l>Was within hearing of the Meſſenger:</l>
                     <l>At laſt he was within, without all doubt,</l>
                     <l>Becauſe he heard the priſoners going out,</l>
                     <l>Gives him a ſhilling, bids him have good cheer,</l>
                     <l>He was glad to ſee him, ſorry to ſee him here,</l>
                     <l>And ſo he parts, proteſting for to come,</l>
                     <l>He knows not when, this is his wretched doom</l>
                     <l>Of undone debtors, and my kinſmans Tomb.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Nice.</speaker>
                     <l>Since bleeding cleanſeth veins, I hope to finde</l>
                     <l>Th'expence of tears will purifie the minde:</l>
                     <l>What is this writing Sir?</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <pb facs="tcp:114636:30"/>
                     <speaker>Fly.</speaker>
                     <l>'Tis his own hand,</l>
                     <l>One hour befor his death he writ Epitaph.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Nice.</speaker>
                     <p>With his own hand? pray read it.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Fly.</speaker>
                     <p>I ſhall Sir.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <lg>
                     <head>EPITAPH.</head>
                     <l>I which once with life did move,</l>
                     <l>Here lye Coffin'd up, to prove</l>
                     <l>Till death I was <hi>Splendora's</hi> Love.</l>
                  </lg>
                  <lg>
                     <l>I that have with many groans,</l>
                     <l>And wet eyes waſht the priſon ſtones,</l>
                     <l>For want of Money, pay my bones.</l>
                  </lg>
                  <lg>
                     <l>Let none with exclamation call,</l>
                     <l>Upon my name, and ſcorn my fall,</l>
                     <l>I ow'd but little, and paid all.</l>
                  </lg>
                  <stage>Mercurie.</stage>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Nice.</speaker>
                     <l>Thou haſt paid all indeed, thy breath and all,</l>
                     <l>Iſ't were no fin I could beſtow a wiſh,</l>
                     <l>That life would viſit theſe cold corps agen.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Fly.</speaker>
                     <l>Where ſhall we bury him Sir, the cuſtome is</l>
                     <l>To bury men in debt ith' New-Churchyard;</l>
                     <l>Shall we diſpoſe him there?</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Nice.</speaker>
                     <l>No, ſince he's dead he ſhall be well interr'd,</l>
                     <l>Though half my eſtate waſte for it, I have cauſe,</l>
                     <l>He lov'd <hi>Splendora,</hi> poor Girl ſhe'l dye too;</l>
                     <l>To your charge I commit this forty pound,</l>
                     <stage>Gives Rivers the Bag</stage>
                     <l>To provide mourning; I'le have Surgeons ſtrait,</l>
                     <l>That ſhall embalm the body.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <stage>Exit Rivers.</stage>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Fly.</speaker>
                     <l>You ſhew your ſelf a noble Gentleman,</l>
                     <l>Whoſe memory we'l pray for; here <hi>Frank</hi> diſpatch.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Rivers.</speaker>
                     <p>It ſhall be done.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Fly.</speaker>
                     <l>Sir, here be Gentlemen that lov'd him, are</l>
                     <l>Willing to expreſs their loves, they have a Dirge.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Nice.</speaker>
                     <p>They are welcom, I'le attend their ceremony<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
                     </p>
                  </sp>
                  <stage>
                     <hi>They ſing. The Dirge.</hi>
                     <l>FRom ſelling, or from mortgaging of Lands,</l>
                     <l>From turning over goods in others hands,</l>
                     <l>And from the ſetting of our marks to bands.</l>
                  </stage>
                  <stage>Omnes Cant. Libera nos Domine.</stage>
                  <stage>
                     <l>From cruelty that keeps good men in awe,</l>
                     <l>From Serjeants, and ſuch Griffins of the Law,</l>
                     <l>And from the chattering of an Yeild-hall Daw.</l>
                  </stage>
                  <stage>Libera nos Domine.</stage>
                  <stage>
                     <pb facs="tcp:114636:31"/>
                     <l>From living at a miſerable rate,</l>
                     <l>In priſon where all people are ingrate;</l>
                     <l>And from the Porters at the Compter gate.</l>
                  </stage>
                  <stage>Libera nos Domine.</stage>
                  <stage>
                     <l>From being dragg'd in there with cruel gripes,</l>
                     <l>By an old curſed Catchpole called <hi>Tripes,</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>From paying for our Candles and our Pipes,</l>
                  </stage>
                  <stage>Libera nos Domine.</stage>
                  <stage>
                     <l>Next from the Stocks, the Hole, and Little-eaſe,</l>
                     <l>Sad places, which kind Nature do diſpleaſe,</l>
                     <l>And from the ratling of the Keepers Keys,</l>
                  </stage>
                  <stage>Libera nos Domine.</stage>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Fly.</speaker>
                     <p>Is all perform'd?</p>
                     <stage>Enter Rivers<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
                     </stage>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Riv.</speaker>
                     <p>To a tittle, here's a diſcharge from the Office.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Fly.</speaker>
                     <l>Then riſe from thy dead ſleep thou man of care,</l>
                     <l>Thy debt is paid, there's joyful news for thee.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Nice.</speaker>
                     <p>Am I deluded,</p>
                  </sp>
                  <stage>Enter Splend.</stage>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Fly.</speaker>
                     <l>Not a jot, come old man embrace him for your ſon,</l>
                     <l>Though he be poor, he is a Gentleman, and meritorious.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Splend.</speaker>
                     <p>But art thou living?</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Nice.</speaker>
                     <p>I, you know it well enough, you ſhall even go toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther for your plots, I have paid my ſelf it ſeems.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Rivers.</speaker>
                     <p>Your Money lies ith' Office Sir.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Nice.</speaker>
                     <p>'Tis very well, who comes here?</p>
                     <stage>Ent. Trimwel.</stage>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Wild.</speaker>
                     <p>Ware ho! here comes a mad man.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Trim.</speaker>
                     <l>Yes, a horn-mad man, Myruon are you there?</l>
                     <l>And your Sweetheart <hi>Rivers,</hi> I muſt part you;</l>
                     <l>Unhand him impudence.</l>
                     <stage>Rivers draws.</stage>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Riv.</speaker>
                     <p>Sir, if you lay a violent hand on her, I touch your heart.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Trim.</speaker>
                     <l>Gentlemen, Is there law or conſcience in this?</l>
                     <l>To keep a mans wife, as they ſay, in ſpight on's teeth.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Mrs. Trim.</speaker>
                     <p>
                        <hi>F. Rivers</hi> is more kind then I expected,</p>
                     <stage>aſide</stage>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Rivers.</speaker>
                     <l>Your jealouſie hath wrackt her vertuous name,</l>
                     <l>And by my life ſhe's free from actual ill.</l>
                     <l>As e're thy mother was.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Mrs Trim.</speaker>
                     <p>He'l ne'r believe you,</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Rivers.</speaker>
                     <l>No, he ſhall I warrant you,</l>
                     <l>E're I commit her to your curſed uſage,</l>
                     <l>I'l ſee ſome reformation of your life.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Trim.</speaker>
                     <p>You'l ſee't.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <pb facs="tcp:114636:31"/>
                     <speaker>Rivers.</speaker>
                     <l>Yes Sir, I'le ſee't.</l>
                     <l>My Mothers daughter ſhall not be expos'd</l>
                     <l>Unto your giddy humors.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Trim.</speaker>
                     <p>Your Mothers daughter?</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Riv.</speaker>
                     <p>Yes Sir, my Siſter.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Mrs. Trim.</speaker>
                     <p>What trick is this?</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Trim.</speaker>
                     <p>Pray what may I call your name Sir.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Rivers.</speaker>
                     <l>I never fear'd it, though I have diſguis'd it,</l>
                     <l>For ſome ends which beſt concern my ſelf,</l>
                     <l>Before I went to <hi>France,</hi> men that would know</l>
                     <l>By my own name to call me, call'd me <hi>Brooks.</hi>
                     </l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Mrs. Trim.</speaker>
                     <p>My brother <hi>Frederick?</hi>
                     </p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Rivers.</speaker>
                     <p>The ſame Siſter; I muſt talk with you.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Trim.</speaker>
                     <p>Oh, my ſhame! Brother I hope you'l forgive me.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Rivers.</speaker>
                     <p>This is no time nor place for our contention.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Nice.</speaker>
                     <p>Who comes here?</p>
                     <stage>Enter Bellaflora richly attired.</stage>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Fly.</speaker>
                     <l>Either my eyes deceive me, or here comes</l>
                     <l>The form of <hi>Bellaflora.</hi>
                     </l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Bella.</speaker>
                     <p>What do you gaze? Do you not know me Sir?</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Fly.</speaker>
                     <p>Yes ſure, I know you; Are not you Bellaflora?</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Bella.</speaker>
                     <p>That is my name.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Fly.</speaker>
                     <p>I know it is, but were not you diſguis'd, and call'd <hi>Fairchaſte?</hi>
                     </p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Bell.</speaker>
                     <p>I remember your amorous Alphabet.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Fly.</speaker>
                     <p>O my ſtrange excellent fortune; can you forgive all?</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Bella.</speaker>
                     <p>Yes, and ſeal my ſelf thy own for ever.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Wild.</speaker>
                     <p>My dear Couſin.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Bella.</speaker>
                     <p>How Sir?</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Fly.</speaker>
                     <p>Tis ſo indeed, the <hi>Wildblood's</hi> out, this is your couſin <hi>Worthlove.</hi>
                     </p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Bell.</speaker>
                     <p>Welcome from <hi>France</hi> good Couſin.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Wild.</speaker>
                     <p>Fair couſin I thank thee, this unity contents me.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Riv.</speaker>
                     <p>As I live here's <hi>Sir</hi> R. <hi>Lamard</hi> that broke the priſon, how the devil dares he venter.</p>
                     <stage>Ent. Sir Reverence.</stage>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Sir Rev.</speaker>
                     <p>Be your leave Zhentelmen, room for <hi>Sir Reveren.</hi> who be come to claim his Lady, his Madam.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Nice.</speaker>
                     <p>How came you out of priſon Sir.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Sir Rev.</speaker>
                     <p>Begar me pay de mony, and now me come to your dautera.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Nice.</speaker>
                     <p>Now you have paid away your mony, the truth is, Sir ſhe is diſpos'd of to another.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Keep.</speaker>
                     <p>And we'l diſpoſe of you that can break priſons.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Sir Rev.</speaker>
                     <p>Begar here be de Keeper, vat fall me do now?</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <pb facs="tcp:114636:32"/>
                     <speaker>Pim.</speaker>
                     <p>Nay, you'r faſt enough, we'l take an order for your ſli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Sir Rev.</speaker>
                     <p>Zhentelmen vill no man be my bayl?</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Nice.</speaker>
                     <p>The ſum is too great for me.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Sir Rev.</speaker>
                     <p>Pray Zhentelmen.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Fly.</speaker>
                     <p>Not I.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Rivers.</speaker>
                     <p>Nor I.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Wild.</speaker>
                     <p>Nor I.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Keep.</speaker>
                     <p>Come Sir, you muſt to priſon agen.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Sir Rev.</speaker>
                     <p>Mus, begar me vill not.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Pimpw.</speaker>
                     <p>Then we muſt force you Sir.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Sir Rev.</speaker>
                     <l>You Pimping rogue, why do you tug me thus?</l>
                     <l>You know me well enough.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Pim.</speaker>
                     <p>What is your tongue chang'd, what tricks have you?</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Sir Rev.</speaker>
                     <p>I'le ſpeak with Mr. <hi>Nice.</hi> Pray Sir, peruſe that Picture and Letter.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Nice.</speaker>
                     <p>'Tis my wives picture ſure; <hi>Splendora,</hi> was not this your Mothers picture?</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Splend.</speaker>
                     <p>Yes Sir, the very ſame ſhe gave my brother, when he went to <hi>Paris.</hi>
                     </p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Nice</speaker>
                     <p>And this my hand, the Letter that I ſent him.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Sir Rev.</speaker>
                     <p>And I your ſon, come to crave a bleſſing.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Nice.</speaker>
                     <p>And with my heart thou haſt it.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Riv.</speaker>
                     <p>
                        <hi>Will Nice.</hi>
                     </p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Sir Rev.</speaker>
                     <p>Mr. <hi>Brooks</hi> your ſervant.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Fly.</speaker>
                     <p>Noble Mr. <hi>Nice.</hi>
                     </p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Sir Rev.</speaker>
                     <p>Hah, my politick <hi>Stephen.</hi>
                     </p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Fly.</speaker>
                     <p>No, my politick <hi>William.</hi>
                     </p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Wild.</speaker>
                     <p>Sir I am yours, and joy to ſee you in <hi>England.</hi>
                     </p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Splend.</speaker>
                     <p>Welcome to <hi>London</hi> brother, you can court a Lady moſt exactly in broken French.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Sir Rev.</speaker>
                     <p>I am glad it pleas'd you ſiſter; Keepers I'le quit you preſently, that Action which was entred was a plot of mine, to have my father match this Gentleman with my kind ſiſter; there's no danger in't I can aſſure you.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Keep.</speaker>
                     <p>Well, I'm contented Sir.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Nice.</speaker>
                     <p>You are wags I ſee; were you ſent ſeven years ago <hi>France,</hi> and come agen to cozen your friends, but Heaven be your joy. Come, cannot you expreſs a little of your French action with theſe Ladies, ſhall we not have a Dance?</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Fly.</speaker>
                     <p>And very fit, methinks the time requires it.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Rivers.</speaker>
                     <p>With all my heart.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Wild.</speaker>
                     <p>And mine.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Fly.</speaker>
                     <p>Every man take his Lady then.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <stage>They Dance.</stage>
                  <sp>
                     <pb facs="tcp:114636:32"/>
                     <speaker>Nice.</speaker>
                     <p>Gentlemen, y'have done exceeding well; if you pleaſe to walk in, Dinner at this hour waits for you.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Fly.</speaker>
                     <p>Come my mad merry Mates and fellow-Travellers, let's in and chat the ſtory of our Travels, the tricks of our Diſguiſes, with the queint and jovial Humours which we have found ith' Compter.</p>
                     <l>To marry and be civill our next care is,</l>
                     <l>We now have done enough for Youths Fegaries.</l>
                  </sp>
               </div>
            </div>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
      <back>
         <div type="epilogue">
            <head>Epilogue.</head>
            <lg>
               <l>WEll; How is't now? we heard you laugh, but pray.</l>
               <l>Was it at us, the Poet, or the Play?</l>
               <l>The Poet's full of joy though, to the brim,</l>
               <l>And ſayes, he's ſure ye do not laugh at him;</l>
               <l>Becauſe, he findes you onely laugh at that,</l>
               <l>Which he deſires may be worth laughing at:</l>
               <l>And then he heard you Clap; that Verdict ſtands</l>
               <l>In Law, he hath it under all your hands;</l>
               <l>Vnleſs when we were freed from <hi>Woodſtreet Den,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>You had a plot to Clap us up agen:</l>
               <l>But waving all, we (without more ſuſpence)</l>
               <l>Accept your Clapping in the better ſenſe.</l>
               <l>This is the ſum, I have no more to ſay,</l>
               <l>Either for Poet, Actors, or the Play:</l>
               <l>If his dull Humours pleaſe not, we implore,</l>
               <l>That you'l go all toth' <hi>Compter</hi> and ſee more.</l>
            </lg>
         </div>
         <div type="note">
            <p>THis Comedy, called, <hi>The Walks of Iſling ton and Hogsdon, With the Humours of Woodſtreet-Compter,</hi> may be Acted: This 2. Auguſt, 1641.</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>Henry Herbert.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </back>
   </text>
</TEI>
