<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>The enchanted lovers: a pastoral / by Sr. William Lower Knight.</title>
            <author>Lower, William, Sir, 1600?-1662.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1658</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 151 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 52 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-12">2011-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A88624</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing L3314</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Thomason E1905_1</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R210000</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99868842</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99868842</idno>
            <idno type="VID">170544</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A88624)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 170544)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Thomason Tracts ; 236:E1905[1])</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>The enchanted lovers: a pastoral / by Sr. William Lower Knight.</title>
                  <author>Lower, William, Sir, 1600?-1662.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>104 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed by Adrian Vlack,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>Hage :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1658.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>With an engraved title. Cf. Greg.</note>
                  <note>A slip bearing three lines of text which were inadvertently omitted, is pasted at the bottom of D12v.</note>
                  <note>Annotation on Thomason copy: "June".</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the British Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Pastoral drama, English --  17th century.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2009-12</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-12</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-01</date>
            <label>Kayla Ondracek</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-10</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Rekeyed and resubmitted</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-11</date>
            <label>Kayla Ondracek</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-11</date>
            <label>Kayla Ondracek</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-06</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:170544:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>THE ENCHANTED LOVERS: A PASTORAL By S<hi rend="sup">r.</hi> WILLIAM LOWER Knight.</p>
            <q>Amico Roſa, Inimco Spina.</q>
            <p>HAGE: Printed by ADRIAN VLACK, 1658.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="dramatis_personae">
            <pb facs="tcp:170544:2"/>
            <head>ACTORS.</head>
            <list>
               <item>
                  <label>Therſander.</label> A Cavalier diſguiſed in the ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bit of a Shepheard in love with Diana.</item>
               <item>
                  <label>Thimantes.</label> Diſguiſed alſo in the habit of a Shepheard in love with Iſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>menia.</item>
               <item>
                  <label>Clidamant.</label> Diſguiſed alſo in the habit of a Shepheard in love with Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thenia.</item>
               <item>
                  <label>Melnitus.</label> A Shepheard of the Iland in love with Diana.</item>
               <item>
                  <label>Mercator.</label> — A Merchant of Sevil.</item>
               <item>
                  <label>Diana.</label> A young Lady diſguiſed in the habit of a Shepheardeſſe</item>
               <item>
                  <label>Parthenia.</label> Neece to the Princeſs, in love with Clidamant.</item>
               <item>
                  <label>Iſmenia.</label> A young Lady diſguiſed in the habit of a Shepheardeſs.</item>
               <item>
                  <label>Moliſſa.</label> The Princeſs of the Iſland, and Inchantreſs, in love with Therſander.</item>
            </list>
            <p>The Goddeſs <hi>Diana.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>The Scene is in the Iland of Erithrea in Portugal.</hi>
            </p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="pastoral">
            <pb facs="tcp:170544:2"/>
            <head>THE ENCHANTED LOVERS. A PASTORAL.</head>
            <div n="1" type="act">
               <head>ACTUS I.</head>
               <div type="scene">
                  <head>SCENE I. MERCATOR, MELINTUS.</head>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>MERCATOR.</speaker>
                     <l>IF you have any ſervice to command me</l>
                     <l>At <hi>Sevil,</hi> honour me with your Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſſion,</l>
                     <l>To morrow I embarke, and leave the Ile,</l>
                     <l>Until you Mart returns, and games renue.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>MELINTUS.</speaker>
                     <l>But firſt you'l kiſſe the fair hands of the Nimph,</l>
                     <l>And take her paſport with you?</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>MERCATOR.</speaker>
                     <l>That's a duty</l>
                     <l>I dare not fail in, though my intereſt</l>
                     <l>Were not concern'd in't. I intend this day</l>
                     <pb n="6" facs="tcp:170544:3"/>
                     <l>To carry her my casket of my richeſt</l>
                     <l>And choiceſt merchandiſe; when she hath bought</l>
                     <l>What beſt pleaſeth her fancy, I shall be</l>
                     <l>Diſmiſt, having no more commodities</l>
                     <l>To ſell unto the Shepheards of her Court.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>MELINTUS.</speaker>
                     <p>Have you ſold well?</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>MERCATOR.</speaker>
                     <l>To what end should I feign?</l>
                     <l>The trade goes well enough, I complain not:</l>
                     <l>Rich Rubies, Pearls of price, bright Diamonds,</l>
                     <l>Store of fair Coral, coſtly Amber-greece,</l>
                     <l>Portraits, and other ſuch dainty deviſes,</l>
                     <l>Have paſſed through my fingers at good rates:</l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Diana's</hi> feſtival is ſtill kept ſolemn;</l>
                     <l>And as the games which fail not every year</l>
                     <l>To be renu'd, invite unto thoſe woods</l>
                     <l>The neighbouring Shepheards, to diſpute the prizes</l>
                     <l>Propoſed on thoſe dayes, I ſaw among them</l>
                     <l>Some noble ſtrangers clad in paſtoral weeds</l>
                     <l>That for the honour of this Iſland choſe it</l>
                     <l>Their ſanctuary and repoſe.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>MELINTUS.</speaker>
                     <l>You need not</l>
                     <l>Wonder at this, the place which they have choſen</l>
                     <l>Denotes their judgments; here ambition</l>
                     <l>Hath no imployment; if at any time</l>
                     <l>We ſigh here, 'tis for love, no other paſſion</l>
                     <l>Is ſeen among us; though this Iſland be</l>
                     <l>A part of <hi>Portugal,</hi> we have our laws,</l>
                     <l>And Empire to our ſelves; she that rules here</l>
                     <l>Hath not the name of Queen, we ſubjects are</l>
                     <l>Our Soveraigns companions, and her vertue</l>
                     <l>Makes us to taſte ſo much repoſe, that she</l>
                     <pb n="7" facs="tcp:170544:3"/>
                     <l>Hath put the Sheephook into the hands of</l>
                     <l>A hundred Hero's, who wearied with Lawrels,</l>
                     <l>And the noiſe of the war, are here retir'd</l>
                     <l>From the four corners of the World: She rules</l>
                     <l>So ſweetly, that crime onely feels her anger.</l>
                     <l>And as she is deſcended from the blood</l>
                     <l>Of <hi>Zoroaſtres,</hi> she knows well the vertue</l>
                     <l>Of Herbs, and th' influence of every ſtar;</l>
                     <l>She underſtands the ſecret miſteries</l>
                     <l>Of Magick, and ſometimes makes uſe of it</l>
                     <l>To ſerve her intereſts; there is no Prince</l>
                     <l>Nor Monarch that ſtands not in fear of her.</l>
                     <l>And ſuffereth her not to raign in peace</l>
                     <l>For his own ſafety.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>MERCATOR.</speaker>
                     <l>I know this Aſyle,</l>
                     <l>And charming reſidence looks not with envy</l>
                     <l>Upon the Court o' th' King of <hi>Portugal;</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>Beſides I am not ignorant that the fair</l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Iſmenia,</hi> drawn here, by the ſweet report,</l>
                     <l>Of theſe inchanting pleaſures, to enjoy them</l>
                     <l>In quiet, left the favour of her Queen;</l>
                     <l>And that this beauty by a ſudden change,</l>
                     <l>Adds no ſmall luſtre to this Paradiſe.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>MELINTUS.</speaker>
                     <l>See where she comes, <hi>Diana</hi> too with her,</l>
                     <l>I muſt in private ſpeak unto this fair one;</l>
                     <l>An intereſt of love obligeth me</l>
                     <l>Continually to make her my devotions.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>MERCATOR.</speaker>
                     <l>Go Sir, and proſper, may your Saint prove ſweet</l>
                     <l>And gentle as thoſe South-gales I expect</l>
                     <l>In my embarkment.— <stage>Exit <hi>Mercator.</hi>
                        </stage>
                     </l>
                  </sp>
               </div>
               <div type="scene">
                  <pb facs="tcp:170544:4"/>
                  <head>SCENA II. DIANA, MELINTUS, IS MENIA. DIANA not ſeeing MELINTUS.</head>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>DIANA.</speaker>
                     <l>TRue, I hate that horrid noiſe;</l>
                     <l>Now my free thought releas'd from ſuch a trouble,</l>
                     <l>Enjoyes it ſelf.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>MELINTUS to DIANA.</speaker>
                     <l>So ſoon to quit the ſports,</l>
                     <l>What was your fancy?</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>DIANA.</speaker>
                     <l>To avoid diſcourſe</l>
                     <l>That troubled me, and here I meet with new.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>MELINTUS.</speaker>
                     <l>Can ſuch a ſubject as brings homage to you,</l>
                     <l>Produce th' effect you ſpeak?</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>DIANA.</speaker>
                     <l>What doth not pleaſe me,</l>
                     <l>Both troubles and offends me.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>MELINTUS.</speaker>
                     <l>You will one day</l>
                     <l>Quit thoſe diſdainful rigours?</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>DIANA.</speaker>
                     <l>Yes, when you</l>
                     <l>Have neither hope, nor love.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>MELINTUS.</speaker>
                     <l>D'ye entertain</l>
                     <l>Every one thus that loves you?</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>DIANA.</speaker>
                     <l>If he be ſuch</l>
                     <l>As you, I uſe him juſt in the ſame manner.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>MELINTUS.</speaker>
                     <p>Surely the Shepheard Clidamant ſpeeds better.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <pb n="9" facs="tcp:170544:4"/>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>DIANA.</speaker>
                     <l>'Tis then aſſuredly becauſe he doth not</l>
                     <l>Reſemble you.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>MELINTUS.</speaker>
                     <l>He entertain'd diſcourſe.</l>
                     <l>With you in gentle whiſpers at the Sports.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>DIANA.</speaker>
                     <l>I do confeſs it,</l>
                     <l>We talk'd of you, and of your little skill.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>MELINTUS.</speaker>
                     <p>Your ſubject was more ſerious, without doubt.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>DIANA.</speaker>
                     <l>What e'r it was. yours, I am ſure, offends me.</l>
                     <l>Remove this hated object from mine eyes;</l>
                     <l>Your preſence will at laſt provoke my anger.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>MELINTUS.</speaker>
                     <l>Can one diſpleaſe you, ſpeaking of your Loves?</l>
                     <l>Thou Husband'ſt for him that ſo ſweet diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>courſe.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>ISMENIA.</speaker>
                     <l>Every one knows that who but ſpeaks <hi>Melintus,</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>Speaks jealous.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>MELINTUS.</speaker>
                     <l>It is no ſecret what men think of thee;</l>
                     <l>Every one knows, that who ſpeaks but <hi>Iſmenia,</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>Speaks cocket.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>ISMENIA.</speaker>
                     <l>Really thou haſt much reaſon</l>
                     <l>To be afflicted at that late diſcourſe,</l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Clidamant</hi> merits much, and I'le oblige him.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>DIANA.</speaker>
                     <p>Leave us.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>MELINTUS.</speaker>
                     <l>He doth expect you, and I trouble you;</l>
                     <l>But wee'l find out a way to croſs his fortune.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <pb n="10" facs="tcp:170544:5"/>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>DIANA to ISMENIA</speaker>
                     <p>He thinks that <hi>Clidamant</hi> enjoys my love.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>ISMENIA.</speaker>
                     <l>Thou haſt no reaſon, Shepheardeſs, to draw him</l>
                     <l>Out of his errour: in the mean time wilt thou</l>
                     <l>Not yield thee to the faithful ſervices,</l>
                     <l>The prayers and tears of the devout <hi>Therſander?</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>Wilt thou not love him yet? he that encourag'd</l>
                     <l>By thy fair preſence, only to pleaſe thee,</l>
                     <l>Hath gain'd ſo many prizes, who to give</l>
                     <l>Thy anger no pretence, thought he loves much,</l>
                     <l>Can more be ſilent, ſince the ardent flame</l>
                     <l>Where with he burns for thee, is only known,</l>
                     <l>To me, unto <hi>Thimantes,</hi> and thy ſelf.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>DIANA.</speaker>
                     <p>Ne'r ſpeak unto me of it.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>ISMENIA.</speaker>
                     <l>What! ſtill cruel?</l>
                     <l>But hearken, I will give thee an adviſe</l>
                     <l>Shall touch thee; whilſt we may, we should lay hold of</l>
                     <l>The flying time; he only maketh beauties,</l>
                     <l>And he deſtroys them; in the lovely ſeaſon</l>
                     <l>That thine laſts, uſe the gifts which nature gives thee;</l>
                     <l>Thou wilt one day loſe this fair luſtre which</l>
                     <l>So charmeth hearts, and be an object of</l>
                     <l>Comtempt, as now thou art of adoration.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>DIANA.</speaker>
                     <l>Rather that love, whoſe Orator thou art,</l>
                     <l>Yet know'ſt his uſe ſo little, doth times office;</l>
                     <l>'T is he that withereth a face; the cares,</l>
                     <l>The troubles and the griefs, which by his means</l>
                     <l>Poſſeſs a heart, deface the lovely features,</l>
                     <l>And mow the flowers<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> he is like time the Tyrant</l>
                     <l>Of all things; he in a few dayes dryes up</l>
                     <l>Our Roſes, and our Lillies.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <pb n="11" facs="tcp:170544:5"/>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>ISMENIA.</speaker>
                     <l>Shepheardeſs,</l>
                     <l>Such fear hath ſmal foundation, quit this thought</l>
                     <l>For thy own intereſt; when love is once</l>
                     <l>Lodg'd in the heart, the ey hath then more light</l>
                     <l>The face receiveth thence its full perfection;</l>
                     <l>Then we eſteem us, then we pleaſe our ſelves,</l>
                     <l>And know out utmoſt value, we correct</l>
                     <l>By art even to the leaſt defect, we call</l>
                     <l>Our Glaſs to counſel in the ordering</l>
                     <l>Our gate, our carriage, and our countenance;</l>
                     <l>There our eye cheers with ſmiles, or kills with frowns,</l>
                     <l>Or faintly darts its glances, or with ſtrength,</l>
                     <l>Either to wound neer hand, or further of;</l>
                     <l>Therefore once more for thy own intereſt,</l>
                     <l>I ſay unto thee, love, at leaſt a little,</l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Therſander</hi> that adores thee.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>DIANA.</speaker>
                     <l>Really,</l>
                     <l>Thou doſt ſurpriſe me, to ſpeak thus unto me,</l>
                     <l>Thou that haſt never yet had love, nor thought</l>
                     <l>Tending to that ſick paſſion, thou that mak'ſt</l>
                     <l>So many Lovers only for thy glory,</l>
                     <l>Without remembring one of them, thou that</l>
                     <l>Pleaſeſt thy ſelf by turns in their diſcourſe,</l>
                     <l>Thou that wilt gain all, &amp; conſerve thee nothing.</l>
                     <l>Thou ſuffereſt <hi>Thimantes</hi> to adore thee</l>
                     <l>To day; but tell me wilt thou entertain</l>
                     <l>His love to morrow?</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>ISMENIA.</speaker>
                     <l>I love, but I have alwayes had my method</l>
                     <l>In love, the Lover that is troubleſome</l>
                     <l>Unto me, is my Lover for a day;</l>
                     <l>I burn not yet for love, not do I ſigh for't:</l>
                     <l>I make a ſport on't ſtill, but ne'r a torment;</l>
                     <l>In thruſting no one of, I'm every day</l>
                     <l>Attended by a multitude of ſervants</l>
                     <l>That preſent courtship to me, and all ſtrive</l>
                     <pb n="12" facs="tcp:170544:6"/>
                     <l>Who shall be formoſt, on whom I command</l>
                     <l>And raign as Princeſs; they ſuppoſe they pleaſe me</l>
                     <l>In putting up my praiſes; when I go</l>
                     <l>Unto the Temple, they fail not to follow,</l>
                     <l>And carefully to tread in all my ſteps.</l>
                     <l>I am not pleas'd to ſee in ſuch brave Shepheards</l>
                     <l>A troop of ſlaves attending on my train;</l>
                     <l>I pleaſe them all in flattering their deſires:</l>
                     <l>I'm much delighted, when I make them jealous,</l>
                     <l>Provided that their jealouſy extend not</l>
                     <l>So far as, to betake themſelves to arms</l>
                     <l>For th' honour of my beautyl; this high point</l>
                     <l>Of evidences might, perhaps, enrage</l>
                     <l>Even all my other lovers.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>DIANA.</speaker>
                     <l>Ha! how ill</l>
                     <l>Thou know'ſt love, and his maximes, I behold</l>
                     <l>Thy changes as ſo many crimes; for my part,</l>
                     <l>If my heart were ta'ne with an object once,</l>
                     <l>I could not paſs from love unto contempt;</l>
                     <l>I should be fix'd unto my firſt Idea,</l>
                     <l>And that God wholly should poſſeſs my thoughts.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>ISMENIA.</speaker>
                     <l>Well then, <hi>Diana,</hi> love, if thou think'ſt fit,</l>
                     <l>Beyond the grave, and make ſo fait a fire</l>
                     <l>Ariſe beneath thy ashes.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>DIANA.</speaker>
                     <p>Oh, alas!</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>ISMENIA.</speaker>
                     <p>What ſignify thoſe ſighs?</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>DIANA.</speaker>
                     <l>They ſignify</l>
                     <l>The ſorrow of the heart.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <pb n="13" facs="tcp:170544:6"/>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>ISMENIA.</speaker>
                     <l>But whence proceeds</l>
                     <l>That ſorrow? is it from thy brothers death,</l>
                     <l>Or from ſome lovers? come, deal plainly with me,</l>
                     <l>Doſt thou not love <hi>Therſander</hi> yet at laſt?</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>DIANA.</speaker>
                     <p>No, I aſſure thee.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>ISMENIA.</speaker>
                     <p>Speak, I'm very ſecret.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>DIANA.</speaker>
                     <l>I'le tell thee then, in <hi>Sevil</hi> I receiv'd</l>
                     <l>Both life and love, <hi>Cleagenor, Iſmenia,</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>Is the name of the Conquerour, whoſe image</l>
                     <l>Is graven in my heart.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>ISMENIA.</speaker>
                     <l>O Gods! how this diſcourſe</l>
                     <l>Hath coſened my thought, I was about</l>
                     <l>To give inſtructions; — but purſue.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>DIANA.</speaker>
                     <l>Our parents</l>
                     <l>Approv'd our love, and the day for our marriage</l>
                     <l>Already was appointed, when <hi>Nearchus,</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>Provoked by an infamous deſire,</l>
                     <l>Came to ſolicit me unlawfully</l>
                     <l>In favour of his flame; this favourite</l>
                     <l>Unto the King after a paſſion painted,</l>
                     <l>And coloured with ſighs, called his preſents</l>
                     <l>To the aſſiſtance of his faith; but this</l>
                     <l>Proving effectleſs, he reſolv'd my ruin;</l>
                     <l>He came with open force to ſatisfy</l>
                     <l>His beaſtly and unruly appetite;</l>
                     <l>And to that end would carry me away.</l>
                     <l>My Mother having notice at that inſtant</l>
                     <l>Of his deſign, made me to take a drink,</l>
                     <l>To fruſtrate it, and then, her ſubt'le policy</l>
                     <pb n="14" facs="tcp:170544:7"/>
                     <l>Spread through the Town the rumour of my death:</l>
                     <l>Indeed the vertue of this drink procur'd me</l>
                     <l>So long a ſleep, that it appear'd to be</l>
                     <l>The ſleep of death; <hi>Nearchus</hi> terrified</l>
                     <l>With this ſad news, came to behold it painted</l>
                     <l>Upon my face; remorſe of conſcience</l>
                     <l>Within his heart then, quarrel'd with his love:</l>
                     <l>His ſad deſpair arm'd him to kill himſelf:</l>
                     <l>But whilſt his ſoul was troubled herewith,</l>
                     <l>I was conveyed ſecretly into</l>
                     <l>A Bark; ſcarce had I yet finish'd my ſleep,</l>
                     <l>But at my firſt waking I ſaw my ſelf</l>
                     <l>Upon the Sea. My Mother then related</l>
                     <l>The whole adventure to me, and the ſecret</l>
                     <l>Impoſture of my feigned death, when ſuddenly</l>
                     <l>A ſtorm brake the diſcourſe, horrour and death</l>
                     <l>March'd on the floods: alas, what shall I ſay?</l>
                     <l>Our veſſel being carried by the fury</l>
                     <l>O'th' winds and waves, was ſplit upon a rock,</l>
                     <l>The ſeveral pieces floated on the waters;</l>
                     <l>I know not which o'th' Gods took care of me</l>
                     <l>In putting one under my trembling hand,</l>
                     <l>Which making me paſs on thoſe moving graves</l>
                     <l>Through the diſturbed empire of the winds,</l>
                     <l>Carried me to the shore in all apparence</l>
                     <l>Devoid of life; here in this quiet Iſland</l>
                     <l>Of <hi>Erithrea</hi> where <hi>Meliſſa</hi> raigns</l>
                     <l>My body found a receptacle; she</l>
                     <l>Returning at that inſtant from the chaſe,</l>
                     <l>Perceiv'd it lying, which th'enraged Sea</l>
                     <l>Yet threatened on its banks, and that ſame God.</l>
                     <l>Which would compleat his miracle, inclin'd</l>
                     <l>Her heart to pitty at this ſpectacle:</l>
                     <l>She cauſ'd me to be carried to her Court:</l>
                     <l>It is unto her ſuccour that I owe</l>
                     <pb n="15" facs="tcp:170544:7"/>
                     <l>The remnant of my dayes: here I firſt chang'd</l>
                     <l>My name, the better to aſſure my flight,</l>
                     <l>And ſo to diſappoint <hi>Nearchus</hi> purſuit.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>ISMENIA.</speaker>
                     <p>How Shepheardeſs, is not thy Name <hi>Diana?</hi>
                     </p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>DIANNA.</speaker>
                     <l>No, <hi>Celia</hi> was my true and only name;</l>
                     <l>But for my ſafety I made to <hi>Metiſſa</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>A feign'd relation of the miſeries</l>
                     <l>Of my ſad life; ſince she receiv'd me</l>
                     <l>Into her palace, where I live with her,</l>
                     <l>And am now of her Court. Seven times the Sun</l>
                     <l>Hath finish'd his Carier, ſince I have ſeen,</l>
                     <l>Or heard news of my mother.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>ISMENIA.</speaker>
                     <l>Was <hi>Cleagenor</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>Inform'd of all this?</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>DIANA.</speaker>
                     <l>Oh, alas! this is</l>
                     <l>One of the point that cauſeth my affliction:</l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Cleagener</hi> ſurpriſed by the ſame</l>
                     <l>Impoſture, came to ſee me in my bed,</l>
                     <l>As in my grave: I wonder that the noiſe</l>
                     <l>Of his redoubled cryes brake not my ſleep:</l>
                     <l>The heat to revenge me dry'd all his tears:</l>
                     <l>He found his rival, and aſſaulted him;</l>
                     <l>They fought on equal terms; <hi>Nearchus</hi> fell</l>
                     <l>Under his arms for dead; <hi>Cleagenor</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>was forc'd to fly t'avoid the fury of</l>
                     <l>Th'offended King: his ſudden flight gave not</l>
                     <l>My Mother oportunity t' inform him</l>
                     <l>(As she intended) with the fiction</l>
                     <l>Of my pretended death: ſince his departure</l>
                     <l>'Tis now ſeven years compleat, in all which time</l>
                     <l>I've heard no news of him; ſo that I know not</l>
                     <l>Whether I mourn the living, or the dead;</l>
                     <pb n="16" facs="tcp:170544:8"/>
                     <l>In the mean time to weep my fate more freely,</l>
                     <l>And to conceal my miſerable fortune,</l>
                     <l>I feign'd a Brothers death.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>ISMENIA.</speaker>
                     <l>I'm ſenſible</l>
                     <l>Of thy misfortune, and will bear a part</l>
                     <l>In thy ſad grief, if that will make it leſſe;</l>
                     <l>I no more now condemne thy ſighs, nor tears;</l>
                     <l>But yet at laſt preſerve thy beauty from</l>
                     <l>Thoſe murthering ſorrows; in this doubtfull caſe</l>
                     <l>Fix thy fair thoughts upon ſome other object;</l>
                     <l>If death hath ſeiz'd thy Servant, ſure thou loſeſt</l>
                     <l>Too many tears and ſighs; or grant he live,</l>
                     <l>Iſt probable that he will keep his conſtancy</l>
                     <l>For thee whom he thinks dead? but here's my Lover.</l>
                  </sp>
               </div>
               <div type="scene">
                  <head>SCENA III. THIMANTES, DIANA, ISMENIA.</head>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>ISMENIA to THIMANTES.</speaker>
                     <p>WHat buſines brings thee hither?</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>THIMANTES.</speaker>
                     <l>Here I come</l>
                     <l>A little to divert my thought.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>DIANA.</speaker>
                     <p>What thought?</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>THIMANTES.</speaker>
                     <p>'Tis a diſeaſe which doth aſſault my ſenſe.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>ISMENIA.</speaker>
                     <p>What iſt, without more circumſtance?</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>THIMANTES.</speaker>
                     <l>My plaint</l>
                     <l>Without words would expreſs it; at the ſports</l>
                     <l>Too many Shepheards had unto my grief</l>
                     <pb n="17" facs="tcp:170544:8"/>
                     <l>Too long thy free ear, and perhaps, thy heart;</l>
                     <l>A World of people preſſed round about thee:</l>
                     <l>The Shepheard <hi>Dorilas,</hi> me thought, diſcours'd</l>
                     <l>Too long with thee, I ſaw ſo many others</l>
                     <l>Proſtrated at thy foot —</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>ISMENIA.</speaker>
                     <l>Without more words</l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Thimantes</hi> is become a jealous fool.</l>
                     <l>Since thou wilt love me, learn to know me well:</l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Thimantes</hi> I am free, and will no Maſter;</l>
                     <l>I'le ne'r depend on any but my ſelf.</l>
                     <l>Tell me, I pray thee, did I ever promiſe</l>
                     <l>To ſpeak to none but thee? doſt thou imagine</l>
                     <l>So vainly, that thou art the only Lover</l>
                     <l>That ſerves me? have not I yet ſome which ought</l>
                     <l>To be conſerv'd? and amongſt all the Shepheards,</l>
                     <l>Whoſe faith I have receiv'd, if I should open</l>
                     <l>My mouth and eyes on none of them but thee,</l>
                     <l>And that one of thoſe dayes thy mind should change;</l>
                     <l>And mine change too, (as all this well may happen)</l>
                     <l>Would all the others, jealous of this kindneſs</l>
                     <l>Expreſs'd to thee thus in particular,</l>
                     <l>Be ſtill my Lovers, though I had loſt thee?</l>
                     <l>And if my liberty were not expoſ'd</l>
                     <l>For all, which of them would commiſerate</l>
                     <l>My fortune in thy loſſe; I think upon</l>
                     <l>Th'event of things, which thou canſt not aſſure:</l>
                     <l>At leaſt if one quits me, another takes me:</l>
                     <l>Conſider if this humour pleaſeth thee,</l>
                     <l>If thou canſt ſerve me all thy life time thus,</l>
                     <l>And not be jealous; if thou canſt, hope one day</l>
                     <l>Both mouth and hand, and happily the heart</l>
                     <l>May flatter thy affection.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <pb n="18" facs="tcp:170544:9"/>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>THIMANTES.</speaker>
                     <l>This way</l>
                     <l>Seems very ſtrange unto me, but almoſt</l>
                     <l>Every fair evening ſome appointed place</l>
                     <l>Of meeting ſeems t'aſſure me of thy love</l>
                     <l>Sufficiently, and not to flatter me</l>
                     <l>With frivolous hope.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>ISMENIA.</speaker>
                     <l>Yet hitherto it is</l>
                     <l>But airy words.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>THIMANTES.</speaker>
                     <l>I hope all things from time</l>
                     <l>In waiting for that day, our names engraven</l>
                     <l>In every place, will ſpeak my love, <hi>Iſmenia,</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>I promiſe—</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>ISMENIA.</speaker>
                     <l>But no more, here comes <hi>Therſander;</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>That Shepheard, whoſe enflamed heart thine eyes</l>
                     <l>Hath rendered as hes—</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>DIANA.</speaker>
                     <l>Well <hi>Iſmenia,</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>I leave you.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>ISMENIA.</speaker>
                     <l>This is too much rigour, truſt me,</l>
                     <l>At leaſt afford the face, if thou deny'ſt</l>
                     <l>The heart.</l>
                  </sp>
               </div>
               <div type="scene">
                  <head>SCENA IV. THERSANDER, DIANA, THI<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>MANTES, ISMENIA.</head>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>THERSANDER to DIANA.</speaker>
                     <l>OH ſtay, dear object ſtay, thou that art cauſe</l>
                     <l>Of all my torments, I have but one word</l>
                     <l>To ſay before I dye, the Nimph hath crown'd</l>
                     <l>My valour with theſe prizes, here I come</l>
                     <pb n="19" facs="tcp:170544:9"/>
                     <l>To lay them at thy feet, with them my heart:</l>
                     <l>If thou wilt triumph on this feſtival day.</l>
                     <l>Suffer at leaſt thy conqueſt in thy ſight,</l>
                     <l>That's all th' ambition of this captive heart.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>DIANA.</speaker>
                     <l>Captive to me? if ſo, make it change Maſter,</l>
                     <l>I freely do releaſe it; break its chain</l>
                     <l>Thy ſelf, if thy deſign be not to have me</l>
                     <l>Free it with my own hand.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>THERSANDER.</speaker>
                     <l>Alas! it is not</l>
                     <l>Its liberty that I deſire.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>DIANA.</speaker>
                     <l>Then let it</l>
                     <l>Live ſtill a ſlave, and ſigh.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>THERSANDER.</speaker>
                     <l>How, Shepheardeſs!</l>
                     <l>Refuſe a heart, this precious preſent which</l>
                     <l>Is alwayes worth a Temple, and the Gods!</l>
                     <l>Think well upon it, it becomes thy juſtice</l>
                     <l>Not to deſpiſe this noble ſacrifice,</l>
                     <l>Since I give but the ſame victime and incenſe</l>
                     <l>Unto the powers above; in my opinion</l>
                     <l>Our Goddeſs in the Temple is leſs fair,</l>
                     <l>And thou doſt bear the bright name of <hi>Diana,</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>As well as she.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>DIANA.</speaker>
                     <l>Since this rich preſent is</l>
                     <l>Of ſuch high value, as 'tis worthy of</l>
                     <l>A Temple and the Gods, I believe, Shepheard,</l>
                     <l>That it becomes my juſtice not t'accept</l>
                     <l>This noble ſarifice, and I should wrong</l>
                     <l>Our puiſſant Gods in daring to partake</l>
                     <l>Their glory, and to share their incenſe with them,</l>
                     <l>My name's <hi>Diana,</hi> to thy eyes I'm fair;</l>
                     <l>But I am not a Goddeſs like to her.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <pb n="20" facs="tcp:170544:10"/>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>THERSANDER.</speaker>
                     <l>Although thou haſt no Temple, nor no Altars,</l>
                     <l>Thou mak'ſt thy ſelf adored; 'tis to day</l>
                     <l>Thy feſtival which I have celebrated:</l>
                     <l>I have no other worship, nor no other</l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Diana,</hi> the fire of my love is not</l>
                     <l>A profane fire, and if ſome ſpark thereof</l>
                     <l>Warm not thy breaſt a little, I muſt ſuffer</l>
                     <l>The violent heat on't</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>DIANA.</speaker>
                     <l>Rather I adviſe thee,</l>
                     <l>Quench it with my contempts, this remedy</l>
                     <l>Will cure thee, that thou shalt complain no more.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>THERSANDER.</speaker>
                     <l>Good Gods! what remedy is this which thou</l>
                     <l>Offereſt me here? I muſt dye, shepheardeſs,</l>
                     <l>If thou cur'ſt ſo; flatter at leaſt, I pray thee,</l>
                     <l>With on ſole word the love which thou haſt raiſ'd;</l>
                     <l>If I'm, not happy, make me think I am ſo.</l>
                     <l>Alas! I cannot hear a ſingle ſyllable</l>
                     <l>To ſuccour me; if thus thou cureſt, Shephear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deſs.</l>
                     <l>I muſt dye, there is no prevention for't</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>ISMENIA.</speaker>
                     <l>Why carrieſt thou a heart ſtill ſo rebellious</l>
                     <l>To love?</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>THIMANTES,</speaker>
                     <l>Why doſt thou perſecute with ſcorn</l>
                     <l>This faithful Shepheard?</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>DIANA.</speaker>
                     <p>It is beſt be gone.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>THERSANDER.</speaker>
                     <l>Yet thruſt of thy diſdain, if thou wilt ſpare</l>
                     <l>My hand, my death, finish the forming of</l>
                     <pb n="21" facs="tcp:170544:10"/>
                     <l>The ſword that kils me, one word more of hate,</l>
                     <l>And I die preſently before thine eys;</l>
                     <l>Speak, anſwer me.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>ISMENIA.</speaker>
                     <p>No more, here comes the Nymph.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>DIANA.</speaker>
                     <l>Happy arrival, which hath freed me from</l>
                     <l>So great at touble!</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>THERSANDER.</speaker>
                     <l>Well for my part then,</l>
                     <l>I'le try the temper of the marble rocks:</l>
                     <l>My plaints may pierce them, though they could not move</l>
                     <l>A Virgins heart to pitty, much leſſe love.</l>
                  </sp>
               </div>
               <div type="scene">
                  <head>SCENA V. MELISSA, PARTHENIA, DIANA, ISME<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>NIA, THIMANTES, CLIDA<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>MANT, MELINTUS.</head>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>MELISSA.</speaker>
                     <l>SInce a full year and more that I have govern'd</l>
                     <l>This happy Iſland in the right and lawful</l>
                     <l>Line and ſucceſſion of my Anceſtours</l>
                     <l>By the death of my Siſter, and ſince firſt</l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Diana's</hi> feaſts were celebrated here,</l>
                     <l>Never ſo many Laurels crown'd your heads,</l>
                     <l>Nor ever any day ordain'd for paſtime</l>
                     <l>Hath entertain'd mine eyes with ſuch delight.</l>
                     <l>Every one ſtriving to bear hence the prize</l>
                     <l>Propoſ'd to his contention, shew'd his skill,</l>
                     <l>Both at the Courſe and Lute; how hand ſomly</l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Therſander</hi> did behave him at theſe exerciſes!</l>
                     <l>With what a grace he acted every thing!</l>
                     <l>How charming was his port! and if I may</l>
                     <pb n="22" facs="tcp:170544:11"/>
                     <l>Say what I think of him, he muſt be ſprung</l>
                     <l>Either from Kings or Gods; how happy is</l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Thimantes</hi> in his friendship!</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>THIMANTES.</speaker>
                     <l>This happineſs which I enjoy's not new,</l>
                     <l>It hath a longer date then from to day:</l>
                     <l>His name is precious to me; 't was my fortune</l>
                     <l>To have the benefit of his acquaintance</l>
                     <l>At my laſt voyage, I ſaw his arrival</l>
                     <l>Form his own native country at the Court</l>
                     <l>O'th King of <hi>Portugal;</hi> the ſympathy</l>
                     <l>Of humors which one man hath with another</l>
                     <l>Tied us together in ſo firm a friendship</l>
                     <l>That having met him ſad and full of thought,</l>
                     <l>I prevail'd with him as to bring him here,</l>
                     <l>In hope that in this quiet region where</l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Meliſſa</hi> reigns, he should loſe all his grief.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>MELISSA.</speaker>
                     <l>Indeed although that proſperous Shepheard hath</l>
                     <l>Received all the prizes from my hand</l>
                     <l>Wherewith he's crown'd, I find him notwith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding</l>
                     <l>Stil melancholy may not this be in him</l>
                     <l>Some ſad effect of love, bleſt Shepheardeſs,</l>
                     <l>Who e'r thou art! thrice happy is thy fortune,</l>
                     <l>In which this noble ſtranger bound his choice!</l>
                     <l>He is ſo far above the common merit,</l>
                     <l>That a Nymph should not much abaſe her ſelf</l>
                     <l>In loving him.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>CLIDAMANT.</speaker>
                     <l>Indeed he merits much,</l>
                     <l>And we eſteem him all, we love his vertues,</l>
                     <l>Without being jealous of them.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>PARTHENIA.</speaker>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Clidamant</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>Comes nothing short of him in my opinion.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <pb n="23" facs="tcp:170544:11"/>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>ISMENIA.</speaker>
                     <p>
                        <hi>Thimantes</hi> too will go as far as he.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>DIANA.</speaker>
                     <l>Another time, <hi>Melintus</hi> without doubt</l>
                     <l>Will perform better.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>MELINTVS.</speaker>
                     <l>Yes, when you shal turn</l>
                     <l>Your eys on that ſide.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>MELISSA.</speaker>
                     <l>Shepheards, once again</l>
                     <l>Prepare, I pray you, for the Nuptials</l>
                     <l>Of <hi>Thirſis</hi> with <hi>Parthenia;</hi> Neece, that Shepheard</l>
                     <l>Is worthy of you, and you are not ignorant</l>
                     <l>That I intend, as ſoon as he returns,</l>
                     <l>To make him (as I hope) your happy husband.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>PARTHENIA.</speaker>
                     <stage>aſide</stage>
                     <l>Yes, if my heart can ſuffer violence.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>MELISSA.</speaker>
                     <l>In the mean time, let's go unto the Temple.</l>
                     <l>Our thanks and our devotions to pay</l>
                     <l>Vnto the Gods on this ſo glorious day.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <trailer>The end of the firſt Act.</trailer>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div n="2" type="act">
               <pb n="24" facs="tcp:170544:12"/>
               <head>ACTUS II.</head>
               <div type="scene">
                  <head>SCENA I. ISMENIA, THERSANDER, THIMANTES.</head>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>ISMENIA.</speaker>
                     <l>'TIs true, <hi>Therſander,</hi> I have done for thee</l>
                     <l>Aſmuch as poſſibly I could, I made</l>
                     <l>Thy ſighs, thy conſtancy, thy faith appear</l>
                     <l>For to perſwade her, but I loſt my labour,</l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Diana</hi> is inſenſible, her heart,</l>
                     <l>Which loves ſweet applications cannot touch,</l>
                     <l>Among ſo many rocks, is become rock.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>THERSANDER.</speaker>
                     <l>What shall I doe, <hi>Thimantes?</hi> what a rude</l>
                     <l>And rigorous fortune ſteers my deſtiny?</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>THIMANTES.</speaker>
                     <p>Quit that ingrateful, and come forth of ſlavery</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>THERSANDER.</speaker>
                     <l>How shall I come forth? I'm born miſerable</l>
                     <l>Under the frowning, and the fatal aſpect</l>
                     <l>Of an ungentle Star, Which in deſpight</l>
                     <l>Of all my ſtudies to defend me from it;</l>
                     <l>Purſues <hi>Cleagenor</hi> under the name</l>
                     <l>Of poor <hi>Therſander.</hi>
                     </l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>ISMENIA.</speaker>
                     <stage>Softly.</stage>
                     <l>What is that I hear!</l>
                     <l>Good Gods!</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>THIMANTES.</speaker>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Therſander,</hi> what haft thou diſcover'd?</l>
                     <l>Hath thy own mouth betrayed thus thy ſecret?</l>
                     <l>See into what great danger thy imprudence</l>
                     <l>Puts thee at preſent; feareſt thou no more,</l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Nearchus,</hi> and his power?</l>
                  </sp>
                  <pb n="25" facs="tcp:170544:12"/>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>THERSANDER.</speaker>
                     <l>No, I fear nothing</l>
                     <l>After this ſentence, but ſeek death, for ſince</l>
                     <l>It is reſolv'd by fate that I muſt die,</l>
                     <l>What matter is it, by what arm it be,</l>
                     <l>Whether <hi>Nearchus,</hi> or <hi>Diana</hi> kill me.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>ISMENIA.</speaker>
                     <l>Oh Gods! how happy is he? — <stage>ſoftly.</stage>
                     </l>
                     <l>Hath not she</l>
                     <l>For whom thou dieſt had ſome intelligence</l>
                     <l>That thy heart loves elſewhere? if it be ſo,</l>
                     <l>And that thy inconſtancy procures thy torment,</l>
                     <l>Thou wrongfully accuſeſt her of cruelty.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>THERSANDER.</speaker>
                     <l>Quite contrary, this love therewith thou ſeeſt</l>
                     <l>My heart diſturb'd, is a ſure teſtimony</l>
                     <l>Of my fidelity: 'tis true, alas!</l>
                     <l>I ſometime lov'd an object of ſuch beauty,</l>
                     <l>That the Gods never fram'd ſo fair a peece:</l>
                     <l>The Roſes and the Lillies form'd the colour</l>
                     <l>Which dy'd her cheeks, and in herſparkling eys</l>
                     <l>The Sun was painted; to expreſs unto thee</l>
                     <l>Yet better her divine perfections.</l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Diana</hi> is her Portrait to the life</l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Celia</hi> is ſeen in her; she like <hi>Diana</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>Had a Mageſtick carriage, she had</l>
                     <l>A mouth, and eys like her, she had an air,</l>
                     <l>Fierce too like hers, but amiable; laſtly</l>
                     <l>In every thing she ſeem'd <hi>Diana's</hi> ſelf:</l>
                     <l>My heart is conſtant therefore as before,</l>
                     <l>Since ſtill I love her in her living Portrait.</l>
                     <l>I thought at firſt then, that her death was falſe,</l>
                     <l>And that <hi>Diana</hi> was that lovely object;</l>
                     <l>But when I few <hi>Diana</hi> entertain</l>
                     <l>With ſuch contempt the fervent love wherewith</l>
                     <pb n="26" facs="tcp:170544:13"/>
                     <l>My heart was taken, when I ſaw her rigours,</l>
                     <l>And infinite hatred, I perceiv'd my errour,</l>
                     <l>And ſaid this is not <hi>Celia;</hi> ſo that</l>
                     <l>I ſaw well by her cruelties indeed</l>
                     <l>That I purſu'd her picture, and had paſſion</l>
                     <l>But for a Portrait.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>ISMENIA.</speaker>
                     <p>What! is <hi>Celia</hi> dead then?</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>THERSANDER.</speaker>
                     <l>Alas! that's my affliction, I ſaw her</l>
                     <l>Stretch'd out upon her death-bed dead, <hi>Iſmenia;</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>And more dead yet then she, I ſaw thoſe places</l>
                     <l>Shine with a certain reſt of brightneſs which</l>
                     <l>Her eyes had darted; preſently on this</l>
                     <l>I had a Combat with <hi>Nearchus</hi> for</l>
                     <l>This charming Beauty; that proud favourite</l>
                     <l>Unto the King by infamous deſires,</l>
                     <l>Form'd him an object to his filthy pleaſures,</l>
                     <l>This outrage was intended to her ſweetneſs:</l>
                     <l>We fought on this occaſion, it was</l>
                     <l>My fortune to diſarm him; but the death</l>
                     <l>Of <hi>Celia,</hi> and the anger of the King,</l>
                     <l>(To ſave me from the rigor of the Law)</l>
                     <l>Enforc'd me to a flight, and made me wander</l>
                     <l>Seven year from Province unto Province: laſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly</l>
                     <l>Wearied to ſee the Court of every Prince,</l>
                     <l>I thought to free me of all dangers here</l>
                     <l>Under the feign'd name of <hi>Therſander,</hi> and</l>
                     <l>The habit of a Shepheard: to diſguiſe me</l>
                     <l>Yet better, the afflictions of my heart</l>
                     <l>Have chang'd my Viſage.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>ISMENIA.</speaker>
                     <l>Haſt thou nothing with thee</l>
                     <l>That formerly was <hi>Celia's?</hi>
                     </l>
                  </sp>
                  <pb n="27" facs="tcp:170544:13"/>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>THERSANDER.</speaker>
                     <l>Yes, one day</l>
                     <l>I receiv'd from her hand this pretious pledge</l>
                     <l>Of her unfeigned love, behold this Portrait,</l>
                     <l>And judge, I pray thee, if I love <hi>Diana,</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>Or <hi>Celia.</hi>
                     </l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>ISMENIA.</speaker>
                     <l>Let me have this Portrait; with it</l>
                     <l>I'l cure thy evil, <hi>Diana</hi> ſeeing it</l>
                     <l>Will become gentle, I'l go shew it her.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>THERSANDER.</speaker>
                     <l>What wilt thou do, <hi>Iſmenia?</hi> but I ſee</l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Diana:</hi> O Gods! end my miſery.</l>
                  </sp>
               </div>
               <div type="scene">
                  <head>SCENA II. DIANA, THERSANDER, ISMENIA, THI<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>MANTES.</head>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>DIANA.</speaker>
                     <p>I Sought thee every where.—to <hi>Iſmenia.</hi>
                     </p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>THERSANDER.</speaker>
                     <l>You will oblige me,—to <hi>Iſmenia.</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Iſmenia,</hi> to reſtore my Portrait to me.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>ISMENIA</speaker>
                     <l>Troubleſome Shepheard!</l>
                     <l>I have much to ſay—to <hi>Diana</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>To thee in private, therefore let us enter</l>
                     <l>Into this Wood.— <stage>Exit <hi>Iſmenia</hi> and <hi>Diana.</hi>
                        </stage>
                     </l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>THERSANDER</speaker>
                     <l>Shew her that Portrait! oh my martyrdom!</l>
                     <l>Traitrous <hi>Iſmenia,</hi> is this that faith</l>
                     <l>For which <hi>Thimantes</hi> alwaies anſwered</l>
                     <l>To me for thee? yes it is by thy counſels,</l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Thimantes,</hi> only that my ſeduc'd ſoul</l>
                     <pb n="28" facs="tcp:170544:14"/>
                     <l>Left her the conduct of my faithfull love;</l>
                     <l>Nothing from thee or me can work upon her,</l>
                     <l>She jeers at all; but let us find her out.</l>
                     <stage>
                        <hi>Exit</hi> Therſander <hi>and</hi> Thimantes.</stage>
                     <stage>Iſmenia <hi>returns with</hi> Diana.</stage>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>ISMENIA.</speaker>
                     <l>I ſee w'are private here, we may ſpeak freely.</l>
                     <l>A Miſtreſs yet at laſt ſighs for <hi>Therſander,</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>And one too in this Iſland far leſſe cruel</l>
                     <l>Then thee; accept his ſervice, and embrace</l>
                     <l>His faith: this portrait which thou ſeeſt here,</l>
                     <l>He receiv'd from her as a faithfull witneſs</l>
                     <l>Of their reciprocal and mutual fires.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>DIANA.</speaker>
                     <p>What do I ſee?</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>ISMENIA.</speaker>
                     <l>That portrait (as I take it)</l>
                     <l>Whereof <hi>Therſander</hi> is ſo proud.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>DIANA.</speaker>
                     <l>I gave</l>
                     <l>Such a one to <hi>Cleagenor; Iſmenia,</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>Who gave it thee?</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>ISMENIA.</speaker>
                     <p>
                        <hi>Cleagenor</hi> himſelf.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>DIANA.</speaker>
                     <l>O Gods! what ſaieſt thou to me? thou art in</l>
                     <l>An extream errour.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>ISMINIA.</speaker>
                     <l>I tell thee again</l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Cleagenor</hi> himſelf gave it to me</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>DIANA.</speaker>
                     <p>This diſcourſe holds no credit.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>ISMENIA.</speaker>
                     <l>Every day</l>
                     <l>Almoſt I ſee him, and thou ſeeſt him alſo</l>
                     <pb n="29" facs="tcp:170544:14"/>
                     <l>As well as I.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>DIANA.</speaker>
                     <p>I comprehend not theſe obſcurities.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>ISMENIA.</speaker>
                     <p>He loves thee, and thou flieſt him.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>DIANA.</speaker>
                     <l>I fly</l>
                     <l>None but <hi>Therſander.</hi>
                     </l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>ISMENIA.</speaker>
                     <l>Well, henceforth accuſe</l>
                     <l>None but thy ſelf of theſe diſaſters, 'tis</l>
                     <l>The ſame <hi>Cleagenor</hi> that loveth thee,</l>
                     <l>And whom thou fli'ſt.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>DIANA.</speaker>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Cleagenor! Iſmenia;</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>That cannot be, is't poſſible that I</l>
                     <l>Should have been two moneths without know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing him,</l>
                     <l>For ſo long 'tis ſince he arriv'd among us.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>ISMENIA.</speaker>
                     <l>Thy grief hood-winck'd thine eys, thou couldſt not ſee him.</l>
                     <l>Think'ſt thou that ſince thoſe ſeven years thou haſt liv'd</l>
                     <l>Upon thoſe fair banks, time that changeth all things,</l>
                     <l>Hath not yet chang'd a face? there comes <hi>Ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſander;</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>Take a full ſurvey of him, whilſt I hold him</l>
                     <l>In ſome diſcourſe; make shew as if thou'd ſten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter</l>
                     <l>Into that Wood, and have a care thou do not</l>
                     <l>Diſcover thee till I have ordered</l>
                     <l>Thy meeting with him.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <pb n="30" facs="tcp:170544:15"/>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>DIANA.</speaker>
                     <p>Happy pledge of love!</p>
                     <stage>Entring into the Wood.</stage>
                  </sp>
               </div>
               <div type="scene">
                  <head>SCENA III. THERSANDER, THIMANTES, ISMENIA, DIANA.</head>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>THERSANDER to THIMANTES.</speaker>
                     <l>THou ſeeſt what she hath done; unto <hi>Diana</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>Sh' 'as given the Portrait.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>THIMANTES.</speaker>
                     <l>See she enters there</l>
                     <l>Into that Wood.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>ISMENIA.</speaker>
                     <p>A word with thee <hi>Therſander,</hi>
                     </p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>THERSANDER.</speaker>
                     <l>Perfidious, finish here thy crime, and be</l>
                     <l>My murtherer; ſtrike, ſtrike this heart, I pray thee,</l>
                     <l>That hopes no more; but by what intereſt</l>
                     <l>Haſt thou betrai'd me?</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>ISMENIA.</speaker>
                     <p>Why complaineſt thou?</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>THERSANDER.</speaker>
                     <l>O groſs diſſimulation! dar'ſt thou yet</l>
                     <l>To ask what is my plaint?</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>DIANA.</speaker>
                     <p>He hath his gate.</p>
                     <stage>Softly, looking on him, where she was hidden.</stage>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>ISMENIA.</speaker>
                     <p>Thy heat hears nothing, give me leave to ſpeak.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>THERSANDER.</speaker>
                     <l>Yes, to feign more, and to lie at thy pleaſure,</l>
                     <l>Am I oblig'd ſtil to thee for my life?</l>
                  </sp>
                  <pb n="31" facs="tcp:170544:15"/>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>ISMENIA.</speaker>
                     <p>How ſoon love doth degenerate into folly?</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>THIMANTES.</speaker>
                     <p>
                        <hi>Therſander,</hi> hear her.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>THERSANDER.</speaker>
                     <p>What is't she can ſay?</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>ISMENIA.</speaker>
                     <l>Since th'art ſo obſtinate, let thy love go</l>
                     <l>Which way it will, I'l have no more to do in't.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>THERSANDER.</speaker>
                     <p>Speak then, what wilt thou?</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>ISMENIA.</speaker>
                     <p>I have nought to ſay now.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>THIMANTES.</speaker>
                     <p>Thou would'ſt ſpeak to him.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>ISMENIA.</speaker>
                     <p>'Twas to laugh a little.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>THIMANTES.</speaker>
                     <p>I pray thee, ſpeak unto him.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>THERSANDER.</speaker>
                     <l>I conjure thee,</l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Iſmenia,</hi> in the name of all the Gods,</l>
                     <l>Jeer not my Paſſion.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>ISMENIA.</speaker>
                     <l>It is now my turn</l>
                     <l>To be perverſe.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>THERSANDER.</speaker>
                     <p>I hear thee, ſpeak, what ſai'ſt thou?</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>ISMENIA.</speaker>
                     <l>Since thou wilt have it, know then that a Rival</l>
                     <l>Hath caus'd thy grief and torments.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>THERSANDER.</speaker>
                     <l>How, a Rival!</l>
                     <l>At that Word I'm all fire, a Rival!</l>
                  </sp>
                  <pb n="32" facs="tcp:170544:16"/>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>ISMENIA.</speaker>
                     <l>Yes,</l>
                     <l>A Rival, good <hi>Therſander,</hi> but a lov'd one.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>THERSANDER.</speaker>
                     <p>What! loved of <hi>Diana?</hi>
                     </p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>ISMENIA.</speaker>
                     <l>Yes of her,</l>
                     <l>And more too, of thy ſelf.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>THERSANDER.</speaker>
                     <l>That's very ſtrange;</l>
                     <l>How should I chuſe but bear a mortal hatred</l>
                     <l>To him my Miſtreſs loves; who e'r he be,</l>
                     <l>I muſt revenged die.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>DIANA</speaker>
                     <stage>Softly.</stage>
                     <l>If this should be</l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Cleagenor,</hi> O Gods! how is he chang'd?</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>THERSANDER.</speaker>
                     <p>Where is that Rival?</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>ISMENIA.</speaker>
                     <l>With thee, <hi>Therſander;</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>Thou would'ſt defend him, if occaſion were,</l>
                     <l>At the expence of all thy blood; believe me,</l>
                     <l>Thou never leaveſt him.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>THERSANDER.</speaker>
                     <l>Without diſſembling, —to <hi>Thimantes</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>Tell me <hi>Thimantes,</hi> art not thou that Rival,</l>
                     <l>She means? I think thou art my friend, deal plainly</l>
                     <l>And freely with me, art not thou that cruel,</l>
                     <l>That falſe and traiterous Rival?</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>THIMANTES.</speaker>
                     <l>Anſwer him,</l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Iſmenia.</hi>
                     </l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>THERSANDER.</speaker>
                     <p>Well, what wilt thou ſay at laſt?</p>
                  </sp>
                  <pb n="33" facs="tcp:170544:16"/>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>ISMENIA.</speaker>
                     <p>
                        <hi>Therſander</hi> hath for Rival in his love.—</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>THERSANDER.</speaker>
                     <p>Speak, whom?</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>ISMENIA.</speaker>
                     <p>
                        <hi>Cleagenor,</hi>
                     </p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>THERSANDER.</speaker>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Cleagenor!</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Iſmenia,</hi> ha! my joy, ſure, is extream;</l>
                     <l>True, I confeſs, I love this Rival equal</l>
                     <l>Unto my ſelf, and if he may be loved</l>
                     <l>Of th' object whom I ſerve, I will adore</l>
                     <l>My chains Without condemning her of ri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gour.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>ISMENIA.</speaker>
                     <l>Thou haſt loſt nothing by this bout, thy for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tune</l>
                     <l>May create envy, fair <hi>Diana</hi> hath</l>
                     <l>Yielded to <hi>Celia's</hi> portrait.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>DIANA.</speaker>
                     <stage>Softly,</stage>
                     <l>Who, to ſee</l>
                     <l>Thoſe decay'd features, could have known that face?</l>
                     <l>But my love hath at laſt drawn them afresh</l>
                     <l>Within my memory; I muſt draw neer him,</l>
                     <l>And yield to my impatience.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>THERSANDER, <hi>to</hi> ISMENIA.</speaker>
                     <l>Pardon me,</l>
                     <l>I can't believe thee; but here comes <hi>Diana;</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>See if her eys ha' n't the ſame cruelty,</l>
                     <l>Alwaies the ſame pride, and the ſame diſdain.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>DIANA.</speaker>
                     <p>
                        <hi>Iſmenia,</hi> I am come to tell thee ſomething.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>ISMENIA.</speaker>
                     <p>Me <hi>Celia?</hi>
                     </p>
                  </sp>
                  <pb n="34" facs="tcp:170544:17"/>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>THERSANDER.</speaker>
                     <p>How, <hi>Celia?</hi>
                     </p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>ISMENIA.</speaker>
                     <p>Yes, <hi>Celia.</hi>
                     </p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>THERSANDER.</speaker>
                     <l>Alas! I'm in an error; 'tis her eyes.</l>
                     <l>Her gate, her countenance, but not her heart.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>ISMENIA.</speaker>
                     <l>'Tis she, <hi>Therſander,</hi> whom thou do'ſt behold,</l>
                     <l>It is very ſelf.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>THERSANDER.</speaker>
                     <l>How! is't a cuſtome</l>
                     <l>To call forth from the boſom of the Grave</l>
                     <l>Departed ſouls? and by what priviledge</l>
                     <l>Hath that God, who at the eternal ſleep</l>
                     <l>Preſides, ordain'd her waking?</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>DIANA, <hi>to</hi> THERSANDER.</speaker>
                     <l>Though thy faith</l>
                     <l>Finds this point ſtrange, is not love ſtrong e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nough</l>
                     <l>To make thee to believe a Miracle?</l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Cleagenor</hi> ſees me, and knows me not:</l>
                     <l>How comes it, is my Portrait falſe? have J</l>
                     <l>No more artractions? ſee if't be thy <hi>Celia,</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>At leaſt if't be not she; it is no more</l>
                     <l>That beauty which was late ſo cruel to thee;</l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Cleagenor!</hi>
                     </l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>THERSANDER.</speaker>
                     <p>My <hi>Celia!</hi>
                     </p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>DIANA.</speaker>
                     <l>Is it poſſible,</l>
                     <l>O Gods! that J should ſee again what J</l>
                     <l>Beſt love i' th' World?</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>THERSANDER.</speaker>
                     <p>Is it you that J ſee?</p>
                  </sp>
                  <pb n="35" facs="tcp:170544:17"/>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>ISMENIA.</speaker>
                     <p>Take heed, be moderate, one may die with joy.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>THIMANTES.</speaker>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Iſmenia,</hi> follow this example here;</l>
                     <l>Grant only at this inſtant but a kiſſe</l>
                     <l>To my impatience, ſee at laſt <hi>Diana</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>Ceaſeth to be unkind.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>ISMENIA.</speaker>
                     <l>What! doth the object rouſe thee, and th' ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ample</l>
                     <l>Provoke thy ſpirits? thou wilt have but one kiſs?</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>THIMANTES.</speaker>
                     <p>I will be ſatisfied.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>ISMENIA.</speaker>
                     <l>Give me then</l>
                     <l>Some verſes, or at leaſt a noſe gay of</l>
                     <l>The choiceſt flowers.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>THIMANTES.</speaker>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Iſmenia,</hi> I'l not fail</l>
                     <l>To bring them thee.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>ISMENIA.</speaker>
                     <l>Then trouble not thy ſelf,</l>
                     <l>The kiſſe is thine.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>THIMANTES.</speaker>
                     <l>Wilt thou with hold from me</l>
                     <l>So long what is my due?</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>ISMENIA.</speaker>
                     <l>It will be better</l>
                     <l>When it is much expected, and long'd for.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>THERSANDER.</speaker>
                     <p>Behold my whole adventure in few words.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>DIANA.</speaker>
                     <l>I've made thee too a full deſcription</l>
                     <l>Of my misfortunes thou ſeeſt how I feign'd</l>
                     <l>(To give my grief full vent) a Brothers death</l>
                     <pb n="36" facs="tcp:170544:18"/>
                     <l>In weeping of my lovers.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>THERSANDER.</speaker>
                     <l>What felicity</l>
                     <l>Do I injoy now?</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>THIMANTES.</speaker>
                     <l>Uſe your utmoſt skil</l>
                     <l>To make it laſting to you, and beware of</l>
                     <l>The fickleneſs of fortune, and her wrongs.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>THERSANDER.</speaker>
                     <l>What! have we yet any thing more to fear?</l>
                     <l>Is not that blind inconſtant Goddeſs weary</l>
                     <l>Of perſecuting us?</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>THIMANTES.</speaker>
                     <l>Love is a child,</l>
                     <l>He muſt be govern'd well, <hi>Diana's</hi> beauty</l>
                     <l>Hath gain'd her lovers, they may hurt, <hi>Therſan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der;</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Melintus</hi> hath a ſubtle wit, and we</l>
                     <l>Both know he loves <hi>Daina,</hi> and beſides</l>
                     <l>Is jealous of her; fear ſome foul play from him,</l>
                     <l>If thou appear his Rival; he diſpoſeth</l>
                     <l>The ſpirit of <hi>Meliſſa</hi> at his pleaſure;</l>
                     <l>When he shall ſee you ſerve as obſtacle</l>
                     <l>Unto his love, he will take ſpeedy order</l>
                     <l>For your removal.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>THERSANDER.</speaker>
                     <l>But to hinder him</l>
                     <l>To hurt me, I conceive <hi>Diana</hi> hath</l>
                     <l>No leſſe power on the ſpirit of the Nymph.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>THIMANTES.</speaker>
                     <l>But if the Nymph loves thee, as I obſerv'd</l>
                     <l>Her heart expreſſed ſome ſuch matter lately,</l>
                     <l>When at her laſt return home from the Games,</l>
                     <l>Her free confeſſion to us all, declar'd</l>
                     <l>How much she did eſteem thee, but at laſt</l>
                     <pb n="37" facs="tcp:170544:18"/>
                     <l>With ſuch an eſteem that love followed</l>
                     <l>Cloſe at the heels in plain terms, and indeed</l>
                     <l>Spoken by her of purpoſe, if she loves thee,</l>
                     <l>I ſay (as I'm confirmed in that thought)</l>
                     <l>How wilt thou ſteer thy courſe?</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>ISMENIA.</speaker>
                     <l>'Tis very true,</l>
                     <l>Her diſcourſe comes into my memory.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>THERSANDER.</speaker>
                     <p>O Gods! what's this you utter?</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>DIANA.</speaker>
                     <l>For my part</l>
                     <l>I begin to believe it, and remember</l>
                     <l>The paſſage too, I fear all things from thence;</l>
                     <l>This is the only miſchief we should shun.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>ISMENIA.</speaker>
                     <l>What can she not do 'gainſt your intereſts,</l>
                     <l>When your refuſe shall come to arm her anger</l>
                     <l>Againſt you? Know that with a ſingle word,</l>
                     <l>I'th twinckling of an eye too, she can calm</l>
                     <l>The floods and make a mutiny amongſt them,</l>
                     <l>Call froth corrupted bodies from their graves,</l>
                     <l>Make their cold ashes ſpeak, and their pale ghoſts</l>
                     <l>To walk; theſe were the ſecrets, <hi>Zoroastres</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>Taught, whil'ſt he raign'd, to his poſterity;</l>
                     <l>She is deſcended from him; and to give</l>
                     <l>Her ſelf content, will make uſe of her art</l>
                     <l>To ſerve her paſſion.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>THERSANDER.</speaker>
                     <l>I know that her skill</l>
                     <l>Extends to Magick. Yes I fear her love</l>
                     <l>With ſo much power, and yield unto thy counſel</l>
                     <l>Adviſe us what to do.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>THIMANTE'S.</speaker>
                     <l>Diſugiſe your ſelves</l>
                     <pb n="39" facs="tcp:170544:19"/>
                     <l>Under the names of Brother, and of Siſter,</l>
                     <l>In the mean time we'l ſpread abroad the rumor</l>
                     <l>Of this event that every one shall hear it</l>
                     <l>Within the Iſland.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>THEERSANDER.</speaker>
                     <p>J approve this project.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>DIANA.</speaker>
                     <p>My life lies on it.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>ISMENIA.</speaker>
                     <l>I go to begin</l>
                     <l>To lie unto <hi>Parthenia.</hi>
                     </l>
                  </sp>
               </div>
               <div type="scene">
                  <head>SCENA IV. PARTHENIA, ISMENIA, DIANA, THERSANDER, THIMANTES.</head>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>PARTHENIA.</speaker>
                     <l>
                        <hi>JSmenia,</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>I would ſpeak one word with thee but a mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>ISMENIA.</speaker>
                     <l>Immediately when you have born a part</l>
                     <l>In the contentment of this pair; <hi>Diana</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>Hath for the future no more cauſe to weep</l>
                     <l>Heaven hath been pleas'd that she hath found her brother.</l>
                     <l>It is this happy Shepheard, they acknowledge</l>
                     <l>Each other.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>PARTHENIA.</speaker>
                     <l>This event, J muſt confeſs</l>
                     <l>Confounds my ſpirit; <hi>Therſander</hi> found her bro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther?</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>DIANA.</speaker>
                     <l>Yes Nymph, it is the ſame,</l>
                     <l>For whom my grief was hither to extream.</l>
                     <pb n="38" facs="tcp:170544:19"/>
                     <l>The Gods at length have heard my prayers and ſighs.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>THERSANDER.</speaker>
                     <p>Yes, Madam they have granted our deſires.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>PARTHENIA.</speaker>
                     <l>J'm very glad on't, and my ſoul is ravish'd</l>
                     <l>With this good fortune of our friends, which makes</l>
                     <l>Our lives content, <hi>Diana</hi> will obilge me</l>
                     <l>If she pleaſe at her leiſure to inform me</l>
                     <l>with the diſcovery; but acquaint the Nymph</l>
                     <l>Therewith, and to that purpoſe go to ſee her.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>THERSANDER.</speaker>
                     <p>We ow that duty to our Soveraign.</p>
                     <stage>Exeunt <hi>Therſ</hi> and <hi>Diana.</hi>
                     </stage>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>PARTHENIA.</speaker>
                     <l>In the mean time <hi>Iſmenia</hi> and my ſelf</l>
                     <l>May entertain each other in diſcourſe,</l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Thimantes,</hi> J believe, will not be jealous.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>THIMANTES</speaker>
                     <l>Let not a third come, Madam and J fear</l>
                     <l>Nothing from you.— <stage>Exit <hi>Thimantes.</hi>
                        </stage>
                     </l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>PARTHENIA.</speaker>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Iſmenia,</hi> J know not,</l>
                     <l>If J may ſafely tell a ſecret to thee,</l>
                     <l>Alas!</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>ISMENIA.</speaker>
                     <l>J know it well, ſince the heart ſighs;</l>
                     <l>When one would ſay J love, and dares not ſpeak is,</l>
                     <l>The heart at the nam'd point gives an Alas.</l>
                     <l>Have not J well divin'd?</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>PARTHENIA.</speaker>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Iſmenia.</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>I do confeſs it, ſee too, if thou canſt</l>
                     <l>Divine the object that procures my grief</l>
                     <l>Let me not ſpeak him, ſpare my cheeks thoſe</l>
                     <l>blushes.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <pb n="40" facs="tcp:170544:20"/>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>ISMENIA.</speaker>
                     <l>I cannot, a ſigh carries not ſo far;</l>
                     <l>You love; but what more, is beyond my skil</l>
                     <l>To underſtand, unleſs vour ſelf unfold</l>
                     <l>That ſigh unto me by its cauſe.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>PARTHENIA.</speaker>
                     <l>'Tis true</l>
                     <l>I love.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>ISMENIA.</speaker>
                     <p>But whom?</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>PARTHENIA.</speaker>
                     <p>'Tis—</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>ISMENIA.</speaker>
                     <p>Outwith't.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>PARTHENIA.</speaker>
                     <p>
                        <hi>Clidamant.</hi>
                     </p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>ISMENIA,</speaker>
                     <l>Behold a handſom way to name a Lover;</l>
                     <l>Ha! how you fear your lips should touch upon it!</l>
                     <l>One muſt draw 't word by word out of your mouth;</l>
                     <l>You have then but one lover; really</l>
                     <l>'Tis well as't happens; had you liſts of them</l>
                     <l>As I have, which I name, and reckon over</l>
                     <l>Every hour of the day, your bashfullneſs</l>
                     <l>Would well become you; love is a fair fruit,</l>
                     <l>But then it muſt be gathered, modeſty</l>
                     <l>Leaves it to fall and wither, but I pray you</l>
                     <l>What will <hi>Meliſſa</hi> ſay to't, who intends</l>
                     <l>To match her Neece to <hi>Thirſis?</hi>
                     </l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>PARTHENIA.</speaker>
                     <l>Oh! I hate</l>
                     <l>That <hi>Thirſis,</hi> and shall be even in deſpair,</l>
                     <l>If the Nymph force me to obſerve my duty</l>
                     <l>In that particular; yet I would keep it</l>
                     <pb n="41" facs="tcp:170544:20"/>
                     <l>Without diſturbance, if the love I bear</l>
                     <l>To <hi>Clidamant</hi> should not return me his;</l>
                     <l>For to ſpeak truly I am violent</l>
                     <l>Where honour doth ingage me, therefore would I</l>
                     <l>Have his heart to be ſounded, and as I</l>
                     <l>Find it diſpos'd, I should purſue my love,</l>
                     <l>Or quench my flame.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>ISMENIA.</speaker>
                     <l>Speak unto him your ſelf,</l>
                     <l>Nothing's more eaſie.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>PARTHENIA.</speaker>
                     <l>But, <hi>Iſmenia.</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>Thou haſt a wit would help me; if I should</l>
                     <l>Speak to him, he hath little underſtanding</l>
                     <l>If he should not know that I firſt was taken</l>
                     <l>And I should ſin againſt the rule of maids</l>
                     <l>To make ſuch a confeſſion.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>ISMENIA.</speaker>
                     <p>You may write then,</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>PARTHENIA.</speaker>
                     <l>That is all one, ſtill the ſame point of honour</l>
                     <l>Forbids it me; my Letter would diſcover</l>
                     <l>My love, and make him boaſt thereof, perhaps,</l>
                     <l>To my dishonour, if he might have once</l>
                     <l>That mark on't in his hand.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>ISMENIA.</speaker>
                     <l>Let him then</l>
                     <l>Divine it, if he be Aſtrologer.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>PARTHENIA.</speaker>
                     <p>Treat not my paſſion thus with railery.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>ISMENIA.</speaker>
                     <l>I muſt then ſerve you in it, I perceive;</l>
                     <l>Well I'l about it with my beſt invention;</l>
                     <l>I'l write a Letter to him, and invite him</l>
                     <l>By a feign'd love, as ſoon as it is night,</l>
                     <pb n="42" facs="tcp:170544:21"/>
                     <l>To meet me at the Eccho of the Garden,</l>
                     <l>To entertain us there.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>PARTHENIA.</speaker>
                     <l>So in my abſence.</l>
                     <l>Thou shalt diſcern his thought.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>ISMENIA.</speaker>
                     <l>This buſineſs</l>
                     <l>Concerns you, Madam, and requires your pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſence.</l>
                     <l>You shall ſpeak ſoftly to him, and in thoſe</l>
                     <l>Sweet moments, you shall underſtand much bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter</l>
                     <l>What his thoughts are, and thus you may your ſelf,</l>
                     <l>To find out if he loves, ſpeak of your ſelf.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>PARTHENIA.</speaker>
                     <p>Thou wilt be preſent too?</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>ISMENIA.</speaker>
                     <l>Yes, J'l ſo well</l>
                     <l>Contrive it, that he shal believe undoubtedly</l>
                     <l>That it is I that ſpeak.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>PARTHENIA.</speaker>
                     <l>But how can we</l>
                     <l>Speak to the Eccho, for thou know'ſt the Nymph,</l>
                     <l>As ſoon as it is night, retires her ſelf,</l>
                     <l>And then we cannot come there, what deviſe now</l>
                     <l>Haſt thou that we may ſpeak to him?</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>ISMENIA.</speaker>
                     <l>Cannot we</l>
                     <l>Speak to him from the terraſs which joins cloſe</l>
                     <l>Unto the Garden; you know that you can</l>
                     <l>Conveniently come there at any hour</l>
                     <l>From your apartment; 'tis upon this ground,</l>
                     <l>And theſe conjunctures, that I've ta'n the plot</l>
                     <l>For my invention.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>PARTHENIA.</speaker>
                     <l>J admire thy wit,</l>
                     <pb n="43" facs="tcp:170544:21"/>
                     <l>Tis wonderfull induſtrious and ready.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>ISMENIA.</speaker>
                     <l>I'l write the Letter here before your eyes,</l>
                     <l>Behold the paper for it.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>PARTHENIA.</speaker>
                     <l>How, theſe are</l>
                     <l>Thy writing Tables!</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>ISMENIA.</speaker>
                     <l>They can ſpeak of Paſſions</l>
                     <l>Diſcreet and ſecret; J'l about my buſineſs,</l>
                     <l>And uſe my ſmootheſt ſtile.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>PARTHENIA,</speaker>
                     <l>Eſpecially</l>
                     <l>Appoint him wel the hour and place of meeting:</l>
                     <l>How redevable am J to thy wit</l>
                     <l>For this great favour? what do J not ow thee</l>
                     <l>For this good office, thou giv'ſt me again.</l>
                     <l>Life, and repoſe.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>ISMENIA.</speaker>
                     <l>See what J write unto him</l>
                     <l>In two words for you, they are very preſſing,</l>
                     <l>And will ingage him to betake himſelf</l>
                     <l>Unto the place appointed to know more.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>PARTHENIA.</speaker>
                     <p>'Tis very well; it reſts now how to giv' 't him.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>ISMENIA.</speaker>
                     <p>Leave me the care of that; but here he comes.</p>
                  </sp>
               </div>
               <div type="scene">
                  <pb n="44" facs="tcp:170544:22"/>
                  <head>SCENA V. MELINTUS, CLIDAMANT, PARTHENIA, ISMENIA.</head>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>MELINTUS, to CLIDAMANT.</speaker>
                     <p>YES, J have heard <hi>Diana</hi> is his ſiſter.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>CLIDAMANT, to PARTHENIA.</speaker>
                     <l>Madam, <hi>Melintus</hi> and my ſelfare going</l>
                     <l>To ſeek <hi>Therſander,</hi> to congratulare</l>
                     <l>With him his happy meeting with his ſiſter.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>ISMENIA, <hi>to</hi> CLIDAMANT.</speaker>
                     <stage>ſeftly</stage>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Therſander</hi>'s happy, and thou art no leſſe,</l>
                     <l>Since thy good fortune offereth it ſelf</l>
                     <l>Unto thy hand, from whence thou mai'ſt expect</l>
                     <l>All that thou canſt deſire without that jealous.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>PARTHENIA, <hi>to</hi> ISMENIA.</speaker>
                     <p>Come, let us go, the Nymph expecteth us.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>ISMENIA, <hi>ſoftly to</hi> CLIDAMANT.</speaker>
                     <l>Having no opportunity at preſent</l>
                     <l>To ſpeak unto thee, read, J think 't will pleaſe thee.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>CLIDAMANT.</speaker>
                     <l>Read it, J think 't will pleaſe thee, what i'th name</l>
                     <l>Of wonder doth she mean?</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>MELINTUS.</speaker>
                     <l>Take but the pain</l>
                     <l>To open, and to read it thou shalt find.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>CLIDAMANT.</speaker>
                     <l>J think, J may make thine eys withneſſes</l>
                     <l>Of what it doth contain, there's nothing in it</l>
                     <l>Secret of ſerious, <hi>Iſmenia</hi> loves</l>
                     <l>To jeſt, and to be talk'd of; and this is</l>
                     <pb n="45" facs="tcp:170544:22"/>
                     <l>Some new piece of her wonted merry wit.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>MELINTUS.</speaker>
                     <p>J am impatient, prethee open it.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>CLIDAMANT.</speaker>
                     <l>Let me ſee what divertiſement is here,</l>
                     <l>Which she expounds good fortune, what is this?</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>He reads.</speaker>
                     <l>Liſt of my Lovers by an exact order</l>
                     <l>Of Alphabet.</l>
                     <l>'Tis very well put of;</l>
                     <l>But ſo far forth as J can ſee yet, neither</l>
                     <l>Obſetve J here <hi>Melintus</hi> or my ſelf.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>MELINTUS.</speaker>
                     <l>For my part, J renounce there; turn the leaf,</l>
                     <l>Go on.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>CLIDAMANT,</speaker>
                     <stage>reads.</stage>
                     <p>
                        <hi>Stanza's of</hi> Dorilas <hi>upon inconſtancy.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <lg>
                        <l>'Tis true, <hi>Iſmenia</hi> thou are fair,</l>
                        <l>But more inconſtant then the air;</l>
                        <l>And every Lover is a Mark</l>
                        <l>Expoſed to thy humourous dart;</l>
                        <l>As ſoon as he meets thy diſdain,</l>
                        <l>He flies to death to cure his pain,</l>
                        <l>And makes but one large ſtep in all</l>
                        <l>From his bright glory to his fall.</l>
                     </lg>
                     <lg>
                        <l>With theſe defects yet thou canſt charm;</l>
                        <l>But I'l not love, for fear of harm;</l>
                        <l>Yet J approve all things in thee,</l>
                        <l>Yea even to thy inconſtancy;</l>
                        <pb n="46" facs="tcp:170544:23"/>
                        <l>And will not, to incur thy hate,</l>
                        <l>Jealous <hi>Melintus</hi> imitate,</l>
                        <l>Whoſe humour every thing offends,</l>
                        <l>And nothing pleaſeth but its ends.</l>
                     </lg>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>CLIDAMANT.</speaker>
                     <p>
                        <hi>Melintus,</hi> what ſai'ſt thou unto them?</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>MELINTUS.</speaker>
                     <l>J ſee for what deſign she put thoſe Tables</l>
                     <l>Into thy hand, J call'd her cocket lately,</l>
                     <l>And that, it ſeems, provok'd her to return me</l>
                     <l>The injury with one of the ſame nature.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>CLIDAMANT,</speaker>
                     <stage>continues to read.</stage>
                     <l>Sonnet of <hi>Silvio,</hi> my moſt faithfull Lover.</l>
                     <l>A Madrigal of <hi>Thirſis,</hi>—what's this follows,</l>
                     <l>Unto the Shepheard <hi>Clidamant.</hi>
                     </l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>CLIDAMANT.</speaker>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Melintus,</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>Am J not purblinde, ſee if this name doth Strike thine eyes thus like mine!</l>
                     <stage>Melintus <hi>looking into the writing Tables.</hi>
                     </stage>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>MELINTUS.</speaker>
                     <l>Nothing 's more certain,</l>
                     <l>It is addreſs'd to thee; thou art more happy</l>
                     <l>Then thou imagin'ſt</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>CLIDAMANT,</speaker>
                     <stage>reads.</stage>
                     <l>
                        <hi>As ſoon as the dark shadows of the night</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Hang o'r the light,</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>At th' Eccho of the Garden let us meet;</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>But be diſcreet;</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>'Tis love invites thee; more anon,</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>When w' 're alone.</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Iſmenia.</hi>
                     </l>
                     <stage>Melintus <hi>would take the writing Tables.</hi>
                     </stage>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>MELINTUS.</speaker>
                     <l>Prethee let me ſee them,</l>
                     <pb n="47" facs="tcp:170544:23"/>
                     <l>Grant me this favor—not, then J, believe</l>
                     <l>Thou do'ſt diſguiſe the truth, and read'ſt <hi>Iſmenia,</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>When 'tis ſubſcrib'd <hi>Diana.</hi>
                     </l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>CLIDAMANT.</speaker>
                     <l>Oh fond jealous!</l>
                     <l>How long wilt thou thus be thy own tormenter?</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>MELINTUS.</speaker>
                     <p>Yet shew them me.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>CLIDAMANT.</speaker>
                     <l>To cure thy troubled ſpirit,</l>
                     <l>J 'l firſt o'r come thy curioſity;</l>
                     <l>And ſince the diſcreet Lover, what vain heat</l>
                     <l>So ever preſſeth thee, never shews thus</l>
                     <l>His Miſtreſs name—</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>MELINTUS.</speaker>
                     <p>But—</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>CLIDAMANT.</speaker>
                     <l>Quit thoſe blind ſuſpicions; as ſoon</l>
                     <l>As it is night I'l go unto the Eccho</l>
                     <l>Alone, and with our noiſe; <hi>I</hi>'m all a fire</l>
                     <l>To know what she will tell me, in the mean time</l>
                     <l>Let's go unto the Nymph to ſeek <hi>Therſander.</hi>
                     </l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>MELINTUS,</speaker>
                     <stage>ſofly</stage>
                     <l>To be more ſure, and to inform my ſelf</l>
                     <l>Yet fuller of thy faith in this my doubt,</l>
                     <l>I'l to the Eccho too, and ſind it out.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <trailer>The end of the ſecond Act.</trailer>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div n="3" type="act">
               <pb n="48" facs="tcp:170544:24"/>
               <head>ACTUS III.</head>
               <div type="scene">
                  <head>SCENA I. MELISSA, DIANA.</head>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>MELISSA.</speaker>
                     <l>I Say to thee again that J receive</l>
                     <l>Much pleaſute at this news, that thou, <hi>Diana,</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>Art ſiſter to the generous <hi>Therſander;</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>He hath inform'd me with the ſtrange misfor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tune</l>
                     <l>Which ſeparated on the churlish Sea</l>
                     <l>The Brother from the Siſter, in what place</l>
                     <l>Upon a plank, eſcaped from the wrack,</l>
                     <l>The ſtorm remov'd him from the anger of</l>
                     <l>Th' inraged Sea, what countries he hath ſeen,</l>
                     <l>What pains and troubles he hath undergone;</l>
                     <l>Laſtly he nam'd the happy fortune which</l>
                     <l>Conducted him to us here; I thank Heaven,</l>
                     <l>That made thee know him, I'm as ſenſible</l>
                     <l>Of this content as thou canſt be thy ſelf;</l>
                     <l>He is ſo highly qualified, that he's worthy</l>
                     <l>The name of King, ye both shal find with me</l>
                     <l>A Sanctuary, and what ever fortune</l>
                     <l>Ye have, I will partake it good or bad;</l>
                     <l>My fortunes, ye shall bare too, ſo that all things</l>
                     <l>Between us shall be common: I believe</l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Diana</hi> towards me will be ſo well</l>
                     <l>Diſpos'd of her part, and that whatſoever</l>
                     <l>Concerns me, will touch her.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>DIANA.</speaker>
                     <l>Madam, I should</l>
                     <l>Be barbarouſly ingratefull otherwiſe;</l>
                     <pb n="49" facs="tcp:170544:24"/>
                     <l>I ſtill remember that being on the Shore,</l>
                     <l>Caſt as a wretched wrack there by the floods,</l>
                     <l>Expecting every minute deaths approach,</l>
                     <l>I met with you my port and ſanctuary:</l>
                     <l>Oh that I have not power for all this goodneſs</l>
                     <l>T'expreſs how much acknowledgement I have!</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>MELISSA.</speaker>
                     <p>Thou haſt.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>DIANA.</speaker>
                     <p>How Madam?</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>MELISSA.</speaker>
                     <l>In expecting nothing</l>
                     <l>But death as I do now, thou canſt be to me</l>
                     <l>At thy turn both my port and ſancturary;</l>
                     <l>Thou canſt ſubdue the enemy that braves me,</l>
                     <l>That of a Soveraign will make a ſlave;</l>
                     <l>He's in thy power, thou canſt abate his courage.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>DIANA.</speaker>
                     <p>What is that enemy which troubles you?</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>MELISSA.</speaker>
                     <l>He's one whoſe Magick can enchant the arms</l>
                     <l>Of the moſt Valiant; he can draw tears from</l>
                     <l>The moſt Heroick; nothing is ſo ſtrong,</l>
                     <l>Which he can't compaſs; and without reſpect</l>
                     <l>To any place or perſon whatſoever,</l>
                     <l>He equally diſtributeth his flames.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>DIANA.</speaker>
                     <p>I know him not yet by this Character.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>MELISSA.</speaker>
                     <l>How know'ſt thou not that tyrant of great Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>narcks?</l>
                     <l>That famons Conqueror of Conquerours,</l>
                     <l>Who notwithſtanding is but a blind child?</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>DIANA.</speaker>
                     <l>If J durſt to expreſs me, J believe,</l>
                     <pb n="50" facs="tcp:170544:25"/>
                     <l>I know him.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>MELISSA.</speaker>
                     <p>Speak it freely.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>DIANA.</speaker>
                     <l>I'm miſtaken,</l>
                     <l>Or I have ſeen love painted in ſuch colours,</l>
                     <l>Blind and a child, yet a great Conquerour.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>MELISSA.</speaker>
                     <p>'Tis the ſame love whereof I ſpeak unto thee</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>DIANA.</speaker>
                     <l>Who is the happy Lover that procures</l>
                     <l>Your martyrdome?</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>MELISSA.</speaker>
                     <l>Alas! could'ſt thou not ſpare me</l>
                     <l>The shame to ſpeak him? cover, gentle night,</l>
                     <l>Immediately thoſe places and my brow</l>
                     <l>With the ſame colour, ſo to pleaſe my heat;</l>
                     <l>I love; but let us finish ſince I've ſaid</l>
                     <l>I love, <hi>Therſander</hi> is my object.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>DIANA.</speaker>
                     <l>What,</l>
                     <l>My Brother?</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>MELISSA.</speaker>
                     <l>He. If his heart be a prize</l>
                     <l>Not eaſie to be gain'd, there's nothing which</l>
                     <l>I would ſpare for him, I would arm to have him;</l>
                     <l>Nought should oppoſe me, every obſtacle</l>
                     <l>J would o'rcome; already by ſome words</l>
                     <l>Which he obſerv'd not, ſpoken by the bie,</l>
                     <l>My love was half expreſſed.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>DIANA.</speaker>
                     <l>As he should not</l>
                     <l>Dare to pretend unto ſo great an honour,</l>
                     <l>He would be criminal, if he believed</l>
                     <l>To underſtand you.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <pb n="51" facs="tcp:170544:25"/>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>MELISSA.</speaker>
                     <l>Well then, be thou here</l>
                     <l>The mouth and true interpreter of my heart,</l>
                     <l>Expreſs the kind heat of my timerous ſoul;</l>
                     <l>Tell him that I'm a ſubject to his Laws,</l>
                     <l>That he may boldly fix his thoughts upon</l>
                     <l>The perſon of <hi>Meliſsa,</hi> and not fear</l>
                     <l>To be condemn'd, that his ambition</l>
                     <l>May ſoar ſo high a pitch, and not be check'd,</l>
                     <l>That he may ſigh the ſame ſighs with a King;</l>
                     <l>Husband thar heart for me, to which mine aims;</l>
                     <l>But let him not think that it comes from me;</l>
                     <l>My honour would receive a prejudice</l>
                     <l>By ſuch a thought, thou only shalt acquaint him</l>
                     <l>With this, as from thy ſelf.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>DIANA.</speaker>
                     <l>J underſtand you,</l>
                     <l>He muſt needs yield to this; I'l do your will.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>MELISSA.</speaker>
                     <l>As ſoon as he appears, I will retire me,</l>
                     <l>And from one of theſe places I shall hear</l>
                     <l>Every word that you ſpeak one to another</l>
                     <l>In reference to my flame.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>DIANA.</speaker>
                     <l>I should methinks</l>
                     <l>Act with more freeneſs, if J were to treat</l>
                     <l>With him alone.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>MELISSA.</speaker>
                     <l>No, J will hear my ſelf</l>
                     <l>What he thinks of me, J can beſt of all</l>
                     <l>Truſt mine own ears and eyes in this affair.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>DIANA.</speaker>
                     <p>But, Madam, after all—</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>MELISSA.</speaker>
                     <l>Shepheardeſs,</l>
                     <pb n="52" facs="tcp:170544:26"/>
                     <l>The thing's reſolv'd, thou need'ſt not ſay no more.</l>
                     <l>Untill he come, J pray thee, entertain</l>
                     <l>Theſe woods here with ſome air, and let us ſee</l>
                     <l>If the Eccho will anſwer to thy diſcourſe;</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>DIANA.</speaker>
                     <l>Your prayer is a command; ſome plaints of love</l>
                     <l>Shall make the ſubject of it.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>MELISSA.</speaker>
                     <p>What thou wilt.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <q>
                     <floatingText xml:lang="eng">
                        <body>
                           <div type="song">
                              <head>DIANAS Song.</head>
                              <lg>
                                 <l>Ye Trees, ye Rocks, perfumed Valleys, ſweet</l>
                                 <l>And charming Zephirs, murmuring fountains keep</l>
                                 <l>My griefs cloſe in your boſome, you alone</l>
                                 <l>Are witneſſes unto my fires and mone,</l>
                                 <l>Tell me if my ſad heart, not daring to</l>
                                 <l>Delare it it ſelf, at leaſt may ſigh its woe?</l>
                                 <l>May ſigh its woe—Eccho.</l>
                              </lg>
                              <lg>
                                 <l>Well then my ſighs, make no noiſe as pe paſſe</l>
                                 <l>The airy Regions only breath alas</l>
                                 <l>Vnto the heart that ſent you forth; ſince I</l>
                                 <l>Can't ſpeak to thee, dear object of my cry,</l>
                                 <l>Let th' Ecco, that's attentive, ſay for me</l>
                                 <l>That if I love (as ſure I do) 'tis thee.</l>
                                 <l>'tis thee—Eccho</l>
                              </lg>
                           </div>
                        </body>
                     </floatingText>
                  </q>
               </div>
               <div type="scene">
                  <pb n="53" facs="tcp:170544:26"/>
                  <head>SCENA II. THERSANDER, MELISSA, DIANA.</head>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>THERSANDER.</speaker>
                     <p>
                        <hi>DIana</hi>'s here about, her voice aſſures me.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>MELISSA <hi>to</hi> DIANA.</speaker>
                     <stage>ſoftly</stage>
                     <l>Thy Brother comes here, take this opportunity.</l>
                     <l>Be ſure thou ſpeak unto him loud enough;</l>
                     <l>Thou art my only hope; I go from hence</l>
                     <l>To hear, and to obſerve thee.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>DIANA.</speaker>
                     <stage>ſoftly.</stage>
                     <l>We are undone,</l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Therſander</hi> will diſcover all in ſpeaking.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>THERSANDER.</speaker>
                     <l>'Tis now no longer time to utter ſighs,</l>
                     <l>Let us reſume our joy, and dry our tears,</l>
                     <l>Crown our ſad ſpirits with flowers, and think no more of</l>
                     <l>Our paſs'd misfortunes, let's form our diſcourſe</l>
                     <l>Of the moſt pleaſant thoughts, and let us chat</l>
                     <l>Of love.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>DIANA.</speaker>
                     <l>Let me alone, I'l entertain thee</l>
                     <l>Upon that ſubject.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>THEERSANDER.</speaker>
                     <l>It belongs to me</l>
                     <l>To ſpeak of that, and when I do conſider</l>
                     <l>With what darts in my heart—</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>DIANA.</speaker>
                     <l>I know it well</l>
                     <l>'Tis of a longer date then from to day,</l>
                     <l>That I have read thy heart; and I believe</l>
                     <pb n="54" facs="tcp:170544:27"/>
                     <l>That never any one hath ſeen a Brother</l>
                     <l>To love his ſiſter ſo.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>THERSANDER.</speaker>
                     <l>The love wherewith</l>
                     <l>I am aſſaulted, and would make thee ſee,</l>
                     <l>Exceeds that of a brother, it begets,</l>
                     <l>Complaints and Sighs, it driveth to deſpair,</l>
                     <l>And kills; the love we bear unto a Siſter,</l>
                     <l>Makes not ſo many ſufferings; but J love—</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>DIANA.</speaker>
                     <l>J divine whom, thou burneſt with deſire</l>
                     <l>To ſpeak unto me here of <hi>Celiaes</hi> love.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>THERSANDER.</speaker>
                     <l>Thou do'ſt divine right, J take a great pleaſure</l>
                     <l>To ſpeak of it with thee; methinks I ſee her</l>
                     <l>Still when J look on thee; how ſit I find thee</l>
                     <l>To be the faithfull guardian of my love,</l>
                     <l>Aſſur'd of thy fidelity, and that</l>
                     <l>Thy heart is alwaies mine.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>DIANA.</speaker>
                     <p>Thou need'ſt not doubt it.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>THERSANDER.</speaker>
                     <p>O my dear!</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>DIANA.</speaker>
                     <l>Brother I'm not ignorant</l>
                     <l>How dear I am unto thee.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>THIMANTES.</speaker>
                     <p>Thy fair eyes—</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>DIANA.</speaker>
                     <l>How! flatter and court thy ſiſter</l>
                     <l>By thy diſcourſe?</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>THERSANDER.</speaker>
                     <l>I cannot ſpeak, unto thee</l>
                     <l>Thou interrupt'ſt me ſtill.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <pb n="55" facs="tcp:170544:27"/>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>DIANA.</speaker>
                     <l>Th' advice is worth it, and I'l give thee notice</l>
                     <l>That from eſteem they paſs to love for thee,</l>
                     <l>That ſcarce arrivedſt thou unto this place</l>
                     <l>But thy good fortune without any trouble</l>
                     <l>Gain'd thee the conqueſt of a heart, for which</l>
                     <l>Great Kings will envie thee, it is <hi>Meliſſa</hi>'s.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>THERSANDER.</speaker>
                     <p>O Gods! what doſt thou ſay?</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>DIANA.</speaker>
                     <l>What doth aſtonish thee,</l>
                     <l>I ſee how thou art troubled to believe it.</l>
                     <p>This great heart finds no place yet in thy faith:</p>
                     <l>To make thee happy in't, I muſt imbrace thee.</l>
                     <stage>She ſpeaks ſoftly to him, in imbracing him. The Nymph hears our diſcourſe, 'tis fit thou feign. She ſpeaks loud again.</stage>
                     <l>Wilt thou not yield to this exceſs of honour?</l>
                     <l>Think that thy <hi>Celia</hi> in this conjuncture,</l>
                     <l>Hath no reſentment in her heart againſt thee,</l>
                     <l>Nor murmurs at it.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>THERSANDER.</speaker>
                     <l>In this extaſie</l>
                     <l>Wherein I am through this exceſs of honour,</l>
                     <l>I'm ſeeking of my ſelf, but cannot find me.</l>
                     <l>How! dare to love the Nymph? t'aſpire to her?</l>
                     <l>No my ambition's not ſo criminal.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>DIANA.</speaker>
                     <p>Under thoſe high reſpects, J ſee thy love.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>THERSANDER.</speaker>
                     <l>How can I otherwiſe expreſs it, Siſter?</l>
                     <l>It the Nymph tempts me, and will make a crime on't,</l>
                     <l>It shall then have the name but of a lawfull</l>
                     <pb n="56" facs="tcp:170544:28"/>
                     <l>Reſpect; and if I ſee occaſion</l>
                     <l>T'expreſs me further on this point, this lawfull</l>
                     <l>Reſpect shall bear the bolder name of love.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>DIANA.</speaker>
                     <l>Brotherm, it hath that name, and J am ready</l>
                     <l>To boaſt unto her, her illuſtrious conqueſt:</l>
                     <l>But the Sun, J perceive, plungeth himſelf</l>
                     <l>I' th' waters, and the shadows ſeiſe the tops</l>
                     <l>O' th' Mountains, it is time now to betake me</l>
                     <l>Unto <hi>Meliſſa;</hi> but behold, she comes.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <stage>Meliſſa <hi>comes forth from the place where she was hidden.</hi>
                  </stage>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>MELISSA.</speaker>
                     <p>What ſerious diſcourſe have you together?</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>DIANA.</speaker>
                     <l>Our ſubject is of Love, of Miſtreſſes,</l>
                     <l>Of Servants, and of Sighs.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>MELISSA.</speaker>
                     <l>What! hath <hi>Therſander</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>Already gotten him a Miſtreſs?</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>THERSANDER.</speaker>
                     <l>Madam,</l>
                     <l>I have too little merit and addreſs:</l>
                     <l>Beſides to ſerve, to honour and obey you,</l>
                     <l>I have no other thought; our diſcourſe was,</l>
                     <l>Your goodneſs for us, which my heart shall ever</l>
                     <l>Record as in a Regiſter of Braſs,</l>
                     <l>Where my acknowledgements shall never paſs.</l>
                  </sp>
               </div>
               <div type="scene">
                  <pb n="57" facs="tcp:170544:28"/>
                  <head>SCENA III. MELINTUS, MELISSA, DIANA, THER<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>SANDER.</head>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>MELINTVS.</speaker>
                     <stage>calling.</stage>
                     <p>HO, <hi>Clidamant!</hi>
                     </p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>MELISSA.</speaker>
                     <l>It is enough, let's go,</l>
                     <l>I hear ſome noiſe, and would not be ſeen here</l>
                     <l>I' rh' night.—</l>
                     <stage>Exeunt <hi>Meliſſa, Diana, Therſander.</hi>
                     </stage>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>MELINTUS,</speaker>
                     <stage>continuing to call.</stage>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Iſmenia, Clidamant!</hi> they hear,</l>
                     <l>But flie me, and the night robs my ſight of them;</l>
                     <l>But this is not <hi>Iſmenia,</hi> and I am</l>
                     <l>Deceived much, if I ſaw not the gate,</l>
                     <l>The ſtature, and the geſture of <hi>Diana;</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>Yes, <hi>Clidamant</hi> abus'd me with a lie,</l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Diana</hi> builds his fortune at my coſt,</l>
                     <l>And that note which he would conceal from me</l>
                     <l>Without doubt was ſubſcrib'd with her fair hand;</l>
                     <l>Yes, 'twas <hi>Dianaes,</hi> though he read <hi>Iſmenia,</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>To ſpare my grief a little, and my trouble.</l>
                     <l>How ſimple was J that J followed</l>
                     <l>Not cloſe upon his ſteps: but ſoft, methinks,</l>
                     <l>J hear a noiſe, perhaps it may be he.</l>
                  </sp>
               </div>
               <div type="scene">
                  <pb n="58" facs="tcp:170544:29"/>
                  <head>SCENA IV. CLIDAMANT, MELINTUS.</head>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>CLIDAMANT.</speaker>
                     <l>O Night, lend me thy ſilence, make theſe woods</l>
                     <l>To hold their peace in th' abſence of the day,</l>
                     <l>And let no ſound be heard here but my love:</l>
                     <l>At laſt I'm happily delivered from</l>
                     <l>A troubleſome companion, that would</l>
                     <l>Obſtruct my fortune, that ſame jealous Shep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>heard</l>
                     <l>Without reſpect and faith.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>MELINTUS.</speaker>
                     <l>I'm much oblig'd</l>
                     <l>Unto thee for this noble character</l>
                     <l>Thou giv'ſt me; in deſpight of all my care</l>
                     <l>And cunning thou art come without my com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pany</l>
                     <l>To ſee thy lovely Miſtreſs.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>CLIDAMANT.</speaker>
                     <l>I came here</l>
                     <l>To meet another perſon: for my Miſtreſs,</l>
                     <l>I have already ſpoken with her fully.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>MELINTUS.</speaker>
                     <l>Yes, if mine eyes deceiv'd me not, thou talkd'ſt</l>
                     <l>Unto <hi>Diana,</hi> and ſeeing me follow,</l>
                     <l>Ye both fled at one time, theſe Woods conceal'd you.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>CLIDAMANT.</speaker>
                     <p>Good Gods! what ſaieſt thou to me?</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>MELINTUS.</speaker>
                     <l>But I'l be</l>
                     <l>More wiſe another time, and heed you better.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>CLIDAMANT.</speaker>
                     <l>I underſtand not what this language means,</l>
                     <l>But this diſtruſt doth me an injury:</l>
                     <pb n="59" facs="tcp:170544:29"/>
                     <l>Why covet'ſt thou t' accompany me thus,</l>
                     <l>Since th' object that expecteth me, forbids it;</l>
                     <l>Deſireſt thou to publish ſecret paſſions?</l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Iſmenia</hi> in thy ſight gave me thoſe Tables;</l>
                     <l>'Tis she that doth expect me at the place</l>
                     <l>Appointed; for <hi>Diana,</hi> she knows nothing</l>
                     <l>Of this invention: if thou canſt, injoy</l>
                     <l>That lovely Shepheardeſs and think not me</l>
                     <l>Guilty of any treaſon, I ſeek only</l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Iſmenia,</hi> and shun ſociety:</l>
                     <l>In this affair, Shepheard retire thy ſelf</l>
                     <l>And leave my love in peace, why wouldſt thou do me</l>
                     <l>So ill an office?</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>MELINTUS.</speaker>
                     <l>This appointed meeting</l>
                     <l>Denotes ſome artifice; I obſerv'd lately</l>
                     <l>At our laſt Games the amorous commerce</l>
                     <l>That paſs'd between <hi>Diana</hi> and thy ſelf,</l>
                     <l>So many kind reſpects, ſuch gentle glances,</l>
                     <l>And private whilſperings forming the ſuſpicion</l>
                     <l>That ſtill awakes me.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>CLIDAMANT.</speaker>
                     <l>Ceaſe to trouble me,</l>
                     <l>And thy ſelf too unneceſſarily;</l>
                     <l>Our diſcourſe only was an effect of</l>
                     <l>Civility; I ſay again, I leave</l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Diana</hi> to thee; oh how perfectly</l>
                     <l>I hate thoſe vain ſuſpicions and condemn them!</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>MELINTUS.</speaker>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Iſmenia</hi>'s very free she would have had</l>
                     <l>Boldneſs enough to expreſs her love by day,</l>
                     <l>Why should she make choice of the night to ſpeak it?</l>
                     <l>Why dar'd she not to utter it in words,</l>
                     <l>But writ it to thee?</l>
                  </sp>
                  <pb n="60" facs="tcp:170544:30"/>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>CLIDAMANT.</speaker>
                     <l>In vain jealous Shepheard,</l>
                     <l>Thou askeſt me that queſtion, all that I</l>
                     <l>Can ſay unto thee, is that I am ſent for;</l>
                     <l>I cannot tell thee more if the occaſion</l>
                     <l>Be good or bad; if J could ſatisfie thee</l>
                     <l>Upon that point, believ't thou should'ſt excuſe me.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>MELINTUS.</speaker>
                     <p>I'l follow thee where ere thou goeſt.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>CLIDAMANT.</speaker>
                     <l>Oh Gods!</l>
                     <l>What a Tormentor have I?</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>MELINTUS.</speaker>
                     <p>I attend thee,</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>CLIDAMANT.</speaker>
                     <l>Then ſtay thou here, I'l leave the place unto thee.</l>
                     <l>I ſeign to withdraw, to withdraw him alſo. <stage>ſoftly. Exit.</stage>
                     </l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>MELINTUS.</speaker>
                     <l>What! leav'ſt thou me alone? and cunningly</l>
                     <l>Hid'ſt me thoſe ſecrets, which yet I muſt know:</l>
                     <l>Feign as much as thou wilt, in ſpight of thee</l>
                     <l>I will ſind out to which of thoſe two objects</l>
                     <l>Thou giv'ſt thy faith, and doſt direct they vows,</l>
                     <l>I'l be a witneſs of thy ſecret love;</l>
                     <l>Another shall inform me on't, <hi>Thimantes</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>Will tell me all the Plot; to him I'l go,</l>
                     <l>And give him notice of the aſſignation;</l>
                     <l>He'l come to let me know ſure, if <hi>Diana</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>Appeareth there; or if it be <hi>Iſmenia,</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>J shall do him a miſchief; when <hi>Thimantes</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>Shall ſee his Miſtreſs appoint ſecret meetings</l>
                     <l>To others then himſelf at ſuch an hour,</l>
                     <pb n="61" facs="tcp:170544:30"/>
                     <l>He hath a poor ſpirit if he loves her ſtill:</l>
                     <l>So shall I have pleaſure in my reſentment</l>
                     <l>In weakning the ſierceneſs of <hi>Iſmenia,</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>And of her ſervant, I'l to him immediately.</l>
                  </sp>
               </div>
               <div type="scene">
                  <head>SCENA V. PARTHENIA, ISMENIA.</head>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>PARTHENIA, <hi>upon the terraſs.</hi>
                     </speaker>
                     <p>I Hear a noiſe, <hi>Iſmenia,</hi> is't not <hi>Clidamant?</hi>
                     </p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>ISMENIA.</speaker>
                     <p>Fear not, we shall hear of him preſently.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>PARTHENIA.</speaker>
                     <l>J hear no more noiſe, all is husht and ſtill;</l>
                     <l>Only the night, and ſilence raigneth here.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>ISMENIA.</speaker>
                     <l>Hark, J hear ſomething, let us handſomly</l>
                     <l>Diſſemble now.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>PARTHENIA.</speaker>
                     <l>Oh how I feel my ſoul</l>
                     <l>Seiſed with love and fear!</l>
                  </sp>
               </div>
               <div type="scene">
                  <head>SCENA VI. CLIDAMANT, ISMENIA, PARTHENIA.</head>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>CLIDAMANT.</speaker>
                     <l>NO perſon follows me,</l>
                     <l>J am at liberty; jealous <hi>Melintus</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>Haunteth my ſteps no more.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>ISMENIA.</speaker>
                     <p>Madam, 'tis he.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <pb n="62" facs="tcp:170544:31"/>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>CLIDAMANT,</speaker>
                     <l>Well I'l go on to inſtruct me what <hi>Iſmenia</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>Hath to impart unto me in theſe Gardens;</l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Iſmenia!</hi>
                     </l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>ISMENIA.</speaker>
                     <p>
                        <hi>Clidamant.</hi>
                     </p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>CLIDAMANT.</speaker>
                     <p>Is it thee, <hi>Iſmenia?</hi>
                     </p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>ISMENIA.</speaker>
                     <p>Yes, I expect thee.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>CLIDAMANT.</speaker>
                     <l>Thou may'ſt have pretence</l>
                     <l>T'accuſe my tardy comming, but a jealous—</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>ISMENIA.</speaker>
                     <l>It is enough, thou art belov'd, aſſure thee;</l>
                     <l>Draw neer; but let us ſpeak ſoft, I'm afraid</l>
                     <l>We should be heard.—</l>
                     <stage>Put your ſelf in my place and take this opportunity. ſoftly.</stage>
                  </sp>
               </div>
               <div type="scene">
                  <head>SCENA VII. THIMANTES, CLIDAMANT, PARTHE<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>NIA, ISMENIA.</head>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>THIMANTES.</speaker>
                     <stage>
                        <hi>Speaking to</hi> Melintus <hi>behind the Stage.</hi>
                     </stage>
                     <l>I Am oblig'd to thee for this advertiſement;</l>
                     <l>If J find at the Eccho either of them,</l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Diana</hi> or <hi>Iſmenia,</hi> believe me,</l>
                     <l>I'l faithfully report it, to remove</l>
                     <l>Thy trouble, if J can: <hi>Iſmenia</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>Appoints me very often here to meet her,</l>
                     <l>Where, notwithſtanding her inconſtancy,</l>
                     <l>Her mouth in ſecret giveth me the hope</l>
                     <l>Of a moſt conſtant love, and for a pledge</l>
                     <pb n="63" facs="tcp:170544:31"/>
                     <l>Of her faith, never any but my ſelf</l>
                     <l>At thoſe hours entertains diſcourſe with her:</l>
                     <l>I'l to her now, and charge her with this crime</l>
                     <l>Of comming here without acquainting me.</l>
                     <l>I'l approach ſoftly without making noiſe</l>
                     <l>Leſt it might raiſe a ſcandal in the night;</l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Iſmenia,</hi>
                     </l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>CLIDAMANT.</speaker>
                     <stage>
                        <hi>quitting</hi> Parth.</stage>
                     <l>Some noiſe hath ſtruck mine car,</l>
                     <l>I'l return to you— <stage>Exit.</stage>
                     </l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>PARTHENIA.</speaker>
                     <l>O what feat is comparable</l>
                     <l>To mine! <hi>Iſmenia,</hi> come to me preſently.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>CLIDAMANT,</speaker>
                     <stage>
                        <hi>ſpeaking to</hi> Thimantes, <hi>whom he takes for</hi> Melintus.</stage>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Melintus,</hi> really I can no longer</l>
                     <l>Suffer your importunity? why should you</l>
                     <l>Imagine that J am the Author of</l>
                     <l>Your trouble? J ſpeak to no perſon here</l>
                     <l>But to the Shepheardeſs <hi>Iſmenia;</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>J tell thee once again, she ſent for me,</l>
                     <l>And J am certain that the note is written</l>
                     <l>And ſigned with her hand; 'tis true, this fair one</l>
                     <l>Sighs only for the love of me, her mouth</l>
                     <l>Hath told it me already, and I anſwer</l>
                     <l>Unto her fires with a mutual heat;</l>
                     <l>Aſſure your ſelf, and ſettle upon this</l>
                     <l>My faithfull proteſtation, that <hi>Diana</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>Ne'r made me ſigh.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>THIMANTES.</speaker>
                     <stage>ſoftly.</stage>
                     <p>O moſt perfidious!</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>CLIDAMANT.</speaker>
                     <l>See what an injury you do me now,</l>
                     <l>To ſatisfie you yet more fully hold,</l>
                     <pb n="64" facs="tcp:170544:32"/>
                     <l>There are the writing Tables, ſee her name.</l>
                     <l>Examin't well, and take repoſe at laſt</l>
                     <l>Without diſturbing mine. D'ye place your glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry</l>
                     <l>In perſecuting me?</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>THIMANTES.</speaker>
                     <stage>ſoftly.</stage>
                     <l>Shame of my love,</l>
                     <l>Depart my memory, J have wherewith</l>
                     <l>Both to reproach, and to convict thy falshood;</l>
                     <l>And when I've done it, treacherous ſpirit, I'l quit thee,</l>
                     <l>And then J shall be ſatisfied.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>CLIDAMANT.</speaker>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Melintus,</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>What is't thou murmur'ſt yet? J muſt break with thee,</l>
                     <l>If this ſtrange humour laſts, in acting thus,</l>
                     <l>You will loſe all your friends, your jealous head,</l>
                     <l>And ſtrange fantaſtick humours, but he's gone;</l>
                     <l>I will return unto the object which</l>
                     <l>Both charms and loves me.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>PARTHENIA, <hi>to</hi> ISMENIA.</speaker>
                     <l>There's our diſcourſe,</l>
                     <l>Make an end on't thy ſelf.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>CLIDAMANT.</speaker>
                     <l>I'm rid at laſt</l>
                     <l>Of my impertinent; jealous <hi>Melintus</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>Hath left me now.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>ISMENIA.</speaker>
                     <l>Adieu, let us retire.</l>
                     <l>I'm certainly inform'd that thy ambition</l>
                     <l>Aſpireth to <hi>Parthenia,</hi> in vain then</l>
                     <l>Thou holdeſt me diſcourſe.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>CLIDAMANT.</speaker>
                     <l>In two words J will tell thee, that J have</l>
                     <pb n="65" facs="tcp:170544:32"/>
                     <l>Too full a knowledge of the eminence</l>
                     <l>Of her condition, as to dare to lift</l>
                     <l>My hope ſo high: Oh if I durſt to love her;</l>
                     <l>But being leſs ambitious, J obey</l>
                     <l>My duty, and J better know my ſelf.</l>
                     <l>Adieu until to morrow.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>PARTHENIA, <hi>to</hi> ISMENIA.</speaker>
                     <l>Oh <hi>Iſmenia!</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>What content have J? and how skilfull art thou</l>
                     <l>In this affair of love? I do admire</l>
                     <l>Thy wit, and thy invention; the thing</l>
                     <l>Anſwered my wish.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>ISMENIA.</speaker>
                     <l>By this diſcourſe of his</l>
                     <l>You may perceive love under that reſpect,</l>
                     <l>Like fire under its ashes; 'tis not lately,</l>
                     <l>Your charms have taken him.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>PARTHENIA.</speaker>
                     <p>In the mean time—</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>ISMENIA.</speaker>
                     <l>In the mean time, live all fair wits, ſay J;</l>
                     <l>Without me, you had been reduc'd unto</l>
                     <l>A ſad condition, to die with grief,</l>
                     <l>And love, without expreſſing it.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>PARTHENIA.</speaker>
                     <l>'Tis late;</l>
                     <l>Come, in the abſence of the day let's prove,</l>
                     <l>If ſleep will follow on the ſteps of love.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <trailer>The end of the Third Act.</trailer>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div n="4" type="act">
               <pb n="66" facs="tcp:170544:33"/>
               <head>ACTUS IV.</head>
               <div type="scene">
                  <head>SCENA I. THIMANTES, ISMENIA.</head>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>THIMANTES.</speaker>
                     <l>HOw! in the night, perfidious, to exaſperate</l>
                     <l>My anger, dar'ſt thou to grant private meet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ings</l>
                     <l>To any but my ſelf? yea in the night</l>
                     <l>Without light and attendance in the Garden,</l>
                     <l>Thou entertain'dſt the Shepheard <hi>Clidamant.</hi>
                     </l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>ISMENIA.</speaker>
                     <l>How's this! <hi>Thimantes</hi> in a rage, O Gods!</l>
                     <l>Who would have thought it?</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>THIMANTES.</speaker>
                     <l>Wilt thou ſay that J</l>
                     <l>Complain now without reaſon, that J have</l>
                     <l>A crack'd brain, and bleer'd eyes? it is too long,</l>
                     <l>Inconſtant, to arreſt thy ſpirits, behold</l>
                     <l>This witneſs, it hath told me every thing;</l>
                     <l>Yet J should not believe that thou wert guilty,</l>
                     <l>If ſuch an evidence accus'd thee not,</l>
                     <l>But ſince J diſ-ingage my faith to thee,</l>
                     <l>This very inſtant, J reſtore thy papers</l>
                     <l>And will have nothing more to do with thee.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>ISMENIA.</speaker>
                     <l>Well, let it be ſo then, J doubt it not,</l>
                     <l>But J shall be provided in good time;</l>
                     <l>When one forſakes me, preſently another</l>
                     <l>Offers his ſervice, otherwiſe J should,</l>
                     <l>In this unlucky moment of thy change,</l>
                     <l>Be deſtitute of an officious Lover;</l>
                     <l>But thanks unto the Gods, more then one calls me</l>
                     <pb n="67" facs="tcp:170544:33"/>
                     <l>His Miſtreſs, and J shall have no leſs courtship</l>
                     <l>And preſs for thy departure, theſe notes here</l>
                     <l>Expreſs the names of thoſe that I've ſubjected,</l>
                     <l>I'l blot thee preſently out of my Table-book.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>THIMANTES.</speaker>
                     <p>Light Shepheardeſs!</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>ISMENIA.</speaker>
                     <l>For all this J am troubled</l>
                     <l>For thy diſquiet, without further jeſting,</l>
                     <l>Know that this trouble which poſſeſſeth thee</l>
                     <l>Proceeds but from a fiction, ſpeedily</l>
                     <l>I'l clear it to thee, only have but patience</l>
                     <l>To ſtay here till the Shepheard <hi>Clidamant</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>Arrives, before whom <hi>I</hi> have order to</l>
                     <l>Diſcover the deceit; and then <hi>I</hi> know</l>
                     <l>Thou wilt excuſe me for it.—<hi>here he comes.</hi>
                     </l>
                  </sp>
               </div>
               <div type="scene">
                  <head>SCENA II. CLIDAMANT, ISMENIA, THIMANTES.</head>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>CLIDAMANT.</speaker>
                     <l>HAve J not ſtaid too long? ſuſpect me not,</l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Thimantes,</hi> J was ſent for: well what is</l>
                     <l>Your pleaſure?</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>ISMENIA.</speaker>
                     <l>Thy misfortune is extream</l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Thimantes</hi> cannot ſuffer that another</l>
                     <l>Should love me, and one that accompt intends</l>
                     <l>To meaſure with thee ſword and arm to day.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>CLIDAMANT.</speaker>
                     <l>He is my friend, and therefore J am loath</l>
                     <l>To have a quarrel with him; to accord it,</l>
                     <l>Chuſe of us two him whom thou think'ſt moſt faithfull.</l>
                     <pb n="68" facs="tcp:170544:34"/>
                     <l>I am content to ſtand unto my fortune,</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>ISMENIA.</speaker>
                     <p>
                        <hi>Thimantes,</hi> what ſay you?</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>THIMANTES.</speaker>
                     <p>J agree to 't.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>ISMENIA, <hi>to</hi> CLIDAMANT.</speaker>
                     <l>Then thus; for him, J do confeſs I love him</l>
                     <l>A little, but for thee,—nothing at all.</l>
                     <l>My mouth interprets truely what my heart thinks</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>CLIDAMANT,</speaker>
                     <l>O the moſt fickle and moſt want on iſſue</l>
                     <l>Of the inconſtant ſex! thou lov'ſt a momen,</l>
                     <l>J love a moment alſo.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>ISMENIA.</speaker>
                     <l>Notwithſtanding</l>
                     <l>J have a ſecret to impart unto thee.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>CLIDAMANT.</speaker>
                     <l>A Secret in thy heart loſeth its name</l>
                     <l>In leſs time then a minute, without doubt:</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>ISMENIA.</speaker>
                     <l>Thou thought'ſt laſt night, that I diſcours'd with thee</l>
                     <l>At th' Eccho of the Garden?</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>CLIDAMANT.</speaker>
                     <p>Yes,</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>ISMENIA.</speaker>
                     <l>But what</l>
                     <l>If thou wert then deceiv'd, and that another</l>
                     <l>In my place counterfeited there my voice?</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>CLIDAMANT.</speaker>
                     <p>What haſt thou told me?</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>ISMENIA.</speaker>
                     <p>That which may be true.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <pb n="69" facs="tcp:170544:34"/>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>CLIDAMANT.</speaker>
                     <l>J cannot comprehend it, nor find thee;</l>
                     <l>Thou doſt do nothing but deceive at all times,</l>
                     <l>And in all places; thou canſt turn thy heart</l>
                     <l>And eyes into all ſences; how! another</l>
                     <l>Poſſeſs my place?</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>ISMENIA.</speaker>
                     <l>What if by this adviſe</l>
                     <l>J gained thee the heart of a fair Miſtreſs,</l>
                     <l>One that 's illuſtrious, and of noble blood,</l>
                     <l>And who after the Nymph hath the chief rank!</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>CLIDAMANT.</speaker>
                     <l>Well feign thy fill, thou may'ſt ſpeak what thou liſt;</l>
                     <l>I'm henceforth in no humour but to laugh.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>ISMENIA.</speaker>
                     <l>If by the greateſt oaths wherein my honour</l>
                     <l>Can be ingag'd, thou wilt believe the truth</l>
                     <l>Of what J told thee, that another perſon</l>
                     <l>Beſide my ſelf receiv'd thy vows laſt night</l>
                     <l>J hope thou wilt find out ſome fitter Epithies</l>
                     <l>Then falſe and wavering for me.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>CLIDAMANT.</speaker>
                     <l>After ſuch</l>
                     <l>An obligation, my charity</l>
                     <l>Would ſway me much.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>ISMENIA.</speaker>
                     <l>Then ſolemnly J ſwear,</l>
                     <l>It was <hi>Parthenia</hi> in my place, to whom</l>
                     <l>Thou didſt expreſs thy love; she borrowed</l>
                     <l>My name and shape, and thine eyes ſuffered</l>
                     <l>This ſweet impoſture.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>CLIDAMANT.</speaker>
                     <l>Still thou doſt abuſe me,</l>
                     <l>J knew thee by thy voice.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <pb n="70" facs="tcp:170544:35"/>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>ISMENIA.</speaker>
                     <l>When we ſpake loud,</l>
                     <l>'T was <hi>I</hi> that ſpake; then preſently <hi>Parthenia</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>Advancing in my place diſcovered ſoftly</l>
                     <l>Her ſoul and thought unto thee: after this,</l>
                     <l>Iudge, if <hi>I</hi> have deſerv'd from thee, or no.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>CLIDAMANT.</speaker>
                     <l>How! is it poſſible that she, to whoſe</l>
                     <l>High rank, <hi>I</hi> should not dare t' aſpire unto</l>
                     <l>So much as in a thought, that she to whom</l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>I</hi> durſt not ſpeak a word in way of plaint,</l>
                     <l>That she, to whom my high reſpect conceal'd</l>
                     <l>My amity, should yet feel pitty for me?</l>
                     <l>Alas! this cannot be, 'tis ſin to think it.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>ISMENIA.</speaker>
                     <l>Thou shalt ſee if <hi>I</hi> lie, and how sh' eſteems thee;</l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>I</hi> wait her here.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>CLIDAMANT.</speaker>
                     <l>Therein <hi>I</hi> should obtain</l>
                     <l>The hight of my ambition; for this favour,</l>
                     <l>Oh let me kiſs thy hands and die with plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure.</l>
                  </sp>
               </div>
               <div type="scene">
                  <head>SCENA III. PARTHENIA, ISMENIA, CLIDAMAN<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>TES, THIMANTES.</head>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>PARTHENIA.</speaker>
                     <l>WHat ſpectacle is this? I ſee <hi>Iſmenia</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>Sports with my fortune, if <hi>I</hi> trouble you,</l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>I</hi> will retire, continue that rare favour;</l>
                     <l>Who freely gives the hands, may give the heart.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <pb n="71" facs="tcp:170544:35"/>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>ISMENIA.</speaker>
                     <l>Ha! Madam, really you are a novice</l>
                     <l>In love; <hi>I</hi> gave him intimation of</l>
                     <l>The arri fice we us'd, and he at firſt</l>
                     <l>Received my diſcourſe with ſo much joy,</l>
                     <l>That he crav'd from me that civility.</l>
                     <l>Unto what jealous ſtrange ſuſpitions</l>
                     <l>Are you drawn by this object! he but aim'd</l>
                     <l>To kiſs my hand, and you are like to die for't?</l>
                     <l>Trouble you ſelf no more thus to no purpoſe.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>PARTHEIA.</speaker>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Iſmenia</hi> thou reſtor'ſt me life, and reſt,</l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>I</hi> love thee, <hi>Clidamant;</hi> this jealous fit,</l>
                     <l>Methinks, might well have ſpared me the shame</l>
                     <l>Of telling it.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>CLIDAMANT.</speaker>
                     <p>Fair Nymph, believe—</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>PARTHENIA.</speaker>
                     <l>But let us</l>
                     <l>Enter into this Wood.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>CLIDAMANT.</speaker>
                     <l>
                        <hi>I</hi> wish the Eccho,</l>
                     <l>Sometimes a friend to Lovers, would redouble</l>
                     <l>My voice in ſaying to you that J love,</l>
                     <l>And make you to repeat my words, J love.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>PARTHENIA.</speaker>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Iſmenia,</hi> be a faithful witneſs of</l>
                     <l>Our chaſt amours, and come along with us</l>
                     <l>To hear what we diſcourſe, <hi>Thimantes</hi> be</l>
                     <l>Diſcreet and ſecret.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>THIMANTES.</speaker>
                     <l>Madam, I'm all ſilence.</l>
                     <l>See, what a ſtrange unneceſſary evil</l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Is</hi> that a jealous perſon doth ſuſtain;</l>
                     <l>Foolish <hi>Melintus</hi> how thou art deceiv'd</l>
                     <pb n="72" facs="tcp:170544:36"/>
                     <l>In thinking that <hi>Diana</hi> is the object</l>
                     <l>Gf <hi>Clidamant</hi>'s affection—here she comes</l>
                     <l>Diſcourſing with her brother, J will leave them.</l>
                  </sp>
               </div>
               <div type="scene">
                  <head>SCENA IV. DIANA, THERSANDER.</head>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>DIANA.</speaker>
                     <l>LEt us conſider what we are to do,</l>
                     <l>She loves thee infinitely, and J have</l>
                     <l>Command from her to ſpeak to thee again,</l>
                     <l>In her behalf.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>THERSANDER.</speaker>
                     <p>Adviſe me what to do.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>DIANA.</speaker>
                     <l>Since the Nymph loves thee with ſuch paſſion,</l>
                     <l>As I perceive she doth, 'tis ft thou flatter</l>
                     <l>Her grief a little, otherwiſe I fear</l>
                     <l>That I shall loſe thee after having found thee.</l>
                     <l>What miſchief can she not do, when provoked?</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>THERSANDER.</speaker>
                     <p>Since there needs but to feign all will ſucceed.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>DIANA.</speaker>
                     <l>In the mean time, <hi>Iſmenia</hi> will be carefull</l>
                     <l>To inquire for us, when the Merchant-ship</l>
                     <l>That's bound for <hi>Sevill</hi> will be fully ready</l>
                     <l>To ſet ſail from the harbour; we shall hire him</l>
                     <l>To land us where we will; till when, our care</l>
                     <l>Muſt be not to offend the Nymph, for fear</l>
                     <l>She ruine us; she'l preſently be here.</l>
                     <l>She's come already; act the Lover well,</l>
                     <l>Diſſemble handſomly, therein conſiſts</l>
                     <l>All that we can expect.</l>
                  </sp>
               </div>
               <div type="scene">
                  <pb n="73" facs="tcp:170544:36"/>
                  <head>SCENA V. MELISSA, DIANA, THERSANDER.</head>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>MELISSA.</speaker>
                     <l>A Word, <hi>Diana.</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>Haſt thou remov'd that fatal obſtacle,</l>
                     <l>Which came to intetrupt the pleaſant courſe</l>
                     <l>Of my affections? haſt thou ſetled</l>
                     <l>My lifes content, and razed <hi>Celia</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>Out of thy Brothers ſpirit?</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>DIANA.</speaker>
                     <l>His heart follows</l>
                     <l>Where my voice and his glory calleth him,</l>
                     <l>And cheerfully yieldeth obedience</l>
                     <l>To ſuch ſweet Laws.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>MELISSA.</speaker>
                     <l>Bleſſed Interpreter</l>
                     <l>Of a moſt ardent love! haſt thou adviſ'd him</l>
                     <l>To keep it ſecret?</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>DIANA.</speaker>
                     <l>Only that point, Madam,</l>
                     <l>J have forgotten, but J will redeem it;</l>
                     <l>And tell him on't before you; if you pleaſe</l>
                     <l>That I go for him.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>MELISSA.</speaker>
                     <l>Go, and bring him hither.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>DIANA.</speaker>
                     <stage>ſoftly.</stage>
                     <l>Feign handſomely unto her</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>THERSANDER.</speaker>
                     <stage>
                        <hi>ſoftly to</hi> Diana.</stage>
                     <l>Fear it not.</l>
                     <l>I'l ſpeak before her but of you, and to you,</l>
                     <l>And yet not make her jealous.</l>
                     <pb n="74" facs="tcp:170544:37"/>
                     <stage>
                        <hi>Then he ſaith to</hi> Meliſſa, <hi>by whoſe ſide is</hi> Diana, <hi>whom he looks upon.</hi>
                     </stage>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>THERSANDER.</speaker>
                     <stage>aloud.</stage>
                     <l>Could you doubt</l>
                     <l>My heart should be ſo ſtupid, and inſenſible</l>
                     <l>Of my felicity how happy is</l>
                     <l>My fortune, and how gentle was the ſtorm</l>
                     <l>That gave me this bleſs'd port, whereof great Kings</l>
                     <l>Are jealous? What proud Conqueror would not</l>
                     <l>Submit and lay his arms down with himſelf</l>
                     <l>At the fair feet of ſuch a charming object?</l>
                     <l>A rude obdurate rock, would be conſum'd,</l>
                     <l>The coldeſt Marble would be kindled by it:</l>
                     <l>Yes, Madam, a fair eye but openeth</l>
                     <l>Its lid here, &amp; 'tis day; the nights black shadows</l>
                     <l>Fly only from the Sun of thoſe bright eyes,</l>
                     <l>Her fires too at the ſight of them grow pale.</l>
                     <l>I muſt confeſs then, Madam, that J love them,</l>
                     <l>And that J live more in this beauteous object</l>
                     <l>Then in my ſelf: my ſpirit is charmed with</l>
                     <l>A happineſs unparallell'd, when J</l>
                     <l>Think that J love them, and am lov'd again.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>MELISSA.</speaker>
                     <p>Come, thou but feigneſt love? do not abuſe me.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>THERSANDER.</speaker>
                     <l>O Gods! what do you ſay? Madam, J love</l>
                     <l>Or rather J adore.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>MELISSA.</speaker>
                     <l>How haſt thou then</l>
                     <l>Diſpos'd of <hi>Celia</hi> that reign'd o'r thy heart?</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>THERSANDER.</speaker>
                     <l>That affair's ordered well, I've put her intereſts</l>
                     <l>Into my Siſters hands; sh' 'ath promis'd me</l>
                     <pb n="75" facs="tcp:170544:37"/>
                     <l>To make all fair of that ſide, and will anſwer</l>
                     <l>To me for her.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>MELISSA.</speaker>
                     <l>Haſt thou not boaſted to me</l>
                     <l>That her eyes were the object of thy love?</l>
                     <l>That for thy ſake she cherished the light</l>
                     <l>Of the alternate day, and that they would</l>
                     <l>Cover themſelves with an eternal night,</l>
                     <l>If thou shouldſt ceaſe to live or to be faithfull:</l>
                     <l>Think well of thy part what th'aſt promiſed;</l>
                     <l>Be firm, be conſtant, fail not in that point,</l>
                     <l>Conſider not at all this ſupream greatneſs;</l>
                     <l>Stick to thine object, love it for it ſelf,</l>
                     <l>And have no intereſt for thy ambition,</l>
                     <l>Flatter thee with the honour to poſſeſs her,</l>
                     <l>Look only if she loves thee, not if she</l>
                     <l>Enricheth thee; the beauty whom thou ſerv'ſt,</l>
                     <l>Should be thy crown, all greatneſs whatſoever</l>
                     <l>Should be eſteem'd in thy accompt beneath it.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>THERSANDER.</speaker>
                     <l>Ne'r doubt it, Madam, J shall have thoſe thoughts;</l>
                     <l>Greatneſs shall never blind me ſo far forth</l>
                     <l>As to oblige me to forget my love;</l>
                     <l>Which alwaies shall pure as the day ſtar burn</l>
                     <l>Baſe intereſt shall never ſully me.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>DIANA.</speaker>
                     <p>I'l tell my Brother now, what I forgate</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>
                        <hi>To</hi> THERSANDER.</speaker>
                     <l>If thou know'ſt well to love, know thou as wel</l>
                     <l>To hold thy peace, love like the other Gods,</l>
                     <l>Is not without his ſecrets, he is ſerv'd</l>
                     <l>Sometimes by hearts that can't expreſs them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves:</l>
                     <l>Take heed how thou provoke his jealous power,</l>
                     <pb n="76" facs="tcp:170544:38"/>
                     <l>Adore his Altars, but adore in ſilence;</l>
                     <l>For ſilence is a part of his Religion;</l>
                     <l>And oftentimes this fierce God is offended</l>
                     <l>At his own name; if any thing hereof</l>
                     <l>Should be known in the Iſle, thou art undone:</l>
                     <l>Love, without ſpeaking of it, that's the law,</l>
                     <l>Which is impoſed on thee; she for her part</l>
                     <l>Will love thee likewiſe, uſe the ſecret well,</l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Meliſſa</hi> otherwiſe would die with grief;</l>
                     <l>J know th' exceſs of love wherewith thy ſoul</l>
                     <l>Is filled; but for thy own intereſt,</l>
                     <l>Put a ſeal on thy mouth.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>MELISSA.</speaker>
                     <l>Yes, have a care</l>
                     <l>That none ſuſpect our love, I'l take my time</l>
                     <l>To publish it, in the mean time I'l ſtudy</l>
                     <l>Thy ſetrlement and they repoſe which makes</l>
                     <l>That of my life; this free confeſſion now,</l>
                     <l>Would call up envy from her Cell, and make</l>
                     <l>Our greateſt <hi>Hero</hi>'s, to diſpute with thee</l>
                     <l>What J have promis'd thee, thine enemies.</l>
                     <l>Judge then how precious thy obedience is;</l>
                     <l>Since all thy good and happineſs depends</l>
                     <l>Upon thy ſilence.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>THERSANDER.</speaker>
                     <l>Sure, J should be ſtrucken</l>
                     <l>With a ſtrange blindneſs, if J obſerv'd not</l>
                     <l>This your command; J will obey ſo well,</l>
                     <l>That, Madam, even you your ſelf shal doubt</l>
                     <l>Whether J love, or whether you J love.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>MELISSA.</speaker>
                     <l>In the mean time thy ſiſter shall aſſiſt me,</l>
                     <l>And have the ordering of our Amours;</l>
                     <l>Believe what she shall ſay, ſince I will make her</l>
                     <l>My only boſom friend, unto whoſe truſt,</l>
                     <pb n="77" facs="tcp:170544:38"/>
                     <l>J will commit the ſecrets of my heart.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>THERSANDER.</speaker>
                     <l>J will make uſe of her in the ſame manner.</l>
                     <stage>
                        <hi>Enter</hi> Melintus, <hi>he ſpeaks to</hi> Meliſſa</stage>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>MELINTUS.</speaker>
                     <l>Madam, a Jeweller, that uſeth ſtill.</l>
                     <l>To come unto the Games, deſires acceſſe</l>
                     <l>Unto your preſence.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>MELISSA.</speaker>
                     <l>Cauſe him to come in:</l>
                     <l>This <hi>Sevil</hi> Merchant cometh every year</l>
                     <l>To ſell and traffick in the Iſland with us.</l>
                  </sp>
               </div>
               <div type="scene">
                  <head>SCENA VI. MELISSA, MERCATOR, THERSANDER, DIANA, MELINTUS.</head>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>MELISSA.</speaker>
                     <p>SHall you remain ſometime yet on our shore?</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>MERCATOR.</speaker>
                     <l>I ſtay but for your Paſsport to depart.</l>
                     <l>Every year, Madam, by your Highneſs bounty</l>
                     <l>My traſſick thrives ſo well, that whatſoever</l>
                     <l>Commodities I bring unto you Iſle,</l>
                     <l>J carry nothing back, you empty ſtill</l>
                     <l>My casket: now I'l shew you, if you pleaſe,</l>
                     <l>ſuch rarities, as can be had no where</l>
                     <l>But in my hands.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>MELISSA.</speaker>
                     <p>Let's ſee them.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>MERCATOR.</speaker>
                     <l>Here's a Diamond</l>
                     <l>Darts flame of all ſides.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <pb n="78" facs="tcp:170544:39"/>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>MELISSA.</speaker>
                     <l>'Tis a ſparkling ſtone</l>
                     <l>I like his luſtre.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>MERCATOR.</speaker>
                     <p>Will you have it, Madam?</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>MELISSA.</speaker>
                     <l>I'l tell you preſently, shew all at once,</l>
                     <l>Then I shall ſoon chuſe: let me ſee that Coral.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>MERCATOR.</speaker>
                     <l>The piece is very fair; till now your Iſle</l>
                     <l>Hath never ſeen the like.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>MELISSA.</speaker>
                     <p>And what's that other?</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>MERCATOR.</speaker>
                     <l>A piece of Amber-greece; Madam, 'tis rare</l>
                     <l>And of great price; I have paſs'd divers Seas</l>
                     <l>To purchaſe it; alone 'tis worth as much</l>
                     <l>As all my casket.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>DIANA.</speaker>
                     <l>For my part, J cannot</l>
                     <l>See any thing that's new here.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>MERCATOR.</speaker>
                     <l>Shepheardeſs,</l>
                     <l>This rope of Pearl is very rich and new,</l>
                     <l>'T would make you look more fair, more gay, more ſparkling.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>MELISSA.</speaker>
                     <l>Without thoſe Ornaments of Art, she is</l>
                     <l>Charming enough, she needs no ſtrange additi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons.</l>
                     <l>She maketh all our Shepheards die for love:</l>
                     <l>But for all this, though you are fair without them</l>
                     <l>I will beſtow them on you, if you like them.</l>
                     <l>What ſaies <hi>Diana.</hi>
                     </l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>DIANA.</speaker>
                     <p>Madam, your great bounties—</p>
                  </sp>
                  <pb n="79" facs="tcp:170544:39"/>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>MELISSA.</speaker>
                     <p>Lay them aſide.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>MERCATOR.</speaker>
                     <l>But, Madam, look upon</l>
                     <l>This Maſter-piece of Art, it is the Portrait</l>
                     <l>In little of the King of <hi>Andalouſia.</hi>
                     </l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>MELISSA.</speaker>
                     <l>He's one of the beſt made that I have ſeen.</l>
                     <l>And who is this?</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>MERCATOR.</speaker>
                     <l>It is his favourite</l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Nearchus</hi> ſometime Prince of <hi>Pichery,</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>Who by a beauty fatal through her charms,</l>
                     <l>Gave up his arms, and life unto his Rival,</l>
                     <l>A gallant Gentleman, his name <hi>Cleagenor,</hi>
                     </l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>THERSANDER,</speaker>
                     <stage>the firſt line ſoftly.</stage>
                     <l>May I believe! good Gods! how he obſerves me?</l>
                     <l>But are you certain of <hi>Nearchus</hi> death?</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>MERCATOR.</speaker>
                     <l>He return'd ſorely wounded from the fight,</l>
                     <l>And died four daies after, as all know.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>MELISSA.</speaker>
                     <p>His valour ſeems yet painted in his face.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>MERCATOR.</speaker>
                     <l>But he that conquer'd him had more by much.</l>
                     <l>Behold his Portrait.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>THERSANDER.</speaker>
                     <stage>ſoftly</stage>
                     <p>Oh! what sheweth he?</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>MELISSA.</speaker>
                     <p>Is this that valiiant <hi>Cleagenor?</hi>
                     </p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>MERCATOR.</speaker>
                     <p>Yes, 'tis his picture.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>THERSANDER.</speaker>
                     <stage>ſoftly,</stage>
                     <p>O unlucky accident!</p>
                  </sp>
                  <pb n="80" facs="tcp:170544:40"/>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>MERCATOR.</speaker>
                     <l>Of all thoſe that J had, this only 's left me:</l>
                     <l>Th' offended King commanded me to carry them</l>
                     <l>Unto all places where J went, and traffick'd,</l>
                     <l>That ſo he might be known, and then arreſted;</l>
                     <l>For after this great Combat, to ſecure</l>
                     <l>His head from purſuit, he took flight immedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ately.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>MELISSA.</speaker>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Therſander,</hi> in my judgement, nothing can</l>
                     <l>Better reſemble you, J think your ſiſter</l>
                     <l>Will ſay as much.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>THERSANDER.</speaker>
                     <l>Madam, we ſee that Nature</l>
                     <l>Sports ſometimes in her works, and makes ſome feitures</l>
                     <l>In faces to reſemble ſomewhat neerly.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>MELISSA.</speaker>
                     <p>This Merchant,, I believe, 's of my opinion.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>MERCATOR.</speaker>
                     <p>Madam, without doubt, 'tis <hi>Cleagenor,</hi>
                     </p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>THERSANDER.</speaker>
                     <l>The thing is little certain on the faith</l>
                     <l>And bare ground of a Portrait.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>MERCATOR.</speaker>
                     <l>Sir, you are</l>
                     <l>The very ſame, I am confirmed now</l>
                     <l>In my firſt thoughts, all that which hitherto</l>
                     <l>Hindered me to judge ſo, was the name of</l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Therſander,</hi> and the habit of a Shepheard.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>THERSANDER.</speaker>
                     <p>Who! J, <hi>Cleagenor?</hi>
                     </p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>MERCATOR.</speaker>
                     <l>Yes, Sir, J ſaw you</l>
                     <l>The laſt yeer in the fortunate Iſlands, and</l>
                     <l>Not above four moneths ſince in <hi>Portugal;</hi>
                     </l>
                     <pb n="81" facs="tcp:170544:40"/>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Sevll</hi>'s your native Country; ſince you meet here</l>
                     <l>Your ſafety, to what purpoſe should you cover</l>
                     <l>Thoſe things with ſilence?</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>MELISSA.</speaker>
                     <l>Sure, you need not blush,</l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Therſander,</hi> at this fair acknowledgement.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>THERSANDER.</speaker>
                     <l>I confeſs, Madam, that J blush a little,</l>
                     <l>Not that mine arm hath not done all that which</l>
                     <l>It ought to do in the death of my Rival,</l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Nearchus</hi> was too rash, and inſolent;</l>
                     <l>From the fair and unſpotted object which</l>
                     <l>Made my moſt chaſt deſires, he in his thoughts</l>
                     <l>Formed the object of his filthy pleaſures;</l>
                     <l>But he hath paid for't, and his death is juſt</l>
                     <l>Only the thing that troubles and afflicts me,</l>
                     <l>And for which I am ſorry at my heart,</l>
                     <l>Is that J told you nothing of my ſecret.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>MELISSA.</speaker>
                     <l>J gueſs the cauſe of it, and know your thought.</l>
                     <l>And what fear troubled it, and that you choſe</l>
                     <l>Another name only to free you from</l>
                     <l>The penalty o'th' Law; but fear not any thing;</l>
                     <l>I'l oppoſe power to power for your defence;</l>
                     <l>Your intereſts are mine, J'l make your peace;</l>
                     <l>The King of <hi>Andalouſia</hi> shall be weary</l>
                     <l>Of perſecuting you; if he perſift</l>
                     <l>To trouble your repoſe, J'l invade his:</l>
                     <l>If he refuſe to grant what we demand,</l>
                     <l>From our requeſt we will proceed to arms.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>THERSANDER.</speaker>
                     <l>What obligation have you upon me</l>
                     <l>For all your goodneſs?</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>MELISSA.</speaker>
                     <l>But let's make an end</l>
                     <pb n="82" facs="tcp:170544:41"/>
                     <l>Of ſeeing all the rarities.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>MERCATOR.</speaker>
                     <l>Behold</l>
                     <l>With admiration, Madam, this rare piece,</l>
                     <l>It is <hi>Diana</hi>'s Picture.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>MELISSA.</speaker>
                     <p>How <hi>Dianaes?</hi>
                     </p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>DIANA.</speaker>
                     <stage>ſoftly.</stage>
                     <p>O ſad misfotrune!</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>MERCATOK.</speaker>
                     <l>It is the Divinity,</l>
                     <l>Whoſe Temple's here, the Goddeſs of this place.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>DIANA.</speaker>
                     <stage>ſoftly</stage>
                     <p>I ceaſe to tremble, all is well again.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>MELISSA.</speaker>
                     <p>What Portrait's this?</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>MERCATOR.</speaker>
                     <l>It is a Beauties, Madam,</l>
                     <l>Whoſe heavenly graces made two deſperate Lo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vers,</l>
                     <l>That ſight for her, arm for the field, and fight;</l>
                     <l>It is that fair ones whom I told you of</l>
                     <l>For Whom <hi>Cleagenor</hi> and <hi>Nearchus</hi> burn'd,</l>
                     <l>And who purſued hotly by two Rivals,</l>
                     <l>Coft the one flight, and life unto the other.</l>
                     <l>After <hi>Nearchus</hi> death, I bought his Portraits:</l>
                     <l>This that he had without doubt's to the life.</l>
                     <l>But who can better then <hi>Cleagenor</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>Inſtruct you in this point?</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>MELISSA, <hi>to</hi> THERSANDER.</speaker>
                     <p>D' ye know this piece?</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>THERSANDER.</speaker>
                     <p>I know not what to ſay on't.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>MELISSA.</speaker>
                     <l>I obſerve</l>
                     <l>Much of thy ſiſters air in't.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <pb n="83" facs="tcp:170544:41"/>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>DIANA.</speaker>
                     <l>O ye Gods!</l>
                     <l>Turn aſide this misfortune.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>MELISSA.</speaker>
                     <l>Really</l>
                     <l>The glaſs, <hi>Diana,</hi> which receives thy image,</l>
                     <l>Repreſents leſs thy shape and countenance;</l>
                     <l>And any other but the Painter would</l>
                     <l>Believe indeed that the finish'd this Portrait</l>
                     <l>Upon thy preſence.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>MERCATOR</speaker>
                     <l>There's no doubt of it.</l>
                     <l>One may admire in this adventure how</l>
                     <l>Art imitateth nature: it is she</l>
                     <l>For whom <hi>Nearchus</hi> ſigh'd.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>THERSANDER.</speaker>
                     <stage>ſoftly.</stage>
                     <l>O Gods! where are we?</l>
                     <l>Our fortunes now are deſperate.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>DIANA.</speaker>
                     <p>Know'ſt thou me?</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>MERCATOR.</speaker>
                     <l>I am of the ſame Town, and therefore know you;</l>
                     <l>Your mother is <hi>Melora,</hi> and she dwells</l>
                     <l>At <hi>Sevil;</hi> I shal make her a glad woman</l>
                     <l>At my return, to tell her that her <hi>Celia</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>Lives yet, and is in health here in this Iſland.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>MELISSA.</speaker>
                     <p>How! <hi>Celia?</hi>
                     </p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>MERCATOR.</speaker>
                     <p>Yes, Madam, that is her name,</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>DIANA.</speaker>
                     <l>What could of errour blindeth thy ſoul thus?</l>
                     <l>That <hi>Celia</hi> whom thou mean'ſt, and doſt diſcourſe of,</l>
                     <l>Died before <hi>Nearchus.</hi>
                     </l>
                  </sp>
                  <pb n="84" facs="tcp:170544:42"/>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>MERCATORS.</speaker>
                     <l>It was believ'd ſo</l>
                     <l>At firſt; but ſince, all <hi>Sevil</hi> knows the contrary,</l>
                     <l>And that falſe death is now no more a myſtery</l>
                     <l>Unto me; J know where the mourning went,</l>
                     <l>And how a Coffin only was interr'd</l>
                     <l>Inſtead of you, that this apparent ſign</l>
                     <l>Of your death only could ſecure you from</l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Nearchus</hi> ill deſigns; I know beſides</l>
                     <l>That you betook your ſelf unto the Sea,</l>
                     <l>Where you ſight not, but for <hi>Cleagenor;</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>The Sea prov'd falſe to you, and to your mother,</l>
                     <l>And ſeparated you one from another</l>
                     <l>By the aſſiſtance of a hideous ſtorm:</l>
                     <l>She having ſav'd her ſelf upon a plank</l>
                     <l>Sought you from one end of the World to th'o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther;</l>
                     <l>But hearing no news of you, she believ'd</l>
                     <l>At her return to <hi>Sevil</hi> that the Sea</l>
                     <l>Had ſwallowed you, and death had made her ſearch</l>
                     <l>Unprofitable.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>DIANA.</speaker>
                     <l>Thou knoweſt ſecrets which</l>
                     <l>To me are Riddles.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>MERCATOR.</speaker>
                     <l>Wherefore should you, Lady,</l>
                     <l>Diſſemble thus your knowledge of a thing</l>
                     <l>Which is no more conceal'd; one of your people</l>
                     <l>A complice of the Plot, divulg'd it lately;</l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Melora</hi> too ſince her return reveal'd</l>
                     <l>The whole Impoſture, all impediment</l>
                     <l>Being remov'd after <hi>Nearchus</hi> death:</l>
                     <l>This that I know, I underſtood from her.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>THERSANDER.</speaker>
                     <p>All this thou ſaieſt, is ſtrange news unto us.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <pb n="85" facs="tcp:170544:42"/>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>MERCATOR.</speaker>
                     <l>You have the art, I ſee, well to diſſemble;</l>
                     <l>But by your favour might it not be you</l>
                     <l>That did imploy a friend unto me lately</l>
                     <l>To pray me to receive into my bark</l>
                     <l>Two Shepheards, natives of the Town of <hi>Sevil?</hi>
                     </l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>THERSANDER.</speaker>
                     <l>Madam, this Merchant doth compoſe Romants.</l>
                     <l>And tells you all theſe ſtrange adventures only,</l>
                     <l>To shew his wit, and faculty that way.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>MELISSA.</speaker>
                     <l>Yet his diſcourſe in not without ſome ground,</l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>I</hi> find good reaſon ſo to judge of it;</l>
                     <l>If I remember well, you willingly</l>
                     <l>Did put the intereſt of <hi>Celia</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>Into your ſiſters hands, she promiſed</l>
                     <l>To make all fair of that ſide, and to anſwer</l>
                     <l>To you for her: Merchant, another time</l>
                     <l>See us again. How both of you abuſe me</l>
                     <l>With an Impoſture form'd under falſe name's</l>
                     <l>To carry on your love in a diſguiſe!</l>
                     <l>What in my Palace, in my Court, my preſence,</l>
                     <l>Sport with my perſon thus in a contempt!</l>
                     <l>Inſolent wretches, you shall feel what force</l>
                     <l>My anger hath when thus provok'd, I'l make you—</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>THERSANDER.</speaker>
                     <p>Oh, Madam!</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>MELISSA.</speaker>
                     <l>Go, Impoſtor, thou shalt anſwer</l>
                     <l>For all the troubles of my heart; none ever</l>
                     <l>Affro ntd me yet without punishment:</l>
                     <l>I'l ſacrifice you both to my diſgrace,</l>
                     <l>In ſuch a manner, that ye shal repent</l>
                     <l>Eternally that e'r ye made me blush:</l>
                     <l>Depart my ſight.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <pb n="86" facs="tcp:170544:43"/>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>THERSANDER.</speaker>
                     <p>O what misfortune's this!</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>MELISSA, <hi>to</hi> MELINTUS.</speaker>
                     <l>See that you ſeparate them one from another</l>
                     <l>In ſeveral apartment, that they may</l>
                     <l>Hold no diſcourſe together. O miſfortune</l>
                     <l>Not to be parallell'd! What shall I do?</l>
                     <l>Of whom should I take counſel in this caſe?</l>
                     <l>Shall I hear yet my love that murmureth?</l>
                     <l>Ought I to ſuffer, or repel the injury?</l>
                     <l>It is reſolv'd in my offended heart</l>
                     <l>That thoſe black Paſſions shal ſucceed my love,</l>
                     <l>By which the ſoul when in diſorder, breaks</l>
                     <l>The chain wherewith she's ti'd, break forth my fury,</l>
                     <l>And ruine theſe ingratefull they shal know</l>
                     <l>My power, as they have ſeen my goodneſs to the:</l>
                     <l>They shall not mock at my ſimplicity,</l>
                     <l>Nor reproach me for my credulity:</l>
                     <l>How! treacherous <hi>Therſander;</hi> oh! that name</l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Therſander</hi> combats yet within my heart,</l>
                     <l>In its defence, my ſpirits at this name</l>
                     <l>Are wavering, and my anger's weak, my hate</l>
                     <l>Is in ſuſpenſe; I am not pleas'd with that</l>
                     <l>Which I demand; I fear what J would moſt.</l>
                     <l>Ha traitor, muſt J to torment my ſelf</l>
                     <l>Suſpend my judgement upon thy deſtruction?</l>
                     <l>Muſt J diſpute the caſe within myſelf</l>
                     <l>As doubtfull to determine, no paſs ſentence</l>
                     <l>Againſt him for this barbarous affront:</l>
                     <l>Arm my deſpair, and inſpire thou my rage:</l>
                     <l>And let me ſee how faithfully my Art</l>
                     <l>Will ſerve my vengeance in the punishment</l>
                     <l>Of theſe ingratefull Lovers, I intend not</l>
                     <l>To give a ſudden death to either of them,</l>
                     <pb n="87" facs="tcp:170544:43"/>
                     <l>But they shall ſuffer that which shall be worſe:</l>
                     <l>By the effect, and ſtrange force of my charms,</l>
                     <l>They shall have, without dying, every day</l>
                     <l>A thouſand deaths; I will continually</l>
                     <l>By turns afflict the ſad eyes of the Lover,</l>
                     <l>And of his Miſtreſs: both of them shal ſee,</l>
                     <l>That they may ſuffer equally, each other</l>
                     <l>To die and to revive, this punishment</l>
                     <l>Is ſtrange and cruell; but 'tis that I uſe</l>
                     <l>In my revenges; come, why loiter we</l>
                     <l>In our deſign? my heart like flint shall be</l>
                     <l>Inſenſible of their calamity.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <trailer>The end of the Fourth Act.</trailer>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div n="5" type="act">
               <pb n="88" facs="tcp:170544:44"/>
               <head>ACTUS V.</head>
               <div type="scene">
                  <head>SCENA I. CLIDAMANT, PARTHENIA.</head>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>CLIDAMANT.</speaker>
                     <l>MIne eyes and ears ne'r ſaw, nor heard the like</l>
                     <l>The miſerable cryes of thoſe poor Lovers</l>
                     <l>Fill all theſe places with aſtonishment.</l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Therſander</hi> and <hi>Diana</hi> are ſo chang'd,</l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>I</hi> could ſcarce know them, as I now came from them:</l>
                     <l>Pale death by turns skipping from face to face,</l>
                     <l>Can't make them yet to dye unto their love:</l>
                     <l>But, Madam, is it true what's publish'd here</l>
                     <l>Among the people, that thoſe ſtrange inchant<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments</l>
                     <l>Come from <hi>Meliſſa?</hi>
                     </l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>PARTHENIA.</speaker>
                     <l>Yes, they are the works</l>
                     <l>Of her Art, without doubt, she could do more yet</l>
                     <l>Nothing's too hard for her, the deſtiny</l>
                     <l>Of mortals ſeems to be held in her hands,</l>
                     <l>And as she pleaſeth, she diſpoſeth it.</l>
                     <l>What can she not do, when she is in choler?</l>
                     <l>The miſerable <hi>Thirſis</hi> feels th'effect,</l>
                     <l>And rigour of her power by ſad experience.</l>
                     <l>Hath not ſame yet inform'd you with his ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferings?</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>CLIDAMANT.</speaker>
                     <p>Yes, Madam, J have heard them fully ſpoken.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>PARTHENIA.</speaker>
                     <l>You know then that he lov'd <hi>Roſelia,</hi>
                     </l>
                     <pb n="89" facs="tcp:170544:44"/>
                     <l>And ſo deceiv'd the expectation,</l>
                     <l>And deſire of the Nymph who hitherto</l>
                     <l>Deſign'd him for my husband, and knows not</l>
                     <l>That <hi>I</hi> have love for you; to her commands</l>
                     <l>This Shepheard was Rebellious: what did she?</l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Roſelia</hi> was fair, she became ſick;</l>
                     <l>She wept, she pined, she complain'd; the brightnes</l>
                     <l>Of her fair eyes, extinguish'd in a moment:</l>
                     <l>The whiteneſs of her Lillies as ſoon faded;</l>
                     <l>And of ſo many beauties there remain'd</l>
                     <l>Only the place, where ſometime their ſeat was,</l>
                     <l>Her Lover that perceiv'd her taken from him,</l>
                     <l>Seeks her in every place, but cannot find her:</l>
                     <l>That was a Maſter-piece of her Apprentiship;</l>
                     <l>But this without doubt is another work</l>
                     <l>Of higer knowledge; if in her reſentment</l>
                     <l>But for my intereſt she made poor <hi>Thirſis</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>A miſerable Lover, judge how far</l>
                     <l>She may be carried, mov'd at her offence,</l>
                     <l>In her revenge for her own intereſt.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>CLIDAMANT.</speaker>
                     <l>If the Nymph knew the love <hi>I</hi> have for you,</l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>I</hi> could expect no other uſage from her;</l>
                     <l>She would without doubt cauſe me to be carried</l>
                     <l>unto ſome fearfull Iſland where <hi>I</hi> should</l>
                     <l>Be rendered miſerable all my days:</l>
                     <l>But let her art do what it can againſt me</l>
                     <l>Imployed by her hate, it shall work nothing</l>
                     <l>Upon my faith, to do it prejudice:</l>
                     <l>Oh! could <hi>I</hi> flatter me with the ſame hope,</l>
                     <l>That you would have like conſtancy for me!</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>PARTHENIA.</speaker>
                     <l>You need not doubt of it, <hi>I</hi>'m wholly yours,</l>
                     <l>My love is ſtrong, and little fears her anger;</l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>I</hi>'l keep it ſtill ſincere and firm unto you:</l>
                     <pb n="104" facs="tcp:170544:45"/>
                     <l>And you shall find me conſtant unto death:</l>
                     <l>Should she deſtroy me with her power, &amp; kil me</l>
                     <l>I'le rather dye my ſelf, then my affection.</l>
                     <l>My life can't pay the debt J owe unto you.</l>
                  </sp>
               </div>
               <div type="scene">
                  <head>SCENA II. ISMENIA, THIMANTES, PARTHENIA, CLIDAMANT.</head>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>ISNENIA.</speaker>
                     <l>WHat ſtrange news do we hear? is it true, Madam,</l>
                     <l>That by th'effects of fortune and inchantment,</l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Theſander</hi> and <hi>Diana</hi> dye by turns,</l>
                     <l>And live again to wail their miſeries?</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>PARTHENIA.</speaker>
                     <p>
                        <hi>Iſmenia,</hi> tis too true, they are inchanted.</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>THIMANTES.</speaker>
                     <l>If <hi>I</hi> durſt ſpeak my thoughts, &amp; what I've heard,</l>
                     <l>They impute this injuftice to the Nymph.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>PARTHENIA.</speaker>
                     <l>It is not to be doubted but she is</l>
                     <l>The Author of it, and this cruel punishment</l>
                     <l>Denoteth that she ſtudies high revenge,</l>
                     <l>When she's offended.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>CLIDAMANT.</speaker>
                     <l>Whatſo'er her power be</l>
                     <l>Which cauſeth fear, let us go preſently</l>
                     <l>With our complaint unto her: in my judgement,</l>
                     <l>This is no way to make her ſelf obey'd:</l>
                     <l>Fear is the parent not of love, but hate.</l>
                     <l>And that ſame fatal art which her revenge</l>
                     <pb n="97" facs="tcp:170544:45"/>
                     <l>Calls to her aid, eſtablisheth her crime,</l>
                     <l>And not her power. But here J ſee she comes.</l>
                  </sp>
               </div>
               <div type="scene">
                  <head>SCENA III. MELISSA, MELINTUS, CLIDAMAT, PAR<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>THENIA, THIMANTES, ISMENIA.</head>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>MELISSA <hi>to</hi> MELINTUS.</speaker>
                     <p>WHat doth this ſtroak ſurprize thee?</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>MELINTUS.</speaker>
                     <l>Truly, Madam,</l>
                     <l>Their punishment's too great, and all the Jſfland</l>
                     <l>Murmureth at it.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>MELISSA.</speaker>
                     <l>Shepheards, what ſay you?</l>
                     <l>Can J revenge me of an injury?</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>CLIDAMANT.</speaker>
                     <l>Ye, Madam, and th'eſtate wherin y'ave put them</l>
                     <l>Hath made all thoſe their friends that envi'd them.</l>
                     <l>Hear our petitions for them, and be pleas'd</l>
                     <l>To do them juſtice: what have they committed</l>
                     <l>Worthy of ſuch a punishment? for having</l>
                     <l>Hid their love from you, lived in your Court</l>
                     <l>Under the name of brother, and of ſiſter,</l>
                     <l>Deceiv'd the hope and envy of their Rivals,</l>
                     <l>Conſerv'd their honour, and, perhaps, their life,</l>
                     <l>
                        <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>s this ſo great a crime, as should be punish'd</l>
                     <l>By charmes which have no end? muſt they be made</l>
                     <l>To dye, and to revive continually</l>
                     <l>By turns, and by a ſtrange unworthy fate</l>
                     <pb n="62" facs="tcp:170544:46"/>
                     <l>The living be inforc'd ſucceſsively</l>
                     <l>Still to lament the dead? their pittious cryes,</l>
                     <l>And hideous clamours give both ſouls &amp; mouths</l>
                     <l>Unto thoſe rocks to join in plaints with me:</l>
                     <l>The whole Iſle's moved with them, and diſturb'd</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>PARTHENIA.</speaker>
                     <l>Madam, I join in this petition,</l>
                     <l>Vouchſafe to hear me: O forbear to dart</l>
                     <l>Thunder and wrath upon this happy place,</l>
                     <l>Where the Gods liberally pour upon mortals</l>
                     <l>So many and ſo great felicities:</l>
                     <l>Begin not to diſturb the ſweet repoſe</l>
                     <l>Of an abode that's favoured by Heaven,</l>
                     <l>To pleaſe thoſe Shepheards, whoſe devotions</l>
                     <l>May fix upon ſome other Sanctuary</l>
                     <l>More ſafe, and other Soveraigns more ſweet.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>THIMANTES.</speaker>
                     <l>Yes, Madam, ſtop the mouth of this ſad murmur,</l>
                     <l>Let it be ſmother'd, this inchantment hath</l>
                     <l>Continued too long, break, break the charm,</l>
                     <l>And pacifie our ſpirits immediately,</l>
                     <l>Which are aſtonished at this proceeding.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>ISMENIA.</speaker>
                     <l>If in the freedom which J uſe too frequently,</l>
                     <l>My mouth might date to ſpeak, and not di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pleaſe you,</l>
                     <l>I should then tell you that this rigid courſe</l>
                     <l>You take, would leave you here ner Shephear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deſſes</l>
                     <l>Nor Shepheards; they would ſeek this place no more</l>
                     <l>For their retrait and ſanctuary, but shun it</l>
                     <l>Like a deſtroying rock; and this fair Iland</l>
                     <l>The glory of the world, would be a wilderneſs:</l>
                     <l>To enjoy ſubjects, rule your paſsions better,</l>
                     <l>
                        <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                           <desc>••</desc>
                        </gap>d be more ſoveraign over your ſelf.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <pb n="63" facs="tcp:170544:46"/>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>MELISSA.</speaker>
                     <l>Shepheards, and Shepheardeſſes, your diſcourſes</l>
                     <l>Aſtonish and ſurprize me, know, my Art,</l>
                     <l>Is a ſufficient warrant for my actions;</l>
                     <l>J could do greater yet, and ſtranger too:</l>
                     <l>Though this which you have ſeen ſeemeth unjuſt</l>
                     <l>Unto you, have you any right, or priviledge</l>
                     <l>To complain to me, and to murmur thus?</l>
                     <l>Much leſs to reprehend, and cenſure me?</l>
                     <l>How! should the bold Shepheard <hi>Therſander</hi> dare</l>
                     <l>To injure me, and to deride my power?</l>
                     <l>Should he preſume to lay aſide his duty</l>
                     <l>And reſpect for me, and I wink at it,</l>
                     <l>That ſo can punish ſuch an inſolence?</l>
                     <l>Preſume it not, the blood of <hi>Zoroaſtres</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>Is not yet born under ſo ill a ſtar,</l>
                     <l>J know its influence better, and can uſe it</l>
                     <l>To the deſtruction of thoſe that wrong me:</l>
                     <l>Yes, Shepheards, <hi>I</hi> am skilful in the qualities</l>
                     <l>Of herbs and roots, and as <hi>I</hi> have occaſion</l>
                     <l>J chuſe them, ſome for poyſon, ſome for medi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cine:</l>
                     <l>When <hi>I</hi> wil, I preſcribed ſome to confound</l>
                     <l>The memorie, and to diſtract the ſpirit;</l>
                     <l>But thoſe obnoxious weeds I never uſe</l>
                     <l>But for their punishment that do offend me;</l>
                     <l>Have I not reaſon to maintain my rank</l>
                     <l>In dignity and honour? thoſe that dare</l>
                     <l>To brave me, without doubt, hazard themſelves:</l>
                     <l>My ſcepter's guarded with enwreathed ſerpents,</l>
                     <l>Whoſe fearful aſpects bid all keep aloof,</l>
                     <l>And threaten death to thoſe that dare to touch it:</l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Thirſis</hi> hath felt their ſtings: what reaſon had he</l>
                     <l>To be an enemy to his ovvn fortune</l>
                     <l>And intereſt, in foolishly refuſing</l>
                     <l>The honour of the name to be my Nephevv:</l>
                     <pb n="103" facs="tcp:170544:47"/>
                     <l>I will advance him, and expect that he</l>
                     <l>Shall yet accept this honourable title</l>
                     <l>Of Husband to my Neece; <hi>Parthenia,</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>Your colour changes, but in vain you hide</l>
                     <l>Your thoughts from me, I can diſcover them,</l>
                     <l>I know that you love <hi>Clidamant,</hi> and more</l>
                     <l>What you deſign, and what you do diſcourſe;</l>
                     <l>But underſtand both one and t'other of you,</l>
                     <l>That I muſt be obey'd in what I will;</l>
                     <l>My power can force it; take heed ye provoke not</l>
                     <l>My anger; if J may not be belov'd,</l>
                     <l>J will be fear'd.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>PARTHENIA.</speaker>
                     <p>Madam—</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>MELISSA.</speaker>
                     <l>It is enough,</l>
                     <l>You know my prohibition.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>CLIDAMANT,</speaker>
                     <l>
                        <hi>I</hi> hope</l>
                     <l>To bend her, but at preſent let's ſay nothing.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>THIMANTES.</speaker>
                     <l>We all know your high rank and quality</l>
                     <l>With reverence and reſpect, ſo in that notion</l>
                     <l>We imploy but our prayers to perſwade you;</l>
                     <l>They are our onely arms, be touched with them,</l>
                     <l>And diſsipate theſe charms: <hi>Therſander,</hi> now</l>
                     <l>Begins t'awake out of his fatal fit;</l>
                     <l>You'l hear his plaints and clamours preſently,</l>
                     <l>His cryes and his deſpair for his dear Miſtreſs</l>
                     <l>This is the hour, wherein he is tormented:</l>
                     <l>This object without doubt before your eyes</l>
                     <l>Will raiſe up pitty, Madam, in your heart:</l>
                     <l>His ſighs will quench your anger, and prevail</l>
                     <l>Much more then we; ſee he begins to move:</l>
                     <l>Madam, you will be touch'd, to hear him ſpeak.</l>
                  </sp>
               </div>
               <div type="scene">
                  <pb n="102" facs="tcp:170544:47"/>
                  <head>SCENA IV. THERSANDER, DIANA, MELISSA, ISME<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>NIA, PARTHENIA, CLIDAMANT, THIMANTES.</head>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>THERSANDER <hi>by</hi> DIANAS <hi>body.</hi>
                     </speaker>
                     <l>O Lamentable object! why mine eyes</l>
                     <l>Were ye not cover'd with eternal darkneſs,</l>
                     <l>That J might not have ſeen this fatal ſpectacle?</l>
                     <l>Oh! what cauſe have I to complain of fortune,</l>
                     <l>That my ſleep is not the laſt ſleep of death?</l>
                     <l>In the night of the Grave <hi>I</hi> should take reſt,</l>
                     <l>And not be ty'd to die thus all my life,</l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>I</hi> should be there but duſt, and this ſad ſight</l>
                     <l>Should not have martyred my heart and eyes.</l>
                     <l>Yes, my dear Miſtreſs, ſometime my delight,</l>
                     <l>Thy ſight is now my greateſt punishment,</l>
                     <l>And in this ſad eſtate wherein I ſee thee,</l>
                     <l>Thou which wert once my joy, art now my grief;</l>
                     <l>Thy body's but a trunk that gives me horror,</l>
                     <l>Thy head all over's ſmoaking with thy blood,</l>
                     <l>The graces lodge no more there, I ſee death</l>
                     <l>In every place, where I ſaw love before:</l>
                     <l>How! doſt thou live no more then have I loſt thee</l>
                     <l>As ſoon as found thee hopes born and deſtroy'd</l>
                     <l>With an immortal love, fantoſine of fortune</l>
                     <l>Which laſts good but a day, wealth too ſoon loſt,</l>
                     <l>Brightneſs too ſoon put out, exceſſive joy,</l>
                     <l>To which ſo many plaints ſo ſoon ſucceed,</l>
                     <l>Why in that ſplendor where with all you ſlatter'd,</l>
                     <l>My name, did you promice ſo much unto me,</l>
                     <l>And give ſo little. Fair eyes, ſometimes conque<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rous,</l>
                     <l>Whose lightsafe shut up in eternal night</l>
                     <pb n="96" facs="tcp:170544:48"/>
                     <l>In ſpight of all my prayers, call me not</l>
                     <l>From death unto the light; is't poſsible</l>
                     <l>That <hi>I</hi> can ſee here what <hi>Diana</hi> ſees not</l>
                     <l>No, no, <hi>I</hi> live no more ſince she is dead;</l>
                     <l>Yet my heart moves; but this laſt ſtrugling is</l>
                     <l>But a ſmall ſpark that's left behind, and shines</l>
                     <l>A little after death; 'tis but a vapour,</l>
                     <l>An exaltation, a wind, a ſmoak,</l>
                     <l>Laſt dying and laſt kindled; <hi>I</hi> am coming</l>
                     <l>To join with thee, object of my deſire,</l>
                     <l>To give thee ſoul for ſoul, and ſigh for ſigh;</l>
                     <l>Death is my aid, my hope is but in her;</l>
                     <l>I will expreſs that I am faithful to thee</l>
                     <l>In that, not able to ſurvive thy fate,</l>
                     <l>I put my ſelf into the arms of death.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>CLIDAMANT.</speaker>
                     <l>Madam, you ſee how great his torment is,</l>
                     <l>And whereunto your hatred hath reduc'd him;</l>
                     <l>You ſee beſides how far without proportion</l>
                     <l>Of the crime to the punishment, the power</l>
                     <l>Of your inchantment goes; theſe woods weep at it;</l>
                     <l>And theſe rocks which before heard no com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plaints,</l>
                     <l>Are pierc'd now with his cryes, and become ſoft,</l>
                     <l>And ſenſible, the Eccho likewiſe mourns,</l>
                     <l>And should you onely, Madam, be without</l>
                     <l>Compaſsion for him.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>MELISSA.</speaker>
                     <l>Yes, without compaſsion;</l>
                     <l>Since he took pleaſure alwaies to diſpleaſe me,</l>
                     <l>I'le pleaſe my ſelf by a moſt juſt return</l>
                     <l>Jn my revenge, and never ceaſe t'afflict him:</l>
                     <l>No, think not that J will incline to pitty.</l>
                     <l>I'm too much injur'd to be pacifi'd</l>
                     <l>His ſorrow makes my joy, and I am glad</l>
                     <l>To ſee that by this famous punishment</l>
                     <pb n="97" facs="tcp:170544:48"/>
                     <l>
                        <hi>I</hi> shall eſtablish my authority.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>THIMANTES.</speaker>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Diana</hi>'s turn is now; ſee he revives</l>
                     <l>To weep her lover, and immediately</l>
                     <l>To follow him by the force of your Art:</l>
                     <l>Sad ſpectacle? hearken unto her grief,</l>
                     <l>And ope your eyes, and heart to her complaints,</l>
                  </sp>
                  <stage>Diana <hi>upon</hi> Therſanders <hi>body.</hi>
                  </stage>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>DIANA.</speaker>
                     <l>What, my dear Lover, art thou then but duſt!</l>
                     <l>Alas! thy mouth wants ſpeech, and thine eyes light.</l>
                     <l>But inſpight of the plot which makes me ſigh,</l>
                     <l>I have the happineſs yet to lament thee:</l>
                     <l>Flow, flow, my tears, and pour upon this object</l>
                     <l>Torrents of flame, not water, there is nothing</l>
                     <l>So cold in the dark boſom of the Grave,</l>
                     <l>Which the fire of theſe Rivers cannot warm:</l>
                     <l>Yes, by my tears at laſt, my cryes, my plaints,</l>
                     <l>Dear ashes, I will kindle you again,</l>
                     <l>Though cold now and extinguish'd like the Phenix</l>
                     <l>I'le raiſe you up again by force of ſights,</l>
                     <l>Which you shall Eccho to me.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>THIMANTES.</speaker>
                     <l>Madam can you</l>
                     <l>Behold this ſight, and not be moved at it!</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>DIANA.</speaker>
                     <l>Love, canſt thou not anſwer to my deſires!</l>
                     <l>Thou art a miracle thy ſelf, and therefore,</l>
                     <l>Methinks, should'ſt do one: art thou in the world</l>
                     <pb n="98" facs="tcp:170544:49"/>
                     <l>No more a ſource of life? oh canſt thou not</l>
                     <l>Reſtore my lover to me, from whoſe armes</l>
                     <l>They 'ave ravish'd him; which of the Gods can call him</l>
                     <l>Back from the gates of death, if thou canſt not?</l>
                     <l>My dear <hi>Cleagenor,</hi> J pray thee, anſwer me</l>
                     <l>By theſe my tender ſighs, by <hi>Celia's</hi> name;</l>
                     <l>How's this! I can pronounce thy name, and mine</l>
                     <l>And yet, O Gods! thou anſwereſt me nothing;</l>
                     <l>I ſee, alas! thy mouth and eyes ſtill shut:</l>
                     <l>He's dead, and theſe names cannot touch him now.</l>
                     <l>Love, ſince thou haſt no power to ſuccour me</l>
                     <l>In that point as to make him live, at leaſt</l>
                     <l>Make me to dye: <hi>I</hi> come, my faithful lover,</l>
                     <l>It is impoſsible I should ſurvive thee;</l>
                     <l>I feel that my deſpair t'enjoy thee here</l>
                     <l>Gives me to death; my heart hath loſt the ſpirits</l>
                     <l>Which made it move, J ſcarce can utter more:</l>
                     <l>Happy thy <hi>Celia,</hi> if her death could give</l>
                     <l>Thee life again, if thy ſleep might have end</l>
                     <l>By mine, and if I could with all my blood</l>
                     <l>Redeem thine; J have done, any love is coming</l>
                     <l>To meet thy flame, and <hi>I</hi> espire upon thee</l>
                     <l>The reſt of my ſad ſoul.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>CLIDAMANT.</speaker>
                     <l>What! is your heart</l>
                     <l>Not touch'd yet with this object? are you ſtill</l>
                     <l>Jnſenſible of ſo much grief as she</l>
                     <l>Suffers by your means? oh! let pitty yet</l>
                     <l>Diſarm your anger, the Inchanted Lovers</l>
                     <pb n="99" facs="tcp:170544:49"/>
                     <l>Have ſuffered enough Nymph, break the charm.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>MELISSA.</speaker>
                     <l>Yes, I am touch'd at laſt, J muſt confeſs,</l>
                     <l>And really am ſorry for the evil</l>
                     <l>Which they have drawn through their temerity</l>
                     <l>Upon themſelves; but though their grief appea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeth</l>
                     <l>My anger now, the charm which I have made</l>
                     <l>J can't undo; to tell you truly, Shepheards,</l>
                     <l>Jt is ſo ſtrong that onely a Divinity</l>
                     <l>Can break the chance on't; tis decree'd by fate</l>
                     <l>That it shall laſt yet longer, and J cannot</l>
                     <l>Prevent it, though it be my proper work.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>THIMANTES.</speaker>
                     <l>How! cannot you prevent it? heavenly Gods,</l>
                     <l>What ſaying's this? no, no, you have not left</l>
                     <l>Your anger, but retain it ſtill; and willing</l>
                     <l>To punish them, and to revenge your wrong,</l>
                     <l>Will make of them a laſting ſpectacle</l>
                     <l>Unto the eyes of all; and to excuſe</l>
                     <l>Your ſelf the better of this cruelty,</l>
                     <l>Would put it off to ſome Divinity;</l>
                     <l>But the Gods by our prayers and tears appeas'd,</l>
                     <l>Jnſpight of your attempts, wil ſtop your charms:</l>
                     <l>Yes, Madam, the great Gods condemn your plots,</l>
                     <l>They are the Soveraigns, and abſolute Maſters</l>
                     <l>Of deſtiny, we hope all things from them,</l>
                     <l>And that they'l ſuffer crime no longer here</l>
                     <l>To raign and tyranize. Thou Goddeſs, which</l>
                     <l>Art in this place ador'd which holdeſt fate,</l>
                     <l>And fortune in thy hands, which hateſt crime,</l>
                     <l>and whoſe cares keep the Shepheards that ſerve thee</l>
                     <pb n="100" facs="tcp:170544:50"/>
                     <l>In this delightful Iſland, look upon</l>
                     <l>The ſad eſtate whereto love hat reduc'd</l>
                     <l>Two miſerable Lovers, whom the Nymph</l>
                     <l>Purſues with horrid cruelty to death</l>
                     <l>By fatal charmes, deſtroy the power of them,</l>
                     <l>And render to this government again</l>
                     <l>The liberty to lover, and to declare it.</l>
                     <stage>Thunder and lightning.</stage>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>PARTHENIA.</speaker>
                     <l>Ha! what a ſudden flash of lightning's this,</l>
                     <l>That ſtrikes mine eyes, and what a clap of thun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der</l>
                     <l>Shakes all this place?</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>ISMENIA.</speaker>
                     <l>With what a thick black cloud</l>
                     <l>The Skie is cover'd?</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>MELISSA.</speaker>
                     <l>
                        <hi>I</hi> believe Heaven trembles,</l>
                     <l>And its Arch openeth; behold the Goddeſs</l>
                     <l>Deſcends, and maketh ſign, as if she'd ſpeak:</l>
                     <l>We muſt give audience.</l>
                  </sp>
               </div>
               <div type="scene">
                  <pb n="101" facs="tcp:170544:50"/>
                  <head>SCENA Ultima. <hi>The Goddeſſe</hi> DIANA.</head>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>DIANA.</speaker>
                     <l>YOur prayers are heard, let nothing trouble you,</l>
                     <l>Fair <hi>Celia</hi> and her Lover both shal live</l>
                     <l>And love for ever, their afflictions</l>
                     <l>Are ended, and I have diſſolv'd the charm,</l>
                     <l>No accident shall henceforth trouble them.</l>
                     <l>They ſtir'd up pity in you, now they may</l>
                     <l>Make you to envy them; ſearch all Records,</l>
                     <l>You'l find no ſubject equal to their love.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>THERSANDER, <hi>to</hi> DIANA.</speaker>
                     <p>By what inchantment is thy life reſtord?</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>DIANA, <hi>to</hi> THERSANDER.</speaker>
                     <l>By what inchantment do'ft thou live again?</l>
                     <stage>The Goddeſſe continues.</stage>
                     <l>I'l recompenſe their inexemplar vertues,</l>
                     <l>And pay the price of their affection;</l>
                     <l>To conſummate their happy Nuptials,</l>
                     <l>I'l ope my Temple, and aſſure you all</l>
                     <l>Of my protection. 'Tis my pleaſure alſo</l>
                     <l>That the love of the Shepheard <hi>Clidamant</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>Be at the ſame time crown'd with <hi>Hymen</hi>'s ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nours,</l>
                     <l>And that he end his daies with ſweet <hi>Parthenia,</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>That henceforth he command in the Iſle with her;</l>
                     <l>My juſtice hath made choice of them to reign.</l>
                     <pb n="102" facs="tcp:170544:51"/>
                     <l>The Nymph I do degrade, she is too criminal,</l>
                     <l>And diſpenſe you of your obedience to her;</l>
                     <l>I'l make the power of her Art unuſefull;</l>
                     <l>And free this Iſland from all future fear,</l>
                     <l>And danger; but to ſave her from the Thunder</l>
                     <l>Of the offended Gods, I will recive her</l>
                     <l>Into my Temple, which shall be her Sanctuary.</l>
                     <l>Her Sex hath long enough ruled the Province,</l>
                     <l>I'l change the order of its Government,</l>
                     <l>And henceforth it shall be under the power,</l>
                     <l>And wiſe adminiſtration of a Prince,</l>
                     <l>Which shall be of the blood of <hi>Clidamant</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>From father unto ſon.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <stage>Meliſſa <hi>ſeeing the Goddeſs to aſcend.</hi>
                  </stage>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>MELISSA.</speaker>
                     <l>I confeſſe Goddeſſe,</l>
                     <l>You do me juſtice in approving crime</l>
                     <l>One makes himſelf a complice: without you,</l>
                     <l>The Gods, high Soveraigns, Maſters, and diſpo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſers</l>
                     <l>Of deſtiny, would, ſure, have punish'd me</l>
                     <l>With death; I go into your temple now</l>
                     <l>To imploy other charms, to wash away</l>
                     <l>My criminal defilements with my tears</l>
                     <l>To pray unto the immortal powers, whilſt J</l>
                     <l>Have breath, and ſo diſarm them at your Altars:</l>
                     <l>But to the end her law may be fullfill'd</l>
                     <l>In every point, <hi>Cleagener,</hi> fail not</l>
                     <l>To love your <hi>Celia.</hi>
                     </l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>THERSANDER.</speaker>
                     <l>O how redevable</l>
                     <l>Am I to your rare goodneſs?</l>
                  </sp>
                  <pb n="103" facs="tcp:170544:51"/>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>MELISSA.</speaker>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Clidamant,</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>Enjoy what you deſerve, accept <hi>Parthenia,</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>With her, the crown, and ſucceed happily</l>
                     <l>The rank which I freely reſign unto you.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>CLIDAMANT.</speaker>
                     <l>You command ſtill, and keep your Soveraign rank,</l>
                     <l>When the raign is conferr'd upon your blood;</l>
                     <l>And by all my reſpects, I shall expreſs</l>
                     <l>That 'tis but in your name that I'l be Maſter.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>PARTHENIA.</speaker>
                     <l>Though Heavens kind hand chuſeth a husband for me,</l>
                     <l>Since you allow him, I'l hold him of you,</l>
                     <l>And will poſſeſs no honour here, nor power,</l>
                     <l>But to expreſs the more my ſervice to you,</l>
                     <l>And my acknowledgements.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>THIMANTES.</speaker>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Iſmenia,</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>Muſt we not couple too?</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>ISMENIA.</speaker>
                     <l>Yes, if the Goddeſs</l>
                     <l>Had ſaid it; we'l defer our marriage,</l>
                     <l>Till she deſcends again.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>CLIDAMANT.</speaker>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Iſmenia,</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>I command in this place now, and J will it.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>ISMENIA.</speaker>
                     <l>Since you will have it, I accept his vows</l>
                     <l>Offaithfull ſervice. If <hi>Melintus</hi> too</l>
                     <l>Hath shaken of his jealouſie, J muſt</l>
                     <l>Be reconcil'd with him.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <pb n="104" facs="tcp:170544:52"/>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>MELINTUS.</speaker>
                     <l>Well, J agree to 't.</l>
                     <l>Let us remain friends.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>CLIDAMANT.</speaker>
                     <l>Heaven hath promis'd us.</l>
                     <l>That we shall all be happy, let us go</l>
                     <l>Forthwith unto the Temple to conclude</l>
                     <l>This triple marriage, and henceforth we shall</l>
                     <l>Honour this day as a great Feſtival.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
               </div>
            </div>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
