<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>The sisters, a comedie, as it was acted at the private house in Black Fryers written by James Shirley. Never printed before.</title>
            <author>Shirley, James, 1596-1666.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1652</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 135 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 38 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2012-10">2012-10 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A93178</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing S3485</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R230287</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99895970</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99895970</idno>
            <idno type="VID">153591</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A93178)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 153591)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 2371:14)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>The sisters, a comedie, as it was acted at the private house in Black Fryers written by James Shirley. Never printed before.</title>
                  <author>Shirley, James, 1596-1666.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[8], 58, [2] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>printed for Humphrey Robinson at the Three Pigeons, and Humphrey Moseley at the Prince's Armes in St. Paul's Church-yard,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1652.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in the Folger Shakespeare Library, Washington, D.C..</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2011-06</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-07</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-11</date>
            <label>Ali Jakobson</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-11</date>
            <label>Ali Jakobson</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-05</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:153591:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:153591:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:153591:2" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:153591:2"/>
            <p>THE SISTERS, A COMEDIE, AS It was acted at the private Houſe IN <hi>BLACK FRYERS,</hi>
            </p>
            <p>WRITTEN By JAMES SHIRLEY.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Never Printed before.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON,</hi> Printed for <hi>Humphrey Robinſon</hi> at the Three Pigeons, and <hi>Humphrey Moſeley</hi> at the Prince's Arms in St. <hi>Paul's</hi> Church-yard. 1652.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="dedication">
            <pb facs="tcp:153591:3"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:153591:3"/>
            <head>To the moſt worthily Honoured <hi>William Paulet</hi> Eſquire.</head>
            <opener>
               <salute>SIR,</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>COmpoſitions of this nature, have here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tofore been graced by the acceptance, and protection of the greateſt Nobility (I may ſay Princes) but in this age, when the Scene of Drammatick Poetry is changed into a wilderneſs, it is hard to find a pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tron to a legitimate muſe. Many that were wont to encourage Poems, are faln beneath the proverbiall want of the compoſers, and by their ruins are only at leaſure to take meaſure with their eye, of what they have been. Some extinguiſhed with their fortune, have this happineſs, to be out of capacity of further ſhipwrack, while their ſad remaynes peep out of the ſea, and may ſerve naked marks, and caution to other Navigators, Malignant ſtars the while! In this unequall condition of the time, give me leave to congratulate my own felicity, that hath di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rected this Comedy unto you, who wear your no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bleneſs with more ſecurity, than titles, and a name that continues bright and impaſsible among the conſtellations in our Sphear of <hi>Engliſh</hi> honour. I <gap reason="missing" extent="1 page">
                  <desc>〈1 page missing〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb facs="tcp:153591:4"/>dare not detain you, Sir, with too long a Preface; if you pleaſe to entertain theſe Papers, as the modeſt tender of my ſervice, I ſhall receive it as a moſt kind influence upon me; and you will engage to all your commands, the humble heart of</p>
            <closer>
               <salute>Sir,</salute>
               <signed>Your faithfull Honourer, <hi>JA. SHIRLEY.</hi>
               </signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="prologue">
            <pb facs="tcp:153591:4"/>
            <head>Prologue at the Black-Fryers.</head>
            <lg>
               <l>DOes this look like a Term? I cannot tell,</l>
               <l>Our Poet thinks the whole Town is not well,</l>
               <l>Has took ſome Phyſick lately, and for fear</l>
               <l>Of catching cold dares not ſalute this Ayr.</l>
               <l>But ther's another reaſon, I hear ſay</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>London</hi> is gone to <hi>York,</hi> 'tis a great way;</l>
               <l>Pox o'the Proverb, and of him ſay I,</l>
               <l>That look'd ore <hi>Lincoln,</hi> cauſe that <hi>was,</hi> muſt we</l>
               <l>Be now tranſlated North? I could rail to</l>
               <l>On Gammar <hi>Shiptons</hi> Ghoſt, but 't wo' not doe,</l>
               <l>The Town will ſtill be <hi>flecking,</hi> and a Play</l>
               <l>Though ne'r ſo new, will ſtarve the ſecond day:</l>
               <l>Upon theſe very hard conditions,</l>
               <l>Our Poet will not purchaſe many Towns;</l>
               <l>And if you leave us too, we cannot thrive,</l>
               <l>I'l promiſe neither Play nor Poet live</l>
               <l>Till ye come back, think what you do, you ſee</l>
               <l>What audience we have, what Company</l>
               <l>"<hi>To</hi> Shakeſpear <hi>comes, whoſe mirth did once beguile</hi>
               </l>
               <l>"<hi>Dull hours, and buskind, made even ſorrow ſmile,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>"<hi>So lovely were the wounds, that men would ſay</hi>
               </l>
               <l>"<hi>They could endure the bleeding a whole day:</hi>
               </l>
               <l>He has but few friends lately, think o'that,</l>
               <l>Hee'l come no more, and others have his fate.</l>
               <l>"Fletcher <hi>the Muſes darling, and choice love</hi>
               </l>
               <l>"<hi>Of</hi> Phoebus, <hi>the delight of every Grove;</hi>
               </l>
               <l>"<hi>Vpon whoſe head the Laurel grew, whoſe wit</hi>
               </l>
               <l>"<hi>Was the Times wonder, and example yet,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>'Tis within memory, Trees did not throng,</l>
               <l>As once the Story ſaid to <hi>Orpheus</hi> ſong.</l>
               <l>"Johnſon, <hi>t' whoſe name, wiſe Art did bow, and Wit</hi>
               </l>
               <l>"<hi>Is only juſtified by honouring it:</hi>
               </l>
               <pb facs="tcp:153591:5"/>
               <l>"<hi>To hear whoſe touch, how would the learned Quire</hi>
               </l>
               <l>"<hi>With ſilence ſtoop? and when he took his Lyre,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>"Apollo <hi>dropt his Lute, aſham'd to ſee</hi>
               </l>
               <l>"<hi>A Rival to the God of Harmonie.</hi>
               </l>
               <l>You do forſake <hi>him</hi> too, we muſt deplore</l>
               <l>This fate, fot we do know it by our <hi>door.</hi>
               </l>
               <l>How muſt this Author fear then, with his guilt</l>
               <l>Of weakneſs to thrive here, where late was ſpilt</l>
               <l>The <hi>Muſes</hi> own blood, if being but a few,</l>
               <l>You not conſpire, and meet more frequent too?</l>
               <l>There are not now <hi>nine Muſes,</hi> and you may</l>
               <l>Be kind to ours, if not, he bad me ſay,</l>
               <l>Though while you careleſs kill the reſt, and laugh,</l>
               <l>Yet he may live to write your <hi>Epitaph.</hi>
               </l>
            </lg>
            <pb facs="tcp:153591:5"/>
         </div>
         <div type="dramatis_personae">
            <pb facs="tcp:153591:6"/>
            <head>Perſons.</head>
            <list>
               <item>FArneſe, <hi>Prince of Parma.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Contarini, <hi>a Noble man.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Antonio, <hi>Uncle to the Siſters.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Frapolo, <hi>the chief Bandit.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Longino <hi>Bandits.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Strozzo <hi>Bandits.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Rangino <hi>Bandits.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Pachequo <hi>Bandits.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Lucio, Paulina's <hi>Steward.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Giovanni <hi>Servants to</hi> Paulina.</item>
               <item>Stephanio <hi>Servants to</hi> Paulina.</item>
               <item>Fabio.</item>
               <item>Piperollo, <hi>Sonne to</hi> Fabio.</item>
               <item>Countrymen.</item>
               <item>Citizens.</item>
               <item>Petitioners.</item>
               <item>A Scholar.</item>
               <item>Pulcheria <hi>diſguiſed, and under the name of</hi> vergerid</item>
               <item>Paulina <hi>Siſters.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Angellina <hi>Siſters.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Morulla, <hi>Wife to</hi> Fabio.</item>
               <item>Gentlewomen.</item>
            </list>
            <p>
               <hi>Scene Parma.</hi>
            </p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="play">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:153591:6"/>
            <head>THE SISTERS.</head>
            <div n="1" type="act">
               <head>ACT I.</head>
               <stage>Enter Frapolo, Longino, Pacheco, Rangone, Strozzo, and other Banditi.</stage>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Lon.</speaker>
                  <l>
                     <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg> Like not this laſt Proclamation.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Ra.</speaker>
                  <l>Nor I.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>St.</speaker>
                  <l>It ſtartled me to read it.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Fr.</speaker>
                  <l>Did you read? tis a fault <hi>Strozzo</hi> a fault</l>
                  <l>I'l have no theef hereafter learn to read;</l>
                  <l>Threaten us with long winded Proclamations?</l>
                  <l>We are ſafe within our Woods, and Territories,</l>
                  <l>And are above his Edicts; Have not wee</l>
                  <l>A Common-wealth among our ſelves, ye <hi>Tripolites?</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>A Common-wealth? a Kingdom; and I am</l>
                  <l>The Prince of <hi>Qui-Vala's,</hi> your Sovereign theef,</l>
                  <l>And you are all my Subjects.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Lo.</speaker>
                  <l>We are—</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Fr.</speaker>
                  <l>And is there one ſo baſe to change Complexion,</l>
                  <l>Becauſe we are proſcrib'd? I'l be no Prince.</l>
                  <l>I have a grudging on me to be honeſt,</l>
                  <l>And leave you to the fear of hemp, and hunger;</l>
                  <l>Have I by ſtratagems ſo oft preſerv'd you,</l>
                  <l>When you were howling out your lives, and lead</l>
                  <l>A way in Dog-couples by ruſty Officers?</l>
                  <l>And are you ſtruck dead with a Paper pellet?</l>
                  <l>Your bloud turn'd Whay, becauſe there is reward</l>
                  <l>Promis'd to bring our heads in? I renounce you—</l>
                  <l>Land Rats—</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <pb n="2" facs="tcp:153591:7"/>
                  <speaker>Pa.</speaker>
                  <l>Moſt excellent <hi>Frapolo,</hi> they recant;</l>
                  <l>A little humane frailty may be pardon'd.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Fr.</speaker>
                  <l>Shall theeves, whoſe predeceſſors have been Kings,</l>
                  <l>And conquer'd worlds, be factious, and ſchiſmaticall?</l>
                  <l>I ſpeak not for my ſelf, but your own ſakes,</l>
                  <l>Whoſe Impudence, and art in valiant theft,</l>
                  <l>Hereafter, may advance you to be Princes.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Lo.</speaker>
                  <l>You have confirmed us.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Fr.</speaker>
                  <l>You were beſt be rogues, and one betray another,</l>
                  <l>To get the baſe reward; do, loſe your honour,</l>
                  <l>Live branded, and be pointed at i'th ſtreet,</l>
                  <l>There goes a Raſcall that betrai'd his Prince,</l>
                  <l>Or cut the throat of his Comrade, this will</l>
                  <l>Shew well i'th'Chronicles— Stand fair you varlets,</l>
                  <l>Becauſe we cannot tell whoſe heart is treacherous,</l>
                  <l>I will examine all your Phiſnomies,</l>
                  <l>And in whoſe face ſoever I can find</l>
                  <l>A ſcandalous line, or look that may beget</l>
                  <l>Suſpition of a Man that wo'not die</l>
                  <l>An honourable Rebell, and defie</l>
                  <l>The Laws, I'le ſhoot him preſently.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Lo.</speaker>
                  <l>Hang Laws,</l>
                  <l>And thoſe that make'em, Conſcience is a Varlet;</l>
                  <l>Stand fair and ſhew complexions.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Fr.</speaker>
                  <l>Ye are all valiant, honeſt theeve landers,</l>
                  <l>And I will be your Prince agen, and dy w'ee,</l>
                  <l>As boldly, as they dare invent—</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Ra.</speaker>
                  <l>Hang Cowards.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Fr.</speaker>
                  <l>I will not have you theeves among your ſelves.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Lo.</speaker>
                  <l>How's that, and pleaſe thy Excellence, not theeves?</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Fr.</speaker>
                  <l>Not theeves one to another; but Religious—</l>
                  <l>There is a kind of a Religion</l>
                  <l>We Outlaws muſt obſerve.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>St.</speaker>
                  <l>I never knew</l>
                  <l>Religion yet, and 'twill be now unſeaſonable</l>
                  <l>To learn.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <pb n="3" facs="tcp:153591:7"/>
                  <speaker>Ra.</speaker>
                  <l>I'l be of no Religion.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Fr.</speaker>
                  <l>Who was ſo bold</l>
                  <l>To ſay he would have no Religion?</l>
                  <l>What man is he, hopes to be drunk, to whore,</l>
                  <l>To ſc<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>pe the wheels, the Gallies, and the gallowes</l>
                  <l>And be of no Religion?</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Lo.</speaker>
                  <l>He ſays right.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Fr.</speaker>
                  <l>Yee ſhall be of what Religion I pleaſe.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Pa.</speaker>
                  <l>Tis fit we ſhould, <hi>Frapolo</hi> is our Monarch.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Fr.</speaker>
                  <l>And yet I muſt conſider of ſome fit one</l>
                  <l>That ſhall become our trade</l>
                  <l>And conſtitutions; hum! Silence.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Str.</speaker>
                  <l>Nay, nay Prince, take time to think on't,</l>
                  <l>Ther's no haſt.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Fr.</speaker>
                  <l>I have thought,</l>
                  <l>And you ſhall be no <hi>Pagans, Jews,</hi> nor <hi>Chriſtians.</hi>
                  </l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Lo.</speaker>
                  <l>What then?</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Fr.</speaker>
                  <l>But every man ſhall be of all Religions.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Ra.</speaker>
                  <l>I like that well.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Fr.</speaker>
                  <l>Why ſhould I clog your Conſcience, or confine it?</l>
                  <l>Do but obey your Prince, and I pronounce</l>
                  <l>You ſhall live Grandees, till the State Phangs catch you,</l>
                  <l>And when you come unto the Wheel, or Gibbet,</l>
                  <l>Bid figo for the World, and go out Martyrs.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Omnes.</speaker>
                  <l>A Prince, a Prince!</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Fr.</speaker>
                  <l>Provided, that no theef</l>
                  <l>Makes a Confeſſion at his Death, or peach</l>
                  <l>His Tribe, or make a ſhew of penitence,</l>
                  <l>To make the Butter-women melt, and draw</l>
                  <l>Compaſſion from the toothleſs muſty rabble;</l>
                  <l>This will exclude the benefit of that Canon</l>
                  <l>Declares you Martyrs for the Cauſe.</l>
               </sp>
               <stage>Anoiſe within.</stage>
               <stage>Exit Longino.</stage>
               <l>Scout and diſcover.</l>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Ra.</speaker>
                  <l>Tis a howling voice.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Fr.</speaker>
                  <l>What Cry was that?</l>
               </sp>
               <stage>
                  <pb n="4" facs="tcp:153591:8"/>
                  <hi>Enter Longino.</hi>
               </stage>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Lo.</speaker>
                  <l>Of one, whoſe pocket has given up the Ghoſt,</l>
                  <l>And with the fear his body ſhould do ſo,</l>
                  <l>He howles O'this faſhion.</l>
               </sp>
               <stage>They put on Vizards.</stage>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Fr.</speaker>
                  <l>Bring him to our preſence.</l>
               </sp>
               <stage>Piperollo brought in.</stage>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Pi.</speaker>
                  <l>Gentlemen, tis very cold, I beſeech you</l>
                  <l>Do not ſtrip my Skin off, you are not ſure</l>
                  <l>I ſhall go to a fire when I go out of</l>
                  <l>This World; and yet as I am, I confeſſe</l>
                  <l>I ſhall yield very little burn'd.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Lo.</speaker>
                  <l>Knock out his brains.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Pa.</speaker>
                  <l>Piſtoll him.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>St.</speaker>
                  <l>Cut's throat.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Pi.</speaker>
                  <l>Gentlemen, hear me— I am very ſorry,</l>
                  <l>I had no greater ſum— but if you pleaſe</l>
                  <l>To reprieve a poor wretch, I may do you ſervice,</l>
                  <l>And if you knew my inclination,</l>
                  <l>You would not be too Cruell.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Fr.</speaker>
                  <l>To what are you inclin'd Sirra?</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Pi.</speaker>
                  <l>I have been commended for a Dexterity</l>
                  <l>At your fellonious trade; for Gentlemen,</l>
                  <l>I have been a Pickpocket of a child, and have</l>
                  <l>Theſe many years been thought a pretty houſe-theef,</l>
                  <l>Mary I have not yet breeding abroad</l>
                  <l>With ſuch deſerving men, but I ſhall be</l>
                  <l>Moſt glad to learn, and if you pleaſe t' accept</l>
                  <l>Me to your tribe, I have Intelligence</l>
                  <l>Where money lyes hid, and very few Spirits</l>
                  <l>To guard it.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Fr.</speaker>
                  <l>Be confident, and be cover'd.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Lo.</speaker>
                  <l>Let him be one of us.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Fr.</speaker>
                  <l>Be brief, where is this treaſure?</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Pi.</speaker>
                  <l>I have an old Father, and Mother, Gentlemen,</l>
                  <l>Pleaſe you beſtow a viſit upon them;</l>
                  <pb n="5" facs="tcp:153591:8"/>
                  <l>They have ſome Goldfinches, having new ſold</l>
                  <l>A peece of Land, was given 'em by the rich</l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Vincenzo,</hi> Father to the famous, proud</l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Paulina,</hi> now his heir.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Lo.</speaker>
                  <l>The glorious Daughter</l>
                  <l>Of old <hi>Vincenzo?</hi> ſhe's a <hi>Semiramis.</hi>
                  </l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Pi.</speaker>
                  <l>The very ſame; if you would viſit her,</l>
                  <l>I am acquainted with the houſe.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Fr.</speaker>
                  <l>Wee'l take a time to think on her; to th'point.</l>
                  <l>What ready money has your Father Sirra?</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Pi.</speaker>
                  <l>Tis but two days ago ſince he receiv'd</l>
                  <l>Six hundred Piſtolets, I can direct</l>
                  <l>To a Cedar Cheſt, where the fine ſum lies dormant.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>St.</speaker>
                  <l>What Servants has your Father?</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Pi.</speaker>
                  <l>Alas none, they are miſerable Hinds,</l>
                  <l>And make me all the drudge, you need not fear</l>
                  <l>The Court-du-Guard; if you pleaſe let me go</l>
                  <l>An honeſt theeves part, and furniſh me</l>
                  <l>With a Devills complexion, to hide my own,</l>
                  <l>I will conduct you.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Fr.</speaker>
                  <l>A very honeſt fellow!</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Pi.</speaker>
                  <l>I do not love to be ingratefull where</l>
                  <l>I'm kindly us'd, my heart is honeſt.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Fr.</speaker>
                  <l>Is he thy own Father?</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Pi.</speaker>
                  <l>My own Father and Mother Sir, the cauſe</l>
                  <l>Would not be ſo naturall elſe, and meritorious.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Fr.</speaker>
                  <l>A precious rogue, fit him inſtantly</l>
                  <l>With a diſguiſe, and let him have that face</l>
                  <l>The Devill wore in the laſt anti-maſque.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Pi.</speaker>
                  <l>It cannot be too ugly Sir to fright 'em.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Fr.</speaker>
                  <l>But if he fail in any Circumſtance—</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Pi.</speaker>
                  <l>'Tis not far off, I know the neareſt way.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Fr.</speaker>
                  <l>Or give the leaſt ſuſpition to betray you,</l>
                  <l>Be ſure you cut his throat.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Lo.</speaker>
                  <l>We ſhall.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Pi.</speaker>
                  <l>I thank You Sir, d'ee think I'l be a Traytor?</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <pb n="6" facs="tcp:153591:9"/>
                  <speaker>Lo.</speaker>
                  <l>Come firſt along with us.</l>
               </sp>
               <stage>Exeunt.</stage>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Fr.</speaker>
                  <l>You heard this fellow name the proud <hi>Paulina,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>Her Cheſts are worth the rifling.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Pa.</speaker>
                  <l>The Caſtle is impregnable ſhe lives in.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Fr.</speaker>
                  <l>Was that ſpoke like an underſtanding theef,</l>
                  <l>A true <hi>Bandit?</hi> How I do bluſh for thee?</l>
                  <l>Was not the Orchard of <hi>Heſperides</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>Watcht by a fierce, and flaming Dragon, robd?</l>
                  <l>Shall wee deſpair to reach her golden Apples?</l>
                  <l>Wee'l make diſcovery of the place, and perſons,</l>
                  <l>Put it to Fate, let Stars do what they pleaſe;</l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Mercury</hi> is a Stronger theef than <hi>Hercules.</hi>
                  </l>
               </sp>
               <stage>Exeunt.</stage>
               <stage>Enter Giovanni Stephanio.</stage>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Gio.</speaker>
                  <l>What a brave time have we had, ſince our</l>
                  <l>Old Maſter died?</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>St.</speaker>
                  <l>Though he were a gallant man, his Daughter</l>
                  <l>Makes his Memory burn dym, and (compar'd</l>
                  <l>To her) he liv'd but like a Hermit in a Cell,</l>
                  <l>She is all Magnificent, a <hi>Bererice,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>Every hair of her head worth ſtellyfying.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Gio.</speaker>
                  <l>But my Lady, for ſo we muſt call her,</l>
                  <l>May be of kin to <hi>Lucifer</hi> for pride;</l>
                  <l>How many brave Gentlemen hath ſhe deſpis'd,</l>
                  <l>When once their bliſter of Love broke out,</l>
                  <l>And they made offer of Mariage?</l>
               </sp>
               <stage>Enter Antonio, Angellina.</stage>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Ste.</speaker>
                  <l>Here is her Siſter <hi>Angellina</hi> a virgin</l>
                  <l>Of another conſtitution, their two natures</l>
                  <l>As different are, as the two Poles, our Miſtreſs</l>
                  <l>Cannot be ſo Tyrannically proud</l>
                  <l>As ſhe is ſweet, and humble.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Gio.</speaker>
                  <l>That's the reaſon her Father left her only</l>
                  <l>As much as would commend her to a Nunnery.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>St.</speaker>
                  <l>Her Uncle dotes upon her.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Gio.</speaker>
                  <l>He does love her.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <pb n="7" facs="tcp:153591:9"/>
                  <speaker>St.</speaker>
                  <l>Tis an old blunt brave fellow; but he has</l>
                  <l>Quite loſt our gallant Ladies good opinion,</l>
                  <l>He is out of grace.</l>
               </sp>
               <stage>Ex. Ant. Ang.</stage>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Gio.</speaker>
                  <l>Becauſe he would correct her inſolence,</l>
                  <l>Who oblig'd by her father to the care of</l>
                  <l>Her governour, wo'not tie up his Counſell,</l>
                  <l>Which he enforces ſometimes ſo paſſionately,</l>
                  <l>It is a ſport to hear her contempt of his gravity.</l>
                  <stage>Enter Paulina, Antonio.</stage>
                  <l>He has met my Lady, I ſee a quarrell</l>
                  <l>In their looks already, let us withd raw</l>
                  <l>Behind that Lobby, we may hear, and</l>
                  <l>Laugh ſecurely.</l>
               </sp>
               <stage>Exeunt.</stage>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>An.</speaker>
                  <l>How long have you been ſpeechleſs? am</l>
                  <l>Not I your Uncle? why do you look ſo ſcurvily?</l>
                  <l>I do not think you are a Princeſſe yet,</l>
                  <l>And therefore take the boldneſs to ſalute you,</l>
                  <l>Without the Ceremony of Petitioners</l>
                  <l>That haunt your Ladiſhips charity; or if</l>
                  <l>You thought me deſpicable, your Siſter has</l>
                  <l>Deſerv'd your ſmile.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Pa.</speaker>
                  <l>It may be ſo—</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>An.</speaker>
                  <l>Buffoones,</l>
                  <l>That make an Idoll of you, and can pawn</l>
                  <l>Their Souls to flatter you, ſhould be entertaind,</l>
                  <l>And Courted to your vanity. I bluſh for you;</l>
                  <l>Will nothing bring you into ſenſe of Honour</l>
                  <l>Or Modeſty? I ha done.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Pa.</speaker>
                  <l>It will become you;</l>
                  <l>You do preſume too much.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>An.</speaker>
                  <l>Preſume? why, are</l>
                  <l>Not you <hi>Paulina</hi> am not I <hi>Antonio</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>Your Uncle? ſpeak.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Pa.</speaker>
                  <l>I do remember Sir,</l>
                  <l>I calld you ſo, while you preſerv'd your wits,</l>
                  <pb n="8" facs="tcp:153591:10"/>
                  <l>And may acknowledge you again, upon</l>
                  <l>Sober Conditions, and your Senſes perfect.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>An.</speaker>
                  <l>Sober Conditions? am I Drunk, Gipſey?</l>
                  <l>What fleſh is able to forbear. Doſt hear?</l>
                  <l>Thou haſt drunk a Devill.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Pa.</speaker>
                  <l>I did not ſee him in my Cup.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>An.</speaker>
                  <l>And he has ſweld thee to this monſtrous pride,</l>
                  <l>More than thy Sex beſide; if thou goeſt on</l>
                  <l>At this rate, thou wilt make <hi>Lucifer</hi> an Ape,</l>
                  <l>He muſt be thy Diſciple.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Pa.</speaker>
                  <l>The Old thing raves.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>An.</speaker>
                  <l>Thing? what thing? thank heaven thou</l>
                  <l>Art a woman; I would beat thee into a Poltiſe—</l>
                  <l>When didſt thou ſay thy prayers?</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Pa.</speaker>
                  <l>You know I keep a Chaplain.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>An.</speaker>
                  <l>Thy Soul wants deſperate lancing;</l>
                  <l>Ther's an eternall Ulcer in thy heart,</l>
                  <l>Te Witches cannot ſuck it dry, there is</l>
                  <l>A bath of Poyſon in thee.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Pa.</speaker>
                  <l>I ſhall pity him;</l>
                  <l>A Poſſet, and to bed with him, his head</l>
                  <l>Does want the benefit of ſleep; how wild</l>
                  <l>The good man looks?</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>An.</speaker>
                  <l>Thou art—</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Pa.</speaker>
                  <l>The Miſtreſs of this Caſtle as I take it,</l>
                  <l>Without your Legacy.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>An.</speaker>
                  <l>I could rail upon the dead for't; doſt thou not fear</l>
                  <l>Thy Fathers ghoſt ſhould haunt thee?</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Pa.</speaker>
                  <l>I never think upon him, and it was</l>
                  <l>His providence to leave me an eſtate,</l>
                  <l>To keep me from thoſe Malancholy fancies,</l>
                  <l>And I will have you my caprichious Uncle</l>
                  <l>Know, in the Circle of theſe my Dominions,</l>
                  <l>I will have no Competitor.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>An.</speaker>
                  <l>Dominions?</l>
                  <l>Was ever ſuch an inſolence? are not you</l>
                  <pb n="9" facs="tcp:153591:10"/>
                  <l>ome Queen conceald?</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Pa.</speaker>
                  <l>I am Independent, and ſole regent here.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>An.</speaker>
                  <l>So ſo,</l>
                  <l>Where's your Nobility? they are to blame</l>
                  <l>Not to attend—</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Pa.</speaker>
                  <l>Who waits?</l>
               </sp>
               <stage>Enter Giovanni, Stephanio.</stage>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>An.</speaker>
                  <l>But they do want white Staves, this is</l>
                  <l>Not State enough.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Pa.</speaker>
                  <l>It ſhall be mended, let them be remembred.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>An.</speaker>
                  <l>She's in earneſt—and</l>
                  <l>If I were worthy to adviſe you Madam,</l>
                  <l>Your grace ſhould be a little more reſerv'd,</l>
                  <l>And entertain none that did treat of Mariage</l>
                  <l>To your private conference, untill they had</l>
                  <l>In publick receiv'd audience like Ambaſſadors.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Pa.</speaker>
                  <l>I like the Counſell well, it ſhall be ſo,</l>
                  <l>The next that comes ſhall find it my good Uncle.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>An.</speaker>
                  <l>She's incorrigible.</l>
                  <l>What if you commanded thoſe that do attend</l>
                  <l>Your perſon to obſerve you on their knees</l>
                  <l>Sometimes, they muſt be humble to your highneſs;</l>
                  <l>I can forget my gray hairs, name, and bloud,</l>
                  <l>And teach your Servants duty.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Pa.</speaker>
                  <l>The example</l>
                  <l>Will edifie the houſhold, and you may,</l>
                  <l>By fair degrees riſe to our Princely favour.</l>
               </sp>
               <stage>Enter Lucio.</stage>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Lu.</speaker>
                  <l>Madam, the Lord <hi>Contarini</hi> is arrived</l>
                  <l>The Caſtle.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Pa.</speaker>
                  <l>He comes a woing to me, let it be</l>
                  <l>Your Office reverend Uncle to acquaint him,</l>
                  <l>Our pleaſure is to give him Audience</l>
                  <l>To Morrow in full State, untill when Uncle,</l>
                  <l>Make it your care his entertainment be</l>
                  <l>Such as becomes the greatneſs of his bloud,</l>
                  <pb n="10" facs="tcp:153591:11"/>
                  <l>And one, on whom the Prince, we know, beſtows</l>
                  <l>His ſpeciall grace.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>An.</speaker>
                  <l>D'ee hear ſweet Niece? be not you tranſporte</l>
                  <l>This is no dream, the man is no mock-lord.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Pa.</speaker>
                  <l>I'l be a Princeſs here, as you directed,</l>
                  <l>If he can humble himſelf to Ceremony,</l>
                  <l>Promiſe him honourable acceſs, and freedom,</l>
                  <l>If the Conditions pleaſe him not, he may</l>
                  <l>Return, and leave our Court.</l>
               </sp>
               <stage>
                  <hi>Ex<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="4 letters">
                        <desc>••••</desc>
                     </gap>
                  </hi>
               </stage>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>An.</speaker>
                  <l>Is this in Nature? well I'l follow her,</l>
                  <l>And if ſhe be not paſt all ſhame, and ſenſes,</l>
                  <l>I will humble or confound her.</l>
               </sp>
               <stage>Ex</stage>
            </div>
            <div n="2" type="act">
               <head>ACT II.</head>
               <stage>Enter Longino, Strozzo, Binding Fabio, and Morulla.</stage>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Mo.</speaker>
                  <l>AH ſweet Gentlemen, we are very poor,</l>
                  <l>And have a great Charge.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Str.</speaker>
                  <l>We do come to eaſe you of your charge.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Fa.</speaker>
                  <l>Pity my age.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>St.</speaker>
                  <l>You muſt then pity our youth.</l>
               </sp>
               <stage>Enter Piperollo viſarded with three bags.</stage>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Pi.</speaker>
                  <l>Here, ſhare and ſhare like.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Mo.</speaker>
                  <l>Alas we are undone.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>St.</speaker>
                  <l>What ſhall we do with them?</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Pi.</speaker>
                  <l>If you have bound her hands and feet, you</l>
                  <l>May try whether ſhe be a Witch or no, there's</l>
                  <l>A Pond in the backſide, if ſhe ſwim, ſo—</l>
                  <l>For him?</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Fa.</speaker>
                  <l>Have ſome compaſſion, tis our whole eſtate.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Lo.</speaker>
                  <l>You have a Son, a pious child we hear.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <pb n="11" facs="tcp:153591:11"/>
                  <speaker>St.</speaker>
                  <l>He will not let you want.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Mo.</speaker>
                  <l>Alas poor boy, he little thinks what we</l>
                  <l>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ith care and providence laid up for him</l>
                  <l>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>hould thus be loſt. O pity Gentlemen.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Pi.</speaker>
                  <l>Boh—Lets away.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>St.</speaker>
                  <l>I begin to find a kind of a compunction,</l>
                  <l>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>et us be charitable theeves for once—</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Lo.</speaker>
                  <l>And return half,</l>
                  <l>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>hat ſay you?</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Pi.</speaker>
                  <l>Not a gazet, y'are not ſuch fooliſh theeves;</l>
                  <l>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>art with preſent money? part with my life firſt.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>St.</speaker>
                  <l>Not to your Parents?</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Pi.</speaker>
                  <l>We uſe them well, becauſe we do not carry</l>
                  <l>Their Cowes away; there they have Cheeſe, and Butter,</l>
                  <l>Bread comes by nature, and they both can glean,</l>
                  <l>There's water in the Well too; not a penny—</l>
                  <l>If you will be ſo charitable, defalk</l>
                  <l>From your own ſhares, mine is a juſt theeves part;</l>
                  <l>I look for thanks, diſtribute your own alms;</l>
                  <l>Theſe things muſt be employ'd to better uſes.</l>
                  <l>Is a Father, and Mother conſiderable</l>
                  <l>To ready mony; oh! fie—boh!</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>St.</speaker>
                  <l>Then we muſt over-rule you.</l>
               </sp>
               <stage>Trips up his heels.</stage>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Pi.</speaker>
                  <l>Ah what do you mean?</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>St.</speaker>
                  <l>Baul and betray your ſelf at your own perill.</l>
                  <l>We will be bold with your theeves part—</l>
                  <l>Come neerer—Look you good Woman,</l>
                  <l>You ſhall not loſe your thirds, ſay you have met</l>
                  <l>With honeſt theeves; this ſhall ſuffice at preſent,</l>
                  <l>Which we but borrow neither, that you may not</l>
                  <l>Suſpect our payment, you ſhall have ſecurity,</l>
                  <l>This honeſt man bound for't, and ſo we leave you.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Fa.</speaker>
                  <l>Tis money.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Mo.</speaker>
                  <l>And left one of their fellows bound.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Fa.</speaker>
                  <l>Do we not dream Wife? I dare not come neer</l>
                  <l>Him.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <pb n="12" facs="tcp:153591:12"/>
                  <speaker>Mo.</speaker>
                  <l>They are gone, I'l ſee his complexion;</l>
                  <l>Who's this?</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Fa.</speaker>
                  <l>Our own Son <hi>Piperollo?</hi>
                  </l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Pi.</speaker>
                  <l>Pray Father give me your bleſſing, ah—</l>
                  <l>Mother do not ſtone me to death with that</l>
                  <l>Money bag, I am your Son.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Mo.</speaker>
                  <l>My Son? I know thee not.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Pi.</speaker>
                  <l>A liar, you know Mother, is worſe than a</l>
                  <l>Theef; do not deſtroy the hopes of your Family,</l>
                  <l>Alas, I was drawn in, and made a theef</l>
                  <l>In my own defence, they ſwore to cut my throat</l>
                  <l>Elſe, do you think I had ſo little grace—</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Mo.</speaker>
                  <l>Did they ſo? I'l try what I can do.</l>
               </sp>
               <stage>She draws her knife.</stage>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Pi.</speaker>
                  <l>Oh my quibibles! ſweet Mother, remember</l>
                  <l>You were a woman in your days, that knew</l>
                  <l>What's what, and the true difference of things.</l>
                  <l>I am a man yet, your forgiveneſſe may</l>
                  <l>Make me a true man. Libbing, and hanging</l>
                  <l>Are no helps to poſterity, I am your own</l>
                  <l>Sweet fleſh and bloud—Oh.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Mo.</speaker>
                  <l>Kick him out of doors.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Pi.</speaker>
                  <l>I thank you, this Correction may do me good;</l>
                  <l>Gently, ah gently; ſhall I not ask you bleſſing,</l>
                  <l>A twelve-month hence?</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Both.</speaker>
                  <l>Never.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Pi.</speaker>
                  <l>I wo'not.</l>
                  <l>My Mother has a deadly lift with her leg.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Fa.</speaker>
                  <l>Boh, you tadpole.</l>
               </sp>
               <stage>Exeunt.</stage>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Pi.</speaker>
                  <l>I ſhall do no good o'this trade.</l>
                  <l>Now to my wits, this is no world to ſtarve in.</l>
               </sp>
               <stage>Exit</stage>
               <stage>Enter Lucio, Giovanni, Stephanio, with white Staves.</stage>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Lu.</speaker>
                  <l>This is very fine; do not theſe Staves become us?</l>
                  <l>But will my Lady be thus mad, and give</l>
                  <pb n="13" facs="tcp:153591:12"/>
                  <l>The Lord <hi>Contarini</hi> Audience in ſuch State?</l>
                  <l>She takes upon her like a very Princeſs.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Gio.</speaker>
                  <l>But is't not ſtrange, her Uncle ſhould thus humor her?</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Ste.</speaker>
                  <l>He gave her the firſt hint, which ſhe purfues</l>
                  <l>To his vexation.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Luc.</speaker>
                  <l>But will my Lord ſtoop to this mockery?</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Gio.</speaker>
                  <l>He is prepar'd by her Uncle; 'twil be ſport,</l>
                  <l>If ſhe but carry it with pride enough.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Gio.</speaker>
                  <l>Let her alone.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>St.</speaker>
                  <l>And if my Lord wants confidence—</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Gio.</speaker>
                  <l>I think her impudence will make him bluſh,</l>
                  <l>And put him out; I have ſeen a Counterfeit</l>
                  <l>With ſuch a Majeſty compoſe himſelf,</l>
                  <l>He thought himſelf a Prince, could frown as ſcornfully,</l>
                  <l>And give his hand out to great Lords to kiſs,</l>
                  <l>With as much grace, as all the Royall bloud</l>
                  <l>Had muſterd in his veins.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Lu</speaker>
                  <l>Some Monarch</l>
                  <l>Of Innes a Court in <hi>England</hi> ſure; but when</l>
                  <l>His reign expires, and Chriſtmas in the grave</l>
                  <l>Cold as the Turkies coffind up in cruſt,</l>
                  <l>That walk like Ghoſts, and glide to ſeverall Tables,</l>
                  <l>When Inſtruments are hoarſe with ſitting up,</l>
                  <l>When the gay triumph ceaſes, and the treaſure</l>
                  <l>Divided, all the Offices laid up,</l>
                  <l>And the new cloathes in Lavender, what then?</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Gio.</speaker>
                  <l>Why then the man that kiſt his highneſs hand</l>
                  <l>O'r night, may juſtle him for the wall next morning,</l>
                  <l>And have it too; if he come off with all</l>
                  <l>His wits, the Play is paid for, and he fit</l>
                  <l>For travell.</l>
                  <stage>Enter Contarini, Antonio, Vergerio, they whiſper.</stage>
                  <l>My Ladies Uncle, and the Lord <hi>Contarini.</hi>
                  </l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Ver.</speaker>
                  <l>My Lord <hi>Contarini</hi> expects when he</l>
                  <l>May have the happineſs to preſent his ſervice</l>
                  <pb n="14" facs="tcp:153591:13"/>
                  <l>To your great Lady.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Lu.</speaker>
                  <l>We ſhall Sir acquaint her.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Ver.</speaker>
                  <l>Your Office Sir?</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Lu.</speaker>
                  <l>Her Steward.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Ver.</speaker>
                  <l>Yours I pray?</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>St.</speaker>
                  <l>Mine, Treaſurer.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Gio.</speaker>
                  <l>Mine, Controller.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Ver.</speaker>
                  <l>I kiſs your hands; this may be worth my Lord</l>
                  <l>Curioſity.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>An.</speaker>
                  <l>For the mirths ſake, my Lord be pleas'd, you ma<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>
                  </l>
                  <l>Do an act of Charity and reſtore her Senſes;</l>
                  <l>I'l wait on you again.</l>
               </sp>
               <stage>Exit.</stage>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Con.</speaker>
                  <l>Now <hi>Vergerio?</hi>
                  </l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Ver.</speaker>
                  <l>The expectation is increas'd, her Officers</l>
                  <l>Obſerve the State; were your affections earneſt</l>
                  <l>And I my Lord your Miſtreſſe, I ſhould truſt</l>
                  <l>Her pride.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Con.</speaker>
                  <l>Unleſs ſhe raviſh me.</l>
               </sp>
               <stage>Enter Antonio.</stage>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>An.</speaker>
                  <l>She's upon entrance, her madneſs holds,</l>
                  <l>Your confidence may convert her, ſhees my Neece</l>
                  <l>And I am ſorry for it.</l>
               </sp>
               <stage>Enter Paulina attended in State, Angellina, Ladies.</stage>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Pa.</speaker>
                  <l>Give him acceſſe.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Con.</speaker>
                  <l>What Ladies that ſtands on her right hand?</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>An.</speaker>
                  <l>Her younger Siſter, that does vex me as much</l>
                  <l>With her humility, as the other with</l>
                  <l>Her impudence.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Con.</speaker>
                  <l>An excellent peece, <hi>Vergerio.</hi>
                  </l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Ver.</speaker>
                  <l>Which my Lord?</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Con.</speaker>
                  <l>Madam, the glory of your time and Nation,</l>
                  <l>Whoſe looks do ſhine with Majeſty, and ſhoot</l>
                  <l>A flame t' undoe the admirer, O call in</l>
                  <l>Some beams that wait upon the thrones of light,</l>
                  <l>Or I ſhall fall your ſacrifice, and not finiſh</l>
                  <pb n="15" facs="tcp:153591:13"/>
                  <l>What my great Maſter gave me in charge.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Lu.</speaker>
                  <l>Has the Prince a mind to her himſelf.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>St.</speaker>
                  <l>Tis not impoſſible.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Pa.</speaker>
                  <l>Speak on my Lord.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>An.</speaker>
                  <l>Gipſey, ſhe does believe the lightning <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap> her eys</l>
                  <l>Will blaſt indeed, how ſcornfully ſhe <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 span">
                        <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                     </gap>
                  </l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Con.</speaker>
                  <l>I come from the great Sovereign of hearts,</l>
                  <l>Whoſe glorious monarchy uncircumſcrib'd,</l>
                  <l>Extends to all the habitable world,</l>
                  <l>Where ever land or lover ſtretch'd his arm,</l>
                  <l>Whoſe Scepter's not like that of common Kings,</l>
                  <l>But a bright golden ſhaft feather'd with ſighs,</l>
                  <l>And headed with a flame, which finds acceſs,</l>
                  <l>Like ſubtill lightning to the moſt ſecure,</l>
                  <l>And ſtubborn Cell that ever yet inclos'd</l>
                  <l>A humane thought—</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Lu.</speaker>
                  <l>He flies high.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Gio.</speaker>
                  <l>Tis his arrow—</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Pa.</speaker>
                  <l>Speak this great name.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Con.</speaker>
                  <l>The moſt immortall Prince of Love—</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Gio.</speaker>
                  <l>A high and mighty Prince indeed.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Lu.</speaker>
                  <l>Tis not our Prince of <hi>Parma</hi> then?</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Con.</speaker>
                  <l>Unto your beauty Madam, that makes ſweet</l>
                  <l>The breath of Fame, in his name I am ſent</l>
                  <l>To offer up a Servant, rich with wonder,</l>
                  <l>And humble thoughts that honour you; who can</l>
                  <l>See thoſe perfections and not adore</l>
                  <l>The Divine Owner? Brightneſs that offends</l>
                  <l>The inhocent eye that gazes, is in you</l>
                  <l>The cure of blindneſs, and the filmes that hang</l>
                  <l>Upon the humble ſight, fall off and vaniſh,</l>
                  <l>That it may take new life and light from you.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>An.</speaker>
                  <l>Is ſhe not yet ridiculous to her ſelf?</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Con.</speaker>
                  <l>I can leave Cupids Court to live with you,</l>
                  <l>And all thoſe bowers, where an eternall ſpring</l>
                  <l>Makes every flower in love with it's own beauty.</l>
                  <pb n="16" facs="tcp:153591:14"/>
                  <l>The wind whoſe airy wings convey all ſweetneſs</l>
                  <l>That ſenſe can entertain, I would exchange</l>
                  <l>But to be near your breath; and think there dwels</l>
                  <l>A harmony in your voice, above the airs</l>
                  <l>Of all thoſe charming Birds by love ſelected</l>
                  <l>From every wood to be his quire. I fear</l>
                  <l>I am too bold, and may be thought to wander;</l>
                  <l>If Madam you accept my amorous vows,</l>
                  <l>Which live yet in the weak expreſſion</l>
                  <l>Of him that honours you, time will produce</l>
                  <l>A white and fortunate hour to crown our loves</l>
                  <l>With nuptiall happineſs.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Pa.</speaker>
                  <l>You have relation</l>
                  <l>To the Court of <hi>Parma,</hi> your name Lord</l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Contarini,</hi> you have no Meſſage from you Maſter?</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Con.</speaker>
                  <l>Madam your ſame hath fild his Court, and he</l>
                  <l>Preſents by me his Princely wiſhes of</l>
                  <l>Your happineſs, and ſhould he ſee your perſon,</l>
                  <l>Like mine, his heart I fear would melt into</l>
                  <l>A ſtream of Love and Admiration.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Pa.</speaker>
                  <l>Sir, we accept in good part greeting from</l>
                  <l>The Prince, but you have no commiſſion</l>
                  <l>To treat for him; the ſubſtance of your own</l>
                  <l>Affair will ask our pauſe, we will take time</l>
                  <l>To anſwer, which till you receive, you may</l>
                  <l>Command our Court.</l>
               </sp>
               <stage>Exeunt Paulina, Servant</stage>
               <stage>Angellina ſtayes.</stage>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Ver.</speaker>
                  <l>Proud folly!</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Ant.</speaker>
                  <l>Prodigious impudence!</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Con.</speaker>
                  <l>What think you Signior?</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Ant.</speaker>
                  <l>I am confounded, I'l to her agen.</l>
               </sp>
               <stage>
                  <hi>Ex<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>
                  </hi>
               </stage>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Ang.</speaker>
                  <l>When ſhall I awake?</l>
                  <l>This ſure is but a dream, the Gentleman</l>
                  <l>Cannot ſo much miſtake his time and Language.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Con.</speaker>
                  <l>I came with Curioſity to ſee</l>
                  <l>Her pride ſo talk'd of, but my heart I feel</l>
                  <pb n="17" facs="tcp:153591:14"/>
                  <l>Is taken with an object of true ſweetneſs.</l>
                  <l>Is't not a lovely figure? ſay <hi>Vergerio.</hi>
                  </l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Ver.</speaker>
                  <l>If but her mind anſwer that fair proportion,</l>
                  <l>My Lord ſhe is worth love, but being Siſter</l>
                  <l>To a woman of ſuch pride—</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Con.</speaker>
                  <l>I prethee leave me.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Ver.</speaker>
                  <l>She is very beautifull; my Lord is taken.</l>
               </sp>
               <stage>Exit.</stage>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Con.</speaker>
                  <l>Lady, but that ther's ſtory for your births,</l>
                  <l>I ſhould make judgment by your modeſt face,</l>
                  <l>This arrogant woman could not be your Siſter.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Ang.</speaker>
                  <l>Sir, if your expectation be not anſwered</l>
                  <l>With her full worth, I ſhall beſeech you name her</l>
                  <l>With leſs diſgrace, (our bloud ſo neer) it cannot</l>
                  <l>Be gratefull to my ear, to hear her blemiſhes.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Con.</speaker>
                  <l>I was prepar'd before to meet this goodneſs;</l>
                  <l>Theſe words and looks become that innocent ſpring</l>
                  <l>From whence they flow, vertue hath ſuch an army</l>
                  <l>About your heart, ther's nothing can approach</l>
                  <l>Ill to betray it, or proceed from you</l>
                  <l>But warranted by honour.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>An.</speaker>
                  <l>I know not,</l>
                  <l>But ſure my Lord, you talk too fine a language</l>
                  <l>For me to underſtand; we are far from Court,</l>
                  <l>Where though you may ſpeak Truth, you cloath it with</l>
                  <l>Such trim and gay apparell, we that only</l>
                  <l>Know her in plainneſs, and ſimplicity,</l>
                  <l>Cannot tell how to truſt our ears, or know,</l>
                  <l>When men diſſemble.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Con.</speaker>
                  <l>By your own love</l>
                  <l>To truth, you muſt beleeve me, when I ſay,</l>
                  <l>Although it took beginning from this viſit,</l>
                  <l>I love no beauty but your ſelf.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Ang.</speaker>
                  <l>You ſaid you lov'd my Siſter, and expreſt</l>
                  <l>Your paſſion in ſuch mighty phraſe and fancie</l>
                  <l>I thought your ſoul had made a buſineſs on't,</l>
                  <l>Pardon the weakneſs of my faith if I</l>
                  <pb n="18" facs="tcp:153591:15"/>
                  <l>Dare not believe this change.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Con.</speaker>
                  <l>Your Siſter, Lady,</l>
                  <l>I came to viſit, not affect, I heard,</l>
                  <l>And had a purpoſe but to try how neer</l>
                  <l>The wonder of her pride (pardon ſweet Virgin)</l>
                  <l>Came to a truth, nor did I Court her with</l>
                  <l>The language of a meaning lover; but</l>
                  <l>Prepared by your Vncle, meant to make her ſee</l>
                  <l>Her miſerable folly; I dare not</l>
                  <l>Preſent ſuch Mockeries to you; ſuſpect not</l>
                  <l>This haſty addreſs; by your fair ſelf, I love you.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Ang.</speaker>
                  <l>My Lord, If I beleev'd this, reall Courtſhip,</l>
                  <l>I ſhould not entertain your honour with a</l>
                  <l>A fruitleſs Expectation, but declare,</l>
                  <l>Beſides my want of fortune, beauty, birth,</l>
                  <l>To make me worth your love, I am already</l>
                  <l>Contracted by my Father to Religion,</l>
                  <l>Whoſe will I cheerfully obey, and wait</l>
                  <l>When my good Uncle will diſpoſe me to</l>
                  <l>A Nunnery.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Con.</speaker>
                  <l>A Nunnery?</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Ang.</speaker>
                  <l>Where for</l>
                  <l>So great an honour you pretend to me</l>
                  <l>A moſt unworthy maid, I'l offer up</l>
                  <l>My prayers, that you may chooſe a heart more equall</l>
                  <l>To your own love, and greatneſs.</l>
               </sp>
               <stage>Enter Antonio, Paulina, and Servants.</stage>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Con.</speaker>
                  <l>Nay you muſt</l>
                  <l>Not leave me ſo, we are interrupted, you</l>
                  <l>May truſt me fair one with a neerer Conference.</l>
               </sp>
               <stage>Exeunt.</stage>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Pa.</speaker>
                  <l>Alas poor old man.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Ant.</speaker>
                  <l>The Old man before your borrowed Ladiſhip</l>
                  <l>Is bold to keep his head warm, and to tell you</l>
                  <l>You are a Puppet, take that to your title;</l>
                  <l>Of honour.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Pa.</speaker>
                  <l>So Sir, none reſtrain his inſolence?</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <pb n="19" facs="tcp:153591:15"/>
                  <speaker>Ant.</speaker>
                  <l>I'l make him ſwallow down his ſtaff of Office</l>
                  <l>That ſtirs. I ha'not done. Canſt be ſo impudent</l>
                  <l>To think his Lordſhip does not laugh at thee?</l>
                  <l>Your eys the thrones of light? a brace of Lanthorns,</l>
                  <l>In which two ſnufs of Candle cloſe to th'ſocket,</l>
                  <l>Appear like fire-drakes, and will ſerve to light</l>
                  <l>A traveller into a Ditch. You Madam Majeſty,</l>
                  <l>And the glory of a Nation?</l>
                  <l>Tho'art a diſeaſe to Honour, Modeſty,</l>
                  <l>A Feaver in thy Fathers bloud, a Gangren</l>
                  <l>Upon his name, a Pox upon thee for't;</l>
                  <l>Ther's one diſeaſe more, yet I have not done.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Pa.</speaker>
                  <l>My Charity may invite, if theſe fits hold,</l>
                  <l>Some cloſe proviſion for you 'mong mad men;</l>
                  <l>I do command you leave my houſe.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Ant.</speaker>
                  <l>I wo'not,</l>
                  <l>I'l fire the houſe; doſt hear? thou wo't burn well,</l>
                  <l>Th'aſt Oil enough about thy face, and all</l>
                  <l>Thy body Pitch, very combuſtible.</l>
                  <l>But I'l not be damn'd for thee, now I think on't,</l>
                  <l>And ſince no Counſell will prevail, I'l ſave</l>
                  <l>My ſelf. Before I go, give but a reaſon</l>
                  <l>Why thou doſt ſlight this gallant Lord, and ſquint</l>
                  <l>As if he were Groom or Foot man.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Pa.</speaker>
                  <l>I'l tell you,</l>
                  <l>You would have the truth.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Ant.</speaker>
                  <l>If thou canſt ſpeak any.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Pa.</speaker>
                  <l>I do eſteem my ſelf</l>
                  <l>More equall for his Maſter.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Ant.</speaker>
                  <l>Who, the Prince?</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Pa.</speaker>
                  <l>No, the blind Prince of Love, you are wiſe Uncle,</l>
                  <l>But I am out of Poetry.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Ant.</speaker>
                  <l>I think I were beſt cut off thy head, and ſave</l>
                  <l>The Laws a labour—Ther's no talking to her.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Pa.</speaker>
                  <l>I am of your mind Uncle, you may edifie</l>
                  <l>Your charge, my younger Siſter, ſhe's not proud,</l>
                  <pb n="20" facs="tcp:153591:16"/>
                  <l>Pray take her w'ee, ſhee'l become the Cloiſter;</l>
                  <l>Go, and be mortified together, take her,</l>
                  <l>I am weary of her.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Ant.</speaker>
                  <l>And I of thee;</l>
                  <l>She ſhall be further oft too, thou'lt infect her,</l>
                  <l>Although her fooliſh Father, (yet he was</l>
                  <l>My Brother) I have not power to ſpeak</l>
                  <l>Well o'th'dead, gave thee his whole Eſtate,</l>
                  <l>I have a fortune, doſt thou hear? I have,</l>
                  <l>And to vex thee, thy Siſter ſhall have that,</l>
                  <l>I'l ſee, and I can make her proud, I'l do't;</l>
                  <l>She ſhall have Servants, Suters, Fidlers, Flatterers,</l>
                  <l>Fine Cloathes, and all the food that can provoke</l>
                  <l>To glorifie her ſenſe; I have bags to ſpare,</l>
                  <l>She ſhall not to a Nunnery to vex thee,</l>
                  <l>I ſay again ſhe ſhall not, wee'l have humours;</l>
                  <l>The to'ther Pox upon thee, and farewell.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Pa.</speaker>
                  <l>I fear he's mad indeed. Let me have Muſick,</l>
                  <l>This talk has made me Melancholy.</l>
               </sp>
               <stage>Exeunt.</stage>
            </div>
            <div n="3" type="act">
               <head>ACT III.</head>
               <stage>Enter Lucio, Piperollo.</stage>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Lu.</speaker>
                  <l>FOr thy Mothers ſake thou ſhalt be entertain'd.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Pi.</speaker>
                  <l>An under Butler would fit me rarely,</l>
                  <l>Ther's none i'th'houſe that ſhall be ſooner drunk,</l>
                  <l>Nor oftner for my Ladies credit Sir.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Lu.</speaker>
                  <l>Can you write?</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Pi.</speaker>
                  <l>And read in print Sir.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Lu.</speaker>
                  <l>Art thou faithfull? may a man truſt thee?</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Pi.</speaker>
                  <l>For more than I'l ſpeak on; truſted? I was boun<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>
                  </l>
                  <l>For two Gentlemen lately, that could not take up</l>
                  <l>Five hundred Piſtols upon other ſecurity,</l>
                  <pb n="21" facs="tcp:153591:16"/>
                  <l>My Father and Mother knows it; I ſhall never</l>
                  <l>Endure a theef for a thing that I know, alas</l>
                  <l>You know I am a neighbors child, my mother</l>
                  <l>Was your good Ladies nurſe.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Lu.</speaker>
                  <l>Do not I know thy Mother?</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Pi.</speaker>
                  <l>Better it may be, than I know my Father.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Lu.</speaker>
                  <l>Till ſome Office fall i'th'houſe, you ſhall ſerve me,</l>
                  <l>And ride with me, to receive my Ladies Rents.</l>
               </sp>
               <stage>Enter Controller Giovanni.</stage>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Gio.</speaker>
                  <l>Mr. Steward, yonder are the rareſt fellows,</l>
                  <l>In ſuch phantaſticall habits too, they call</l>
                  <l>Themſelves Mathematicians.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Lu.</speaker>
                  <l>What do they come for?</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Gio.</speaker>
                  <l>To offer their ſervice to my Lady, and tell fortunes.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Lu.</speaker>
                  <l>Have they no chief?</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Gio.</speaker>
                  <l>Yes a quaint philoſophicall fellow, they call</l>
                  <l>Him a <hi>Caldean,</hi> a great Schollar, they do</l>
                  <l>Not come for money like your ſtarch'd fac'd</l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Egyptians,</hi> but carry things for the credit of</l>
                  <l>The Mathematiques honourably; my Lady hath</l>
                  <l>Given the <hi>Caldean</hi> her Nativity, who is to conſult</l>
                  <l>With the Ephemerides, and give account how</l>
                  <l>The Stars wil dispoſe of her.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Pi.</speaker>
                  <l>We ſhall know all our fortunes then.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Gio.</speaker>
                  <l>The worſt of his train can diſcipher hands,</l>
                  <l>Tell foreheads.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Pi.</speaker>
                  <l>And Noſes.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Gio.</speaker>
                  <l>One at the firſt ſight did but whiſper to my</l>
                  <l>Ladies Gentlewoman, and ſhe did ſo bluſh</l>
                  <l>Through her Tiffany.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Pi.</speaker>
                  <l>That's no great matter, I have ſeen one bluſh</l>
                  <l>Through a Plaiſter of <hi>Paris.</hi>
                  </l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Lu.</speaker>
                  <l>How's that?</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Pi.</speaker>
                  <l>A kind of <hi>French</hi> painting Sir.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Gio.</speaker>
                  <l>Well ſaid <hi>Piperollo;</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>I have entertain'd him; but my Lady.</l>
               </sp>
               <stage>
                  <pb n="22" facs="tcp:153591:17"/>
                  <hi>Enter Paulina, Gentlewomen.</hi>
               </stage>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Pa.</speaker>
                  <l>The <hi>Caldean</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>Pleaſes me, I long to hear my fortune,</l>
                  <l>If it be good he ſhall have a reward</l>
                  <l>To cheriſh his great Art, and worth my bounty;</l>
                  <l>What if my Stars ſhould frown?</l>
                  <l>Didſt bid 'em follow?</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Ste.</speaker>
                  <l>They are all ready Madam.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Pi.</speaker>
                  <l>Muſicall knaves.</l>
               </sp>
               <stage>Enter Longino, Rancone, Pacheco, Strozzo, in queint diſguiſes.</stage>
               <lg>
                  <head>A Song.</head>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Beauty and the various grace,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>That adorn the ſweeteſt faces,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Here take their glorious throne; may be</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>That is the God of Archerie,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Never aim one angry Dart,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>But ſoft, and gentle as your heart,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Court it with flame, and rich perfume,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>To light, and ſweeten, not conſume.</hi>
                  </l>
               </lg>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Pa.</speaker>
                  <l>Not the <hi>Caldean</hi> come yet? my thoughts are</l>
                  <l>Inflam'd with fierce deſire to know my Deſtiny;</l>
                  <l>You have skill Gentlemen; but I'l expect</l>
                  <l>The judgment of your Maſter on my Fate;</l>
                  <l>When the great man of art returns acquaint me.</l>
               </sp>
               <stage>Exit.</stage>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Ste.</speaker>
                  <l>Come my friends, lets loſe no time; Sir.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Lo.</speaker>
                  <l>I am for you to the extent of my Art Signiour.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Ra.</speaker>
                  <l>If it pleaſe you, let me peruſe your hand.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Lu.</speaker>
                  <l>'Tis at your ſervice.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Pi.</speaker>
                  <l>Pleaſe you to examine my Palm; can you</l>
                  <l>Tell me learned Sir, what is paſt?</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Pa.</speaker>
                  <l>You know that already.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Pi.</speaker>
                  <l>'Twill be a ſatisfaction to me, if you can</l>
                  <l>Make it appear, that you know ſomething</l>
                  <l>In that point.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Lo.</speaker>
                  <l>A Fracture in the Mercuriall line, and the</l>
                  <pb n="23" facs="tcp:153591:17"/>
                  <l>Mount of <hi>Saturn</hi> ill characted I you are</l>
                  <stage>Strazzo picks</stage>
                  <l>Neer a misfortune Sir.</l>
               </sp>
               <stage>Stephani. pocket.</stage>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Ra.</speaker>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Jupiters</hi> Mount is well form'd and colour'd</l>
                  <l>A Croſs conſpicuous, the Suns Mount well</l>
                  <l>Figur'd, and <hi>linea ſolis,</hi> without any interſection,</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Lu.</speaker>
                  <l>Your Iudgment upon that Sir?</l>
               </sp>
               <stage>Enter Antonio.</stage>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>An.</speaker>
                  <l>More Anticks yet? What Nation have we here,</l>
                  <l>Fortune flingers!</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Sir.</speaker>
                  <l>You ſhall know yours immediately.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>An.</speaker>
                  <l>Her houſe is open for theſe Mountebanks,</l>
                  <l>Cheaters, and Tumblers, that can foiſt and flatter</l>
                  <l>My Lady Gugaw; Every office open,</l>
                  <l>When Poor men that have worth and want an Alms,</l>
                  <l>May periſh ere they paſs the Porters lodge;</l>
                  <l>What are you Sir?</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Str.</speaker>
                  <l>One of the Mathematicians noble Signior.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>An.</speaker>
                  <l>Mathematicians? Mungrell,</l>
                  <l>How durſt thou take that learned name upon thee?</l>
                  <l>You are one of thoſe knaves that ſtroul the Country,</l>
                  <l>And live by picking worms out of fools fingers.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Str.</speaker>
                  <l>And ſomething out of your trunks, my reverend <hi>Cato.</hi>
                  </l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>An.</speaker>
                  <l>Buſie the raskals are, how the rogues ſtink?</l>
                  <l>I'l ſend your Regiment a Quarter-maſter.</l>
               </sp>
               <stage>Exit.</stage>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Str.</speaker>
                  <l>Now to my other gameſter.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Pa.</speaker>
                  <l>You have been—</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Pi.</speaker>
                  <l>What Sir?</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Pa.</speaker>
                  <l>In your ear—a theef.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Pi.</speaker>
                  <l>He has a Devil; good Sir not too loud.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Pa.</speaker>
                  <l>And you ſhall be—</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Pi.</speaker>
                  <l>Hang'd I warrant you.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Pa.</speaker>
                  <l>Let me ſee tother hand.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Pi.</speaker>
                  <l>Shall it ſcape with burning?</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Ra.</speaker>
                  <l>You ſhall be a Lord.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Lu.</speaker>
                  <l>A Lord.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Ra.</speaker>
                  <l>Hum, yes, a Lord infallibly.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <pb n="24" facs="tcp:153591:18"/>
                  <speaker>Pa.</speaker>
                  <l>You ſhall be a Knight Sir.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Pi.</speaker>
                  <l>Of the theeves Order, and wear my rich</l>
                  <l>Collar of hemp; is't not ſo?</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Pa.</speaker>
                  <l>An honourable Knight, upon my word.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Lu.</speaker>
                  <l>A Lord— Pray give your opinion.</l>
               </sp>
               <stage>To Longino.</stage>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Lo.</speaker>
                  <l>Your hand— you ſhall be a right worſhipfull—</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Lu.</speaker>
                  <l>One of your tribe told me I ſhould be a Lord.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Str.</speaker>
                  <l>And ſhall be us'd accordingly, Lords are tranſitory.</l>
               </sp>
               <stage>
                  <hi>Strozzo picks Luc<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>oes pocket.</hi>
               </stage>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Lo.</speaker>
                  <l>Let me ſee tother hand. I marry Sir, this line</l>
                  <l>Cleeres the doubt, and markes you right</l>
                  <l>Honourable, which makes up the tother half</l>
                  <l>Of your fortune Signior, theſe two parallell lines</l>
                  <l>From the dexter angle to be the Mount of <hi>Sol,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>Has made all plain, you muſt be a Lord.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Pi.</speaker>
                  <l>He has given you a very good reaſon Sir,</l>
                  <l>A man can have but half his fortune in one</l>
                  <l>Hand, and two right worſhipfulls makes up</l>
                  <l>One right honourable; theſe are rare fellowes,</l>
                  <l>I am predeſtinate to be a Knight,</l>
                  <l>The Stars may do their pleaſure, I obey.</l>
                  <l>This ſhould be the <hi>Caldean.</hi>
                  </l>
               </sp>
               <stage>Enter Frapolo, Castruchio he whiſpers to the reſt.</stage>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Fr.</speaker>
                  <l>I have narrowly obſerved the Caſtle, and</l>
                  <l>Where the treaſure lies, I know my Lady</l>
                  <l>In honour will entertain us this night, and</l>
                  <l>When they are aſleep wee'l take our opportunity</l>
                  <l>To rifle her Exchequer, boyes, mean time</l>
                  <l>Let me alone to humour her proud Nature;</l>
                  <l>I will ſo claw her ambition.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Lu.</speaker>
                  <l>In the interim, I'l put a queſtion to</l>
                  <l>His Aſtrology. Sir, If you pleaſe till my Lady</l>
                  <l>Return to ſatisfie her Seward, and oblige him</l>
                  <l>By your Art, one of your under Mathematicks</l>
                  <l>Has given me a Comfortable Deſtinie.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Fr.</speaker>
                  <l>Your hand. When were you born?</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <pb n="25" facs="tcp:153591:18"/>
                  <speaker>Lu.</speaker>
                  <l>I know not Sir.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Ran.</speaker>
                  <l>A Lord—</l>
               </sp>
               <stage>R. whiſpers</stage>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Fr.</speaker>
                  <l>No Matter, <hi>Venus</hi> in the Aſcendent with</l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Sol,</hi> being Lady of your ſeventh; hum, hum,</l>
                  <l>With <hi>Iupiter,</hi> deſignes you to be a Lord.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Lu.</speaker>
                  <l>They all agree; the miracle of learning!</l>
                  <l>One queſtion more I beſeeth you Sir, I</l>
                  <l>Am to ride with my Man to receive my Ladies</l>
                  <l>Rent to morrow through the Forreſt—</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Fr.</speaker>
                  <l>Go to.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Lu.</speaker>
                  <l>Now I deſire to know, whether we ſhall be</l>
                  <l>Rob'd in our return or no?</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Fr.</speaker>
                  <l>What time do you think preciſely to come</l>
                  <l>Back Sir, for we ſhould know the very minute.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Lu.</speaker>
                  <l>The Money is ready Sir, and we do purpoſe,</l>
                  <l>In your ear—</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Fr.</speaker>
                  <l>Yes, you ſhall be rob'd, ther's nothing in</l>
                  <l>Nature to prevent it.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Pi.</speaker>
                  <l>Will they kill us, and pleaſe you?</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Fr.</speaker>
                  <l>No, they ſhall not kill you, they ſhall only</l>
                  <l>Take your money, and break your pate, that</l>
                  <l>Will be all.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Pi.</speaker>
                  <l>Why let 'em rob us Sir, the loſs of our Money</l>
                  <l>Will be an evidence of our preferment, and you</l>
                  <l>May have more aſſurance to be a Lord, and</l>
                  <l>I of my Knighthood— My Lady Sir.</l>
               </sp>
               <stage>Enter Paulina.</stage>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Fr.</speaker>
                  <l>Madam, the Stars ſhine with their full beams</l>
                  <l>Upon you, Who by me their interpreter, ſalute</l>
                  <l>You with a glorious fortune: For <hi>Leo's</hi> Lord of your</l>
                  <l>Horoſcope in the right angle of heaven, and a royall</l>
                  <l>Fixt Sar calld <hi>Regulus,</hi> or the Lions hart, culminating</l>
                  <l>With him, and a naturall reception between <hi>Mars,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>And <hi>Sol</hi> Lord of the tenth, being in the firſt with</l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Mercury</hi> and <hi>Venus</hi> in the houſe of honour, beſides</l>
                  <l>A Conjunction of <hi>Iupiter</hi> and <hi>Luna</hi> in <hi>Piſces,</hi> in</l>
                  <l>The houſe of Mariage. I muſt give Iudgment.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <pb n="26" facs="tcp:153591:19"/>
                  <speaker>Pa.</speaker>
                  <l>I ſhall beſeech your cleerer language.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Fr.</speaker>
                  <l>You ſhall be Married to a Prince, it is inevitable.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Pa.</speaker>
                  <l>A Prince?</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Lu.</speaker>
                  <l>May not I come to be a Lord then?</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Pi.</speaker>
                  <l>And I a Knight?</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Pa.</speaker>
                  <l>When ſhall I ſee him?</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Fr.</speaker>
                  <l>He ſhall within few days viſit your Caſtle,</l>
                  <l>Drawn hither with the fame of your perſon,</l>
                  <l>And bravery. I need not inſtruct you to entertain</l>
                  <l>Him with State and Ceremony becoming his</l>
                  <l>Excellence, but if he Court you not into his arms,</l>
                  <l>I will renounce the Stars, and ſay there is no</l>
                  <l>Truth in Aſtrology.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Pa.</speaker>
                  <l>How my thoughts ſwel already.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Fr.</speaker>
                  <l>She has ſwallowe'd it.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Pa.</speaker>
                  <l>Give him five hundred Piſtolets.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Fr.</speaker>
                  <l>Do not wrong ſo much</l>
                  <l>One that does honour you; as I bribe not</l>
                  <l>The Stars to tell me their Decrees, I dare not</l>
                  <l>For money ſell their Secrets, and if any</l>
                  <l>That have relation to me preſume</l>
                  <l>To take a <hi>Iulio</hi>—</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Lo.</speaker>
                  <l>By no means Madam—</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Pa.</speaker>
                  <l>I like it that no Mercenary ends</l>
                  <l>Guide 'em to flatter me.</l>
               </sp>
               <stage>
                  <hi>A Drum <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ar off.</hi>
               </stage>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Lo.</speaker>
                  <l>Is not that a March?</l>
               </sp>
               <stage>Exit.</stage>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Pi.</speaker>
                  <l>If it entrench not too far upon your art,</l>
                  <l>This Prince, Sir, has a Name.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Fr.</speaker>
                  <l>And rules this Province,</l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Ferneſe</hi> is a Bachelour.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Pa.</speaker>
                  <l>The Prince of <hi>Parma?</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>My bloud refines in every vein already,</l>
                  <l>Dull heavy Souls that are content to drudge</l>
                  <l>In humble thoughts.</l>
               </sp>
               <stage>Enter Longino and whiſpers to Frapolo.</stage>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Lo.</speaker>
                  <l>I Fear we are betraid;</l>
                  <pb n="27" facs="tcp:153591:19"/>
                  <l>The Countries up and marching to the Caſtle,</l>
                  <l>We may be all ſurpriz'd let us to, horſe—</l>
               </sp>
               <stage>Exit.</stage>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Pa.</speaker>
                  <l>Deny not, Sir, this night an entertainment,</l>
                  <l>Such as my Caſtle yields, it ſha'not ſpread</l>
                  <l>To receive gueſts more welcome.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Lu.</speaker>
                  <l>A Drum Madam.</l>
               </sp>
               <stage>Exit.</stage>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Ra.</speaker>
                  <l>Muſt we not ſtay and rob the houſe to night?</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Er.</speaker>
                  <l>Madam, my art foretells I cannot be</l>
                  <l>Safe to remain here, at my return</l>
                  <l>I wo'not baulk your Caſtle, i'th' mean time</l>
                  <l>Cheriſh high thoughts, your Stars do call you Princeſs,</l>
                  <l>So kiſſing your fair hand—</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Pa.</speaker>
                  <l>Make me not ſo unhappy.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Fr.</speaker>
                  <l>There is no diſpute with Deſtinie,</l>
                  <l>I take my humble leave, away to horſe.</l>
               </sp>
               <stage>Exeunt.</stage>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Pa.</speaker>
                  <l>This more amazeth me, what danger ſhould</l>
                  <l>Provoke this haſt, if it prove their concernment,</l>
                  <l>I muſt believe they do converſe with Fate,</l>
                  <l>And truſt to them as Oracles; a Princeſs?</l>
                  <l>Was not my Soul Propheticall?</l>
               </sp>
               <stage>Enter Lucio.</stage>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Lu.</speaker>
                  <l>Madam, ſome accident hath rais'd your tenants,</l>
                  <l>They march in fury this way, in ſtrange poſtures</l>
                  <l>And Arms, as if they came to ſtorm the Caſtle.</l>
               </sp>
               <stage>Enter Piperelle.</stage>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Pi.</speaker>
                  <l>Madam, we are all undone, the Clubs are up,</l>
                  <l>Your Tenants are turn'd Rebels, and by this time</l>
                  <l>Entred the Hall; and threaten to ſurprize</l>
                  <l>I know not whom; But the <hi>Caldean,</hi> and</l>
                  <l>His troop are vaniſh'd, they foreſaw this tempeſt.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Pa.</speaker>
                  <l>What ſhould this mean?</l>
               </sp>
               <stage>Enter Countrymen armed.</stage>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>1</speaker>
                  <l>Come on you men of luſty <hi>Chine,</hi> Dear Lady</l>
                  <l>Be not affrighted, Captain of thy Guard</l>
                  <l>Am I, thy naturall Tenant, and thy Vaſſall;</l>
                  <l>Where be theſe Sunburnt <hi>Aethiopians?</hi>
                  </l>
                  <pb n="28" facs="tcp:153591:20"/>
                  <l>I wo'not leave one Canting Rogue alive.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Pa.</speaker>
                  <l>What <hi>Aethiopians,</hi> what Canting Rogues?</l>
                  <l>Do not your Clounſhips know me?</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>1</speaker>
                  <l>Know our Princeſs?</l>
                  <l>We honour thee, and riſe in thy defence;</l>
                  <l>Where be theſe theeves? we heard there were</l>
                  <l>A Regiment, that came to Cheat and Plunder.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Pa.</speaker>
                  <l>Y'are a Knot</l>
                  <l>Of knaves and fools, and ſhall repent this inſolence;</l>
                  <l>You that command in chief, good Captain <hi>Bumbard,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>May teach your Raggamuffins face about,</l>
                  <l>Was it your ſtratagem to fright my gueſts?</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>1</speaker>
                  <l>Your Uncle told us Madam, and commanded.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Pa.</speaker>
                  <l>Was it his plot? he's ſtill my enemy.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>1</speaker>
                  <l>Pard on us Madam,</l>
                  <l>We came ſimply hither to do you ſervice;</l>
                  <l>Kneel, or we ſhall all be ſtript out of our Tenements.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Pa.</speaker>
                  <l>My Uncle has abus'd you,</l>
                  <l>But this ſubmiſſion takes our anger off,</l>
                  <l>Continue dutifull to my Commands,</l>
                  <l>And you ſhall be remembred; <hi>Piperollo—</hi>
                  </l>
               </sp>
               <stage>Exit.</stage>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Pi.</speaker>
                  <l>I know the Buttery Madam; follow me,</l>
                  <l>It is my Ladies pleaſure you be drunk,</l>
                  <l>And thank her grace ye keep your Copiholds;</l>
                  <l>Dee you bring up the rear, I'l march in front.</l>
               </sp>
               <stage>Exeunt.</stage>
               <stage>Enter Antonio, Contarini.</stage>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Ant.</speaker>
                  <l>Paſſion O'me, it is to great an honour,</l>
                  <l>Refuſe a man of your high bloud and name,</l>
                  <l>That Courts her honourably? I could beat her.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Con.</speaker>
                  <l>'Tis not impoſſible at my return</l>
                  <l>To find a change. I muſt to Court agen.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Ver.</speaker>
                  <l>The horſes my Lord are ready.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Con.</speaker>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Vergerio—</hi>
                  </l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Ant.</speaker>
                  <l>What a Baggage 'tis, ſhees all for the Nunnery,</l>
                  <l>She ſha not have her will, I'l undo my ſelf</l>
                  <l>But I'l deſtroy this Modeſty; if I could</l>
                  <pb n="29" facs="tcp:153591:20"/>
                  <l>But make her proud there were ſome hope on her.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Ver.</speaker>
                  <l>My Lord you may command, but how unfit,</l>
                  <l>I am to manage this affair.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Con.</speaker>
                  <l>Thou haſt a powerfull Language, it prevail'd</l>
                  <l>On me when I firſt ſaw thee, ſince which time</l>
                  <l>I have not deſerv'd unkindly from thee, and</l>
                  <l>This truſt ſpeaks more than Common favour.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Ver.</speaker>
                  <l>Make me his advocate to <hi>Angellina?</hi>
                  </l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>An.</speaker>
                  <l>My Lord, if you can ſtill preſerve theſe thoughts</l>
                  <l>Of honour to us, leave her to my Counſell.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Con.</speaker>
                  <l>Moſt cheerfully, I am not deſperate;</l>
                  <l>This Gentleman I'l leave to wait upon her,</l>
                  <l>Who is privy to my Counſells, and affection.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>An.</speaker>
                  <l>Your Lordſhip hath found truſt in him, but that</l>
                  <l>Sha'not excuſe my care, to make her know</l>
                  <l>Her happineſs, and the Honour of our Family,</l>
                  <l>By meeting your commands. She's here.</l>
                  <stage>Enter Angellina, Franceſcina.</stage>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Franceſcina</hi> tell me, what hope of your Miſtreſs?</l>
                  <l>How does thy Counſell work? does ſhe pray leſs</l>
                  <l>Then ſhe was wont? or liſten now and then</l>
                  <l>When thou talk'ſt wantonly, does ſhe ſmile upon't?</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Fr.</speaker>
                  <l>Between our ſelves, I put her to a ſmiling</l>
                  <l>Bluſh.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Ant.</speaker>
                  <l>What ſaid ſhe, tell me on thy modeſty,</l>
                  <l>When ſhe found her dear delight, the legend</l>
                  <l>Of the Saints remov'd, and <hi>Ovids</hi> tales of</l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Jupiter</hi> put in the place?</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Fr.</speaker>
                  <l>She ſaid, that <hi>Iupiter</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>Was a moſt ſenſuall Heretick, and the ceſtus</l>
                  <l>That <hi>Venus</hi> wore was not St. <hi>Francis</hi> girdle.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Ant.</speaker>
                  <l>How did ſhe like the picture of <hi>Leander,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>Swimming the <hi>Helleſpont</hi> upon his back?</l>
                  <l>How that of <hi>Cleopatra</hi> kiſſing <hi>Antony?</hi>
                  </l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Fr.</speaker>
                  <l>She Says that Queen was none of the poor Clares,</l>
                  <pb n="30" facs="tcp:153591:21"/>
                  <l>But one bread up in black <hi>Aegyptian</hi> Darkneſs;</l>
                  <l>All I can ſay, ſhe is not deſperate,</l>
                  <l>I ſing no Anthems to her.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Ant.</speaker>
                  <l>What ſays ſhe to her dancing Maſter?</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Fr.</speaker>
                  <l>She is paſt her honor; that's a precious fellow,</l>
                  <l>She'l laugh to ſee him gamboll with his limbs,</l>
                  <l>His head flies like a Ball about the room,</l>
                  <l>You'd think he were at Tennis with it.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Ang.</speaker>
                  <l>Though in the guilt and knowledge of my own</l>
                  <l>Defects, to anſwer ſuch an honourable</l>
                  <l>Eſteem of me, I dare not yet preſume</l>
                  <l>To meet it; I ſhall want no pious thoughts</l>
                  <l>For this ſo great a bounty to a poor</l>
                  <l>Deſertleſſe Virgin.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Ant.</speaker>
                  <l>Hang your pious thoughts</l>
                  <l>And love my Lord.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Con.</speaker>
                  <l>Not for the wealth of <hi>Parma</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>Should my Cauſe force one cloud upon her face</l>
                  <l>Or put her eys to the expence of tears,</l>
                  <l>It ſhall be argument for me to hope,</l>
                  <l>If ſhe accept this youth to wait upon her,</l>
                  <l>Who may in ſome auſpicious hour, prepare me</l>
                  <l>A gentle ſeat within her heart, mean time</l>
                  <l>I leave upon your Virgin lip the faith,</l>
                  <l>Of your true Servant Lady.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Ant.</speaker>
                  <l>I'l attend you</l>
                  <l>To horſe my Lord.</l>
               </sp>
               <stage>Exeunt.</stage>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Ang.</speaker>
                  <l>Poor miſerable maid,</l>
                  <l>Faln now beneath the pity of thy ſelf;</l>
                  <l>My heart, on which ſo late a flame of Heaven</l>
                  <l>Stream'd comfort in my holy reſolutions,</l>
                  <l>Is fil'd with love, but not of <hi>Contarini,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>Whoſe paſſion may deſerve anothers welcome.</l>
                  <l>I prethee <hi>Franceſcina</hi> take thy Lute</l>
                  <l>And let me hear thy voice.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Fr.</speaker>
                  <l>I can ſing <hi>Venus</hi> and <hi>Adonis</hi> to you.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <pb n="31" facs="tcp:153591:21"/>
                  <speaker>Ang.</speaker>
                  <l>Any thing.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Fr.</speaker>
                  <l>Or will you hear the pleaſant Dity</l>
                  <l>How fair <hi>Caliſto</hi> firſt became a Nunne.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Ang.</speaker>
                  <l>I prethee do not name a Nun, the flame</l>
                  <l>That I feel here deſerves no Veſtall name.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Fr.</speaker>
                  <l>I'l do my beſt to fit you,</l>
                  <l>Ther's no ſuch tool in nature as a Chambermaid</l>
                  <l>To work upon her Miſtreſs.</l>
               </sp>
               <stage>Exeunt.</stage>
            </div>
            <div n="4" type="act">
               <head>ACT IIII.</head>
               <stage>Enter Frapolo, Longino, Strozzo, Pacheco, with the reſt.</stage>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Fr.</speaker>
                  <l>IT was a fatall buſineſs to loſe ſuch</l>
                  <l>An opportunity.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Lo.</speaker>
                  <l>My Lady was wound up ſo rarely.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Str.</speaker>
                  <l>We were betraid for certain; 'twas high</l>
                  <l>Time to ſcud, and get into our Territories;</l>
                  <l>Now we are ſafe in our Grots, ſecure as</l>
                  <l>The <hi>Minotaur,</hi> and keep the clew of our</l>
                  <l>Own Labyrinths.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Pa.</speaker>
                  <l>We loſt a rare deſign, but in my opinion,</l>
                  <l>Tis better ſcouting here with our heads on,</l>
                  <l>Than have 'em carryed in by Clowns at the Court rate.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Fr.</speaker>
                  <l>The ignorant Rogues would nere ha 'ſold</l>
                  <l>Them to their worth.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Lo.</speaker>
                  <l>And they dare as ſoon venter upon Hell,</l>
                  <l>As Shoot their heads into this Furnace.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Fr.</speaker>
                  <l>But this <hi>Claridiana</hi> ſha'not ſcape ſo,</l>
                  <l>I am reſolv'd to viſit her again, and I am</l>
                  <l>Glad I prepar'd another expectation, theſe</l>
                  <l>Difficulties ſhall make our next attempt</l>
                  <l>More glorious.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <pb n="32" facs="tcp:153591:22"/>
                  <speaker>Lo.</speaker>
                  <l>Thoſe ſhapes will conjure up the Bores again.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>St.</speaker>
                  <l>She does expect the <hi>Caldean.</hi>
                  </l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Fr.</speaker>
                  <l>Hang the <hi>Caldean.</hi> I have a new device</l>
                  <l>Shall ſcoure the Caſtle, and make Dame</l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Guinever</hi> with all her pride, thank and adore</l>
                  <l>The invention.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Lo.</speaker>
                  <l>How dear <hi>Frapolo?</hi> how?</l>
               </sp>
               <stage>Whooting within.</stage>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Fr.</speaker>
                  <l>Scout and diſcover, <hi>Strozzo.</hi>
                  </l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Str.</speaker>
                  <l>I ſee but two men coming down the Hill.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Fr.</speaker>
                  <l>Cannot their worſhips travell with leſs noiſe?</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Lo.</speaker>
                  <l>They durſt not be ſo confident without a number,</l>
                  <l>'Tis good to be ſecure, the noiſe approaches,</l>
                  <l>Lets to our ſhells.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Fr.</speaker>
                  <l>Do you lie perdue ſtill.</l>
               </sp>
               <stage>They retire.</stage>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Pa.</speaker>
                  <l>I do not like their confidence, theſe may be</l>
                  <l>The enemies ſcouts, lets non engage to ſoon</l>
                  <l>For fear of a reſerve. The State has threatned</l>
                  <l>To ſend their Vermin forth.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Fr.</speaker>
                  <l>Obſcure: cloſe, cloſe.</l>
               </sp>
               <stage>Enter Lucio, Piperollo.</stage>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Lu.</speaker>
                  <l>What doſt thou mean?</l>
                  <l>Thou haſt a mind to be rob'd indeed.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Pi.</speaker>
                  <l>I would have art maintain'd in reputation,</l>
                  <l>You know my Lady is to be a Princeſs,</l>
                  <l>And you muſt be a Lord, and I be dubbed,</l>
                  <l>But if we be not rob'd, I know not how</l>
                  <l>To truſt the Mathematicks or the Stars;</l>
                  <l>I am afraid all the <hi>Bandits</hi> are hang'd,</l>
                  <l>A thouſand Piſtols ſhould not fear to travell.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Lu</speaker>
                  <l>It is not wiſdom to proclaim our charge,</l>
                  <l>Though I could be content to be a Lord,</l>
                  <l>I am not over hearty, theeves are theeves,</l>
                  <l>And life is precious, prethee lets make haſt.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Pi.</speaker>
                  <l>Illo ho ho,</l>
                  <l>Think upon your honour, are there no Gentlemen?</l>
                  <l>No wanting Gentlemen that know how to ſpend</l>
                  <pb n="33" facs="tcp:153591:22"/>
                  <l>A quantity of Gold?</l>
                  <l>There is no thief in Nature.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Str.</speaker>
                  <l>The Gentleman</l>
                  <l>Is very merry, they that mean well, and</l>
                  <l>Have their wits about 'em, do not uſe</l>
                  <l>To call upon our Tribe. This is a plot,</l>
                  <l>A very plot, and yet the Coaſt is cleer,</l>
                  <l>Now I may reach their voice.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Pi.</speaker>
                  <l>It wo'not be, was ever men diſtreſt ſo?</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Lu.</speaker>
                  <l>Come we are well yet <hi>Piperollo,</hi> if</l>
                  <l>The Stars Decree our robbery, it will follow.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Pi.</speaker>
                  <l>I pray Sir lets ſit down here, as you hope to</l>
                  <l>Be a Lord, we muſt do our endeavour and help</l>
                  <l>The Fates. Do but hear reaſon Sir.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Str.</speaker>
                  <l>'Tis my proud Madams Steward, and our quondam</l>
                  <l>Fellow thief; they were told their fortunes</l>
                  <l>To be rob'd; Here had been a purchaſe loſt</l>
                  <l>If I had not lain perdue. You ſhall be</l>
                  <l>Diſpatcht preſently, never fear it.</l>
               </sp>
               <stage>He Whiſtles.</stage>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Lu</speaker>
                  <l>What's that? I do not like that tune.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Pi.</speaker>
                  <l>Hum, I am not in love with that Quailpipe.</l>
                  <l>I could dwindle, but that I have a ſtrong</l>
                  <l>Faith in the Mathematicks. Theeves and be</l>
                  <l>Thy Will.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Lu.</speaker>
                  <l>If they ſhould cut our throats now—this is</l>
                  <l>Your folly; would I were off.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Pi.</speaker>
                  <l>Would I were a Knight in an embroidered</l>
                  <l>Diſh clout. Have a good heart Sir, ther's</l>
                  <l>No more to be ſaid in't, let the Stars take</l>
                  <l>Their courſe, 'tis my Ladies money—and if</l>
                  <l>We be rob'd, we are ſo much the neerer to preferment.</l>
               </sp>
               <stage>Enter Frapolo and the reſt.</stage>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Lu.</speaker>
                  <l>Ah ſweet Gentlemen take but the Money—</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Pi.</speaker>
                  <l>'Tis ready told; nay, nay, we are friends;</l>
                  <l>Give us but a Mote under your hands for</l>
                  <l>My Ladies ſatisfaction, that you have received</l>
                  <l>It Gentlemen.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <pb n="34" facs="tcp:153591:23"/>
                  <speaker>Lu.</speaker>
                  <l>You need not trouble your ſelves to tell it Gentle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men,</l>
                  <l>It is all right.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Lo.</speaker>
                  <l>So, ſo, wee'l take your words.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Pi.</speaker>
                  <l>I ſhould know that vizard, the garments</l>
                  <l>That you wear too I have ſeen Old acquaintance?</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Fr.</speaker>
                  <l>Does he know you? cut his throat.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Pi.</speaker>
                  <l>No Sir, I do not know him, nor any man, nor</l>
                  <l>My ſelf, I was not once rob'd before, neither</l>
                  <l>Did I help any man to rob my own Father and Mother;</l>
                  <l>I knew no Cedar cheſt I, I diſclaim it, nor</l>
                  <l>Was any man that I know left bound for the</l>
                  <l>Money; ye are all honeſt Gentlemen,</l>
                  <l>And I congratulate our good fortune, that you</l>
                  <l>Came ſo luckily in the very nick, we had carried</l>
                  <l>Home the money elſe in good ſadneſs— Sir,</l>
                  <l>We are made for ever—rare Mathematicians!</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Fr.</speaker>
                  <l>What's that you talk ſirra of Mathematicians?</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Pi.</speaker>
                  <l>It pleaſed ſome of the learned tribe to viſit</l>
                  <l>My Lady not long ſince, but they are well I</l>
                  <l>Hope, they told us we ſhould be rob'd, and</l>
                  <l>'Tis done; bleſſed <hi>Caldean!</hi>
                  </l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Fr.</speaker>
                  <l>What became on 'em?</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Pi.</speaker>
                  <l>They ſcap'd a ſcouring, for my Ladies Cinicall</l>
                  <l>Uncle, in meer malice to learning, rais'd</l>
                  <l>The Towns upon em, perſwading the hobbinolls</l>
                  <l>They came to rob the houſe; but honored</l>
                  <l>Be the Stars, they brought 'em off at the</l>
                  <l>Back gate.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Fr.</speaker>
                  <l>They ſeem honeſt fellows, let 'em live, and Paſs.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Lu.</speaker>
                  <l>We humbly thank you Gentlemen, come <hi>Piperollo.</hi>
                  </l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Pi.</speaker>
                  <l>And yet, now I remember, there wants a</l>
                  <l>Circumſtance, my pate is not broke yet,</l>
                  <l>That was a Clauſe the <hi>Caldean</hi> was a little</l>
                  <l>Out.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <pb n="35" facs="tcp:153591:23"/>
                  <speaker>Fr.</speaker>
                  <l>I had forgot, will you be prating ſirra?</l>
               </sp>
               <stage>Fr. breaks his head.</stage>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Pi.</speaker>
                  <l>Now tis done, I thank you, dear Gentlemen,</l>
                  <l>I thank you, go forth and be a Knight;</l>
                  <l>Mathematician I adore thee, it bleeds;</l>
                  <l>Where are you Sir? all is compleat, and my</l>
                  <l>Head is broke according to prophecie. Oh</l>
                  <l>Admirable <hi>Caldean!</hi>
                  </l>
               </sp>
               <stage>Exeunt.</stage>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Lo.</speaker>
                  <l>We have not loſt all my Ladies money, but</l>
                  <l>To your plot <hi>Frapolo.</hi>
                  </l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Fr.</speaker>
                  <l>This hath ripend it, and I appear a</l>
                  <l>Blazing Star already.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Str.</speaker>
                  <l>What's the myſtery?</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Fr.</speaker>
                  <l>You know I am your Prince.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Lo.</speaker>
                  <l>'Tis Acknowledged.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Fr.</speaker>
                  <l>We will in State viſit the proud <hi>Paulina,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>I am the Prince <hi>Farneſe,</hi> and you</l>
                  <l>Are all my Lords and privy Counſellors</l>
                  <l>Bear up for honour of your Prince.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Lo.</speaker>
                  <l>I apprehend it, 'tis a moſt rare deſign,</l>
                  <l>She will be mad to meet it.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Pa.</speaker>
                  <l>Will you marry her?</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Fr.</speaker>
                  <l>I cannot tell, there may be a neceſſity,</l>
                  <l>But when I ha' the wench, her Plate and Jewels,</l>
                  <l>And other ſums, I have caſt already whither.</l>
                  <l>We muſt tranſport our ſelves—wee'l divide all.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Lo.</speaker>
                  <l>And the wench too?</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Fr.</speaker>
                  <l>No not the wench, untill I caſt the Concubine;</l>
                  <l>Remember who I am, the choice of fleſh</l>
                  <l>Is my prerogative; no murmuring,</l>
                  <l>You ſhall provide our Robes.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Str.</speaker>
                  <l>Now we are rogues to purpoſe.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Fr.</speaker>
                  <l>I am your Prince, and the worſt theef</l>
                  <l>A States-mans.</l>
               </sp>
               <stage>
                  <hi>Omnes</hi> A Prince, A Prince.</stage>
               <stage>Exeunt.</stage>
               <stage>Enter Angellina, and Franceſcina.</stage>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Ang.</speaker>
                  <l>Where is <hi>Vergerio?</hi>
                  </l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <pb n="36" facs="tcp:153591:24"/>
                  <speaker>Fr.</speaker>
                  <l>I know not Madam.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Ang.</speaker>
                  <l>Madam? I prethee leave that folly,</l>
                  <l>I am no Lady, call me <hi>Angellina.</hi>
                  </l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Fr.</speaker>
                  <l>I'l call you Madam, 'tis a name in faſhion,</l>
                  <l>What do you want to juſtifie that title?</l>
                  <l>Have you not Beauty, Jewels, Gold at pleaſure?</l>
                  <l>Fine Cloathes, high Food, and men as motley, as</l>
                  <l>The Ambaſſadors to wait? does not your Uncle</l>
                  <l>Allow you all that can make up a Lady?</l>
                  <l>Pardon my boldneſs Madam, I beſeech you.</l>
               </sp>
               <stage>Enter two Gentlewomen.</stage>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Ang.</speaker>
                  <l>What are theſe?</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Fr.</speaker>
                  <l>The Gentlewomen were commended, Madam,</l>
                  <l>Moſt excellent in their Art about great Ladies;</l>
                  <l>And come to tender you their humble ſervice.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>1</speaker>
                  <l>Moſt proud if you accept our duties Madam.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Fr.</speaker>
                  <l>Look you, they're proud already, they have no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing</l>
                  <l>But their trade to live on; ſhe with the face</l>
                  <l>Spotted with <hi>Ermins,</hi> hath been late in <hi>France,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>And knows the mode to a Mathematicall point,</l>
                  <l>She has the theory of Song, but loſt</l>
                  <l>The practick part by ſitting up a nights;</l>
                  <l>She danceth ſtill, can talk in ſeverall languages,</l>
                  <l>And has the art of every game, to inſtruct</l>
                  <l>A novice Lady—</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Ang.</speaker>
                  <l>To loſe time.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Fr.</speaker>
                  <l>And what</l>
                  <l>Age, do you think the other Gentlewoman</l>
                  <l>Carries? that ſimpers ſo? the miracle</l>
                  <l>Of Painting! ſhe preſents ſcarce five and twenty,</l>
                  <l>But if you credit Church Records, ſhe numbers</l>
                  <l>But five ſhort of threeſcore, <hi>Medea</hi> had</l>
                  <l>No charmes like her, to preſerve youth, and beauty;</l>
                  <l>She hath the art of making eys, new hair,</l>
                  <l>And Ivory teeth, hath skill in making fruitfull,</l>
                  <l>And is an excellent Midwife; ſhe hath cur'd</l>
                  <pb n="37" facs="tcp:153591:24"/>
                  <l>A man that had no Noſe, and a Court-Lady</l>
                  <l>That had no Tongue.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Ang.</speaker>
                  <l>Theſe are tranſcendent qualities;</l>
                  <l>Since tis my Uncles pleaſure, they may wait,</l>
                  <l>But not to ſerve me.</l>
               </sp>
               <stage>One knocks.</stage>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Fr.</speaker>
                  <l>Who's that knocks ſo modeſtly?</l>
                  <l>'Tis not your Dancing-Maſter, nor the Doctor,</l>
                  <l>They have more confidence.</l>
                  <l>'Tis the Parſons Nephew, come from the Univerſity,</l>
                  <l>Some ſay a pretty Schollar, and a wit;</l>
                  <l>Hath an Ambition to kiſs your hand</l>
                  <l>And tender his firſt fruits.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Ang.</speaker>
                  <l>What's that?</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Fr.</speaker>
                  <l>Some Poetry.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>1</speaker>
                  <l>By any means Madam, you muſt be flatter'd,</l>
                  <l>Great Ladies cannot live els.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Ang.</speaker>
                  <l>Let him enter.</l>
               </sp>
               <stage>Enter Schollar.</stage>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Sch</speaker>
                  <l>Darling of beauty, faireſt <hi>Angellina,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>Thus low the Muſes bow, and ſend by me</l>
                  <l>An abſtract of your ſelf; oh make the Paper</l>
                  <l>More white by kiſſing your fair hand, and with</l>
                  <l>Your breath, like a ſoft Weſtern gale, perfume</l>
                  <l>Theſe lines created in your praiſe.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Ang.</speaker>
                  <l>What's heer?— I am</l>
                  <l>A ſtranger to you Sir, and to your language,</l>
                  <l>Theſe words have no relation to me;</l>
                  <l>I pity men of your high fancy, ſhould</l>
                  <l>Diſhonour their own names, by forming ſuch</l>
                  <l>Prodigious ſhapes of beauty in our ſex.</l>
                  <l>If I were really what you would commend,</l>
                  <l>Mankind would flie me; get a Painter Sir,</l>
                  <l>And when he has wrought a woman by your fancy,</l>
                  <l>See if you know her again; were it not fine,</l>
                  <l>If you ſhould ſee your Miſtreſs without hair?</l>
                  <l>Dreſt only with thoſe glittering beams you talk of?</l>
                  <l>Two Suns inſtead of Eys, and they not melt</l>
                  <l>The forhead made of Snow; no Cheeks, but two</l>
                  <pb n="38" facs="tcp:153591:25"/>
                  <l>Roſes inoculated upon a Lillie?</l>
                  <l>Between, a pendent Alablaſter Noſe?</l>
                  <l>Her Lips cut out of Corall, and no Teeth,</l>
                  <l>But Strings of Pearl; Her Tongue a Nightingales;</l>
                  <l>Her chin a rump of Ivory; and ſo forth?</l>
                  <l>Would not this ſtrange <hi>Chimera</hi> fright your ſelf?</l>
                  <l>And yet you take the boldneſs to preſent us,</l>
                  <l>And think we muſt applaud, and thank you for</l>
                  <l>Our ſelves made Monſters by your art; no more</l>
                  <l>Of this for ſhame; loſe not your time and honour</l>
                  <l>In this fantaſtick Idoll; you will ſay,</l>
                  <l>The world is peeviſh, and not kind to virtue;</l>
                  <l>Give him ten Piſtolets to cure his poverty,</l>
                  <l>There are good ſeeds in him and they may</l>
                  <l>Grow with ſome Cheriſhing.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Sch.</speaker>
                  <l>You are enough</l>
                  <l>To vindicate your Sex, I ſhall not bluſh</l>
                  <l>To write your ſtory.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Fr.</speaker>
                  <l>You ſhall owe me Sir</l>
                  <l>An Anagram, and a Poeſy too for</l>
                  <l>My next Ring.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Sch.</speaker>
                  <l>You ſhall command my faculty,</l>
                  <l>My deareſt <hi>Abigall</hi>
                  </l>
               </sp>
               <stage>Exit.</stage>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Fr.</speaker>
                  <l>Thank you ſweet Sir <hi>Roger.</hi>
                  </l>
               </sp>
               <stage>Enter four Citizens.</stage>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>1</speaker>
                  <l>Is her Ladiſhip at leaſure?</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Ang.</speaker>
                  <l>What are theſe?</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>2</speaker>
                  <l>We are humble ſutes Madam for your Favour.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Ang.</speaker>
                  <l>Speak your requeſt.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>1</speaker>
                  <l>I am a Tailor Madam</l>
                  <l>That holds intelligence with forein Courts</l>
                  <l>To furniſh Ladies with new Faſhions.</l>
                  <l>And I have patterns of the ſtrangeſt ſhapes</l>
                  <l>That ever Ladies long'd for.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Ang.</speaker>
                  <l>I believe it.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>2</speaker>
                  <l>I have the ambition to own the name</l>
                  <pb n="39" facs="tcp:153591:25"/>
                  <l>Of your Perfumer Madam.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>3</speaker>
                  <l>I your Jeweller;</l>
                  <l>What think you of that Carcanet ſweet Madam?</l>
                  <l>The Pearls are Orient, I have a Diamond</l>
                  <l>The Sultan gave one of his Concubines,</l>
                  <l>It weighes —20 caracts, if it pleaſe you Madam,</l>
                  <l>To wear it in the Court, and I'l attend</l>
                  <l>Your Ladiſhip ſix moneths hence to pay me for't;</l>
                  <l>I know your Uncle Madam.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Ang.</speaker>
                  <l>This is his plot.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Fr.</speaker>
                  <l>By all means take it.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Ang.</speaker>
                  <l>Excuſe me; what are you? ſpeak your deſire.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>4</speaker>
                  <l>I would preſent you Madam with a pair</l>
                  <l>Of curious Spurs.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Ang.</speaker>
                  <l>For what uſe prethee?</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>4</speaker>
                  <l>For what you pleaſe, I ſee all men of trade</l>
                  <l>Apply themſelves to gain relation to you,</l>
                  <l>And I would be your Spurrier.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Ang.</speaker>
                  <l>Do Ladies wear Spurs my friend?</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>4</speaker>
                  <l>They may in time, who knows what may be done,</l>
                  <l>If one great Lady would begin, they ride</l>
                  <l>Like men already; 'tis all one to me,</l>
                  <l>So I may have the Credit of your name,</l>
                  <l>And privilege to ſwell above my neighbors.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Ang.</speaker>
                  <l>When I ſtand, Gentlemen, in need of your</l>
                  <l>Profeſſions, I'l ſend for you, i'th' mean time</l>
                  <l>You ſhall need no Solicitour.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Omnes.</speaker>
                  <l>Your Servants.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>4</speaker>
                  <l>Buy a Spur.</l>
               </sp>
               <stage>Exeunt.</stage>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Ang.</speaker>
                  <l>I prethee let me not be troubled with</l>
                  <l>This kind of People <hi>Franceſcina;</hi> Ladies</l>
                  <l>Have a fine time, if they be all thus viſited.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Fr.</speaker>
                  <l>You are rude and ſawcy fellows to intrude</l>
                  <l>So far without my Ladies licence.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Ang.</speaker>
                  <l>What makes thee ſo impatient? will they not</l>
                  <l>Be gone?</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <pb n="40" facs="tcp:153591:26"/>
                  <speaker>Fr.</speaker>
                  <l>Gone? here's a new regiment is preſſing forward</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Ang.</speaker>
                  <l>What are they?</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Fr.</speaker>
                  <l>Beggers.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Ang.</speaker>
                  <l>How?</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Fr.</speaker>
                  <l>And tell me I abuſe your Charity,</l>
                  <l>To keep off their Petitions; we muſt have</l>
                  <l>A Court-du-guard, I think, and Centries plac'd</l>
                  <l>At every dore.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Ang.</speaker>
                  <l>I prethee let 'em enter.</l>
               </sp>
               <stage>Enter three Petitioners.</stage>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Fr.</speaker>
                  <l>The room will not be ſweet again this three days;</l>
                  <l>But if it be your pleaſure—know your diſtance.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Ang.</speaker>
                  <l>The blind, and lame, what's your condition Sir?</l>
                  <l>1 As miſerable Madam as the Sea,</l>
                  <l>That ſwallow'd all my wealth, can make a man,</l>
                  <l>That once commanded thouſands, I bluſh to beg</l>
                  <l>But Nature too impatient of ſterving</l>
                  <l>Compels me to this boldneſs, you may ſoon</l>
                  <l>Peruſe my tragick ſtory there.</l>
               </sp>
               <stage>Gives a Paper.</stage>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Ang.</speaker>
                  <l>Good old man!</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Fr.</speaker>
                  <l>What is his loſs to you?</l>
                  <l>2 My Petition too;</l>
                  <l>A poor blind man, that hath loſt more by fire</l>
                  <l>Than his eſtate valued a thouſand times;</l>
                  <l>And 'tis but equall, fire ſhould ſpoil my eys,</l>
                  <l>That raviſh'd me of all, was precious to 'em,</l>
                  <l>A wife and pretty Children.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Ang.</speaker>
                  <l>Burn'd?</l>
                  <l>2 All burn'd;</l>
                  <l>And what my eys cannot afford their memory</l>
                  <l>My poor heart weeps in bloud.</l>
                  <l>3 I am a Souldier</l>
                  <l>That in my Countries ſervice loſt my limbs;</l>
                  <l>I've had more lead in bullets taken from me</l>
                  <l>Than would repair ſome Steeple.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Fr.</speaker>
                  <l>Ring the bells,</l>
                  <pb n="41" facs="tcp:153591:26"/>
                  <l>That was a loud one!</l>
                  <l>3 I have given wounds have kil'd the lookers on</l>
                  <l>With horror of their gaping, and have march'd</l>
                  <l>Ten miles a day thus deep —</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Fr.</speaker>
                  <l>In dirt?</l>
                  <l>3 In blood.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Fr.</speaker>
                  <l>Upon thoſe wooden leggs?</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>An.</speaker>
                  <l>Poor ſouls! I pitty 'em, here honeſt men,</l>
                  <l>Divide this bag, and pray for my good Uncle.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Omnes.</speaker>
                  <l>Bleſſings on you, Madam.</l>
                  <l>2. Equall diviſion, come.</l>
                  <l>1. Stay, in the firſt place, I brought you hither,</l>
                  <l>Therefore my part is moſt conſiderable.</l>
                  <l>3. I'l have no Prerogative.</l>
                  <l>2. Nor I.</l>
                  <l>1. But I will.</l>
                  <l>Do not I know you both for cheating Raſcals?</l>
                  <l>Thus are good meanings cozen'd, and you ſha'not</l>
                  <l>Loſe your reward; ſend for ſome Officers.</l>
                  <l>2, 3. We are betraid.</l>
               </sp>
               <stage>
                  <hi>Ex.</hi> 2, 3.</stage>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Ant.</speaker>
                  <l>My Uncle.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Ant.</speaker>
                  <l>They have found their eyes and leggs again,</l>
                  <l>Neece I obſerve your Charity, but you ſee not</l>
                  <l>The inſide of theſe things, and I did mean</l>
                  <l>And hope theſe ſums might ſerve your ſelf;</l>
                  <l>Some Ladies would have conſidered</l>
                  <l>A new Gown and trinkets; <hi>Franceſcina,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>I ſee little amendment, ſhe'l undo me</l>
                  <l>In pious uſes.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Fr.</speaker>
                  <l>She has entertain'd theſe Gentlewomen.</l>
                  <stage>Enter Vergerio.</stage>
                  <l>And that young Gentleman does good upon her.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>An.</speaker>
                  <l>I like it well, he's carefull of my Lord,</l>
                  <l>And if ſhe meet his honorable treaty,</l>
                  <l>She may learn Pride at Court, ſhould our Art fail.</l>
                  <l>She ſmiles — I wo'not interrupt 'em.</l>
               </sp>
               <stage>
                  <pb n="42" facs="tcp:153591:27"/>
                  <hi>Enter Giovanni.</hi>
               </stage>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Gio.</speaker>
                  <l>My Lady entreats the preſence of her Siſter.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>An.</speaker>
                  <l>Do's ſhe entreat? Yes, you may viſit her</l>
                  <l>Sir if you pleaſe, I'l truſt her to your conduct.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Ver.</speaker>
                  <l>'Tis my ambition to attend her.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>An.</speaker>
                  <l>Hark you,</l>
                  <l>Remember who you are, and carry things</l>
                  <l>For the credit of my heir, and one that muſt be</l>
                  <l>Right Honourable ſhortly, if I hear</l>
                  <l>Thou flout'ſt her, thou ſha't have another Gown</l>
                  <l>And Petticoat embroider'd, or but beat her</l>
                  <l>And put me to a penſion; fare you well,</l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Franteſcina</hi> wait, wait all upon your Miſtreſs.</l>
               </sp>
               <stage>Exeunt.</stage>
               <stage>Enter Paulina.</stage>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Pa.</speaker>
                  <l>No news yet of the Prince? he fill'd my dreams</l>
                  <l>Laſt night, it was a golden glorious ſlumber;</l>
                  <l>Me-thought we both were led into a Temple,</l>
                  <l>Where all our rites of Mariage were perform'd</l>
                  <l>In the preſence of a thouſand Angel-<hi>Cupids.</hi>
                  </l>
               </sp>
               <stage>Enter Piperollo, and ſtumbles.</stage>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Pi.</speaker>
                  <l>'Twas my devotion, Madam, to preſent you</l>
                  <l>The News, I could not break my neck upon</l>
                  <l>A better cauſe.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Pa.</speaker>
                  <l>Is the Prince come?</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Pi.</speaker>
                  <l>The Prince is at your ſervice; though I ſlipt</l>
                  <l>At Chamber door, it is my happineſs</l>
                  <l>To be the firſt Meſſenger.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Pa.</speaker>
                  <l>Of what?</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Pi.</speaker>
                  <l>I deſire no reward Madam, 'tis ſufficient</l>
                  <l>I know what will become of us all, you</l>
                  <l>Remember the <hi>Caldean;</hi> all has happen'd,</l>
                  <l>I thank Aſtrology.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Pa.</speaker>
                  <l>For what?</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Pi.</speaker>
                  <l>Your money is gone, your rents have been recei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved,</l>
                  <l>And my head broke to purpoſe; things are viſible.</l>
                  <stage>
                     <pb n="43" facs="tcp:153591:27"/>
                     <hi>Enter Lucio.</hi>
                  </stage>
                  <l>My Maſter can confirm it.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Pa.</speaker>
                  <l>What's this prodigie?</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Lu.</speaker>
                  <l>Madam 'tis done, we have been rob'd.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Pa.</speaker>
                  <l>How?</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Lu.</speaker>
                  <l>As the <hi>Caldean</hi> and the Stars would have it,</l>
                  <l>Juſt to a minute.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Pi.</speaker>
                  <l>Rare Mathematician!</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Pa.</speaker>
                  <l>I'l hang you both,</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Pi.</speaker>
                  <l>You may, and be no Princeſs.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Pa.</speaker>
                  <l>Did he foretell this loſs?</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Pi.</speaker>
                  <l>Is my pate broken? Do I live, and hope</l>
                  <l>To kneel, and ſay, If pleaſe your Grace, to call</l>
                  <l>Him Lord, and anſwer to a Knight? — we're made.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Pa.</speaker>
                  <l>Be at a diſtance,</l>
                  <l>If there be truth in the <hi>Caldeans</hi> Art,</l>
                  <l>Theſe inconſiderable loſſes are</l>
                  <l>A new preſage of my approaching greatneſs.</l>
               </sp>
               <stage>
                  <hi>Enter Stephanio, and Longino, diſguiz<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>d.</hi>
               </stage>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>St.</speaker>
                  <l>One from the Prince.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Lo.</speaker>
                  <l>His Highneſs <hi>Farneſe,</hi> Madam, greets your</l>
                  <l>Ladiſhip, and int<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>nds to be your Gueſt this night,</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Pa.</speaker>
                  <l>It will be an honour</l>
                  <l>My life muſt ow him duty for.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Pi.</speaker>
                  <l>Do not you feel a Lordſhip creep up</l>
                  <l>By your ſhort ribs?</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Lo.</speaker>
                  <l>His Grace is not far off.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Pa.</speaker>
                  <l>Preſent the humble duty of his handmaid,</l>
                  <l>And ſay my Caſtle droops til it receive him;</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Lo.</speaker>
                  <l>I ſhall Madam.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Pa.</speaker>
                  <l>We muſt prepare to meet and entertain him;</l>
                  <l>All things have been Prophetical.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Pi.</speaker>
                  <l>My very good Lord.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Lu.</speaker>
                  <l>Right Worſhipfull <hi>Piperollo.</hi>
                  </l>
               </sp>
               <stage>Exeunt.</stage>
               <stage>Enter Vergerio, Angellina, Servants aloof.</stage>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Ver.</speaker>
                  <l>In my pity</l>
                  <pb n="44" facs="tcp:153591:28"/>
                  <l>That ſo much innocence ſhould not be loſt</l>
                  <l>On faithleſs <hi>Contarini,</hi> I have landed</l>
                  <l>Upon your knowledge this unhappy ſecret.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Ang.</speaker>
                  <l>Promis'd his faith to another? twas ill done,</l>
                  <l>To work my Uncle, and deſtroy my thoughts</l>
                  <l>Of a religious life.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Ve.</speaker>
                  <l>You may collect</l>
                  <l>Thoſe pure deſires again,</l>
                  <l>Heaven will be ſoon invited, and a ſecond</l>
                  <l>Reſolve confirm that happineſs.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Ang.</speaker>
                  <l>May we not,</l>
                  <l>Without ſo ſtrict forſaking of the world,</l>
                  <l>Be capable of bleſſing, and meet heaven</l>
                  <l>At laſt, though erring Nature guide ſometime</l>
                  <l>Out of the neareſt way?</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Ver.</speaker>
                  <l>Yes <hi>Angellina.</hi>
                  </l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>An.</speaker>
                  <l>I muſt be no Votary,</l>
                  <l>But when you turn a Fryer then.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Ver.</speaker>
                  <l>How Lady?</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>An.</speaker>
                  <l>Sir you have merited for this diſcovery</l>
                  <l>All that I am to ſerve you, and unleſs</l>
                  <l>You help me in this Labyrinth, I muſt</l>
                  <l>Live in deſpair of Freedom.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Ver.</speaker>
                  <l>Any ſervice;</l>
                  <l>There's ſo much ſweetneſs in you, I could lay</l>
                  <l>My life a Sacrifice, be confident</l>
                  <l>I muſt be left of heaven, when I forſake you.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>An.</speaker>
                  <l>And I dare truſt your Virtue with a ſecret</l>
                  <l>I have not told my Ghoſtly Father.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Fr.</speaker>
                  <l>I know not what opinion my Lord has</l>
                  <l>of his ſmooth Advocate, but I ſhould gather</l>
                  <l>By Symptomes of my Miſtreſs, ſhe is ſick</l>
                  <l>Of the younger Gentleman.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Ver.</speaker>
                  <l>I dare not hope</l>
                  <l>This bleſſing, 'tis an honour plac'd on me</l>
                  <l>That has no value, I am a ſtranger,</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>An.</speaker>
                  <l>You are no ſtranger here.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <pb n="45" facs="tcp:153591:28"/>
                  <speaker>Ver.</speaker>
                  <l>Your Uncle too—</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Ang.</speaker>
                  <l>May erre in his election.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Ver.</speaker>
                  <l>But his anger—</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Ang.</speaker>
                  <l>My prayer and tears may ſoften.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Ver.</speaker>
                  <l>Do not dreſs</l>
                  <l>Your eys with ſorrow <hi>Angellina,</hi> this</l>
                  <l>Too gracious an influence upon</l>
                  <l>Your ſervant muſt command my utmoſt duty.</l>
                  <l>Upon this white hand I breath out my heart,</l>
                  <l>And when I pay affection to another</l>
                  <l>Miſtreſs, in your revenge, her beauty blaſt me!</l>
                  <l>But we may be obſerv'd.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Ang.</speaker>
                  <l>Be all my guide.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Ver.</speaker>
                  <l>This muſt be manag'd wiſely, we are loſt els.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Ang.</speaker>
                  <l>We are now arriv'd the Caſtle <hi>Franceſcina.</hi>
                  </l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Fr.</speaker>
                  <l>We attend.</l>
               </sp>
               <stage>Exeunt.</stage>
               <stage>Enter Prince Farneſe, Contarini.</stage>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Fa.</speaker>
                  <l>I am <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>ſcur'd ſufficiently.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Con.</speaker>
                  <l>My life on't.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Fa.</speaker>
                  <l>Here are great preparations, and the people</l>
                  <l>Flock as to ſee ſome triumph, this <hi>Paulina</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>Will be ador'd i'th' Country.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Con.</speaker>
                  <l>But her Siſter,</l>
                  <l>With an extreme of ſweetneſs and humility</l>
                  <l>Will take the wonder off, ſhe ſo tranſcends.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Fa.</speaker>
                  <l>Your words fall from you,</l>
                  <l>I have obſervd my Lord, with too much paſſion;</l>
                  <l>She's but a woman, and may be no miracle,</l>
                  <l>When a clear eye is Judge.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Con.</speaker>
                  <l>Sir I owe</l>
                  <l>All that I am in fortune, name and greatneſs</l>
                  <l>Unto your perſon, next whom, give me leave</l>
                  <l>To ſay I rate no expectation</l>
                  <l>Equall to be her ſervant, yet I find</l>
                  <l>Her cold to thoſe deſires, that court her with</l>
                  <l>All honour, I ſhall humbly beg, your grace</l>
                  <pb n="46" facs="tcp:153591:29"/>
                  <l>When you converſe, will interpoſe your favour,</l>
                  <l>And by your Mediation perfect all</l>
                  <l>That can be nam'd my happine<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>s.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Far.</speaker>
                  <l>You expreſs</l>
                  <l>A ſtrong Captivity in ſo ſmall acquaintance;</l>
                  <l>Well my Lord truſt to me; is this her Caſtle?</l>
                  <stage>Enter Piperollo.</stage>
                  <l>By your favour Sir.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Pi.</speaker>
                  <l>Speak quickly whats your buſineſs?</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Far.</speaker>
                  <l>Is this <hi>Paulina's</hi> Caſtle?</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Pi.</speaker>
                  <l>Plain <hi>Paulina?</hi> and is this her Caſtle?</l>
                  <l>My friend you want ſome breeding, ſhe that owes</l>
                  <l>This Palace, for a Prince hath made it ſo,</l>
                  <l>Is not far off; turn your eys backward Sir,</l>
                  <l>And tell your ſelf without a perſpective</l>
                  <l>What man is coming towards us?</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Far.</speaker>
                  <l>Worthy Sir.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Pi.</speaker>
                  <l>Put of your hats and hear his name, <hi>Farneſe</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>The Prince of <hi>Parma's</hi> there, I kiſt his hand,</l>
                  <l>My breath is ſince the ſweeter.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Far.</speaker>
                  <l>The Prince, where?</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Pi.</speaker>
                  <l>You'l find him with my Lady whom he came</l>
                  <l>To viſit, if you'l promiſe to be drunk,</l>
                  <l>Take what's a ſecret yet, he comes to marry her,</l>
                  <l>Or ther's no truth in Stars, ſhe is to be</l>
                  <l>His ſpouſe; farewell, and thank my worſhip heartily.</l>
               </sp>
               <stage>Exit.</stage>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Con.</speaker>
                  <l>This fellow's mad!</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Fr.</speaker>
                  <l>He kiſt the Princes hand,</l>
                  <l>What myſtery is this?</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Con.</speaker>
                  <l>See, they approach.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Far.</speaker>
                  <l>I am not loſt ſure in this cloud, they march</l>
                  <l>In State this way.</l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Loud Muſick.</hi>
                  </l>
               </sp>
               <stage>Enter Frapolo, Paulina, a Train of Gallants and Ladies, Vergerin, Angellina.</stage>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Ang.</speaker>
                  <l>How, an Impoſtor?</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <pb n="47" facs="tcp:153591:29"/>
                  <speaker>Ver.</speaker>
                  <l>Sure I know the Prince.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Ang.</speaker>
                  <l>Conceal it yet.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Far.</speaker>
                  <l>What Gentleman is that?</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Lon.</speaker>
                  <l>The Prince of <hi>Parma</hi> Sir.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Con</speaker>
                  <l>This will be worth obſerving.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Far.</speaker>
                  <l>Do we not both dream? that <hi>Paulina?</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>How diſdainfully ſhe moves?</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Con.</speaker>
                  <l>That's her younger Siſter upon whom</l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Vergerio</hi> waits.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Far.</speaker>
                  <l>He knows I am the Prince.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Con.</speaker>
                  <l>How do you like her Sir?</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Fa.</speaker>
                  <l>Ha? tis not fit to tell thee.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Con.</speaker>
                  <l>Does ſhe not anſwer my Character?</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Fa.</speaker>
                  <l>On my heart a fair one?</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Con.</speaker>
                  <l>Pray tell me how you like her Sir.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Fa.</speaker>
                  <l>Not yet.</l>
                  <l>I am loſt in wonder of her ſweetneſs. Bid</l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Vergerio</hi> bring her to <hi>Antonio's;</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>I'l be his gueſt to night.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Con</speaker>
                  <l>I ſhall obey Sir.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Pi.</speaker>
                  <l>Make room for the Prince, fellows bear back;</l>
                  <l>You are not to be Knighted friend I take it.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Fa.</speaker>
                  <l>Thus can the flame of Heaven with ſubtill art,</l>
                  <l>Leave the skin whole, yet quite conſume the heart.</l>
               </sp>
               <stage>Exeunt.</stage>
            </div>
            <div n="5" type="act">
               <head>ACT V.</head>
               <stage>Enter Contarini, Antenio.</stage>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>An.</speaker>
                  <l>MY Neece has had a pretty warm night on't,</l>
                  <l>'Tis a bold knave to take the Prince upon him</l>
                  <l>I did believe the noyes, and was conſidering</l>
                  <l>How to contrive my peace with her good grace.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <pb n="48" facs="tcp:153591:30"/>
                  <speaker>Con.</speaker>
                  <l>You have no fear to ſuffer now?</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Ant.</speaker>
                  <l>I thank</l>
                  <l>Your Lordſhip, that has made my houſe and knowledge</l>
                  <l>So fortunate, by the preſence of our great</l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Farneſe,</hi> 'tis an honour makes me young;</l>
                  <l>And yet this Raſcal troubles me, that durſt</l>
                  <l>Come in the Princes name, and charge my Neece</l>
                  <l>So home too; Is't not Treaſon Sir?</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Con.</speaker>
                  <l>Of higheſt nature.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Ant.</speaker>
                  <l>Let him then taſt the Law; yet I commend</l>
                  <l>His Spirit, that would ſcorn to die for Felonie,</l>
                  <l>And when his head goes off, the ſhame and grief</l>
                  <l>May help to break her heart: I do not love her,</l>
                  <l>And then my Girl, my <hi>Angellina's</hi> heir,</l>
                  <l>And you her Lord and mine.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Con.</speaker>
                  <l>My hopes are fair,</l>
                  <l>The Prince himſelf having vouchſaf'd to be</l>
                  <l>My Advocate.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Ant.</speaker>
                  <l>He muſt command all here.</l>
                  <stage>Enter Farneſe, and Angellina.</stage>
                  <l>'Tis a good Prince, and loves you well, and let me</l>
                  <l>Without boaſt, tell you my Lord, ſhe brings</l>
                  <l>No common Blood, though we live dark i'th' Country</l>
                  <l>I can derive her from the great <hi>Urſini,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>But we have been eclips'd.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Far.</speaker>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Contarint</hi> leave us. You may ſtay <hi>Antonio;</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>Is't not an honour to your Family</l>
                  <l>A Prince ſhould court your Neece into his arms?</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Ant.</speaker>
                  <l>I muſt confeſs, 'tis good enough for ſuch</l>
                  <l>A Baggage, they will make together Sir,</l>
                  <l>A moſt excellent ſhew upon the Scaffold.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Far.</speaker>
                  <l>The Impoſtor, and <hi>Paulina's</hi> pride, takes off</l>
                  <l>Your underſtanding; I do court your Neece</l>
                  <l>Fair <hi>Angellina.</hi>
                  </l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Ant.</speaker>
                  <l>How Sir?</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Far.</speaker>
                  <l>And as becomes a Princeſs.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Ant.</speaker>
                  <l>Your Grace is merry.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <pb n="49" facs="tcp:153591:30"/>
                  <speaker>Far.</speaker>
                  <l>I know not, but there's Magick in her eyes.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>An:</speaker>
                  <l>Magick? and ſhe be a Witch, I ha'done with her.</l>
                  <l>Does he love <hi>Angelina?</hi> Pleaſe your Highneſs—</l>
                  <l>Do you affect this Girl?</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Far.</speaker>
                  <l>Religiouſly.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>An.</speaker>
                  <l>And have you all your Princely wits about ye?</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Far.</speaker>
                  <l>This Language is but coarſe. I tell you Sir</l>
                  <l>The Virgin muſt be mine.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>An.</speaker>
                  <l>Your Whore?</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Far.</speaker>
                  <l>My Princeſs.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>An.</speaker>
                  <l>That's another matter.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Far.</speaker>
                  <l>Shew your obedience,</l>
                  <l>You have commands upon her as a Father.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>An.</speaker>
                  <l>I know not what to ſay, but I'l perſwade;</l>
                  <l>Hark you Neece, you hear what the Prince ſays,</l>
                  <l>'Tis now no time to think of Nunneries.</l>
                  <l>Be rul'd then, and love ſomebody; if you have</l>
                  <l>Promis'd my Lord, I ſay make good that promiſe,</l>
                  <l>If not, the Prince is worth conſidering.</l>
                  <l>The Gentleman will make you a round Iointure.</l>
                  <l>If thou beeſt free, love him, to vex thy Siſter,</l>
                  <l>Who may upon ſubmiſſion be receiv'd</l>
                  <l>To Grace, and riſe in time a Madam Nurſe</l>
                  <l>To your heir apparent. I have done my duty.</l>
                  <l>But this is no great honeſty, to cheat</l>
                  <l>My Lord. I ſee the greateſt men are fleſh</l>
                  <l>And blood, our ſouls are much upon a making;</l>
                  <l>All men that are in love deal with the Devil,</l>
                  <l>Only with this difference, he that dotes</l>
                  <l>Upon a Woman is abſolutely poſſeſt;</l>
                  <l>And he that loves the leaſt is haunted</l>
                  <l>With a Familiar.</l>
               </sp>
               <stage>Enter a Servant</stage>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Ser.</speaker>
                  <l>Old <hi>Fabio</hi> Sir your Tenant, with much buſineſs</l>
                  <l>Jn's face, deſires to ſpeak with you, I could hardly</l>
                  <l>Keep him from preſſing in, his Wife he ſayes</l>
                  <l>Is Lunatick.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <pb n="50" facs="tcp:153591:31"/>
                  <speaker>Ant.</speaker>
                  <l>We ſhall all be mad ſhortly,</l>
                  <l>Where is the Knave?</l>
               </sp>
               <stage>Exit.</stage>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Aug.</speaker>
                  <l>I dare do Sir as much to ſhew my duty</l>
                  <l>As any Maid alive; I dare dye for you.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Fa.</speaker>
                  <l>And yet you dare not love.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Ang.</speaker>
                  <l>Not in that ſenſe</l>
                  <l>You invite me to.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Far.</speaker>
                  <l>My Courtſhip carries</l>
                  <l>No ſtain to fright you, what I have propounded</l>
                  <l>Is worth the Ambition of a greater Lady;</l>
                  <l>Though you profeſs ſo liberally, I find</l>
                  <l>Your cunning, and becauſe I have ſo much</l>
                  <l>Deſcended from my Title, you aſſume</l>
                  <l>This unbecomming Nicety, take heed,</l>
                  <l>I can be angry.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Ang.</speaker>
                  <l>As you are a Man</l>
                  <l>That paſſion may come neer you Sir; and as</l>
                  <l>You are my Prince, you may command my death</l>
                  <l>To follow and Appeaſe it, but you ſaid you lov'd me.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Far.</speaker>
                  <l>I doe, if you can wiſely entertain it.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>An.</speaker>
                  <l>Then you muſt love my honor,</l>
                  <l>A Virgins wealth, for every honeſt Man</l>
                  <l>Or Woman has an honor, and that has</l>
                  <l>Engag'd my heart already by a Contract;</l>
                  <l>This tye diſſolv'd with juſtice, I ſhould kneel</l>
                  <l>To ask your Princely favour.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Far.</speaker>
                  <l>I am anſwer'd.</l>
                  <l>Who waits? call my Lord <hi>Contarini</hi> hither.</l>
               </sp>
               <stage>Enter Contarini.</stage>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Con.</speaker>
                  <l>Sir.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Far.</speaker>
                  <l>You might have mock'd another perſon,</l>
                  <l>And not have made me a ridiculous ſtory</l>
                  <l>To your Miſtreſs Sir.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Con.</speaker>
                  <l>I underſtand you not.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Far.</speaker>
                  <l>Engage me to mediation for her love,</l>
                  <l>With a pretence how much my act ſhould honor</l>
                  <pb n="51" facs="tcp:153591:31"/>
                  <l>Your faint hopes, when you are conſcious of a</l>
                  <l>Contract, already paſt between you.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Con.</speaker>
                  <l>Contract Sir?</l>
                  <l>She never yet gave me any language</l>
                  <l>Did promiſe hope, ſhe ſtill concluded me</l>
                  <l>With going to a Cloiſter.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Far.</speaker>
                  <l>How's this fair one?</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>An.</speaker>
                  <l>It is moſt ſure I am contracted.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Con.</speaker>
                  <l>To whom?</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>An.</speaker>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Vergerio</hi> your Lordſhips Agent.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Con.</speaker>
                  <l>That boy betray me?</l>
                  <l>In whom I took delight, made him my friend,</l>
                  <l>He play the Traytor? I'l be reveng'd upon</l>
                  <l>His heart.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Far.</speaker>
                  <l>Contain your paſſion <hi>Contarini,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>Her beauty had apower a bove my friendſhip,</l>
                  <l>It well might ſhake his faith, and yet'tis ſtrange.</l>
                  <l>Call in <hi>Vergerio.</hi>
                  </l>
               </sp>
               <stage>Enter Vergerio.</stage>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Ver.</speaker>
                  <l>I have heard all,</l>
                  <l>And come to meet my ſentence. You're a Prince</l>
                  <l>Gainſt whom I dare not lift a thought; I ſee</l>
                  <l>What ſtorm is riſing, yet let this, great Sir,</l>
                  <l>Invite your mercy to me, I have made</l>
                  <l>No breach againſt your love, and that which wa<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>
                  </l>
                  <l>My fault to his, may be excus'd, by what</l>
                  <l>He felt himſelf love not to be reſiſted.</l>
                  <l>This Virgin I lay claim to, and her vowes</l>
                  <l>No Subject muſt compell me to reſigne;</l>
                  <l>But if the Prince think me unfit, and call</l>
                  <l>This treaſure from my boſome, and can place</l>
                  <l>His love, where I ſo chaſtly have delighted,</l>
                  <l>I will not keep a thought that ſhall repine,</l>
                  <l>When I am miſerable in her abſence,</l>
                  <l>But give my intereſt cheerfully; to you,</l>
                  <l>My Lord, I anſwer, I have made no treſpaſs,</l>
                  <pb n="52" facs="tcp:153591:32"/>
                  <l>And ſhall, ſo pleaſe your highneſs to be Iudge,</l>
                  <l>Make it appear.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Con:</speaker>
                  <l>Was ever ſuch an impudence?</l>
                  <l>This preſence does protect him, I ſhould els</l>
                  <l>Write treaſon on his heart; But <hi>Angellina</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>I pity thy undoing, how canſt thou</l>
                  <l>Expect a truth from him, betrays his Maſter?</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>An.</speaker>
                  <l>My Lord, you have been faulty ſure, and this</l>
                  <l>(not worthy to be call'd a loſs of me)</l>
                  <l>Was meant by Providence to wake your faith,</l>
                  <l>That's owing to another.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Far.</speaker>
                  <l>Poſſible?</l>
                  <l>The Vice-roy of <hi>Sicilies</hi> Daughter? <hi>Pulcheria.</hi>
                  </l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Con.</speaker>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Pulcheria</hi> here?</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Ver.</speaker>
                  <l>Here <hi>Contarini.</hi>
                  </l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Con.</speaker>
                  <l>Ha, prov'd a Woman, oh my ſhame and folly!</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Ver.</speaker>
                  <l>Pardon my too much love, that made me fear</l>
                  <l>You had forgot <hi>Pulcheria,</hi> though you left</l>
                  <l>Your vowes and me at <hi>Sicily,</hi> when you were</l>
                  <l>Embaſſadour from the Prince.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Con.</speaker>
                  <l>Whence embarqu'd</l>
                  <l>Thou brought'ſt me news <hi>Pulcheria</hi> was dround,</l>
                  <l>And thou for her ſake entertain'd my ſervant,</l>
                  <l>Welcome, at once receive me and forgive me.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Fa.</speaker>
                  <l>I had your promiſe, were this contract void</l>
                  <l>In honour, nor will take from my own merit</l>
                  <l>To think when your conſiderate thoughts come home,</l>
                  <l>You can pretend excuſe to your own happineſs,</l>
                  <l>Which leſt you may ſuſpect, let us in ſtate</l>
                  <l>Viſit <hi>Paulina,</hi> and unmask that counterfeit</l>
                  <l>Which hath uſurp'd our name.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Ver.</speaker>
                  <l>Sir we attend you,</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Con.</speaker>
                  <l>This bleſſing muſt require a ſpacious ſoul,</l>
                  <l>Mine is too narrow to receive.</l>
               </sp>
               <stage>Exeunt.</stage>
               <stage>Enter Steward, and Piperollo.</stage>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Lu.</speaker>
                  <l>I am not yet created honourable.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <pb n="53" facs="tcp:153591:32"/>
                  <speaker>Fi.</speaker>
                  <l>Sir, things muſt have their time, but will his high<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs</l>
                  <l>Remove ſo ſuddenly, and carry my Lady</l>
                  <l>To th' Court with him? tis a moſt ſweet young Prince.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Lu.</speaker>
                  <l>Order was given to pack up her plate,</l>
                  <l>Her gold and Jewels, for he means to have</l>
                  <l>Tiltings and triumphs when he comes to <hi>Parma.</hi>
                  </l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Fi.</speaker>
                  <l>There it is fit we ſhould expect our honours.</l>
                  <l>I will attend the Prince.</l>
               </sp>
               <stage>Exit.</stage>
               <stage>Enter Contarini.</stage>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Con.</speaker>
                  <l>Signior <hi>Lu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>io.</hi>
                  </l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Lu.</speaker>
                  <l>Your good Lordſhip.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Con.</speaker>
                  <l>Pray tell my Lady, I would kiſs her hand,</l>
                  <l>And ſhall preſent news will ſecure their welcome.</l>
                  <l>I come from the Prince.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Lu.</speaker>
                  <l>The Prince my Lord?</l>
                  <l>He is within—</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Con.</speaker>
                  <l>A ſmall march off the Caſtle, and commanded</l>
                  <l>Me to prepare her, that he comes to be</l>
                  <l>Her gueſt.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Lu.</speaker>
                  <l>My Lord, I will acquaint ſome of the bed-cham<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber, but,</l>
                  <l>When did your Lordſhip ſee his Highneſs?</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Con.</speaker>
                  <l>I left him at the Park gate.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Lu.</speaker>
                  <l>This is the neareſt way unleſs his highneſs</l>
                  <l>Have leap'd a window, or can walk inviſible.</l>
                  <l>Your Lordſhip may have ſome conceit. I'l go Sir.</l>
               </sp>
               <stage>Exit.</stage>
               <stage>Enter Piperollo.</stage>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Pi</speaker>
                  <l>What is the meaning that ther's ſuch a guard</l>
                  <l>Upon our Caſtle? 'tis beſiedg'd, and no man</l>
                  <l>Suffer'd go forth; this is ſome Lord or other</l>
                  <l>By his ſtradling.</l>
               </sp>
               <stage>Enter Lucio, Longino, Strozzo, and the reſt.</stage>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Lo.</speaker>
                  <l>From the Prince? that he?</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Pi.</speaker>
                  <l>'Tis as I tell you Sir, ther's a little army,</l>
                  <l>Surrounds the Caſtle.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Lo.</speaker>
                  <l>They have no order from his highneſs.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <pb n="54" facs="tcp:153591:33"/>
                  <speaker>Str.</speaker>
                  <l>We are betraid agen.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Lon.</speaker>
                  <l>Sir, would you ſpeak with the Prince?</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Con.</speaker>
                  <l>Why have you ſuch a thing within the Caſtle?</l>
                  <l>Who dares be ſo much Traitour to uſurpe</l>
                  <l>That title? Wher's that Puppet, Gentlemen?</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Lu.</speaker>
                  <l>That is his Secretary.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Pi.</speaker>
                  <l>The reſt are Lords and Privie Counſellors.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Ca.</speaker>
                  <l>We are undone.</l>
               </sp>
               <stage>Enter Farneſe, Vergerio, Angellina, Attendants.</stage>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>La.</speaker>
                  <l>Tis he, the very he, I dare not look on him;</l>
                  <l>Oh for an impudence worth a Chronicle,</l>
                  <l>To out ace him now, it were a poſſible thing,</l>
                  <l>If People would believe—</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Lu.</speaker>
                  <l>I'l tell my Lady, they are vaniſh'd; hum,</l>
                  <l>I do not like that face.</l>
               </sp>
               <stage>Exit.</stage>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Far.</speaker>
                  <l>Come hither fellow, whom do you ſerve?</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Pi.</speaker>
                  <l>I know not Sir.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Fa.</speaker>
                  <l>What Prince have you within?</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Pi.</speaker>
                  <l>The prince of Darkneſs.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Fa.</speaker>
                  <l>What is this fellow?</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Pi.</speaker>
                  <l>a Knight o'th' Poſt, the Peſtle is too honourable.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Fr.</speaker>
                  <l>Where is your Excellent Lady?</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Pi.</speaker>
                  <l>I have a gueſs</l>
                  <l>If things go on, as I ſuſpect, ſhe will be —</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Fr.</speaker>
                  <l>Where?</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Pi.</speaker>
                  <l>At her wits end very ſhortly.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Fr.</speaker>
                  <l>An ingenious fellow?</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Pi.</speaker>
                  <l>I have convers'd a little with the Mathematicks,</l>
                  <l>Sir, Who is that Gentlewoman, not that I am ignorant,</l>
                  <l>But to ſatisfie a doubt?</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Ver.</speaker>
                  <l>She is one that may be</l>
                  <l>The Prince of <hi>Parma's</hi> Lady, when the Prieſt</l>
                  <l>Hath done his Office.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Pi.</speaker>
                  <l>If I be not miſtaken</l>
                  <l>Here comes the Princeſſe, that is <hi>Angellina</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>The younger Siſter.</l>
               </sp>
               <stage>
                  <pb n="55" facs="tcp:153591:33"/>
                  <hi>Enter Paulina.</hi>
               </stage>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Pa.</speaker>
                  <l>It is my wonder you that have the face</l>
                  <l>And garb of Gentlemen, ſhould dare to be</l>
                  <l>So inſolent, to affront our perſon,</l>
                  <l>And his, to whom your hearts and knees owe reverence.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Far.</speaker>
                  <l>Command the Impoſtor forth,</l>
                  <l>Seize on the Traitors.</l>
               </sp>
               <stage>Enter Longino.</stage>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Lo.</speaker>
                  <l>His Grace will be here preſently, fear not Madam,</l>
                  <l>I would venter a Neck-breaking at ſome window,</l>
                  <l>And be content to crawl away a Cripple;</l>
                  <l>But there's no hope to ſcape the Multitude</l>
                  <l>That will be ſcrambling for my limbs. Great Sir,</l>
                  <l>I challenge the privilege of the laſt <hi>Bando,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <stage>Kneels.</stage>
                  <l>He that can bring <hi>Frapolo</hi> the chief Bandit,</l>
                  <l>Beſide what was proclam'd other reward,</l>
                  <l>Shall have free pardon for all paſt-offences;</l>
                  <l>To that Grace I appeal, and here produce</l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Frapolo.</hi>
                  </l>
               </sp>
               <stage>Enter Frapolo, Strozzo, &amp;c.</stage>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Pa.</speaker>
                  <l>This amazeth me.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Fr.</speaker>
                  <l>Can you ſtand</l>
                  <l>The dazeling Sun ſo long, and not be ſtruck</l>
                  <l>Blind for this bold affront? what wildneſs brought you</l>
                  <l>In multitudes to fright my happy peace,</l>
                  <l>And this good Ladies, my moſt vertuous Conſort?</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Lo.</speaker>
                  <l>He bears up ſtill!</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Fr.</speaker>
                  <l>Have all my cares and watchings to preſerve</l>
                  <l>Your lives, and deareſt liberties, deſerv'd</l>
                  <l>This ſtrange return, and at a time when moſt</l>
                  <l>Your happineſs is concern'd, ſince by our Mariage</l>
                  <l>With this ſweet Lady, full of grace and beauty,</l>
                  <l>You may expect an Heir to bleſs your Countrey.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Con.</speaker>
                  <l>Will you ſuffer him?</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Fr.</speaker>
                  <l>'Tis time your Prince were dead, and when I am</l>
                  <l>Companion to my Fathers duſt, theſe tumults</l>
                  <l>Fomented by ſeditious men, that are</l>
                  <pb n="56" facs="tcp:153591:34"/>
                  <l>Weary of Plenty, and delights of Peace,</l>
                  <l>Shall not approach to interrupt the calm</l>
                  <l>Good Princes after Death enjoy. Go home,</l>
                  <l>I pray depart, I rather will ſubmit</l>
                  <l>To be depos'd, than wear a power or title</l>
                  <l>That ſhall not all be dedicate to ſerve you;</l>
                  <l>My life is but the gift of Heaven, to waſt it</l>
                  <l>For your dear ſakes, my People are my Children,</l>
                  <l>Whom I am bound in Nature and Religion</l>
                  <l>To cheriſh and protect. Perhaps you have</l>
                  <l>Some grievance to preſent, you ſhall have juſtice</l>
                  <l>Againſt the proudeſt here; I look not on</l>
                  <l>Nobility of Birth. Office, or Fortunes,</l>
                  <l>The pooreſt ſubject has a Native Charter</l>
                  <l>And a Birth-right to th' Laws, and Common wealth,</l>
                  <l>Which with an equall, and impartial ſtream,</l>
                  <l>Shall flow to every boſom.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Str.</speaker>
                  <l>Pious Prince!</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Far.</speaker>
                  <l>I am at a loſs to hear him; ſure I am</l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Farneſe,</hi> if I be not loſt by the way.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Pi.</speaker>
                  <l>Stand off Gentlemen, — let me ſee — which?</l>
                  <l>Hum! this — no, th'other. Hum! ſend for a Lion</l>
                  <l>And turn him looſe, he wo'not hurt the true Prince.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Far.</speaker>
                  <l>Do not you know me Sir?</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Fra.</speaker>
                  <l>Yes, I know you too well, but it ſtands not</l>
                  <l>With my honor; what compoſition?</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Far.</speaker>
                  <l>Who am I? Gentlemen, how dare ye ſuffer</l>
                  <l>This thing to talk? if I be your <hi>Farneſe.</hi>
                  </l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Fra.</speaker>
                  <l>I ſay I am the Prince,</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Far.</speaker>
                  <l>Prince of what?</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Fra.</speaker>
                  <l>Of Rogues, and pleaſe thy Excellence.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Pa.</speaker>
                  <l>How?</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Fra.</speaker>
                  <l>You muſt excuſe, I can hold out no longer</l>
                  <l>Theſe were my Subjects Sir, and if they find</l>
                  <l>Your Mercy, I'm but one, whoſe head remov'd,</l>
                  <l>Or nooz'd, this Lady will be ſoon a Widdow,</l>
                  <pb n="57" facs="tcp:153591:34"/>
                  <l>Whom I have not deceiv'd, 'twas her Ambition</l>
                  <l>To go no leſs than Prince, and now you have one,</l>
                  <l>During this Gentlemans pleaſure.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Pa.</speaker>
                  <l>What ſcorn ſhall I become?</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Far.</speaker>
                  <l>Let him be guarded, and all his puppet Lords.</l>
               </sp>
               <stage>Enter Antonio, Fabio, Morulla.</stage>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>An.</speaker>
                  <l>News, news, excellent news; I ſhall leap</l>
                  <l>Out of my fleſh for joy. Sir I have undertook</l>
                  <l>For your pardon to this reverend couple,</l>
                  <l>They heard my Neece was to be maried</l>
                  <l>To the Prince, and thought it treaſon to conceal —</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Far.</speaker>
                  <l>What?</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>An.</speaker>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Paulina</hi> is not my Neece, no blood of mine;</l>
                  <l>Where is this Lady and her Pageant Prince?</l>
                  <l>The truth is, ſhe is not <hi>Paulina,</hi> but their</l>
                  <l>Own Daughter.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Fra.</speaker>
                  <l>Poſſible? then we are both cheated.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>An.</speaker>
                  <l>Whom ſhe obtruded on our Family</l>
                  <l>When our <hi>Paulina</hi> died an Infant, with her,</l>
                  <l>A Nurſe to both; Does your Grace apprehend?</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Fab.</speaker>
                  <l>We do beſeech your pardon.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>An.</speaker>
                  <l>Now <hi>Angellina</hi> thou art heir to all.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Pip.</speaker>
                  <l>By all this Circumſtance you are but my Siſter!</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Con.</speaker>
                  <l>The Prince is prov'd a Prince of Theeves.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>An.</speaker>
                  <l>Why ther's a Baggage and a Theef well met then.</l>
                  <l>I knew ſhe was a Baſtard, or a Changeling.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Pau.</speaker>
                  <l>Where ſhall I hide my ſhame? O curſt Ambi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion!</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Ant.</speaker>
                  <l>Give you joy Sir, my moſt illuſtrious Nephew,</l>
                  <l>Joy to thy inviſible Grace.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Fra.</speaker>
                  <l>Thanks to our loving Uncle:</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Far.</speaker>
                  <l>Take hence the Traitors.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Ang.</speaker>
                  <l>Sir I beſeech a pardon to their lives.</l>
                  <l>Let nothing of my ſtory be remembred</l>
                  <l>With ſuch a Tragedie, 'tis my firſt Petition.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Far.</speaker>
                  <l>I muſt not deny thee; all thank her Virtue;</l>
                  <l>Live you, and love that Gentlewoman; But</l>
                  <pb n="58" facs="tcp:153591:35"/>
                  <l>It were a ſin to innocence, and our honor</l>
                  <l>Would encourage Treaſon by example,</l>
                  <l>If they ſhould ſcape all Juſtice, take 'em to Cuſtody:</l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Frapolo,</hi> we confine you to this Caſtle,</l>
                  <l>Where If ſhe pleaſe your Bride may accompany you</l>
                  <l>Till we determine otherwiſe.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Fra.</speaker>
                  <l>'Tis ſome mercy; but</l>
                  <l>I ſhall be getting Children, and two nothings</l>
                  <l>Wo'not maintain a Family, 'twere as good</l>
                  <l>To hang me out o'th'way, 'ere Charge come on,</l>
                  <l>Or take away my tools, I ſhall be working.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Far.</speaker>
                  <l>Proviſion ſhall be made you ſhall not ſterve</l>
                  <l>Nor ſurfet Sir.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Ang.</speaker>
                  <l>Becauſe I call'd her Siſter,</l>
                  <l>I will contribute ſomething to their fortune.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Far.</speaker>
                  <l>What thy own goodneſs will direct; and now</l>
                  <l>Remove the Scene to Court, to perfect there</l>
                  <l>My own, and <hi>Parma's</hi> happineſs; pride has</l>
                  <l>Met with ſevere reward, and that high juſtice</l>
                  <l>(That Governs all) though envy break with her</l>
                  <l>Own Poyſon, calls the Amazed World to ſee</l>
                  <l>What bleſſings wait upon <hi>Humility.</hi>
                  </l>
               </sp>
               <stage>Exeunt.</stage>
            </div>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
      <back>
         <div type="epilogue">
            <pb facs="tcp:153591:35"/>
            <head>Epilogue.</head>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Frapolo.</speaker>
               <p>Gentlemen, do not ſay you ſee me; I have made an eſcape from the Prince and <hi>Paulina;</hi> his graces word is but mortall, and not ſecurity enough for me; for all this Sun-ſhine he may hang me, when I come to <hi>Parma,</hi> for an example, and therefore I have choſen, rather to truſt to my legs, than a reconcil'd State-Enemy.</p>
               <lg>
                  <l>Two'not be worth your glory to betray</l>
                  <l>A man diſtreſt, whom your own mercy may</l>
                  <l>Preſerve to better ſervice; rather then</l>
                  <l>Go back I'l ſtand your Iuſtice Gentlemen.</l>
                  <l>I've plaid the thief, but you, as the caſe ſtands,</l>
                  <l>May ſave or kill, my lif's now in your hands.</l>
               </lg>
            </sp>
            <pb facs="tcp:153591:36"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:153591:36"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:153591:37"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:153591:37"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:153591:38"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:153591:38" rendition="simple:additions"/>
         </div>
      </back>
   </text>
</TEI>
