<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>The brothers, a comedie, as it was acted at the private house in Black Fryers Written by James Shirley. Never printed before.</title>
            <author>Shirley, James, 1596-1666.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1652</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 163 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 79 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2012-10">2012-10 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A93166</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing S3460</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R230284</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99895967</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99895967</idno>
            <idno type="VID">153588</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A93166)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 153588)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 2371:11)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>The brothers, a comedie, as it was acted at the private house in Black Fryers Written by James Shirley. Never printed before.</title>
                  <author>Shirley, James, 1596-1666.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[4], 72 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>printed for Humphrey Robinson at the Three Pigeons, and Humphrey Moseley at the Prince Armes in St. Paul's Church-yard,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1652.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in the Folger Shakespeare Library, Washington, D.C..</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2011-06</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-07</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-08</date>
            <label>Greg Schutz</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-08</date>
            <label>Greg Schutz</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-05</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:153588:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:153588:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:153588:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:153588:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:153588:3" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:153588:3"/>
            <p>THE BROTHERS, A COMEDIE, <hi>AS</hi> It was Acted at the private Houſe IN <hi>BLACK FRYERS.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>WRITTEN By JAMES SHIRLEY.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Never Printed before.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON,</hi> Printed for <hi>Humphrey Robinſon</hi> at the Three Pigeons, and <hi>Humphrey Moſeley</hi> at the Prince Armes in St. <hi>Paul's</hi> Church-yard. 1652.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="dedication">
            <pb facs="tcp:153588:4"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:153588:4"/>
            <head>To his truly Noble Friend THO: STANLEY <abbr>Eſq</abbr>
            </head>
            <opener>
               <salute>SIR,</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>The Memory and Contempla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of good Offices recei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved, which, by their own na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, and impulſion, have inclined other men to bee active in their returnes, have not wrought me into ſo much boldneſs; For when I conſidered my obligation to your favors I was ſtill deter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red by their greatneſs and number; For in my poverty I had thoughts not without Ambition to reach them with ſome merit, but when I was ſtudying to proportion my gratitude, I fell much lower than when I was the object of your mercy. The way to releeve my ſelf, is no more to look at what you have confer'd, but on
<pb facs="tcp:153588:5"/>the beſtower, for I have now learn'd to ſepa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rate you from your benefits, and to couvey my ſelf into your pardon, by the exerciſe of your Charity. Thus in place of cancelling my former debts, I put your vertue to a new diſburſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment: Witneſs this Compoſition, which after its birth, had in my thoughts a dedication to your name, although it but now took the bold<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs to wear it in the forehean both as an Or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nament and preſerver. You were pleas'd to grace it with your fair opinion, when it was re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſented, and though it appear not in that naturall Dreſs of the Scene, nor ſo powerfull, as when it had the ſoul of action, yet your ſmile upon it now will give it ſecond animati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on; by which I ſhall derive after ſo long a ſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lence, a Confirmation of my happineſs, in be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing ſtill received</p>
            <closer>
               <salute>Sir</salute>
               <signed>Your moſt humble Servant <hi>JAMES SHIRLEY.</hi>
               </signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="play">
            <pb facs="tcp:153588:5"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:153588:6"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:153588:6"/>
            <head>THE BROTHERS.</head>
            <div n="1" type="act">
               <head>ACT I.</head>
               <stage>Enter Franciſco, Jacinta, Feliſarda.</stage>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Franciſco.</speaker>
                  <l>
                     <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg> Take my leave <hi>Jacinta,</hi> and cannot wiſh you</l>
                  <l>More happineſs than you poſſeſs.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Jacin.</speaker>
                  <l>You muſt</l>
                  <l>Diſſemble, or it is within your wiſhes</l>
                  <l>To make your ſelf, <hi>Franciſco,</hi> mine, which would be</l>
                  <l>A fair addition to me, in my faith</l>
                  <l>Of that moſt noble love you have profeſt.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Fran.</speaker>
                  <l>When you but dare to own me, I am paſt</l>
                  <l>The fear of any deſtiny that can</l>
                  <stage>Enter Don Carlos and Servant</stage>
                  <l>Divide us—but your Father. Your own virtue</l>
                  <l>Be ſtill your guard. I do not like this watch</l>
                  <l>Upon our meeting, pretty <hi>Peliſarda.</hi>
                  </l>
               </sp>
               <stage>Exit</stage>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Car.</speaker>
                  <l>Tel Signior <hi>Franciſco</hi> I would ſpeak with him</l>
                  <l>I do not like his frequent viſites: though</l>
                  <l>His birth and generous parts deſerve to march</l>
                  <l>With men of honorable name, I am</l>
                  <l>Without ambition to ſacrifiſe</l>
                  <l>My daughter to his penſion for life.</l>
               </sp>
               <stage>Enter Franciſco</stage>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Fran.</speaker>
                  <l>Your pleaſure ſir?</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Car.</speaker>
                  <l>Hath hitherto <hi>Franciſco</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>Been to affect you in the liſt of thoſe</l>
                  <pb n="2" facs="tcp:153588:7"/>
                  <l>I held my freinds.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Fra.</speaker>
                  <l>I hope no forfeit made</l>
                  <l>By me, hath loſt that good opinion</l>
                  <l>You plac'd upon me.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Car.</speaker>
                  <l>I cannot tell</l>
                  <l>How you may be tranſported with deſires</l>
                  <l>Above my thoughts t' allow, I would not have</l>
                  <l>My ſilence, and the free acceſs y' have had</l>
                  <l>To my houſe, (which ſtill is open to wiſe gueſts,)</l>
                  <l>Betray me, or my Daughter to the mirth</l>
                  <l>And talk of men i'th' <hi>Plaſſa,</hi> My eſtate</l>
                  <l>Doth walk upon ſound Feet, and though I make</l>
                  <l>No exception to your blood, or perſon, ſir,</l>
                  <l>The portion I have fixt upon <hi>Jacinta,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>Beſide the wealth her liberall Aunt bequeath'd her,</l>
                  <l>Is more than your thin Younger brother's fortune</l>
                  <l>Should lay a ſiege, or hope to. I am plain.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Fr.</speaker>
                  <l>And ſomething paſſionate (if I underſtand you)</l>
                  <l>Without a cauſe. I am a gentleman,</l>
                  <l>With as much ſenſe of honor, as the proudeſt</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Don</speaker>
                  <l>that doth ride on's foot cloth, and can drop</l>
                  <l>Gold to the numerous minutes of his age</l>
                  <l>And let me not be loſt for want of that,</l>
                  <l>Deſerves not to be nam'd to fill the ballance</l>
                  <l>Againſt true honour— let me tell you ſir,</l>
                  <l>Virtue and blood are weigh'd againſt themſelves,</l>
                  <l>You cannot know the price of theſe, when either</l>
                  <l>Scale is not poiz'd with things of the ſame nature</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Car.</speaker>
                  <l>Y'are very right, and therefore I do weigh</l>
                  <l>My Daughters wealth againſt your fortunes ſir,</l>
                  <l>I take it they are things in the ſame ſpecie,</l>
                  <l>And find it eaſie to diſtinguiſh, yours</l>
                  <l>Can hold ſmall competition, and by</l>
                  <l>A conſequence that Fathers uſe t'infeire,</l>
                  <l>As little hope to equall in affections.</l>
                  <l>Sir I muſt tell you I eſteem <hi>Jacinta</hi>
                  </l>
                  <pb facs="tcp:153588:7"/>
                  <pb facs="tcp:153588:8"/>
                  <pb n="3" facs="tcp:153588:8"/>
                  <l>Fit every way to meet your Elder Brother,</l>
                  <l>Whoſe Birth will intreſt him ſo much in that</l>
                  <l>Full fortune which your Father now is Lord of,</l>
                  <l>Your expectations may prompt you look</l>
                  <l>Without much curioſitie for a <hi>Bride,</hi>
                  </l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Fran.</speaker>
                  <l>I ſhall believe thy ſoul is made of Atomes,</l>
                  <l>That placeth ſo much happineſs in Duſt.</l>
                  <stage>aſide</stage>
                  <l>Sir, I can quit your Jealouſie, my thoughts</l>
                  <l>Levell beneath your Daughter, and ſhall be</l>
                  <l>Happie if you conſent I may devote</l>
                  <l>My applications to <hi>Feliſarda,</hi> your Neece.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Car.</speaker>
                  <l>Is it my Neece? I ask your pardon.</l>
                  <l>Nay then be welcome, and t'encourage you,</l>
                  <l>Although her Father a poor Gentleman</l>
                  <l>My brother, by the malice of the ſea</l>
                  <l>And winds, have loſt what might have rank'd him even</l>
                  <l>With ſome that ride upon their reverend mules,</l>
                  <l>I'l find a portion for her, if you ſtrike</l>
                  <l>Affectionate heartes, and joy to call you Nephew.</l>
                  <l>Pray be not angry, that I take a care</l>
                  <l>To place my own, where I may ſee it anſwerd</l>
                  <l>With State, as well as Family.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Fran.</speaker>
                  <l>You ſhew</l>
                  <l>A provident Father. I ſhall not then</l>
                  <l>B' indanger'd to your ſcruple, if I addreſs</l>
                  <l>My ſervices to her, whoſe humble fortune,</l>
                  <l>In the relation to your blood, and nobleneſs,</l>
                  <l>Is wealth enough to me?</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Car.</speaker>
                  <l>I wiſh it proſper.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Fra.</speaker>
                  <l>You have much honor'd me.</l>
               </sp>
               <stage>Exit,</stage>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Car.</speaker>
                  <l>That ſcruple's vaniſh'd.</l>
                  <l>Theſe are conſiderings, with which Parents muſt</l>
                  <l>Timely prevent the folly, and the fall</l>
                  <l>Of Children, apt to loſe themſelves in ſhadowes</l>
                  <l>And gaudy apparitions.</l>
               </sp>
               <stage>Enter Servant.</stage>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Ser.</speaker>
                  <l>Your Son</l>
                  <pb n="4" facs="tcp:153588:9"/>
                  <l>Is come from <hi>Salamanca</hi> Sir.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Car.</speaker>
                  <l>I hope</l>
                  <l>Philoſophy hath by this time tam'd his wildneſs,</l>
                  <l>I have been carefull not to feed his riots.</l>
                  <l>Hee's welcome; my next ſtudie is to chooſe</l>
                  <l>A wiſe for him,</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Servant,</speaker>
                  <l>With him a Gentleman.</l>
                  <l>That ſeems of noble quality.</l>
               </sp>
               <stage>Enter Luys and Alberto.</stage>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Luys.</speaker>
                  <l>Your bleſſing,</l>
                  <l>Next vvhich 'tvvil be a happineſs, if you</l>
                  <l>Embrace this noble Gentleman <hi>Don, Alberto,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>To whoſe affection I have been engag'd.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Alber.</speaker>
                  <l>Our ſtudies grew together, and our loves.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Car.</speaker>
                  <l>You do an honour to us.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Lu.</speaker>
                  <l>If he thrive</l>
                  <l>Upon his fair intents fir to my Siſter,</l>
                  <l>Whoſe character he ha's took delight to hear</l>
                  <l>From me ſometimes, it will enlarge our honor.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Car.</speaker>
                  <l>He has improved in language— his eſtate?</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Lu.</speaker>
                  <l>Six thouſand ducats fir <hi>per Annum</hi> clear</l>
                  <l>In his poſſeſſion, beſide</l>
                  <l>The legacie of a Granam when ſhe dyes</l>
                  <l>That ha's outliy'd 6. cats within their family.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Car.</speaker>
                  <l>This taſts again of the old humor, hee's</l>
                  <l>Not ſetled yet.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Lu.</speaker>
                  <l>Your pardon fir, I cannot</l>
                  <l>With any patience think of an old woman,</l>
                  <l>They are agues to my nature, ſhe that lives</l>
                  <l>To three ſcore is a witch, and fit for fuell</l>
                  <l>By the Civill law. I hope my mother's well.</l>
                  <l>Sir I beſeech you, be not you miſtaken,</l>
                  <l>I am not what I was, I'm ſtrangely alter'd</l>
                  <l>From the wild garbe, and can diſcourſe moſt gravely</l>
                  <l>Of any thing but old and toothleſs women.</l>
                  <l>Do not you think it fit, ſhe ſhould be burn'd fir,</l>
                  <pb facs="tcp:153588:9"/>
                  <pb facs="tcp:153588:10"/>
                  <pb n="5" facs="tcp:153588:10"/>
                  <l>That lives within an Hoſpitall till the roof</l>
                  <l>Conſume to duſt, and no more left for covering</l>
                  <l>Than is kept up in one continued Cobweb,</l>
                  <l>Through which the birds may ſee her when ſhe creeps</l>
                  <l>Under a ſpiders canopie; what think you?</l>
                  <l>Speak your own conſcience.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Car.</speaker>
                  <l>A young wife will cure</l>
                  <l>This angry heat of blood. You are moſt welcome,</l>
                  <l>Command my houſe, and if you can affect</l>
                  <l>My Daughter, for whoſe love (as my Son here</l>
                  <l>Prepares me) you took this paines, I ſhall</l>
                  <l>Make equall propoſitions. I knew</l>
                  <l>Your Father well, <hi>Don Roderigo,</hi> who</l>
                  <l>Gave up his life with honor 'gainſt the <hi>Moores.</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>Once more y' are welcome: Son <hi>Luys</hi> ſhew</l>
                  <l>The way to your Siſter, and bid her entertain</l>
                  <l>Your friend with all the love her modeſty,</l>
                  <l>And my commands may prompt her to.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Alber.</speaker>
                  <l>You much oblige my ſervices.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Lu.</speaker>
                  <l>Remember <hi>Don</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>Conditions, if my Siſter and you join</l>
                  <l>Your coppiholds, I have a life muſt be</l>
                  <l>Maintain'd till the old man dye, hang his penſion,</l>
                  <l>'Two'not keep me in ſalads. I'le conduct you.</l>
               </sp>
               <stage>Exe. Alb. &amp; Luys.</stage>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Car.</speaker>
                  <l>I like his perſon well, and his calm geſture</l>
                  <l>Speakes for his other compoſition.</l>
                  <l>The eſtate is competent, my Daughter is</l>
                  <l>Obedient, which rich Parents call a bleſſing,</l>
                  <l>Whoſe wiſdom is to advance their name, and fortunes.</l>
                  <stage>Enter Don Ramyres</stage>
                  <l>My Son is all my ſtudie now,</l>
                  <l>My noble <hi>Don Ramyres,</hi> you look cheerfull.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Ramy.</speaker>
                  <l>'Tis a good <hi>omen,</hi> I ha' buiſneſs w'ee</l>
                  <l>Such as cannot deſpair your entertaiment;</l>
                  <l>You have a Daughter.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Car.</speaker>
                  <l>I would you had one;</l>
                  <pb n="6" facs="tcp:153588:11"/>
                  <l>I ſhould be willing to tranſlate a Son,</l>
                  <l>And by his mariage be moſt proud to call</l>
                  <l>Your Daughter mine.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Ramy.</speaker>
                  <l>You are next a Prophet, Signior,</l>
                  <l>And but the Sexes differ, ſpeak my thoughts;</l>
                  <l>Tis harmony on both fides; to be ſhort</l>
                  <l>For let our gravities not waſte time, and breath</l>
                  <l>In our affaires, give the Young leave to court</l>
                  <l>And ſpin out dayes in amorous circumſtance;</l>
                  <l>My Son <hi>Fernando,</hi> I need not call him Heir,</l>
                  <l>His birth concludes it, I would commend</l>
                  <l>To fair <hi>Jacinta:</hi> 't can be no diſhonour</l>
                  <l>To your Family to mix with mine.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Car.</speaker>
                  <l>Tis an addition</l>
                  <l>Will add a luſter rather to our blood.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Ramy.</speaker>
                  <l>Tis my affection to you Daughter, which confirm'd</l>
                  <l>By obſervation of her virtue, makes</l>
                  <l>Me wiſh this tye between 'em; I may ſafely</l>
                  <l>Expect you will aſſure a portion that</l>
                  <l>His Fortunes will deſerve, who muſt enjoy</l>
                  <l>What I poſſeſs, unleſs you diſaffect</l>
                  <l>His perſon, or dechne his education,</l>
                  <l>Which hath not ſpar'd my coffers to advance him</l>
                  <l>In the beſt form of Gentleman.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Car.</speaker>
                  <l>I want</l>
                  <l>Abilities of tongue to anſwer this</l>
                  <l>Your freedome, and the bounty of your nature,</l>
                  <l>Towards my Daughter, and ſo far am from</l>
                  <l>Exception to <hi>Fernando,</hi> there's no <hi>Cavalliero</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>In <hi>Spain</hi> I wiſh to thrive ſo well in her opinion.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Ramy.</speaker>
                  <l>T will be his encouragement,</l>
                  <l>If he entrench upon no others intereſt,</l>
                  <l>I mean not to except, how well he can</l>
                  <l>Deſerve her nobly from a Rivall, if</l>
                  <l>Her heart be not contracted, this were to</l>
                  <l>Engage'em both to loſs of Peace, and Honor,</l>
                  <pb facs="tcp:153588:11"/>
                  <pb facs="tcp:153588:12"/>
                  <pb n="7" facs="tcp:153588:12"/>
                  <l>Perhaps betray a Life.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Car.</speaker>
                  <l>You argue nobly,</l>
                  <l>She is yet Miſtris of her thoughts, and free,</l>
                  <l>While her Obedience doth keep in truſt</l>
                  <l>Her heart; till I direct it, which ſhall be</l>
                  <l>To love, and chooſe your Son to live within it.</l>
                  <l>Have I ſaid home?</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Ramy.</speaker>
                  <l>You have. When they have met</l>
                  <l>We may conclude the Doury, and confirm</l>
                  <l>Our mutuall aſſurances, till then farewel.</l>
               </sp>
               <stage>Exit.</stage>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Car.</speaker>
                  <l>I like this well; <hi>Ramyres</hi> has</l>
                  <l>A fortune for a Grande. <hi>Don Alberto</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>Muſt now excuſe me, if my vote preferre</l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Fernando,</hi> whom my Daughter muſt accept</l>
                  <l>Or forfeit me. The new gueſt is not warm</l>
                  <l>In his acceſs, and ſha'not feel with what</l>
                  <l>Soft art, and ſubtle wayes, I ſteer her paſſion;</l>
                  <l>Yet were <hi>Alberto</hi>'s ſtate ten <hi>Maravides</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>Above <hi>Ramyre</hi>'s, I ſhould place him firſt.</l>
                  <l>Fame is an empty noiſe, Virtue a word</l>
                  <l>There's not a Jew will lend two Ducate; on.</l>
                  <l>He is return'd, I muſt prepare <hi>Jacinta.</hi>
                  </l>
               </sp>
               <stage>Exit.</stage>
               <stage>Enter Ramyres and Fernando.</stage>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Fer.</speaker>
                  <l>I hope my paſt life hath not ſir ſo ill</l>
                  <l>Deſerv'd, you ſhould be jealous of my duty</l>
                  <l>When you command, although in things of this</l>
                  <l>High nature, man being nothing more concern'd,</l>
                  <l>Next the divine conſiderations,</l>
                  <l>Than in the choyce of her that muſt divide</l>
                  <l>The joyes and ſufferings of his life, a Son</l>
                  <l>May modeſtly inſiſt upon the privilege</l>
                  <l>That Love by his great charter hath conferr'd</l>
                  <l>On every heart, not to be forc'd, yet I</l>
                  <l>Freely reſign my will, and what men call</l>
                  <l>Affection, to that object you preſent me.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Ramyr.</speaker>
                  <l>Apply your ſelf then to <hi>Don Carlo</hi>'s daughter</l>
                  <pb n="8" facs="tcp:153588:13"/>
                  <l>Shee's young, fair, rich, and virtuous, and I've had</l>
                  <l>Full treatie with her Father, who expects</l>
                  <l>Your vifit.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Fer.</speaker>
                  <l>Young, fair, rich, and virtuous,</l>
                  <l>Four excellencies ſeldom met in one;</l>
                  <l>She cannot ſure want ſervants, that commands</l>
                  <l>Under ſo many titles. I could wiſh,</l>
                  <l>(So much I have ambition to be thought</l>
                  <l>Obedient ſir,) ſhe were but one of thoſe.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Ramy.</speaker>
                  <l>She is all, and one.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Fer.</speaker>
                  <l>My duty were not leſs</l>
                  <l>If I forgave my ſelf a happineſs</l>
                  <l>To perfect your comands; ſir, I am ready,</l>
                  <l>To try my fortune.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Ramy.</speaker>
                  <l>There is no fear of thy repulſe, and when</l>
                  <l>Thou doſt confirm her gain'd to thy affection,</l>
                  <l>My greateſt act, and care of life is over.</l>
                  <l>Go on and proſper.</l>
               </sp>
               <stage>Exit</stage>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Fer.</speaker>
                  <l>He is paſſionate,</l>
                  <l>And like the fury of the winds, more loud</l>
                  <l>By oppoſition; ſuch a providence</l>
                  <l>May be mine one day when I am a Father,</l>
                  <l>And he for whoſe advance my cares are meant,</l>
                  <l>Like me, may with a fair and formall ſhew</l>
                  <l>Diſguiſe his thoughts too, yet I am to blame,</l>
                  <l>For my affection to a dream, a thing</l>
                  <l>With which my eyes only converſt, to hazard</l>
                  <l>A Fathers love, and the rich peace it brings;</l>
                  <stage>Enter Franciſco.</stage>
                  <l>I'l uncreate the face I dote upon</l>
                  <l>And be my ſelf, or — what? my brother?</l>
                  <l>Now <hi>Franciſco,</hi> you met my father?</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Fran.</speaker>
                  <l>Yes, and he</l>
                  <l>Lookes as ſome newes had much exalted him.</l>
                  <l>You are not ſo merry in the face, what Is't?</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Ferd.</speaker>
                  <l>Nothing.</l>
               </sp>
               <pb facs="tcp:153588:13"/>
               <pb facs="tcp:153588:14"/>
               <pb n="9" facs="tcp:153588:14"/>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Fran.</speaker>
                  <l>You held no controverſies with him?</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Ferd.</speaker>
                  <l>no.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Fran.</speaker>
                  <l>I cannot gueſs he was angry by his ſmiles;</l>
                  <l>How did you part?</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Ferd.</speaker>
                  <l>exceding kindly.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Fran.</speaker>
                  <l>What changes your complexion?</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Ferd.</speaker>
                  <l>Th'art deceived.</l>
                  <l>Pre'the' how do men look that are in love?</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Fran.</speaker>
                  <l>Why? as they did before; what alteration</l>
                  <l>Have you obſerv'd in me?</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Ferd.</speaker>
                  <l>You have then a Miſtris,</l>
                  <l>And thrive upon her favours but thou art</l>
                  <l>My brother, I' deliver thee a ſecret,</l>
                  <l>I was at St. <hi>Sebaſtians</hi> laſt Sunday</l>
                  <l>At Veſpers.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Fran.</speaker>
                  <l>Is it a ſecret that you went to church?</l>
                  <l>You need not bluſh to tell your ghoſtly Father.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Ferd.</speaker>
                  <l>I pre'thee leave thy impertinence; there I ſaw</l>
                  <l>So ſweet a face, ſo harmleſs, ſo intent</l>
                  <l>Upon her prayers, it froſted my devotion</l>
                  <l>To gaze on her, till by degrces I took</l>
                  <l>Her fair Idea through my covetous eye,</l>
                  <l>Into my heart, and know not how to eaſe</l>
                  <l>It fince of the impreſſion.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Fran.</speaker>
                  <l>So, proceed.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Fer.</speaker>
                  <l>Her eye did ſeem to labour with a tear,</l>
                  <l>Which ſuddenly took birth, but overweigh'd</l>
                  <l>With it's own ſwelling, drop'd upon her boſome,</l>
                  <l>Which by reflexion of her light, appear'd</l>
                  <l>As nature meant her ſorrrw for an ornament;</l>
                  <l>After her looks grew chearfull, and I ſaw</l>
                  <l>A ſmile ſhoot gracefull upward from her eyes,</l>
                  <l>As if they had gain'd a victory o'r grief,</l>
                  <l>And with it many beames twiſted themſelves,</l>
                  <l>Upon whoſe golden threads the Angells walk</l>
                  <l>To and again from heaven.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Fran.</speaker>
                  <l>I do beleeve</l>
                  <l>By all theſe metaphors, you are in love;</l>
                  <l>I ſee you have a fancie, but proceed,</l>
                  <pb n="10" facs="tcp:153588:15"/>
                  <l>And be not melancholy.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Ferd.</speaker>
                  <l>I have told thee all.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Fran.</speaker>
                  <l>This is indeed a viſion; you have</l>
                  <l>But ſeen her all this while, if I may counſell you</l>
                  <l>You ſhould proceed, her face is nothing when</l>
                  <l>You have perus'd the reſt.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Ferd.</speaker>
                  <l>Tis dangerous.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Fran.</speaker>
                  <l>You muſt excuſe me Brother,</l>
                  <l>There can be no hurt in a handſome woman,</l>
                  <l>For if her face delight ſo much, what will</l>
                  <l>The enjoying of ſo ſweet a pile of beauty?</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Ferd.</speaker>
                  <l>Thou haſt infus'd a confidence, I will</l>
                  <l>Embrace this counſell, you ſhall with me Brother,</l>
                  <l>And ſee how I behave my-ſelf, the Lady</l>
                  <l>Is not far off.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Fran.</speaker>
                  <l>Withall my heart, I'e pawn</l>
                  <l>My life you ſhall enjoy her; what is ſhe</l>
                  <l>Of fleſh, and blood, that will deny, when ſhe</l>
                  <l>Is fairly courted? may I know the name</l>
                  <l>Of this lov'd Mrs? you may clear your thoughts,</l>
                  <l>I dare have no deſign to wrong your love.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Ferd.</speaker>
                  <l>What think you Brother of the fair <hi>Jacinta?</hi>
                  </l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Fran.</speaker>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Don Carlo</hi>'s Daughter?</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Ferd.</speaker>
                  <l>To that happy coaſt</l>
                  <l>I now am ſayling; we loſe time, clap on</l>
                  <l>More wings thou feather'd God; thou haſt put fire</l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Franciſco</hi> into my drooping thoughts, and as</l>
                  <l>They had already bargaind with the wind,</l>
                  <l>They are aloft, and chide loves lazie motion.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Fran.</speaker>
                  <l>A word before you fly; but is <hi>Jacinta</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>Your Miſtris then?</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Ferd.</speaker>
                  <l>The beautifull <hi>Jacinta.</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>Doſt think I ſha'not proſper? what is ſhe</l>
                  <l>Of fleſh and blood, that can deny, when ſhe</l>
                  <l>Is fairly courted? add to this my happineſs,</l>
                  <l>That ſhee's the Miſtris, whom, from all her ſex</l>
                  <l>My Father hath made choice of for my courtſhip;</l>
                  <pb facs="tcp:153588:15"/>
                  <pb facs="tcp:153588:16"/>
                  <pb n="11" facs="tcp:153588:16"/>
                  <l>He hath already treated with <hi>Don Carlos,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>And 'twas his laſt command, I ſhould addreſs</l>
                  <l>My preſent viſit to her.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Fran.</speaker>
                  <l>Very well;</l>
                  <l>If this be truth, you need not trouble wings</l>
                  <l>To overtake this Lady, to my knowledge</l>
                  <l>(I'm ſerious now) ſhe has beſtowd her heart</l>
                  <l>Vpon a friend, who has already fortified</l>
                  <l>Himſelf againſt the world, that would oppoſe</l>
                  <l>His title to't.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Ferd.</speaker>
                  <l>From what intelligence</l>
                  <l>Have you gaind this? her Father knows it not.</l>
                  <l>Come, theſe are but ſubtle pretences ſcattered</l>
                  <l>By ſome, who cunningly thus hope to make</l>
                  <l>Themſelves a victory, by cutting off</l>
                  <l>More fruitfull expectations, this muſt</l>
                  <l>Not diſingage me, prithee walk.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Fran.</speaker>
                  <l>I can produce my Author, here, <hi>Fernando.</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>And with my blood defend that intereſt</l>
                  <l>She gave me, with intent I ſhould preſerve it.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Ferd.</speaker>
                  <l>How, is ſhe yours <hi>Franciſco?</hi>
                  </l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Fran.</speaker>
                  <l>Mine, if hearts</l>
                  <l>Have power to make aſſurance.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Ferd.</speaker>
                  <l>Tis ſome happineſs</l>
                  <l>I have no ſtranger to oppoſe, whoſe high</l>
                  <l>And ſtubborn ſoul would not releaſe this treaſure</l>
                  <l>But make me force it through his blood. <hi>Franciſco</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>And <hi>Fernando</hi> are two rillets from one Spring,</l>
                  <l>I will not doubt he will reſigne, to make</l>
                  <l>Me fortunate; or ſhould his will be cold</l>
                  <l>And ſome cloſe thoughts ſuggeſt I had no privilege</l>
                  <l>By Eldeſt birth, but came a ſlie Intruder</l>
                  <l>Upon his right of love, there is a tye</l>
                  <l>Of Nature and Obedience to a Father</l>
                  <l>Will make him give this bleſſing from his boſom,</l>
                  <l>And ſtrip his amorous ſoul of all his wealth</l>
                  <l>That may Inveſt my wiſhes.</l>
               </sp>
               <pb n="12" facs="tcp:153588:17"/>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Fran.</speaker>
                  <l>I read not this</l>
                  <l>In any of the reverend Caſuiſts;</l>
                  <l>No inequality being in our blood</l>
                  <l>The law of nature meant we ſhould be equal;</l>
                  <l>It was firſt tyranny, then partiall cuſto me,</l>
                  <l>Made you more capable of Land. Would you</l>
                  <l>Be lord of us, becauſe you are firſt born,</l>
                  <l>And make our ſouls your tenants too? when I've</l>
                  <l>Nam'd you my Elder brother, I exclude</l>
                  <l>All ſervitude; Juſtice that makes me love you</l>
                  <l>Carries an equall law to both;</l>
                  <l>Nay I can love you more if I conſider you</l>
                  <l>(Without the chain of blood) a freind, than all</l>
                  <l>The bonds of nature can enforce me to;</l>
                  <l>In both relations give me leave to love you</l>
                  <l>As much as man, but not reſign my Miſtris.</l>
                  <l>You aſcend higher, and perſwade by what</l>
                  <l>Obedience is owing to a Father,</l>
                  <l>They give us life, a good Son keepes it for him,</l>
                  <l>And every drop bled in their cauſe, a glory;</l>
                  <l>I can acknovvledge this, and ſacrifiſe</l>
                  <l>Life, Fortunes, a poor recompence to loſe</l>
                  <l>(Were they all multipli'd) to ſhew my duty;</l>
                  <l>But theſe are things may be reſign'd, a Miſtris</l>
                  <l>Is not a vvealth in ballance vvith the vvorld,</l>
                  <l>But much above the poize of all it's happineſs,</l>
                  <l>And equall vvith our honor, riveted</l>
                  <l>Into our ſoul, it leaves her not, vvhen death</l>
                  <l>Hath ſhook this body off, but flies vvith it</l>
                  <l>More ſvvift, to love it in the other vvorld.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Ferd.</speaker>
                  <l>You are very paſſionate.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Fran.</speaker>
                  <l>I am very juſt,</l>
                  <l>And you ſhall find it brother e'r you tvvine</l>
                  <l>With my <hi>Jacinta,</hi> mine, if vovves may give</l>
                  <l>Poſſeſſion of each other's ſoul.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Ferd.</speaker>
                  <l>No more</l>
                  <pb facs="tcp:153588:17"/>
                  <pb facs="tcp:153588:18"/>
                  <pb n="13" facs="tcp:153588:18"/>
                  <l>May ſhe be worthy of thy heart, till mine</l>
                  <l>Do entertain a treaſon to divide you;</l>
                  <l>But I, to ſatisfie my Father, muſt</l>
                  <l>Preſent my ſelf, and truſt me, will ſo manage</l>
                  <l>My love to her, as thou ſhalt have no cauſe</l>
                  <l>To Interpret me a rivall <hi>O Franciſco</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>Our loves are of a kindred, for mine is</l>
                  <l>Devote to <hi>Feliſarda,</hi> to her Coſen</l>
                  <l>Poor <hi>Feliſarda.</hi>
                  </l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Fran.</speaker>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Theodoros</hi> Daughter?</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Ferd.</speaker>
                  <l>We never yet chang'd language, nor doth ſhe</l>
                  <l>Imagin with what thoughts I honour her;</l>
                  <l>But here is the diſtraction, thou canſt not</l>
                  <l>Expect more oppoſition from <hi>Don Carlos,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>Than I muſt from my Father, if he knew</l>
                  <l>Where I have plac'd my heart.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Fran.</speaker>
                  <l>Let us aſſiſt</l>
                  <l>Each other then, till time, and ſome kind ſtarres</l>
                  <l>Mature our love.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Ferd.</speaker>
                  <l>Let Fathers look at wealth, tis all their Saint:</l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Hearts are freeborn, and love knows no conſtraint.</hi>
                  </l>
               </sp>
               <stage>Exeunt</stage>
            </div>
            <div n="2" type="act">
               <head>ACT II.</head>
               <stage>Enter Luys and Jacinta.</stage>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Luis</speaker>
                  <l>HOw do you like <hi>Alberto</hi> Siſter? is he not</l>
                  <l>A gallant Gentleman?</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Jacin.</speaker>
                  <l>For what good Brother?</l>
                  <l>cannot Judge his Intellectualls,</l>
                  <l>But we have plentie of more proper men</l>
                  <l>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>n <hi>Spain.</hi>
                  </l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Luys</speaker>
                  <l>He is anexcellent Scholar,</l>
                  <l>He was ſtill Emperour in the Schooles, and ſince</l>
                  <l>He ſtudied Logick and Philoſophy,</l>
                  <l>He was the flow'r of's time at <hi>Salamanca.</hi>
                  </l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Iacin.</speaker>
                  <l>Tis pittie he ſhould be gather'd then.</l>
               </sp>
               <pb n="14" facs="tcp:153588:19"/>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Lu</speaker>
                  <l>What be gather'd?</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Ja</speaker>
                  <l>The flower you talk on.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Lu.</speaker>
                  <l>If you affect him Siſter, he may grow,</l>
                  <l>And you may keep him ſtill for ſeed pleaſe you.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Ja.</speaker>
                  <l>And ſell him out at ſowing time to Gardners.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Lu.</speaker>
                  <l>Come, you muſt love him.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Ja.</speaker>
                  <l>Ha's he the Black-art?</l>
                  <l>I know not how Magick or Philters may</l>
                  <l>Prevail, and yet he lookes ſuſpitiouſly.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Lu.</speaker>
                  <l>You think y' are witty now, d'ee hear, you muſt</l>
                  <l>Affect him for my ſake.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Ja.</speaker>
                  <l>Now you ſpeak reaſon;</l>
                  <l>I may for your ſake dote upon him, Brother,</l>
                  <l>This is a conjuration may do much.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Lu.</speaker>
                  <l>Well ſaid,</l>
                  <l>Thou art my Siſter, this good nature ſhews it.</l>
                  <l>And now I'le tell thee, I ha' promis'd him</l>
                  <l>As much as mariage comes too, and I loſe</l>
                  <l>My houor, if my <hi>Don</hi> receive the canvas.</l>
                  <l>He ha's a good eſtate, and I have borrow'd</l>
                  <l>Conſiderable monies of him Siſter,</l>
                  <l>Peeces of eight, and tranſitory Ducats.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Ja.</speaker>
                  <l>Which muſt be paid.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Lu.</speaker>
                  <l>Not if you marry him;</l>
                  <l>Conditions have been thought on.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Ja.</speaker>
                  <l>How? conditions?</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Lu.</speaker>
                  <l>And ſome revenew was convenient</l>
                  <l>To do things like a Gentleman, I may</l>
                  <l>Tell you, my Father is a litle coſtive,</l>
                  <l>Purſe-bound, his penſion cannot find me tooth-picks,</l>
                  <l>I muſt live till he dye 'tis fit you know;</l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Alberto</hi> ha's an Exchequer, which upon</l>
                  <l>Thy ſmiles will ſtill be open.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Ja.</speaker>
                  <l>Very good;</l>
                  <l>Then you upon the matter have ſold me to him</l>
                  <l>To find you ſpending money?</l>
               </sp>
               <pb facs="tcp:153588:19"/>
               <pb facs="tcp:153588:20"/>
               <pb n="15" facs="tcp:153588:20"/>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Lu.</speaker>
                  <l>No, not ſold;</l>
                  <l>W' are at no certain price; ſummes have been lent</l>
                  <l>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>n expectation, or ſo, and may again.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Ja.</speaker>
                  <l>You deſerve Brother I ſhould hate you now.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Lu.</speaker>
                  <l>'Tis all one to me, ſo you love him;</l>
                  <l>For my part I defire but my expences.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Ja.</speaker>
                  <l>What if another man ſupply your wants</l>
                  <l>Upon the ſame conditions of my love?</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Lu.</speaker>
                  <l>I am indifferent, ſo I have my charges,</l>
                  <l>My neceſſary wine and women paid for,</l>
                  <l>Love where you pleaſe your ſelf; I am but one,</l>
                  <l>I would not ſee him want that's all, becauſe</l>
                  <l>My Father is not yet reſolv'd about</l>
                  <l>His going to heaven.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Ja.</speaker>
                  <l>Well ſir, for <hi>Don Alberto,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>You ſhall be his advocate no more, and there's</l>
                  <l>A Fee to bribe your ſilence in his cauſe.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Lu.</speaker>
                  <l>Why, thank you ſiſter,— will you dye a virgin?</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Ja.</speaker>
                  <l>Why do yo ask?</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Lu.</speaker>
                  <l>I would ſpeak for ſomebody, tell me but whom</l>
                  <l>You have a mind to, and I'le plead for him,</l>
                  <l>And if he be a <hi>Don</hi> he will confider it;</l>
                  <l>You may give me what you will, beſides.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Ja.</speaker>
                  <l>When I</l>
                  <l>Reſolve, You ſhall be acquainted.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Lu.</speaker>
                  <l>But d'ee hear,</l>
                  <l>Untill you do reſolve, I would loſe no time,</l>
                  <l>'Tis good keeping a freind, and a warm client;</l>
                  <l>You may look lovingly upon <hi>Alberto,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>And let him hope at all adventures, in</l>
                  <l>Two moneths you may be otherwiſe provided</l>
                  <l>And he may hang himſelf, i'th meane time</l>
                  <l>Some favours now and then to the poor Gentleman</l>
                  <l>Will doe him good, and me no hurt, beſides</l>
                  <l>You'l pleaſe my Father in't, whoſe vote is for him,</l>
                  <l>And that's a thing materiall. I am</l>
                  <pb n="16" facs="tcp:153588:21"/>
                  <l>To meet with <hi>Don Alberto,</hi> and ſome Gentlemen,</l>
                  <l>I will preſerve his confidence, and tell him</l>
                  <l>I ha' talkd with thee. Have you any more</l>
                  <l>Of this complexion? cauſe I know not what</l>
                  <l>Occaſions I may have to keep my credit</l>
                  <l>With men of mark and honour, vvhere I am going;</l>
                  <l>You are my Fathers darling, and command</l>
                  <l>His yellovv Ingots; tother <hi>Doblon D'oro.</hi>
                  </l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Ja.</speaker>
                  <l>So I may bring a rent-charge upon my ſelf.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Lu.</speaker>
                  <l>The tother drop of orient mercie, come.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Ja.</speaker>
                  <l>You care not vvhat accounts I give my Father.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Lu.</speaker>
                  <l>Thou haſt tvventy vvayes to coſen him, vvedge i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>
                  </l>
                  <l>Into the next Bill, he vvears Spectacles,</l>
                  <l>And loves to read—<hi>Item</hi> for pious uſes.</l>
                  <l>Can it be leſs to help a brother? vvell ſaid.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Ja.</speaker>
                  <l>Let not this feed your riot.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Luys</speaker>
                  <l>By no means.</l>
                  <l>I am for no <hi>Carthuſians</hi> to day.</l>
                  <stage>Enter Carlos, Fernando, Franciſco, and Feliſarda.</stage>
                  <l>Farevvell dear Siſter—vvho is that?</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Ja.</speaker>
                  <l>My Father</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Lu.</speaker>
                  <l>I cannot indure that old mans company.</l>
               </sp>
               <stage>Exit.</stage>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Car.</speaker>
                  <l>I am paſt complement, and muſt acknovvledge</l>
                  <l>Your fair intentions honor us, ſhe is no Goddeſs</l>
                  <l>Of beauty Sir, but let me without pride</l>
                  <l>Boaſt my ſelf bleſt, <hi>Fernando,</hi> in her virtues,</l>
                  <l>And that which crowns em all obedience.</l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Jacinta,</hi> Entertain this Gentleman</l>
                  <l>With all becoming thoughts of Love, his merit</l>
                  <l>(Out of no raſh, but mature judgement,) hath</l>
                  <l>Prevaild with me, to name him to the firſt</l>
                  <l>And nobleſt place within your heart.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Ferd.</speaker>
                  <l>Untill this hour I never had the conſidence</l>
                  <l>More than to think of love, and hide a flame</l>
                  <l>That almoſt hath conſum'd me. You may think</l>
                  <pb facs="tcp:153588:21"/>
                  <pb facs="tcp:153588:22"/>
                  <pb n="17" facs="tcp:153588:22"/>
                  <l>It worth a ſmile, and that <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 span">
                        <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                     </gap> flouriſh</l>
                  <l>To ſhew my vanity of wit or language,</l>
                  <l>But when you underſtand that I bring hither</l>
                  <l>No young affection, but a love took in</l>
                  <l>Long ſince at my ambitious eye, it may</l>
                  <l>Beget your gentle thought, or will, to cure me.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Jac.</speaker>
                  <l>Pardon me, if the more you ſtrive to print</l>
                  <l>A truth on this ſhort ſtory of your paſſion,</l>
                  <l>The more I find my ſelf inclin'd to wonder,</l>
                  <l>Since you ſeem to inferre, You took in the</l>
                  <l>Diſeaſe at ſight of me, I cannot be</l>
                  <l>So ignorant, as not to have receiv'd</l>
                  <l>Your Name and Character, but never knew</l>
                  <l>Before, when you did grace us with a viſit,</l>
                  <l>And how then at ſuch diſtance you contracted</l>
                  <l>A danger ſo conſuming, is above</l>
                  <l>My knowledge, not my pittie, if you could</l>
                  <l>Direct me to the cure with Virgin honor.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Car.</speaker>
                  <l>So, ſo, I leave you to the amorous Dialogue,</l>
                  <l>Preſume you have my voice.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Jac.</speaker>
                  <l>Sir, with your pardon,</l>
                  <l>You lead me to a Wilderneſs, and take</l>
                  <l>Your ſelf away, that ſhould be guide; do you</l>
                  <l>Engage me to affect this <hi>Don Fernando</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>In earneſt?</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Car.</speaker>
                  <l>Yes.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Jac.</speaker>
                  <l>You did direct my love</l>
                  <l>To <hi>Don Alberto.</hi>
                  </l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Car.</speaker>
                  <l>I diſpence with that</l>
                  <l>Command; you may by fair degrees, and honor,</l>
                  <l>Quit his addreſſes, and diſpoſe your ſelf</l>
                  <l>Miſtris and Bride to <hi>Don Ramyres</hi> heir.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Feliſ.</speaker>
                  <l>It does not thus become you ſir, to mock</l>
                  <l>A Virgin never injur'd you; he is</l>
                  <l>Your elder Brother, I am here beneath</l>
                  <l>The levell of his thoughts, i'th' nature of</l>
                  <l>A ſervant to my Coſen, and depend</l>
                  <pb n="18" facs="tcp:153588:23"/>
                  <l>Upon my Uncles charity.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Fran.</speaker>
                  <l>May I be</l>
                  <l>Curſt in my own affections, if I</l>
                  <l>Delude thee, though to atchieve our beſt deſires</l>
                  <l>We ſeem to diſſemble thus before <hi>Don Carlos.</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>This is a ſecret yet to poor <hi>Jacinta.</hi>
                  </l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Car.</speaker>
                  <l>You have my will; obey it.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Ja.</speaker>
                  <l>Hath <hi>Franciſco</hi> broken his faith already?</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Car.</speaker>
                  <l>May you both joy, where you have plac'd your loves.</l>
                  <l>You apply cloſe <hi>Franciſco.</hi>
                  </l>
               </sp>
               <stage>Exit</stage>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Fran.</speaker>
                  <l>With your good favour,</l>
                  <l>I fairty hope.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Ford.</speaker>
                  <l>Your Father's gone <hi>Jacinta.</hi>
                  </l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Ja.</speaker>
                  <l>I ſhould be</l>
                  <l>Equally pleas'd if you would leave me too.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Feliſ.</speaker>
                  <l>This is a change.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Ja.</speaker>
                  <l>Unkind <hi>Franciſco</hi> hear me.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Fran.</speaker>
                  <l>Tis my meaning. Brother I ha' prepard</l>
                  <l>Your ſtory there with <hi>Feliſarda;</hi> loſe</l>
                  <l>No time.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Ferd.</speaker>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Jacinta,</hi> clear your thoughts agen,</l>
                  <l>And pardon that I took a ſhape to fright you;</l>
                  <l>I ſhall not grieve to ſee <hi>Franciſco</hi> proſper,</l>
                  <l>And merit all your favours, ſince my hopes</l>
                  <l>Muſt thrive, or have their Funerall here.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Ja.</speaker>
                  <l>Are we</l>
                  <l>So bleſt <hi>Franciſco?</hi> th'ast a noble Brother.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Ferd.</speaker>
                  <l>I may ſuppoſe my Brother, <hi>Feliſarda,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>Hath made it now no ſecret, that I love you;</l>
                  <l>And ſince our ſtars have ſo contriv'd, that we</l>
                  <l>Have means to aſſiſt our mutuall ambitions,</l>
                  <l>Do not you make their influence unprofitable;</l>
                  <l>Tis the firſt boldneſs I ere tooke to viſit you,</l>
                  <l>Although my eyes have often with delight</l>
                  <l>And ſatisfaction to my heart obſerv'd you.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>
                     <hi>
                        <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>eliſ.</hi>
                  </speaker>
                  <l>You ſeem a noble Gentleman, and can take</l>
                  <pb facs="tcp:153588:23"/>
                  <pb facs="tcp:153588:24"/>
                  <pb n="19" facs="tcp:153588:24"/>
                  <l>But litle glory to undo a Maid,</l>
                  <l>Whoſe Fortunes cannot bring you any triumph.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Ferd.</speaker>
                  <l>How mean you faireſt?</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Feliſ.</speaker>
                  <l>Not to be flattered Sir</l>
                  <l>Into a ſin, to cure my poverty;</l>
                  <l>For men whoſe expectations are like yours,</l>
                  <l>Come not with honour to court ſuch as I am,</l>
                  <l>(Loſt to the World for want of portion)</l>
                  <l>But with ſome untam'd heat of blood.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Fer.</speaker>
                  <l>I dare</l>
                  <l>With conſcience of my pure intent, try what</l>
                  <l>Rudeneſs you find upon my lip, tis chaſt</l>
                  <l>As the deſires that breath upon my language.</l>
                  <l>I began <hi>Feliſarda</hi> to affect thee</l>
                  <l>By ſeeing thee at Prayers, thy vertue wing'd</l>
                  <l>Loves Arrow firſt, and 'twere a ſacrilege</l>
                  <l>To chooſe thee now for ſin, that haſt a power</l>
                  <l>To make this place a Temple by thy Innocence.</l>
                  <l>I know thy poverty, and came not to</l>
                  <l>Bribe it againſt thy chaſtity; if thou</l>
                  <l>Vouchſafe thy fair and honeſt love, it ſhall</l>
                  <l>Adorn my fortunes, which ſhall ſtoop to ſerve it</l>
                  <l>In ſpight of friends or deſtiny.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Fran.</speaker>
                  <l>My Brother</l>
                  <l>Knows my whole Intereſt in thee, to whom</l>
                  <l>My Fathers care directed him, but we</l>
                  <l>Thus mutually reſolve to aid each other.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Ja.</speaker>
                  <l>This muſt be wiſely manag'd of all ſides;</l>
                  <l>Parents have narrow eyes.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Fran.</speaker>
                  <l>Our meeting thus</l>
                  <l>Will happily ſecure us from their Jealouſie;</l>
                  <l>Our Fathers muſt not know this countermarch.</l>
               </sp>
               <stage>Enter Carlos.</stage>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Car.</speaker>
                  <l>Ha; I like not this; <hi>Fernando</hi> at buſie courtſhip</l>
                  <l>With <hi>Feliſarda,</hi> and <hi>Franciſco</hi> ſo</l>
                  <l>Cloſe with my Daughter.</l>
               </sp>
               <pb n="20" facs="tcp:153588:25"/>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Jac.</speaker>
                  <l>Las we are betrail'd.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Feliſ.</speaker>
                  <l>My Unkle.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Ferd.</speaker>
                  <l>You are her Kinſwoman, and of her boſom,</l>
                  <l>I prethee in my abſence, plead to fair</l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Jacinta</hi> for me; as an earneſt of</l>
                  <l>My gratitude, accept this trifle from me.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Car.</speaker>
                  <l>Ha, 'tis a Jewell.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Feliſ.</speaker>
                  <l>Without this reward</l>
                  <l>I ſhould ſolicite ſir your cauſe, and do</l>
                  <l>My duty to <hi>Ton Carlos,</hi> who deſires it.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Ferd.</speaker>
                  <l>I take my leave.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Fran.</speaker>
                  <l>Madam, I ſhall be proud</l>
                  <l>To call you Siſter, but you will prepare</l>
                  <l>Another happineſs if you vouchſafe</l>
                  <l>To ſpeak for me to pretty <hi>Feliſarda,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>She 's bound to hear your counſel and obey it,</l>
                  <l>If I may owe this favour to your charity.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Jacin.</speaker>
                  <l>Your goodneſs will deſerve more.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Fran.</speaker>
                  <l>I muſt follow him.</l>
               </sp>
               <stage>Exit.</stage>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Car.</speaker>
                  <l>Do you take notice <hi>Feliſarda,</hi> that</l>
                  <l>You live here on the bounty of an Unkle?</l>
                  <l>Your Father had but ill news from the Indies.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Feliſ.</speaker>
                  <l>Sir, as your goodneſs wants no teſtimony,</l>
                  <l>I ſhall attend it with all humble ſervices.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Car.</speaker>
                  <l>How durſt you in the preſence of my Daughter,</l>
                  <l>Maintain ſuch whiſpers with <hi>Fernando,</hi> ha?</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Feliſ.</speaker>
                  <l>Sir, he was pleas'd—</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Car.</speaker>
                  <l>No more, I here diſcharge you.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Jacinta,</speaker>
                  <l>I'l provide one to attend you</l>
                  <l>With leſs relation to your blood. I'l hear</l>
                  <l>Of no defence, away—out of my dores.</l>
                  <l>Go to your Father <hi>Signior Teodo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>o:</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>His ſhips may riſe agen were ſunk by th' <hi>Hollander,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>And Fleet from St. <hi>Thome,</hi> he may prefer you</l>
                  <l>To ſome Rich <hi>Don,</hi> or who knows but you may,</l>
                  <l>Born on the Plumes of his eſtate, be made</l>
                  <pb facs="tcp:153588:25"/>
                  <pb n="20" facs="tcp:153588:26"/>
                  <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                     <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <pb facs="tcp:153588:26"/>
                  <pb facs="tcp:153588:27"/>
                  <pb n="21" facs="tcp:153588:27"/>
                  <l>In time a proud <hi>Condeſſa,</hi> ſo <hi>adios</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Mui illuſtre Sennora Feliſarda.</hi>
                  </l>
               </sp>
               <stage>Exit.</stage>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Ja.</speaker>
                  <l>Thus have I heard a tall ſhip has been wrack'd</l>
                  <l>By ſome ſtrange guſt within the <hi>Bay:</hi> his paſſion</l>
                  <l>Admits of no diſpute. O my poor Coſe,</l>
                  <l>I fear my turn is next to be an exile,</l>
                  <l>Thy abſence muſt deprive me of <hi>Franciſco,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>Who can no more glad his <hi>Jacintas</hi> eyes,</l>
                  <l>With a pretence to viſit thee.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Feliſ.</speaker>
                  <l>Tis not</l>
                  <l>My fear to ſuffer want ſo much afflicts me,</l>
                  <l>As that I muſt loſe you, but he returnes.</l>
               </sp>
               <stage>Enter Carlos with a Letter, and Servant.</stage>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Car.</speaker>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Don Pedro de Fuente Calada</hi> comming hither,</l>
                  <l>With <hi>Don Alberto,</hi> and my Son?</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Serv.</speaker>
                  <l>Yes ſir, the Count deſires to ſee <hi>Jacinta</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>Whom your Son has ſo commended, and ſent me</l>
                  <l>To give you notice.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Car.</speaker>
                  <l>Ha <hi>Iacinta,</hi> retire</l>
                  <l>To your cloſet, and put on your richeſt Jewels,</l>
                  <l>A Count is come to viſit you; <hi>Feliſarda</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>There may be ſome more art us'd in her dreſs,</l>
                  <l>To take the eyes of greatneſs.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Iac.</speaker>
                  <l>Sir you ſpeak</l>
                  <l>As I were meant for ſacrifice, or ſale;</l>
                  <l>The Count <hi>Don Pedro</hi>—</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Car.</speaker>
                  <l>No reply; be carefull,</l>
                  <l>And humble in your office <hi>Feliſarda,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>And you may live, and eat here, till <hi>Iacinta</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>Provide another ſervant to attend her,</l>
                  <l>Which may be three whole dayes; my anger is</l>
                  <l>Not everlaſting; bid my Wife come to me.</l>
                  <stage>Enter Alſimira.</stage>
                  <l>I expect an honourable gueſt, the Count <hi>Don Pedro,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>To ſee our Daughter, whom I have commanded</l>
                  <pb n="22" facs="tcp:153588:28"/>
                  <l>To appear with all her riches to attract him.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Alſi.</speaker>
                  <l>If his Intents be honourable, I have heard</l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Don Pedro</hi> loves a hanſom <hi>Donna.</hi>
                  </l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Car.</speaker>
                  <l>He had better cool his hot blood i'the froſen</l>
                  <l>Sea, and riſe thence a rock of Adamant</l>
                  <l>To draw more wonder to the North, than but</l>
                  <l>Attempt to wrong her chaſtity.</l>
                  <stage>Enter Don Pedro, Luys and Alberto.</stage>
                  <l>This from <hi>Don Pedro</hi> is an honor binds</l>
                  <l>The ſervice of our lives.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Ped.</speaker>
                  <l>Noble <hi>Don Carlos.</hi>
                  </l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Alſi.</speaker>
                  <l>If we had been prepar'd, we ſhould have met</l>
                  <l>This grace with more becoming Entertainment.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Ped.</speaker>
                  <l>Tis fair, and equall to my wiſhes,—ſhe</l>
                  <l>Does ſmel of roſted Garlick; this your Siſter?</l>
               </sp>
               <stage>He kiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes Al.</stage>
               <stage>Enter Jacinta and Feliſarda.</stage>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Luys</speaker>
                  <l>That is my Mother, here is <hi>Jacinta</hi> Sir.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Ped.</speaker>
                  <l>She has a tempting ſhape, I now am pleas'd.</l>
                  <l>I Uſe to kiſs all; hum a pretty thing?</l>
               </sp>
               <stage>To Pheliſ.</stage>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Car.</speaker>
                  <l>I like not his buſie eyes on <hi>Feliſarda.</hi>
                  </l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Alber.</speaker>
                  <l>You will be faithfull to me?</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Luys</speaker>
                  <l>Who, I faithfull? how ſhall I live elſe?</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Car.</speaker>
                  <l>Son <hi>Luys.</hi>
                  </l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Alber.</speaker>
                  <l>Madam.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Ped.</speaker>
                  <l>Will you be pleas'd admit <hi>Don Pedro,</hi> by</l>
                  <l>The Title of your ſervant, to preſume</l>
                  <l>Somtime to wait upon you.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Jacin.</speaker>
                  <l>It were pride</l>
                  <l>And ſawcy ambition ſir in me, to think</l>
                  <l>You can deſcend ſo much from your great birth,</l>
                  <l>To own a name, and office ſo beneath you.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Ped.</speaker>
                  <l>I that before thought women eaſie trifles,</l>
                  <l>And things which nature meant only to quench</l>
                  <l>High flames in man, am taken with this Lady.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Luys</speaker>
                  <l>thou haſt wrong'd the fair <hi>Jacinta,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>Thy praiſe was thyn, and cold, <hi>Spain</hi> is not rich</l>
                  <pb facs="tcp:153588:28"/>
                  <pb facs="tcp:153588:29"/>
                  <pb n="23" facs="tcp:153588:29"/>
                  <l>Enough to boaſt her equall: and I love her.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Luys</speaker>
                  <l>Oh ſhe will be to proud to know it Sir.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Ped.</speaker>
                  <l>Proud, ſhe muſt be, whoſe eyes have ſuch com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mand.</l>
                  <l>She has a pretty ſervant too, <hi>Luys,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>I like 'em both.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Luys.</speaker>
                  <l>How, both?</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Ped.</speaker>
                  <l>They will do well,</l>
                  <l>One for a Wife, the other for a Concubine.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Luys</speaker>
                  <l>It will becom your high blood.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Ped.</speaker>
                  <l>Say I kiſs</l>
                  <l>Her white hand, and preſent her with theſe Pearls?</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Luys</speaker>
                  <l>Your honor ſhall command.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Ped.</speaker>
                  <l>Your Daughter has a moſt magnetick face,</l>
                  <l>And I pronounce her happy, your conſent</l>
                  <l>Confirmes her mine.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Car.</speaker>
                  <l>Ther's nothing in my blood, or fortune, but</l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Don Pedro</hi> ſhall command. I was Propheticall?</l>
                  <l>Come hither <hi>Alſimira,</hi> wouldſt imagine?</l>
                  <l>Hee's taken with <hi>Jacinta,</hi> and hath praid</l>
                  <l>Already my conſent.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Aliſ.</speaker>
                  <l>Believe not all</l>
                  <l>That great men ſpeak are Oracles, our Daughter—</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Car.</speaker>
                  <l>If ſhe be ſtubborn, uncreates her ſelf,</l>
                  <l>Be you wiſe, and counſell her to this ambition,</l>
                  <l>Or thus I looſe you all; ha turn away,</l>
                  <l>That Faery ſhees a Witch, the Count talks with her.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Alb.</speaker>
                  <l>I hope you hold me not Sir leſs deſerving</l>
                  <l>Than when you gave me free acceſs to plead</l>
                  <l>My ſervice to your Daughter—if that <hi>Don</hi>—</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Car.</speaker>
                  <l>Sir you too much prejudicate my thoughts</l>
                  <l>I muſt give due reſpects to men of honor,</l>
                  <l>Nor is it fit I ſhould impoſe upon</l>
                  <l>The Freedom of <hi>Jacintas</hi> love.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Alb.</speaker>
                  <l>Y'are noble.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Car.</speaker>
                  <l>My Lord.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Alb.</speaker>
                  <l>I do not like this <hi>Don.</hi>
                  </l>
               </sp>
               <pb n="24" facs="tcp:153588:30"/>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Luys</speaker>
                  <l>Th'art of my mind, I do not like him neither,</l>
                  <l>And yet the blackbirds in the buſh, ſee what</l>
                  <l>preſent be would give my ſiſter.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Alb.</speaker>
                  <l>Did ſhe refuſe it?</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Luys</speaker>
                  <l>I never mean ſhe ſhall, what wrong my friend?</l>
                  <l>Yet I'l take all, and let him hang himſelf;</l>
                  <stage>embraces him:</stage>
                  <l>If he would ſend his eyes, I would undertake</l>
                  <l>To carry 'em to the I<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>weller, they would off,</l>
                  <l>For pretty coadſtones. Have no fear, my Mother</l>
                  <l>Is for you too, you muſt fee both your Advocates.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Car.</speaker>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Jacinta.</hi>
                  </l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Jacin.</speaker>
                  <l>Sir.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Luys</speaker>
                  <l>She takes her ſelf much honor'd.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Ped.</speaker>
                  <l>You oblige.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Luys</speaker>
                  <l>Let me alone to carry things.</l>
                  <l>Be confident to truſt me with your honor,</l>
                  <l>If it would pawn for any thing.</l>
               </sp>
               <stage>[aſide]</stage>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Iac.</speaker>
                  <l>I'm not perfect</l>
                  <l>How to neglect <hi>Alberto</hi> yet, and muſt I</l>
                  <l>Throw off <hi>Fernando,</hi> but new Entertain'd</l>
                  <l>By your command? the World will conſure ſtrangely.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Car.</speaker>
                  <l>The World will praiſe thy wiſdom, &amp; my care;</l>
                  <l>Or if ſome giddy tongues condemn what's good,</l>
                  <l>Muſt wee be ſervile to that fear, and loſe</l>
                  <l>That which will make us Judges of their folly,</l>
                  <l>And damn it with a frown of ſtate? they'r fooles</l>
                  <l>That dote upon thoſe ſhaddowes, Idle talk,</l>
                  <l>The ſlime of Earth-worms, that doth ſhine to coſen</l>
                  <l>Infants, 'tis fit wee raiſe our thoughts to ſubſtances.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Jac.</speaker>
                  <l>Let modeſty and nature plead a little,</l>
                  <l>If I appear not fond to Entertain him.</l>
                  <l>I may collect more ſtrength by time and counſell,</l>
                  <l>And for your ſatisfaction dare profeſs</l>
                  <l>My Lord hath too much grac'd the low <hi>Jacinta</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>With a pretence ſo noble, but I ſhould</l>
                  <l>Be held not worth his perſon, and too light</l>
                  <pb facs="tcp:153588:30"/>
                  <pb facs="tcp:153588:31"/>
                  <pb n="25" facs="tcp:153588:31"/>
                  <l>At his firſt breath of courtſhip to fall from</l>
                  <l>My Virgin ſtrength, and give my ſelf his captive.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Car.</speaker>
                  <l>I ſhall alow that ceremony; the Count</l>
                  <l>Makes an addreſs.</l>
               </sp>
               <stage>Ex Alſi. Feliſard.</stage>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Ped.</speaker>
                  <l>I muſt uſe thrift in my delight, my eyes</l>
                  <l>Are prowd, and muſt be taught by abſence how</l>
                  <l>To value ſuch a Miſtris. I do miſs the chambermaid.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Car.</speaker>
                  <l>It will become me to attend.</l>
               </sp>
               <stage>Ex. Alber. &amp; Jacin.</stage>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Ped.</speaker>
                  <l>Your pardon.</l>
                  <l>I'l take it for an honor, if your Sonne</l>
                  <l>Be pleas'd—but to my coach?</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Luys.</speaker>
                  <l>Oh my good Lord!</l>
                  <l>So much I am your creature, if you knew</l>
                  <l>But where to match me, I would be your coach-horſe.</l>
               </sp>
               <stage>Exe. Pedro &amp; Luys.</stage>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Car.</speaker>
                  <l>So, ſo, <hi>Iacinta's</hi> ſtarres do ſmile upon her,</l>
                  <l>'Twil be a match, were but my Son as fair</l>
                  <l>In expectation of a bride, I'd write</l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Nil ultra</hi> to my cares, he is to aery</l>
                  <l>And volatile, a wife would timely fix him,</l>
                  <l>And make him fit to manage my eſtate.</l>
                  <stage>Enter Luys.</stage>
                  <l>But he returnes, I'l feel his pulſe.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Luys,</speaker>
                  <l>thou ſeeſt how near <hi>Iacinta</hi> is to happineſs.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Luys</speaker>
                  <l>I did ſome office in't, ſhe may thank me.</l>
                  <l>I firſt inſpir'd his Lordſhip.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Car.</speaker>
                  <l>Such a providence</l>
                  <l>To build thy ſelf a Fortune by ſome brave</l>
                  <l>And noble mariage would become thy ſtudy,</l>
                  <l>And make thy Father willingly reſign</l>
                  <l>His breath, with confidence to know thee wiſe</l>
                  <l>To govern what my Induſtry hath gatherd;</l>
                  <l>What think'ſt thou of a wife?</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Luys.</speaker>
                  <l>I think little ſir.</l>
                  <pb n="26" facs="tcp:153588:32"/>
                  <l>What ſhould I do with a Wife?</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Car.</speaker>
                  <l>Imitate me, and ſtudy fame, and wealth</l>
                  <l>To thy poſterity. Have I with care</l>
                  <l>Acquir'd ſuch an eſtate, that muſt not laſt</l>
                  <l>Two Generations?</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Luys.</speaker>
                  <l>The way to make it</l>
                  <l>Laſt, is not to think of Wiving; for my part</l>
                  <l>(Sir with your pardon, if I may ſpeak freely)</l>
                  <l>I had opinion once I was your Son,</l>
                  <l>But fearing by your narrow exhibition</l>
                  <l>You lov'd me not, I had a controverſie</l>
                  <l>Within my thoughts, whether I ſhould reſolve</l>
                  <l>To geld my ſelf, or turn a begging Frier.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Car.</speaker>
                  <l>A begging Frier?</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Luys</speaker>
                  <l>Tis as I tell you Sir;</l>
                  <l>This laſt I fixt upon, and ha' been ſtudying</l>
                  <l>Where I conveniently might raiſe a ſum</l>
                  <l>To compaſs a hair ſhirt Sir,</l>
                  <l>To make triall before I thruſt my ſelf</l>
                  <l>Point blank into the Order.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Car.</speaker>
                  <l>Thus wild Sons interpret ſtill</l>
                  <l>A prudent Father; but you may diſcharge</l>
                  <l>Your Jealouſies, unleſs it be your own</l>
                  <l>Devotion to be chaſt, and live a recluſe.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Luys</speaker>
                  <l>For that I can be ruld; I ha' not liv'd</l>
                  <l>After the rate of hating any women</l>
                  <l>But I can hear of Mariage, if it be</l>
                  <l>Your pleaſure: but theſe Wives Sir are ſuch tickle</l>
                  <l>Things, not one hardly ſtaid amongſt a thouſand;</l>
                  <l>Beſide, unleſs you finde one very rich</l>
                  <l>A man may caſt a way himſelf, and get</l>
                  <l>A bundle of Beggeries, Mouths, that day and night,</l>
                  <l>Are open like Hell Gates, to feed; I would not</l>
                  <l>Hazard my Freedom, and the bleſſings Heaven</l>
                  <l>Has lent you Sir, upon a Wife with nothing.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Car.</speaker>
                  <l>Thy penſion doubles for that word; in Earneſt,</l>
                  <pb facs="tcp:153588:32"/>
                  <pb facs="tcp:153588:33"/>
                  <pb n="27" facs="tcp:153588:33"/>
                  <l>How much I like this wiſdom; take this Purſe,</l>
                  <l>I will have no account, and find me out</l>
                  <l>A wealthy Maid or Widdow, but not ugly.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Luys</speaker>
                  <l>No? not ilfavourd Sir, if ſhe be rich?</l>
                  <l>A little old or crippel'd?</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Car.</speaker>
                  <l>I wo'not ha'thee</l>
                  <l>Mary a crooked, deform'd thing, becauſe</l>
                  <l>She may have children—</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Luys</speaker>
                  <l>Not, unleſs ſhe have</l>
                  <l>An Infinit wealth to make 'em ſtrait ſir;</l>
                  <l>I'le marry a witch ſo ſhe have mony ſir.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Car.</speaker>
                  <l>No, on no terms a Monſter.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Luys</speaker>
                  <l>Then I wo'not.</l>
                  <l>And now it comes into my mind, they talk of</l>
                  <l>A young rich Widdow, <hi>Donna Eſtifaniar,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>What do you think of her?</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Car.</speaker>
                  <l>Thou haſt nam'd one</l>
                  <l>To my own deſires, ſhe lives a Widdow ſtill,</l>
                  <l>But ſhe has refus'd many brave <hi>Dons.</hi>
                  </l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Luys.</speaker>
                  <l>No matter,</l>
                  <l>I like her ſir the better.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Car.</speaker>
                  <l>She gives good entertainment.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Luys</speaker>
                  <l>I will have her</l>
                  <l>If you but ſay the word. I wear a charm</l>
                  <l>To catch a Widdow; but this Purſe will hardly</l>
                  <l>Laſt till we finiſh, I muſt do things with honor.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Car.</speaker>
                  <l>Thou ſhalt be furniſh'd like my Son; kneel down</l>
                  <l>And ask me bleſſing, I do long to give it thee.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Luys</speaker>
                  <l>I have your bleſſing here.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Car.</speaker>
                  <l>Ile find thee out</l>
                  <l>Some Jewells to preſent thy Miſtris too.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Luys</speaker>
                  <l>'Two'not be much amiſs, the Gold will go</l>
                  <l>The farther Sir. I know not how this</l>
                  <stage>Exit Car.</stage>
                  <l>Came about, unleſs <hi>Don Pedros</hi> coming to</l>
                  <l>My Siſter ha' made him mad, &amp; wrought this miracle.</l>
                  <l>How carefull he was I ſhould not mary one</l>
                  <pb n="28" facs="tcp:153588:34"/>
                  <l>Deform'd, I ha' choſe the hanſomeſt things thus far,</l>
                  <l>And I mary with a Witch at theſe years, let the Devill</l>
                  <l>Ride my wild Mare to death; and now I</l>
                  <l>Conſider on't I wo'not have the Widdow,</l>
                  <l>For fear o'th'worſt, yet I'l to her,</l>
                  <l>And make a buſineſs on't to keep the old</l>
                  <l>Mans Baggs in motion; this with ſome good</l>
                  <l>Husbandry, and no play, may laſt a Fortnight,</l>
                  <l>Tis very Gold: yes, it will pay ſome ſcores,</l>
                  <l>Maintaine my <hi>Negro,</hi> and a brace of Whores.</l>
                  <l>Now fiddles do your worſt.</l>
               </sp>
               <stage>Exit.</stage>
            </div>
            <div n="3" type="act">
               <head>ACT III.</head>
               <stage>Enter Ramyres, Fernando.</stage>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Ramy.</speaker>
                  <l>How, no ſucceſs? where lies the oppoſition?</l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Don Carlos</hi> equall with my ſelf profeſt</l>
                  <l>His free deſires, and to diſpoſe his Daughter</l>
                  <l>To meet thee with all loving entertainments.</l>
                  <l>What can ſhe argue to thy birth, or perſon,</l>
                  <l>Attended with ſo plentifull a fortune?</l>
                  <l>I muſt believe thy courtſhip dull and faulty:</l>
                  <l>When I was at thy years and ſpring of blood</l>
                  <l>I wound my ſelf like air among the Ladies,</l>
                  <l>Commanding every boſom, and could dwell</l>
                  <l>Upon their lips like their own breath, their eyes</l>
                  <l>Doubled their Beams on me, and ſhe that was</l>
                  <l>Of hardeſt compoſition, whom no love</l>
                  <l>Could ſoften, when I came with charm of language,</l>
                  <l>Her Froſt would ſtrait diſſolve, and from her eyes</l>
                  <l>Her heart came weeping forth to woo me take it.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Ferd.</speaker>
                  <l>Yet you that did with a <hi>Magnetick</hi> Chain</l>
                  <l>Attract ſo many, could poſſeſs but one;</l>
                  <l>I came not to <hi>Don Carlos</hi> houſe with cold</l>
                  <pb facs="tcp:153588:34"/>
                  <pb facs="tcp:153588:35"/>
                  <pb n="29" facs="tcp:153588:35"/>
                  <l>Or lukewarm thoughts, but arm'd with active fire</l>
                  <l>That would have melted any heart but hers,</l>
                  <l>Bound up with ribs of treble Ice againſt me,</l>
                  <l>By which I found there is another fate</l>
                  <l>That governs love, againſt whoſe ſecret doom</l>
                  <l>In vain is eloquence or force.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Ra.</speaker>
                  <l>So Obſtinate?</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Ferd.</speaker>
                  <l>Nothing that I could ſay</l>
                  <l>In my own cauſe, could make her tongue or looks</l>
                  <l>Promiſe an expectation to thrive</l>
                  <l>By any after ſervice, this diſdain</l>
                  <l>I did reſent, as it became my honor,</l>
                  <l>And now confirm'd againſt her pride, have thought</l>
                  <l>Of ſomthing, that with your conſent, may t<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>me</l>
                  <l>Her ſcorn, or puniſh it to her repentance.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Ra.</speaker>
                  <l>Name it.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Ferd.</speaker>
                  <l>She has a Kinſwoman lives with her,</l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Feliſarda</hi> Daughter to <hi>Signior Teodore,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>A trade fall'n Merchant, Brother to <hi>Don Carlos,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>This <hi>Feliſ.</hi> that now lives on the charity of her Uncle,</l>
                  <l>Half ſervant, half companion to <hi>Iacinta,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>And fair, I would pretend to love, obſerve me ſir,</l>
                  <l>And in their preſence court her as my Miſtris;</l>
                  <l>Me thinks I ſee already how <hi>Iacinta</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>Doth fret and frown.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Ra.</speaker>
                  <l>I like it well.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Ferd.</speaker>
                  <l>To ſee her Coſen ſo prefer'd, it is</l>
                  <l>The nature fir of women to be vext</l>
                  <l>When they know any of their ſervants court</l>
                  <l>Another, and that love they thought not worth</l>
                  <l>Their own reward, will ſting 'em to the ſoul,</l>
                  <l>VVhen ti's tranſlated where it meets with love,</l>
                  <l>And this will either break her ſtubborn heart,</l>
                  <l>Or humble her.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Ra.</speaker>
                  <l>But what if this pretence,</l>
                  <l>By ſuch degrees convay avvay your heart,</l>
                  <pb n="30" facs="tcp:153588:36"/>
                  <l>That when <hi>Jacinta</hi> comes to ſenſe, you cannot</l>
                  <l>Retrive your paſſion from the laſt, or ſay</l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Feliſarda</hi> ſhould believe you, and give up</l>
                  <l>Her heart to your poſſeſſion, when you</l>
                  <l>Are by your firſt deſires invited back,</l>
                  <l>What cure for <hi>Feliſardas</hi> wound, if you</l>
                  <l>Affect her not? although I like that part</l>
                  <l>Of your revenge, I would not have my Son</l>
                  <l>Carry the hated brand of cruelty,</l>
                  <l>Or hear <hi>Fernando</hi> broke a Ladies heart;</l>
                  <l>But live upon his clear, and honeſt truth,</l>
                  <l>And if <hi>Jacinta</hi> have not valued him,</l>
                  <l>Find his own eſtimation in ſome other</l>
                  <l>By fair and noble Courtſhip; Virtue is</l>
                  <l>Above the gaudy ſhine of Gold<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> and if</l>
                  <l>My Son love where his honor cannot ſuffer,</l>
                  <l>The want of Dower, I can forgive.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Ferd.</speaker>
                  <l>You now, read exc'lent charity, and like a Father,</l>
                  <l>It is the harmony I would hear, I chide</l>
                  <l>My fears that did ſuſpect you would prefer</l>
                  <l>Wealth in a Bride; there is no beauty, or eſtate, compar'd</l>
                  <l>To that reſulteth from the ſoul; I dare</l>
                  <l>Now ope this narrow Cloſet, and preſent</l>
                  <l>The name I love above the World, it is</l>
                  <l>Sir <hi>Feliſarda,</hi> equall in her blood,</l>
                  <l>Within whoſe vertuous poverty</l>
                  <l>More Treaſures are containd, than in thoſe veins</l>
                  <l>Of earth, which opend by our ſlaves, do bleed</l>
                  <l>Such floods of Gold into the lap of <hi>Spain.</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>Pardon my long concealment of her name,</l>
                  <l>Twas ſin againſt your virtue, and once more</l>
                  <l>Speak in that bleſſed Language, I may hope</l>
                  <l>To call this Virgin mine.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Ra.</speaker>
                  <l>How long have you</l>
                  <l>Been taken with this female holineſs?</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Ferd.</speaker>
                  <l>Before <hi>Jacinta</hi> was propounded, this</l>
                  <pb facs="tcp:153588:36"/>
                  <pb facs="tcp:153588:37"/>
                  <pb n="31" facs="tcp:153588:37"/>
                  <l>Took firm poſſeſſion of my faith.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Ra.</speaker>
                  <l>Thou haſt diſcoverd thy deſtruction, fooliſh Boy.</l>
                  <l>Was this your policy to be reveng'd</l>
                  <l>Upon <hi>Jacinta,</hi> whom my providence</l>
                  <l>Elected to preſerve our name and family,</l>
                  <l>To dote upon a Begger? thou haſt flung</l>
                  <l>A fire into my brain; either reſolve</l>
                  <l>To perfect my commands, and throwing off</l>
                  <l>That trifle thou haſt prais'd, prefer <hi>Jacinta</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>To the beſt ſeat within thy hart, and marry her</l>
                  <l>Or live a ſtranger to me, and diveſted</l>
                  <l>Of all thoſe rights; which nature, and thy Birth</l>
                  <l>Have fla<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ter'd thee with hope to find; expect not</l>
                  <l>Alive, the ſtipend of a Groom to feed thee,</l>
                  <l>Nor dead, the naked charity of a ſhroud</l>
                  <l>To hide thee from the Worms.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Ferd.</speaker>
                  <l>O ſir, call back</l>
                  <l>That murdering ſentence, it were ſin to let</l>
                  <l>This paſſion dvvell upon you, nor vvould Heaven,</l>
                  <l>Whoſe eyes ſurvey our frailty, ſuffer</l>
                  <l>So vvild a rage poſſeſſe you.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Ra</speaker>
                  <l>Tis vvithin thy ovvn obedience to divert it.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Ferd.</speaker>
                  <l>When you have heard vvhat I can ſay more,</l>
                  <l>You vvill chide your fierce command.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Ra.</speaker>
                  <l>What Riddles this?</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Ferd.</speaker>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Jacinta</hi> is already made anothers, and my force</l>
                  <l>Upon her vowes, can be no leſs than ſacrilege.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Ra.</speaker>
                  <l>This is ſome nevv pretence.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Ferd</speaker>
                  <l>Sir, not to vvaſt your patience, ſhe hath given</l>
                  <l>Her ſelf by holy contract to <hi>Franciſco.</hi>
                  </l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Ra.</speaker>
                  <l>Thy younger Brother?</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Ferd.</speaker>
                  <l>This I knovv vvill calm</l>
                  <l>Your fury, and thoſe eyes that threatend lightning</l>
                  <l>VVith ſmiles applaud <hi>Franciſcos</hi> fate, and praiſe</l>
                  <l>My diſobedience.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Ra.</speaker>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Franciſcos</hi> Miſtris?</l>
               </sp>
               <pb n="32" facs="tcp:153588:38"/>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Ferd.</speaker>
                  <l>His wife confirm'd by vows, &amp; change of hearts,</l>
                  <l>I had it from themſelves, when either ſtrove</l>
                  <l>Whoſe circumſtance ſhould credit moſt their ſtory,</l>
                  <l>Her tear or his concluſive groan, to ſeal</l>
                  <l>Their mariage, but both were equall ſir,</l>
                  <l>What curſe had I deſerv'd, that ſhould divorce</l>
                  <l>This Innocent pair of lovers?</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Ra.</speaker>
                  <l>All this talk</l>
                  <l>Which fooliſh thou interpret'ſt thy defence,</l>
                  <l>Hath but inlarg'd thy folly, and that act</l>
                  <l>Which in <hi>Franciſco</hi> I commend, upbraides</l>
                  <l>Thy own degenerate baſeneſs: ſhall thy brother</l>
                  <l>Who carries all his portion in his blood</l>
                  <l>Look high, and carefull of his honor aim</l>
                  <l>At fortunes, and with confidence atchieve</l>
                  <l>His glorious end, and ſhall his Elder brother</l>
                  <l>Ingag'd by neareſt tye to advance his name,</l>
                  <l>Lye beating in the common tract of guls,</l>
                  <l>And ſacrifice his birth and expectations</l>
                  <l>To a cozening face, and poverty? inſtead</l>
                  <l>Of adding mon'ments, that to the world</l>
                  <l>Should be his living Chronicle, to bury</l>
                  <l>His own, and all the antique honors (he</l>
                  <l>Ne'r ſweat for, but were caſt into his blood)</l>
                  <l>Within a dunghill? thou haſt forfeited</l>
                  <l>Thy birthright, which <hi>Franciſco</hi> ſhall inherit,</l>
                  <l>Nor ſhall the loſs of my Eſtate be all</l>
                  <l>Thy puniſhment; hear and believe with horror,</l>
                  <l>If thou renounce not her that hath bewitch'd</l>
                  <l>Thy heart, <hi>Feliſarda,</hi> and by ſuch a choice</l>
                  <l>I ſhall affect, redeem this ſcandall nobly,</l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Fernando</hi> from this minute I pronounce</l>
                  <l>Heir to his Fathers curſe; be vviſe or periſh.</l>
               </sp>
               <stage>Exit. Ra.</stage>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Ferd.</speaker>
                  <l>Why does not all the ſtock of thunder fall?</l>
                  <pb facs="tcp:153588:38"/>
                  <pb facs="tcp:153588:39"/>
                  <pb n="33" facs="tcp:153588:39"/>
                  <stage>Enter Franciſco.</stage>
                  <l>Or the fierce winds from their cloſe Caves, let looſe,</l>
                  <l>Now ſhake me into Atoms?</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Fran.</speaker>
                  <l>Fy noble Brother, what can ſo deject</l>
                  <l>Your Maſculine thoughts? is this don like <hi>Fernando!</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>Whoſe reſolute ſoul ſo late was arm'd to fight</l>
                  <l>With all the miſeries of man, and triumph</l>
                  <l>With patience of a Martyr? I obſerv'd</l>
                  <l>My Father late come from you.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Ferd.</speaker>
                  <l>Yes <hi>Franciſco,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>He hath left his curſe upon me.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Fran.</speaker>
                  <l>How?</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Ferd.</speaker>
                  <l>His curſe, doſt comprehend what that word caryes</l>
                  <l>Shot from a Fathers angry breath? unleſs</l>
                  <l>I tear poor <hi>Feliſarda</hi> from my heart,</l>
                  <l>He hath pronounc'd me heir to all his curſes.</l>
                  <l>Does this fright thee <hi>Franciſco?</hi> thou haſt cauſe</l>
                  <l>To dance in ſoul for this, tis only I</l>
                  <l>Muſt loſe, and mourn, thou ſhalt have all, I am</l>
                  <l>Degraded from my birth, while he affects</l>
                  <l>Thy forward youth, and only calls thee Son,</l>
                  <l>Son of his active ſpirit, and applauds</l>
                  <l>Thy progreſs with <hi>Jacinta,</hi> in whoſe ſmiles</l>
                  <l>Thou maiſt ſee all thy wiſhes waiting for thee,</l>
                  <l>Whilſt poor <hi>Fernando</hi> for her ſake muſt ſtand</l>
                  <l>An excommunicate from every bleſſing,</l>
                  <l>A thing that dare not give my ſelf a name,</l>
                  <l>But flung into the Worlds neceſſities,</l>
                  <l>Untill in time with wonder of my wants</l>
                  <l>I turn a ragged ſtatue, on whoſe forehead</l>
                  <l>Each clown may carve his motto.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Fran.</speaker>
                  <l>Will it call</l>
                  <l>His bleſſing back if you can quit your love</l>
                  <l>To <hi>Feliſarda?</hi> ſhe is now a ſtranger</l>
                  <l>To her Unkles houſe, I met one of his ſervants</l>
                  <l>Who told me on ſome Jealous apprehenſion,</l>
                  <pb n="34" facs="tcp:153588:40"/>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Don Carlos</hi> had diſcharg'd and baniſh'd her.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Ferd.</speaker>
                  <l>He could not be ſo barbarous.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Fran.</speaker>
                  <l>You know her Fathers Poverty.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Ferd.</speaker>
                  <l>And her Wealth of Virtue.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Fran.</speaker>
                  <l>It is worth your Counſell,</l>
                  <l>To examin what you may preſerve, if wiſely</l>
                  <l>You could perſwade your heart to love ſome nother —</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Ferd.</speaker>
                  <l>What was't <hi>Franciſco</hi> ſaid?</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Fran.</speaker>
                  <l>Whoſe equall Birth,</l>
                  <l>And Virtues, may invite a noble change.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Ferd.</speaker>
                  <l>Do not you love <hi>Jacinta?</hi>
                  </l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Fran.</speaker>
                  <l>Moſt religiouſly.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Ferd.</speaker>
                  <l>If you can but contrive your hearts at diſtance</l>
                  <l>And in contempt of honor, and your faith</l>
                  <l>Sacred to Heaven, and love, diſclaim your Miſtris,</l>
                  <l>I may be happy yet, what ſay? I know</l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Jacinta</hi>'s Wiſe, and when ſhe underſtands</l>
                  <l>How much it will advance, her charity—</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Fra.</speaker>
                  <l>Our caſe is not the ſame with your's good brothe<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>
                  </l>
                  <l>Wee have been long acquainted, to contract</l>
                  <l>Affections, if I underſtand, your loves</l>
                  <l>Are young, and had no time for growth.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Ferd.</speaker>
                  <l>Do not wound me.</l>
                  <l>Tis falſe, by Love it ſelf thou haſt deſerv'd</l>
                  <l>'I ſhould forget thee now; doſt thou conſider</l>
                  <l>Love, (that doth make all harmony in our ſoul,</l>
                  <l>And ſeated in that nobleſt place of life,</l>
                  <l>The heart) with things that are the ſlaves of time,</l>
                  <l>And that like common ſeedes, thrown into Earth,</l>
                  <l>It muſt have leiſure to corrupt, and after</l>
                  <l>Much expectation, riſe to name and vigor.</l>
                  <l>Love is not like the child that grows, and gets</l>
                  <l>By ſlow degrees perfection, but created</l>
                  <l>Like the firſt man, at full ſtrength the firſt minute,</l>
                  <l>It makes a noble choice, and gains from time</l>
                  <l>To be call'd only conſtant, not increas'd.</l>
                  <pb facs="tcp:153588:40"/>
                  <pb facs="tcp:153588:41"/>
                  <pb n="35" facs="tcp:153588:41"/>
                  <l>Preſerve thy own affections, and think mine</l>
                  <l>Noble as they, I ſhall ſuſpect thy love</l>
                  <l>To me elſe; prethee leave me.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Fran.</speaker>
                  <l>I'l obey,</l>
                  <l>And ſtudy how to ſerve you.</l>
               </sp>
               <stage>Exit.</stage>
               <stage>Enter Feliſarda.</stage>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Ferd.</speaker>
                  <l>Ha, tis <hi>Feliſarda.</hi>
                  </l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Feliſ.</speaker>
                  <l>Turnd out like one that had been falſe, where ſhall</l>
                  <l>Poor <hi>Feliſarda</hi> wander? were it not</l>
                  <l>To ask a Fathers bleſſing, I would viſit</l>
                  <l>Some Wilderneſs, e'r thus preſent my ſelf</l>
                  <l>His burden and his ſorrow.</l>
               </sp>
               <stage>Enter Pedro.</stage>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Ped.</speaker>
                  <l>Had you no relation to <hi>Jacinta</hi> pretty one?</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Feliſ.</speaker>
                  <l>I was her ſervant.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Ped.</speaker>
                  <l>Come, you ſhall be my Miſtris; they have us'd</l>
                  <l>Thee ſcurvily, I will provide thee a lodging.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Feliſ.</speaker>
                  <l>I ſhall not uſe your bounty ſir for that.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Ped.</speaker>
                  <l>Thou art a hanſom <hi>Dona,</hi> here's a Piſtolet,</l>
                  <l>Meet me i'th'evening, wot?</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Feliſ.</speaker>
                  <l>Where, and for what?</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Ped.</speaker>
                  <l>The where, at thy own choice, the what, thy honor.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Feliſ.</speaker>
                  <l>You are not noble.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Ped.</speaker>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Don Pedro</hi> will Embrace thy buxom body.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Ferd.</speaker>
                  <l>You muſt unhand this Virgin.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Feliſ.</speaker>
                  <l>For goodneſs Sir,</l>
                  <l>Add not your anger to my ſufferings.</l>
                  <l>Unhappy <hi>Feliſarda.</hi>
                  </l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Ped.</speaker>
                  <l>Is ſhe a friend of yours Signior?</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Ferd.</speaker>
                  <l>She is not for your ſinfull knowledge <hi>Don.</hi>
                  </l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Ped.</speaker>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Baſer los manos, adios Signiora. Diabolo!</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>My blood is high and hot, unleſs I marry timely,</l>
                  <l>I muſt ſeek out a Female Julip.</l>
               </sp>
               <stage>Exit.</stage>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Feliſ.</speaker>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Don Carlo's</hi> fear of you was my firſt error,</l>
                  <l>But I accept my baniſhment, and ſhall</l>
                  <l>Humble my ſelf to my poor Fathers Fortune;</l>
                  <pb n="36" facs="tcp:153588:42"/>
                  <l>You will be ſir diſhonour'd to be ſeen</l>
                  <l>Wich ſuch a walking miſtry.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Ferd.</speaker>
                  <l>Thy Unkle</l>
                  <l>Hath plaid the Tyrant with thee, but loſe not</l>
                  <l>Thy vertuous courage; how our ſtories meet</l>
                  <l>And challenge kindred in affliction!</l>
                  <l>Oh <hi>Feliſarda!</hi> I do ſuffer too,</l>
                  <l>And for thy ſake, thou ſhalt know more; til I</l>
                  <l>Salute thee at thy Fathers houſe, preſerve</l>
                  <l>Good thoughts of thy <hi>Fernando,</hi> and accept</l>
                  <l>This litle Gold, no bribe againſt thy honor.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Feliſ.</speaker>
                  <l>My beſt return muſt be, my Prayers.</l>
               </sp>
               <stage>Exit.</stage>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Ferd.</speaker>
                  <l>Farewell.</l>
                  <l>Tis not impoſſible my Father may</l>
                  <l>Retract his cruelty, and by time, and ſome</l>
                  <l>Diſcreet wayes yet be wrought to like, what now</l>
                  <l>His paſſion wo'not let him ſee, her virtue.</l>
                  <l>How many Seas are met to wraſtle here?</l>
               </sp>
               <stage>Exit.</stage>
               <stage>Enter Jacinta and Alberto.</stage>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Iac.</speaker>
                  <l>I love you ſir ſo well, that I could wiſh</l>
                  <l>You were a Witch;</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Alb.</speaker>
                  <l>A Witch, your reaſon Lady?</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Ja.</speaker>
                  <l>Then twere within the circle of your art</l>
                  <l>By ſome device to rid me of <hi>Don Pedro,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>Or if you could by any ſpell but get</l>
                  <l>My Father diſaffect him—</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Alber.</speaker>
                  <l>A Witch? thats a way about, I were beſt cut his</l>
                  <l>Throat a little.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Jac.</speaker>
                  <l>You 're much beholding to my Brother ſir,</l>
                  <l>He ſtill commends you; ſuch an Advocate</l>
                  <l>Deſerves his fee.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Alb.</speaker>
                  <l>Unles my cauſe ſucceed</l>
                  <l>He has been feed too much; your Brother, Lady,</l>
                  <l>Preſerves a noble friendſhip; if I were ſure</l>
                  <l>You would be mine <hi>Jacima,</hi> I could tarry</l>
                  <l>Till your Father dyc.</l>
               </sp>
               <pb facs="tcp:153588:42"/>
               <pb facs="tcp:153588:43"/>
               <pb n="37" facs="tcp:153588:43"/>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Iac.</speaker>
                  <l>But how can you procure</l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Don Pedro</hi> to have patience ſo long,</l>
                  <l>Whom my Father pleads for and prefers?</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Alber.</speaker>
                  <l>There, ther's the miſchief, I muſt poiſon him;</l>
                  <l>One Fig ſends him to <hi>Erebus,</hi> tis in</l>
                  <l>Your power and wit to ſpin out time, I may</l>
                  <l>Invent a means for his conveyance. Ha!</l>
               </sp>
               <stage>Enter Carlos, Eſtefania, Luys.</stage>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Ia.</speaker>
                  <l>The Lady <hi>Eſtefania.</hi>
                  </l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Car.</speaker>
                  <l>Welcome again,</l>
                  <l>This is an honour to us, where's <hi>Iacinta?</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>Salute this noble Lady. Ha, <hi>Luys,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>Haſt thou prevail'd already?</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Luys</speaker>
                  <l>I'm i'th' way you ſee,</l>
                  <l>She has not been obſerv'd they ſay to walk</l>
                  <l>So freely with ſome men that boaſt more favour.</l>
               </sp>
               <stage>Enter Pedro.</stage>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Ped.</speaker>
                  <l>What makes the Lady <hi>Eſtefania</hi> here?</l>
                  <l>I like not their converſe, this day is ominous.</l>
               </sp>
               <stage>Exit.</stage>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Car.</speaker>
                  <l>Was't not the Count <hi>Don Pedro</hi> that retird?</l>
                  <l>VVhat object here diſpleas'd him?</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Alber.</speaker>
                  <l>Ha, ha, didſt ſee the <hi>Don?</hi>
                  </l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Car.</speaker>
                  <l>Preſerve your mirth—I muſt be ſatisfied.</l>
               </sp>
               <stage>Exit.</stage>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Luys</speaker>
                  <l>I'l lay a thouſand Ducats that my coſtive</l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Don</hi> has been tampering with my VViddow, I</l>
                  <l>Obſerv'd (when I by chance let fall diſcourſe)</l>
                  <l>How much he was an amorous ſervant to</l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Iacinta,</hi> ſhe chang'd her colour and did make</l>
                  <l>Such buſineſs how my Siſter did affect him,</l>
                  <l>That I may gueſs, though I make uſe on't otherwiſe</l>
                  <l>To the old man, to keep the pulſes of</l>
                  <l>His Purſe in play, ſhe came to examin chiefly</l>
                  <l>How matters here proceeded; well, if ſhe love him—</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Alber.</speaker>
                  <l>Shee is thy Miſtris.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Luys</speaker>
                  <l>My Miſtris? yes, but any man ſhall mary her.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Alb.</speaker>
                  <l>How?</l>
               </sp>
               <pb n="38" facs="tcp:153588:44"/>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Luys.</speaker>
                  <l>She is a Widdovv, <hi>Don,</hi> conſider that,</l>
                  <l>Has buried one vvas thought a <hi>Hercules,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>Tvvo cubits taller, and a man that cut</l>
                  <l>Three Inches deeper in the ſay, than I, conſider that too,</l>
                  <l>She may be cock a tvventy, nay for ought</l>
                  <l>I knovv ſhe is Immortall.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Alb.</speaker>
                  <l>What doſt vvith her?</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Luys</speaker>
                  <l>Faith nothing yet,</l>
                  <l>And have but little hope, I think ſhee's honeſt.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Alb.</speaker>
                  <l>Do's ſhe love thee?</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Luys</speaker>
                  <l>At her ovvn perill, vv'are not come to articles;</l>
                  <l>There is no vvit in vviving, give me a vvhore;</l>
                  <l>But that I ovv thee money, thou ſhouldſt never</l>
                  <l>Marry my Siſter neither?</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Alb.</speaker>
                  <l>Not <hi>Jacinta?</hi>
                  </l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Luys</speaker>
                  <l>No, nor any other ſimpering piece of honeſty,</l>
                  <l>If I might counſell thee, vvhile any vvench</l>
                  <l>Were extant, and the ſtewes inhabited;</l>
                  <l>Is't fit, a Freeborn Gentleman ſhould be chain'd</l>
                  <l>Tenant for life to one? Hang mariage ſhackles,</l>
                  <l>Ty the Tovvn Buls to'th'ſtake, vve muſt have concubins.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Jac.</speaker>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Don Pedro</hi> vvas too blame, and truſt me Madam</l>
                  <l>He ſhall find nothing here t' advance his triumph.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Eſtef.</speaker>
                  <l>You are Virtuous <hi>Jacinta;</hi> I preſum'd</l>
                  <l>When I ſhould land my ſufferings on your knovvledge,</l>
                  <l>You vvould excuſe my unexpected viſit.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Jac.</speaker>
                  <l>My Brother has been Juſt in the relation</l>
                  <l>Hovv he purſues my love, but I ſhall be</l>
                  <l>Happy to ſerve your Juſtice, and muſt tell</l>
                  <l>The noble <hi>Eſtefania,</hi> my heart,</l>
                  <l>By all that love can teach to bind a faith,</l>
                  <l>Is plac'd vvhere it ſhall never injure vvhat</l>
                  <l>Your mutuall vovvs contracted; I ſmile not</l>
                  <l>With mine ovvn eyes upon him, 'tis my Fathers</l>
                  <l>Severe command to love him, but this ſtory</l>
                  <l>Cleer'd to my Father vvould ſecure us both.</l>
               </sp>
               <pb facs="tcp:153588:44"/>
               <pb facs="tcp:153588:45"/>
               <pb n="39" facs="tcp:153588:45"/>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Eſtef.</speaker>
                  <l>If any faith or ſervice in me can</l>
                  <l>Deſerve this goodneſs, cheerfully employ it.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Jac.</speaker>
                  <l>I will be confident to uſe your Virtue.</l>
               </sp>
               <stage>Enter Carlos.</stage>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Eſtef.</speaker>
                  <l>I will refuſe no office.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Jac.</speaker>
                  <l>My Father comes moſt aptly.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Alb.</speaker>
                  <l>Ha, ha, ha, have pitty on my ſpleen,</l>
                  <l>I ſhall crack a rib elſe, ha, ha, ha.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Car.</speaker>
                  <l>You are very mery, <hi>Don Alberto;</hi> Son,</l>
                  <l>You may be of the counſell too, this houſe</l>
                  <l>Is mine I take it, I adviſe you would</l>
                  <l>Frequent it leſs.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Alb.</speaker>
                  <l>How Sir?</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Car.</speaker>
                  <l>I do not like your viſits,</l>
                  <l>And to remove the cauſe, my Daughter is</l>
                  <l>Already ſir diſpos'd, to one above</l>
                  <l>Your birth and fortune, ſo fare-you-well.</l>
                  <l>You underſtand, now laugh and pick your teeth.</l>
                  <l>Daughter—</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Alb.</speaker>
                  <l>Did you hear this <hi>Luys?</hi>
                  </l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Luys</speaker>
                  <l>I, the old man raves.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Alber.</speaker>
                  <l>Muſt not frequent his houſe.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Luys</speaker>
                  <l>Would 'twere in a flame, ſo his mony and I</l>
                  <l>Were out on't.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Alb.</speaker>
                  <l>But thy Siſter—</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Luys</speaker>
                  <l>Would be refin'd i'th' fire, let her burn too.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Alb.</speaker>
                  <l>My friend, if I have not <hi>Jacinta,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>There are certain ſums of money—</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Luys</speaker>
                  <l>I am not of your mind <hi>Don,</hi> the ſums are moſt uncertain.</l>
                  <l>Come, you did laugh too loud, my Father is</l>
                  <l>A Stoick, but deſpair not; go to your lodging,</l>
                  <l>I'l ſee thee anon, and either bring thee money</l>
                  <l>Or elſe ſome reaſons why I do not bring it,</l>
                  <l>We won't go to Law, I'l pawn the widdow</l>
                  <l>Rather than thou ſhalt want; go ſay thy prayers,</l>
                  <l>And ſhew thy teeth no more, till I come to thee.</l>
                  <pb n="40" facs="tcp:153588:46"/>
                  <l>Now the buſineſs here?</l>
               </sp>
               <stage>Exit Alber.</stage>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Car.</speaker>
                  <l>Wee have agreed <hi>Jacinta,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>And he to morrow privately</l>
                  <l>Will at the Church expect thee; tis an age</l>
                  <l>Till I ſalute the Bride to this great <hi>Don,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>Whoſe thoughts are wing'd t' enjoy thee, and reſolve</l>
                  <l>No more delay, prepare to meet this Honor.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Luys</speaker>
                  <l>To morrow? this muſt be croſt.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Car.</speaker>
                  <l>My next ambition Madam will be perfect</l>
                  <l>To call you by ſome nearer name; my Son—</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Eſt.</speaker>
                  <l>Is a moſt noble Gentleman, I know not</l>
                  <l>Where lives ſo clear a merit.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Luys.</speaker>
                  <l>Oh ſweet Madam.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Car.</speaker>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Jacinta.</hi>
                  </l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Luys</speaker>
                  <l>I have a ſute to you.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Eſt.</speaker>
                  <l>To me?</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Luys</speaker>
                  <l>Only that you would not dote too much upon me,</l>
                  <l>A gentle eaſie ſober pace in love</l>
                  <l>Goes far, and is much better than a gallop; if you pleaſe</l>
                  <l>We may hold one another in hand, and love</l>
                  <l>This ſeaven yeares, without ſealing and delivering.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Eſt.</speaker>
                  <l>Withall my heart.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Luys</speaker>
                  <l>You'l do me a pleaſure Madam.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Eſt.</speaker>
                  <l>You inſtruct well.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Luys</speaker>
                  <l>This Courtſhip is not common.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Eſt.</speaker>
                  <l>I confeſs it.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Car.</speaker>
                  <l>Son <hi>Luys.</hi>
                  </l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Luys</speaker>
                  <l>Sir.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Car.</speaker>
                  <l>Let her not cool.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Luys</speaker>
                  <l>And ſhe do,</l>
                  <l>I know the way to heat her again.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Eſt.</speaker>
                  <l>I will not yet reveal my abuſe <hi>Iacinta,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>And if you pleaſe to favor a deſign,</l>
                  <l>I have a plot may ſerve to both our happineſs.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Jac.</speaker>
                  <l>I'l obey.</l>
                  <l>There is a trembling in my heart.</l>
               </sp>
               <pb facs="tcp:153588:46"/>
               <pb facs="tcp:153588:47"/>
               <pb n="41" facs="tcp:153588:47"/>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Car.</speaker>
                  <l>You muſt not leave us yet Madam.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Eſt.</speaker>
                  <l>You may command me.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Luys</speaker>
                  <l>My <hi>Don</hi> ſo rampart, ther's ſomthing in this pannier</l>
                  <l>Shall ſpoil your match to morow; <hi>Don Alberto,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>When I diſcloſe, ſhall worſhip me: be drunk,</l>
                  <l>Cancell arreers, and beg to lend more money.</l>
               </sp>
               <stage>Exe:</stage>
            </div>
            <div n="4" type="act">
               <head>ACT IV.</head>
               <stage>Enter Ramyres, Franciſce &amp; Notarie.</stage>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Ra.</speaker>
                  <l>'Tis moſt exactly done, and firm.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Notar.</speaker>
                  <l>I could,</l>
                  <l>Omiting or inſerting but a word, or particle,</l>
                  <l>Trouble the whole conveyance,</l>
                  <l>And make work for the law till doom's-day: but—</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Fran.</speaker>
                  <l>Is't poſſible?</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Notar</speaker>
                  <l>You do not know the quirks of a Scrivano,</l>
                  <l>A daſh undoes a Family, a point,</l>
                  <l>An artificiall accent i't'h wrong place,</l>
                  <l>Shall poyſon an Eſtate, tranſlate your Land</l>
                  <l>In <hi>Spain</hi> now into either of both <hi>Indies,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>In leſs time than our Gallions of Plate</l>
                  <l>Are ſayling hither; but you are my friend,</l>
                  <l>And noble benefactor.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Ramy.</speaker>
                  <l>Ther's more for your reward.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Notar.</speaker>
                  <l>I humbly thank you Signior. <hi>Su Criade.</hi>
                  </l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Fran.</speaker>
                  <l>Farewell.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Notar.</speaker>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Su Servidor.</hi>
                  </l>
               </sp>
               <stage>Exit.</stage>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Ramy.</speaker>
                  <l>This deed makes thee my Heir <hi>Franciſce,</hi> and</l>
                  <l>Will like a powerfull ſpell upon <hi>Don Carlos,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>Whoſe ſoul is ſuperſtitious upon Wealth,</l>
                  <l>Win his conſent to make <hi>Iacinta</hi> thine.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Fran.</speaker>
                  <l>Sir, I cannot ſay my duty ſhall deſerve it</l>
                  <l>Since nature, and religion, without all</l>
                  <pb n="42" facs="tcp:153588:48"/>
                  <l>This bounty challenges my beſt obedience.</l>
               </sp>
               <stage>Enter Fernando.</stage>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Ramy</speaker>
                  <l>Away, thy ſight</l>
                  <l>Is my diſeaſe.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Fer.</speaker>
                  <l>Your bleſſing ſir I kneel for.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Ramy.</speaker>
                  <l>What Impudence is this? wilt thou ſubſcribe</l>
                  <l>To take off mine, thy curſe on <hi>Feliſarda?</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>For I do hate her heartily; diſclaim</l>
                  <l>All promiſe, contract, or converſe for ever,</l>
                  <l>I'm elſe inexorable.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Fer.</speaker>
                  <l>Sir.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Ramy.</speaker>
                  <l>His eyes ſhoot poyſon at me, ha? he has</l>
                  <l>Bewitched me ſure, what coldneſs thus invades me?</l>
                  <l>Ther's ſomthing creeping to my heart. <hi>Franſciſco?</hi> ha?</l>
                  <l>Poſſeſs this gift of thy Inheritance;</l>
                  <l>Convey me to my chamber, oh—<hi>Fernando,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>If thou doſt hope I ſhould take off my curſe,</l>
                  <l>Do not approach my ſight, unleſs I ſend for thee.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Fran.</speaker>
                  <l>Forbear good Brother; <hi>Diego, Roderigo,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>Your hands t' aſſiſt my Father, one go for his</l>
                  <l>Phyſician.</l>
               </sp>
               <stage>Enter two Servants.</stage>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Fer</speaker>
                  <l>This turn is fatall, and affrights me, but</l>
                  <l>Heaven has more charity than to let him die</l>
                  <l>With ſuch a hard heart, 'twere a ſin, next his</l>
                  <l>Want of compaſſion, to ſuſpect he can</l>
                  <l>Take his Eternall flight and leave <hi>Fernando</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>This deſperate Legacie, he will change</l>
                  <l>The curſe into ſome little prayer I hope,</l>
                  <l>And then —</l>
               </sp>
               <stage>Enter Servant and Phyſician.</stage>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Serv.</speaker>
                  <l>Make haſt I beſeech you Doctor.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Phyſ.</speaker>
                  <l>Noble <hi>Fernando.</hi>
                  </l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Fer.</speaker>
                  <l>As you would have men think your art is meant</l>
                  <l>Not to abuſe mankind, employ it all</l>
                  <l>To cure my poor ſick Father.</l>
               </sp>
               <pb facs="tcp:153588:48"/>
               <pb facs="tcp:153588:49"/>
               <pb n="43" facs="tcp:153588:49"/>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Phiſ.</speaker>
                  <l>Fear it not ſir.</l>
               </sp>
               <stage>Ex. Phyſ. Serv.</stage>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Fer.</speaker>
                  <l>But there is more than your thin skill requir'd</l>
                  <l>To ſtate a health, your Recipes perplex't</l>
                  <l>With tough names, are but mockeries, and noiſe,</l>
                  <l>Without ſome dew from Heaven, to mix and make 'em</l>
                  <stage>Enter Servant.</stage>
                  <l>Thrive, in the application: what now?</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Ser.</speaker>
                  <l>Oh ſir, I am ſent for the Confeſſor,</l>
                  <l>The Doctor fears him much, your Brother ſaies</l>
                  <l>You muſt have patience, and not Enter Sir;</l>
                  <l>Your Father is a going, good old man,</l>
                  <l>And having made him Heir, is loth your preſence</l>
                  <l>Should interrupt his Journey.</l>
               </sp>
               <stage>Exit.</stage>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Fer.</speaker>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Franciſco</hi> may be honeſt, yet me thinks</l>
                  <l>It would become his love to interpoſe</l>
                  <l>For my acceſs, at ſuch a needfull hour,</l>
                  <l>And mediate for my bleſſing, not aſſiſt</l>
                  <l>Unkindly thus my baniſhment. I'l not</l>
                  <l>Be loſt ſo tamely, ſhall my Father dye</l>
                  <l>And not <hi>Fernando</hi> take his leave—I dare not.</l>
                  <l>If thou doſt hope I ſhould take off this curſe,</l>
                  <l>Do not approach untill I ſend—'twas ſo,</l>
                  <l>And 'tis a law that binds above my blood.</l>
                  <stage>Enter Confeſſor and Servant.</stage>
                  <l>Make haſt good Father, and if heaven deny</l>
                  <l>Him life, let not his charity dye too.</l>
                  <l>One curſe may ſink us both, ſay how I kneel</l>
                  <l>And beg he would bequeath me but his bleſſing;</l>
                  <l>Then though <hi>Franciſco</hi> be his Heir, I ſhall</l>
                  <l>Live happy, and take comfort in my tears,</l>
                  <l>When I remember him ſo kind a Father.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Confeſ.</speaker>
                  <l>It is my duty.</l>
               </sp>
               <stage>Exit.</stage>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Fer.</speaker>
                  <l>Do your holy office.</l>
                  <l>Thoſe fond Philoſophers that magnifie</l>
                  <l>Our human nature, and did boaſt wee had</l>
                  <pb n="44" facs="tcp:153588:50"/>
                  <l>Such a prerogative in our rationall ſoul,</l>
                  <l>Converſt but little with the World, confin'd</l>
                  <l>To cells, and unfrequented woods, they knew not</l>
                  <l>The fierce vexation of community,</l>
                  <l>Elſe they had taught, our reaſon is our loſs,</l>
                  <l>And but a priviledge that exceedeth ſenſe,</l>
                  <l>By nearer apprehenſion, of what wounds,</l>
                  <l>To know our ſelves moſt miſerable. My heart</l>
                  <stage>Enter Phyſician and Franciſco.</stage>
                  <l>Is teeming with new fears—Ha, is he dead?</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Phy.</speaker>
                  <l>Not dead, but in a deſperate condition,</l>
                  <l>And ſo that little breath remaines wee have</l>
                  <l>Remitted to his Confeſſor, whoſe Office</l>
                  <l>Is all that's left.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Fran.</speaker>
                  <l>Is there no hope of life then?</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Phyſ.</speaker>
                  <l>None.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Fer.</speaker>
                  <l>Is he not mercifull to <hi>Fernando</hi> yet? no talk o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> me</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Phyſ.</speaker>
                  <l>I find he takes no pleaſure</l>
                  <l>To hear you nam'd: <hi>Franciſco</hi> to us all</l>
                  <l>He did confirm his Heir, with many bleſſings.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Fer.</speaker>
                  <l>And not one left for me? oh take me in</l>
                  <l>Thou gentle Earth, and let me creep through all</l>
                  <l>Thy dark and hollow crannies, till I find</l>
                  <l>Another way to come into the World,</l>
                  <l>For all the Air I breath-in here is poyſon'd.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Fran</speaker>
                  <l>Wee muſt have patience Brother, it was no</l>
                  <l>Ambitious thought of mine to ſupplant you;</l>
                  <l>He may live yet, and you be reconcil'd.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Fer.</speaker>
                  <l>That was ſome kindneſs yet <hi>Franciſco;</hi> but</l>
                  <l>I charge thee by the nearneſs of our blood,</l>
                  <l>When I am made this mockery, and wonder,</l>
                  <l>I know not where to find out charity,</l>
                  <l>If unawares a chance direct my weary</l>
                  <l>And wither'd Feet to ſome fair Houſe of thine,</l>
                  <l>Where plenty with full bleſſings crowns thy table,</l>
                  <l>If my thin face betray my want of food,</l>
                  <pb facs="tcp:153588:50"/>
                  <pb facs="tcp:153588:51"/>
                  <pb n="45" facs="tcp:153588:51"/>
                  <l>Do not deſpiſe me, cauſe 'I was thy Brother.</l>
               </sp>
               <stage>Inter Confeſſor.</stage>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Fran.</speaker>
                  <l>Leave theſe imagin'd horrors, I muſt not</l>
                  <l>Live when my Brother is thus miſerable.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Fer.</speaker>
                  <l>Ther's ſomthing in that face looks comfortably.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Confeſ.</speaker>
                  <l>Your Father ſir is dead, his will to make</l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Franciſco</hi> the ſole Maſter of his Fortunes</l>
                  <l>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>s now irrevocable, a ſmall Penſion</l>
                  <l>He hath given you for life, which with his bleſſing</l>
                  <l>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>s all the benefit I bring.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Fer.</speaker>
                  <l>Ha, bleſſing; ſpeak it agen good Father.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Confeſ.</speaker>
                  <l>I did apply ſome lenitives to ſoften</l>
                  <l>His anger, and prevail'd; your Father hath</l>
                  <l>Revers'd that heavy cenſure of his curſe,</l>
                  <l>And in the place bequeath'd his prayer and bleſſing.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Fer.</speaker>
                  <l>I am new created by his charity.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Confeſ.</speaker>
                  <l>Some ceremonies are behind, he did</l>
                  <l>Deſire to be interr'd within our Covent,</l>
                  <l>And left his Sepulture to me, I am confident</l>
                  <l>Your pieties will give me leave—</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Fran.</speaker>
                  <l>His will in all things I obey, and yours</l>
                  <l>Moſt reverend Father; order as you pleaſe</l>
                  <l>His Body; wee may after celebrate</l>
                  <l>With all due obſequies his Funerall.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Fer.</speaker>
                  <l>Why you alone obey? I am your Brother:</l>
                  <l>My Fathers Eldeſt Son, though not his Heir.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Fran.</speaker>
                  <l>It pleas'd my Father ſir to think me worthy</l>
                  <l>Of ſuch a title, you ſhall find me kind,</l>
                  <l>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>f you can look on matters without Envie.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Fer.</speaker>
                  <l>If I can look on matters without Envie?</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Fran.</speaker>
                  <l>You may live here ſtill.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Per.</speaker>
                  <l>I may live here <hi>Franciſco?</hi>
                  </l>
                  <stage>Enter a Gentleman with a letter</stage>
                  <l>Conditions? I would not underſtand</l>
                  <l>This Dialect.</l>
               </sp>
               <pb n="46" facs="tcp:153588:52"/>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Fran.</speaker>
                  <l>With me, from Madam <hi>Eſtefania?</hi>
                  </l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Gent.</speaker>
                  <l>If you be Signior <hi>Franciſco.</hi>
                  </l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Fer.</speaker>
                  <l>Sleighted? I find my Father was not dead till now.</l>
                  <l>Croud not you Jealous thoughts ſo thick into</l>
                  <l>My Brain, leſt you do tempt me to an Act</l>
                  <l>Will forfeit all agen.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Fran.</speaker>
                  <l>This is <hi>Jacintas</hi> character <hi>[Reads]—Fail not to meet</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>As you timely will prevent the danger of my rape.</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>My ſoul! Eſtefania <hi>can inſtruct you all particulars</hi>—</l>
                  <l>My ſervice to your Lady, ſay I ſhall obey her commands.</l>
               </sp>
               <stage>Exit Gent.</stage>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Fer.</speaker>
                  <l>Is that an Inventory you peruſe?</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Fran.</speaker>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Fernando</hi> you muſt pardon me, ther's ſomthing</l>
                  <l>Of Eſſence to my life, exacts my care,</l>
                  <l>And perſon, I muſt leave you, we may ſeaſonably</l>
                  <l>Confer of things at my return. <hi>Jacinta.</hi>
                     <stage>Exit.</stage>
                  </l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Fer.</speaker>
                  <l>Tis clear I am neglected, he did name</l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Jacinta</hi> too, in triumph, and is gone,</l>
                  <l>Big with his glories to divide 'em there,</l>
                  <l>And laugh at what my conſtant love hath made me.</l>
                  <l>My heart is in a ſtorm, and day growes black,</l>
                  <l>Ther's not a ſtar in Heaven will lend a beam</l>
                  <l>To light me to my ruine. <hi>Feliſarda!</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>That name is both my haven, and my ſhipwrack.
<stage>Exit.</stage>
                  </l>
               </sp>
               <stage>Enter Alberto and Luys.</stage>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Alb.</speaker>
                  <l>Excellent.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Luys</speaker>
                  <l>You'l give me now a generall releaſe</l>
                  <l>For all the ſums I ow you?</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Alb.</speaker>
                  <l>Thou haſt bleſt me.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Luys.</speaker>
                  <l>I was born to do you good; about it preſently</l>
                  <l>Now you know where to ambuſh, away I ſay</l>
                  <l>And get comrads: <hi>Jacinta</hi> and my Mother</l>
                  <l>Is all the carriage, you may know the coach</l>
                  <l>By the old womans cough ere it come neer you.</l>
                  <l>She has a deſperate malice to one tooth left</l>
                  <l>Still in her gums, till ſhe has ſhook that out;</l>
                  <pb facs="tcp:153588:52"/>
                  <pb facs="tcp:153588:53"/>
                  <pb n="47" facs="tcp:153588:53"/>
                  <l>You wo'not need a warning peece, farewell.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Alb.</speaker>
                  <l>Farewel, why whats the matter? you ſhanot leave me;</l>
                  <l>Thy Mother wo'not know thee in a Viſard.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Luys.</speaker>
                  <l>You muſt excuſe me friend, I would Joyn w'ee</l>
                  <l>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>'th' ſurpriſe, but that—</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Alb.</speaker>
                  <l>What I prethee?</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Luys.</speaker>
                  <l>I have extraordinary buſineſs, that concerns me</l>
                  <l>As neer as life.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Alb.</speaker>
                  <l>May not I know't? thou art going</l>
                  <l>To the Widdow now, thy Miſtris.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Lu.</speaker>
                  <l>Tis a buſineſs of more conſequence;</l>
                  <l>Doſt think I would leave thee, and there were not</l>
                  <l>Such a neceſſity?</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Alb.</speaker>
                  <l>For what?</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Luys.</speaker>
                  <l>And there were no more Siſters in the World,</l>
                  <l>You muſt excuſe me.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Alb.</speaker>
                  <l>Nay, nay, we muſt not part, unleſs I know</l>
                  <l>This myſtery, ſome reaſon vvhy you leave me.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Luys.</speaker>
                  <l>If you vvill needs knovv, there's a vvench ſtaies for me,</l>
                  <l>The toy I told thee on; farevvell <hi>Alberto.</hi>
                  </l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Alb.</speaker>
                  <l>But vvill you leave ſuch buſineſs and a friend?</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Luys.</speaker>
                  <l>Buſineſs? art thou a Gentleman &amp; vvouldſt have</l>
                  <l>Me leave a Ladie I ha'not ſeen this three year</l>
                  <l>For buſineſs or a friend?</l>
                  <l>I muſt to her; if I had a heart</l>
                  <l>Ten Tun of Iron,</l>
                  <l>This Female Adamant vvould dravv it to her,</l>
                  <l>I feel it going; I do tell thee <hi>Don,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>There is no buſineſs ſo materiall</l>
                  <l>In nature as a vvench, and if thou art my friend</l>
                  <l>Thou vvouldſt leave my Siſter novv in ſuch a cauſe</l>
                  <l>And bear me company, I muſt be drunk,</l>
                  <l>And ſhe muſt pick my pocket too, that is</l>
                  <l>Another ſecret vvhen vve meet together</l>
                  <l>That never failes.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Alb.</speaker>
                  <l>Why art thou deſperate?</l>
                  <pb n="48" facs="tcp:153588:54"/>
                  <l>Doſt not thou fear thy body?</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Luys</speaker>
                  <l>A wench is Phyſick</l>
                  <l>My body has been us'd too, leave thy prating,</l>
                  <l>And let me take my courſe.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Alb.</speaker>
                  <l>And you be ſo reſolute—</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Luys</speaker>
                  <l>I muſt give you one advice before you go;</l>
                  <l>VVhen my Siſter's in thy cuſtody, obſerve</l>
                  <l>The time and place, and things convenient,</l>
                  <l>And ſtand not fooling about ceremonies</l>
                  <l>But put her to't.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Alb.</speaker>
                  <l>Thou wouldſt not have me raviſh her?</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Luys.</speaker>
                  <l>Yes but I would,</l>
                  <l>Shee's no Siſter of mine if ſhe cry out</l>
                  <l>For ſuch a buſineſs, ſhe has more wit.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Alb.</speaker>
                  <l>VVas ever ſuch a mad-cap.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Luys</speaker>
                  <l>I'l not pray for thee.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Alb.</speaker>
                  <l>I ſha'not proſper if thou doſt.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Luys</speaker>
                  <l>Thy hand, Ile drink thy health, &amp; hang thy ſelf.</l>
                  <l>Farewell.</l>
               </sp>
               <stage>Exeunt.</stage>
               <stage>Enter Iacinta and Eſtefania.</stage>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Iac.</speaker>
                  <l>You tell me wonders Madam, <hi>Don Ramyres</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>Dead, his Son <hi>Fernando</hi> diſinherited,</l>
                  <l>And young <hi>Franciſco</hi> made his heir?</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Fſtef.</speaker>
                  <l>I took</l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Franciſcos</hi> word.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Jac.</speaker>
                  <l>Tis ſtrange.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Eſtef.</speaker>
                  <l>Your ſtars ſmile on you.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Iac.</speaker>
                  <l>Yet I much pitty the poor Gentleman.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Eſt.</speaker>
                  <l>Buſie your thought about your own, <hi>Franciſco—</hi>
                  </l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Ia.</speaker>
                  <l>Hath promis'd not to fail?</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Eſt.</speaker>
                  <l>He waits where he can eaſily obſerve</l>
                  <l>How ſoon the coaſt is clear to viſit you.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Ja.</speaker>
                  <l>So, ſo, thus hooded</l>
                  <l>The day cannot diſtinguiſh our two faces,</l>
                  <l>And for your voice, you know how to diſguize it</l>
                  <l>By imitation of my cold and hoarſeneſs,</l>
                  <pb facs="tcp:153588:54"/>
                  <pb facs="tcp:153588:55"/>
                  <pb n="49" facs="tcp:153588:55"/>
                  <l>And when you come to Church —</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Eſte.</speaker>
                  <l>Let me alone, there l'l produce the Contract,</l>
                  <l>Which will ſurpriſe <hi>Don Pedro,</hi> and your Father,</l>
                  <l>To ſee me challenge him, I ha' prepar'd the Prieſt too,</l>
                  <l>Whoſe holy Eloquence may aſſiſt, how ever</l>
                  <l>This will give you opportunity to perfect</l>
                  <l>Your wiſhes with your ſervant, put the reſt</l>
                  <l>To fate <hi>Jacinta.</hi>
                  </l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Jac.</speaker>
                  <l>I hear ſome approach, retire into my Cloſet.—</l>
               </sp>
               <stage>Enter Carlos and Pedro.</stage>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Car.</speaker>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Jacinta. Jac.</hi> Sir.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Car.</speaker>
                  <l>Not thy voicerecover'd?</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Ja.</speaker>
                  <l>A violent cold—</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Car.</speaker>
                  <l>Count <hi>Pedro</hi> muſt ſalute you ere we go.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Pedro.</speaker>
                  <l>Impute it to devotion, that I make</l>
                  <l>Such haſt to be within thy armes,</l>
                  <l>One kiſs and I ſhall carry with me</l>
                  <l>Another ſoul, and count with Joy the minutes</l>
                  <l>I am to expect this happineſs.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Car.</speaker>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Jacinta</hi> you follow with your Mother in the Coach;</l>
                  <l>My Lord I wait you. <hi>Ped.</hi> Ther's Heaven upon her lip.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Iac.</speaker>
                  <l>He has kiſt, and took his leave I hope.</l>
                  <stage>Enter Eſtefania.</stage>
                  <l>I muſt owe all my happineſs to you ſweet Madam,</l>
                  <l>I had been loſt without your art to help me.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Eſte</speaker>
                  <l>Love wo'not leave his votaries.</l>
               </sp>
               <stage>Cough within. Exit.</stage>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Iac.</speaker>
                  <l>I hear my Mothers cough, I ha'finiſh'd</l>
                  <l>And you muſt act your part:</l>
               </sp>
               <stage>Enter Alſimira.</stage>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Alſ.</speaker>
                  <l>Come are you ready Daughter? the Coach ſtayes.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Eſty.</speaker>
                  <l>I attend</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Alſi.</speaker>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Don Pedro</hi> will cure your cold before the morn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing.</l>
               </sp>
               <stage>Enter Franciſco and takes away Iacinta.</stage>
               <stage>Enter Teodore and Feliſarda.</stage>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Teo.</speaker>
                  <l>What duty <hi>Feliſarda</hi> ſhall we pay</l>
                  <pb n="50" facs="tcp:153588:56"/>
                  <l>To Heaven for this laſt care of us?</l>
                  <l>Let not thy eyes,</l>
                  <l>Although thy grief become 'em, be in love</l>
                  <l>With tears, I Propheſie a joy ſhall weigh</l>
                  <l>Down all our ſufferings, I ſee comfort break</l>
                  <l>Like day, whoſe forehead chears the world; if <hi>Don</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Fernando</hi> love thee, he is a Gentleman,</l>
                  <l>Confirm'd in all that's honorable, and cannot</l>
                  <l>Forget whom his own vertue hath made choice</l>
                  <l>To ſhine upon.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Feliſ.</speaker>
                  <l>Unleſs my Innocence,</l>
                  <l>Apt to believe a flattering tongue, ſee not</l>
                  <l>The Serpent couch, and hide his ſpeckled breſt</l>
                  <l>Among the flowers; but it were ſin to think</l>
                  <l>He can diſſemble, Father, and I know not,</l>
                  <l>Since I was firſt the object of his charity,</l>
                  <l>I find a pious gratitude diſperſe</l>
                  <l>Within my ſoul, and every thought of him</l>
                  <l>Engenders a warm ſigh within me, which</l>
                  <l>Like curles of holy Incenſe overtake</l>
                  <l>Each other in my boſom, and enlarge</l>
                  <l>With their Embrace his ſweet remembrance.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Teo.</speaker>
                  <l>Cheriſh</l>
                  <l>Thoſe thoughts, and where ſuch noble worth invites,</l>
                  <l>Be bold to call it love.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Feliſ.</speaker>
                  <l>It is too much</l>
                  <l>Ambition to hope he ſhould be juſt</l>
                  <l>To me, or keep his honor, when I look on</l>
                  <l>The pale complexion of my wants; and yet</l>
                  <l>Vnleſs he loves me dearly, I am loſt,</l>
                  <l>And if he have but mock'd me into faith,</l>
                  <l>He might as well have murdered me, for I</l>
                  <l>Shall have no heart to live, if his neglect</l>
                  <l>Deface what my affection printed there.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Teo.</speaker>
                  <l>There is no feare of his revolt, loſe not</l>
                  <l>His character. I muſt attend ſome buſineſs.</l>
                  <pb facs="tcp:153588:56"/>
                  <pb facs="tcp:153588:57"/>
                  <pb n="51" facs="tcp:153588:57"/>
                  <l>If <hi>Don Fernando</hi> viſit thee, preſerve</l>
                  <l>His fair opinion, and thou maiſt live</l>
                  <l>Above thy Uncles pitty.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Feliſ.</speaker>
                  <l>Will you leave me?</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Teo.</speaker>
                  <l>My ſtay ſhall not be long; the Garden will</l>
                  <l>With ſmiling flowres encourage thee to walk,</l>
                  <l>And raiſe thy drooping eyes, with hope to ſee</l>
               </sp>
               <l>A ſpring like theirs, upon thee.</l>
               <stage>Exit.</stage>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Feliſ.</speaker>
                  <l>Why ſhould I</l>
                  <l>Give any entertainment to my fears?</l>
                  <l>Suſpicions are but like the ſhape of clouds,</l>
                  <l>And idle forms i'th' air, we make to fright us.</l>
                  <l>I will admit no jealous thought to wound</l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Fernandos</hi> truth, but with that chearfullneſs,</l>
                  <l>My own firſt clear intents to honour him</l>
                  <l>Can arm me with, expect to meet his faith</l>
                  <l>As noble as he promis'd—Ha! tis he.</l>
               </sp>
               <stage>Enter Fernando.</stage>
               <l>My poor heart trembles like a timerous leaf,</l>
               <l>Which the wind ſhakes upon his ſickly ſtalk,</l>
               <l>And frights into a Palſey. <hi>Fer. Feliſarda!</hi>
               </l>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Feliſ.</speaker>
                  <l>Shall I want fortitude to bid him welcome?</l>
                  <l>Sir, if you think there is a heart alive</l>
                  <l>That can be gratefull, and with humble thoughts,</l>
                  <l>And Prayers reward your piety, deſpife not</l>
                  <l>The offer of it here; you have not caſt</l>
                  <l>Your bounty on a Rock, while the ſeeds thrive</l>
                  <l>Where you did place your Charity; my joy</l>
                  <l>May ſeem ill dreſt to come like ſorrow thus,</l>
                  <l>But you may ſee through every tear, and find</l>
                  <l>My eyes meant Innocence, and your hearty welcome.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Fer.</speaker>
                  <l>Who did prepare thee <hi>Feliſarda</hi> thus</l>
                  <l>To entertain me weeping? ſure our ſoules</l>
                  <l>Meet and converſe, and we not know't; there is</l>
                  <l>Such beauty in that watry circle, I</l>
                  <l>Am fearfull to come neer, and breath a kiſs</l>
                  <l>Upon thy cheek, leſt I pollute that Criſtall,</l>
                  <pb n="52" facs="tcp:153588:58"/>
                  <l>And yet I muſt ſalute thee, and I dare</l>
                  <l>With one warm ſigh meet, and dry up this ſorrow.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Feliſ.</speaker>
                  <l>I ſhall forget all miſery; for when</l>
                  <l>I look upon the World, and race of men,</l>
                  <l>I find 'em proud, and all ſo unacquainted</l>
                  <l>With pitty to ſuch miſerable things</l>
                  <l>As poverty hath made us, that I muſt</l>
                  <l>Conclude you ſent from Heaven.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Fer.</speaker>
                  <l>Oh do not Flatter</l>
                  <l>Thy ſelf poor <hi>Feliſarda;</hi> I'm Mortall,</l>
                  <l>The life I bear about me is not mine,</l>
                  <l>But borrow'd to come to thee once again,</l>
                  <l>And ere I go, to clear how much I love thee—</l>
                  <l>But firſt I have a ſtory to deliver,</l>
                  <l>A tale will make thee ſad, but I muſt tell it,</l>
                  <l>There is one dead that lov'd thee not.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Feliſ.</speaker>
                  <l>One dead</l>
                  <l>That lov'd not me? this carries fir in nature</l>
                  <l>No killing ſound; I ſhall be ſad to know</l>
                  <l>I did deſerve an Enemy, or he want</l>
                  <l>A Charity at death.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Fer.</speaker>
                  <l>Thy cruell Enemy,</l>
                  <l>And my beſt friend, hath took Eternall leave</l>
                  <l>And's gone, to heaven I hope, excuſe my tears,</l>
                  <l>It is a tribute I muſt pay his memory,</l>
                  <l>For I did love my Father.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Feliſ.</speaker>
                  <l>Ha! your Father?</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Fer.</speaker>
                  <l>Yes <hi>Feliſarda,</hi> he is gone, that in</l>
                  <l>The morning promis'd many years, but death</l>
                  <l>Hath in few hours made him as ſtiff, as all</l>
                  <l>The winds, and winter, had thrown cold upon him,</l>
                  <l>And wiſper'd him to marble.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Feliſ.</speaker>
                  <l>Now truſt me,</l>
                  <l>My heart weepes for him, but I underſtand</l>
                  <l>Not hovv I vvas concern'd in his diſpleaſure;</l>
                  <l>And in ſuch height as you profeſs.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Fer.</speaker>
                  <l>He did</l>
                  <pb facs="tcp:153588:58"/>
                  <pb facs="tcp:153588:59"/>
                  <pb n="53" facs="tcp:153588:59"/>
                  <l>Command me on his bleſſing to forſake thee;</l>
                  <l>Was't not a cruell precept, to inforce</l>
                  <l>The ſoul, and curſe his Son for honeſt love?</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Feliſ.</speaker>
                  <l>This is a wound indeed.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Fer.</speaker>
                  <l>But not ſo mortall;</l>
                  <l>For his laſt breath was Balſom pour'd upon it,</l>
                  <l>By which he did reverſe his malediction;</l>
                  <l>And I that groan'd beneath the weight of that</l>
                  <l>Anathema, ſunk almoſt to deſpair,</l>
                  <l>Where night and heavy ſhades hung round about me,</l>
                  <l>Found my ſelf riſing like the morning Star</l>
                  <l>To view the World.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Feliſ.</speaker>
                  <l>Never I hope to be</l>
                  <l>Eclips'd agen.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Fer.</speaker>
                  <l>This was a welcom bleſſing.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Fe.</speaker>
                  <l>Heaven had a care of both; my joyes are mighty.</l>
                  <l>Vouchſafe me ſir your pardon if I bluſh</l>
                  <l>And ſay I love, but rather than the peace</l>
                  <l>That ſhould preſerve your boſom, ſuffer for</l>
                  <l>My ſake, 'twere better I were dead.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Fer.</speaker>
                  <l>No, live.</l>
                  <l>And live for ever happy, thou deſerved'ſt it.</l>
                  <l>It is <hi>Fernando</hi> doth make haſt to ſleep</l>
                  <l>In his forgotten duſt.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Feliſ.</speaker>
                  <l>Thoſe accents did</l>
                  <l>Not ſound ſo cheerfully.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Fer.</speaker>
                  <l>doſt love me?</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Feliſ.</speaker>
                  <l>Sir.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Fer.</speaker>
                  <l>Do not, I prethee do not, I am loſt,</l>
                  <l>Alas I am no more <hi>Fernando,</hi> there</l>
                  <l>Is nothing but the Empty name of him</l>
                  <l>That did betray thee, place a guard about</l>
                  <l>Thy heart be time, I am not worth this ſweetneſs.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Feliſ.</speaker>
                  <l>Did not <hi>Fernando</hi> ſpeak all this? alas</l>
                  <l>He knew that I was poor before, and needed not</l>
                  <l>Deſpiſe me now for that.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Fer.</speaker>
                  <l>Deſert me goodneſs</l>
                  <pb n="54" facs="tcp:153588:60"/>
                  <l>When I upbraid thy wants. 'Tis I am poor,</l>
                  <l>For I ha' not a ſtock in all the World</l>
                  <l>Of ſo much duſt, as would contrive one narrow</l>
                  <l>Cabin to ſhroud a worm; my dying Father</l>
                  <l>Hath given away my Birthright to <hi>Franciſco,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>I'm diſinherited, thrown out of all,</l>
                  <l>But the ſmall Earth I borrow, thus to walk on;</l>
                  <l>And having nothing left, I come to kiſs thee,</l>
                  <l>And take my everlaſting leave of thee too.</l>
                  <l>Farewell, this will perſwade thee to conſent</l>
                  <l>To my Eternall abſence.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Feliſ.</speaker>
                  <l>I muſt beſeech you ſtay a little ſir,</l>
                  <l>And clear my faith. Hath your diſpleaſed Father</l>
                  <l>Depriv'd you then of all, and made <hi>Franciſco</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>The Lord of your Inheritance, without hope</l>
                  <l>To be repair'd in Fortune?</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Fer.</speaker>
                  <l>'Tis ſad truth.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Feliſ.</speaker>
                  <l>This is a happineſs I did not look for.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Fer.</speaker>
                  <l>A happineſs?</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Feliſ.</speaker>
                  <l>Yes Sir, a happineſs.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Fer.</speaker>
                  <l>Can <hi>Feliſarda</hi> take delight to hear</l>
                  <l>What hath undone her ſervant?</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Feliſ.</speaker>
                  <l>Heaven avert it.</l>
                  <l>But 'tis not worth my grief to be aſſur'd</l>
                  <l>That this will bring me nearer now to him</l>
                  <l>Whom I moſt honor of the World; and tis</l>
                  <l>My pride, if you exceed me not in Fortune,</l>
                  <l>That I can boaſt my heart, as high, and rich,</l>
                  <l>With noble flame, and every way your equall,</l>
                  <l>And if you be as poor as I <hi>Fernando,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>I can deſerve you now, and love you more</l>
                  <l>Than when your expectation carried all</l>
                  <l>The pride and bloſſoms of the ſpring upon it.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Fer.</speaker>
                  <l>Thoſe ſhadowes will not feed more than our fancies;</l>
                  <l>Two poverties will keep but a thin table;</l>
                  <l>And while wee dream of this high nouriſhment,</l>
                  <pb facs="tcp:153588:60"/>
                  <pb facs="tcp:153588:61"/>
                  <pb n="55" facs="tcp:153588:61"/>
                  <l>Wee do but ſtarve more gloriouſly.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Feliſ.</speaker>
                  <l>'Tis eaſe.</l>
                  <l>And wealth firſt taught us art to ſurfet by;</l>
                  <l>Nature is wiſe, not coſtly, and will ſpread</l>
                  <l>A table for us in the Wilderneſs;</l>
                  <l>And the kind Earth keep us alive, and healthfull,</l>
                  <l>With what her boſom doth invite us to;</l>
                  <l>The brooks, not there ſuſpected as the Wine</l>
                  <l>That ſomtime Princes quaff, are all tranſparent,</l>
                  <l>And with their pretty murmurs call to taſt 'em.</l>
                  <l>In every tree a <hi>Choriſter</hi> to ſing</l>
                  <l>Health to our loves, our lives ſhall there be free</l>
                  <l>As the firſt knowledge was from ſin, and all</l>
                  <l>Our dreams as Innocent.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Fer.</speaker>
                  <l>Oh <hi>Feliſarda?</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>If thou didſt own leſs Virtue, I might prove</l>
                  <l>Unkind and marry thee, but being ſo rich</l>
                  <l>In goodneſs, it becomes me not to bring</l>
                  <l>One that is poor, in every vvorth, to vvaſt</l>
                  <l>So excellent a Dower, be free, and meet</l>
                  <l>One that hath Wealth to cheriſh it, I ſhall</l>
                  <l>Undo thee quite, but pray for me, as I,</l>
                  <l>That thou maiſt change for a more happy Bridgroom;</l>
                  <l>I dare as ſoon be guilty of my death,</l>
                  <l>As make thee miſerable by expecting me.</l>
                  <l>Farwell, and do not wrong my ſoul, to think</l>
                  <l>That any ſtorm could ſeparate us two,</l>
                  <l>But that I have no fortune now to ſerve thee.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Feliſ.</speaker>
                  <l>This will be no exception ſir, I hope,</l>
                  <l>When wee are both dead, yet our bodies may</l>
                  <l>Be cold, and ſtrangers in the Winding ſheet;</l>
                  <l>We ſhall be married when our ſpirits meets.</l>
               </sp>
               <stage>Excunt.</stage>
            </div>
            <div n="5" type="act">
               <head>Act V.</head>
               <stage>Enter Carlos, Pedro.</stage>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Pe.</speaker>
                  <l>Your daughter does not uſe me well <hi>Don Carlos.</hi>
                  </l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Car.</speaker>
                  <l>I know not what to think,</l>
                  <pb n="56" facs="tcp:153588:62"/>
                  <l>Some great misfortune muſt be the cauſe.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Ped.</speaker>
                  <l>Not yet appear? they might,</l>
                  <l>And they had crept like <hi>Tortoyſes,</hi> Ariv'd</l>
                  <l>Before this time.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Car.</speaker>
                  <l>There is ſome ſtrange diſaſter.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Ped.</speaker>
                  <l>The Coach orethrown, and both their lives</l>
                  <l>Endanger'd, can but excuſe'm.</l>
                  <stage>Enter Alſimira.</stage>
                  <l>Oh my Lord, <hi>Don Carlos.</hi>
                  </l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Ped.</speaker>
                  <l>The Tragick voice of women ſtricks mine eare.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Car.</speaker>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Alſimira?</hi>
                  </l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Ped.</speaker>
                  <l>Madam.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Car.</speaker>
                  <l>Where is our Daughter?</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Alſi.</speaker>
                  <l>My fear almoſt diſtracts me, ſhe is gone,</l>
                  <l>Stoln, raviſh'd from me.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Ped.</speaker>
                  <l>Ha.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Alſt.</speaker>
                  <l>An armed Troop</l>
                  <l>In Viſards forc'd her from my coach; and heaven</l>
                  <l>Knows where they have hurried the poor <hi>Jacinta.</hi>
                  </l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Car.</speaker>
                  <l>A troop of armed Devils.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Ped.</speaker>
                  <l>Let them be</l>
                  <l>A legion, they are all damn'd.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Al.</speaker>
                  <l>Nay they were men and mortall ſure.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Ped.</speaker>
                  <l>I w'on'ot leave one ſoul amongſt them all.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Car.</speaker>
                  <l>Mine is in torment.</l>
                  <l>I'th'hope &amp; height of my ambition</l>
                  <l>To be thus cros'd! how ſcap'd you?</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Alſi.</speaker>
                  <l>Alas I was not young enough, I offer'd</l>
                  <l>My ſelf to bear her company, and ſuffer</l>
                  <l>As much as ſhe did, but one boyſterous fellow</l>
                  <l>With a ſtarch'd voice, and a worſe vizard, took me</l>
                  <l>Juſt here above my Sciatica, and quoited me</l>
                  <l>Into the coach <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>gen upon my head,</l>
                  <l>I had alarum in't for half an hour,</l>
                  <l>And ſo I ſcap'd with life.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Ped.</speaker>
                  <l>Did they uſe her with any rigor?</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Alſi.</speaker>
                  <l>To ſay truth they were gentle enough to her.</l>
               </sp>
               <pb facs="tcp:153588:62"/>
               <pb facs="tcp:153588:63"/>
               <pb n="57" facs="tcp:153588:63"/>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Ped.</speaker>
                  <l>That mollifies. and they may live.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Car.</speaker>
                  <l>Hell overtake 'em, lets return, they had better</l>
                  <l>Committed inceſt, than this rape.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Ped.</speaker>
                  <l>They had better raviſh'd <hi>Proſerpine</hi> before</l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Don Lucifer</hi>'s own face. I am all fury.</l>
               </sp>
               <stage>Excunt.</stage>
               <stage>Enter Alberto and Estefania.</stage>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Alb.</speaker>
                  <l>Pardon my de<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>r <hi>Jacinta,</hi> It was love</l>
                  <l>That threw me on this act, I had no patience</l>
                  <l>To ſee thee forc'd into a mariage</l>
                  <l>By a covetous Father, whoſe devotion</l>
                  <l>Is only Wealth and Title; I eſteem</l>
                  <l>No danger, if at laſt the fair <hi>Jacinta</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>Smile and allow this duty; let not ſilence</l>
                  <l>Deprive me longer of thy voice, whoſe every</l>
                  <l>Accent will pleaſe, though it pronounce my ſentence;</l>
                  <l>There's death in this Eclipſs too, ſweet diſmiſs</l>
                  <l>Thy ungentle veil, and let thy eyes make bright</l>
                  <l>This melancholy air, that droops and dies</l>
                  <l>For want of thy reſtoring beams.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Eſt.</speaker>
                  <l>Now ſir,</l>
                  <l>What think you of your Miſtris?</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Al.</speaker>
                  <l>You are the Lady <hi>Eſtefania</hi> I take it.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Eſt.</speaker>
                  <l>Yes, you did take me from the coach</l>
                  <stage>Alberto</stage>
                  <l>But by a conſequence I find, you thought</l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Jacinta</hi> in your power, I could have told you,</l>
                  <l>Had you diſcover'd ſooner what you were,</l>
                  <l>Where to have found your Miſtris, but ſhee's now</l>
                  <l>Above your hope, and by the prieſt ere this</l>
                  <l>Made wife to <hi>Don Franciſco.</hi>
                  </l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Alb.</speaker>
                  <l>To <hi>Don Pedro?</hi>
                  </l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Eſt.</speaker>
                  <l>It was not fir impoſſible that I</l>
                  <l>(Had not your violence prevented me)</l>
                  <l>(By a plot between <hi>Jacinta</hi> and my ſelf,</l>
                  <l>To take her place and perſon in the coach)</l>
                  <l>Had by this time been married to Count <hi>Pedro,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>Whom I have povver and Juſtice ſir to challenge</l>
                  <pb n="58" facs="tcp:153588:64"/>
                  <l>If Contracts carry weight.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Al.</speaker>
                  <l>Have I ſo long</l>
                  <l>Ly'n beating at the buſh, and is the bird</l>
                  <l>Fled to <hi>Franciſco?</hi>
                  </l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Eſt.</speaker>
                  <l>I ſhould ſhew I had</l>
                  <l>A paſſion ſir, and ſenſe of this captivity,</l>
                  <l>But that I find 'twas error, and not will</l>
                  <l>Lead you to this; and your own loſs now made</l>
                  <l>Irreparable, helpes to tye up my anger.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Al.</speaker>
                  <l>Madam, I muſt confeſs a wrong, and dare</l>
                  <l>Submit to let your anger puniſh me,</l>
                  <l>For I deſpiſe my ſelf, now I have loſt</l>
                  <l>My expectation, and if you pleaſe</l>
                  <l>To think I had no malice in this act</l>
                  <l>To you, You can propoſe no ſatisfaction</l>
                  <l>I ſhall eſteem a penance to repair you,</l>
                  <l>As far as my poor life, if you'l direct it.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Eſt.</speaker>
                  <l>'Tis nobly promis'd ſir. You ſhall redeem</l>
                  <l>In my thoughts what is paſt, if you be pleas'd</l>
                  <l>To make my ſtay no longer here; I have</l>
                  <l>No deſperate aim to make <hi>Don Pedro</hi> yet</l>
                  <l>Know how to right me, or make publick what</l>
                  <l>Should bind his honor to perform.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Al.</speaker>
                  <l>Was not <hi>Luys</hi> Madam entertain'd your Servant?</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Eſt.</speaker>
                  <l>I ſhall make known the ſtory if you walk</l>
                  <l>But to <hi>Don Carlos</hi> Houſe.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Al.</speaker>
                  <l>You ſhall command me.</l>
               </sp>
               <stage>Excunt.</stage>
               <stage>Enter Carlos, Alſimira, and Servant.</stage>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Car.</speaker>
                  <l>No newes yet of <hi>Jacinta?</hi>
                  </l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Al.</speaker>
                  <l>None.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Car.</speaker>
                  <l>He muſt</l>
                  <l>Not live in <hi>Spain,</hi> nor in the World, if my</l>
                  <l>Revenge can overtake him, that has ſtoln</l>
                  <l>My Daughter; could you not by voice or habit</l>
                  <l>Gueſs at the raviſher? Ye are traitors all.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Alſi.</speaker>
                  <l>Now I conſider better, I ſuſpect</l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Alberto</hi> one of the conſpiracie,</l>
                  <pb facs="tcp:153588:64"/>
                  <pb facs="tcp:153588:65"/>
                  <pb n="59" facs="tcp:153588:65"/>
                  <l>Some voice did ſound like his. You know he lov'd her.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Car.</speaker>
                  <l>Ha! <hi>Alberto?</hi>
                  </l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Alſi.</speaker>
                  <l>And how he might engage ſome Ruffians</l>
                  <l>To croſs <hi>Don Pedro.</hi>
                  </l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Car.</speaker>
                  <l>'Twas he, where's <hi>Luys?</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>I do not like his abſence, thei'r both guilty;</l>
                  <l>My own blood turnd a rebell? ſend for the Alcaides,</l>
                  <l>They ſhall both trot like theeves to the Corrigidor.</l>
                  <l>Where is Count <hi>Pedro?</hi>
                  </l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Alſi.</speaker>
                  <l>Gon in ſearch of his loſt Miſtris.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Car.</speaker>
                  <l>When all things were ripe,</l>
                  <l>The very Prieſt prepar'd to ſeal our Ioyes,</l>
                  <l>A work my brain did labour for, and ſweat</l>
                  <l>With hope to ſee accompliſh'd, undermin'd?</l>
                  <l>And in a Minute all blown up?</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Alſi.</speaker>
                  <l>Have patience</l>
                  <l>She may be found agen.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Car.</speaker>
                  <l>But how my Lord</l>
                  <l>May be inclin'd to accept her foil'd, or wounded</l>
                  <stage>Enter Luys drunk.</stage>
                  <l>In fame—</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Alſi.</speaker>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Luys</hi> is here.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Car.</speaker>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Borachio,</hi> here's a ſpectacle! more affliction?</l>
                  <l>Where is your Siſter, whats become of <hi>Jacinta?</hi>
                  </l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Lu.</speaker>
                  <l>My Siſter and <hi>Jacinta</hi> are gone together.</l>
                  <l>I know all the buſineſs.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Alſi.</speaker>
                  <l>Where is ſhe?</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Lu.</speaker>
                  <l>She is very well, I know not where ſhe is.</l>
                  <l>But <hi>Don Alberto</hi> is an honeſt Gentleman,</l>
                  <l>And has by this time done the feat.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Car.</speaker>
                  <l>Confuſion—</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Lu.</speaker>
                  <l>You think you had all the wit, it was my plot.</l>
                  <l>You may thank heaven that you are old, and ugly,</l>
                  <stage>to Alſini</stage>
                  <l>You had been no Mother of this World. But ſir,</l>
                  <l>I have ſome newes would be deliver'd privately.</l>
                  <l>Mother of mine, avant.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Car.</speaker>
                  <l>Th'art not my Son.</l>
                  <l>Was ever man ſo miſerable? away</l>
                  <l>Thou ſpunge; get him to ſleeep,</l>
               </sp>
               <pb n="44" facs="tcp:153588:66"/>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Alſi.</speaker>
                  <l>I dare not medle with him.</l>
               </sp>
               <stage>
                  <hi>Ex</hi> Siſt</stage>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Lu.</speaker>
                  <l>In ſobriety a word. <hi>Car.</hi> Where is <hi>Alberto?</hi>
                  </l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Lu.</speaker>
                  <l>Where every honeſt man ſhould be abed, with <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap>,</l>
                  <l>Old man, I ha'conſider'd o'the former mater we talk'd on</l>
                  <l>And would do things like a dutiful ſon, but I find that a</l>
                  <l>Wife is not altogether ſo convenient for me as a—</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Car.</speaker>
                  <l>Will none deliver me?</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Lu.</speaker>
                  <l>They are ſomewhat ſlug,</l>
                  <l>Now I have found out an excellent tumbler,</l>
                  <p>That can do the Somerſet, pleaſe you to be acquainted with her, and give me your opinion, She ſhall play with all the ſtews in Chriſtendome, for all you are worth, if I live, and yet ſhe is but 17 there's a peri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>winkle, I had a Gemini, before I went to travell, And I am bound in conſcience, if you think fit, to ſee her well Provided for—</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Car.</speaker>
                  <l>With whips, i'l have her skin flead off.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Lu.</speaker>
                  <l>Her skin fled off? doſt thou know mortal man</l>
                  <l>What thou haſt ſaid? I tel the <hi>Don,</hi> nothing can come neer</l>
                  <l>Her in the ſhape of an Officer, ſhe is a very Baſilisk &amp; wil</l>
                  <l>Kill em with her eyes 3 ſcore yards point blank, but you</l>
                  <l>May talk, &amp; do your pleaſure with her, for I came a</l>
                  <l>Purpoſe to bring her to your lodging, if you love me,</l>
                  <l>Do but ſee her, it ſhall coſt you nothing, you ſhall</l>
                  <l>Be my friend, hang money?</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Car.</speaker>
                  <l>Thus will my ſtate conſume, vexation!</l>
                  <l>What ſhall I do? when you have ſlept <hi>Luys</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>I'l tell you more, attend him to his Chamber</l>
                  <l>And make his Door faſt.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Luys</speaker>
                  <l>You vvill conſider on't, upon thoſe terms, I vvil go</l>
                  <l>Sleep at vvinckling.</l>
               </sp>
               <stage>Exit.</stage>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Car.</speaker>
                  <l>And vvo'not all this take a vvay my ſenſes?</l>
                  <l>My Son is loft too, this is all a curſe</l>
                  <l>For my ambition and my Avarice.</l>
               </sp>
               <stage>Enter Alſimra and a ſervant with a Letter.</stage>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Alſ.</speaker>
                  <l>Nevvs <hi>Don Carlos</hi> from our Daughter.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Car.</speaker>
                  <l>Ha, a Letteri 'tis <hi>Iacintas</hi> hand.</l>
               </sp>
               <pb facs="tcp:153588:66"/>
               <pb facs="tcp:153588:67"/>
               <pb n="45" facs="tcp:153588:67"/>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Alſi.</speaker>
                  <l>Knovv'ſt vvhere ſhe is?</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Ser.</speaker>
                  <l>Yes Madam, and her reſolution</l>
                  <stage>Carl. reads.</stage>
                  <l>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>o attend her Father, with my Maſter <hi>Don Pranciſco</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>f <hi>Don Carlos</hi> pleaſe to admit 'em, the matters done.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Alſi.</speaker>
                  <l>What matter?</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Ser.</speaker>
                  <l>They are as faſt as any Prieſt can make em.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Car.</speaker>
                  <l>Wife to <hi>Franciſco,</hi> now his Fathers heir?</l>
                  <l>That's ſome allay, if it be true, ſhe writes,</l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Don Pedro</hi> was contracted to <hi>Eſtefania,</hi> who ſupplied</l>
                  <l>Her perſon in the Coach—twas not <hi>Jacinta</hi> was raviſh'd</l>
                  <l>Then, <hi>Don Pedro</hi> was not noble, after he had made faith,</l>
                  <l>To intangle my <hi>Iacinta.</hi> Hum, ſay they ſhall</l>
                  <l>Be welcome. <hi>Ser.</hi> They are preſent fir.</l>
               </sp>
               <stage>Enter Franciſco and Iacinta.</stage>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Car.</speaker>
                  <l>I am nor yet collected, but'if this</l>
                  <l>Paper be juſtified, I receive you both.</l>
                  <l>Peruſe thoſe wonders <hi>Alſimira.</hi>
                  </l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Iacin.</speaker>
                  <l>Sir, though by the tye of nature you may chal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lenge</l>
                  <l>All duty, this is done ſo like a Father</l>
                  <l>It exceeds all your care.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Fran.</speaker>
                  <l>Let this confirme,</l>
                  <l>I bring a fortune not to be deſpis'd,</l>
                  <l>But were I Maſter of the World, I ſhould</l>
                  <l>At price of all my wealth, thiuk this a treaſure</l>
                  <l>Purchac'd too cheap.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Car.</speaker>
                  <l>My bleſſing and my prayers, I'm new created,</l>
                  <l>And bow to that great providence; all Joy</l>
                  <l>Spread through your ſoules; this is not much amiſs.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Fran.</speaker>
                  <l>But what's become of Madam <hi>Eſtefania</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>That took <hi>Iacintas</hi> place?</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Alſi.</speaker>
                  <l>Forc'd from the Coach</l>
                  <l>By <hi>Don Alberto,</hi> thinking her my Daughter</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Iacin.</speaker>
                  <l>That part of our plot fail'd, but my intents</l>
                  <l>Were fair, and to aſſiſt this injur'd Ladie</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Ser.</speaker>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Don Pedro</hi> ſir.</l>
               </sp>
               <stage>Enter Servant.</stage>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Car.</speaker>
                  <l>You ſhall for ſome few minutes.</l>
                  <pb n="62" facs="tcp:153588:68"/>
                  <l>Withdraw into that Chamber, in his paſſion</l>
                  <l>He may be violent, leave me to moderate.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Fra.</speaker>
                  <l>I ſhall obey you fir.</l>
               </sp>
               <stage>Exit</stage>
               <stage>Enter Pedro.</stage>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Fed.</speaker>
                  <l>Was ever man of my great birth and fortune</l>
                  <l>Affronted thus? I am become the talk</l>
                  <l>Of every <hi>Picaro</hi> and <hi>Ladron,</hi> I challenge</l>
                  <l>A reparation of my honor; where's</l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Jacinta?</hi> tis a plot, a bace contrivement</l>
                  <l>To make my name ridiculous, the ſubject</l>
                  <l>Of every ſcurrill language.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Car.</speaker>
                  <l>My Lord with pardon</l>
                  <l>Of your <hi>Alteſa,</hi> y'are not Injur'd here,</l>
                  <l>Unleſs I have been faulty in too much</l>
                  <l>Obſervance, and deſires to ſerve your perſon,</l>
                  <l>VVith almoſt ſacrifice of my Daughter.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Ped.</speaker>
                  <l>Ha! too much to me?</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Car.</speaker>
                  <l>I would you had remembred</l>
                  <l>How much your Honor was engag'd before,</l>
                  <l>By Contract to another, when you mock'd</l>
                  <l>The Innocent <hi>Jacinta,</hi> now not mine.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Ped.</speaker>
                  <l>VVho hath traduc'd my fame, or mention'd me</l>
                  <l>VVith that diſhonour? I diſclaim all Contracts.</l>
                  <l>The unconfin'd Aire's not more free, than I</l>
                  <l>To all the World, except your beauteous Daughter.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Car.</speaker>
                  <l>Do you know the Lady <hi>Eſtefania?</hi>
                  </l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Ped.</speaker>
                  <l>Dares ſhe make ſaucie claim? my breath diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolves it</l>
                  <l>If every Lady whom we grace with our</l>
                  <l>Converſe ſhould, challenge men of my Nobility—</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Car.</speaker>
                  <l>I wiſh my Lord you could evade it, for</l>
                  <l>The honor of my Family; if your conſcience</l>
                  <l>Or Art can nullifie that Ladies sintereſt</l>
                  <l>I am reſolv'd—my Son <hi>Luys</hi> ſhall
<stage>Aſide.</stage>
                  </l>
                  <l>Then marry With that Widdow, I have no other</l>
                  <l>Ambition.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Ped.</speaker>
                  <l>You are wiſe, and I</l>
                  <pb facs="tcp:153588:68"/>
                  <pb facs="tcp:153588:69"/>
                  <pb n="63" facs="tcp:153588:69"/>
                  <l>Am fortified to clear my ſelf thought-free</l>
                  <stage>Enter Alberto, Fſtefania with a Letter.</stage>
                  <l>From any promiſe to that ſullen Madam.</l>
                  <l>Ha! tis <hi>Jacinta,</hi> and ſhe wears the Jewell</l>
                  <l>I did preſent, conſpicuouſly; I ask</l>
                  <l>No reaſor for thy abſence, let me chain</l>
                  <l>My darling in this amorous curl, tis happineſs</l>
                  <l>Enough to repoſſeſs thee, not the policie</l>
                  <l>And power of Hell ſhall ſeparate us agen.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Fſte.</speaker>
                  <l>It is but Juſtice ſir. <hi>Ped.</hi> Ha! <hi>Eſtefania.</hi>
                  </l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Alb.</speaker>
                  <l>Do you know her ſir?</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Eſte.</speaker>
                  <l>Do you know this character? <hi>Ped.</hi> Conſpiracy.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Eſt.</speaker>
                  <l>When this is read <hi>Don Carlos</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>You will imagine he has wrong'd your Daughter.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Car.</speaker>
                  <l>Is this your hand Count <hi>Pedro?</hi>
                  </l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Ped.</speaker>
                  <l>Mine—tis counterfeit</l>
                  <l>Upon my honor, and I thus diſſolve</l>
                  <l>Thy inſolent claim.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Eſte.</speaker>
                  <l>Nothing can bind I ſee</l>
                  <l>A falſe heart</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Car.</speaker>
                  <l>This muſt give you freedom Madam,</l>
                  <l>If you releaſe his haſty vow.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Eſte.</speaker>
                  <l>Faith cannot</l>
                  <l>Be compeld ſir.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Ped.</speaker>
                  <l>Theſe are all Impoſtures;</l>
                  <l>I take my ſelf into my ſelf.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Alb.</speaker>
                  <l>What ſhall become of her my noble Count?</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Ped.</speaker>
                  <l>I pitty her</l>
                  <l>But cannot cure her wound, and if you be</l>
                  <l>Her friend, adviſe her to contain her paſſions,</l>
                  <l>And wiſely love one that can entertain it.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Alb.</speaker>
                  <l>You hear this Madam?</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Eſte.</speaker>
                  <l>And can ſmile upon</l>
                  <l>His viol ated fath.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Car.</speaker>
                  <l>Now for <hi>Luys,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>To ſtrike in with the Widdow.</l>
               </sp>
               <pb n="48" facs="tcp:153588:70"/>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Servant.</speaker>
                  <l>Hae's a ſleep.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Car.</speaker>
                  <l>Ile wake and quicken him.</l>
               </sp>
               <stage>Exit.</stage>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>
                     <hi>
                        <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>ſte.</hi>
                  </speaker>
                  <l>Hadſt thou bin worth my love, I ſhould have held</l>
                  <l>Thee worth my anger ſhadow, of a Lord.</l>
                  <l>Thy greatneſs I deſpiſe, and think thee now</l>
                  <l>Too poor for my revenge, and freely give</l>
                  <l>Thee back thy barren promiſes, and when</l>
                  <l>I read in ſtory, one that has been perjur'd,</l>
                  <l>I'l write <hi>Don Pearo</hi> in the place of him</l>
                  <l>That brok his faith, and thank my fate t' have miſt thee.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Alb.</speaker>
                  <l>If you pleaſe Madam, while he is i'th' humor</l>
                  <l>Of being baſe, I'l make him gather up</l>
                  <l>Theſe paper reliques, which he ſhall make him ſelf</l>
                  <l>Up into rolls, and having ſwallowed 'em</l>
                  <l>For Pills, thank you, his Phyſick was ſo gentle.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Eſte.</speaker>
                  <l>It will be too much time &amp; breath loſt on him.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Alber.</speaker>
                  <l>It will become me Madam to attend you.</l>
               </sp>
               <stage>Exit Eſte.</stage>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Ped.</speaker>
                  <l>So, ſhe is taken off' and my path free</l>
                  <l>To <hi>Carlos</hi> Daughter.</l>
               </sp>
               <stage>Enter Carlos and Luys.</stage>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Luys.</speaker>
                  <l>Contracted to <hi>Don Pedro?</hi> ſay.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Car.</speaker>
                  <l>She was, where is <hi>Eſtefania?</hi>
                  </l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Ped.</speaker>
                  <l>Gone with <hi>Alberto;</hi> proud to wait upon</l>
                  <l>The Lady I neglected.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Car.</speaker>
                  <l>Follow 'em <hi>Luys?</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>I do not like he ſhould inſinuate</l>
                  <l>Now ſhe is free, and his hopes deſperat in</l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Jacintas</hi> love. <hi>Luys</hi> How long have I ſlept ſir?</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Car.</speaker>
                  <l>Thou doſt dream ſtill, perſue the Widdow now</l>
                  <l>Or never look at ſuch a fortune.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Luys</speaker>
                  <l>Is ſhe gone with <hi>Alberto?</hi> what if I ſay,</l>
                  <l>I have lain with her, and that ſhee's with child by me?</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Car.</speaker>
                  <l>That would ſtain both your fames; away and welcom</l>
                  <l>When thou return'ſt, and ſhe confirm'd.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Luys</speaker>
                  <l>Ile confirm her, or confound ſomebody,</l>
                  <pb facs="tcp:153588:70"/>
                  <pb facs="tcp:153588:71"/>
                  <pb n="65" facs="tcp:153588:71"/>
                  <l>No more, I am awake, this is <hi>Don Pedro</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>I'l talk with him firſt, vvill you juſtefie,</l>
                  <l>The Widdovv is a Widdovv ſtill, and ſweet</l>
                  <l>For all your Contract, that you have not been</l>
                  <l>My rivall as they ſay after the fleſh,</l>
                  <l>And that you did not knovv I had a mind,</l>
                  <l>Or not a mind, to do the deed of Matrimony?</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Ped.</speaker>
                  <l>Not I upon my honor.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Luys</speaker>
                  <l>You are vvitneſs—novv to <hi>Alberte.</hi>
                  </l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Car.</speaker>
                  <l>Manage the bufineſs temperatly.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Luys</speaker>
                  <l>Let me alone to be temperate, if I do not coſen</l>
                  <l>Some body, let me never drink Sack agen.</l>
               </sp>
               <stage>Exit.</stage>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Car.</speaker>
                  <l>What think you of <hi>Jacinta</hi> novv my Lord?</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Ped.</speaker>
                  <l>As on the Saint I pay my chief devotions.</l>
               </sp>
               <stage>Enter Fernando.</stage>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Fer.</speaker>
                  <l>I come to ſeek one, that I late call'd Brother,</l>
                  <l>But he hath forfeted that Name, and Juſtice</l>
                  <l>Weary of ſuch a prodigy in nature</l>
                  <l>Hath arm'd me thus in her revenge, <hi>Don Carlos,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>Obſcure him not, no darkneſs can protect him,</l>
                  <l>My ſvvord ſhall forrage every room like lightning,</l>
                  <l>No Cave but it ſhall viſit, and through ribs</l>
                  <l>Of ſteel compell my paſſage to his heart,</l>
                  <l>Although I meet him in his Miſtr is Armes,</l>
                  <l>The lovers Sanctuary, I dare force <hi>Franciſco,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>And vvith my Svvord cut the Embrace that chains him,</l>
                  <l>Rather then he ſhall glory in my ruines,</l>
                  <l>And revell out, thoſe honors, vvith her, he</l>
                  <l>Took from my blood.</l>
               </sp>
               <stage>Enter Franciſco with a Parchment.</stage>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Fra.</speaker>
                  <l>It ſhall not need <hi>Fernando.</hi>
                  </l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Ped.</speaker>
                  <l>Hum, here is like to be a bloody buſineſs,</l>
                  <l>I'l not diſturb 'em.</l>
               </sp>
               <stage>Exit.</stage>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Car.</speaker>
                  <l>As you are Brothers, by your Fathers duſt</l>
                  <l>That ſhould ſleep quiet in his Urne, by her</l>
                  <l>Dear name that gave you life, that novv prayes for you,</l>
                  <pb n="66" facs="tcp:153588:72"/>
                  <l>Chide this unnaturall furie.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Fra.</speaker>
                  <l>VVhat demands <hi>Fernando?</hi>
                  </l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Fer.</speaker>
                  <l>My inheritance wrought from me</l>
                  <l>By thy ſlie creeping to ſupplant my birth,</l>
                  <l>And cheat our Fathers eaſie ſoul, unvvorthily</l>
                  <l>Betraying to his anger for thy luſt</l>
                  <l>Of wealth, the love and promiſe of two hearts,</l>
                  <l>Poor <hi>Feliſarda</hi> and <hi>Fernando</hi> now</l>
                  <l>Wither at ſoul, and rob'd by thee of that</l>
                  <l>Should cheriſh virtue, like to rifled Pilgrims</l>
                  <l>Met on the way, and having told their ſtory,</l>
                  <l>And drop'd their even teares for both their loſs,</l>
                  <l>Wander from one another.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Fra.</speaker>
                  <l>Tis not ſure</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Fernando,</speaker>
                  <l>but his paſion (that obeys not</l>
                  <l>The counſel of his reaſon) would accuſe me,</l>
                  <l>And if my Father now, ſince ſpirits loſe not</l>
                  <l>Intelligence, but more active when they have</l>
                  <l>Shook off their chains of fleſh, would leave his dwel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling,</l>
                  <l>And viſit this courſe orbe agen: my Innocence</l>
                  <l>Should dare the appeal, and make <hi>Fernando</hi> ſee</l>
                  <l>His empty accuſations.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Fer.</speaker>
                  <l>He that thrives</l>
                  <l>By wicked art, has confidence to dreſs</l>
                  <l>His action with ſimplicity, and ſhapes</l>
                  <l>To cheat our credulous natures, tis my wonder</l>
                  <l>Thou durſt do ſo much injury <hi>Franciſco</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>As muſt provoke my Juſtice, to revenge,</l>
                  <l>Yet wear no Sword.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Fra.</speaker>
                  <l>I need no guard, I know</l>
                  <l>Thou darſt not kill me.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Fer.</speaker>
                  <l>Dare I not?</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Fra.</speaker>
                  <l>And name thy cauſe, tis thy ſuſpition not <hi>Fran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciſo</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>Hath wrought thee high and paſſionate, to aſſure it,</l>
                  <l>If you dare violate, I dare poſſeſs you</l>
                  <l>Wit hall my title to your Land.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Car.</speaker>
                  <l>How is that?</l>
                  <pb facs="tcp:153588:72"/>
                  <pb facs="tcp:153588:73"/>
                  <pb n="67" facs="tcp:153588:73"/>
                  <l>Will you reſign the intereſt to ſuch</l>
                  <l>A fair Eſtate, and wrong my Daughter ſir?</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Fra</speaker>
                  <l>Let him receive it at his perill.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Fer.</speaker>
                  <l>Ha!</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Fra.</speaker>
                  <l>It was my Fathers act, not mine, he trembled</l>
                  <l>To hear his curſe alive, what horror will</l>
                  <l>His conſcience feel, when he ſhall ſpurn his duſt,</l>
                  <l>And call the reverend ſhade from his bleſt ſeat,</l>
                  <l>To this bad World again, to walk and fright him?</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Car.</speaker>
                  <l>I am abus'd</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Fer.</speaker>
                  <l>Can this be more than dream?</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Fra.</speaker>
                  <l>Sir you may cancell it, but think withall</l>
                  <l>How you can anſwer him that's dead, when he</l>
                  <l>Shall charge your timorous ſoul for this contempt</l>
                  <l>To nature and Religion, to break</l>
                  <l>His laſt bequeſt, and breath, that ſeal'd your bleſſings?</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Car.</speaker>
                  <l>Theſe are fine fancies.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Fer.</speaker>
                  <l>Here, and may it proſper,</l>
                  <l>Where my good Father meant it, I'm orecome.</l>
                  <l>Forgive me, and enjoy it, I may find</l>
                  <l>Some Earth that is not thine, where I may dy</l>
                  <l>And take up a dark Chamber, love <hi>Jacinta,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>And while I ſeek out where to be forgotten</l>
                  <l>Live happy, and devide the ſpring between you,</l>
               </sp>
               <stage>Enter Ramires, Feliſarda, and Teodoro, aloof.</stage>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Fra.</speaker>
                  <l>So, ſo, all's well agen.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Ram.</speaker>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Fernando</hi> ſtay.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Fer.</speaker>
                  <l>Ha, my Father and <hi>Feliſarda?</hi>
                  </l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Car.</speaker>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Don Ramyres</hi> and my Neece?</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Fer.</speaker>
                  <l>Are they both dead?</l>
                  <stage>Fer. Kneels.</stage>
                  <l>I dare kneel too, they do converſe. <hi>Don Carlos</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>Do not you know that ſhape? 'tis wondrous like</l>
                  <l>Your Neece.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Car.</speaker>
                  <l>And that your Father, ha!</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Fer.</speaker>
                  <l>How long hath <hi>Feliſarda</hi> been a ſad</l>
                  <l>Companion to the ſhades? I did not think</l>
                  <l>To find thee in this pale ſociety,</l>
                  <l>Of ghoſts ſo ſoon.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Feliſar.</speaker>
                  <l>I am alive <hi>Fernando,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <pb n="68" facs="tcp:153588:74"/>
                  <l>And <hi>Don Ramires</hi> ſtill, thy living Father.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Fra.</speaker>
                  <l>You may believe it ſir, I was o'th' counſell.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Fer.</speaker>
                  <l>It is a joy will tempt me, wiſh to live</l>
                  <l>Here, without more ambition to change</l>
                  <l>For bleſſings of the other World; and is</l>
                  <l>My Father willing that wee both ſhould live?</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Car.</speaker>
                  <l>Men thought you dead.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Ramir.</speaker>
                  <l>It lay within the knowledge of <hi>Franciſco</hi> and ſome few</l>
                  <l>By this device to advance my younger Son</l>
                  <l>To a Mariage with <hi>Jacinta</hi> ſir, and try</l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Fernando</hi>'s Piety and his Miſtris Vertue,</l>
                  <l>Which I have found worth him, and my acceptance,</l>
                  <l>With her I give thee what thy birth did challenge.</l>
                  <l>Receive thy <hi>Feliſarda.</hi>
                  </l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Fer.</speaker>
                  <l>'Tis a joy,</l>
                  <l>So flowing, it drowns all my faculties,</l>
                  <l>My ſoul will not contain I fear, but loſe</l>
                  <l>And leave me in this extaſie.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Car.</speaker>
                  <l>I am cheated.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Ra.</speaker>
                  <l>Not ſo, what dower you add above that fortune,</l>
                  <l>Deſcends upon her by your Siſters Legacie</l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Franciſco</hi> ſhall deſerve, with a proportion</l>
                  <stage>Enter Franciſco and Jacinta.</stage>
                  <l>Out of my ſtate; live, and be happy both,</l>
                  <l>You ſhall not want a Father in my care.</l>
                  <l>Our children thus increas'd <hi>Don Carlos,</hi> 'tis</l>
                  <l>Our ſhame if we neglect 'em; <hi>Teodore</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>You now may call me Brother.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Theſ.</speaker>
                  <l>I'm honor'd.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Car.</speaker>
                  <l>Well, take my bleſſing too, love her <hi>Franciſco.</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>My bounty is to come, and if my Son</l>
                  <l>But finiſh with his Miſtris—hee's return'd,</l>
                  <stage>Enter Luys.</stage>
                  <l>Where is the Widdow?</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Lu.</speaker>
                  <l>Sure enough.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Car.</speaker>
                  <l>And <hi>Don Alberto.</hi>
                  </l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Lu.</speaker>
                  <l>I ha made him ſure too, I ha pepper'd him.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Car.</speaker>
                  <l>How?</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Lu.</speaker>
                  <l>In your ear, I ha cut his throat, do none perſue</l>
               </sp>
               <pb facs="tcp:153588:74"/>
               <pb facs="tcp:153588:75"/>
               <pb n="69" facs="tcp:153588:75"/>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Car.</speaker>
                  <l>I hope thou haſt not kil'd him? ha!</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Lu.</speaker>
                  <l>You hope to late, I could not help it, you ſaid</l>
                  <l>He was my Rivall.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Car.</speaker>
                  <l>Not to loud.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Lù.</speaker>
                  <l>Where, where ſhall I obſcure me, the Alcaides</l>
                  <l>Will be here preſently, and ſearch for me.</l>
                  <l>I left him giving up the ghoſt, at a cranny</l>
                  <l>I made into his ſide, through which a man</l>
                  <l>Might ſee into his midriff.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Car.</speaker>
                  <l>Art thou deſperate?</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Lu.</speaker>
                  <l>Beſide one window that did look into his lungs,</l>
                  <l>From whence his wind came ſtrong enough,</l>
                  <l>In ſix hours ſail to diſpatch a Carrack to the ſtraightes.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Car.</speaker>
                  <l>I'm mad.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Lu.</speaker>
                  <l>I ſhould neglect my life, but 'twould not ſound well</l>
                  <l>With your honor that <hi>Don Carlos</hi> Son was hang'd,</l>
                  <l>Or put into the Gallies; are they not come yet?</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Car.</speaker>
                  <l>I am undone, there is no ſafety here,</l>
                  <l>Make faſt thoſe doors, and by the Poſtern gate</l>
                  <l>Thou maiſt eſcape, take the beſt Horſe, away.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Lu.</speaker>
                  <l>I ſhall want money ſir.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Car.</speaker>
                  <l>Come follow me?</l>
                  <l>This accident I fear will quite diſtract me.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Lu.</speaker>
                  <l>You muſt diſpatch me quickly ſir, there is</l>
                  <l>No ſtaying to tell the money, gee't me in lump,</l>
                  <l>I'l count it afterwards, good ſir make haſt.</l>
               </sp>
               <stage>Exit. Lu. &amp; Car.</stage>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Ra.</speaker>
                  <l>Something hath hapned that doth freſh</l>
                  <l>Perplex him.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Fra.</speaker>
                  <l>Where is <hi>Don Pedro?</hi>
                  </l>
               </sp>
               <stage>Enter Pedro.</stage>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Fer.</speaker>
                  <l>Hee's here.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Ped.</speaker>
                  <l>The ſtorm is over ſure, I hear no noiſe,</l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Toledos</hi> are aſleep, <hi>Jacinta?</hi> have</l>
                  <l>I found my love?</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Fran.</speaker>
                  <l>Here 'twas loſt indeed,</l>
                  <l>I muſt allow no ſuch Familiarity</l>
                  <l>With my Wife.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Ped.</speaker>
                  <l>How? married?</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Ja.</speaker>
                  <l>'Tis moſt true my Lord.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Ped.</speaker>
                  <l>You have not us'd me thus?</l>
               </sp>
               <pb n="70" facs="tcp:153588:76"/>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Fra.</speaker>
                  <l>It had been Impious to divorce your heart</l>
                  <l>From <hi>Eſtefania;</hi> My good Lord, wee know</l>
                  <l>Your Lordſhip is religious in your promiſes.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Ped.</speaker>
                  <l>I defy all <hi>Eſtefanias,</hi> Lady you are civill.</l>
               </sp>
               <stage>To Fe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſ.</stage>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Fer.</speaker>
                  <l>It will become my care ſo to preſerve her</l>
                  <l>My Honorable Count.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Ped.</speaker>
                  <l>Honorable?</l>
                  <l>It appeares not by theſe contempts.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Ramyr.</speaker>
                  <l>Your Lordſhip cannot want a Female Furniture.</l>
               </sp>
               <stage>Enter Alberto and Eſtefania.</stage>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Ped.</speaker>
                  <l>I muſt have ſome body now I'm prepar'd, my blood</l>
                  <l>Will take itill, would I had <hi>Eſtefaenia;</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>Shee's here, Madam I hope you have</l>
                  <l>A better faith than to believe I was in Earneſt,</l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Don Pedro</hi> is only at your ſervice.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Eſte.</speaker>
                  <l>'Tis too late ſir, this Gent. is witneſs,</l>
                  <l>Of your ſurrender, and is now poſſeſt</l>
                  <l>Of all that's mine.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Al.</speaker>
                  <l>It was your Noble bounty,</l>
                  <l>For which I cannot ſtudy a return</l>
                  <l>More apt than to reſign to your good Lordſhip,</l>
                  <l>My Intereſt in <hi>Jacinta,</hi> give you joy Count.</l>
                  <l>Such a rich Widdow ſerves my turn.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Ped.</speaker>
                  <l>So ſo,</l>
                  <l>If I conſider well this is but Juſtice.</l>
               </sp>
               <stage>Enter Carlos.</stage>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Car.</speaker>
                  <l>Ha, are not you <hi>Don Alberto:</hi> fetch back <hi>Luys.</hi>
                  </l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Al.</speaker>
                  <l>The very ſame ſir, and this Lady is my Wife,</l>
                  <l>Pleaſe you ſalute her.</l>
               </sp>
               <stage>Enter Luys.</stage>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Luys</speaker>
                  <l>Sir for the credit of your wiſdom talk not,</l>
                  <l>The man you ſee's alive and married too,</l>
                  <l>With my conſent, alas I ow'd him mony,</l>
                  <l>That Widdow has paid all, I muſt be honeſt,</l>
                  <l>I had no heart to leave you ſo unſatisfied,</l>
                  <l>Theſe ſums muſt go for other debts,</l>
                  <pb facs="tcp:153588:76"/>
                  <pb facs="tcp:153588:77"/>
                  <pb n="71" facs="tcp:153588:77"/>
                  <l>My debts do clog my conſcience, and are better</l>
                  <l>W<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 span">
                        <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                     </gap> are timely paid ſir, then let run</l>
                  <l>With their <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>g Teeth to bite your ſtate hereafter,</l>
                  <l>A<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 span">
                        <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                     </gap> when I am free you dare but truſt me—</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>
                     <hi>
                        <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                           <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                        </gap>
                     </hi>
                  </speaker>
                  <l>Was ever Father cheated thus, come hither,</l>
                  <l>H<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 span">
                        <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                     </gap> thou be ſo impudent?</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>
                     <hi>
                        <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 span">
                           <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                        </gap>
                     </hi>
                  </speaker>
                  <l>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 span">
                        <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                     </gap> cannot help it ſir, unleſs you dye</l>
                  <l>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 span">
                        <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                     </gap> me better means, I ſhall make bold</l>
                  <l>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 span">
                        <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                     </gap> devices, you are my Father ſir,</l>
                  <l>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 span">
                        <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                     </gap> bound—</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Car.</speaker>
                  <l>To coſen me?</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>
                     <hi>
                        <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                           <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                        </gap>
                     </hi>
                  </speaker>
                  <l>All muſt be mine, and if</l>
                  <l>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 span">
                        <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                     </gap> ſelf a little before the day,</l>
                  <l>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 span">
                        <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                     </gap> be no loſer when you come to reckon,</l>
                  <l>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap> 
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ha'not make a breach twixt you and I,</l>
                  <l>They are honeſt men I ow this money too,</l>
                  <l>When I am cleer preſcribe me any method</l>
                  <l>And rank me like your ſon, I will deſerve</l>
                  <l>Y<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 chunk">
                        <desc>…</desc>
                     </gap> ſhall forget my wildneſs, and acknowledge me</l>
                  <l>A convert without blemiſh to your family.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>
                     <hi>
                        <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 chunk">
                           <desc>…</desc>
                        </gap>m<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>.</hi>
                  </speaker>
                  <l>I muſt be Interceſſor.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>
                     <hi>J<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>c<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>n</hi>
                  </speaker>
                  <l>And we all.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Car.</speaker>
                  <l>I'l think upon't.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Ped.</speaker>
                  <l>Since I cannot have <hi>Jacinta,</hi> I deſire</l>
                  <l>I may have her Brother.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Lu.</speaker>
                  <l>Not in marriage.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Ped.</speaker>
                  <l>I like his wit, his ſpirit, and his humor,</l>
                  <l>D<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> not you love a wench?</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Lu.</speaker>
                  <l>Yes ſir.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Ped.</speaker>
                  <l>Thou ſha't never want.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Lu.</speaker>
                  <l>Wenches?</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Ped.</speaker>
                  <l>Wee'l live together, and if thy Father</l>
                  <l>Be n<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>t bountifull, thou ſhalt command my fortune.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Lu.</speaker>
                  <l>You ſpeak nobly.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Ped.</speaker>
                  <l>Ladies, I ask your pardon</l>
                  <l>Unleſs you hold me deſperate, diſdaine not</l>
                  <l>That I may this day wait upon your triumph,</l>
                  <l>And to each Bride offer ſome guift to expiate</l>
                  <l>My folly and offence.</l>
               </sp>
               <pb n="72" facs="tcp:153588:78"/>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Rami.</speaker>
                  <l>You are too bountifull.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Car.</speaker>
                  <l>Y'are all my gueſts to day.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Rami.</speaker>
                  <l>I beg your next</l>
                  <l>Remove may place the Scen of Joy with me,</l>
                  <l>My houſe ſhall be much honor'd, lead the way</l>
                  <l>With Verſe and Wine let Poets crown this day.</l>
               </sp>
               <stage>Exeunt omnes.</stage>
            </div>
            <div type="epilogue">
               <head>Epilogue. <hi>Pedro.</hi>
               </head>
               <lg>
                  <l>
                     <hi>SO ſo, your dangers over, and the ſtate</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Secure, as when our Fleet in Eighty Eight</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Was fir'd and ſcatter'd, to confirm it true</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Here is</hi> Don Pedro <hi>taken Priſoner too,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>I'm at your mercy Gentlemen, and I</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Confeſs without a rack conſpiracy,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>So far as my poor part i'th' Play comes too,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>But I am innocent from hurt to you,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>And I dare quit the reſt from any plot</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Meant but to pleaſe, if you believe it not</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>I dare make oath, your hands can do no leſs</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Than certifie your friends what I confeſs.</hi>
                  </l>
               </lg>
            </div>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
            <pb facs="tcp:153588:78"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:153588:79"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:153588:79"/>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
