<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>The cardinal, a tragedie, as it was acted at the private house in Black Fryers, wriiten by James Shirley. Not printed before</title>
            <author>Shirley, James, 1596-1666.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1652</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 154 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 41 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2012-10">2012-10 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A93167</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing S3461</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R230011</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99895772</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99895772</idno>
            <idno type="VID">153343</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A93167)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 153343)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 2359:28)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>The cardinal, a tragedie, as it was acted at the private house in Black Fryers, wriiten by James Shirley. Not printed before</title>
                  <author>Shirley, James, 1596-1666.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[8], 69, [3] p. :   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>printed for Humphrey Robinson at the Three Pigeons, and Humphrey Moseley at the Princes Arms in St. Paul's Church-yard,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1652.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Also published as part of: Six new playes, ... All written by James Shirley.--Wing (CD-ROM edition) S3486.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in the Folger Shakespeare Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2011-06</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-06</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-07</date>
            <label>Lauren Proux</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-07</date>
            <label>Lauren Proux</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-05</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:153343:1"/>
            <p>THE CARDINAL, A TRAGEDIE, AS It was acted at the private Houſe IN <hi>BLACK FRYERS,</hi> WRITTEN By JAMES SHIRLEY.</p>
            <p>Not Printed before.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON,</hi> Printed for <hi>Humphrey Robinſon</hi> at the Pigeons, and <hi>Humphrey Moſeley</hi> at the Arms in St. <hi>Paul</hi>'s Church-yard. 1652.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="dedication">
            <pb facs="tcp:153343:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:153343:2"/>
            <head>To my worthily honored Friend <hi>G. B.</hi> Eſq</head>
            <opener>
               <salute>SIR,</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>
               <hi>I</hi> Did ſuffer at the firſt ſome contention with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in me, and looking upon my ſelf, was inclined to ſtifle my ambitious thoughts in this Dedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cation; but when ſome time, and a happy con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſation, had preferred me to more acquaintance with you, (which was more argument to me, than the fame I had heard of your reputation, with the most temperate and ingenious men) I found you not only an excellent Judge, but a good Man: at this my modesty took full encouragement, to make this offering, which as I conceive to be the beſt of my flock, I knew not a better Altar whereon to make it a ſacrifice, with this proteſtation, that it comes (and that is it only, which makes all devoti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons
<pb facs="tcp:153343:3"/>acceptable) from the heart, and your candid acceptance will bind me with all my ſervices, and remembrance, to merit a reception with you, in the quality and honour of,</p>
            <closer>
               <salute>Sir,</salute>
               <signed>Your moſt humble devoted Servant, <hi>JA. SHIRLEY</hi>
               </signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="prologue">
            <pb facs="tcp:153343:3"/>
            <head>Prologue.</head>
            <lg>
               <l>THe Cardinal, cauſe we expreſs no ſcene,</l>
               <l>We doe believe moſt of you Gentlemen</l>
               <l>Are at this hour in <hi>France,</hi> and buſie there,</l>
               <l>Though you vouchſafe to lend your bodies here;</l>
               <l>But keep your fancy active, till you know</l>
               <l>By th' progreſs of our Play, 'tis nothing ſo;</l>
               <l>A Poets art is to lead on your thought</l>
               <l>Through ſubtle paths and workings of a plot,</l>
               <l>And where your expectation does not thrive,</l>
               <l>If things fall better, yet you may forgive;</l>
               <l>I will ſay nothing poſitive, you may</l>
               <l>Think what you pleaſe, we call it but a Play,</l>
               <l>Whether the comick Muſe, or Ladies love,</l>
               <l>Romance, or direfull Tragedy it prove,</l>
               <l>The Bill determines not; and would you be</l>
               <l>Perſwaded, I would have't a Comedie,</l>
               <l>For all the purple in the name, and ſtate</l>
               <l>Of him that owns it; but 'tis left to fate;</l>
               <l>Yet I will tell you e'r you ſee it plaid,</l>
               <l>What the Author, and he bluſht too, when he ſaid</l>
               <l>(Comparing with his own for 't had been pride</l>
               <l>He thought, to build his wit a Pyramyde.</l>
               <l>Vpon anothers wounded Fame,) this Play</l>
               <l>Might rivall with his beſt, and dar'd to ſay</l>
               <l>Troth I am out; he ſaid no more; you then,</l>
               <l>When'ts done, may ſay your pleaſures Gentlemen.</l>
            </lg>
         </div>
         <div type="encomium">
            <pb facs="tcp:153343:4"/>
            <head>To the ſurviving Honour and Ornament of the Engliſh Scene, <hi>Iames Shirley.</hi>
            </head>
            <lg>
               <l>AS Fate, which doth all human matters ſway,</l>
               <l>Makes produeſt things grow up into decay;</l>
               <l>And when they are to envyed greatneſs grown,</l>
               <l>She wantonly falls off, and throws them down:</l>
               <l>So, when our Engliſh Dramma was at hight,</l>
               <l>And ſhin'd, and rul'd with Majeſty and might,</l>
               <l>A ſudden whirlwind threw it from it ſeat,</l>
               <l>Deflowr'd the Groves, and quench'd the Muſes heat.</l>
               <l>Yet as in Saints, and Martyr'd bodies, when</l>
               <l>They cannot call their bleſſed Souls agen</l>
               <l>To earth; Reliques, and aſhes men preſerve,</l>
               <l>And think they do, but what, bleſt they deſerve:</l>
               <l>So I, by my devotion led, aſpire</l>
               <l>To keep alive your noble Veſtal fire,</l>
               <l>Honour this piece, which ſhews, Sir, you have been</l>
               <l>The laſt ſupporter of the dying Scene;</l>
               <l>And though I do not tell you, how you dreſs</l>
               <l>Virtue in gloryes, and bold vice depreſs;</l>
               <l>Nor celebrate your lovely Dutcheſs fall,</l>
               <l>Or the juſt ruine of your Cardinal;</l>
               <l>Yet this I dare aſſert, when men have nam'd</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Iohnſon</hi> (the Nations Laureat,) the fam'd</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Beaumont,</hi> and <hi>Fletcher,</hi> he, that wo'not ſee</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Shirley,</hi> the fourth, muſt forfeit his beſt ey.</l>
            </lg>
            <closer>
               <signed>HALL.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="dramatis_personae">
            <pb facs="tcp:153343:4"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:153343:5"/>
            <head>Perſons.</head>
            <list>
               <item>
                  <hi>KIng of</hi> Navarre.</item>
               <item>Cardinal.</item>
               <item>Columbo, <hi>the Cardinals Nephew.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Alvarez.</item>
               <item>Hernando, <hi>a Colonel.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Alphonſo.</item>
               <item>Lords.</item>
               <item>Secretary <hi>to the Dutcheſs.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Colonels</item>
               <item>Antonelli, <hi>the Cardinals Servant.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Surgion.</item>
               <item>Guard.</item>
               <item>Attendants, &amp;c.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Dutcheſs</hi> Roſaura<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
               </item>
               <item>Valeria, <hi>Ladies.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Celinda, <hi>Ladies.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Placentia, <hi>a Lady that waits upon the Dutcheſs.</hi>
               </item>
            </list>
            <p>
               <hi>Scene Navarre.</hi>
            </p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="play">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:153343:5"/>
            <head>THE CARDINAL.</head>
            <div n="1" type="act">
               <head>ACT I.</head>
               <stage>Enter two Lords (at one door) Secretary (at the other.)</stage>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>1 <hi>Lord.</hi>
                  </speaker>
                  <l>
                     <seg rend="decorInit">W</seg>Ho is that?</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>2 <hi>Lo.</hi>
                  </speaker>
                  <l>The Dutcheſs Secretary.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>1 <hi>Lo.</hi>
                  </speaker>
                  <l>Signior.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Secr.</speaker>
                  <l>Your Lordſhips Servant.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>1 <hi>Lo.</hi>
                  </speaker>
                  <l>How does her Grace ſince ſhe left her mourning</l>
                  <l>For the young Duke <hi>Mendoza,</hi> whoſe timeleſs death</l>
                  <l>At Sea, left her a Virgin and a Widdow?</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>2 <hi>Lo.</hi>
                  </speaker>
                  <l>Shee's now inclining to a ſecond Bride,</l>
                  <l>When is the day of mighty mariage</l>
                  <l>To our great Cardinals Nephew, <hi>Don Columbo?</hi>
                  </l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Secr.</speaker>
                  <l>When they agree; they wo'not ſteal to Church,</l>
                  <l>I gueſs the ceremonies will be loud, and publick.</l>
                  <l>Your Lordſhips will excuſe me.</l>
               </sp>
               <stage>Exit.</stage>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>1 <hi>Lo.</hi>
                  </speaker>
                  <l>When they agree? alas poor Lady, ſhe</l>
                  <l>Dotes not upon <hi>Columbo,</hi> when ſhe thinks</l>
                  <l>Of the young Count <hi>D'Alvarez,</hi> divorc'd from her</l>
                  <l>By the Kings power.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>2 <hi>Lo.</hi>
                  </speaker>
                  <l>And Counſell of the Cardinal to advance</l>
                  <l>His Nephew to the Dutcheſs bed; 'tis not well.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>1 <hi>Lo.</hi>
                  </speaker>
                  <l>Take heed, the Cardinal holds intelligence</l>
                  <pb facs="tcp:153343:6"/>
                  <l>With every bird i'th' air.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>2 <hi>Lo.</hi>
                  </speaker>
                  <l>Death on his purple pride,</l>
                  <l>He governs all, and yet, <hi>Columbo</hi> is</l>
                  <l>A gallant Gentleman.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>1 <hi>Lo.</hi>
                  </speaker>
                  <l>The darling of the War, whom Victory</l>
                  <l>Hath often courted; a man of daring</l>
                  <l>And moſt exalted ſpirit, pride in him</l>
                  <l>Dwels like an ornament, where ſo much honour</l>
                  <l>Secures his praiſe.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>2 <hi>Lo.</hi>
                  </speaker>
                  <l>This is no argument</l>
                  <l>He ſhould uſurp, and wear <hi>Alvarez</hi> title</l>
                  <l>To the fair Dutcheſs, men of coarſer blood</l>
                  <l>Would not ſo tamely give this treaſure up.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>1 <hi>Lo.</hi>
                  </speaker>
                  <l>Although <hi>Columbos</hi> name is great in war,</l>
                  <l>Whoſe glorious art and practice is above</l>
                  <l>The greatneſs of <hi>Alvarez,</hi> yet he cannot</l>
                  <l>Want ſoul, in whom alone ſurvives the virtue</l>
                  <l>Of many noble Anceſtors, being the laſt</l>
                  <l>Of his great family</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>2 <hi>Lo.</hi>
                  </speaker>
                  <l>'Tis not ſafe, you'l ſay, to wraſtle with the King.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>1 <hi>Lo.</hi>
                  </speaker>
                  <l>More danger if the Cardinal be diſpleas'd,</l>
                  <l>Who ſits at helm of State; Count <hi>D' Alvarez</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>Is wiſer to obey the ſtream, than by</l>
                  <l>Inſiſting on his privilege to her love,</l>
                  <l>Put both their fate upon a ſtorm.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>2 <hi>Lo.</hi>
                  </speaker>
                  <l>If Wiſdom, not inborn Fear make him compoſe,</l>
                  <l>I like it; how does the Dutcheſs bear herſelf?</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>1 <hi>Lo.</hi>
                  </speaker>
                  <l>She moves by the rapture of another wheel</l>
                  <l>That muſt be obey'd, like ſome ſad paſſenger,</l>
                  <l>That looks upon the coaſt his wiſhes fly to,</l>
                  <l>But is tranſported by an adverſe wind, ſometimes</l>
                  <l>A churliſh Pilot.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>2 <hi>Lo.</hi>
                  </speaker>
                  <l>She has a ſweet and noble nature.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>1 <hi>Lo.</hi>
                  </speaker>
                  <l>That commend; <hi>Alvarez, Hymen</hi> cannot tie</l>
                  <l>A knot of two more equall hearts and blood.</l>
               </sp>
               <pb facs="tcp:153343:6"/>
               <stage>Enter Alphonſo.</stage>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>2 <hi>Lo.</hi>
                  </speaker>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Alphonſo?</hi>
                  </l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Alph.</speaker>
                  <l>My good Lord.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>1 <hi>Lo.</hi>
                  </speaker>
                  <l>What great affair</l>
                  <l>Hath brought you from the confines?</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Alp.</speaker>
                  <l>Such as will</l>
                  <l>Be worth your counſells, when the King hath read</l>
                  <l>My Letters from the Governour; the <hi>Arragonians,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>Violating their confederate oath and league,</l>
                  <l>Are now in arms; they have not yet marcht towards us,</l>
                  <l>But 'tis not ſafe to expect if we may timely</l>
                  <l>Prevent Invaſion</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>2 <hi>Lo.</hi>
                  </speaker>
                  <l>Dare they be ſo inſolent?</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>1 <hi>Lo.</hi>
                  </speaker>
                  <l>This ſtorm I did foreſee.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>2 <hi>Lo.</hi>
                  </speaker>
                  <l>What have they, but the ſweetneſs of the King,</l>
                  <l>To make a crime?</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>1 <hi>Lo.</hi>
                  </speaker>
                  <l>But how appears the Cardinal</l>
                  <l>At this news?</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Alp.</speaker>
                  <l>Not pale, although</l>
                  <l>He knows they have no cauſe to think him innocent,</l>
                  <l>As by whoſe Counſell they were once ſurpriz'd.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>1 <hi>Lo.</hi>
                  </speaker>
                  <l>There is more</l>
                  <l>Than all our preſent art can fathome in</l>
                  <l>This ſtory, and I fear I may conclude,</l>
                  <l>This flame has breath at home to cheriſh it;</l>
                  <l>Ther's treaſon in ſome hearts, whoſe faces are</l>
                  <l>Smooth to the State.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Alp.</speaker>
                  <l>My Lords, I take my leave.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>2 <hi>Lo.</hi>
                  </speaker>
                  <l>Your friends good Captain.</l>
               </sp>
               <stage>Excunt.</stage>
               <stage>Enter Dutcheſs, Valeria, Celinda.</stage>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Val.</speaker>
                  <l>Sweet Madam be leſs thoughtfull, this obedience</l>
                  <l>To paſſion, will deſtroy the nobleſt frame</l>
                  <l>Of beauty that this Kingdom ever boaſted.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Cel.</speaker>
                  <l>This ſadneſs might become your other habit,</l>
                  <l>And ceremonious black for him that died;</l>
                  <pb facs="tcp:153343:7"/>
                  <l>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>he times of ſorrow are expir'd, and all</l>
                  <l>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>he joys that wait upon the Court, your birth,</l>
                  <l>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>nd a new <hi>Hymen</hi> that is coming towards you,</l>
                  <l>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>nvite a change.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Dut.</speaker>
                  <l>Ladies, I thank you both,</l>
                  <l>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> pray excuſe a little melancholy</l>
                  <l>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>hat is behind, my year of mourning hath not</l>
                  <l>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>o cleer'd my account with ſorrow, but there may</l>
                  <l>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ome dark thoughts ſtay, with ſad reflections,</l>
                  <l>Upon my heart for him I loſt; even this</l>
                  <l>New dreſs, and ſmiling garment, meant to ſhew</l>
                  <l>A peace concluded twixt my grief and me,</l>
                  <l>Is but a ſad remembrance: but I reſolve</l>
                  <l>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>o entertain more pleaſing thoughts, and if</l>
                  <l>You wiſh me heartily to ſmile, you muſt</l>
                  <l>Not mention grief, not in advice to leave it;</l>
                  <l>Such Counſells open but afreſh the wounds</l>
                  <l>Ye would cloſe up; and keep alive the cauſe,</l>
                  <l>Whoſe bleeding you would cure; lets talk of ſomething</l>
                  <l>That may delight; you two are read in all</l>
                  <l>The Hiſtories of our Court; tell me <hi>Valeria,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>Who has thy vote for the moſt handſome man?</l>
                  <l>Thus I muſt counterfeit a peace, when all</l>
                  <l>Within me is at mutiny.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Val.</speaker>
                  <l>I have examin'd</l>
                  <l>All that are Candidates for the praiſe of Ladies.</l>
                  <l>But find—may I ſpeak boldly to your Grace?</l>
                  <l>And will you not return it in your mirth,</l>
                  <l>To make me bluſh?</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Dut.</speaker>
                  <l>No, no; ſpeak freely.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Val.</speaker>
                  <l>I wo'not rack your patience Madam, but</l>
                  <l>Were I a Princeſs, I ſhould think Count <hi>D' Alvarez</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>Had ſweetneſs to deſerve me from the world.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Dut.</speaker>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Alvarez!</hi> ſhee's a ſpy upon my heart.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Val.</speaker>
                  <l>Hee's young, and active, and compos'd moſt ſweet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Dut.</speaker>
                  <l>I have ſeen a face more tempting.</l>
               </sp>
               <pb facs="tcp:153343:7"/>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Val.</speaker>
                  <l>It had then</l>
                  <l>Too much of woman in't, his eys ſpeak movingly</l>
                  <l>Which may excuſe his voice, and lead away</l>
                  <l>All female pride his captive; His hair Black,</l>
                  <l>Which naturally falling into curl's—</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Dut.</speaker>
                  <l>Prethee no more, thou art in love with him.</l>
                  <l>The man in your eſteem <hi>Celinda</hi> now?</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Cel.</speaker>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Alvarez</hi> is (I muſt confeſs) a Gentleman</l>
                  <l>Of handſome compoſition, but with</l>
                  <l>His mind (the greater excellence) I think</l>
                  <l>Another may delight a Lady more,</l>
                  <l>If man be well conſidered, that's <hi>Columbo,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>Now, Madam, voted to be yours.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Dut.</speaker>
                  <l>My Torment!</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Val.</speaker>
                  <l>She affects him not.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Cel.</speaker>
                  <l>He has perſon, and a bravery beyond</l>
                  <l>All men that I obſerve.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Val.</speaker>
                  <l>He is a Souldier,</l>
                  <l>A rough-hewn man, and may ſhew well at diſtance;</l>
                  <l>His talk will fright a Lady; War, and grim-</l>
                  <l>Fac'd-honor are his Miſtriſſes; he raves</l>
                  <l>To hear a Lute; Love meant him not his Prieſt.</l>
                  <l>Again your pardon Madam; we may talk,</l>
                  <l>But you have art to chooſe and crown affection.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Dut.</speaker>
                  <l>What is it to be born above theſe Ladies</l>
                  <l>And want their freedom? they are not conſtrain'd,</l>
                  <l>Nor ſlav'd by their own greatneſs, or the Kings;</l>
                  <l>But let their free hearts look abroad, and chooſe</l>
                  <l>By their own eys to love; I muſt repair</l>
                  <l>My poor afflicted boſome, and aſſume</l>
                  <l>The privilege I was born with; which now prompts me</l>
                  <l>To tell the King he hath no power nor art</l>
                  <l>To ſteer a Lovers Soul.</l>
                  <stage>Enter Secretary.</stage>
                  <l>What ſays Count <hi>D'Alvares?</hi>
                  </l>
               </sp>
               <pb n="6" facs="tcp:153343:8"/>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Sec.</speaker>
                  <l>Madam hee'l attend you.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Dut.</speaker>
                  <l>Wait you as I directed, when he comes</l>
                  <l>Acquaint me privately.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Sec.</speaker>
                  <l>Madam, I have news,</l>
                  <l>'Tis now arriv'd the Court, we ſhall have wars.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Dut.</speaker>
                  <l>I find an Army here of killing thoughts.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Sec.</speaker>
                  <l>The King has choſen <hi>Don Columbo</hi> General,</l>
                  <l>Who is immediately to take his leave.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Dut.</speaker>
                  <l>What flood is let into my heart! how far</l>
                  <l>Is he to go?</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Sec.</speaker>
                  <l>To <hi>Arragon.</hi>
                  </l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Dut.</speaker>
                  <l>That's well</l>
                  <l>At firſt, he ſhould not want a pilgrimage</l>
                  <l>To the unknown World, if my thoughts might convey him.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Sec.</speaker>
                  <l>Tis not impoſſible he may go thither.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Dut.</speaker>
                  <l>How?</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Sec.</speaker>
                  <l>To the unknown other World, he goes to fight,</l>
                  <l>That's in his way, ſuch ſtories are in nature.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Dut.</speaker>
                  <l>Conceal this news.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Sec.</speaker>
                  <l>He wo'not be long abſent;</l>
                  <l>The affair will make him ſwift to kiſs your Graces hand.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Dut.</speaker>
                  <l>He cannot flie</l>
                  <l>With too much wing to take his leave; I muſt</l>
                  <l>Be admitted to your conference; ye have</l>
                  <l>Enlarg'd my ſpirits, they ſhall droop no more.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Cel.</speaker>
                  <l>We are happy, if we may advance one thought</l>
                  <l>To your Graces pleaſure.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Val.</speaker>
                  <l>Your ey before was in eclipſe, theſe ſmiles</l>
                  <l>Become you Madam.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Dut.</speaker>
                  <l>I have not skill to contain my ſelf.</l>
               </sp>
               <stage>Enter Placentia.</stage>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Pla.</speaker>
                  <l>The Cardinals Nephew, Madam, <hi>Don Columbo.</hi>
                  </l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Dut.</speaker>
                  <l>Already? attend him.</l>
               </sp>
               <stage>Ex. Plac.</stage>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Val.</speaker>
                  <l>Shall we take our leave?</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Dut.</speaker>
                  <l>He ſhall not know <hi>Valeria</hi> how you prais'd him.</l>
               </sp>
               <pb n="7" facs="tcp:153343:8"/>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Val.</speaker>
                  <l>If He did, Madam, I ſhould have the confidence</l>
                  <l>To tell him my free thoughts.</l>
               </sp>
               <stage>Enter Columbo.</stage>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Dut.</speaker>
                  <l>My Lord, while I'm in ſtudy to requite</l>
                  <l>The Favour you ha' done me, you increaſe</l>
                  <l>My debt to ſuch a ſum, ſtill by a new honouring</l>
                  <l>Your ſervant, I deſpair of my own freedom.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Col.</speaker>
                  <l>Madam, he kiſſeth your white hand, that muſt</l>
                  <l>Not ſurfet in this happineſs—and Ladies,</l>
                  <l>I take your ſmiles for my encouragement:</l>
                  <l>I have not long to practiſe theſe Court t<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>cticks.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Col.</speaker>
                  <l>He has been taught to kiſs.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Dut.</speaker>
                  <l>Ther's ſomething, Sir,</l>
                  <l>Upon your brow I did not read before.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Col.</speaker>
                  <l>Does the Character pleaſe you Madam?</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Dut.</speaker>
                  <l>More,</l>
                  <l>Becauſe it ſpeaks you cheerfull.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Col.</speaker>
                  <l>'Tis for ſuch</l>
                  <l>Acceſs of honour, as muſt make <hi>Columbo</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>Worth all your love; the King is pleas'd to think</l>
                  <l>Me fit to lead his Army.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Dut.</speaker>
                  <l>How, an Army?</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Col.</speaker>
                  <l>We muſt not uſe the Prieſt, till I bring home</l>
                  <l>Another triumph, that now ſtaies for me</l>
                  <l>To reap it in the purple field of glory.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Dut.</speaker>
                  <l>But do you mean to leave me, and expoſe</l>
                  <l>Your ſelf to the devouring war? no enemy</l>
                  <l>Should Divide us; the King is not ſo cruell.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Col.</speaker>
                  <l>The King is honourable, and this grace</l>
                  <l>More anſwers my ambition, than his gift</l>
                  <l>Of thee, and all thy beauty, which I can</l>
                  <l>Love, as becomes thy Souldier, and fight</l>
                  <stage>She weeps</stage>
                  <l>To come agen, a conqueror of thee;</l>
                  <l>Then I muſt chide this fondneſſe.</l>
               </sp>
               <stage>Enter Secretary.</stage>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Sec.</speaker>
                  <l>Madam, the King, and my Lord Cardinal.</l>
               </sp>
               <pb n="8" facs="tcp:153343:9"/>
               <stage>Enter King, Cardinall, and Lords.</stage>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>King:</speaker>
                  <l>Madam, I come to call a Servant from you,</l>
                  <l>And ſtrengthen his excuſe; the publick cauſe</l>
                  <l>Will plead for your conſent; at his return</l>
                  <l>Your mariage ſhall receive triumphant ceremonies;</l>
                  <l>Till then you muſt diſpence.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Card.</speaker>
                  <l>She appears ſad</l>
                  <l>To part with him, I like it fairly Nephew.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Val.</speaker>
                  <l>Is not the General a gallant man?</l>
                  <l>What Lady would deny him a ſmall courteſie?</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Cel.</speaker>
                  <l>Thou haſt converted me, and I begin</l>
                  <l>To wiſh it were no ſin.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Val.</speaker>
                  <l>Leave that to narrow Conſciences.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Cel.</speaker>
                  <l>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 span">
                        <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                     </gap> pleaſant.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Val.</speaker>
                  <l>But <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap> would pleaſe one better. Do ſuch men</l>
                  <l>Lie with their Pages?</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Cel.</speaker>
                  <l>Would'ſt thou make a ſhift?</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Val.</speaker>
                  <l>He is going to a bloody buſineſs;</l>
                  <l>'Tis pity he ſhould dye without ſome heir;</l>
                  <l>That Lady were hard-hearted now that would</l>
                  <l>Not help poſterity, for the meer good</l>
                  <l>O'th' King and Common-wealth.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Col.</speaker>
                  <l>Thou art wild, we may be obſerv'd.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Dut.</speaker>
                  <l>Your will muſt guide me, happineſs and conqueſt</l>
                  <l>Be ever waiting on his ſword.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Col.</speaker>
                  <l>Farewell.</l>
               </sp>
               <stage>Ex. K. Col. Card Lo.</stage>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Dut.</speaker>
                  <l>Pray give leave to examine a few thoughts;</l>
                  <l>Expect me in the Garden.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Ladies</speaker>
                  <l>We attend.</l>
               </sp>
               <stage>Ex. Ladies.</stage>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Dut.</speaker>
                  <l>This is above all expectation happy;</l>
                  <l>Forgive me virtue that I have diſſembled,</l>
                  <l>And witneſs with me, I have not a thought</l>
                  <l>To tempt or to berray him, but ſecure</l>
                  <l>The promiſe I firſt made to love and honour.</l>
               </sp>
               <pb n="9" facs="tcp:153343:9"/>
               <stage>Enter Secretary.</stage>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Sec.</speaker>
                  <l>The Count <hi>D' Alvarez</hi> Madam.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Dut.</speaker>
                  <l>Admit him.</l>
                  <l>And let none enterrupt us; how ſhall I</l>
                  <l>Behave my looks? the guilt of my neglect,</l>
                  <l>Which had no ſeal from hence, will call up blood</l>
                  <l>To write upon my cheeks the ſhame and ſtory</l>
                  <l>In ſome red Letter.</l>
               </sp>
               <stage>Enter D' Alvarez.</stage>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>D' Alv.</speaker>
                  <l>Madam, I preſent</l>
                  <l>One that was glad to obey your Grace, and come</l>
                  <l>To know what your commands are.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Dut.</speaker>
                  <l>Where I once</l>
                  <l>Did promiſe love, a love that had the Power</l>
                  <l>And office of a Prieſt to chain my heart</l>
                  <l>To yours, it were injuſtice to command.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>D' Alv.</speaker>
                  <l>But I can look upon you Madam, as</l>
                  <l>Becomes a ſervant, with as much humility,</l>
                  <l>(In tenderneſs of your honor and great fortune,)</l>
                  <l>Give up, when you call back your bounty, all that</l>
                  <l>Was mine, as I had pride to think them favours.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Dut.</speaker>
                  <l>Hath love taught thee no more aſſurance in</l>
                  <l>Our mutuall vows, thou canſt ſuſpect it poſſible,</l>
                  <l>I ſhould revoke a promiſe made to heaven</l>
                  <l>And thee ſo ſoon? this muſt ariſe from ſome</l>
                  <l>Diſtruſt of thy own Faith.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>D' Alv.</speaker>
                  <l>Your Graces pardon</l>
                  <l>To ſpeak with freedom, I am not ſo old</l>
                  <l>In cunning to betray, nor young in time</l>
                  <l>Not to ſee when, and where I am at loſs,</l>
                  <l>And how to bear my fortune, and my wounds,</l>
                  <l>Which if I look for health muſt ſtill bleed inward,</l>
                  <l>(A hard and deſperate condition;)</l>
                  <l>I am not ignorant your birth and greatneſs,</l>
                  <pb n="10" facs="tcp:153343:10"/>
                  <l>Have plac'd you to grow up with the Kings grace,</l>
                  <l>And jealouſie, which to remove, his power</l>
                  <l>Hath choſen a fit object for your beauty</l>
                  <l>To ſhine upon, <hi>Columbo</hi> his great fvavorite;</l>
                  <l>I am a man, on whom but late the King</l>
                  <l>Has pleas'd to caſt a beam, which was not meant</l>
                  <l>To make me proud, but wiſely to direct,</l>
                  <l>And light me to my ſafety. Oh, Dear Madam!</l>
                  <l>I will not call more witneſs of my love</l>
                  <l>(If you will let me ſtill give it that name)</l>
                  <l>Than this, that I dare make my ſelf a loſer,</l>
                  <l>And to your will give all my bleſſings up;</l>
                  <l>Preſerve your greatneſs and forget a triflle,</l>
                  <l>That ſhall at beſt when you have drawn me up,</l>
                  <l>But hang about you like a cloud, and dim</l>
                  <l>The glories you are born to.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Dut.</speaker>
                  <l>Miſery</l>
                  <l>Of birth and ſtate! that I could ſhift into</l>
                  <l>A meaner blood, or find ſome art to purge</l>
                  <l>That part which makes my veins unequall; yet</l>
                  <l>Thoſe nice diſtinctions have no place in us,</l>
                  <l>Ther's but a ſhadow difference, a title,</l>
                  <l>Thy ſtock partakes as much of noble ſap</l>
                  <l>As that which feeds the root of Kings, and he</l>
                  <l>That writes a Lord, hath all the eſſence of</l>
                  <l>Nobility.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>D' Alv.</speaker>
                  <l>'Tis not a name that makes</l>
                  <l>Our ſeparation, the Kings diſpleaſure</l>
                  <l>Hangs a portent to fright us, and the matter</l>
                  <l>That feeds this exhalation is the Cardinals</l>
                  <l>Plot to advance his Nephew; then <hi>Columbo,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>A man made up for ſome prodigious Act,</l>
                  <l>Is fit to be conſidered; in all three</l>
                  <l>There is no character you fix upon</l>
                  <l>But has a form of ruine to us both.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Dut.</speaker>
                  <l>Then you do look on theſe with fear.</l>
               </sp>
               <pb n="11" facs="tcp:153343:10"/>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>D' Alv.</speaker>
                  <l>With eys</l>
                  <l>That ſhould think tears a duty to lament</l>
                  <l>Your leaſt unkind fate; but my youth dares boldly</l>
                  <l>Meet all the tyranny o'th' ſtars, whoſe black</l>
                  <l>Malevolence but ſhoot my ſingle tragedy;</l>
                  <l>You are above the value of many worlds</l>
                  <l>Peopled with ſuch as I am.</l>
                  <l>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 span">
                        <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                     </gap> if <hi>Columbo</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>Engag'd to war, in his hot thirſt of honor,</l>
                  <l>Find out the Way to death?</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>D' Alv.</speaker>
                  <l>Tis poſſible.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Dut.</speaker>
                  <l>Or ſay, no matter by what art or mo tive</l>
                  <l>He gives his title up, and leave me to</l>
                  <l>My own Election?</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>D' Alv.</speaker>
                  <l>If I then be happy</l>
                  <l>To have a name within your thought, there can</l>
                  <l>Be nothing left to crown me with New bleſſing;</l>
                  <l>But I dream thus of heaven, and wake to find</l>
                  <l>My amorous ſoul a mockery; when the Prieſt</l>
                  <l>Shall tie you to another, and the joys</l>
                  <l>Of mariage leave no thought at leaſure to</l>
                  <l>Look ba<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>k upon <hi>Alvarez,</hi> that muſt wither</l>
                  <l>For loſs of you, yet then I cannot loſe</l>
                  <l>So much of what I was, once in your favour,</l>
                  <l>But in a ſigh pray ſtill you may live happy.</l>
               </sp>
               <stage>Exit.</stage>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Dut.</speaker>
                  <l>My Heart is in a miſt, ſome good ſtar ſmile</l>
                  <l>Upon my reſolution, and direct</l>
                  <l>Two lovers in their chaſt embrace to meet;</l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Columbo's</hi> bed contains my winding ſheet.</l>
               </sp>
               <stage>Exit.</stage>
            </div>
            <div n="2" type="act">
               <pb n="12" facs="tcp:153343:11"/>
               <head>ACT II.</head>
               <stage>Enter General Columbo, Hernando, two Colonels, Alphonſo, two Captains, and other Officers, As at a Councell of War.</stage>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Columbo.</speaker>
                  <l>I See no face in all this Councell, that</l>
                  <l>Hath one pale fear upon't though we arriv'd not</l>
                  <l>So timely to ſecure the Town, which gives</l>
                  <l>Our enemy ſuch triumph.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>1 <hi>Colo.</hi>
                  </speaker>
                  <l>'Twas betraid</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Alp.</speaker>
                  <l>The wealth of that one City</l>
                  <l>Will make the enemy glorious.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>1 <hi>Colo.</hi>
                  </speaker>
                  <l>They dare not plunder it.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Alp.</speaker>
                  <l>They give fair quarter yet,</l>
                  <l>They only ſeal up mens Eſtates, and keep</l>
                  <l>Poſſeſſion for the Cities uſe, they take up</l>
                  <l>Now wares without ſecurity, and he</l>
                  <l>Whoſe ſingle credit will not paſs, puts in</l>
                  <l>Two leane comrades, upon whoſe bonds tis not</l>
                  <l>Religion to deny 'em.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Colu.</speaker>
                  <l>To repair this</l>
                  <l>With honour Gentlemen?</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Her.</speaker>
                  <l>My opinion is</l>
                  <l>To expect a while.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Colu.</speaker>
                  <l>Your reaſon?</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Her.</speaker>
                  <l>Till their own</l>
                  <l>Surfet betray 'em, for their Souldier</l>
                  <l>Bred up with coarſe and common bread, will ſhew</l>
                  <l>Such appetites on the rich cates they find,</l>
                  <l>They will ſpare our ſwords a victory, when their own</l>
                  <l>Riot and Luxury deſtroys 'em.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>1 <hi>Colo.</hi>
                  </speaker>
                  <l>That</l>
                  <pb facs="tcp:153343:11"/>
                  <l>Will ſhew our patience too like a fear.</l>
                  <l>With favour of his excellence I think,</l>
                  <l>The ſpoil of Cities takes not off the courage,</l>
                  <l>But doubles it on Souldiers; beſides,</l>
                  <l>While we have tameneſs to expect, the noiſe</l>
                  <l>Of their ſucceſs and plenty will encreaſe</l>
                  <l>Their Army.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Her.</speaker>
                  <l>'Tis conſiderable, we do not</l>
                  <l>Exceed in Foot or Horſe, our Muſter not</l>
                  <l>'Bove ſixteen thouſand both; and the Infantry</l>
                  <l>Raw, and not diſciplin'd to act.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Alp.</speaker>
                  <l>Their hearts,</l>
                  <l>But with a brave thought of their Countries honour,</l>
                  <l>Will teach 'em how to fight, had they not ſeen</l>
                  <l>A Sword; but we decline our own too much,</l>
                  <l>The men are forward in their arms, and take</l>
                  <l>The uſe with Avarice of Fame.</l>
               </sp>
               <stage>They riſe and talk privately.</stage>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Colu.</speaker>
                  <l>Colonell.</l>
                  <l>I do ſuſpect you are a coward.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Her.</speaker>
                  <l>Sir.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Colu.</speaker>
                  <l>Or elſe a traytor, take your choice, no more,</l>
                  <l>I calld you to a Councell Sir, of war,</l>
                  <l>Yet keep your place.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Her.</speaker>
                  <l>I have worn other names.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Colu.</speaker>
                  <l>Deſerve 'em, ſuch</l>
                  <l>Another were enough to unſoul an Army;</l>
                  <l>Ignobly talk of patience till they drink</l>
                  <l>And reel to death? we came to fight and force 'em</l>
                  <l>To mend their pace; thou haſt no honour in thee,</l>
                  <l>Not enough noble blood to make a bluſh</l>
                  <l>For thy tame Eloquence.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Her.</speaker>
                  <l>My Lord, I know</l>
                  <l>My duty to a Generall, yet there are</l>
                  <l>Some that have known me here; Sir, I deſire</l>
                  <l>To quit my regiment.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Colu.</speaker>
                  <l>You ſhall have licence. Ink and paper—</l>
               </sp>
               <pb facs="tcp:153343:12"/>
               <stage>Enter with Paper and Standiſh.</stage>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>1 <hi>Colo.</hi>
                  </speaker>
                  <l>The General's diſpleas'd.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>2 <hi>Colo.</hi>
                  </speaker>
                  <l>How is't <hi>Hernando?</hi>
                  </l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Her.</speaker>
                  <l>The Generall has found out employment for me,</l>
                  <l>He is writing Letters back.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Al Cap.</speaker>
                  <l>To his Miſtreſs.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Her.</speaker>
                  <l>Pray do not trouble me, yet prethee ſpeak,</l>
                  <l>And flatter not thy friend, doſt think I dare</l>
                  <l>Not draw my ſword, and uſe it, when cauſe</l>
                  <l>With honour calls to action?</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Al. Colo.</speaker>
                  <l>With the moſt valiant man alive.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Her.</speaker>
                  <l>You'l do me ſome diſpleaſure in your loves,</l>
                  <l>Pray to your places.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Colu.</speaker>
                  <l>So,</l>
                  <l>Bear thoſe Letters to the King,</l>
                  <l>It ſpeaks my reſolution before</l>
                  <l>Another Sun decline to charge the enemy.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Her.</speaker>
                  <l>A pretty Court way</l>
                  <l>Of di miſſing an Officer, I obey; ſucceſs</l>
                  <l>Attend your Counſells.</l>
               </sp>
               <stage>Exit.</stage>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Colu.</speaker>
                  <l>If here be any dare not look on danger,</l>
                  <l>And meet it like a man with ſcorn of death,</l>
                  <l>I beg his abſence, and a cowards fear</l>
                  <l>Conſume him to a ghoſt.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>1 <hi>Colo.</hi>
                  </speaker>
                  <l>None ſuch here.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Colu.</speaker>
                  <l>Or if in all your Regiments you find</l>
                  <l>One man that does not ask to bleed with honour,</l>
                  <l>Give him a double pay to leave the Army;</l>
                  <l>Ther's ſervice to be done, will call the ſpirits</l>
                  <l>And aid of Men.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>1 <hi>Colo.</hi>
                  </speaker>
                  <l>You give us all new flame.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Colu.</speaker>
                  <l>I am confirm'd, and you muſt loſe no time;</l>
                  <l>The Souldier that was took laſt night, to me</l>
                  <l>Diſcover'd their whole ſtrength, and that we have</l>
                  <l>A party in the town; the River that</l>
                  <pb facs="tcp:153343:12"/>
                  <l>Opens the City to the Weſt unguarded;</l>
                  <l>We muſt this night uſe art and reſolutions,</l>
                  <l>We cannot fall ingloriouſly.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>1 <hi>Capt.</hi>
                  </speaker>
                  <l>That voice is every mans.</l>
               </sp>
               <stage>Enter Souldier, and Secretary with a Letter.</stage>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Colu.</speaker>
                  <l>What now?</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Soul.</speaker>
                  <l>Letters.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Colu.</speaker>
                  <l>Whence?</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Soul.</speaker>
                  <l>From the Dutcheſs.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Colu.</speaker>
                  <l>They are welcome;</l>
                  <l>Meet at my Tent again this evening; yet ſtay,</l>
                  <l>Some Wine—The Dutcheſs health—</l>
                  <l>See it go round.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Sec.</speaker>
                  <l>It wo'not pleaſe his Excellence.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>1 <hi>Colo.</hi>
                  </speaker>
                  <l>The Dutcheſs health.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>2 <hi>Cap.</hi>
                  </speaker>
                  <l>To me! more wine.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Sec.</speaker>
                  <l>The Clouds are gathering, and his eys ſhoot fire;</l>
                  <l>Obſerve what thunder follows.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>2 <hi>Cap.</hi>
                  </speaker>
                  <l>The Generall has but ill news, I ſuſpect</l>
                  <l>The Dutcheſs ſick, or elſe the King.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>1 <hi>Cap.</hi>
                  </speaker>
                  <l>May be the Cardinal.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>2 <hi>Cap.</hi>
                  </speaker>
                  <l>His ſoul has long been look'd for.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Colu.</speaker>
                  <l>She dares not be ſo infolent! it is</l>
                  <l>The Dutcheſs hand; how am I ſhrunk in Fame</l>
                  <l>TO be thus plaid withall? ſhe writes, and counſels,</l>
                  <l>Under my hand to ſend her back a free</l>
                  <l>Reſigne of all my intereſt to her perſon,</l>
                  <l>Promiſe, or love; that ther's no other way</l>
                  <l>With ſafety of my honour to reviſit her.</l>
                  <l>The woman is poſſeſt with ſome bold Devil,</l>
                  <l>And wants an exorciſm; or I am grown</l>
                  <l>A cheap, dull, phlegmatick fool, a Poſt that's carv'd</l>
                  <l>I'th' common ſtreet, and holding out my forehead</l>
                  <l>To every ſcurrill wit to pin diſgrace</l>
                  <l>And libells on't; did you bring this to me Sir?</l>
                  <pb facs="tcp:153343:13"/>
                  <l>My thanks ſhall warm your heart.</l>
               </sp>
               <stage>Draws a Pistoll.</stage>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Sec.</speaker>
                  <l>Hold, hold, my Lord.</l>
                  <l>I know not what provokes this tempeſt, but</l>
                  <l>Her Grace ne't ſhew'd more freedom from a ſtorm</l>
                  <l>When I receiv'd this paper; if you have</l>
                  <l>A will to do an execution,</l>
                  <l>Your looks without that engin, Sir, may ſerve.</l>
                  <l>I did not like the employment.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Colu.</speaker>
                  <l>Ha, had ſhe</l>
                  <l>No ſymptome in her eye, or face, of anger</l>
                  <l>When ſhe gave this in charge?</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Sec.</speaker>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Serene,</hi> as I</l>
                  <l>Have ſeen <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>e morning riſe upon the ſpring,</l>
                  <l>No trouble in her breath, but ſuch a wind</l>
                  <l>As came to kiſs and fan the ſmiling flowers.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Colu.</speaker>
                  <l>No Poetry.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Sec.</speaker>
                  <l>By all the truth in proſe,</l>
                  <l>By honeſty, and your own honour Sir,</l>
                  <l>I never ſaw her look more calm, and gentle.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Colu.</speaker>
                  <l>I am too paſſionate, you muſt forgive me;</l>
                  <l>I have found it out the Dutcheſs loves me dearly,</l>
                  <l>She expreſt a trouble in her when I took</l>
                  <l>My leave, and chid me with a fullen ey;</l>
                  <l>'Tis a device to haſten my return;</l>
                  <l>Love has a thouſand arts; I'l anſwer it,</l>
                  <l>Beyond her expectation, and put</l>
                  <l>Her ſoul to a noble teſt; your patience Gentlemen;</l>
                  <l>The Kings health will deſerve a ſacrifice of Wine.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Sec.</speaker>
                  <l>I am glad to ſee this change, and thank my wit</l>
                  <l>For my redemption.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>1 <hi>Col.</hi>
                  </speaker>
                  <l>Sir, The Souldiers curſe on him lo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>es not our Maſter.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>2 <hi>Col.</hi>
                  </speaker>
                  <l>And they curſe loud enough to be heard.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>2 <hi>Cap.</hi>
                  </speaker>
                  <l>Their curſe has the nature of Gunpowder.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Sec.</speaker>
                  <l>They do not pray with half the noiſe.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>1 <hi>Col</hi>
                  </speaker>
                  <l>Our Generall is not well mixt,</l>
                  <l>He hes too great a portion of fire.</l>
               </sp>
               <pb n="17" facs="tcp:153343:13"/>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>2 <hi>Col.</hi>
                  </speaker>
                  <l>His Miſtris cool him, her complexion</l>
                  <l>Carries ſome phlegm, when they two meet in bed?</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>2 <hi>Cap.</hi>
                  </speaker>
                  <l>A third may follow.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>1 <hi>Cap.</hi>
                  </speaker>
                  <l>'Tis much pity.</l>
                  <l>The young Duke liv'd not to take the virgin off.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>1 <hi>Col.</hi>
                  </speaker>
                  <l>'T was the Kings act to match two Rabbet ſuck<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>2 <hi>Col.</hi>
                  </speaker>
                  <l>A common trick of State,</l>
                  <l>The little great man marries, travells then</l>
                  <l>Till both grow up; and dies when he ſhould do</l>
                  <l>The feat; theſe things are ſtill unlucky</l>
                  <l>On the male ſide.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Colu.</speaker>
                  <l>This to the Dutcheſs fair hand.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Sec.</speaker>
                  <l>She will think</l>
                  <l>Time hath no wing, till I return.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Colu.</speaker>
                  <l>Gentlemen,</l>
                  <l>Now each man to his quarter, and encourage</l>
                  <l>The Souldier; I ſhall take a pride to know</l>
                  <l>Your diligence, when I viſit all your</l>
                  <l>Severall commands.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Omnes.</speaker>
                  <l>We ſhall expect,</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>2 <hi>Col.</hi>
                  </speaker>
                  <l>And move by your directions.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Colu.</speaker>
                  <l>Y'are all noble.</l>
               </sp>
               <stage>Exeunt.</stage>
               <stage>Enter Cardinal, Dutcheſs, Placentia.</stage>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Card.</speaker>
                  <l>I ſhall perform a viſit dayly, Madam,</l>
                  <l>In th' abſence of my Nephew, and be happy</l>
                  <l>If you accept my care.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Dut.</speaker>
                  <l>You have honour'd me,</l>
                  <l>And if your entertainment have not been</l>
                  <l>Worthy your Graces perſon, 'tis becauſe</l>
                  <l>Nothing can reach it in my power; but where</l>
                  <l>There is no want of zeal, other defect</l>
                  <l>Is only a fault to exerciſe your mercy.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Card.</speaker>
                  <l>You are bounteous in all; I take my leave;</l>
                  <l>My fair Neece, ſhortly, when <hi>Columbo</hi> has</l>
                  <l>Purchas'd more honours to prefer his name,</l>
                  <pb facs="tcp:153343:14"/>
                  <l>And value to your noble thoughts; mean time</l>
                  <l>Be confident you have a friend, whoſe Office,</l>
                  <l>And favour with the King, ſhall be effectuall</l>
                  <l>To ſerve your Grace.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Dut.</speaker>
                  <l>Your own good deeds reward you,</l>
                  <l>Till mine riſe equall to deſerve their benefit.</l>
                  <stage>Exit Cardinal.</stage>
                  <stage>Exit Placen.</stage>
                  <l>Leave me a while.</l>
                  <l>Do not I walk upon the teeth of ſerpents;</l>
                  <l>And, as I had a charm againſt their poyſon,</l>
                  <l>Play with their ſtings, the Cardinal is ſubtle?</l>
                  <l>Whom tis not wiſdom to incenſe, till I</l>
                  <l>Hear to what deſtinie <hi>Columbo</hi> leaves me;</l>
                  <l>May be the greatneſs of his ſoul will ſcorn</l>
                  <l>To own what comes with murmur, If he can</l>
                  <l>Interpret me ſo happily; art come?</l>
               </sp>
               <stage>Enter Secretary with a Letter.</stage>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Sec.</speaker>
                  <l>His Excellence ſalutes your Grace.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Dut:</speaker>
                  <l>Thou haſt</l>
                  <l>A malencholy brow; how did he take my Letter?</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Sec.</speaker>
                  <l>As he would take a blow, with ſo much ſenſe</l>
                  <l>Of anger, his whole ſoul boild in his face,</l>
                  <l>And ſuch prodigious flame in both his eys</l>
                  <l>As they'd been th' only ſeat of fire; and at</l>
                  <l>Each look a <hi>Salamander</hi> leaping forth,</l>
                  <l>Not able to endure the Furnace.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Dut.</speaker>
                  <l>Ha! thou doſt</l>
                  <l>Deſcribe him with ſome horror.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Sec.</speaker>
                  <l>Soon as he</l>
                  <l>Had read again, and underſtood your meaning,</l>
                  <l>His rage had ſhot me with a piſtoll, had not</l>
                  <l>I us'd ſome ſoft, and penitentiall language,</l>
                  <l>To charm the Bullet.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Dut.</speaker>
                  <l>Wait at ſome more diſtance;</l>
                  <l>My ſoul doth bath it felf in a cold dew;</l>
                  <pb n="19" facs="tcp:153343:14"/>
                  <l>I magin, I am opening of a Tomb,</l>
                  <l>Thus I throw off the Marble to diſcover,</l>
                  <l>What antick poſture death preſents in this</l>
                  <l>Pale monument to fright me—</l>
                  <stage>Reads.</stage>
                  <l>Ha? my heart that call'd my blood and ſpirits, to</l>
                  <l>Defend it from the invaſion of my fears,</l>
                  <l>Muſt keep a guard about it ſtill, leſt this</l>
                  <l>Strange and too mighty joy cruſh it to nothing.</l>
               </sp>
               <stage>Antonio.</stage>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Sec.</speaker>
                  <l>Madam.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Dut.</speaker>
                  <l>Bid my Steward give thee</l>
                  <l>Two thouſand Ducates; art ſure I am awake?</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Sec.</speaker>
                  <l>I ſhall be able to reſolve you, Madam,</l>
                  <l>When he has paid them oney.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Dut.</speaker>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Columbo</hi> now is noble.</l>
               </sp>
               <stage>Exit. Dut.</stage>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Sec.</speaker>
                  <l>This is better than I expected, if my Lady be</l>
                  <l>Not mad, and live to juſtifie her bounty.</l>
               </sp>
               <stage>Exit.</stage>
               <stage>Enter King, Alvarez, Hernando, Lords.</stage>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>King.</speaker>
                  <l>The War is left to him. but we muſt have</l>
                  <l>You reconcil'd, if that be all your difference.</l>
                  <l>His rage flows like a torrent, when he meets</l>
                  <l>With oppoſition, leave to wraſtle with him,</l>
                  <l>And his hot blood retreats into a calm,</l>
                  <l>And then he chides his paſſion; you ſhall back</l>
                  <l>With letters from us.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Her.</speaker>
                  <l>Your Commands, are not</l>
                  <l>To be diſputed.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Kin.</speaker>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Alvarez.</hi>
                  </l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>1 <hi>Lo.</hi>
                  </speaker>
                  <l>Loſe not</l>
                  <l>Your ſelf by cool ſubmiſſion, he will find</l>
                  <l>His error, and the want of ſuch a Souldier.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>2 <hi>Lo.</hi>
                  </speaker>
                  <l>Have you ſeen the Cardinal?</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Her.</speaker>
                  <l>Not yet.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>1 <hi>Lo.</hi>
                  </speaker>
                  <l>He wants no plot—</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Her.</speaker>
                  <l>The King I muſt obey;</l>
                  <pb n="20" facs="tcp:153343:15"/>
                  <l>But let the purple Gownman place his engins</l>
                  <l>I'th' dark that wounds me.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>2 <hi>Lo.</hi>
                  </speaker>
                  <l>Be aſſur'd</l>
                  <l>Of what we can to friend you, and the King</l>
                  <l>Cannot forget your ſervice.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Her.</speaker>
                  <l>I am ſorry</l>
                  <l>For that poor Gentleman.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Alvar.</speaker>
                  <l>I muſt conſeſs, Sir,</l>
                  <l>The Dutcheſs has been pleas'd to think me worthy</l>
                  <l>Her favours, and in that degree of honour,</l>
                  <l>That has oblig'd my life to make the beſt</l>
                  <l>Return of ſervice, which is not, with bold</l>
                  <l>Affiance in her love, to interpoſe</l>
                  <l>Againſt her happineſs, and your election;</l>
                  <l>I love ſo much her honour, I have quitted</l>
                  <l>All my deſires, yet would not ſhrink to bleed</l>
                  <l>Out my warm ſtock of life, ſo the laſt drop</l>
                  <l>Might benefit her wiſhes.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Ki.</speaker>
                  <l>I ſhall find</l>
                  <l>A compenſation for this act, <hi>Alvarez,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>I hath much pleaſed us.</l>
               </sp>
               <stage>Enter Dutcheſs with a Letter, Gentleman-Vſher.</stage>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Dut.</speaker>
                  <l>Sir, you are the King,</l>
                  <l>And in that ſacred title it were ſin</l>
                  <l>To doubt a juſtice, all that does concern</l>
                  <l>My eſſence in this world, and a great part</l>
                  <l>Of the other bliſs, lives in you breath.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Ki.</speaker>
                  <l>What intends the Dutcheſs?</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Dut.</speaker>
                  <l>That will inſtruct you, Sir, <hi>Columbo</hi> has</l>
                  <l>Upon ſome better choice, or diſcontent,</l>
                  <l>Set my poor ſoul at freedom.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Ki.</speaker>
                  <l>Tis his character—</l>
                  <stage>Reads,</stage>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Madam, I caſily diſcharge all my pretenſions</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>To your love, and perſon, I leave you to your</hi>
                  </l>
                  <pb n="21" facs="tcp:153343:15"/>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Own choice, and in what you have obliged</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Your ſelf to me, reſume a power to cancell</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>If you pleaſe.</hi>
                  </l>
                  <stage>Columbo.</stage>
                  <l>This is ſtrange.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Dut.</speaker>
                  <l>Now do an act to make</l>
                  <l>Your Chronicle belov'd and read for ever.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Ki.</speaker>
                  <l>Expreſs your ſelf.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Dut.</speaker>
                  <l>Since by Divine infuſion,</l>
                  <l>For tis no art could force the Generall to</l>
                  <l>This Change, ſecond this juſtice and beſtow</l>
                  <l>The heart you would have given from me, by</l>
                  <l>Your ſtrict commands to love <hi>Colnmbo,</hi> where</l>
                  <l>'Twas meant by heaven, and let your breath return</l>
                  <l>Whom you divorc'd, <hi>Alvarez,</hi> mine.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Lords.</speaker>
                  <l>This is but juſtice, Sir.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Ki.</speaker>
                  <l>It was decreed above,</l>
                  <l>And ſince <hi>Columbo</hi> has releas'd his intereſt</l>
                  <l>Which we had wrought him, not without ſome force</l>
                  <l>Upon your will I give you your own wiſhes,</l>
                  <l>Receive your own <hi>Alvarez,</hi> when you pleaſe</l>
                  <l>To celebrate your Nuptial, I invite</l>
                  <l>My ſelf your gueſt.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Dut.</speaker>
                  <l>Eternall bleſſings Crown you.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Omnes.</speaker>
                  <l>And every joy your Mariage</l>
               </sp>
               <stage>Exit King, who meets the Cardinal, they confer.</stage>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Alvar.</speaker>
                  <l>I know not whether I ſhall wonder moſt</l>
                  <l>Or joy to meet this happineſs.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Dut.</speaker>
                  <l>Now the King hath planted us</l>
                  <l>Methinks we grow already, and twiſt our loving ſouls</l>
                  <l>Above the wrath of thunder to divide us.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Alv.</speaker>
                  <l>Ha? The Cardinal</l>
                  <l>Has met the King, I do not like this conference;</l>
                  <l>He looks with anger this way, I expect</l>
                  <l>A tempeſt.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Dut.</speaker>
                  <l>Take no notice of his preſence,</l>
                  <l>Leave me to meet, and anſwer it, if the King</l>
                  <pb n="22" facs="tcp:153343:16"/>
                  <l>Be firm in's Royall word, I fear no lightning;</l>
                  <l>Expect me in the Garden.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Alv.</speaker>
                  <l>I obey,</l>
                  <l>But fear a ſhipwrack on the coaſt.</l>
               </sp>
               <stage>Exit.</stage>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Card.</speaker>
                  <l>Madam.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Dut.</speaker>
                  <l>My Lord.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Car.</speaker>
                  <l>The King ſpeaks of a Letter that has brought</l>
                  <l>A riddle in't.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Dut.</speaker>
                  <l>Tis eaſy to interpret.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Car.</speaker>
                  <l>From my Nephew? may I deſerve the favour?</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Dut.</speaker>
                  <l>He looks as though his eys would fire the paper.</l>
                  <l>They are a pair of Burning glaſſes, and</l>
                  <l>His envious blood doth give 'em flame.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Car.</speaker>
                  <l>What lethargy could thus unſpirit him?</l>
                  <l>I am all wonder; do not believe Madam,</l>
                  <l>But that <hi>Columbo's</hi> love is yet more Sacred,</l>
                  <l>To honour, and your ſelf, than thus to forfeit</l>
                  <l>What I have heard him call the glorious wreath</l>
                  <l>To all his merits, given him by the King,</l>
                  <l>From whom he took you with more pride than ever</l>
                  <l>He came from victory; his kiſſes hang</l>
                  <l>Yet panting on your lips, and he but now</l>
                  <l>Exchang'd religious farewell to return,</l>
                  <l>But with more triumph to be yours.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Dut.</speaker>
                  <l>My Lord,</l>
                  <l>You do believe your Nephews hand was not</l>
                  <l>Surpriz'd or ſtrain'd to this?</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Car.</speaker>
                  <l>Strange arts and windings in the world, moſt dark,</l>
                  <l>And ſubtill progreſſes; who brought this Letter?</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Dut.</speaker>
                  <l>I enquir'd not his name, I thought it not</l>
                  <l>Conſiderable to take ſuch narrow knowledge.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Car.</speaker>
                  <l>Deſert, and honour urg'd it here, nor can</l>
                  <l>I blame you to be angry, yet his perſon</l>
                  <l>Oblig'd, you ſhould have given a nobler pauſe,</l>
                  <l>Before you made your faith and change ſo violent</l>
                  <l>From his known worth, into the arms of one,</l>
                  <pb n="23" facs="tcp:153343:16"/>
                  <l>How ever faſhioned to your amorous wiſh,</l>
                  <l>Not equall to his cheapeſt fame, with all</l>
                  <l>The gloſs of blood and merit.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Dut.</speaker>
                  <l>This compariſon,</l>
                  <l>My good Lord Cardinal, I cannot think,</l>
                  <l>Flows from an even juſtice, it betrayes</l>
                  <l>You partiall where your blood runs.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Car.</speaker>
                  <l>I fear Madam,</l>
                  <l>Your own takes two much licence, and will ſoon,</l>
                  <l>Fall to the cenſure of unruly tongues;</l>
                  <l>Becauſe <hi>Alvarez</hi> has a ſofter cheek,</l>
                  <l>Can like a woman trim his want on hair,</l>
                  <l>Spend half a day with looking in the glaſs</l>
                  <l>To find a poſture to preſent himſelf,</l>
                  <l>And bring more effeminacy than man,</l>
                  <l>Or honour to your bed; muſt he ſupplant him?</l>
                  <l>Take heed, the common murmur when it catches</l>
                  <l>The ſent of a loſt Fame—</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Dut.</speaker>
                  <l>My Fame Lord Cardinal?</l>
                  <l>It ſtands upon an innocence as clear</l>
                  <l>As the devotions you pay to heaven,</l>
                  <l>I ſhall not urge my Lord your ſoft indulgence</l>
                  <l>At my next ſhrift.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Car.</speaker>
                  <l>You are a fine Court Lady.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Dut.</speaker>
                  <l>And you ſhould be a reverend Churchman.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Car.</speaker>
                  <l>One, that if you have not thrown off modeſty.</l>
                  <l>Would counſell you to leave <hi>Alvarez.</hi>
                  </l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Dut.</speaker>
                  <l>Cauſe you dare do worſe</l>
                  <l>Than Mariage, muſt not I be admitted what</l>
                  <l>The Church and Law allowes me?</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Car.</speaker>
                  <l>Inſolent? then you dare marry him?</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Dut.</speaker>
                  <l>Dare? Let your contracted flame and malice, with</l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Columbo's</hi> rage higher than that, meet us</l>
                  <l>When we approach the holy place, claſp'd hand</l>
                  <l>In hand, wee'l break through all your force and ſix</l>
                  <l>Our ſacred vows together there.</l>
               </sp>
               <pb n="24" facs="tcp:153343:17"/>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Car.</speaker>
                  <l>I knew</l>
                  <l>When with as chaſt a brow you promis'd fair</l>
                  <l>To another; you are no diſſembling Lady.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Dut.</speaker>
                  <l>Would all your actions had no falſer lights</l>
                  <l>About 'em.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Car.</speaker>
                  <l>Ha?</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Dut.</speaker>
                  <l>The people would not talk and curſe ſo loud.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Car.</speaker>
                  <l>I'l have you chid into a bluſh for this.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Dut.</speaker>
                  <l>Begin at home great man, ther's cauſe enough,</l>
                  <l>You turn the wrong end of the perſpective</l>
                  <l>Upon your crimes, to drive them to a far,</l>
                  <l>And leſſer ſight, but let your eys look right</l>
                  <l>What giants would your pride and ſurfeit ſeem?</l>
                  <l>How groſs your avarice, eating up whole families?</l>
                  <l>How vaſt are your corruptions and abuſe</l>
                  <l>Of the Kings ear? at which you hang a pendent,</l>
                  <l>Not to adorn, but ulcerate, while the honeſt</l>
                  <l>Nobility, like pictures in the Arras,</l>
                  <l>Serve only for Court-Ornament; if they ſpeak,</l>
                  <l>'Tis when you ſet their tongues, which you wind up,</l>
                  <l>Like clocks to ſtrike at the juſt hour you pleaſe;</l>
                  <l>Leave, leave, my Lord, theſe uſurpations,</l>
                  <l>And be what you were meant a man to cure,</l>
                  <l>Not let in Agues to Religion;</l>
                  <l>Look on the Churches wounds.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Car.</speaker>
                  <l>You dare preſume</l>
                  <l>In your rude ſpleen to me, to abuſe the Church?</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Dut.</speaker>
                  <l>Alas you give falſe aym, my Lord, 'tis your</l>
                  <l>Ambition and Scarlet Sins that tob</l>
                  <l>Her Altar of the glory, and leave wounds</l>
                  <l>Upon her brow; which fetches grief, and paleneſs,</l>
                  <l>Into her cheeks; Making her troubled boſome</l>
                  <l>Pant with her groanes, and ſhroud her holy bluſhes</l>
                  <l>Within your reverend purples.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Car.</speaker>
                  <l>Will you now take breath?</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Dut.</speaker>
                  <l>In hope, my Lord, you will behold your ſelf</l>
                  <pb n="25" facs="tcp:153343:17"/>
                  <l>In a true glaſs, and ſee thoſe injuſt acts</l>
                  <l>That ſo deform you, and by timely cure,</l>
                  <l>Prevent a ſhame before the ſhort haird men</l>
                  <l>Do croud and call for juſtice. I take leave.</l>
               </sp>
               <stage>Exit.</stage>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Car.</speaker>
                  <l>This woman has a ſpirit, that may riſe</l>
                  <l>To tame the Devils, ther's no dealing with</l>
                  <l>Her angry tongue, 'tis action and revenge</l>
                  <l>Muſt calm her fury; were <hi>Columbo</hi> here,</l>
                  <l>I could reſolve, but Letters ſhall be ſent</l>
                  <l>To th'Army which may wake him into ſenſe</l>
                  <l>Of his raſh folly, or direct his ſpirit</l>
                  <l>Some way to ſnatch his honour from this flame,</l>
                  <l>All great men know, <hi>The ſoul of life is ſame.</hi>
                  </l>
               </sp>
               <stage>Exit.</stage>
            </div>
            <div n="3" type="act">
               <head>ACT III.</head>
               <stage>Enter Valeria, Celinda.</stage>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Valeria.</speaker>
                  <l>I Did not think <hi>Celinda</hi> when I prais'd</l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Alvarez</hi> to the Dutcheſs, that things thus</l>
                  <l>Would come about, what does your Ladiſhip</l>
                  <l>Think of <hi>Columbo</hi> now? it ſtaggers all</l>
                  <l>The Court, he ſhould forſake his Miſtreſs, I</l>
                  <l>Am loſt with wonder yet.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Celind.</speaker>
                  <l>'Tis very ſtrange</l>
                  <l>Without a ſpel; but ther's a fate in love,</l>
                  <l>I like him ne'r the worſe.</l>
               </sp>
               <stage>Enter two Lords.</stage>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>1 <hi>Lo.</hi>
                  </speaker>
                  <l>Nothing but mariages, and triumph now.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Val.</speaker>
                  <l>What new acceſs of joy, makes <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 words">
                        <desc>〈◊◊〉</desc>
                     </gap> Lord,</l>
                  <l>So pleaſant?</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>1 <hi>Lo.</hi>
                  </speaker>
                  <l>Ther's a Packet <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 span">
                        <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                     </gap>
                  </l>
                  <pb n="26" facs="tcp:153343:18"/>
                  <l>Makes the King merry, we are all concernd in't?</l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Columbo</hi> hath given the enemy a great,</l>
                  <l>And glorious defeat, and is already</l>
                  <l>Preparing to march home.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Col.</speaker>
                  <l>He thriv'd the better for my prayers.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>2 <hi>Lo.</hi>
                  </speaker>
                  <l>You have been his great admirer, Madam.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>1 <hi>Lo.</hi>
                  </speaker>
                  <l>The King longs to ſee him.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Val.</speaker>
                  <l>This news exalts the Cardinal.</l>
               </sp>
               <stage>Enter Cardinal.</stage>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>1 <hi>Lo.</hi>
                  </speaker>
                  <l>He's here,</l>
                  <l>He appears with diſcontent, the Mariage</l>
                  <l>With Count <hi>D'Alvarez</hi> hath a bitter taſt,</l>
                  <l>And not worn off his palat; but let us leave him.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Ladies.</speaker>
                  <l>We'l to the Dutcheſs.</l>
               </sp>
               <stage>Exeunt. manet Car.</stage>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Card.</speaker>
                  <l>He has not woon ſo much upon the <hi>Arragon</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>As he has loſt at home, and his neglect</l>
                  <l>Of what my ſtudies had contriv'd to adde</l>
                  <l>More luſter to our Family by the acceſs</l>
                  <l>Of the great Dutcheſs fortune, cools his triumph,</l>
                  <l>And makes me wild.</l>
               </sp>
               <stage>Enter Hernando.</stage>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Her.</speaker>
                  <l>My good Lord Cardinal.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Car.</speaker>
                  <l>You made complaint to th' King about your Ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neral.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Her.</speaker>
                  <l>Not a complaint my Lord, I did but ſatisfie</l>
                  <l>Some queſtions o'the Kings.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Car.</speaker>
                  <l>You ſee he thrives</l>
                  <l>Without your perſonal valour, or advice,</l>
                  <l>Moſt grave and learned in the wars.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Her.</speaker>
                  <l>My Lord,</l>
                  <l>I Envy not his fortune.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Car.</speaker>
                  <l>'Tis above</l>
                  <l>Your Malice, and your noiſe not worth his anger,</l>
                  <l>'Tis barking gainſt the moon.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Her.</speaker>
                  <l>More temper would</l>
                  <pb n="27" facs="tcp:153343:18"/>
                  <l>Become that habit.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Car.</speaker>
                  <l>The Military thing would ſhew ſome ſpleen;</l>
                  <l>I'l blow an Army of ſuch Waſps about</l>
                  <l>The world; go look your ſting you left i'th' Camp, Sir.</l>
               </sp>
               <stage>Enter King, and Lords.</stage>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Her.</speaker>
                  <l>The King.</l>
                  <stage>Exit.</stage>
                  <l>This may be one day counted for.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>K.</speaker>
                  <l>All things conſpire my Lord to make you fortunate,</l>
                  <l>Your Nephews glory—</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Car.</speaker>
                  <l>'Twas your cauſe and juſtice</l>
                  <l>Made him victorious, had he been ſo valiant</l>
                  <l>At home, he had had another conqueſt to</l>
                  <l>Invite and bid her welcome to new wars.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>K.</speaker>
                  <l>You muſt be reconcil'd to providence, my Lord;</l>
                  <l>I heard you had a controvercy with</l>
                  <l>The Dutcheſs, I will have you friends.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Car.</speaker>
                  <l>I am not Angry.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>K.</speaker>
                  <l>For my ſake then you ſhall be pleas'd,</l>
                  <l>And with me grace the Mariage;</l>
                  <l>A Churchman muſt ſhew Charity, and ſhine</l>
                  <l>With firſt example, ſhe's a woman.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Car.</speaker>
                  <l>You ſhall preſcribe in all things; Sir, you cannot</l>
                  <l>Accuſe my love, if I ſtill wiſh my Nephew</l>
                  <l>Had been ſo happy to be conſtant to</l>
                  <l>Your own, and my election; yet my brain</l>
                  <l>Cannot reach how this comes about; I know</l>
                  <l>My Nephew lov'd her with a near affection.</l>
               </sp>
               <stage>Enter Hernando.</stage>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>K.</speaker>
                  <l>He'l give you fair account at his return.</l>
                  <l>Colonel, your Letters may be ſpar'd, the General</l>
                  <l>Has finiſh'd, and is coming home.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Her.</speaker>
                  <l>I am glad on't, ſir; my good Lord Cardinal</l>
                  <l>'Tis not impoſſible but ſome man provok'd,</l>
                  <l>May have a precious mind to cut your throat.</l>
               </sp>
               <pb n="28" facs="tcp:153343:19"/>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Car.</speaker>
                  <l>You ſhall command me Noble Colonel;</l>
                  <l>I know you wo'not fail to be at th'wedding.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Her.</speaker>
                  <l>'Tis not <hi>Columbo</hi> that is maried Sir.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Car.</speaker>
                  <l>Go teach the poſtures of the Pike and Musket,</l>
                  <l>Then dril your <hi>Mi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>midons</hi> into a ditch,</l>
                  <l>Where ſterve, and ſtink in pickle, you ſhall find</l>
                  <l>Me reaſonable, you ſee the King expects me.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Her.</speaker>
                  <l>So does the Devill; ſome deſperate hand</l>
                  <l>May help you on your journey.</l>
               </sp>
               <stage>Exeunt.</stage>
               <stage>Enter Secretary and Servants.</stage>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Sec.</speaker>
                  <p>Here this, I this will fit your part: you ſhall wear Slaſhes, becauſe you are a Souldier; here's for the blue mute.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>1</speaker>
                  <p>This doublet will never fit me, Pox ont', are theſe Breeches good enough for a Prince too? <hi>Pedro</hi> playes but a Lord, and he has two laces more in a ſeam.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Sec.</speaker>
                  <p>You muſt conſider <hi>Pedro</hi> is a fooliſh Lord, he may wear what lace he pleaſe.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>2</speaker>
                  <p>Does my beard fit my cloathes well Gentlemen?</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Sec</speaker>
                  <p>Pox o'your beard.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>3</speaker>
                  <p>That will fright away the hair.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>1</speaker>
                  <p>This fellow plays but a mute, &amp; he is ſo troubleſome, and talks.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>3</speaker>
                  <p>Mr. Secretary might have let <hi>Iaques</hi> play the ſoldier, He has a black patch already.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>2</speaker>
                  <p>By your favour Mr. Secretary, I was ask'd who writ this play for us.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Sec.</speaker>
                  <p>For u<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>? why art thou any more than a blew mute?</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>2</speaker>
                  <p>And by my troth, I ſaid, I thought it was all your own.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Sec.</speaker>
                  <p>Away you Coxcomb.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>4</speaker>
                  <p>Do'ſt think he has no more wit then to write a Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>medy? my Ladies Chaplain made the Play, though he is content for the honour and trouble of the buſineſs, to be ſeen in't.</p>
               </sp>
               <pb n="29" facs="tcp:153343:19"/>
               <stage>
                  <hi>Enter</hi> 5th. <hi>Servant.</hi>
               </stage>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>5</speaker>
                  <p>Did any body ſee my head Gentlemen 'twas here but now? I ſhall have never a head to play my part in.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Sec.</speaker>
                  <p>Is thy head gone? 'tis well thy part was not in't, Look, look about, has not <hi>Iaques</hi> it?</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>4</speaker>
                  <p>I his head? two'not come on upon my ſhoulders.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Sec.</speaker>
                  <p>Make haſt Gentlemen I'l ſee whether the King has ſup'd; Look every man to his wardrop and his part.</p>
               </sp>
               <stage>Exit.</stage>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>2</speaker>
                  <p>Is he gone? in my mind a maſque had been fitter for a mariage.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>4</speaker>
                  <p>Why mute? there was no time for't, and the ſcenes Are troubleſome.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>2</speaker>
                  <p>Half a ſcore Deal tack'd together in the clouds, what's that? a Throne to come down and dance; all the properties have been paid forty times over, and are in the Court ſtock, but the Secretary muſt have a play to ſhew his wit.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>4</speaker>
                  <p>Did not I tell thee twas the Chaplains? hold your tongue Mute.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>1</speaker>
                  <p>Under the Roſe and would this cloth of Silver dou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>blet might never come off agen, if there be any more plot then you ſee in the back of my hand.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>2</speaker>
                  <p>You talk of a plot, I'l not give this for the beſt Poets plot in the world and if it be not well carryed.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>4</speaker>
                  <p>Welll ſaid Mnte.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>3</speaker>
                  <p>Ha, ha; <hi>Pedro</hi> ſince he put on his doublet, has repea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted but three lines, and he has broke five butt ons.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>2</speaker>
                  <p>I know not but by this falſe beard, and here's hair e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nough to hang a reaſonable honeſt man, I do not re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>member to ſay a ſtrong line indeed in the whole Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>medy; but when the Chambermaid kiſſes the Cap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>3</speaker>
                  <p>Excellent mute.</p>
               </sp>
               <pb n="30" facs="tcp:153343:20"/>
               <stage>Enter another Servant.</stage>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>5</speaker>
                  <p>They have almoſt ſup'd, and I cannot find my head yet.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>4</speaker>
                  <p>play in thine own.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>5</speaker>
                  <p>Thank you for that, ſo I may have it made a proper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, if I have not a head found me, let Mr. Secretary play my part himſelf without it.</p>
               </sp>
               <stage>Enter Secretary.</stage>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Sec.</speaker>
                  <p>Are you all ready my Maſters? the King is coming through the Gallery, are the women dreſt?</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>1</speaker>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Rogero</hi> wants a head.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Sec.</speaker>
                  <p>Here with a pox to you, take mine, you a player? You a puppy-dog is the Muſick ready?</p>
               </sp>
               <stage>Enter Gentleman-Vſher.</stage>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Gent.</speaker>
                  <p>Gentlemen, it is my Ladies pleaſure that you expect till ſhe call for you, there are a company of Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>valiers in gallant Equipage newly alighted, have offer'd to preſent their Revels in honour of this <hi>Hymen;</hi> and 'tis her Graces command, that you be ſilent till their Enter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tainment be over.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>1</speaker>
                  <p>Gentlemen?</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>2</speaker>
                  <p>Affronted?</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>5</speaker>
                  <p>Mr. Secretary, ther's your head again; a man's a man; have I broken my ſleep to ſtudy fifteen lines for an Ambaſſador, and after that a Conſtable, and is it come to this?</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Sec.</speaker>
                  <p>Patience Gentlemen, be not ſo hot, tis but de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fer'd, and the play may do well enough cold.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>4</speaker>
                  <p>If it be not preſented, the Chaplain will have the greateſt loſs, he loſes his wits.</p>
               </sp>
               <stage>Hoboies.</stage>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Sec.</speaker>
                  <p>This Muſick ſpeaks the King upon entrance; retire, retire, and grumble not.</p>
               </sp>
               <stage>Excunt.</stage>
               <pb n="31" facs="tcp:153343:20"/>
               <stage>Enter King, Cardinal, Alvarez, Dutcheſs, Celinda, Va<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leria, Placentia, Lords, Hernando; (they being ſet) Enter Celumbo, and five more in rich habits Viſarded; between every two a torch bearer: They Dance, and after beckon to Alvarez as deſirous to ſpeak with him.</stage>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Alv.</speaker>
                  <l>With me!</l>
               </sp>
               <stage>They Embrace and whisper</stage>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>K.</speaker>
                  <l>Do you know the Maſquers Madam?</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Dut.</speaker>
                  <l>Not I Sir.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Car.</speaker>
                  <l>Ther's one, but that my Nephew is abroad,</l>
                  <l>And has more ſoul than thus to Jyg upon</l>
                  <l>Their <hi>Hymenrall</hi> night, I ſhould ſuſpect</l>
                  <l>'Twere he.</l>
               </sp>
               <stage>The Maſ quers lead in Alvarez.</stage>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Dut.</speaker>
                  <l>Wher's my Lord <hi>D' Alvarez?</hi>
                  </l>
               </sp>
               <stage>Recorders.</stage>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>K.</speaker>
                  <l>Call in the Bridegroom.</l>
               </sp>
               <stage>Enter Columbo, four Masquers, bring in Alvarez dead, in one of their habits, and having laid him down, Excunt.</stage>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Dut.</speaker>
                  <l>What Miſtery is this?</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Car.</speaker>
                  <l>We want the Bridegroom ſtill.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>K.</speaker>
                  <l>Where is <hi>Alvarez</hi>
                  </l>
               </sp>
               <stage>Columbo points to the body, they an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vizard it, &amp; find Alvar. bleeding.</stage>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Dut.</speaker>
                  <l>Oh 'tis my Lord hee's murder'd.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>K.</speaker>
                  <l>Who durſt commit this horrid act?</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Col.</speaker>
                  <l>I Sir.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>K.</speaker>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Columbo?</hi> ha!</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Col.</speaker>
                  <l>Yes; <hi>Columbo</hi> that dares ſtay</l>
                  <l>To juſtifie that act.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Her.</speaker>
                  <l>Moſt barbarous.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Dut.</speaker>
                  <l>Oh my deareſt Lord!</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>K.</speaker>
                  <l>Our guard ſeize on them all, this ſight doth ſnake</l>
                  <l>All that is man within me; poor <hi>Alvarez</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>Is this thy wedding day?</l>
               </sp>
               <stage>Enter Guard.</stage>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Dut.</speaker>
                  <l>If you do think there is a heaven or pains,</l>
                  <l>To puniſh ſuch black crimes i'th' other world,</l>
                  <pb n="32" facs="tcp:153343:21"/>
                  <l>Let me have ſwift, and ſuch exemplar juſtice</l>
                  <l>As ſhall become this great aſſaſinate,</l>
                  <l>You will take off our faith elſe, and if here</l>
                  <l>Such innocence muſt bleed, and you look on,</l>
                  <l>Poor men that call you Gods on earth, will doubt</l>
                  <l>To obey your Laws, nay practiſe to be Devils,</l>
                  <l>As fearing if ſuch monſtrous ſins go on</l>
                  <l>The Saints will not be ſafe in Heaven.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>K.</speaker>
                  <l>You ſhall,</l>
                  <l>You ſhall have juſtice.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Car.</speaker>
                  <l>Now to come off were brave.</l>
               </sp>
               <stage>Enter Servant.</stage>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Ser.</speaker>
                  <l>The Maſquers, Sir, are fled, their horſe prepar'd</l>
                  <l>At gate expected to receive 'em, where</l>
                  <l>They quickly mounted, coming ſo like friends</l>
                  <l>None could ſuſpect their haſt, which is ſecur'd</l>
                  <l>By advantage of the night.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Col.</speaker>
                  <l>I anſwer for 'em all, 'tis ſtake enough</l>
                  <l>For many lives, but if that poniard</l>
                  <l>Had voice, it would convince they were but all</l>
                  <l>Spectators of my act; and now if you</l>
                  <l>Will give your judgments leave, though at the firſt</l>
                  <l>Face of this object your cool bloods were frighted,</l>
                  <l>I can excuſe this deed and call it Juſtice;</l>
                  <l>An act, your honours, and your office Sir,</l>
                  <l>Is bound to build a Law upon, for others</l>
                  <l>To Imitate; I have but took his life,</l>
                  <l>And puniſh'd her with mercy, who had both</l>
                  <l>Conſpir'd to kill the ſoul of all my fame</l>
                  <l>Read there,—and read an injury as deep</l>
                  <l>In my diſhpnour, as the Devill knew</l>
                  <l>A Woman had capacity or malice</l>
                  <l>To execute read there, how you were cozen'd Sir,</l>
                  <l>Your power affronted, and my faith, her ſmiles</l>
                  <l>A jugling witchcraft to betray and make</l>
                  <l>My love her horſe to ſtalk withall, and catch</l>
                  <l>Her curled Minion.</l>
               </sp>
               <pb n="33" facs="tcp:153343:21"/>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Car.</speaker>
                  <l>Is it poſſible</l>
                  <l>The Dutcheſs could diſſemble ſo, and forfeit</l>
                  <l>Her modeſty with you, and to us all?</l>
                  <l>Yet I muſt pity her; my Nephew has</l>
                  <l>Been too ſevere, though this affront would call</l>
                  <l>A dying man from prayers, and turn him Tiger,</l>
                  <l>There being nothing dearer than our fame,</l>
                  <l>Which, If a common man, whoſe blood has no</l>
                  <l>Ingredient of honour, labour to</l>
                  <l>Preſerve, a Souldier (by his neareſt tye</l>
                  <l>To glory) is above all others, bound</l>
                  <l>To vindicate; and yet it might have been leſs bloody.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Her.</speaker>
                  <l>Charitable Devill!</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>K. Reads.</speaker>
                  <p>
                     <hi>I Pray, my Lord, releaſe under your hand, what you dare challenge in my love or perſon, as a juſt for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feit to my ſelf, this act will ſpeak you honorable to my thoughts, and when you have conquered thus your ſelf, you may proceed to many victories, and after, with ſafety of your famit viſit again</hi>
                  </p>
                  <stage>The loſt <hi>Roſaura.</hi>
                  </stage>
                  <l>To this your Anſwer was a free reſign?</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Col.</speaker>
                  <l>Flatter'd with great opinion of her faith,</l>
                  <l>And my deſert of her (with thought that ſhe,</l>
                  <l>Who ſeem'd to weep and chide my eaſie will</l>
                  <l>To part with her, could not be guilty of</l>
                  <l>A treaſon, or Apoſtacy ſo ſoon,</l>
                  <l>But rather meant this a device to make</l>
                  <l>Me expedite the affairs of War) I ſent</l>
                  <l>That paper, which her wickedneſs not juſtice,</l>
                  <l>Applied (what I meant tryall) her divorce;</l>
                  <l>I lov'd her ſo, I dare call heaven to witneſs</l>
                  <l>I knew not whether I lov'd moſt; while ſhe,</l>
                  <l>With him, whoſe crimſon penitence I provok'd,</l>
                  <l>Conſpir'd my everlaſting infamy;</l>
                  <l>Examine but the circumſtance.</l>
               </sp>
               <pb n="34" facs="tcp:153343:22"/>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Car.</speaker>
                  <l>'Tis clear,</l>
                  <l>This Match was made at home before ſhe ſent</l>
                  <l>That cunning writ, in hope to take him off,</l>
                  <l>As knowing his impatient Soul would ſcorn</l>
                  <l>To own a bleſſing came on crutches to him;</l>
                  <l>It was not well to raiſe his expectation,</l>
                  <l>(Had you, Sir, no affront) to ruine him</l>
                  <l>With ſo much ſcandall and contempt.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>K.</speaker>
                  <l>We have</l>
                  <l>Too plentifull a circumſtance to accuſe</l>
                  <l>You Madam, as the cauſe of your own ſorrows,</l>
                  <l>But not without an acceſſary, more</l>
                  <l>Than young <hi>Alvarez.</hi>
                  </l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Car.</speaker>
                  <l>Any other inſtrument?</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>K.</speaker>
                  <l>Yes I am guilty, with her ſelf, and <hi>Don</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Columbo,</hi> though our acts look'd ſeverall waies,</l>
                  <l>That thought a lover might ſo ſoon be ranſom'd;</l>
                  <l>And did exceed the office of a King</l>
                  <l>To exerciſe dominion over hearts,</l>
                  <l>That owe to the prerogative of heaven</l>
                  <l>Their choice, or Separation; you muſt therefore,</l>
                  <l>When you do kneel for Juſtice, and Revenge,</l>
                  <l>Madam, conſider me a laterall agent</l>
                  <l>In poor <hi>Alvarez</hi> Tragedy.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>1 <hi>Lo.</hi>
                  </speaker>
                  <l>It was your love to <hi>Don Columbo</hi> Sir.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Her.</speaker>
                  <l>So, ſo; the King is charm'd; do you obſerve,</l>
                  <l>How to acquit <hi>Columbo,</hi> he would draw</l>
                  <l>Himſelf into the plot; Heaven, is this Juſtice?</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Car.</speaker>
                  <l>Your Judgment is divine in this.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>K.</speaker>
                  <l>And yet,</l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Columbo</hi> cannot be ſecure, and we</l>
                  <l>Juſt in his pardon, that durſt make ſo great,</l>
                  <l>And inſolent a breach of Law and Duty.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>2 <hi>Lo.</hi>
                  </speaker>
                  <l>Ha, Will he turn agen?</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>K.</speaker>
                  <l>And ſhould we leave</l>
                  <l>This guilt of blood to Heaven, which cries, and ſtrikes,</l>
                  <pb n="35" facs="tcp:153343:22"/>
                  <l>With loud appeals the palace of eternity,</l>
                  <l>Yet here is more to charge <hi>Columbo,</hi> than</l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Alvarez</hi> blood, and bids me puniſh it,</l>
                  <l>Or be no King.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Her.</speaker>
                  <l>'Tis come about my Lords.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>K.</speaker>
                  <l>And If I ſhould forgive</l>
                  <l>His timeleſs death, I cannot the offence,</l>
                  <l>That with ſuch boldneſs ſtruck at me. Has my</l>
                  <l>Indulgence to your merits which are great</l>
                  <l>Made me ſo cheap, your rage could meet, no time</l>
                  <l>Nor place for your revenge, but where my eys</l>
                  <l>Muſt be affrighted, and affronted with</l>
                  <l>The bloody execution? This contempt</l>
                  <l>Of Majeſty tranſcends my power to pardon,</l>
                  <l>And you ſhall feel my anger Sir.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Her.</speaker>
                  <l>Thou ſhalt have one ſhort prayer more for that.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Col.</speaker>
                  <l>Have I i'th' progreſs of my life</l>
                  <l>No actions to plead me up deſerving,</l>
                  <l>Againſt this ceremony?</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Car.</speaker>
                  <l>Contain your ſelf.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Col.</speaker>
                  <l>I muſt be dumb then; where is honour?</l>
                  <l>And gratitude of Kings, when they forget</l>
                  <l>Whoſe hand ſecur'd their greatneſs? take my head off,</l>
                  <l>Examine then which of your ſilken Lords,</l>
                  <l>As I have done, will throw himſelf on dangers;</l>
                  <l>Like to a floting Iland move in blood;</l>
                  <l>And where your great deſence calls him to ſtand</l>
                  <l>A Bullwark, upon his hold breſt to take</l>
                  <l>In death, that you may live: but Souldiers are</l>
                  <l>Your valiant fools, whom when your own ſecurities</l>
                  <l>Are bleeding you can cheriſh, but when once</l>
                  <l>Your ſtate and nerves are knit, not thinking when</l>
                  <l>To uſe their ſurgery again, you caſt</l>
                  <l>Them off, and let them hang in duſty armories,</l>
                  <l>Or make it death to ask for pay.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>K.</speaker>
                  <l>No more,</l>
                  <pb n="36" facs="tcp:153343:23"/>
                  <l>We thought to have put your victory and merits</l>
                  <l>In ballance with <hi>Alvarez</hi> death, which while</l>
                  <l>Our mercy was to Iudge, had been your ſafety;</l>
                  <l>But the affront to us, made greater by</l>
                  <l>This boldneſs to upbraid our royall bounty,</l>
                  <l>Shall tame or make you nothing.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Lor.</speaker>
                  <l>Excellent.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Her.</speaker>
                  <l>The Cardinal is not pleas'd.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Car.</speaker>
                  <l>Humble your ſelf</l>
                  <l>To th' King.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Col.</speaker>
                  <l>And beg my life? let cowards do't</l>
                  <l>That dare not dy, I'l rather have no head</l>
                  <l>Than owe it to his Charity.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>K.</speaker>
                  <l>To th' Caſtle with him.</l>
                  <l>Madam, I leave you to your grief, and what</l>
                  <l>The King can recompence to your tears, or honor</l>
                  <l>Of your dead Lord, expect.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Dut.</speaker>
                  <l>This ſhews like Iuſtice.</l>
               </sp>
               <stage>Exeunt.</stage>
            </div>
            <div n="4" type="act">
               <head>ACT IV.</head>
               <stage>Enter two Lords, Hernando.</stage>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>1 <hi>Lord.</hi>
                  </speaker>
                  <l>THis is the age of wonders.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>2 <hi>Lo.</hi>
                  </speaker>
                  <l>Wonderous miſchiefs.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Her.</speaker>
                  <l>Among thoſe guards which ſome call Tutelar Angels,</l>
                  <l>Whoſe office is to govern Provinces,</l>
                  <l>Is there not one will undertake <hi>Navarre?</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>Hath heaven forſook us quite?</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>1</speaker>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Columbo</hi> at large?</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>2</speaker>
                  <l>And grac'd now more than ever.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>1</speaker>
                  <l>He was not pardon'd,</l>
                  <l>That word was prejudiciall to his fame.</l>
               </sp>
               <pb n="37" facs="tcp:153343:23"/>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Her.</speaker>
                  <l>But as the murder done had been a dream</l>
                  <l>Vaniſh'd to memory, he's courted as</l>
                  <l>Preſerver of his Country; with what chains</l>
                  <l>Of Magick does this Cardinal hold the King?</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>2</speaker>
                  <l>What will you ſay my Lord if they inchant</l>
                  <l>The Dutcheſs now; and by ſome impudent art,</l>
                  <l>Advance a Mariage to <hi>Columbo</hi> yet?</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Her.</speaker>
                  <l>Say? I'l ſay no woman can be ſav'd, nor is't</l>
                  <l>Fit, indeed, any ſhould pretend to Heaven</l>
                  <l>After one ſuch impiety in their ſex,</l>
                  <l>And yet my faith has been ſo ſtager'd, ſince</l>
                  <l>The King reſtor'd <hi>Columbo,</hi> I'l be now</l>
                  <l>Of no Religion.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>1</speaker>
                  <l>'Tis not poſſible</l>
                  <l>She can forgive the murder, I obſerv'd</l>
                  <l>Her tears.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Her.</speaker>
                  <l>Why ſo did I, my Lord,</l>
                  <l>And if they be not honeſt, 'tis to be</l>
                  <l>Half damn'd to look upon a woman weeping.</l>
                  <l>When do you think the Cardinal ſaid his prayers?</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>2</speaker>
                  <l>I know not.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Her.</speaker>
                  <l>Heaven forgive my want of charity</l>
                  <l>But if I were to kill him, he ſhould have</l>
                  <l>No time to pray, his life could be no ſacrifice,</l>
                  <l>Unleſs his ſoul went too.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>1</speaker>
                  <l>That were too much.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Her.</speaker>
                  <l>When you mean to diſpatch him, you may give</l>
                  <l>Time for Confeſſion, they have injur'd me</l>
                  <l>After another rate.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>2</speaker>
                  <l>You are too paſſionate Cozen.</l>
               </sp>
               <stage>Enter Columbo, Colonels, Alfonſo, Courtiers, (they paſs over the Stage.)</stage>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Her.</speaker>
                  <l>How the gay men do flutter to congratulate</l>
                  <l>His Goal delivery? ther's one honeſt man,</l>
                  <l>What pity 'tis a gallant fellow ſhould</l>
                  <pb n="38" facs="tcp:153343:24"/>
                  <l>Depend on knaves for his preferment.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>1</speaker>
                  <l>Except this cruelty upon <hi>Alvarez,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Columbo</hi> has no mighty ſtain upon him;</l>
                  <l>But for his Uncle—</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Her.</speaker>
                  <l>If I had a Son</l>
                  <l>Of twelve years old, that would not fight with him,</l>
                  <l>And ſtake his ſoul againſt his Cardinals Cap,</l>
                  <l>I would diſ-inherit him; Time has took a leaſe</l>
                  <l>But for three lives I hope, a fourth may ſee</l>
                  <l>Honeſty walk without a crutch.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>2</speaker>
                  <l>This is</l>
                  <l>But Air and Wildneſs.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Her.</speaker>
                  <l>I'l ſee the Dutcheſs,</l>
                  <l>You may do well to comfort her,</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>1</speaker>
                  <l>We muſt attend the King.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Her.</speaker>
                  <l>your pleaſures.</l>
               </sp>
               <stage>Exit Her.</stage>
               <stage>Enter King and Cardinal.</stage>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>1</speaker>
                  <l>A Man of a brave ſoul.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>2</speaker>
                  <l>The leſs his ſafety;</l>
                  <l>The King and Cardinal in conſult.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>K.</speaker>
                  <l>Commend us to the Dutcheſs, and imploy</l>
                  <l>What language you think fit, and powerfull</l>
                  <l>To reconcile her to ſome peace. My Lords.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Car.</speaker>
                  <l>Sir, I poſſeſs all for your ſacred uſes.</l>
               </sp>
               <stage>Exeunt Severally.</stage>
               <stage>Enter Secretary and Celinda.</stage>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Sec.</speaker>
                  <l>Madam, you are the welcom'ſt Lady living.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Cel.</speaker>
                  <l>To whom, Mr. Secretary?</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Sec.</speaker>
                  <l>If you have mercy</l>
                  <l>To pardon ſo much boldneſs, I durſt ſay,</l>
                  <l>To me—I am a Gentleman.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Cel.</speaker>
                  <l>And handſome.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Sec.</speaker>
                  <l>But my Lady has much wanted you.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Cel.</speaker>
                  <l>Why Mr. Secretary?</l>
               </sp>
               <pb n="39" facs="tcp:153343:24"/>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Sec.</speaker>
                  <l>You are the prettieſt,</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Cel.</speaker>
                  <l>So.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Sec.</speaker>
                  <l>The witieſt,</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Cel.</speaker>
                  <l>So.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Sec.</speaker>
                  <l>The merrieſt Lady i'th' Court.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Cel.</speaker>
                  <l>And I was wiſh'd to make the Dutcheſs pleaſant.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Sec.</speaker>
                  <l>She never had ſo deep a cauſe of ſorrow,</l>
                  <l>Her Chamber's but a Coffin of a larger</l>
                  <l>Volume, wherein ſhe walks ſo like a Ghoſt,</l>
                  <l>T'would make you pale to ſee her.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Cel.</speaker>
                  <l>Tell her Grace I attend here.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Sec.</speaker>
                  <l>I ſhall moſt willingly.</l>
                  <l>A ſpirited Lady, would I had her in my cloſet,</l>
                  <l>She is excellent company among the Lords,</l>
                  <l>Sure ſhe has an admirable treble—Madam.</l>
               </sp>
               <stage>Exit.</stage>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Cel.</speaker>
                  <l>I do ſuſpect this fellow would be nibling</l>
                  <l>Like ſome whoſe narrow fortunes will not riſe</l>
                  <l>To wear things when the inventions rare, and new,</l>
                  <l>But treading on the heel of pride, they hunt</l>
                  <l>The faſhion when tis crippled, like fell tyrants;</l>
                  <l>I hope I am not old yet, I had the honour</l>
                  <l>To be ſaluted by our Cardinals Nephew</l>
                  <l>This Morning, ther's a man!</l>
               </sp>
               <stage>Enter Secretary.</stage>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Sec.</speaker>
                  <l>I have prevail'd,</l>
                  <l>Sweet Madam uſe what Eloquence you can</l>
                  <l>Upon her, and if ever I be uſefull</l>
                  <l>To your Ladiſhips ſervice, your leaſt breath commands me.</l>
               </sp>
               <stage>Enter Dutcheſs.</stage>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Dut.</speaker>
                  <l>Madam, I come to ask you but one queſtion,</l>
                  <l>If you were in my State, my ſtate of grief,</l>
                  <l>I mean an exile from all happineſs,</l>
                  <l>Of this world, and almoſt of heaven, for my</l>
                  <l>Affliction is finding out deſpair,</l>
                  <pb n="40" facs="tcp:153343:25"/>
                  <l>What would you think of <hi>Don Columbo?</hi>
                  </l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Cel.</speaker>
                  <l>Madam?</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Dut.</speaker>
                  <l>Whoſe Bloody hand wrought all this miſery?</l>
                  <l>Would you not weep as I do? and wiſh rather</l>
                  <l>An everlaſting ſpring of tears to drown</l>
                  <l>Your ſight, than let your eys be curſt to ſee</l>
                  <l>The murderer agen? and glorious?</l>
                  <l>So careleſs of his ſin, that he is made</l>
                  <l>Fit for new <hi>Parricide,</hi> even while his ſoul</l>
                  <l>Is purpled o'r, and reeks with innocent blood.</l>
                  <l>But do not, do not anſwer me, I know</l>
                  <l>You have ſo great a ſpirit, (which I want,</l>
                  <l>The horrour of his fact ſurpriſing all</l>
                  <l>My faculties) you would not let him live:</l>
                  <l>But I, poor I, muſt ſuffer more, ther's not</l>
                  <l>One little ſtar in Heaven will look on me,</l>
                  <l>Unleſs to chooſe me out the mark, on whom</l>
                  <l>It may ſhoot down ſome angry influence.</l>
               </sp>
               <stage>Enter Placentia.</stage>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Pla.</speaker>
                  <l>Madam, her's <hi>Don Columbo</hi> ſays he muſt</l>
                  <l>Speak with your Grace.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Dut.</speaker>
                  <l>But he muſt not, I charge you.</l>
                  <l>None elſe wait? Is this well done,</l>
                  <l>To triumph in his Tyranny? ſpeak Madam,</l>
                  <l>Speak but your conſcience.</l>
               </sp>
               <stage>Enter Columbo, and Secretary.</stage>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Sec.</speaker>
                  <l>Sir, you muſt not ſee her.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Col.</speaker>
                  <l>Not ſee her? were ſhe cabled up above</l>
                  <l>The ſearch of Bullet, or of Fire, were ſhe</l>
                  <l>Within her Grave, and that the tougheſt Mine</l>
                  <l>That ever nature teem'd and groand withall,</l>
                  <l>I would force ſome way to ſee her; do not fear</l>
                  <l>I come to Court you Madam, y'are not worth</l>
                  <l>The humbleſt of my kinder thoughts, I come</l>
                  <pb n="41" facs="tcp:153343:25"/>
                  <l>To ſhew the man you have prokvo'd, and loſt;</l>
                  <l>And tell you what remains of my revenge.</l>
                  <l>Live, but never preſume again to marry,</l>
                  <l>I'l kill the next at th' Altar, and quench all</l>
                  <l>The ſmiling tapers with his blood; if after</l>
                  <l>You dare provoke the Prieſt, and heaven ſo much,</l>
                  <l>To take another, in thy bed I'l cut him from</l>
                  <l>Thy warm embracc, and throw his heart to Ravens.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Cel.</speaker>
                  <l>This will appear an unexampled cruelty.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Col.</speaker>
                  <l>Your pardon Madam, rage, and my revenge</l>
                  <l>Not perfect, took away my eys, you are</l>
                  <l>A noble Lady, this, not worth your ey-beam,</l>
                  <l>One of ſo ſlight a making, and ſo thin,</l>
                  <l>An Autumn leaf is of too great a value</l>
                  <l>To play, which ſhall be ſooneſt loſt i'th' Air;</l>
                  <l>Be pleas'd to own me by ſome name, in your</l>
                  <l>Aſſurance, I deſpiſe to be receiv'd</l>
                  <l>There, let her witneſs that I call</l>
                  <l>You Miſtreſs; honour me to make theſe Pearls</l>
                  <l>Your carkanet.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Cel.</speaker>
                  <l>My Lord, you are too humble in your thoughts.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Col.</speaker>
                  <l>Ther's no vexation too great to puniſh her.</l>
               </sp>
               <stage>Exit.</stage>
               <stage>Enter Secretary.</stage>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Sec.</speaker>
                  <l>Now Nadam?</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Cel.</speaker>
                  <l>Away you ſaucy fellow; Madam, I</l>
                  <l>Muſt be excus'd, if I do think more honourably</l>
                  <l>Than you have cauſe of this great Lord.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Dut.</speaker>
                  <l>Why is not</l>
                  <l>All woman kind concern'd to hate what's impious?</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Cel.</speaker>
                  <l>For my part—</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Dut.</speaker>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Antonio,</hi> is this a woman?</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Sec.</speaker>
                  <l>I know not whether ſhe be man or woman,</l>
                  <l>I ſhould be nimble to find out the Experiment,</l>
                  <l>She look'd with leſs ſtate, when <hi>Columbo</hi> came.</l>
               </sp>
               <pb facs="tcp:153343:26"/>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Dut.</speaker>
                  <l>Let me entreat your abſence, I am cozen'd in her,</l>
                  <l>I took you for a modeſt, honeſt Lady.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Cel.</speaker>
                  <l>Madam, I ſcorn any accuſer, and</l>
                  <l>Deducting the great title of a Dutcheſs,</l>
                  <l>I ſhall not need one grain of your dear honour</l>
                  <l>To make me full weight, if your Grace be jealous</l>
                  <l>I can remove.</l>
               </sp>
               <stage>Exit.</stage>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Sec.</speaker>
                  <l>She is gone.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Dut.</speaker>
                  <l>Prethee remove</l>
                  <l>My fears of her return,—ſhe is not worth</l>
                  <stage>Ex. Sec.</stage>
                  <l>Conſidering, my anger's mounted higher;</l>
                  <l>He need not put in caution for my next</l>
                  <l>Marrage, <hi>Alvarez,</hi> I muſt come to thee,</l>
                  <l>Thy Virgin, Wife, and Widdow, but not till</l>
                  <l>I ha' paid thoſe Tragick duties to thy Herſe,</l>
                  <l>Become my piety and love, but how?</l>
                  <l>Who ſhall inſtruct a way?</l>
               </sp>
               <stage>Enter Placentia.</stage>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Pla.</speaker>
                  <l>Madam, <hi>Don</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Hernando</hi> much deſires to ſpeak with you.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Dut.</speaker>
                  <l>Will not thy own diſcretion think I am</l>
                  <l>Unfit for viſit.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Pla.</speaker>
                  <l>Pleaſe your Grace he brings</l>
                  <l>Something he ſays imports your ear, and love</l>
                  <l>Of the dead Lord <hi>Alvarez.</hi>
                  </l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Dut.</speaker>
                  <l>Then admit him.</l>
               </sp>
               <stage>Enter Hernando.</stage>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Her.</speaker>
                  <l>I would ſpeak, Madam, to your ſelf.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Dut.</speaker>
                  <l>Your abſence.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Her.</speaker>
                  <l>I know not how you Grace wil cenſure ſo</l>
                  <l>Much boldneſs, when you know the affairs I come for.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Dut.</speaker>
                  <l>My Servant has prepar'd me to receive it,</l>
                  <l>If it concern my dead Lord.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Her.</speaker>
                  <l>Can you name</l>
                  <pb facs="tcp:153343:26"/>
                  <l>So much of your <hi>Alvarez</hi> in a breath</l>
                  <l>Without one word of your revenge? O Madam,</l>
                  <l>I come to chide you, and repent my great</l>
                  <l>Opinion of your virtue, that can walk,</l>
                  <l>And ſpend ſo many hours in naked Solitude,</l>
                  <l>As if you thought that no arrear were due</l>
                  <l>To his death, when you had paid his Funerall charges,</l>
                  <l>Made your eys red, and wept a handkercher;</l>
                  <l>I come to tell you that I ſaw him bleed,</l>
                  <l>I, that can challenge nothing in his name,</l>
                  <l>And honour, ſaw his murder'd body warm,</l>
                  <l>And panting with the labour of his ſpirits,</l>
                  <l>Till my amaz'd Soul ſhrunk and hid it ſelf,</l>
                  <l>While barbarous <hi>Columbo</hi> grinning ſtood,</l>
                  <l>And mock'd the weeping wounds; it is too much</l>
                  <l>That you ſhould keep your heart alive, ſo long</l>
                  <l>After this ſpectacle, and not revenge it.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Dut.</speaker>
                  <l>You do not know the buſineſs of my heart,</l>
                  <l>That cenſure me ſo raſhly; yet I thank you,</l>
                  <l>And if you be <hi>Alvarez</hi> friend, dare tell</l>
                  <l>Your confidence, that I deſpiſe my life,</l>
                  <l>But know not how to uſe it in a ſervice,</l>
                  <l>To ſpeak me his revenger, this will need</l>
                  <l>No other proof, than that to you, who may</l>
                  <l>Be ſent with cunning to betray me, I</l>
                  <l>Have made this bold confeſſion, I ſo much</l>
                  <l>Deſire to ſacrifice to that hovering Ghoſt,</l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Columbo's</hi> life, that I am not ambitious</l>
                  <l>To keep my own two minutes after it.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Her.</speaker>
                  <l>If you will call me coward, which is equall</l>
                  <l>To think I am a Traytor, I forgive it,</l>
                  <l>For this brave reſolution, which time</l>
                  <l>And all the Deſtinies muſt aid, I beg</l>
                  <l>That I may kiſs your hand for this, and may</l>
                  <l>The ſoul of angry honour guide it.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Dut.</speaker>
                  <l>Whither?</l>
               </sp>
               <pb facs="tcp:153343:27"/>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Her.</speaker>
                  <l>To <hi>Don Columbo</hi>'s heart.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Dut.</speaker>
                  <l>It is too weak I fear alone.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Her.</speaker>
                  <l>Alone? are you in earneſt? why? will it not</l>
                  <l>Be a diſhonour to your Juſtice, Madam,</l>
                  <l>Another arm ſhould interpoſe? but that</l>
                  <l>It were a ſawcy act to mingle with you,</l>
                  <l>I durſt, nay I am bound in the revenge</l>
                  <l>Of him that's dead, (ſince the whole world has intereſt,</l>
                  <l>In every goodmans loſs) to offer it;</l>
                  <l>Dare you command me, Madam?</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Dut.</speaker>
                  <l>Not command,</l>
                  <l>But I ſhould more than honour ſuch a truth</l>
                  <l>In man, that durſt againſt ſo mighty odds,</l>
                  <l>Appear <hi>Alvarez</hi> friend and mine; the Cardinal—</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Her.</speaker>
                  <l>Is for the ſecond courſe, <hi>Columbo</hi> muſt</l>
                  <l>Be firſt cut up, his Ghoſt muſt lead the dance.</l>
                  <l>Let him dy firſt.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Dut.</speaker>
                  <l>But how?</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Her.</speaker>
                  <l>How? with a Sword, and if I undertake it,</l>
                  <l>I wo'not loſe ſo much of my own honour,</l>
                  <l>To kill him baſely.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Dut.</speaker>
                  <l>How ſhall I reward</l>
                  <l>This infinite ſervice? 'tis not Modeſty,</l>
                  <l>While now my husband groanes beneath his tomb,</l>
                  <l>And calls me to his marble bed, to promiſe</l>
                  <l>What this great act might well deſerve, my ſelf</l>
                  <l>If you ſurvive the Victor, but if thus</l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Alvarez</hi> aſhes be appeas'd it muſt</l>
                  <l>Deſerve an honourable memory;</l>
                  <l>And though <hi>Columbo</hi> (as he had all power,</l>
                  <l>And graſp'd the fates) has vow'd to kill the man</l>
                  <l>That ſhall ſucceed <hi>Alvarez</hi>—</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Her.</speaker>
                  <l>Tyranny.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Dut.</speaker>
                  <l>Yet if ever,</l>
                  <l>I entertain a thought of love hereafter,</l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Hernando</hi> from the world ſhall challenge it,</l>
                  <pb n="45" facs="tcp:153343:27"/>
                  <l>Till when, my Prayers, and fortune, ſhall wait on you.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Her.</speaker>
                  <l>This is too mighty recompence.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Dut.</speaker>
                  <l>'Tis all juſt.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Her.</speaker>
                  <l>If I outlive <hi>Columbo</hi> I muſt not</l>
                  <l>Expect ſecurity at home.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Dut.</speaker>
                  <l>Thou canſt</l>
                  <l>Not fly, where all my fortunes, and my love,</l>
                  <l>Shall not atttend to guard thee.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Her.</speaker>
                  <l>If I dye—</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Dut.</speaker>
                  <l>Thy memory</l>
                  <l>Shall have a ſhrine, the next within my heart</l>
                  <l>To my <hi>Alvarez.</hi>
                  </l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Her.</speaker>
                  <l>Once again your hand,</l>
                  <l>Your cauſe is ſo religious you need</l>
                  <l>Not ſtrengthen it with your prayers, truſt it to me.</l>
               </sp>
               <stage>Enter Placentia, and Cardinal.</stage>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Pla.</speaker>
                  <l>Madam, the Cardinal.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Dut.</speaker>
                  <l>Will you appear?</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Her.</speaker>
                  <l>And he had all the horror of the Devil</l>
                  <l>In's face, I would not balk him.</l>
               </sp>
               <stage>He ſtares upon the Cardinal in his Exit.</stage>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Car.</speaker>
                  <l>What makes <hi>Hernando</hi> here? I do not like</l>
                  <l>They ſhould conſult, I'l take no note; the King</l>
                  <l>Fairly ſalutes your Grace, by whoſe command</l>
                  <l>I am to tell you, though his will and actions</l>
                  <l>Illimited, ſtoop not to ſatisfie</l>
                  <l>The Vulgar inquiſition, he is</l>
                  <l>Yet willing to retain a juſt opinion,</l>
                  <l>With thoſe that are plac'd neer him, and although</l>
                  <l>You look with Natures ey upon your ſelf,</l>
                  <l>Which needs no perſpective to reach, nor art</l>
                  <l>Of any optick to make greater, what</l>
                  <l>Your narrow ſenſe applies an injury,</l>
                  <l>(Our ſelves ſtill neareſt to our ſelves) but ther's</l>
                  <pb n="46" facs="tcp:153343:28"/>
                  <l>Another ey that looks abroad and walks</l>
                  <l>In ſearch of reaſon, and the weight of things,</l>
                  <l>With which if you look on him, you will find</l>
                  <l>His pardon to <hi>Columbo</hi> cannot be</l>
                  <l>So much againſt his juſtice, as your erring</l>
                  <l>Faith would perſwade your anger.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Dut.</speaker>
                  <l>Good my Lord,</l>
                  <l>Your phraſe has too much landſchape and I cannot</l>
                  <l>Diſtinguiſh at this diſtance you preſent</l>
                  <l>The figure perfect, but indeed my eys</l>
                  <l>May pray your Lordſhip find excuſe, for tears</l>
                  <l>Have almoſt made them blind.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Car.</speaker>
                  <l>Fair, peace reſtore 'em!</l>
                  <l>To bring the object nearer, the King ſays,</l>
                  <l>He could not be ſevere to <hi>Don Columbo</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>Without injuſtice to his other merits,</l>
                  <l>Which call more loud for their reward and honour,</l>
                  <l>Than you for your revenge; the Kingdom made</l>
                  <l>Happy by thoſe; you only by the laſt</l>
                  <l>Uunfortunate, nor was it rationall,</l>
                  <l>I ſpeak the Kings own Language, he ſhould dy</l>
                  <l>For taking one mans breath, without whoſe valour</l>
                  <l>None now had been alive, without diſhonour.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Dut.</speaker>
                  <l>In my poor underſtanding, 'tis the Crown</l>
                  <l>Of virtue to proceed in its own tract,</l>
                  <l>Not deviate from honour, if you acquit</l>
                  <l>A man of murder, 'cauſe he has done brave</l>
                  <l>Things in the War, you will bring down his valour</l>
                  <l>To a crime, nay to a baud, if it ſecure</l>
                  <l>A rape, and but teach thoſe that deſerve well</l>
                  <l>To ſin with greater licence; but diſpute</l>
                  <l>Is now too late, my Lord, 'tis done, and you,</l>
                  <l>By the good King, in tender of my ſorrows,</l>
                  <l>Sent to perſwade me, 'tis unreaſonable</l>
                  <l>That Juſtice ſhould repair me.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Car.</speaker>
                  <l>You miſtake,</l>
                  <pb n="47" facs="tcp:153343:28"/>
                  <l>For if <hi>Columbo's</hi> death could make <hi>Alvarez</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>Live, the King had given him up to Law</l>
                  <l>Your bleeding Sacrifice; but when his life</l>
                  <l>Was but another treaſure thrown away,</l>
                  <l>To obey a clamorous Statute, it was wiſdom</l>
                  <l>To himſelf and common ſafety to take off</l>
                  <l>This killing edge of Law, and keep <hi>Columbo</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>To recompence the crime by noble acts,</l>
                  <l>And ſorrow, that in time might draw your pity.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Dut.</speaker>
                  <l>This is a greater tyranny, than that</l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Columbo</hi> exercis'd, he kill'd my Lord,</l>
                  <l>And you not have the charity to let</l>
                  <l>Me think it worth a puniſhment,</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Car.</speaker>
                  <l>To that</l>
                  <l>In my own name, I anſwer; I condemn</l>
                  <l>And urge the blody guilt againſt my Nephew,</l>
                  <l>'Twas violent, and cruell, a black deed,</l>
                  <l>A deed whoſe memory doth make me ſhudder,</l>
                  <l>An act that did betray a tyranous nature,</l>
                  <l>Which he took up in War, the ſchool of vengeance;</l>
                  <l>And though the Kings compaſſion ſpare him here,</l>
                  <l>Unleſs his heart Weep it ſelf out in penitent tears.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Dut.</speaker>
                  <l>This ſounds</l>
                  <l>As you were now a good man.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Car.</speaker>
                  <l>Does your Grace</l>
                  <l>Think I have conſcience to allow the murder?</l>
                  <l>Although when it was done, I did obey</l>
                  <l>The ſtream of nature, as he was my Kinſman,</l>
                  <l>To plead he might not pay his forfeit life,</l>
                  <l>Could I do leſs for one ſo near my bloud?</l>
                  <l>Conſider Madam, and be charitable,</l>
                  <l>Let not this wild injuſtice, make me loſe</l>
                  <l>The character I bear, and reverend habit.</l>
                  <l>To make you full acquainted with my innocence,</l>
                  <l>I challenge here my ſoul, and heaven to witneſs</l>
                  <pb n="48" facs="tcp:153343:29"/>
                  <l>If I had any thought, or knowledge with</l>
                  <l>My nephews plot, or perſon, when he came</l>
                  <l>Under the ſmooth pretence of friend to violate</l>
                  <l>Your hoſpitable laws, and do that act</l>
                  <l>Whoſe frequent mention drawes this tear, a whirlwind</l>
                  <l>Suatch me to endleſs flames.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Dut.</speaker>
                  <l>I muſt believe,</l>
                  <l>And ask your Graces pardon, I confeſs</l>
                  <l>I ha' not lov'd you ſince <hi>Alvarez</hi> death,</l>
                  <l>Though we were recontil'd.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Car.</speaker>
                  <l>I do not blame</l>
                  <l>Your Jealouſie, nor any zeal you had</l>
                  <l>To proſecute revenge againſt me, Madam,</l>
                  <l>As I then ſtood ſuſpected, nor can yet</l>
                  <l>Implore your mercy to <hi>Columbo,</hi> all</l>
                  <l>I have to ſay is to retain my firſt</l>
                  <l>Opinion and credit with your Grace,</l>
                  <l>Which you may think I urge not out of fear</l>
                  <l>Or ends upon you, (ſince, I thank the King,</l>
                  <l>I ſtand firm on the baſe of royall favour)</l>
                  <l>But for your own ſake, and to ſhew I have</l>
                  <l>Compaſſion of your ſufferings.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Dut.</speaker>
                  <l>You have cleer'd</l>
                  <l>A doubt my Lord, and by this fair remonſtrance,</l>
                  <l>Given my ſorrow ſo much truce, to think</l>
                  <l>That we may meet agen, and yet be friends.</l>
                  <l>But be not angry, if I ſtill remember</l>
                  <l>By whom <hi>Alvarez</hi> dyed, and weep, and wake</l>
                  <l>Another Iuſtice with my prayers,</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Car.</speaker>
                  <l>All thoughts</l>
                  <l>That may advance a better peace, dwell with you.</l>
               </sp>
               <stage>Exit.</stage>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Dut.</speaker>
                  <l>How would this cozening Stateſman bribe my Faith</l>
                  <l>With flatteries to think him innocent?</l>
                  <l>No, if his Nephew dy, this Cardinal muſt not</l>
                  <l>Be long-liv'd; all the prayers of a wrong'd Widow</l>
                  <pb n="49" facs="tcp:153343:29"/>
                  <l>Make firm <hi>Hernando</hi>'s Sword, and my own hand</l>
                  <l>Shall have ſome glory in the next revenge;</l>
                  <l>I will pretend my brain with grief diſtracted,</l>
                  <l>It may gain eaſy credit, and beſide</l>
                  <l>The taking off examination</l>
                  <l>For great <hi>Columbo</hi>'s death, it makes what act</l>
                  <l>I do in that believ'd want of my reaſon,</l>
                  <l>Appear no crime, but my defence; look down</l>
                  <l>Soul of my Lord, from thy eternall ſhade,</l>
                  <l>And unto all thy bleſt companions boaſt,</l>
                  <l>Thy Dutcheſs buſie to revenge thy Ghoſt.</l>
               </sp>
               <stage>Exit.</stage>
               <stage>Enter Columbo, Hernando, Alfonſo, Colonel.</stage>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Col.</speaker>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Hernando,</hi> now I love thee, and do half</l>
                  <l>Repent the affront my paſſion threw upon thee.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Her.</speaker>
                  <l>You wo'not be too prodigall o' your penitence.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Colu.</speaker>
                  <l>This makes good thy Nobility of birth,</l>
                  <l>Thou mayſt be worth my anger and my ſword,</l>
                  <l>If thou doſt execute as daringly,</l>
                  <l>As thou provok'ſt a quarrell, I did think</l>
                  <l>Thy ſoul a ſtarveling, or a ſleep.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Her.</speaker>
                  <l>You'l find it</l>
                  <l>Active enough to keep your ſpirit waking,</l>
                  <l>Which to exaſperate, for yet I think</l>
                  <l>It is not high enough to meet my rage—</l>
                  <l>D'ee ſmile?</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Col.</speaker>
                  <l>This noiſe is worth it, Gentlemen;</l>
                  <l>I'm ſorry this great Soldier has engag'd</l>
                  <l>Your travel, all his buſineſs is to talk.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Her.</speaker>
                  <l>A little of your Lordſhips patience,</l>
                  <l>You ſhall have other ſport, and ſwords that will</l>
                  <l>Be as nimble 'bout your heart, as you can wiſh,</l>
                  <l>'Tis pity more than our two ſingle lives,</l>
                  <l>Should be at ſtake.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Colon.</speaker>
                  <l>Make that no ſcruple Sir.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Her.</speaker>
                  <l>To him then that ſurvives if fate allow</l>
                  <pb facs="tcp:153343:30"/>
                  <l>That difference, I ſpeak that he may tell</l>
                  <l>The World, I came not hither on ſlight anger,</l>
                  <l>But to revenge my honour ſtain'd, and trampled on</l>
                  <l>By this proud man, when General, he commanded</l>
                  <l>My abſence from the field.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Colu.</speaker>
                  <l>I do remember,</l>
                  <l>And I'l give your Soul now a diſcharge.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Her.</speaker>
                  <l>I come to meet it, if your courage be ſo fortunate.</l>
                  <l>But there is more than my own injury</l>
                  <l>You muſt account for Sir, if my ſword proſper,</l>
                  <l>Whoſe point and every edge is made more keen</l>
                  <l>With young <hi>Alvarez</hi> blood, in which I had</l>
                  <l>A Noble intereſt; does not that ſin benum</l>
                  <l>Thy Arteries, and turn the guilty flowings,</l>
                  <l>To trembling gelly in thy veins? canſt hear</l>
                  <l>Me name that murder, and thy ſpirits not</l>
                  <l>Struck into air, as thou wert ſhot by ſome</l>
                  <l>Engin from heaven?</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Col.</speaker>
                  <l>You are the Dutcheſs Champion;</l>
                  <l>Thou haſt given me a quarrell now; I grieve</l>
                  <l>It is determin'd all muſt fight, and I</l>
                  <l>Shall loſe much honour in his fall.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Her.</speaker>
                  <l>That Dutcheſs</l>
                  <l>(Whom but to mention with thy breath, is ſacrilege)</l>
                  <l>An Orphan of thy making, and condemn'd</l>
                  <l>By thee to eternall ſolitude, I come</l>
                  <l>To vindicate, and while I am killing thee,</l>
                  <l>By virtue of her prayers ſent up for juſtice,</l>
                  <l>At the ſame time, in heaven I am pardon'd for't.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Col.</speaker>
                  <l>I cannot hear the Bravo.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Her.</speaker>
                  <l>Two words more</l>
                  <l>And take your chance, before you all I muſt</l>
                  <l>Pronounce that noble Lady, without knowledge,</l>
                  <l>Or thought of what I undertake for her.</l>
                  <l>Poor ſoul, Shees now at her Devotions,</l>
                  <l>Buſie with heaven, and wearing out the earth</l>
                  <pb n="51" facs="tcp:153343:30"/>
                  <l>With her ſtiff Knees, and bribing her good Angel</l>
                  <l>With treaſures of her eys, to tell her Lord</l>
                  <l>How much ſhe longs to ſee him; my attempt</l>
                  <l>Needs no commiſſion from her, were I</l>
                  <l>A ſtranger in <hi>Navarre,</hi> the inborn right</l>
                  <l>Of every Gentleman to <hi>Alvarez</hi> loſs,</l>
                  <l>Is reaſon to engage their ſwords, and lives,</l>
                  <l>Againſt the common enemy of virtue.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Colu.</speaker>
                  <l>Now have you finiſh'd? I have an inſtrument</l>
                  <l>Shall cure this noiſe, and fly up to thy tongue,</l>
                  <l>To murder all thy words.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Her.</speaker>
                  <l>One little knot</l>
                  <l>Of phlegm that clogs my ſtomach, and I ba' done;</l>
                  <l>You have an Uncle call'd a Cardinal</l>
                  <l>Would he were lurking now about thy heart,</l>
                  <l>That the ſame wounds might reach you both, and ſend</l>
                  <l>Your reeling ſouls together. Now have at you.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Alph.</speaker>
                  <l>We muſt not Sir be idle.</l>
               </sp>
               <stage>They fight, Colum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bo's Second ſiain.</stage>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Her.</speaker>
                  <l>What think you now of praying?</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Colu.</speaker>
                  <l>Time enough;</l>
                  <stage>He kills Hernando's Second.</stage>
                  <l>Commend me to my friend; the ſcales are even,</l>
                  <l>I would be mercifull, and give you time,</l>
                  <l>Now to conſider of the other World,</l>
                  <l>You'l find your ſoul benighted preſently.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Her.</speaker>
                  <l>I'l find my way i'th' dark.</l>
               </sp>
               <stage>They fight, and cloſe, Columbo gets both the ſwords, and Hernando takes up the ſeconds Weapon.</stage>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Colu</speaker>
                  <l>A ſtumble's dangerous.</l>
                  <l>Now ask thy life—Ha?</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Her.</speaker>
                  <l>I deſpiſe to wear it,</l>
                  <l>A gift from any but the firſt beſtower.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Col.</speaker>
                  <l>I ſcorn a baſe advantage—ha.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Her.</speaker>
                  <l>I am now</l>
                  <l>Out of your debt.</l>
               </sp>
               <stage>Columbo throwes away one of the ſwords. They fight, Hernando wounds Columbo.</stage>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Col.</speaker>
                  <l>Th'aſt don't, and I forgive thee.</l>
                  <l>Give me thy hand, when ſhall we meet again?</l>
               </sp>
               <pb facs="tcp:153343:31"/>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Her.</speaker>
                  <l>Never, I hope.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Col.</speaker>
                  <l>I feel life ebb apace, yet I'l look upwards,</l>
                  <l>And ſhew my face to heaven.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Her.</speaker>
                  <l>The matters done,</l>
                  <l>I muſt not ſtay to bury him.</l>
               </sp>
               <stage>Exit.</stage>
            </div>
            <div n="5" type="act">
               <head>ACT V.</head>
               <stage>Enter two Lords.</stage>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>1 <hi>Lord.</hi>
                  </speaker>
                  <l>
                     <hi>COlumbo</hi>'s death doth much aflict the King.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>2 <hi>Lo.</hi>
                  </speaker>
                  <l>I thought the Cardinal would have loſt his wits</l>
                  <l>At firſt, for's nephew, it drownes all the talk</l>
                  <l>Of the other that were ſlain.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>1</speaker>
                  <l>We are friends.</l>
                  <l>I do ſuſpect <hi>Hernando</hi> had ſome intereſt</l>
                  <l>And knew how their wounds came.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>2</speaker>
                  <l>His flight confirms it,</l>
                  <l>For whom the Cardinal has ſpread his nets.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>1</speaker>
                  <l>He is not ſo weak to truſt himſelf at home</l>
                  <l>To his Enemies gripe.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>2</speaker>
                  <l>All ſtrikes not me ſo much,</l>
                  <l>As that the Dutcheſs, moſt oppreſſed Lady,</l>
                  <l>Should be diſtracted, and before <hi>Columbo</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>Was ſlain.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>1</speaker>
                  <l>But that the Cardinal ſhould be made</l>
                  <l>Her Guardian, is to me above that wonder.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>2</speaker>
                  <l>So it pleas'd the King, and ſhe, with that ſmall ſtock</l>
                  <l>Of reaſon left her, is ſo kind, and ſmooth</l>
                  <l>Upon him.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>1</speaker>
                  <l>She's turn'd a child agen; a madneſs,</l>
                  <l>That would ha' made her brain and blood boil high</l>
                  <pb n="53" facs="tcp:153343:31"/>
                  <l>In which diſtemper ſhe might ha' wrought ſomething.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>2</speaker>
                  <l>Had been to purpoſe.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>1</speaker>
                  <l>The Cardinal is cunning, and how e'r</l>
                  <l>His brow does ſmile, he does ſuſpect <hi>Hernando</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>Took fire from her, and waits a time to puniſh it.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>2</speaker>
                  <l>But what a ſubject of diſgrace, and mirth,</l>
                  <l>Hath poor <hi>Celinda</hi> made herſelf by pride,</l>
                  <l>In her belief <hi>Columbo</hi> was her ſervant.</l>
                  <l>Her head hath ſtoop'd much ſince he died, and ſhe</l>
                  <l>Almoſt ridiculous at Court.</l>
               </sp>
               <stage>Enter Cardinal, Antonelli, Servant.</stage>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>1.</speaker>
                  <l>The Cardinal</l>
                  <l>Is come into the Garden, now—</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Car.</speaker>
                  <l>Walk off,</l>
                  <l>It troubles me the Dutcheſs by her loſs</l>
                  <l>Of brain is now beneath my great revenge,</l>
                  <l>She is not capable to feel my anger,</l>
                  <l>Which like to unregarded thunder ſpent</l>
                  <l>In woods, and lightning aim'd at ſenſeleſs trees,</l>
                  <l>Muſt idly fall, and hurt her not, not to</l>
                  <l>That ſenſe her guilt deſerves a fatall ſtroke,</l>
                  <l>Without the knowledg for what crime to fright her,</l>
                  <l>When ſhe takes leave, and make her tug with death,</l>
                  <l>Untill her ſoul ſweat, is a Pidgeons torment,</l>
                  <l>And ſhe is ſent a babe to the other World,</l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Columbo</hi>'s death will not be ſatisfied,</l>
                  <l>And I but wound her with a two edg'd feather;</l>
                  <l>I muſt do more, I have all opportunity,</l>
                  <l>(She by the King now made my charge) but ſhe's</l>
                  <l>So much a turtle I ſhall loſe by killing her,</l>
                  <l>Perhaps do her a pleaſure, and preferment;</l>
                  <l>That muſt not be.</l>
               </sp>
               <stage>Enter Celinda with a Parchment.</stage>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Anto.</speaker>
                  <l>Is not this ſhe, that would be thought to have been</l>
                  <pb n="54" facs="tcp:153343:32"/>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Columbo</hi>'s Miſtreſs? Madam, his grace is private,</l>
                  <l>And would not be diſturb'd, you may diſpleaſe him.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Cel.</speaker>
                  <l>What will your worſhip wager that he ſhall</l>
                  <l>Be pleas'd again before we part.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Ant.</speaker>
                  <l>I'l ſay this Diamond Madam, 'gainſt a kiſs,</l>
                  <l>And truſt your ſelf to keep the ſtakes.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Cel.</speaker>
                  <l>'Tis done.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Ant.</speaker>
                  <l>I have long had an appetite to this Lady,</l>
                  <l>But the Lords keep her up ſo high— this toy</l>
                  <l>May bring her on.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Car.</speaker>
                  <l>This interruption taſts not of good manners.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Cel.</speaker>
                  <l>But where neceſſity my Lord compells,</l>
                  <l>The boldneſs may meet pardon, and when you</l>
                  <l>Have found my purpoſe, I may leſs appear</l>
                  <l>Unmannerly.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Car.</speaker>
                  <l>To th' buſineſs.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Cel.</speaker>
                  <l>It did pleaſe</l>
                  <l>Your Nephew, Sir, before his death to credit me</l>
                  <l>With ſo much honorable favour, I</l>
                  <l>Am come to tender to his neer'ſt of blood,</l>
                  <l>Your ſelf, what does remain a debt to him.</l>
                  <l>Not to delay your Grace with circumſtance,</l>
                  <l>That deed, if you accept, makes you my heir</l>
                  <l>Of no contemptible eſtate— this way</l>
                  <stage>He reads.</stage>
                  <l>Is only left to ty up ſcurrile tongues,</l>
                  <l>And ſaucy men, that ſince <hi>Columbo</hi>'s death</l>
                  <l>Venture to Libell on my pride, and folly;</l>
                  <l>His greatneſs, and this gift which I enjoy,</l>
                  <l>Still for my life, beyond which term; a Kingdom's,</l>
                  <l>Nothing, will curb the giddy ſpleens of men</l>
                  <l>That live on impudent rime, and railing at</l>
                  <l>Each wandering fame they catch.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Car.</speaker>
                  <l>Madam, this bounty</l>
                  <l>Will bind my gratitude and care to ſerve you.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Cel.</speaker>
                  <l>I am your Graces Servant.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Car.</speaker>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Antonelli,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <stage>Whiſper.</stage>
                  <pb n="55" facs="tcp:153343:32"/>
                  <l>And when this noble Lady viſits me</l>
                  <l>Let her not wait.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Cel.</speaker>
                  <l>What think you my Officious, Sir; his grace</l>
                  <l>Is pleas'd, you may conjecture? I may keep</l>
                  <l>Your Gem, the kiſs was never yours.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Ant.</speaker>
                  <l>Sweet Madam—</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Cel.</speaker>
                  <l>Talk if you dare, you know I muſt not wait,</l>
                  <l>And ſo farewell for this time.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Car.</speaker>
                  <l>'Tis in my brain already, and it formes</l>
                  <l>Apace, good, excellent revenge, and pleaſant!</l>
                  <l>She's now within my talons, 'tis too cheap</l>
                  <l>A ſatisfaction for <hi>Columbo</hi>'s death,</l>
                  <l>Only to kill her by ſoft charm or force,</l>
                  <l>I'l rifle firſt her darling chaſtity,</l>
                  <l>'Twil be after time enough to poyſon her,</l>
                  <l>And ſhe to th' world be thought her own deſtroyer.</l>
                  <l>As I will frame the circumſtance, this night</l>
                  <l>All may be finiſhed; for the Colonel,</l>
                  <l>Her agent in my Nephewes death (whom I</l>
                  <l>Diſturb'd at Counſell with her) I may reach him</l>
                  <l>Hereafter, and be Maſter of his fate.</l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>We ſtarve our Conſcience when we thrive in State.</hi>
                  </l>
               </sp>
               <stage>Exeunt.</stage>
               <stage>Enter Secretary, and Placentia.</stage>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Sec.</speaker>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Placentia,</hi> We two are only left</l>
                  <l>Of my Ladies Servants, let us be true</l>
                  <l>To her, and one another, and be ſure</l>
                  <l>When we are at prayers, to curſe the Cardinal.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Pla.</speaker>
                  <l>I pity my ſweet Lady.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Sec.</speaker>
                  <l>I pity her too, but am a little angry;</l>
                  <l>She might have found another time to loſe</l>
                  <l>Her wits.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Pla.</speaker>
                  <l>That I were a man?</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Sec.</speaker>
                  <l>What would'ſt thou do <hi>Placentia?</hi>
                  </l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>la.</speaker>
                  <l>I would revenge my Lady.</l>
               </sp>
               <pb n="56" facs="tcp:153343:33"/>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Sec.</speaker>
                  <l>'Tis better being a woman, thou mayſt do</l>
                  <l>Things that may proſper better, and the fruit</l>
                  <l>Be thy own another day.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Pla.</speaker>
                  <l>Your wit ſtill loves</l>
                  <l>To play the wanton.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Sec.</speaker>
                  <l>'Tis a ſad time <hi>Placentia,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>Some pleaſure would do well, the truth is, I</l>
                  <l>Am weary of my life, and I would have</l>
                  <l>One fit of mirth before I leave the world.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Pla.</speaker>
                  <l>Do not you bluſh to talk thus wildly?</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Sec.</speaker>
                  <l>'Tis good manners</l>
                  <l>To be a little mad after my Lady;</l>
                  <l>But I ha' done; who is with her now?</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Pla.</speaker>
                  <l>Madam <hi>Valeria.</hi>
                  </l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Sec.</speaker>
                  <l>Not <hi>Celinda?</hi> Ther's a Lady for my humour,</l>
                  <l>A pretty book of fleſh and blood, and well</l>
                  <l>Bound up, in a fair letter too; would I</l>
                  <l>Had her with all the Errata.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Pla.</speaker>
                  <l>She has not</l>
                  <l>An honorable Fame.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Sec.</speaker>
                  <l>Her Fame? that's nothing,</l>
                  <l>A littie ſtain, her wealth will fe<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ch again</l>
                  <l>The colour, and bring honour into her cheeks</l>
                  <l>As freſh; if ſhe were mine, and I had her</l>
                  <l>Exchequer. I know the way to make her honeſt,</l>
                  <l>Honeſt to th' touch, the teſt, and the laſt tryall.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Pla.</speaker>
                  <l>How Prethee?</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Sec.</speaker>
                  <l>Why, firſt I would marry her, that's a verb Materiall;</l>
                  <l>Then I would Print her with an <hi>Index.</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Expurgatorius,</hi> a table drawn</l>
                  <l>Of her Court Hereſies, and when ſhe's read</l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Cum Privilegio,</hi> who dares call her Whore?</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Pla.</speaker>
                  <l>I'l leave you, if you talk thus.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Sec.</speaker>
                  <l>I ha' done,</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Placentia,</speaker>
                  <l>thou may'ſt be better company</l>
                  <l>After another progreſs; and now tell me,</l>
                  <pb n="57" facs="tcp:153343:33"/>
                  <l>Did'ſt ever hear of ſuch a patient madneſs</l>
                  <l>As my Lady is poſſeſt with? ſhe has rav'd</l>
                  <l>But twice; and ſhe would fright the Cardinall,</l>
                  <l>Or at a ſupper if ſhe did but poyſon him,</l>
                  <l>It were a phrenſy I could bear withall;</l>
                  <l>She calls him her dear Governour—</l>
               </sp>
               <stage>Enter Hernando diſguiſed having a Letter.</stage>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Pla.</speaker>
                  <l>Who is this?</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Her.</speaker>
                  <l>Her Secretary? Sir,</l>
                  <l>Here is a Letter if it may have ſo</l>
                  <l>Much happineſs to kiſs her Graces hand.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Sec.</speaker>
                  <l>From whom?</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Her.</speaker>
                  <l>That's not in your Commiſſion Sir</l>
                  <l>To ask, or mine to ſatisfie, ſhe will want</l>
                  <l>No underſtanding when ſhe reads.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Sec.</speaker>
                  <l>Alas,</l>
                  <l>Under your favour Sir, you are miſtaken,</l>
                  <l>Her Grace did never more want underſtanding.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Her.</speaker>
                  <l>How?</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Sec.</speaker>
                  <l>have you not heard, her ſcull is broken Sir</l>
                  <l>And many pieces taken out, ſhe's mad.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Her.</speaker>
                  <l>The ſad fame of her diſtraction</l>
                  <l>Has two much truth it ſeems.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Pla.</speaker>
                  <l>If pleaſe you Sir</l>
                  <l>To expect a while, I will preſent the Letter.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Her.</speaker>
                  <l>Pray do</l>
                  <stage>Exit Placen.</stage>
                  <l>How long has ſhe been thus Diſtemper'd Sir?</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Sec.</speaker>
                  <l>Before the Cardinal came to govern here,</l>
                  <l>Who for that reaſon by the King was made</l>
                  <l>Her Guardian, we are now at his devotion.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Her.</speaker>
                  <l>A Lamb given up to a Tyger! may diſeaſes</l>
                  <l>Soon eat him through his heart!</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Sec.</speaker>
                  <l>Your pardon Sir,</l>
                  <l>I love that voice, I know it too, a little,</l>
                  <l>Are not you? be not angry noble Sir,</l>
                  <pb n="58" facs="tcp:153343:34"/>
                  <l>I can with eaſe be ignorant agen,</l>
                  <l>And think you are another man, but if</l>
                  <l>You be that valiant Gentleman they call —</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Her.</speaker>
                  <l>Whom? What?</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Sec.</speaker>
                  <l>That kill'd, I would not name him if I thought</l>
                  <l>You were not pleas'd to be that very Gentleman.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Her.</speaker>
                  <l>Am I betraid?</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Sec.</speaker>
                  <l>The Devil ſha'not</l>
                  <l>Betray you here, kill me, and I will take</l>
                  <l>My death you are the Noble Colonel;</l>
                  <l>We are all bound to you for the Generals death,</l>
                  <l>Valiant <hi>Hernando?</hi> when my Lady knows</l>
                  <l>You are here, I hope 'twil fetch her wits agen,</l>
                  <l>But do not talk too loud, we are not all</l>
                  <l>Honeſt i'th' houſe, ſome are the Cardinals creatures.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Her.</speaker>
                  <l>Thou wert faithfull to thy Lady, I am glad</l>
                  <l>'Tis night, but tell me how the Churchman uſes</l>
                  <l>The Dutcheſs?</l>
               </sp>
               <stage>Enter Antonelli.</stage>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Sec.</speaker>
                  <l>He carries Angels in his tongue, and face, but I</l>
                  <l>Suſpect his heart, this is one of his ſpawns.</l>
                  <l>Signior <hi>Antonelli.</hi>
                  </l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Ant.</speaker>
                  <l>Honeſt <hi>Antonio.</hi>
                  </l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Sec.</speaker>
                  <l>And how, and how—a friend of mine, where is</l>
                  <l>The Cardinals Grace?</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Her.</speaker>
                  <l>That will be never anſwered.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Aut.</speaker>
                  <l>He means to ſup here with the Dutcheſs.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Sec.</speaker>
                  <l>Will he?</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Ant.</speaker>
                  <l>We'l have the charming bottles at my chamber,</l>
                  <l>Bring that Gentleman, we'l be mighty merry.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Her.</speaker>
                  <l>I may diſturb your jollity.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Ant.</speaker>
                  <l>Farewell ſweet—</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Sec.</speaker>
                  <l>Dear <hi>Antonelli—</hi> a round Pox confound you.</l>
                  <l>This is Court Retorick at the back ſtairs.</l>
               </sp>
               <pb n="59" facs="tcp:153343:34"/>
               <stage>Enter Placentia.</stage>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Pla.</speaker>
                  <l>Do you know this Gentleman?</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Sec.</speaker>
                  <l>Not I.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Pla.</speaker>
                  <l>My Lady preſently diſmiſt <hi>Valeria,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>And bad me bring him to her bed-chamber.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Sec.</speaker>
                  <l>The Gentleman has an honeſt face.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Pla.</speaker>
                  <l>Her words fell from her with ſome evenneſs &amp; joy.</l>
                  <l>Her Grace deſires your preſence.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Her.</speaker>
                  <l>I'l attend her.</l>
               </sp>
               <stage>Exit.</stage>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Sec.</speaker>
                  <l>I would this Soldier had the Cardinal</l>
                  <l>Upon a promontory, with what a ſpring</l>
                  <l>The Churchman would leap down, it were a ſpectacle</l>
                  <l>Moſt rare to ſee him topple from the precipice,</l>
                  <l>And ſouſe in the ſalt water with a noiſe</l>
                  <l>To ſtun the fiſhes; and if he fell into</l>
                  <l>A net, what wonder would the ſimple Sea-guls</l>
                  <l>Have, to draw up the o'rgrown Lobſter,</l>
                  <l>So ready boild? he ſhall have my good wiſhes,</l>
                  <l>This Colonels coming may be lucky. I</l>
                  <l>Will be ſure none ſhall interrupt 'em.</l>
               </sp>
               <stage>Enter Celinda.</stage>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Cel.</speaker>
                  <l>Is her Grace at opportunity?</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Sec.</speaker>
                  <l>No ſweet Madam,</l>
                  <l>She is a ſleep, her Gentlewoman ſays.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Cel.</speaker>
                  <l>My buſineſs is but viſit, I'l expect.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Sec.</speaker>
                  <l>That muſt not be, although I like your company.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Cel.</speaker>
                  <l>You are grown rich Mr. Secretary.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Sec.</speaker>
                  <l>I Madam, Alas!</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Cel.</speaker>
                  <l>I hear you are upon another purchaſe.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Sec.</speaker>
                  <l>I upon a purchaſe?</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Cel.</speaker>
                  <l>If you want any ſum —</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Sec.</speaker>
                  <l>If I could purchaſe your ſweet favour Madam?</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Cel.</speaker>
                  <l>You ſhall command me, and my fortune Sir.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Sec.</speaker>
                  <l>How's this?</l>
               </sp>
               <pb n="60" facs="tcp:153343:35"/>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Cel.</speaker>
                  <l>I have obſerv'd you Sir a ſtaid,</l>
                  <l>And prudent Gentleman— and I ſhall want—</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Sec.</speaker>
                  <l>Not me?</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Cel.</speaker>
                  <l>A Father for ſome Infant; he has credit</l>
                  <stage>Aſide.</stage>
                  <l>Ith' world; I am not the firſt caſt Lady</l>
                  <l>Has married a Secretary.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Sec.</speaker>
                  <l>Shall I wait upon you?</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Cel.</speaker>
                  <l>Whither?</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Sec.</speaker>
                  <l>Any whither.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Cel.</speaker>
                  <l>I may chance lead you then—</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Sec.</speaker>
                  <l>I ſhall be honour'd to obey, my blood</l>
                  <l>Is up, and in this humour I'm for any thing.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Cel.</speaker>
                  <l>Well Sir, I'l try your Manhood.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Sec.</speaker>
                  <l>'Tis my happineſs,</l>
                  <l>You cannot pleaſe me better.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Cel.</speaker>
                  <l>This was ſtruck</l>
                  <l>I'th' opportunity.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Sec.</speaker>
                  <l>I am made for ever.</l>
               </sp>
               <stage>Enter Hernando, and Dutcheſs.</stage>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Her.</speaker>
                  <l>Dear Madam, do not weep.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Dut.</speaker>
                  <l>Y'are very welcome,</l>
                  <l>I ha done, I wo'not ſhed a tear more</l>
                  <l>Till I meet <hi>Alvarez,</hi> then I'l weep for joy;</l>
                  <l>He was a fine young Gentleman, and ſung ſweetly,</l>
                  <l>And you had heard him but the night before</l>
                  <l>We were married, you would ha' ſworn he had been</l>
                  <l>A Swan, and ſung his own ſad Epitaph;</l>
                  <l>But we'l talk o'the Cardinal.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Her.</speaker>
                  <l>Would his death</l>
                  <l>Might ranſom your fair ſenſe, he ſhould not live</l>
                  <l>To triumph in the loſs, beſhrow my manhood;</l>
                  <l>But I begin to melt.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Dut.</speaker>
                  <l>I pray Sir tell me,</l>
                  <l>For I can underſtand, although they ſay</l>
                  <l>I have loſt my wits; but they are ſafe enough,</l>
                  <pb n="61" facs="tcp:153343:35"/>
                  <l>And I ſhall have 'em when the Cardinal dyes;</l>
                  <l>Who had a Letter from his Nephew too</l>
                  <l>Since he was ſlain.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Her.</speaker>
                  <l>From whence?</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Dut.</speaker>
                  <l>I know not where he is? but in ſome Bower</l>
                  <l>Within a Garden he is making Chaplets,</l>
                  <l>And means to ſend me one, but I'l not take it,</l>
                  <l>I have flowers enough I thank him while I live.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Her.</speaker>
                  <l>But do you love your Governour?</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Dut.</speaker>
                  <l>Yes, but I'l never marry him, I am promis'd</l>
                  <l>Already.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Her.</speaker>
                  <l>To whom Madam?</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Dut.</speaker>
                  <l>Do not you</l>
                  <l>Bluſh when you ask me that, muſt not you be</l>
                  <l>My Husband? I know why, but that's a ſecret;</l>
                  <l>Indeed if you believe me, I do love</l>
                  <l>No man alive ſo well as you, the Cardinal</l>
                  <l>Shall never know't, hee'l kill us both, and yet</l>
                  <l>He ſays he loves me dearly, and has promis'd</l>
                  <l>To make me well again, but I'm afraid,</l>
                  <l>One time or other he will give me poyſon.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Her.</speaker>
                  <l>Prevent him Madam, and take nothing from him.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Dut.</speaker>
                  <l>Why, do you think 'twil hurt me?</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Her.</speaker>
                  <l>It will kill you.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Dut.</speaker>
                  <l>I ſhall but dye, and meet my dear lov'd Lord,</l>
                  <l>Whom when I have kiſt, I'l come again, and work</l>
                  <l>A bracelet of my hair for you to carry him,</l>
                  <l>When you are going to heaven, the poeſy ſhall</l>
                  <l>Be my own name, in little tears, that I</l>
                  <l>Will weep next winter, which congeal'd i'th' froſt</l>
                  <l>Will ſhew like ſeed-Pearl, you'l deliver it?</l>
                  <l>I know he'l love, and wear it for my ſake.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Her.</speaker>
                  <l>She is quite loſt.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Dut.</speaker>
                  <l>I pray give me Sir, your pardon,</l>
                  <l>I know I talk not wiſely, but if you had</l>
                  <l>The burthen of my ſorrow, you would miſs</l>
                  <pb n="62" facs="tcp:153343:36"/>
                  <l>Sometimes your better reaſon; now l'm well,</l>
                  <l>What will you do when the Cardinal comes?</l>
                  <l>He muſt not ſee you for the world.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Her.</speaker>
                  <l>He ſha'not,</l>
                  <l>I'l take my leave before he come.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Dut.</speaker>
                  <l>Nay ſtay,</l>
                  <l>I ſhall have no friend left me when you go,</l>
                  <l>He will but ſup, he ſha'not ſtay to ly wi' me,</l>
                  <l>I have the picture of my Lord abed,</l>
                  <l>Three are to much this weather.</l>
               </sp>
               <stage>Enter Plecentia.</stage>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Pla.</speaker>
                  <l>Madam, the Cardinal.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Her.</speaker>
                  <l>He ſhall ſup with the Devil.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Dut.</speaker>
                  <l>I dare not ſtay,</l>
                  <l>The Red-cock will be angry, I'l come agen.</l>
               </sp>
               <stage>Exeunt.</stage>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Her.</speaker>
                  <l>This ſorrow is no fable, now I find</l>
                  <l>My curioſity is ſadly ſatisfied;</l>
                  <l>Ha? if the Dutcheſs in her ſtragled wits,</l>
                  <l>Let fall words to betray me to the Cardinal,</l>
                  <l>The Panther will not leap more fierce to meet</l>
                  <l>His prey, when a long want of food hath parch'd</l>
                  <l>His ſtarved maw, than he to print his rage</l>
                  <l>And tear my heart-ſtrings, every thing is fatall,</l>
                  <l>And yet ſhe talk'd ſometimes with chain of ſenſe,</l>
                  <l>And ſaid ſhe lov'd me; ha, they come not yet;</l>
                  <l>I have a ſword about me, and I left</l>
                  <l>My own ſecurity to viſit death.</l>
                  <l>Yet I may pauſe a little, and conſider</l>
                  <l>Which way does lead me to't moſt honorably;</l>
                  <l>Does not the Chamber that I walk in tremble?</l>
                  <l>What will become of her, and me, and all</l>
                  <l>The world in one ſmall hour? I do not think</l>
                  <l>Ever to ſee the day agen, the wings</l>
                  <l>Of night ſpread o'r me like a ſable Herſe-cloath,</l>
                  <l>The Stars are all cloſe mourners too; but I</l>
                  <l>Muſt not alone to the cold ſilent grave,</l>
                  <l>I muſt not; If thou canſt <hi>Alvarez</hi> open</l>
                  <pb n="63" facs="tcp:153343:36"/>
                  <l>That Ebon curtain, and behold the man,</l>
                  <l>When the worlds juſtice fails ſhall right thy aſhes,</l>
                  <l>And feed their thirſt with blood, thy Dutcheſs is</l>
                  <l>Almoſt a Ghoſt already; and doth wear</l>
                  <l>Her body like a uſeleſs upper garment,</l>
                  <l>The trim and faſhion of it loſt. Ha?</l>
               </sp>
               <stage>Enter Placentia.</stage>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Pla.</speaker>
                  <l>You need not doubt me, Sir, My Lady prays</l>
                  <l>You would not think it long, ſhe in my ear,</l>
                  <l>Commanded me to tell you, that when laſt</l>
                  <l>She drank, ſhe had happy wiſhes to your health.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Her.</speaker>
                  <l>And did the Cardinal pledge it?</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Pla.</speaker>
                  <l>He was not</l>
                  <l>Invited to't, nor muſt he know you are here.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Her.</speaker>
                  <l>What do they talk of prethee?</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Pla.</speaker>
                  <l>His Grace is very pleaſant</l>
                  <stage>A Lute is heard.</stage>
                  <l>And kind to her, but her returns are after</l>
                  <l>The ſad condition of her ſenſe, ſometimes unjoynted.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Her.</speaker>
                  <l>They have Muſick.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Pla.</speaker>
                  <l>A Lute only,</l>
                  <l>His Grace prepard, they ſay, the beſt of <hi>Italy</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>That waits upon my Lord.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Her.</speaker>
                  <l>He thinks the Dutcheſs</l>
                  <l>Is ſtung with a Tarantula.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Pla.</speaker>
                  <l>Your pardon.</l>
                  <l>My duty is expected.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Her.</speaker>
                  <l>Gentle Lady.—a voice too?</l>
                  <lg>
                     <head>Song within.</head>
                     <l>S. <hi>Come my</hi> Daphne, <hi>come away,</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>We do waſt the Cryſtal day;</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>'Tis</hi> Strephon <hi>calls.</hi> Da <hi>What ſays my love?</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>S. <hi>Come follow to the Mirtle Grove,</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Where</hi> Venus <hi>ſhall prepare</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>New Chaplets for thy hair.</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>D. <hi>Were I ſhut up within a Tree,</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>I'd rend my bark to follow thee.</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>S. <hi>My Shepherdeſs, make haſt,</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>The minutes ſlide too faſt:</hi>
                     </l>
                     <pb n="64" facs="tcp:153343:37"/>
                     <l>D. <hi>In thoſe cooler ſhades will I</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Blind, as</hi> Cupid, kiſs thine ey.</l>
                     <l>S. <hi>In thy boſome then I'l ſtay,</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>In ſuch warm Snow who would not loſe his way.</hi>
                     </l>
                     <stage>Chor.</stage>
                     <l>
                        <hi>WE'l laugh and leave the world behind,</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>And Gods themſelves that ſee,</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Shall envy thee, and me;</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>But never find</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Such joys, when they embrace a Deity.</hi>
                     </l>
                  </lg>
                  <l>If at this diſtance I diſtinguiſh, 'tis not</l>
                  <l>Church muſick, and the air's wanton, and no Anthem</l>
                  <l>Sung to't, but ſome ſtrange Ode of love, and kiſſes,</l>
                  <l>What ſhould this mean?— ha, he is coming hither,</l>
                  <l>I am betraid, he marches in her hand,</l>
                  <l>I'l truſt a little more, mute as the Arras</l>
                  <l>My ſword and I here.</l>
               </sp>
               <stage>He obſerves</stage>
               <stage>Enter Cardival, Dutcheſs, Antonelli, and Attendants.</stage>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Car.</speaker>
                  <l>Wait you in the firſt Chamber, and let none</l>
                  <l>Preſume to interrupt us.</l>
                  <stage>Ex. Serv.</stage>
                  <l>She is pleaſant; now for ſome art to poyſon all her inno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cence.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Dut.</speaker>
                  <l>I do not like the Cardinals humour, he</l>
                  <l>Little ſuſpects what gueſt is in my Chamber.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Car.</speaker>
                  <l>Now Madam you are ſafe.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Dut.</speaker>
                  <l>How means your Lordſhip?</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Car.</speaker>
                  <l>Safe in my Arms, ſweet Dutcheſs.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Dut.</speaker>
                  <l>Do not hurt me.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Car.</speaker>
                  <l>Not for the treaſures of the world, you are</l>
                  <l>My pretty charge, had I as many lives</l>
                  <l>As I have carefull thoughts, to do you ſervice,</l>
                  <l>I ſhould think all a happy forfeit to</l>
                  <l>Delight your Grace one minute; 'tis a heaven</l>
                  <l>To ſee you ſmile.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Dut.</speaker>
                  <l>What kindneſs call you this?</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Car.</speaker>
                  <l>It cannot want a name while you preſerve</l>
                  <l>So plentifull a ſweetneſs, it is love.</l>
               </sp>
               <pb n="65" facs="tcp:153343:37"/>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Dut.</speaker>
                  <l>Of me? how ſhall I know't my Lord?</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Car.</speaker>
                  <l>By this, and this, ſwift Meſſengers to whiſper</l>
                  <l>Our hearts to one another.</l>
               </sp>
               <stage>Kiſſes.</stage>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Dut.</speaker>
                  <l>Pray do you come a wooing?</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Car.</speaker>
                  <l>Yes ſweet Madam,</l>
                  <l>You cannot be ſo cruell to deny me.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Dut.</speaker>
                  <l>What my Lord?</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Car.</speaker>
                  <l>Another kiſs.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Dut.</speaker>
                  <l>Can you</l>
                  <l>Diſpenſe with this my Lord? Alas I fear</l>
                  <stage>Aſide.</stage>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Hernando</hi> is aſleep, or vaniſh'd from me.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Car.</speaker>
                  <l>I have mock'd my blood into a flame, and what</l>
                  <l>My angry ſoul had form'd for my revenge,</l>
                  <l>Is now the object of my amorous ſenſe,</l>
                  <l>I have took a ſtrong inchantment from her lips,</l>
                  <l>And fear I ſhall forgive <hi>Columbo's</hi> death</l>
                  <l>If She conſent to my embrace; come Madam.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Dut.</speaker>
                  <l>Whither my Lord?</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Car.</speaker>
                  <l>But to your bed or couch,</l>
                  <l>Where if you will be kind, and but allow</l>
                  <l>Your ſelf a knowledg, love whoſe ſhape and raptures</l>
                  <l>Wiſe Poets have but glorified in dreams,</l>
                  <l>Shall make your chamber his eternall Palace;</l>
                  <l>And with ſuch active and eſſentiall ſtreams</l>
                  <l>Of new delights glide o'r your boſome, you</l>
                  <l>Shall wonder to what unknown world you are</l>
                  <l>By ſome bleſt change tranſlated; why d'e pauſe?</l>
                  <l>And look ſo wild? will you deny your Governour?</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Dut.</speaker>
                  <l>How came you by that Cloven foot?</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Car.</speaker>
                  <l>Your fancy</l>
                  <l>Would turn a traitour to your happineſs;</l>
                  <l>I am your friend, you muſt be kind.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Dut.</speaker>
                  <l>Unhand me,</l>
                  <l>Or I'l cry out a rape.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Car.</speaker>
                  <l>You wo'not ſure?</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Dut.</speaker>
                  <l>I have been cozend with <hi>Hernando's</hi> ſhadow,</l>
                  <l>Here's none but heaven to hear me, help, a rape,</l>
               </sp>
               <pb n="66" facs="tcp:153343:38"/>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Car.</speaker>
                  <l>Are you ſo good at underſtanding then,</l>
                  <l>I muſt uſe other argument.</l>
               </sp>
               <stage>He forces her.</stage>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Her.</speaker>
                  <l>Go to, Cardinal.</l>
               </sp>
               <stage>Strikes him. Ex. Dut.</stage>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Car.</speaker>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Hernando,</hi> Murder, Treaſon, help.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Her.</speaker>
                  <l>An army ſha'not reſcue thee, your blood</l>
                  <l>Is much inflam'd, I have brought a Lancet wi'me,</l>
                  <l>Shall open your hot veins, and cool your fever;</l>
                  <l>To vex thy parting Soul, it was the ſame</l>
                  <l>Engin that pinc'd <hi>Columbo's</hi> heart.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Car.</speaker>
                  <l>Help, Murder.</l>
               </sp>
               <stage>Enter Antonelli and Servants.</stage>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Anton.</speaker>
                  <l>Some ring the bell, 'twil raiſe the Court,</l>
                  <l>My Lord is murder'd, 'tis <hi>Hernando.</hi>
                  </l>
               </sp>
               <stage>The bell rings.</stage>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Her.</speaker>
                  <l>I'l make you all ſome ſport,—So, now we are even,</l>
                  <l>Where is the Dutcheſs, I would take my leave</l>
                  <l>Of her, and then bequeath my curſe among you.</l>
               </sp>
               <stage>Her. ſalls.</stage>
               <stage>Enter King, Dutcheſs, Valeria, Lords, Guard.</stage>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>K.</speaker>
                  <l>How come theſe bloody objects?</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Her.</speaker>
                  <l>With a trick my ſword found out, I hope he's paid.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>1 <hi>Lo</hi>
                  </speaker>
                  <l>I hope ſo to; a Surgeon for my Lord Cardinal.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>K.</speaker>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Hernando?</hi>
                  </l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Dut.</speaker>
                  <l>Iuſtice, Oh Iuſtice Sir, againſt a raviſher.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Her.</speaker>
                  <l>Sir I ha' done you ſervice.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>K.</speaker>
                  <l>A bloody ſervice.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Her.</speaker>
                  <l>'Tis pure Searlet.</l>
               </sp>
               <stage>Enter Surgeon.</stage>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Car.</speaker>
                  <l>After ſuch care to perfect my revenge</l>
                  <l>Thus banded out o'th' world by a womans plot?</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Her.</speaker>
                  <l>I have preſerv'd the Dutcheſs from a rape,</l>
                  <l>Good-night to me and all the world for ever.</l>
               </sp>
               <stage>Dies.</stage>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>K.</speaker>
                  <l>So impious.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Dut.</speaker>
                  <l>'Tis moſt true, <hi>Alvarez</hi> blood</l>
                  <l>Is now reveng'd, I find my brain return,</l>
                  <l>And every ſtragling ſenſe repairing home.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Car.</speaker>
                  <l>I have deſerv'd you ſhould turn from me Sir,</l>
                  <l>My life hath been prodigiouſly wicked,</l>
                  <pb n="67" facs="tcp:153343:38"/>
                  <l>My blood is now the Kingdoms balm; oh Sir,</l>
                  <l>I have abu'd your ear, your truſt, your people,</l>
                  <l>And my own ſacred Office, my conſcience</l>
                  <l>Feels now the ſting, oh ſhew your charity,</l>
                  <l>And with your pardon like a cool ſoft gale</l>
                  <l>Fan my poor ſweating ſoul; that wanders through</l>
                  <l>Unhabitable climes, and parched deſerts;</l>
                  <l>But I am loſt, if the great World forgive me,</l>
                  <l>Unleſs I find your mercy for a crime</l>
                  <l>You know not Madam, yet againſt your life.</l>
                  <l>I muſt confeſs, more than my black intents</l>
                  <l>Upon your honour, y'are already poyſon'd.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>K.</speaker>
                  <l>By whom?</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Car.</speaker>
                  <l>By me,</l>
                  <l>In the revenge I ow'd <hi>Columbo</hi>'s loſs,</l>
                  <l>With your laſt meat was mixt a poyſon that</l>
                  <l>By ſubtle, and by ſure degrees muſt let in death.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>K.</speaker>
                  <l>Look to the Dutcheſs, our Phyſicians?</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Car.</speaker>
                  <l>Stay, I will deſerve her mercy, though I cannot</l>
                  <l>Call back the deed, in proof of my repentance,</l>
                  <l>If the laſt breath of a now dying man</l>
                  <l>May gain your charity, and belief, receive</l>
                  <l>This Ivory box, in it an antidote</l>
                  <l>'Bove that they boaſt the great magiſtrall medicine,</l>
                  <l>That pouder mixt with wine by a moſt rare</l>
                  <l>And quick acceſs to the heart will fortifie it</l>
                  <l>Againſt the rage of the moſt nimble poyſon,</l>
                  <l>I am not worthy to preſent her with it,</l>
                  <l>Oh take it and preſerve her innocent life.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>1 <hi>Lo.</hi>
                  </speaker>
                  <l>Strange, he ſhould have a good thing in ſuch readyneſs.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Car.</speaker>
                  <l>This that which in my jealouſie and ſtate</l>
                  <l>Truſting to falſe predictions of my birth,</l>
                  <l>That I ſh dy by poyſon, I preſerv'd</l>
                  <l>For my own ſafety, wonder not, I made,</l>
                  <l>That my companion was to be my reſuge.</l>
               </sp>
               <stage>Enter Servant with a bowle of Wine.</stage>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>1 <hi>Lo.</hi>
                  </speaker>
                  <l>Her's ſome touch of grace.</l>
               </sp>
               <pb n="68" facs="tcp:153343:39"/>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Car.</speaker>
                  <l>in greater proof of my pure thoughts I take</l>
                  <l>This firſt, and with my dying breath confirm</l>
                  <l>My penitence, it may benefit her life,</l>
                  <l>But not my wounds; oh haſten to preſerve her,</l>
                  <l>And though I merit not her pardon, let not</l>
                  <l>Her fair ſoul be divorc'd</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>K.</speaker>
                  <l>This is ſome charity, may it proſper Madam.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Valeria.</speaker>
                  <l>How does your grace?</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Dut.</speaker>
                  <l>And muſt I owe my life to him whoſe death</l>
                  <l>Was my ambition? take this free acknowledgment,</l>
                  <l>I had intent this night with my own hand</l>
                  <l>To be <hi>Alvarez</hi> luſticer.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>K.</speaker>
                  <l>You were mad,</l>
                  <l>And thought paſt apprehenſion of revenge.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Dut.</speaker>
                  <l>That ſhape I did uſurp, great Sir, to give</l>
                  <l>My Art more freedom and defence, but when</l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Hernando</hi> came to viſit me, I thought</l>
                  <l>I might defer my execution,</l>
                  <l>Which his owe rage ſuppli'd without my guilt,</l>
                  <l>And when his luſt grew high, met with his blood.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>1 <hi>Lo.</hi>
                  </speaker>
                  <l>The Cardial ſmiles.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Car.</speaker>
                  <l>Now my revenge has met</l>
                  <l>With you my nimble Dutcheſs, I have took</l>
                  <l>A ſhape to give my act more freedom too,</l>
                  <l>And now I am ſure ſhe's poyſon'd, with that doze</l>
                  <l>I gave her laſt.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>K.</speaker>
                  <l>Th'art not ſo horrid?</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Dut.</speaker>
                  <l>Ha! ſome Cordiall.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Car.</speaker>
                  <l>Alas no preſervative</l>
                  <l>Hath wings to overtake it, were her heart</l>
                  <l>Lock'd in a quarry, it would ſearch, and kill</l>
                  <l>Before the aids can reach it; I am ſure</l>
                  <l>You ſha not now laugh at me.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>K.</speaker>
                  <l>How came you by that poyſon?</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Car.</speaker>
                  <l>I prepar'd it,</l>
                  <l>Reſolving when I had enjoy'd her, which</l>
                  <pb n="69" facs="tcp:153343:39"/>
                  <l>The Colonel prevented, by ſome art</l>
                  <l>To make her take it, and by death conclude</l>
                  <l>My laſt revenge; you have the fatal Story.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>K.</speaker>
                  <l>This is ſo great a wickedneſs, it will</l>
                  <l>Exceed belief.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Car.</speaker>
                  <l>I knew I could not live.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Surgeon.</speaker>
                  <l>Your wounds, Sir, were not deſperate.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Car.</speaker>
                  <l>Not mortall? ha? were they not mortall?</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Surg.</speaker>
                  <l>If I have skill in Surgery.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Car.</speaker>
                  <l>Then I have caught my ſelf in my own Engin.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>2 <hi>Lo.</hi>
                  </speaker>
                  <l>It was your fate you ſaid to dy by poyſon.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Car.</speaker>
                  <l>That was my own prediction to abuſe</l>
                  <l>Your faith, no humane art can now reſiſt it,</l>
                  <l>I feel it knocking at the ſeat of life,</l>
                  <l>It muſt come in, I have wrackt all my own</l>
                  <l>To try your charities, new it would be rare,</l>
                  <l>If you but waft me with a little prayer,</l>
                  <l>My wings that flag may catch the wind, but 'tis</l>
                  <l>In vain, the miſt is riſen, and ther's none</l>
                  <l>To ſtear my wandring bark.</l>
               </sp>
               <stage>Dyes.</stage>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>1 <hi>Lo.</hi>
                  </speaker>
                  <l>He's dead?</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>K.</speaker>
                  <l>With him</l>
                  <l>Dy all deceived truſt.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>2 <hi>Lo.</hi>
                  </speaker>
                  <l>This was a ſtrange impiety.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>K.</speaker>
                  <l>When men</l>
                  <l>Of Gifts and ſacred Function once decline</l>
                  <l>From virtue, their ill deeds tranſcend example.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Dut.</speaker>
                  <l>The minute's come that I muſt take my leave too.</l>
                  <l>Your hand great Sir, and though you be a King,</l>
                  <l>We may exchange forgiveneſs, heaven forgive,</l>
                  <l>And all the world. I come, I come <hi>Alvarez</hi>
                  </l>
               </sp>
               <stage>Dyes.</stage>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>K.</speaker>
                  <l>Diſpoſe their bodies for becoming funeral;</l>
                  <l>How much are Kings abus'd by thoſe they take</l>
                  <l>To royall grace? whom when they cheriſh moſt</l>
                  <l>By nice indulgence, they doo often arm</l>
                  <l>Againſt themſelves; from whence this maxim ſprings,</l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>None have more need of Perſpectives than Kings.</hi>
                  </l>
                  <stage>Exeunt.</stage>
               </sp>
            </div>
         </div>
         <div type="epilogue">
            <pb facs="tcp:153343:40"/>
            <head>Epilogue.</head>
            <stage>Within.</stage>
            <p>Mr. <hi>Polla'd,</hi> wher's Mr. <hi>Pollard</hi> for the Epi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>logue?</p>
            <stage>He is thruſt upon the Stage, and falls.</stage>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Epilogue.</speaker>
               <l>
                  <hi>I Am coming to you Gentlemen, the Poet</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Has help'd me thus far on my way, but I'l</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Be even with him; the Play is a Tragedy,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>The firſt that ever he compos'd for us,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Wherein he thinks he has done pretily,</hi>
               </l>
               <stage>Enter Servant.</stage>
               <l>
                  <hi>And I am ſenſible; I prethee look</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Is nothing out of joynt? has he broke nothing?</hi>
               </l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Serv.</speaker>
               <l>
                  <hi>Nor Sir, I hope.</hi>
               </l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Epi.</speaker>
               <l>
                  <hi>Yes, he has broke his Epilogue all to peeces,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Canſt thou put it together agen?</hi>
               </l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Ser.</speaker>
               <l>
                  <hi>Not I Sir.</hi>
               </l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Epi.</speaker>
               <l>
                  <hi>Nor I, prethee be gone, hum? Mr. Poet,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>I have a teeming mind to be reveng'd.</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>You may aſſiſt, and not be ſeen in't now.</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>If you pleaſe Gentlemen, for I do know</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>He liſtens to the iſſue of his cauſe,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>But bliſter not your hands in his applauſe,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Your private ſmile, your nod, or hum, to tell</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>My fellows, that you like the buſineſs well;</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>And when without a clap you go away,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>I'l drink a ſmall-bear health to his ſecond day;</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>And break his heart, or make him ſwear, and rage,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>He'l write no more for the unhappy Stage;</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>But that's too much, ſo we ſhould loſe; faith ſhew it,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>And if you like his play, 'ts as well, he knew it.</hi>
               </l>
            </sp>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
      <back>
         <div type="publishers_note">
            <pb facs="tcp:153343:40"/>
            <head>A Catalogue of the Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thors Poems already Printed</head>
            <list>
               <head>Tragedies.</head>
               <item>
                  <hi>THe Traytour</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Philip Chabot Admirall of France</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Loves Cruelty</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>The Maids Revenge</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Dukes Miſtri;</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>The Cardinal.</hi>
               </item>
            </list>
            <list>
               <head>Comedies and Tragi-comedies.</head>
               <item>
                  <hi>The School of Complement</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>The Lady of Pleaſure</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Hide-parke</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>The Conſtant Maid.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <note n="*" place="margin">Falſely aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cribed to <hi>Jo. Fletcher.</hi>
                  </note> 
                  <hi>The Coronation</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>The Changes, or Love in a Maze</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>The Gratefull Servant</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>The Patron of Ireland</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>The Humorous Court</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>The wedding</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>The Ball, or French Dancing Master</hi>
               </item>
               <pb facs="tcp:153343:41" rendition="simple:additions"/>
               <item>
                  <hi>The Gameſter</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>The Example</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>The Bird in a cage</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>The Royall Maſter</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>The Opportunity</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>The Witty Faire one</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>The Impoſture</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>The Brothers</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>The Siſters.</hi>
               </item>
            </list>
            <p>
               <hi>A Maſque of the four Honorable Innes of Court, pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſented before the King and Queens Majesty at</hi> Whitehall <hi>in the Banqueting houſe.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Poems.</hi>
            </p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </back>
   </text>
</TEI>
