<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>The doubtful heir. A tragi-comedie, as it was acted at the private house in Black-Friers written by James Shirley. Never printed before.</title>
            <author>Shirley, James, 1596-1666.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1652</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 165 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 45 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2012-10">2012-10 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A93170</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing S3466</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R230285</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99895968</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99895968</idno>
            <idno type="VID">153589</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A93170)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 153589)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 2371:12)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>The doubtful heir. A tragi-comedie, as it was acted at the private house in Black-Friers written by James Shirley. Never printed before.</title>
                  <author>Shirley, James, 1596-1666.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[6], 74, [2] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>printed for Humphrey Robinson at the three Pigeons, and Humphrey Moseley at the Prince's Armes in St. Paul's Church-yard,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1652.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in the Folger Shakespeare Library, Washington, D.C..</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2011-06</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-06</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-07</date>
            <label>Judith Siefring</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-07</date>
            <label>Judith Siefring</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-05</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:153589:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:153589:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:153589:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:153589:2"/>
            <p>THE DOUBTFUL HEIR. A Tragi-comedie, AS It was Acted at the private Houſe IN <hi>BLACK-FRIERS,</hi> WRITTEN By JAMES SHIRLEY.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Never Printed before.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON,</hi> Printed for <hi>Humphrey Robinſon</hi> at the three Pi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geons, and <hi>Humphrey Moſeley</hi> at the Prince's Arms in St. <hi>Paul's</hi> Church-yard. 1652.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="dedication">
            <pb facs="tcp:153589:3"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:153589:3"/>
            <head>To the moſt worthily honored Sir <hi>Edmund Bowier.</hi>
            </head>
            <opener>
               <salute>SIR,</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">M</seg>Any years are vaniſhed, and a period, not onely of the Scene, but more conſiderable revoluti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons have paſs'd, ſince I had the happineſs to be firſt known to you. I read excellent Characters of you, when you writ but a ſmall Letter, and though my obſervati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, like ſeeds, were not cheriſhed (by the fault of time) to a maturity, yet they begat in me ſuch great reſpect to your perſon, then budding with honour, and expectation, that now after ſo long ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſence, I find them not extinguiſhed; and howſoever at the firſt complexion, I may appear bold, in this haſty interruption, yet your candour will be ſo far in my
<pb facs="tcp:153589:4"/>defence, that I have preſumed thus, ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther to let you know I can ſtill honour you, than unſatisfie my ſelf, by neglecting the firſt opportunity of preſenting my ſervice. Sir, it is a piece, which perhaps you have ſeen in the active repreſent<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment; the eſtimation it gained from thence, will be ſhort of that grace it ſhall derive from your acceptance, by which you will ſhew, how ſtill you dare re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain your nobleneſs, and by renewing your ſmile upon me, encourage me to write my ſelf</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>Your humble Servant, <hi>JA. SHIRLEY.</hi>
               </signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="prologue">
            <pb facs="tcp:153589:4"/>
            <head>Prologue.</head>
            <lg>
               <l>ALl that the Prologue comes for, is to ſay,</l>
               <l>Our Author did not calculate this Play</l>
               <l>For this Meridian; the Banckſide, he knows,</l>
               <l>Are far more skilfull at the Ebbes and flows</l>
               <l>Of water, than of wit, he did not mean</l>
               <l>For the elevation of your poles, this ſcene.</l>
               <l>No ſhews, no dance, and what you moſt delight in,</l>
               <l>Grave underſtanders, here's no target fighting</l>
               <l>Upon the Stage, all work for Cutlers barr'd,</l>
               <l>No bawdery, nor no Ballets; this goes hard;</l>
               <l>But language clean, and what affects you not,</l>
               <l>Without impoſsibilities the Plot;</l>
               <l>No clown, no ſquibs, no Devill in't; oh now</l>
               <l>You Squirrels that want Nuts, what will you do?</l>
               <l>Pray do not crack the benches; and we may</l>
               <l>Hereafter fit your Palats with a Play:</l>
               <l>But you that can contract your ſelves, and ſit</l>
               <l>As you were now in the <hi>Black-Fryers</hi> pit;</l>
               <l>And will not deaf us, with leud noiſe and tongues,</l>
               <l>Becauſe we have no Heart to break our Lungs,</l>
               <l>Will pardon our vaſt Stage, and not diſgrace</l>
               <l>This Play, meant for your perſons, not the place.</l>
            </lg>
         </div>
         <div type="dramatis_personae">
            <pb facs="tcp:153589:5"/>
            <head>The Perſons of the Play.</head>
            <list>
               <item>Leonario, <hi>Prince of</hi> Arragon.</item>
               <item>Ferdinand, <hi>King of</hi> Murcia.</item>
               <item>Rodriguez <hi>Noblemen.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Erneſto, <hi>Noblemen.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Leandro, <hi>Noblemen.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Alfonſo, <hi>Father to</hi> Roſania.</item>
               <item>Olivia, <hi>ſuppoſed Queen of</hi> Murcia.</item>
               <item>Roſania, Alfonſo<hi>'s, Daughter.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Violinda.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Captain.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Citizens.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Courtier.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Officers.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Souldiers.</hi>
               </item>
            </list>
            <p>Scene <hi>Murcia.</hi>
            </p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <head>
            <pb facs="tcp:153589:5"/>THE DOVBTFVLL HEIR.</head>
         <div n="1" type="act">
            <head>ACT. I.</head>
            <stage>Enter Rodriguez and Erneſto.</stage>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Rod.</speaker>
               <l>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>His turn was not expected, Prince <hi>Leonario</hi>
               </l>
               <l>Is much perplext.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Ern.</speaker>
               <l>I cannot blame his Highneſs,</l>
               <l>So neer an expectation of a bleſſing,</l>
               <l>To be thus croſt.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Rod.</speaker>
               <l>The Day of Marriage ſet,</l>
               <l>With the applauſive Vote of both the Kingdoms,</l>
               <l>By an unlookt for War to be put of,</l>
               <l>Would vex a royall ſpleen.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Er.</speaker>
               <l>'Tis but deferr'd.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Rod.</speaker>
               <l>I doe not like the hope on't.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Er.</speaker>
               <l>I pittie</l>
               <l>The Princely lover, worthy (without blemiſh</l>
               <l>To the excelling virtues of the Queen)</l>
               <l>Of as much goodneſs as her ſex contains,</l>
               <l>So Noble in his Nature, Active, bountifull</l>
               <l>Diſcreet, and valiant, if we may believe</l>
               <l>What his young fame profers to every knowledge.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Rod.</speaker>
               <l>This character is not flattery and yet</l>
               <l>The Queen our Miſtriſs is not loſt in this</l>
               <pb n="2" facs="tcp:153589:6"/>
               <l>Juſt praiſe of him.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Er.</speaker>
               <l>I have no thought ſo Impious,</l>
               <l>My dutie never taught me to commend</l>
               <l>But to obey, her Virgin ſweetneſs makes me</l>
               <l>Her juſt admirer but when I obſerve</l>
               <l>Her prudent manage of the State, a ſtrength</l>
               <l>Would become many years, her pious Laws,</l>
               <l>But that without example, made to advance</l>
               <l>Her ſexes Chaſtitie, I forget all</l>
               <l>Beſide worth praiſe, though every leaſt of her</l>
               <l>Deſert would ask a volume. 'Tis his Excellence.</l>
            </sp>
            <stage>Enter Leonario, Captain.</stage>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Rod.</speaker>
               <l>Ther's one not ſorry for theſe Wars.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Er.</speaker>
               <l>'Tis his</l>
               <l>Profeſſion; Souldiers batten in a Tempeſt.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Rod.</speaker>
               <l>And he deſerves employment; yet I think</l>
               <l>Hee'l never purchaſe with his pay.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Leo.</speaker>
               <l>Be confident;</l>
               <l>Your worth will plead alone; the Queen expects me.</l>
            </sp>
            <stage>Ex. Leon.</stage>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Capt.</speaker>
               <l>Your Highneſs humble creature;—ſo, ther's hope yet</l>
               <l>After a time of eaſe, and ſurfet, we</l>
               <l>May cure our ſelves by letting others Bloud.</l>
               <l>My Noble Lords.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Erneſt.</speaker>
               <l>'Morrow Captain, you look blith, and bright.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Capt.</speaker>
               <l>I'l put my Sword to ſcowring that ſhall ſhine.</l>
               <l>I thank Heaven my prayers are heard.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Rod.</speaker>
               <l>What prayers?</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Cap.</speaker>
               <l>That honeſt men may cut knaves throats, and bid</l>
               <l>Defiance to the Hangman; Musk and Civet</l>
               <l>Have too long ſtifled us, ther's no recovery</l>
               <l>Without the ſmell of Gunpowder.</l>
            </sp>
            <stage>Enter two Citizens.</stage>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Er.</speaker>
               <l>But Captain—</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>1 <hi>C.</hi>
               </speaker>
               <l>'Tis he, we muſt not loſe him,</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>2 <hi>C.</hi>
               </speaker>
               <l>He has credit with the Lords it ſeems.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>1 <hi>C.</hi>
               </speaker>
               <l>He has ſpied us.</l>
            </sp>
            <pb n="3" facs="tcp:153589:6"/>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Capt.</speaker>
               <l>My honeſt friends, welcome to Court. My Lords</l>
               <l>Pray grace theſe honeſt Gentlemen, they will</l>
               <l>Deſerve to kiſs your Hands.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>1 <hi>C.</hi>
               </speaker>
               <l>Our buſineſs</l>
               <l>Is to you Captain.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Capt.</speaker>
               <l>Doe you think what theſe brace of Baboons come for?</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Rod.</speaker>
               <l>Not I.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Capt.</speaker>
               <l>By this day for mony, moneys that I owe 'em.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Er.</speaker>
               <l>Is't poſſible?</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Capt.</speaker>
               <l>I ha'mov'd your ſute Gentlemen.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>1 <hi>C.</hi>
               </speaker>
               <l>What ſute?</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Capt.</speaker>
               <l>Touching the Maſque. Which you two in the name</l>
               <l>Of the whole City, offer'd to preſent</l>
               <l>At the Town charges to congratulate</l>
               <l>The Queens intended Marriage; I know</l>
               <l>This Egge was long a hatching and expected,</l>
               <l>But that your Heads could not agree, they being</l>
               <l>Of ſeverall ſizes, ſome upon the ſhoulders</l>
               <l>Of your long-winded Officers, whoſe purſe</l>
               <l>Was made of the Leather with their conſcience.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>1 <hi>Ci.</hi>
               </speaker>
               <l>Does he talk to us of a Maſque?</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>2 <hi>Ci.</hi>
               </speaker>
               <l>Good Captain put your Maſque off, and give us.</l>
               <l>The money that you owe us.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Capt.</speaker>
               <l>Was't not meant nobly?</l>
               <l>But you my good Lords know how much</l>
               <l>The Queen and Prince are ſorry, that ſo rare</l>
               <l>A Preſident of their duty ſhould not be</l>
               <l>Upon record; this villanous War diſtracts</l>
               <l>All civill mirth, but you will be remembred.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>1 <hi>Ci.</hi>
               </speaker>
               <l>We know not what you mean, we have no anticks</l>
               <l>In agitation; if your Captain-ſhip</l>
               <l>Will pay your debts, ſo; there is Law and courſes</l>
               <l>To be taken, and you will find that Juſtice</l>
               <l>Can deal Sir with the Sword as well as Ballance.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Capt.</speaker>
               <l>The Puppys talk Philoſophy; nay then</l>
               <l>I muſt be plain, would I could tice 'em to</l>
               <l>A little treaſon, theyl ne'r hang for felony.</l>
               <pb n="4" facs="tcp:153589:7"/>
               <l>Why, whither doe you think I am going now?</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>1 <hi>Cit.</hi>
               </speaker>
               <l>We care not whither ſo you pay us firſt.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Capt.</speaker>
               <l>Let their own Fathers ſwing, ſo they have mony.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>2 <hi>Cit.</hi>
               </speaker>
               <l>May be you are going to the Wars.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Capt.</speaker>
               <l>Yes Mongrels,</l>
               <l>To fight for your chamlet Faces, while you ſtay at home</l>
               <l>And catch the cramp with telling mony,</l>
               <l>Putting your Guts to Penſion every Day,</l>
               <l>And roots, untill the wind cry out agen you,</l>
               <l>And with your belching backwards ſtifle Men</l>
               <l>That walk the Street, untill the Air be purg'd;</l>
               <l>Muſt we Eat Bullets without Butter. Whelps?</l>
               <l>Have our Throats cut, or drop like Sheep by'th' hundred,</l>
               <l>O' the rot, to buy your Peace, you boding Screechowls?</l>
               <l>And ha' your conſciences ſo courſe a Nap</l>
               <l>To aske money of us?</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>1 <hi>Cit.</hi>
               </speaker>
               <l>You had the conſcience</l>
               <l>To take up our commodities.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Capt.</speaker>
               <l>Reaſon good;</l>
               <l>Should I goe naked leeches?</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>2 <hi>Cit.</hi>
               </speaker>
               <l>No but there is reaſon</l>
               <l>That you ſhould pay good Captain for your warmth.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Capt.</speaker>
               <l>Pay you? for what? for Cloaths, ſuch things as theſe?</l>
               <l>Your tribe is bound to keep us.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>1 <hi>Cit.</hi>
               </speaker>
               <l>How?</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Capt.</speaker>
               <l>Yes, and deſire us to accept your wares,</l>
               <l>To recompence our ſufferings; 'tis we,</l>
               <l>'Tis we that keep your Worſhips warm and living,</l>
               <l>By Marching, Faſting, Fighting, and a thouſand</l>
               <l>Dangers, (you o'r grown moths) you that love gold,</l>
               <l>And wo'not take an Angell ſent from Heaven</l>
               <l>Unleſs you weigh him, you that ſpend the Day</l>
               <l>In looking o'r your debt — Book, and at Night</l>
               <l>Can lap and lecher in your Feather Beds.</l>
               <l>Then ſnort, and dream of fourſcore in the hundred,</l>
               <pb n="5" facs="tcp:153589:7"/>
               <l>Afraid of nothing but the Gout, or what</l>
               <l>Is a more juſt reward for your hard hearts</l>
               <l>The ſtone, which puts you to the charge of Phyſick</l>
               <l>To make you piſs out your laſt Uſurers Gallon,</l>
               <l>Or of a Surgeon to cut you for</l>
               <l>The Pibles, which (if you ſurvive Inciſſion)</l>
               <l>You keep in penny Boxes, like deer reliques,</l>
               <l>And ſhew your friends, when you intend to viſit 'em.</l>
               <l>And beg a Dinner.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Er.</speaker>
               <l>Let not paſſion</l>
               <l>Make you too much abuſe their qulaity;</l>
               <l>The City does contain brave fellows Captain,</l>
               <l>As generous, as bountifull, diſcreet,</l>
               <l>And valiant too, as any boaſt themſelves</l>
               <l>In Court or Camp.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Cap.</speaker>
               <l>I grant you my good Lord,</l>
               <l>And honour all the Noble ſouls within it,</l>
               <l>But theſe are walking ſickneſſes, not Citizens;</l>
               <l>Two ſuch prodigious things with crooked conſciences,</l>
               <l>Though Young yet Old in Uſury—</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>2 <hi>Cit.</hi>
               </speaker>
               <l>All this Captain</l>
               <l>Wo'not pay us our money, which we muſt</l>
               <l>Have, or Petition for to your diſgrace.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Cap.</speaker>
               <l>Well ſince there is no remedy, will you take</l>
               <l>Theſe two Noblemens words for what I owe you?</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>1 <hi>Cit.</hi>
               </speaker>
               <l>Withall our Hearts.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Rod.</speaker>
               <l>That bargain is to make.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Er.</speaker>
               <l>Good Captain, at this time you may excuſe us,</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Capt.</speaker>
               <l>Why, doe your Lordſhips think I'd let you ſurfer,</l>
               <l>Come, y'ar my honourable friends; paſs, paſs</l>
               <l>Your word, Ile pay the mony; hang'em dottrels</l>
               <l>Ile not be beholding to 'em.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Rod.</speaker>
               <l>We had rather you ſhould good Captain.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Capt.</speaker>
               <l>No,—come hither Capons</l>
               <l>Will money content you; ſhall I walk the Street</l>
               <l>Without a Head ake, with your bawling for</l>
               <pb n="6" facs="tcp:153589:8"/>
               <l>The debt when I ha' paid you?</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>2 <hi>Cit.</hi>
               </speaker>
               <l>'Tis but reaſon.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Capt.</speaker>
               <l>I'l fetch you money preſently — you may follow</l>
               <l>If you pleaſe, but theſe Noblemen ſhall ſee</l>
               <l>And witneſs what I pay you, I'l not truſt</l>
               <l>Your <hi>Memorandums.</hi>
               </l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>1 <hi>Cit.</hi>
               </speaker>
               <l>Withall our Hearts Sir.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>2 <hi>Cit.</hi>
               </speaker>
               <l>We deſire no more.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Capt.</speaker>
               <l>I'l wait on you again.</l>
            </sp>
            <stage>Ex. Manent</stage>
            <stage>Enter Leandro, reading a Paper.</stage>
            <stage>Rod. Erneſto.</stage>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Rod.</speaker>
               <l>
                  <hi>Fortune de la guerre.</hi>
               </l>
               <l>My Lord <hi>Leandro?</hi> what papers that</l>
               <l>He ſo intentively peruſes?</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Lean.</speaker>
               <l>I like it and could willingly allow</l>
               <l>The change; the Queen grows mighty in her ſpirit,</l>
               <l>And this match with the Prince would ſwell her State</l>
               <l>Too much; my Lords.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Rod.</speaker>
               <l>We are yours.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Leand.</speaker>
               <l>See what dangerous Papers have been ſcatter'd</l>
               <l>To wound the Title of our Royall Miſtriſs;</l>
               <l>My ſervant brought me this; our Enemie</l>
               <l>Who calls himſelf Prince <hi>Ferdinand</hi> would fain</l>
               <l>Have us believe him Coſen to the Queen,</l>
               <l>She an uſurper of his Crown.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Er.</speaker>
               <l>We all know him dead.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Rod.</speaker>
               <l>I'm ſure I did attend his Funerall.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Lean.</speaker>
               <l>I think I waited too.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Er.</speaker>
               <l>This paper ſayes he was conveyd away,</l>
               <l>And ſo eſcap'd his Uncles cruelty,</l>
               <l>To whoſe protection he was left an Infant;</l>
               <l>He dying, we tranſlated our obedience</l>
               <l>To his Daughter, now our Queen.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Rod.</speaker>
               <l>Here's an Impoſtor.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Leand.</speaker>
               <l>Heaven aid the Innocent ſay I; he has</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Valentias</hi> aid and comes not to Invite</l>
               <l>But force a reſignation; I wiſh things</l>
               <l>Were calm agen.</l>
            </sp>
            <pb n="7" facs="tcp:153589:8"/>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Er.</speaker>
               <l>Prince <hi>Leonario</hi> if ſhe proſper not,</l>
               <l>Is like to be a loſer too.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Leand.</speaker>
               <l>For him</l>
               <l>It matters not, we have more to think on now,</l>
               <l>Than love and complement.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Rod.</speaker>
               <l>I thought he would be Generall</l>
               <l>'Gainſt this pretended <hi>Ferdinand.</hi>
               </l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Leand.</speaker>
               <l>What elſe?</l>
               <l>Her ſweet Heart, that gives <hi>Cupid</hi> in his creſt.</l>
               <l>Alas! there needs no art, nor ſtrength of War</l>
               <l>To advance her cauſe. Juſtice will fight for her</l>
               <l>I'th' Clouds, and victory ſent from Heaven, without</l>
               <l>Her ſouldiers ſweat, will gloriouſly deſcend</l>
               <l>To Crown his Head with Laurell.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Er.</speaker>
               <l>May it prove ſo.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Leand.</speaker>
               <l>I could ſay things would ſtagger your belief,</l>
               <l>But I forgot the Queen ſent for me; to</l>
               <l>You both a ſervant—</l>
            </sp>
            <stage>Exit.</stage>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Er.</speaker>
               <l>I do not like my Lord <hi>Leandros</hi> winding,</l>
               <l>He has been faithfull.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Rod.</speaker>
               <l>Alwaies honourable. The Queen.</l>
            </sp>
            <stage>Enter Queen, Leonario, Captain, Leandro, Violinda, Attendants, Ladies, Gentlemen.</stage>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Leon.</speaker>
               <l>I take this as the greateſt honour Madam</l>
               <l>You could confer; my name is young in War,</l>
               <l>But my affection to your rovall perſon,</l>
               <l>Arm'd with the virtue of your cauſe, ſhall make me</l>
               <l>Doe ſomething worth your name.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Que.</speaker>
               <l>'Twas your requeſt.</l>
               <l>Nor could we place our chief command, but where</l>
               <l>'Tis equald with your Intereſt in us</l>
               <l>And your own merit.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Leon.</speaker>
               <l>Sure my Stars did mean</l>
               <l>This way to make you know, how much my heart</l>
               <l>Dares in your ſervice; and if <hi>Ferdinand,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>For ſo he calls himſelf, poſſeſs a ſoul</l>
               <pb n="8" facs="tcp:153589:9"/>
               <l>Above the vulgar making, we ſhall ſpare</l>
               <l>The Blood of many, and conclude the War</l>
               <l>In ſingle oppoſition.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Leand.</speaker>
               <l>With your Highneſs pardon,</l>
               <l>It not becomes you ſhould Engage your Perſon,</l>
               <l>And ſo great a cauſe ſo dangerouſly;</l>
               <l>It will be too much honor to th' Impoſtor,</l>
               <l>And in the ſuppoſition of the World,</l>
               <l>A ſtrength to his pretence, to bring your Birth</l>
               <l>So low, to humble both your ſelf and fortunes</l>
               <l>To his unworthy Levell, a thing grown</l>
               <l>Up in the Night, a Meteor hanging in</l>
               <l>The Air, prodigiouſly, fed with vapor, and</l>
               <l>Black Influence, ambitious to deceive</l>
               <l>The World, and challenge kindred with the Stars;</l>
               <l>It is too great a venture Sir.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Er.</speaker>
               <l>Since there muſt be a War</l>
               <l>Let the armies meet in Battail theres more hope</l>
               <l>After the worſt to reinforce and proſper,</l>
               <l>Than when the kingdoms put upon one ſtake,</l>
               <l>And one Mans chance to aſſure it.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Que.</speaker>
               <l>I allow</l>
               <l>Your Counſell Lords; but have more argument</l>
               <l>Convincing me, not to run ſuch a hazard</l>
               <l>Of what muſt make <hi>Olivia</hi> rich hereafter;</l>
               <l>A kingdoms loſs may be repair'd, but your</l>
               <l>Life made a Sacrifice to tyrant War.</l>
               <l>May find a welcome to the other ſhades,</l>
               <l>But no tears can Invite you back, to ſhare.</l>
               <l>Or grief, or Joy with me; Ile have no Duell.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Leon.</speaker>
               <l>'Tis a command, and my obedience</l>
               <l>Shall meet it, though I fear 'twill be a ſin</l>
               <l>To be too carefull of my ſelf, but I</l>
               <l>Shall ſtill remember I am your Souldier.</l>
               <l>And this conſider'd ſhall not make me raſh,</l>
               <l>But wiſely teach me to deſerve this title</l>
               <pb n="9" facs="tcp:153589:9"/>
               <l>Which lives but in your honour.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Que.</speaker>
               <l>I'l pray for you,</l>
               <l>And not ſo much for what concerns the State,</l>
               <l>As what your merit hath already gain'd</l>
               <l>Upon my Heart.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Rod.</speaker>
               <l>Bleſſings upon 'em both,</l>
               <l>A curſe upon theſe Wars, that ſpoil their mirth.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Que.</speaker>
               <l>My Lord <hi>Leandro.</hi>
               </l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Leon.</speaker>
               <l>Ther's your Commiſſion Captain, I ſuppoſe</l>
               <l>You have found wayes to empty your Exchequer.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Capt.</speaker>
               <l>My Baggs are not brimfull my Lord. I have</l>
               <l>Defalk'd, and made an ebbe for Wine, and Women,</l>
               <l>And other things that keep poor men alive</l>
               <l>To doe their country ſervice.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Leon.</speaker>
               <l>Pleaſe you walk</l>
               <l>With this Gentleman Captain, he ſhall pay you</l>
               <l>Five hundred pieces that I owe you.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Capt.</speaker>
               <l>Me, your Grace owes me nothing,</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Leon.</speaker>
               <l>I could not pay the debt in better time Sir.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Capt.</speaker>
               <l>Umh! I will take the mony, and allow the miracle.</l>
            </sp>
            <stage>Ex. Capt. &amp; Gent.</stage>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Er.</speaker>
               <l>Did you obſerve the Princes nobleneſs?</l>
               <l>Although the act become him. Yet the manner</l>
               <l>Takes me eſpecially, Heaven preſerve the Captain</l>
               <l>From being Mad.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Leon.</speaker>
               <l>I proſper in your Vote,</l>
               <l>But ſhall I Madam, if that power, which Crowns</l>
               <l>With victory guides me with fair ſucceſs</l>
               <l>In this your War, and triumph ſmile upon us,</l>
               <l>Shall I at my return have that reward</l>
               <l>My ſoul next Heaven affects? ſhall no delay</l>
               <l>(Colder than Froſt to lovers blood,) afflict</l>
               <l>My expectation of our Marriage?</l>
               <l>Although to doubt this be a ſin, yet where</l>
               <l>The ambition is ſo Juſt, I ſhall but right</l>
               <l>My Heart, to have it oft aſſur'd, nor can</l>
               <l>It make your eye leſs rich in ſmiles, when 'tis</l>
               <pb n="10" facs="tcp:153589:10"/>
               <l>Only my love Encourages me to make</l>
               <l>The buſie harmleſs queſtion.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Que.</speaker>
               <l>It does pleaſe me,</l>
               <l>Nor can you ask ſo often, as I have</l>
               <l>A cheerfulneſs to anſwer, that I love you,</l>
               <l>And have propounded nothing dearer to me,</l>
               <l>Than that which perfects chaſt affection,</l>
               <l>And chains two Hearts; the Prieſt with ſadneſs will</l>
               <l>Expect you ſafe agen, but from this War</l>
               <l>When you return, he ſhall not in his Regiſter</l>
               <l>Of Lovers, find one, with more wing hath met</l>
               <l>The boſom of her friend, than glad <hi>Olivia</hi>
               </l>
               <l>To make one ſoul with you.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Leon.</speaker>
               <l>I have enough,</l>
               <l>And thirſt for action in the Field, from whence</l>
               <l>I will bring Harveſt home, or leave my ſelf,</l>
               <l>Happy in life or death to doe you ſervice.</l>
            </sp>
            <stage>Ex. Queen, Leon. Lean. Ladies, attendants.</stage>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Rod.</speaker>
               <l>Well, I'm afraid if <hi>Hymen</hi> ſhould ſet up</l>
               <l>His Tapers now, they would not laſt to light</l>
               <l>His Prieſt, at their return to ſay his Office.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Er.</speaker>
               <l>Hope fairly.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Rod.</speaker>
               <l>I allow his ſpirit, but</l>
               <l>The Prince hath not been practis'd in</l>
               <l>The School of War, where ſtratagems prevail</l>
               <l>Above all perſonall reſolution.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Er.</speaker>
               <l>He cannot want fit counſell to direct</l>
               <l>His early valour, beſides</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Ferdinand</hi> by computation as young as he</l>
               <stage>Enter Captain, two Citizens, and a Souldier.</stage>
               <l>May poize the ſcale. See, the Captain.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>1 <hi>Cit.</hi>
               </speaker>
               <l>We alwaies thought you Noble, and we hope</l>
               <l>You'l take no offence, that our occaſions</l>
               <l>Prevail'd above our modeſtie.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Capt.</speaker>
               <l>I know</l>
               <l>You two are very modeſt; well I'm glad</l>
               <pb n="11" facs="tcp:153589:10"/>
               <l>I am furniſh'd for you: my good Lords I muſt</l>
               <l>Intreat you to be witneſſes of what money</l>
               <l>I pay theſe Gentlemen, that have truſted me.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>2 <hi>Cit.</hi>
               </speaker>
               <l>And will agen; command our Shops.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Capt.</speaker>
               <l>No, ſit there, and ſtarve,</l>
               <l>Or if you like it better take a ſwing</l>
               <l>At your own ſign Poſt.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Er.</speaker>
               <l>Good words Captain.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Capt.</speaker>
               <l>They expect good money, and both good are too much.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>1 <hi>Cit.</hi>
               </speaker>
               <l>We alwaies lov'd you.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>2 <hi>Cit.</hi>
               </speaker>
               <l>And doe ſo ſtill moſt virtuouſly.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Capt.</speaker>
               <l>It does appear,</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>1 <hi>Cit.</hi>
               </speaker>
               <l>And you ſhall find us ready—</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Capt.</speaker>
               <l>I'l make but one fair motion, it will be</l>
               <l>Sufficient tryall of your honeſtie;</l>
               <l>I have five hundred pounds, you ſee me tell it,</l>
               <l>Faith make it up a thouſand 'twixt you both</l>
               <l>Till I come back, you will be Aldermen.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>1 <hi>Cit.</hi>
               </speaker>
               <l>Ne'r a whit the ſooner.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>2 <hi>Cit.</hi>
               </speaker>
               <l>Alas Sir, if it were at another time —</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>1 <hi>Cit.</hi>
               </speaker>
               <l>Hereafter, upon good occaſion you ſhall find—</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Capt.</speaker>
               <l>You both i'th'Pillotie, for ſelling Copper</l>
               <l>Lace by a wrong name; well ther's no remedy,</l>
               <l>I'l keep my word; the money's ready for you.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>1 <hi>Cit.</hi>
               </speaker>
               <l>You are noble Captain.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>2 <hi>Cit.</hi>
               </speaker>
               <l>May you kill all the Queens Enemies.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Capt.</speaker>
               <l>You would not ſcape,</l>
               <l>That Coſen her liege people every day, then.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>2 <hi>Cit.</hi>
               </speaker>
               <l>This payment Captain will come moſt ſeaſonably.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>1 <hi>Cit.</hi>
               </speaker>
               <l>And doe us as much good, as you had given us</l>
               <l>The ſum twice told, another time.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Capt.</speaker>
               <l>Before</l>
               <l>Theſe Noblemen, have you ſuch want</l>
               <l>As you profeſs? you have no Wives nor Children.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>1 <hi>Cit.</hi>
               </speaker>
               <l>I proteſt upon my credit, I am to pay</l>
               <l>This day two hundred pound, or be indanger'd</l>
               <l>To an arreſt.</l>
            </sp>
            <pb n="12" facs="tcp:153589:11"/>
            <sp>
               <speaker>2 <hi>Cit.</hi>
               </speaker>
               <l>And I muſt goe to Priſon</l>
               <l>If before Sun-ſet—</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Capt.</speaker>
               <l>Then 'twill doe you a pleaſure.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Both. Cit.</speaker>
               <l>Above expreſſion.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Capt.</speaker>
               <l>Heres twelve pence a peece for you y'ar fit Men</l>
               <l>To ſerve the Queen:</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Both Cit.</speaker>
               <l>How Captain?</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Capt.</speaker>
               <l>Why in the Wars, chooſe either Pike or Musket,</l>
               <l>You ſhall have that favour.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Both Cit.</speaker>
               <l>We are both undone.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Lords.</speaker>
               <l>Ha, ha, but will you uſe 'em ſo?</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Capt.</speaker>
               <l>Ha' they not ready mony? why d'ee ſtare?</l>
               <l>No thanks for my protection?</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Both Cat.</speaker>
               <l>Protection?</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Capt.</speaker>
               <l>Did you not proteſt you ſhould to priſon elſe?</l>
               <l>Why you unthankfull ſons of falſe light, Sergeant</l>
               <l>Take 'em to thei'r Rendevous</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>1 <hi>Cit.</hi>
               </speaker>
               <l>Captain, a word—we are content—</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Capt.</speaker>
               <l>I'm glad on't, Why d'ee ſtay then.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>1 <hi>Cit.</hi>
               </speaker>
               <l>To abate half our money.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>2 <hi>Cit.</hi>
               </speaker>
               <l>All, all good Captain, he ſhall have all, rather</l>
               <l>Than be ſent a ſouldiering; d'ee know what 'tis?</l>
               <l>'Tis no Artillery Garden, where you come off</l>
               <l>With as you were.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Rod.</speaker>
               <l>This was his Project.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Capt.</speaker>
               <l>Umh'. You will forgive me both your debts?</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>2 <hi>Cit.</hi>
               </speaker>
               <l>And pray Heaven to forgive you too.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Capt.</speaker>
               <l>My Lords, bear witneſs,</l>
               <l>Theſe two would bribe me to abuſe the Queen</l>
               <l>And the preſent ſervice, is this leſs then Treaſon?</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Both Cit.</speaker>
               <l>Oh. <hi>Er.</hi> Nay, nay Captain.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Capt.</speaker>
               <l>There are not two more able Men i'th' Army,</l>
               <l>I mean for bulk; ram me into a Cannon</l>
               <l>If you ſhall buy your ſelves with your eſtates</l>
               <l>From this Imployment; Il not coſen you,</l>
               <l>Your mony is good debt ſtill, you may live,</l>
               <pb n="13" facs="tcp:153589:11"/>
               <l>And aske me for't agen, and I may pay you.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Rod.</speaker>
               <l>But ſhall they ſerve indeed?</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Capt.</speaker>
               <l>That's at their perill</l>
               <l>When they come to'th, field, but goe they ſhall,</l>
               <l>And they were my Coſen-germans.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Both Cit.</speaker>
               <l>Good my Lord ſpeak for us.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Capt.</speaker>
               <l>You doe not know my Lords, but a little ſuffering</l>
               <l>May ſave their ſouls and teach 'em, if they come</l>
               <l>Off, with a quarter of their limbs, compaſſion</l>
               <l>To other Men, that venter their lives for 'em,</l>
               <l>Their conſciences are tough, and muſt be ſuppled,</l>
               <l>When they ſhall faſt, and march ten months in armor,</l>
               <l>Sometimes through Rivers, ſometimes over Mountains,</l>
               <l>And not have ſtraw at Night, to keep their Breech</l>
               <l>From growing to the Earth, in ſtorms, in heats;</l>
               <l>When they have felt the ſoftneſs of a trench</l>
               <l>Thigh deep in water, and their dung to fatten it;</l>
               <l>When they ſhall ſee no meat within a month,</l>
               <l>But chaw their Match like Liquoriſh, and digeſt</l>
               <l>The Bark of trees like Sallads in the Summer;</l>
               <l>When they ſhall live to think theres no ſuch thing</l>
               <l>In Nature as a thirſt, and wonder why</l>
               <l>A Taylor was created; when they have</l>
               <l>As much in ready ſhot, within their fleſh,</l>
               <l>As would ſet up a Plummer, or repair</l>
               <l>A Church with Lead, beſide ten thouſand more</l>
               <l>Afflictions, which they are ſure to find,</l>
               <l>They may have Chriſtianitie, and not put</l>
               <l>A Souldier to the payment of his debts.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Rod.</speaker>
               <l>'Tis a Mad Captain, come my Lord lets leave him.</l>
            </sp>
            <stage>Ex. Lords.</stage>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Capt.</speaker>
               <l>You ſhall have time and place to ſend for mony,</l>
               <l>Or make your Wils; ſet on, who knows but you</l>
               <l>Hereafter may be honeſt, and prove Captains;</l>
               <l>You may have preferment in the Wars for money,</l>
               <l>And ſo my Gentle Creditors, march on.</l>
            </sp>
            <stage>Exeunt.</stage>
         </div>
         <div n="2" type="act">
            <pb n="14" facs="tcp:153589:12"/>
            <head>ACT. II. <hi>Enter Leandro with Letters.</hi>
            </head>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Lean.</speaker>
               <l>THe hope, and care of many years, are in</l>
               <l>One day deſtroy'd; hath Heaven no ſtroke in War?</l>
               <l>Or is old providence aſleep? <hi>Leonar to</hi>
               </l>
               <l>Is comming home with victorie, and brings</l>
               <l>Young <hi>Ferdinand,</hi> whom I expected to</l>
               <l>Salute a King, his Priſoner, and the Queen</l>
               <l>With her new Conqueror, glorious in the ſpoils,</l>
               <l>By putting out this light, will mix their beams</l>
               <l>And burn our eyes out with their ſhine; there is</l>
               <l>No talk but of this triumph, and the people</l>
               <l>Whom I by art and ſecret murmurs had</l>
               <l>Made doubtful at the firſt noiſe of this Conqueſt,</l>
               <l>As they had borrowed ſouls from fear, and folly,</l>
               <l>Adore the riſing Star, and in the praiſe</l>
               <l>Of him and his great fate, wonder that Heaven</l>
               <l>Should hold a Sun, and he ſo bright; nor with</l>
               <l>This flattery content, but they condemn,</l>
               <l>(As low as all their ſins ſhall one day them)</l>
               <l>Him whom the chance of War hath made a Priſoner.</l>
               <l>There is no truſt to policie or time,</l>
               <l>The things of State are whirld by deſtinie,</l>
               <l>To meet their period, Art cannot repair 'em.</l>
            </sp>
            <stage>Enter Servant.</stage>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Ser.</speaker>
               <l>My Lord, the Queen hath ſent for you,</l>
               <l>She is going forth to meet the Prince, and hath</l>
               <l>Commanded none be wanting to attend</l>
               <l>With all the State that may become her, to</l>
               <l>Congratulate the triumph now brought home.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Leand.</speaker>
               <l>I ſhall obey. I muſt attend this glorie;</l>
               <pb n="15" facs="tcp:153589:12"/>
               <l>It is not ſafe to wear a brow, but what</l>
               <l>The Queens example firſt forms into ſmile.</l>
               <l>I here contract my knowledge, and ſeclude</l>
               <l>My wiſhes, ſince they proſper not. I am</l>
               <l>Her Chancelor; as great Offices, and high</l>
               <l>Employments, do expoſe us to moſt danger,</l>
               <l>They oft teach thoſe poſſeſs 'em a State-wiſdom,</l>
               <l>And by Inherent virtues of the place,</l>
               <l>Our fear to loſe, makes us ſecure our ſelves,</l>
               <l>By art more often, than by conſcience;</l>
               <l>But I may be indangered to ſuſpition;</l>
               <l>I like not things; but I delay my attendance.</l>
            </sp>
            <stage>Exit.</stage>
            <stage>Enter Captain, Lieutenant, Antient and Souldiers.</stage>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Capt.</speaker>
               <l>Lieutenant.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Lieu.</speaker>
               <l>Captain.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Capt.</speaker>
               <l>Antient, what think you of the Wars now?</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Ant.</speaker>
               <l>We are come off with Honour.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Lieu.</speaker>
               <l>And our Limbs, Captain.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Capt.</speaker>
               <l>Is that all? who made you a Lieutenant?</l>
               <l>And you Antient? theſe titles were not born w'e,</l>
               <l>You did not wear theſe Buffs and Feathers in</l>
               <l>The memorie of Man, when you receiv'd</l>
               <l>The binding twelve-pence, it was otherwiſe.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Ant.</speaker>
               <l>But you receiv'd, if you remember Captain,</l>
               <l>Beſide what we releaſt in honeſt debt</l>
               <l>Sums for this great Inſtalment, we ha' paid</l>
               <l>I take it for our names.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Capt.</speaker>
               <l>And it became you,</l>
               <l>Now you are Gentlemen my Comrades of honor,</l>
               <l>And I dare walk and drink at Taverns w'e,</l>
               <l>Your oaths become you now, and your ſplay feet;</l>
               <l>You look'd before like Magots, City Worms,</l>
               <l>I ha' made you both brave fellows, fellows to Knights.</l>
               <l>You may be Squires to Ladies too.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Ant.</speaker>
               <l>I think ſo.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Capt.</speaker>
               <l>We are all now of a trade,</l>
               <l>For <hi>Mars</hi> is Maſter of our Companie,</l>
               <pb n="16" facs="tcp:153589:13"/>
               <l>Our Shop is the Field, Reſolution our Stock,</l>
               <l>Honour our Purchaſe, and Fire and Sword</l>
               <l>The Tools we work withall.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Lieu.</speaker>
               <l>But now the Wars are done, I think</l>
               <l>We may ſhut up our Shop, there is no more</l>
               <l>Pay, is there?</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Capt.</speaker>
               <l>Pox upon you; I ſee your ſouls bleat after</l>
               <l>Profit ſtill, a bullet in the right place would</l>
               <l>Ha' knock'd out this humour of getting mony;</l>
               <l>But fear not, though you come off with more</l>
               <l>Limbs than you deſerve, you ſhall have pay.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Ant.</speaker>
               <l>Shall we and not be troubled to fight for't?</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Capt.</speaker>
               <l>Yes, it will be neceſſary you fight, you will</l>
               <l>Ha' your throats cut elſe, and be ſent off like Sheep,</l>
               <l>Doe not fear payment, here be Mandrakes,</l>
               <l>That will rore, and cudgell you to your hearts content,</l>
               <l>You ſha'not walk the Streets now you are</l>
               <l>Officers without a quarrell: pay enough.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Lieu.</speaker>
               <l>A Man had as good be no Lieutenant, as be</l>
               <l>Beaten when he comes home what think you Antient?</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Ant.</speaker>
               <l>For my part I can indure beating as well</l>
               <l>As another if that be all.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Capt.</speaker>
               <l>Will you to your Shops agen?</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Ant.</speaker>
               <l>I have no mind to Wooſted Stockings agen,</l>
               <l>And Shoos that Shine, I would were colours ſtill.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Capt.</speaker>
               <l>Well ſaid Antient come I'l take your fears off;</l>
               <l>Doe not confeſs you are a Lieutenant, or you an</l>
               <l>Antient, and no man will quarrell w'ee, you</l>
               <l>Shall be as ſecure as Chryſome Children.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Lieu.</speaker>
               <l>Shall we? they ſhall rack me e'r Ile confeſs I am</l>
               <l>A Lieutenant or ever ſee the Wars.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Ant.</speaker>
               <l>Or I an Antient. Ile tak't upon my death</l>
               <l>I was never a Souldier in my life.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Capt.</speaker>
               <l>'Tis well done; now becauſe I love you,</l>
               <l>And ſee you have an Itch after honour, ſo</l>
               <l>It may come without blows, Let me adviſe you,</l>
               <pb n="17" facs="tcp:153589:13"/>
               <l>You have moneys at command.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Lieut.</speaker>
               <l>And good debts too.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Cap.</speaker>
               <l>You ſhall both turn Courtiers.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Ant.</speaker>
               <l>Shall we?</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Cap.</speaker>
               <l>I ſay't; for if my phiſnomy deceive me not,</l>
               <l>You two are born to be—</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Both.</speaker>
               <l>What?</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Cap.</speaker>
               <l>Coxbombs. I'l help to make you too;</l>
               <l>You ſhall preſently kiſs the Queens hand;</l>
               <l>You have moneys you ſay, You ſhall never turn</l>
               <l>To your vomit of ſmall Wares. I have friends</l>
               <l>At Court, you may in time be great; And when I come</l>
               <l>With a Petition to your honors, for moneys in arrear,</l>
               <l>Or knocking out ſome raſcals brains, ſuch as you were</l>
               <l>When you wore a girt under your chops, you two</l>
               <l>May ſtand between me and the Gallows.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Ant.</speaker>
               <l>Hang us if we do not.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Capt.</speaker>
               <l>You ſhall buy places preſently. But ſtay,</l>
               <l>Have you a minde to be Officers to the Queen</l>
               <l>In ordinary, or extraordinary?</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Ant.</speaker>
               <l>Extraordinary by all means.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Lieut.</speaker>
               <l>We ſcorn to be ordinary Courtiers.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Capt.</speaker>
               <l>I commend your judgement, that will be</l>
               <l>Chargeable: But—</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Ant.</speaker>
               <l>Hang't, we'l finde money enough, but I more</l>
               <l>Reſolve to be extraordinary.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Capt.</speaker>
               <l>I'l bring you to a Court-Merchant pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſently;</l>
               <l>You will get infinite eſtates.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Both.</speaker>
               <l>A ha Captain.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Capt.</speaker>
               <l>And ſo command the Ladies, if you be bountiful.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Both.</speaker>
               <l>A ha Boy.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Capt.</speaker>
               <l>For I know you do love Wenches;</l>
               <l>You will have all the buſineſs, and the Country</l>
               <l>Come tumbling in upon you like the tide,</l>
               <l>After a moneth: You muſt keep twenty men</l>
               <l>Between you, night and day to tell your money.</l>
               <pb n="18" facs="tcp:153589:14"/>
               <l>Oh 'tis unknown what will become on you,</l>
               <l>If you be rul'd, and take this courſe: Had I</l>
               <l>Moneys like you, I would be—</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Lieut.</speaker>
               <l>Come, we will lend thee moneys too hereafter.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Cap.</speaker>
               <l>Will you, come on, no more Lieutenant now</l>
               <l>Nor Antient.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Ant.</speaker>
               <l>Do ye think we long to be beaten.</l>
            </sp>
            <stage>Exeunt.</stage>
            <stage>Enter Ferdinand (in priſon) Roſania (like a Page.)</stage>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Roſa.</speaker>
               <l>Pray do not grieve for me, I have a heart</l>
               <l>Tha<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> can for your ſake ſuffer more; and when</l>
               <l>The tyranny of your fate calls me to die,</l>
               <l>I can as willingly reſign my breath,</l>
               <l>As go to ſleep.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Ferd.</speaker>
               <l>Can I hear this <hi>Roſania</hi>
               </l>
               <l>Without a freſh wound? That thy love to me</l>
               <l>Should be ſo ill rewarded, th'aſt engag'd</l>
               <l>Thy ſelf too much already; 'tis within</l>
               <l>Thy will, yet to be ſafe, reveal thy ſelf,</l>
               <l>Throw of the cloud that doth eclipſe that brightneſs,</l>
               <l>And they will court thy perſon, and be proud</l>
               <l>With all becoming-honor to receive thee,</l>
               <l>No fear ſhall rob thy cheek of her chaſte blood.</l>
               <l>Oh leave me to my own Stars, and expect</l>
               <l>What ere become of wretched <hi>Ferdinand,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>A happy fate.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Roſa.</speaker>
               <l>Your Councel is unkinde,</l>
               <l>This language would become your charity</l>
               <l>To a ſtranger, but my Intereſt is more</l>
               <l>In thee, then thus with words to be ſent off;</l>
               <l>Our vows have made us one, nor can the names</l>
               <l>Of Father, Countrey, or what can be dear</l>
               <l>In Nature, bribe one thought to wiſh my ſelf</l>
               <l>In Heaven without thy company; it were poor then</l>
               <l>To leave thee here. Then by thy faith I charge thee,</l>
               <l>By this—the firſt and laſt ſeal of our love. <hi>Kiſſes him.</hi>
               </l>
               <l>By all our promiſes, when we did flatter</l>
               <pb n="19" facs="tcp:153589:14"/>
               <l>Our ſelves, and in our fancy took the world</l>
               <l>A peeces, and collected what did like</l>
               <l>Us beſt, to make us a new paradice,</l>
               <l>By that, the nobleſt ornament of thy ſoul,</l>
               <l>Thy honor, I conjure thee, let me ſtill</l>
               <l>Be undiſcovered; What will it avail</l>
               <l>To leave me, whom thou loveſt, and walk alone</l>
               <l>Sad pilgrime to another world? We will</l>
               <l>Converſe in ſoul and ſhoot like Stars, whoſe Beams</l>
               <l>Are twiſted and make bright the ſullen Groves</l>
               <l>Of Lovers as we paſs.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Ferd.</speaker>
               <l>Theſe are but dreams</l>
               <l>Of happineſs, be wiſe <hi>Roſania,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>Thy love is not a friend to make thee miſerable,</l>
               <l>Society in death, where we affect,</l>
               <l>But multiplies our grief; Live thou, Oh live.</l>
               <l>And if thou haſt a tear, when I am dead,</l>
               <l>But drop it to my memory, it ſhall</l>
               <l>More precious then embalming dwell upon me,</l>
               <l>And keep my aſhes pure, my ſpirit ſhall</l>
               <l>At the ſame inſtant in ſome innocent ſhape</l>
               <l>Deſcend upon that earth thou haſt bedew'd;</l>
               <l>And kiſſing the bright tribute of thy eye,</l>
               <l>Shall after wait like thy good Angel on thee.</l>
               <l>There will be none to ſpeak of <hi>Ferdinand</hi>
               </l>
               <l>Without diſdain, if thou dieſt too: Oh live</l>
               <l>A little to defend me, or at leaſt</l>
               <l>To ſay I was no Traitor to thy love,</l>
               <l>And lay the ſhame on death, and my falſe Stars</l>
               <l>That would not let me live to be a King.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Roſa.</speaker>
               <l>Oh <hi>Ferdinand,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>Thou doſt not love me now.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Ferd.</speaker>
               <l>Not love <hi>Roſania?</hi>
               </l>
               <l>If woing thee to live, will not aſſure thee,</l>
               <l>Command me then to die, and ſpare the cruelty</l>
               <l>Of the fair Queen: Not love <hi>Roſania?</hi>
               </l>
               <pb n="20" facs="tcp:153589:15"/>
               <l>If thou wilt but delight to ſee me bleed,</l>
               <l>I will at ſuch a narrow paſſage let</l>
               <l>Out life, it ſhall be many hours in ebbing,</l>
               <l>And my ſoul bathing in the Crimſon ſtream,</l>
               <l>Take pleaſure to be drown'd. I have ſmall time</l>
               <l>To love, and be alive, but I will carry</l>
               <l>So true a Faith to woman hence, as ſhall</l>
               <l>Make poor the world, when I am gone to tell</l>
               <l>The ſtory yonder.—We are interrupted.</l>
            </sp>
            <stage>Enter Keepr.</stage>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Keep.</speaker>
               <l>You muſt prepare your ſelf for preſent trial;</l>
               <l>I have command to attend you to the Judges.</l>
               <l>That Gentleman, and all that did adhere</l>
               <l>To your Conſpiracy, are by the Queens</l>
               <l>Moſt gracious Mercy pardon'd.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Ferd.</speaker>
               <l>In that word</l>
               <l>Th'haſt brought me more then life; I ſhall betray,</l>
               <l>And with my too much joy undo thee again.</l>
               <l>Heaven does command thee live, I muſt obey</l>
               <l>This Summons, I ſhall ſee thee again <hi>Tiberio,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>Before I die.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Roſa.</speaker>
               <l>I'l wait upon you Sir,</l>
               <l>The Queen will not deny me that poor office;</l>
               <l>I know not how to leave you.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Ferd.</speaker>
               <l>Death and I</l>
               <l>Shall meet, and be made friends; but when we part,</l>
               <l>The world ſhall finde thy ſtory in my heart.</l>
            </sp>
            <stage>Exit.</stage>
            <stage>
               <hi>Enter Officers with Bar, Table, Stools, —then</hi> Er<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſto, Rodriguez, Leandro, <hi>Queen, ſupported by</hi> Leonario, Ferdinand, Roſania, <hi>Ladies, Gentle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men, and Guard, who ſet</hi> Ferdinand <hi>to the Bar.</hi>
            </stage>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Queen.</speaker>
               <l>Is that the priſoner at the Bar?</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Leon.</speaker>
               <l>He that pretended himſelf <hi>Ferdinand,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>Your Uncles ſon.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Q.</speaker>
               <l>Proceed to his Arraignment; my Lord <hi>Leandro,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>You know our pleaſure.</l>
            </sp>
            <pb n="21" facs="tcp:153589:15"/>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Lean.</speaker>
               <l>Although the Queen in her own Royal power,</l>
               <l>And without violating Sacred Juſtice, where</l>
               <l>Treaſon comes to invade her, and her Crown</l>
               <l>With open war, need not inſiſt upon</l>
               <l>The Forms, and Circumſtance of Law, but uſe</l>
               <l>Her Sword in preſent execution;</l>
               <l>Yet ſuch is the ſweet temper of her blood,</l>
               <l>And calmneſs of her Nature, though provok'd</l>
               <l>Ino a ſtorm, unto the great'ſt offender</l>
               <l>She ſhuts up no defence, willing to give</l>
               <l>A ſatisfaction to the world how much</l>
               <l>She doth delight in mercy. <hi>Ferdinand,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>For ſo thou doſt pretend thy ſelf, thou art</l>
               <l>Indicted of High Treaſon to Her Majeſtie,</l>
               <l>In that thou haſt uſurp'd relation to</l>
               <l>Her blood; and under name of being her Kinſman,</l>
               <l>Not onely haſt contriv'd to blaſt her Honor</l>
               <l>With Neighbor Princes, but haſt gather'd arms</l>
               <l>To wound the precious boſom of her Countrey,</l>
               <l>And tear the Crown, which Heaven and juſt Succeſſion</l>
               <l>Hath plac'd upon her Royal Head: what canſt</l>
               <l>Thou anſwer to this Treaſon?</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Ferd.</speaker>
               <l>Boldly thus.</l>
               <l>As I was never with the height of all</l>
               <l>My expectation, and the aid of Friends,</l>
               <l>Tranſported one degree above my ſelf,</l>
               <l>So muſt not <hi>Ferdinand,</hi> though his Stars have frown'd</l>
               <l>And the great eye of Providence ſeem to ſlumber.</l>
               <l>While your force thus compel'd, &amp; brought me hither</l>
               <l>With mockery of my Fate, to be arraign'd</l>
               <l>For being a Prince, have any thought beneath</l>
               <l>The Title I was born to; yet I'l not call</l>
               <l>This cruelty in you, nor in the Queen,</l>
               <l>(If I may name her ſo, without injuſtice</l>
               <l>To my own right) a Kingdom is a Garland,</l>
               <l>Worth all Contention; and where right ſeals not</l>
               <l>The true Poſſeſſion, Nature is forgotten,</l>
               <pb n="22" facs="tcp:153589:16"/>
               <l>And blood thought cheap to aſſure it; there is ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing</l>
               <l>Within that excellent Figure, that reſtrains</l>
               <l>A Paſſion here, that elſe would forth like lightning.</l>
               <l>Tis not your ſhape, which yet hath ſo much ſweetneſs</l>
               <l>Some pale religious Hermit might ſuſpect</l>
               <l>You are the bleſſed Saint he pray'd too; no,</l>
               <l>The magick's in our nature, and our blood;</l>
               <l>For both our veins full of one precious purple</l>
               <l>Strike harmony in their motion, I am <hi>Ferdinand,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>And you the fair <hi>Olivia,</hi> brothers children.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Leon.</speaker>
               <l>What inſolence is this?</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Qu.</speaker>
               <l>Oh my Lord, let him</l>
               <l>Be free to plead; for if it be no dream,</l>
               <l>His cauſe will want an Orator: By my blood,</l>
               <l>He does talk bravely.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Rodri.</speaker>
               <l>Theſe are flouriſhes.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Erneſt.</speaker>
               <l>Speak to the treaſon you are charged with</l>
               <l>And confeſs a guilt.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Leond.</speaker>
               <l>He juſtifies himſelf.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Ferd.</speaker>
               <l>If it be treaſon to be born a Prince,</l>
               <l>To have my Fathers Royal Blood move here;</l>
               <l>If it be treaſon, in my infancy</l>
               <l>To have eſcap'd by Divine Providence,</l>
               <l>When my poor life ſhould have been ſacrific'd</l>
               <l>To pleaſe a cruel Uncle, whoſe Ambition</l>
               <l>Surpris'd my Crown, and after made <hi>Olivia</hi>
               </l>
               <l>His Daughter Queen; if it be treaſon, to</l>
               <l>Have been a ſtranger thus long from my Country,</l>
               <l>Bred up with ſilence, of my name, and birth,</l>
               <l>And not till now mature to own my ſelf</l>
               <l>Before a Sun-beam; if it be treaſon</l>
               <l>After ſo long a baniſhment to weep</l>
               <l>A tear of joy upon my Countries boſom,</l>
               <l>And call her mine my juſt inheritance,</l>
               <l>Unl<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ſs you ſtain my blood with baſtardy;</l>
               <l>If it be treaſon, ſtill to love this Earth,</l>
               <pb n="23" facs="tcp:153589:16"/>
               <l>That knew ſo many of my race, her Kings,</l>
               <l>Though late unkindly arm'd to kill her Sovereign,</l>
               <l>As if the effuſion of my blood were left</l>
               <l>To make her fertile, if to love <hi>Olivia,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>My neareſt pledge of blood, although her power</l>
               <l>Hath chain'd her Prince, and made her Lord her pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoner,</l>
               <l>Who ſits with expectation to hear</l>
               <l>That ſentence that muſt make the golden Wreath,</l>
               <l>Secure upon her Brow, by blaſting mine.</l>
               <l>If this be treaſon, I am guilty <hi>Ferd nand.</hi>
               </l>
               <l>Your King's become a traitor, and muſt die</l>
               <l>A black, and moſt inglorious death.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Erneſt.</speaker>
               <l>You offer</l>
               <l>At ſome defence, but come not home; by what</l>
               <l>Engine were you tranſlated hence, or whether</l>
               <l>Convei'd? There was ſome truſt, deceiv'd, when you</l>
               <l>Were carried forth to be preſerv'd, and much</l>
               <l>Care taken ſince, in bringing of you up,</l>
               <l>And giving ſecret Fire to this Ambition.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Ferd.</speaker>
               <l>There wants no teſtimony here, of what</l>
               <l>Concerns the ſtory of my Birth and Infancy,</l>
               <l>If one dare ſpeak, and be an honeſt Lord.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Leand.</speaker>
               <l>Hows that?</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Ferd.</speaker>
               <l>Whoſe love and art ſecur'd me from all tyranny,</l>
               <l>Though here my funeral was believ'd, while I</l>
               <l>Sent to an honorable Friend, his Kinſman,</l>
               <l>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>rew ſafely to the knowledge of my ſelf</l>
               <l>At laſt, till fortune of the War betray'd me</l>
               <l>To this captivity.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Leand.</speaker>
               <l>I biuſh at thee</l>
               <l>Yong-man, whoſe fate hath made thee deſperate,</l>
               <l>And car'ſt not what mans blood thou draw'ſt along</l>
               <l>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>n thy black ſtream, or what mans faith thou mak'ſt</l>
               <l>As hateful as thy crimes.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Erneſt.</speaker>
               <l>That confederate</l>
               <l>Sure has ſome name, declare him, that he may</l>
               <pb n="24" facs="tcp:153589:17"/>
               <l>Thank you for his reward, and loſe his head for't.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Quee.</speaker>
               <l>We always ſee that men in ſuch high natur<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
               </l>
               <l>Deform'd, and guilty, want not ſpecious ſhapes</l>
               <l>To gain their practice friendſhip, and compaſſion,</l>
               <l>But he ſhall feel the puniſhment; d'you ſmile?</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Ferd.</speaker>
               <l>A womans anger is but worth it Madam;</l>
               <l>And if I may have freedom, I muſt ſay,</l>
               <l>Not in contempt of what you ſeem, nor help'd</l>
               <l>By overcharge of paſſion, which but makes</l>
               <l>A fruitleſs noiſe; I have a ſenſe of what</l>
               <l>I am to loſe, a life, but I am ſo fortified</l>
               <l>With valiant thoughts, and innocence, I ſhall,</l>
               <l>When my laſt breath is giving up, to loſe</l>
               <l>Its ſelf i'th' air, be ſo remote from fear,</l>
               <l>That I will caſt my face into one ſmile,</l>
               <l>Which ſhall when I am dead, acquit all trembling,</l>
               <l>And be a ſtory to the world, how free</l>
               <l>From paleneſs <hi>Ferdinand</hi> took leave of earth.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Roſa.</speaker>
               <l>Alas my Lord, you forget me, that can</l>
               <l>Part with ſuch courage.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Ferd.</speaker>
               <l>I forget indeed,</l>
               <l>I thought of death with honor, but my love</l>
               <l>Hath found a way to chide me; O my Boy,</l>
               <l>I can weep now.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Leon.</speaker>
               <l>A ſudden change, he weeps.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Quee.</speaker>
               <l>What Boy is that?</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Ferd.</speaker>
               <l>I prethee take thy ſelf away.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Quee.</speaker>
               <l>Your Spirit</l>
               <l>Does melt it ſeems, and you begin to think</l>
               <l>A life is worth preſerving, though with Infamy.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Ferd.</speaker>
               <l>Goodneſs thy aid again, and tell this great</l>
               <l>Proud woman, I have a Spirit ſcorns her pity.</l>
               <l>Come hither Boy, and let me kiſs thee; thus</l>
               <l>At parting with a good, and pretty ſervant,</l>
               <l>I can without my honor ſtain'd ſhed tears:</l>
               <l>I took thee from thy Friends, to make thee mine;</l>
               <pb n="25" facs="tcp:153589:17"/>
               <l>Is it not truth Boy.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Roſa.</speaker>
               <l>Yes my Lord.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Ferd.</speaker>
               <l>And mean't when I was King to make thee great,</l>
               <l>And ſhall I not, when I can live no longer,</l>
               <l>To cheriſh thee at farewel, drop a tear?</l>
               <l>That I could weep my ſoul upon thee,—But</l>
               <l>You are to ſlow me thinks. I am ſo far</l>
               <l>From dread, I think your forms too tedious.</l>
               <l>I expect my ſentence.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Quee.</speaker>
               <l>Let it ſtay a while.</l>
               <l>What ſecret flame is this? Honor protect me!</l>
               <l>Your Graces fair excuſe, for you—I ſhall</l>
               <l>Return again —</l>
            </sp>
            <stage>Exit.</stage>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Ferd.</speaker>
               <l>And I, with better guard</l>
               <l>After my ſilence in the Grave, to meet</l>
               <l>And plead this cauſe.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Erneſt.</speaker>
               <l>He is diſtracted ſure;</l>
               <l>His perſon I could pity, but his inſolence</l>
               <l>Wants an example; what if we proceed</l>
               <l>To ſentence?</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Leon.</speaker>
               <l>I ſuppoſe the Queen will clear</l>
               <l>Your duties in't.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Leand.</speaker>
               <l>But I'l acquaint her.</l>
            </sp>
            <stage>Exit.</stage>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Rod.</speaker>
               <l>My Lord <hi>Leandro</hi>'s gone.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Erneſt.</speaker>
               <l>His cenſure will</l>
               <l>Be one with ours.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Ferd.</speaker>
               <l>Yet ſhall I publiſh who</l>
               <l>Thou art? I ſhall not die with a calm ſoul</l>
               <l>And leave thee in this cloud.</l>
            </sp>
            <stage>Enter the Queen and Leandro.</stage>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Roſa.</speaker>
               <l>By no means Sir. —The Queen.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Quee.</speaker>
               <l>Whoſe ſervice is ſo forward to our State,</l>
               <l>That when Our pleaſure's known, not to proceed,</l>
               <l>They dare be officious in his Sentence? Are</l>
               <l>We Queen, or do we move by your Protection?</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Erneſt.</speaker>
               <l>Madam, the Prince—</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Quee.</speaker>
               <l>My Lord, you have a Queen.</l>
               <pb n="26" facs="tcp:153589:18"/>
               <l>I not ſuſpect his wiſdom Sir, but he</l>
               <l>Hath no Commiſſion here to be a Judge,</l>
               <l>You were beſt circumſcribe our Regal power,</l>
               <l>And by your ſelves condemn, or pardon all,</l>
               <l>And we ſign to your will: The offence, which you</l>
               <l>Call treaſon ſtrikes at us, and we releaſe it,</l>
               <l>Let me but ſee one curl in any Brow:</l>
               <l>Attend the priſoner hither; —Kiſs our hand.</l>
               <l>Are you ſo mercileſs to think this man</l>
               <l>Fit for a Scaffold. You ſhall Sir be near us,</l>
               <l>And if in this confuſion of your Fortunes</l>
               <l>You can finde gratitude, and love, deſpair not.</l>
               <l>Theſe men that now oppoſe, may finde your title</l>
               <l>Clear to the Kingdom too: Be Sir collected,</l>
               <l>And let us uſe your arm.</l>
            </sp>
            <stage>Exit. Supported by Ferdinand.</stage>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Roſa.</speaker>
               <l>What change is here?</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Leand.</speaker>
               <l>What think you of this Lords?</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Rodri.</speaker>
               <l>I dare not think.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Leon.</speaker>
               <l>Affronted thus? O my vext heart.</l>
            </sp>
            <stage>Exit.</stage>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Roſa.</speaker>
               <l>Ile follow ſtill, and if this be no dream,</l>
               <l>We have ſcap'd a Brook, to meet a greater ſtream.</l>
            </sp>
            <stage>Exeunt.</stage>
         </div>
         <div n="3" type="act">
            <head>ACT. III.</head>
            <stage>
               <hi>Enter</hi> Rodriguez, Erneſto.</stage>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Erneſt.</speaker>
               <l>THough I believ'd her paſſionate, and like</l>
               <l>A Sea, tempeſtuous in her anger, I</l>
               <l>Never thought ſhe would marry him.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Rodri.</speaker>
               <l>She's the Queen,</l>
               <l>But with what honor ſhe could quit the Prince,</l>
               <l>Who (without treaſon) did deſerve her too,</l>
               <l>Comes not within my reach.</l>
            </sp>
            <pb n="27" facs="tcp:153589:18"/>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Erneſt.</speaker>
               <l>If you conſider</l>
               <l>He has been valiant for her to great purpoſe,</l>
               <l>And brought a priſoner home, to mount his Gennet:</l>
               <l>It was a pretty ſervice.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Rod.</speaker>
               <l>How does he bear it.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Erneſt.</speaker>
               <l>He's here, you may enquire it.</l>
            </sp>
            <stage>Enter Leonario (with Letters) and a Servant.</stage>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Leon.</speaker>
               <l>Be ſwift and faithful, <hi>Arragon</hi> bleeds here,</l>
               <l>Nothing but War can right my cauſe and honor.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Serv.</speaker>
               <l>Expect an army great as your own thoughts</l>
               <l>To cut the way to your revenge.</l>
            </sp>
            <stage>Exit.</stage>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Leon.</speaker>
               <l>My Lords <hi>Rodriguez</hi> and <hi>Erneſto.</hi>
               </l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Ambo.</speaker>
               <l>Your Graces ſervants.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Leon.</speaker>
               <l>A man may take the benefit of this Garden,</l>
               <l>Without a Court offence, youh ave had the day</l>
               <l>Of triumph, and the Queen already teeming,</l>
               <l>To bleſs the Kingdom with an Heir; and yet</l>
               <l>You ſee I walk like a poor Neighbor Prince,</l>
               <l>And have my heart ſtill.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Rod.</speaker>
               <l>I am glad you bear it ſo.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Leon.</speaker>
               <l>Nor have I a meaning</l>
               <l>To run my ſelf into deſpair, or ſtrangle</l>
               <l>My better hopes, out of pure melancholy,</l>
               <l>I praiſe the influence of my Stars; there is</l>
               <l>A fire in Cupids Quiver, that will ſcorch</l>
               <l>Through armor; and what's womans fleſh and blood</l>
               <l>To make reſiſtance, though I did not dance</l>
               <l>Upon the marriage night, I wiſh'd her joyes</l>
               <l>I'th' morning.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Erneſt.</speaker>
               <l>Her heart ſhew'd ſhe was pleas'd</l>
               <l>With what ſhe had done; ſhe was as active as</l>
               <l>The air before ſhe went to Bed.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Rod.</speaker>
               <l>But I</l>
               <l>Obſerv'd a declination in the King,</l>
               <l>And as the night approach'd, which ſhould have more</l>
               <l>Inlarg'd his mirth, he grew more melancholy.</l>
            </sp>
            <pb n="28" facs="tcp:153589:19"/>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Leon.</speaker>
               <l>Strange! And ſuch a Bride that took him from</l>
               <l>So great a loſs, to place him in her boſom;</l>
               <l>But he was mark'd for the Queens thoughts, and I</l>
               <l>By deſtiny to bring this pair of Pidgeons</l>
               <l>Together. I expect no more reward,</l>
               <l>The Willow Garland Crowns me, but the Prince</l>
               <l>Is here ſtill.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Erneſt.</speaker>
               <l>Your highneſs hath a noble temper.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Rod.</speaker>
               <l>How ere he ſeem to cover it, his ſoul</l>
               <l>Hath a deep apprehenſion of the affront.</l>
               <l>Let's leave him, our diſcourſe may be diſpleaſing.</l>
               <l>We are ſervants to your Grace.</l>
            </sp>
            <stage>Exeunt Lords</stage>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Leon.</speaker>
               <l>Y'have honor'd me.</l>
               <l>Think I am tame ſtill? let the inconſtant Queen</l>
               <l>Secure her thoughts, and glory in my ſilence;</l>
               <l>This heart is laboring a revenge.</l>
               <stage>Enter Captain.</stage>
               <l>Captain, what news? the Court is merry ſtill?</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Cap.</speaker>
               <l>Not altogether ſo merry as it was hop'd for.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Leon.</speaker>
               <l>Can there be an eclipſe already?</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Cap.</speaker>
               <l>I have not read the Almanack for this year,</l>
               <l>But by my Court Aſtronomie, I finde</l>
               <l>Our Sun and Moon are in no Conjunction;</l>
               <l>They take their fit by turns, the King was cold</l>
               <l>And full of flegm laſt night, and they that wait</l>
               <l>Neer both, report the Queen this morning look'd</l>
               <l>As ſhe had wept.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Leon.</speaker>
               <l>O, tears of joy.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Cap.</speaker>
               <l>Of anger rather, if you ſaw her ſullenneſs.</l>
               <l>She frowns on every man, ſhe turn'd away</l>
               <l>One of her ſervants but this morning, for</l>
               <l>Preſenting her with Verſes, that did praiſe</l>
               <l>The King, and wiſh her fruitful. Her own Page</l>
               <l>Was whipt, for ſaying the King lay with the Queen</l>
               <l>And might for ought he knew, get her with childe ere morning.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Leon.</speaker>
               <l>Thou art humorous.</l>
            </sp>
            <pb n="29" facs="tcp:153589:19"/>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Cap.</speaker>
               <l>And ſo are they.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Leon.</speaker>
               <l>This begins well; and what</l>
               <l>Do people talk abroad of me, and my</l>
               <l>Affront?</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Cap.</speaker>
               <l>Why, they ſay they are ſorry for you,</l>
               <l>Eſpecially the women.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Leon.</speaker>
               <l>Thou art pleaſant.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Cap.</speaker>
               <l>Some that are cheif in counſel, privately</l>
               <l>Suſpect it but a trick of State; and that</l>
               <l>You had diſcover'd underhand the Queen</l>
               <l>Was not—</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Leon.</speaker>
               <l>Leave this mirth; let me indear thy care</l>
               <l>For my intelligence at Court; I muſt</l>
               <l>Not off ſo tamely; and expect me here,</l>
               <l>After a ſmall diſpatch, I have more to impart.</l>
            </sp>
            <stage>Exit.</stage>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Cap.</speaker>
               <l>Your humble creature ſtill Sir. 'Las poor Gent'</l>
               <l>Were I as capable to be entertain'd now, in revenge</l>
               <l>I would mount all the Madams in the Court,</l>
               <l>There ſhould be nothing like a woman in't,</l>
               <l>But I would touz and tumble: Who are theſe?</l>
            </sp>
            <stage>Enter two Citizens.</stage>
            <sp>
               <speaker>1. <hi>Cit.</hi>
               </speaker>
               <l>Save you Sir.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Cap.</speaker>
               <l>It may be ſo.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>2. <hi>Cit.</hi>
               </speaker>
               <l>Pray Sir take no offence, we have been en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quiring</l>
               <l>About the Court for two Gentlemen.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Cap.</speaker>
               <l>And cannot your four eies ſee two Gentlemen</l>
               <l>I'th' Court?</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>1. <hi>Cit.</hi>
               </speaker>
               <l>Excuſe us Sir, we have ſeen many, you</l>
               <l>May gueſs we have relation to the Citie Sir,</l>
               <l>And would be glad to meet two of our old acquain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tances,</l>
               <l>A brace of our Tribe,</l>
               <l>We hear, tranſlated firſt out of the Citie,</l>
               <l>To be Sons o'th' Sword, are ſince turn'd Courtiers.</l>
               <l>Pray d'ye know 'em?</l>
            </sp>
            <stage>Enter Lieutenant and Violinda.</stage>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Cap.</speaker>
               <l>Yes children of the Gown, but their imployment</l>
               <l>Wo not give 'em leave to attend ſuch vulgar confe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rence,</l>
               <pb n="30" facs="tcp:153589:20"/>
               <l>And here comes one of the Moon-calves, does he loo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
               </l>
               <l>Like a Haberdaſher, that's one of the Maids of Honor</l>
               <l>The Weiſel loves a Hens-Neſt, and I have ſetled</l>
               <l>This perſwaſion, That no woman can hold out,</l>
               <l>Now he is ſworn a ſervant extraordinary.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>1. <hi>Cit.</hi>
               </speaker>
               <l>Sir do you know us?</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Lieut.</speaker>
               <l>No.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>2. <hi>Cit.</hi>
               </speaker>
               <l>We were your neighbors, and of the ſame trade</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Cap.</speaker>
               <l>They'l make him ſweat; how the Rogue glotes upon 'em</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>1. <hi>Cit.</hi>
               </speaker>
               <l>We were of your acquaintance, when you ſold Garters.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Lieut.</speaker>
               <l>Go hang your ſelves.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>2. <hi>Cit.</hi>
               </speaker>
               <l>And Statute-lace.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Viol.</speaker>
               <l>What are theſe?</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Lieut.</speaker>
               <l>Poor men that had ſome loſſes late by fire,</l>
               <l>And would become my Clients to procure</l>
               <l>Some Letters Patents to beg by; alas, they are half diſtracted.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>1. <hi>Cit.</hi>
               </speaker>
               <l>He's proud— I have a parcel of Periwigs</l>
               <l>Pleaſe you, for old acquaintance, put 'em off for me,</l>
               <l>Among ſome friends of yours at Court, whoſe skulls</l>
               <l>Are but thinly furniſh'd; the hair is of a</l>
               <l>Gentlewomans ſpinning.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Cap.</speaker>
               <l>I could love this Citizen, and ow him any money</l>
               <l>For his confident abuſing him.</l>
               <stage>Exit Violinda.</stage>
               <l>He has brib'd her abſence with ſome Ring or Bracelet,</l>
               <l>Leaſt ſhe ſhould taſte the diſcovery now.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>1. <hi>Cit.</hi>
               </speaker>
               <l>Methinks you need not be ſo proud.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Lieut.</speaker>
               <l>I would have you to know that I am an ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>traordinary—</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Cap.</speaker>
               <l>Proud Coxcomb.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Lieut.</speaker>
               <l>Servant to the Queen. What I was,</l>
               <l>I am willing to forget;</l>
               <l>What you are, is apparant, I defie the</l>
               <l>Dunghil I came from, and it is <hi>ſcandalum</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Magnatum</hi> to be ſo ſaucy.</l>
            </sp>
            <stage>Exit.</stage>
            <pb n="31" facs="tcp:153589:20"/>
            <sp>
               <speaker>1. <hi>Cit.</hi>
               </speaker>
               <l>I will not leave your worſhip ſo.</l>
            </sp>
            <stage>Exit.</stage>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Cap.</speaker>
               <l>What will this Raſcal do with himſelf?</l>
               <l>Here comes the other Fool to make up the <hi>Gemini.</hi>
               </l>
            </sp>
            <stage>Enter Antient with two Petitions.</stage>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Ant.</speaker>
               <l>Hum, I will not know him—Let me ſee—</l>
               <l>The humble Petition of—</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>2. <hi>Cit.</hi>
               </speaker>
               <l>Save you Matter—</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Ant.</speaker>
               <l>Prethee fellow do not trouble me—</l>
               <l>Humbly praying— The Queen ſhall ſign it.</l>
               <l>Let me ſee this other—</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Cap.</speaker>
               <l>Who the devil will bring him a Petition,</l>
               <l>This Whelp has diſcovered him, and now would</l>
               <l>Pretend himſelf moſt buſily employ'd</l>
               <l>About Petitions to the Queen.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Ant.</speaker>
               <l>Hum, ſhall daily pray for— Hum.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Cap.</speaker>
               <l>More wit and money a your ſide; for your</l>
               <l>Extraordinary place will not hold out.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>2. <hi>Cit.</hi>
               </speaker>
               <l>Sir I have a ſute to you.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Ant.</speaker>
               <l>Is it Embroidered Sattin Sir, or Scarlet?</l>
               <l>Yet if your buſineſs do hold weight and conſequence,</l>
               <l> may deſerve to wear your thankfulneſs</l>
               <l>In Tiſſue or cloth of Bodkin; Ermines are for Princes.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>2. <hi>Cit.</hi>
               </speaker>
               <l>Alas my Suite is not worth your wearing.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Ant.</speaker>
               <l>Good faith Sir you muſt excuſe me, at this time</l>
               <l>My attendance is expected at the Counſel, come</l>
               <l>To my Chamber by five a clock in the morning</l>
               <l>Four days hence, and you ſhall be ſure to finde</l>
               <l>Me—</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Cap.</speaker>
               <l>A ſleep.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>2. <hi>Cit.</hi>
               </speaker>
               <l>But do you not know me?</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Ant.</speaker>
               <l>Hum. Yes I have ſeen your phiſnomy, were you</l>
               <l>Never in a conſpicuous p<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ace, called the Pillorie.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>2. <hi>Cit.</hi>
               </speaker>
               <l>How, the Pillory?</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Cap.</speaker>
               <l>A skirmiſh, and it be thy will.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>2. <hi>Cit.</hi>
               </speaker>
               <l>If it were not in the Court Garden,</l>
               <l>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> would beat out thy brains.</l>
            </sp>
            <pb n="32" facs="tcp:153589:21"/>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Ant.</speaker>
               <l>Take heed, for I am an extraordinary—Sir</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>2. <hi>Cit.</hi>
               </speaker>
               <l>Ratcatcher.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Cap.</speaker>
               <l>You may beat out his brains here as ſecurely</l>
               <l>As if you met him i'th' market; Marry if you do</l>
               <l>Not kill him outright, it is but the loſs</l>
               <l>Of your hand.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>2. <hi>Cit.</hi>
               </speaker>
               <l>I would it were but the loſs of my left hand</l>
               <l>To beat one of thy eyes out— Are you an Ancient?</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Ant.</speaker>
               <l>Thank you for that, ſo I might deſerve</l>
               <l>To be beaten. I am an extraordinary Sir.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Cap.</speaker>
               <l>And deſerves to be beaten accordingly.</l>
               <l>You may kick him without danger.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>2. <hi>Cit.</hi>
               </speaker>
               <l>May I?</l>
            </sp>
            <stage>
               <hi>Enter</hi> 1. <hi>Citizen kicking the Lieutenant.</hi>
            </stage>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Cap.</speaker>
               <l>Look, your friend will ſhew you a preſident</l>
               <l>He is acquainted with the Court latitude.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>1. <hi>Cit.</hi>
               </speaker>
               <l>This is no ſtriking.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Lieut.</speaker>
               <l>I know it is not.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Cap.</speaker>
               <l>They are ſubtle knaves, and know the Law<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
               </l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Lieut.</speaker>
               <l>A pox upon 'em, I feel it.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Ant.</speaker>
               <l>At their peril ſay I, theſe poor things</l>
               <l>Do not believe that we are extraordinary men,</l>
               <l>I ſhall know you another time, I ſhall.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Cap.</speaker>
               <l>If you had known him now it had been better</l>
               <l>For your hanches. Well, I ha' not done with</l>
               <l>Theſe whelps yet, till they are undone.</l>
               <l>I ſhall never be ſufficiently revenged for their affron<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
               </l>
               <l>At Court. The Prince commanded me to</l>
               <l>Expect his return here, I'l not leave</l>
               <stage>Enter Roſania.</stage>
               <l>The Garden. Who's this?</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Roſa.</speaker>
               <l>Is perjury no ſin? or can Heaven be</l>
               <l>So buſie or a ſleep? Such crimes of men</l>
               <l>Paſs with impunity? Let this wake your anger:</l>
               <l>This; <hi>Ferdinand</hi> is married, all his vows</l>
               <pb n="33" facs="tcp:153589:21"/>
               <l>Scatter'd in th' air, diſpers'd like witherd leaves,</l>
               <l>And hurried on the wings of ſome rude Wind,</l>
               <l>Whoſe pride was to deflour the Spring; Oh <hi>Ferdinand,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>Couldſt thou, whilſt yet thy breath was warm with love,</l>
               <l>With love of me, call back thy faith, and tear</l>
               <l>Thy Heart from mine to plant it in her Boſom?</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Capt.</speaker>
               <l>How's this?</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Roſa.</speaker>
               <l>What though ſhe be a Queen? could any thirſt</l>
               <l>Of preſent title flatter thy Soul from me?</l>
               <l>I that left all for thee, and would have calld</l>
               <l>Death for thy cauſe a triumph, now muſt live</l>
               <l>The ſcorn of my own thoughts, deſpis'd by thee.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Capt.</speaker>
               <l>Here's a new buſineſs; this obſcures me quaintly.</l>
            </sp>
            <stage>Enter Leandro.</stage>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Lean.</speaker>
               <l>The King commands you not to leave the Garden.</l>
               <l>He eſpied you from the Gallerie Window, and</l>
               <l>Would have you here attend him.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Roſa.</speaker>
               <l>Sir, may I</l>
               <l>Without offence, ask if the King be merry?</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Leand.</speaker>
               <l>We are ſcarce yet acquainted with his nature,</l>
               <l>But we obſerve no Jubilie in his eyes,</l>
               <l>Nor is the Queen ſo pleaſant as our hopes</l>
               <l>Did promiſe after Marriage.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Roſa.</speaker>
               <l>Pray excuſe this boldneſs.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Leand.</speaker>
               <l>You'l expect his pleaſure here?</l>
            </sp>
            <stage>Exit.</stage>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Roſa.</speaker>
               <l>'Tis my ambition once more to ſee,</l>
               <l>And ſpeak with him, and if his language break not</l>
               <stage>Enter Queen, Leandro.</stage>
               <l>My Heart, I'l take my leave—the Queen.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Leand.</speaker>
               <l>He is a Servant to whom the King</l>
               <l>Was pleas'd to ſhew affection, when he had</l>
               <l>No expectation of your Royall favour.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Que.</speaker>
               <l>I do remember, I obſerv'd him once</l>
               <l>Uſe more than common paſſion to this ſervant,</l>
               <l>And if we may build any confidence</l>
               <l>Upon a fair aſpect, he may deſerve it.</l>
               <pb n="34" facs="tcp:153589:22"/>
               <l>Say we would ſpeak with him; my Heart's oppreſt</l>
               <l>With melancholy, ſomething tels my ſpirit</l>
               <l>I am too tame; have I advanc'd a thing</l>
               <l>Without a name to perch on the ſame Cloud</l>
               <l>With me, and for his ſake ſlighted a Prince,</l>
               <l>My Honour, and his Faith, tranſported with</l>
               <l>My folly and his charms of tongue and perſon?</l>
               <l>And dares he pay me with neglect and coldneſs?</l>
               <l>Oh my vext ſoul! but he ſhall find I have</l>
               <l>A ſenſe of my diſhonour; and yet open</l>
               <l>Wayes become triviall and poor revengers,</l>
               <l>I will doe ſomething that ſhall ſting him to</l>
               <l>Repentance; my Lord you now may leave us.</l>
               <stage>Ex. Leandro.</stage>
               <l>Sir of what Country are you?</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Roſa.</speaker>
               <l>Of <hi>Valentia.</hi>
               </l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Que.</speaker>
               <l>Your name?</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Roſa.</speaker>
               <l>
                  <hi>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>iberio.</hi>
               </l>
               <l>My Parents not ignoble, yet too haſty</l>
               <l>I'th' apprehenſion of Prince <hi>Ferdinand;</hi>
               </l>
               <l>His Fortune (if I may yet call him ſo)</l>
               <l>Gave me to be his page, I muſt confeſs</l>
               <l>My diligence thriv'd ſo well ſince I came to him,</l>
               <l>That he did value me above his ſervant.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Que.</speaker>
               <l>Yet I've not ſeen you wait ſince we were married.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Roſa.</speaker>
               <l>It was no want of dutie Madam, I</l>
               <l>Had late ſome wraſtling with a Feaver, that</l>
               <l>Compeld me to my Chamber, and diſabled me</l>
               <l>For fit attendance.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Que.</speaker>
               <l>Why doſt weep?</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Roſa.</speaker>
               <l>I Madam?</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Que.</speaker>
               <l>I ſee the tears.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Roſa.</speaker>
               <l>They are not ſorrow then to ſee my Maſter</l>
               <l>Poſſeſt of ſo much happineſs in your love,</l>
               <l>And I am confident, his ſoul ſo full</l>
               <l>Of Honour and regard to your great virtues</l>
               <l>Will ſeal him worth your gracious favours Madam,</l>
               <pb n="35" facs="tcp:153589:22"/>
               <l>And the worlds Envie.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Que.</speaker>
               <l>I'l not blame him now</l>
               <l>For loving thee; and ſo much hath thy faith</l>
               <l>And innocence prevail'd, thou ſha't tranſlate</l>
               <l>Thy ſervice, and be mine, he ſhall conſent.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Roſ.</speaker>
               <l>I am to both moſt humble.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Que.</speaker>
               <l>Prethee tell me,</l>
               <l>Making ſo much of thee, he do's impart</l>
               <l>Sometimes the ſecrets of his boſom to thee.</l>
               <l>Tell me what fault he has, for thou know'ſt all.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Roſa.</speaker>
               <l>'Las Madam I know none,</l>
               <l>Or if I did, it ill became the truſt</l>
               <l>And dutie of a ſervant to reveal 'em</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Que.</speaker>
               <l>Thou wer't his bed-fellow?</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Roſ.</speaker>
               <l>Gracious Madam—</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Que.</speaker>
               <l>Do's he not wanton in the night, and talk</l>
               <l>Of Miſtreſſes.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Roſ.</speaker>
               <l>By truth not to me Madam.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Que.</speaker>
               <l>Diſſemble not</l>
               <l>know he has a Miſtreſs.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Roſa.</speaker>
               <l>If love were ever ſo unkind to him—</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Que.</speaker>
               <l>Unkind? why I'ſt a ſin to love? I ſhall</l>
               <l>Suſpect thy Youth has not been free, thy looks</l>
               <l>Betray ſome ſeeds of Love.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Roſa.</speaker>
               <l>By all that's good</l>
               <l>never was in love but with my Maſter.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Capt.</speaker>
               <l>Good.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Que.</speaker>
               <l>He is not worth it.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Roſa.</speaker>
               <l>Madam.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Que.</speaker>
               <l>Be wiſe, and govern well thy hopes. I'l help</l>
               <l>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>hee to a Miſtreſs; th'aſt no Miſtreſs yet?</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Roſa.</speaker>
               <l>But you ſelf Madam.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Que.</speaker>
               <l>It ſhall be no other.</l>
               <l>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>hy Maſter is ingratefull.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Roſ.</speaker>
               <l>Goodneſs aid him.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Que.</speaker>
               <l>And wiſdom thee, thou art a pretty youth,</l>
               <pb n="36" facs="tcp:153589:23"/>
               <l>I will reward thee better, if thou canſt</l>
               <l>Be faithfull and obey.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Roſa.</speaker>
               <l>In all things Madam</l>
               <l>That ſhall become your creature.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Que.</speaker>
               <l>'Tis not ſafe</l>
               <l>To play with a Queens favours, you ſhall wait</l>
               <l>Neer us; forget thy Maſter, and be happy.</l>
            </sp>
            <stage>Exit.</stage>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Roſ.</speaker>
               <l>What clue can guide me in this Labyrinth?</l>
               <l>I would when I had loſt <hi>Ferdinands</hi> Heart</l>
               <l>I had loſt my underſtanding. She returns.</l>
            </sp>
            <stage>Enter Queen.</stage>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Que.</speaker>
               <l>The King is comming this way; now be free,</l>
               <l>Thou ſha't have reaſon afterwards to bleſs</l>
               <l>Thy fate, this cannot choſe but vex him.</l>
            </sp>
            <stage>The Queen is plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſant with Roſ.</stage>
            <stage>Enter Ferdinand.</stage>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Fer.</speaker>
               <l>The Queen ſo pleaſant? ſhe has loſt her ſullenneſs,</l>
               <l>Playes with his Hair, and ſmiles.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Roſ.</speaker>
               <l>Madam, the King</l>
               <l>Obſerves us.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Ferd.</speaker>
               <l>Stroaks his cheek too, ſhe does want</l>
               <l>A <hi>Ganimede;</hi> my poor <hi>Roſania</hi>
               </l>
               <l>Art thou the path ſhe walks on to revenge,</l>
               <l>All is not well within her Heart but mine</l>
               <l>Sinks with the heavy preſſure—ſhe is gone.</l>
               <stage>Exit Queen</stage>
               <l>The Queen does grace you much <hi>Tiberio,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>Thoſe favours are not common.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Roſa.</speaker>
               <l>She is pleas'd</l>
               <l>For your ſake Sir to caſt ſome ſmile upon me;</l>
               <l>I know 'twas your requeſt ſhe ſhould be kind,</l>
               <l>To keep my Heart a live.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Ferd.</speaker>
               <l>Th'art not diſcover'd.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Roſ.</speaker>
               <l>Did not you diſcourſe</l>
               <l>My ſtory to her?</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Ferd.</speaker>
               <l>I?</l>
            </sp>
            <pb n="37" facs="tcp:153589:23"/>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Roſ.</speaker>
               <l>Take heed, yet this</l>
               <l>Will adde but a thin Feather to the ſcale</l>
               <l>Of my misfortune, ſhe knows all, and in</l>
               <l>The pittie of my ſufferings ſayes you are</l>
               <l>Not worth my love, and calls you moſt ingratefull</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Ferd.</speaker>
               <l>We are both loſt, till now there was ſome hope</l>
               <l>How to repair thy ſorrow.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Roſa.</speaker>
               <l>Do not mock me;</l>
               <l>'Tis a worſe tyranny than to kill, to laugh</l>
               <l>At what you have made wretched, 'tis as poſſible</l>
               <l>To call paſt ages back.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Ferd.</speaker>
               <l>Take heed <hi>Roſania,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>And be not Judge of what thou know'ſt not, deareſt.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Roſa.</speaker>
               <l>I know too much.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Ferd.</speaker>
               <l>That I am Married.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Roſa.</speaker>
               <l>Ther's no truth in Man.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Ferd.</speaker>
               <l>You are too raſh; for there is truth in me,</l>
               <l>In <hi>Ferdinand,</hi> though in thy thoughts held black</l>
               <l>And ſtaind prodigiouſly with breach of faith,</l>
               <l>I have not broke my vow, do not compell me</l>
               <l>By thy unbelief to do a Sin I hate</l>
               <l>As much as I love thee.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Roſa.</speaker>
               <l>Have you a Soul?</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Ferd.</speaker>
               <l>Yes, and thy Eye ſhall read it, be but calm,</l>
               <l>That Soul, thou once didſt love, white with his firſt</l>
               <l>Simplicity and faith; I wo'not urge</l>
               <l>In my excuſe the beautie of the Queen</l>
               <l>Enough to melt a Scythian into love,</l>
               <l>But call to mind my dear <hi>Roſania,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>And do but put upon thee <hi>Ferdinand</hi>
               </l>
               <l>So late forgotten by his Stars, a priſoner,</l>
               <l>Slav'd like a villain at the bar, expecting</l>
               <l>At every breath his ſentence, nay admit</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Roſania,</hi> the beſt part of his Soul</l>
               <l>Stood like a weeping fountain to take leave</l>
               <l>Of what ſhe never muſt ſalute agen:</l>
               <pb n="38" facs="tcp:153589:24"/>
               <l>In this extreme, to preſerve <hi>Ferdinand</hi>
               </l>
               <l>And ſave <hi>Roſania,</hi> wouldſt thou ſcorn the breath</l>
               <l>Of mercy, that did Court thee from the Lips</l>
               <l>Of a great Queen? couldſt thou love <hi>Roſania,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>If thou wert <hi>Ferdinand</hi> to loſe thy ſelf?</l>
               <l>Whom ſhe would follow in a ſtream of tears,</l>
               <l>And when ſhe had made an Iland of thy tomb,</l>
               <l>Striving to ſwim to thee, ſhe could not chooſe,</l>
               <l>But drown her ſelf in her own waves. I prethee</l>
               <l>Take reaſon to thee, and when th'aſt conſider'd—</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Roſa.</speaker>
               <l>Perſwade me I am not <hi>Roſania,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>And I will ſay 'tis virtue, and that yet</l>
               <l>Your heart may grow with mine; is not the Queen</l>
               <l>Poſſeſt of that which ſhould have been my title,</l>
               <l>A Wife to <hi>Ferdinand?</hi>
               </l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Ferd.</speaker>
               <l>'Tis confeſt the world</l>
               <l>Doth think it ſo, I did conſent to ceremony.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Roſ.</speaker>
               <l>Call you injoying of the Queen but ceremony?</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Ferd.</speaker>
               <l>Pauſe there, and if thou haſt but ſo much charity</l>
               <l>To think I dare not blaſpheme Heaven, I'l call</l>
               <l>That, and the Angels boldly to my witneſs,</l>
               <l>The Queen's to me a ſtranger yet.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Roſ.</speaker>
               <l>A miracle.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Ferd.</speaker>
               <l>Retain but love, as thou preſerv'ſt thy ſweetneſs,</l>
               <l>And that will teach thee to believe that <hi>Ferdinand,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>How ere ſaluted King is ſtill thy ſubject,</l>
               <l>And though her Husband, in my faith to thee</l>
               <l>The Marriage Bed hath ſtill our Virgin ſheets;</l>
               <l>A Brother might embrace a Siſter, with</l>
               <l>The heat I brought; that this is truth, the power</l>
               <l>And name I have, ſhall only ſerve to make</l>
               <l>Our flight ſecure into another Kingdom,</l>
               <l>And when I part with theſe new ſhining glories,</l>
               <l>Thy faith will be confirm'd, and thou acknowledge</l>
               <l>I ventur'd much to keep my Heart thy ſervant.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Roſ.</speaker>
               <l>I know not what to ſay; is not the Queen</l>
               <l>Diſpleas'd?</l>
            </sp>
            <pb n="39" facs="tcp:153589:24"/>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Ferd.</speaker>
               <l>She is, but cunningly diſguiſeth</l>
               <l>Her paſſion to the World; but I forgot</l>
               <l>What muſt inlarge my fears of her revenge</l>
               <l>If thou be known <hi>Roſania.</hi>
               </l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Roſ.</speaker>
               <l>Loſe that fear,</l>
               <l>I am ſtill ſafe, and now I ſee the cauſe</l>
               <l>Makes her repent her favours, and thy greatneſs;</l>
               <l>Forgive me <hi>Ferdinand,</hi> and yet I know not,</l>
               <l>All is not well, ther's poyſon in this Balſom</l>
               <l>Prepar'd for thee.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Ferd.</speaker>
               <l>From whom?</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Roſ.</speaker>
               <l>
                  <hi>Roſania.</hi>
               </l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Ferd.</speaker>
               <l>When ſhe ſhall but conſent to have me dye,</l>
               <l>She ſhall not trouble poyſon to ſend off</l>
               <l>My deſpis'd life, my ſoul in juſt obedience</l>
               <l>To her command will take a cheerfull flight</l>
               <l>In hope to ſerve her in the other World.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Roſ.</speaker>
               <l>You ſhall know more hereafter, and let this</l>
               <l>Secure your thoughts, ſhe yet beleeves me what</l>
               <l>This ſhape preſents, but without wiſe prevention,</l>
               <l>I fear I ſhall not live too long conceal'd;</l>
               <l>I dare not ſay her honour is a bleeding,</l>
               <l>But a Queen thus diſtaſted may not find</l>
               <l>That Ice within her bloud; we are interrupted.</l>
            </sp>
            <stage>Enter Rodriguez.</stage>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Rodri.</speaker>
               <l>Your pardon Sir; 'tis the Queens pleaſure</l>
               <l>This Gentleman attend her in the Gallery.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Ferd.</speaker>
               <l>He ſhall wait her commands—</l>
               <stage>Ex. Rodri.</stage>
               <l>I know not what to counſell, 'tis not ſafe</l>
               <l>Sweet to neglect her, yet my fears of ſome</l>
               <l>Ill fate, are round about me like a miſt,</l>
               <l>And dark my underſtanding; let a kiſs</l>
               <l>And ſilence teach our ſouls ſome new diſcourſe.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Capt.</speaker>
               <l>Why here's a volume of Intelligence</l>
               <pb n="40" facs="tcp:153589:25"/>
               <l>I'l ſtay no longer to expect the Prince,</l>
               <l>But ſeek him out immediatly; diſguiſes?</l>
               <l>King by your leave, I ſhall untruſs your Miſtreſs.</l>
            </sp>
            <stage>Ex</stage>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Roſa.</speaker>
               <l>I know not what I feel nor what to fear,</l>
               <l>If love e'r meant a Tragedie; 'tis here.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Ford.</speaker>
               <l>If we ne'r meet agen, one more ſalute</l>
               <l>Shall fortifie our lives by joyning breath,</l>
               <l>Nor ſhall our laſt hard fate deny us this,</l>
               <l>To change our faithfull Souls at our laſt kiſs.</l>
            </sp>
            <stage>Exeunt ſeverally.</stage>
         </div>
         <div n="4" type="act">
            <head>ACT. IV.</head>
            <stage>Enter Rodriguez, Leandro, Erneſto.</stage>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Erneſt.</speaker>
               <l>I Know not what to think on't, but if I</l>
               <l>Have any ſenſe, there is ſome new ſtate madneſs</l>
               <l>Crept into Court.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Rodri.</speaker>
               <l>Are we not all a ſleep,</l>
               <l>And theſe fine dreams perplex us?</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Leand.</speaker>
               <l>No 'tis waking.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Rod.</speaker>
               <l>Shew me the tenth part of a reaſon why</l>
               <l>The Queen did Marry him.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Lea.</speaker>
               <l>'Twas deſtinie.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Erneſt.</speaker>
               <l>Why ſince ſhould he be melancholy?</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Rod.</speaker>
               <l>Or ſhe ſo humorus?</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Erneſt.</speaker>
               <l>Not lie together? pray Heaven the Gentleman</l>
               <l>Be found with no defective title in him.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Leand.</speaker>
               <l>Obſerve her favours to that Boy, he was</l>
               <l>His ſervant, now her minion. I like not</l>
               <l>Theſe violent wheels; the whole frame may be ſoon</l>
               <l>Indanger'd, if theſe paſſions be not cur'd.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Rod.</speaker>
               <l>New lodgings for him, neer her own, and he</l>
               <pb n="41" facs="tcp:153589:25"/>
               <l>Given free acceſs to the Bed-chamber.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Leand.</speaker>
               <l>'Tis naught</l>
               <l>Or will be ſo, I pittie the good King;</l>
               <l>Though ſhe have rais'd him to the higheſt glorie</l>
               <l>Her power extended too, yet to make this height</l>
               <l>His precipice, and throw him into ſcorn,</l>
               <l>Nay poyſon the beſt hopes he had of honour,</l>
               <l>And love from her, and in his ſight to Court</l>
               <l>A Boy, his ſervant? It would vex the beſt</l>
               <l>Of all our tempers, if we felt the ſting on't.</l>
            </sp>
            <stage>Enter Roſania and Violinda (paſſing over the Stage.)</stage>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Er.</speaker>
               <l>He's here, that Lady is the Queens Cabinet.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Lean.</speaker>
               <l>They are merry about the Mouth.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Er.</speaker>
               <l>Another ſummons?</l>
               <l>'Tis poſſible the Queen may Marry him too.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Lean.</speaker>
               <l>There is ſome myſterie we cannot reach.</l>
               <l>If we doe well remember, ther's a Law</l>
               <l>Made by her ſelf, as ſoon as ſhe was Queen,</l>
               <l>To keep Wifes Pulſes temperat, and correct</l>
               <l>The inſolent Bloud of Women that had Husbands.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Er.</speaker>
               <l>And Men were not exempted.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Leand.</speaker>
               <l>I ſay no more.</l>
               <l>But Heaven maintain the Law, and the Law-makers,</l>
               <l>And conjure down that Devill,</l>
               <l>'Tis the King and the ſmooth Boy, lets leave 'em.</l>
            </sp>
            <stage>Exeunt Lords.</stage>
            <stage>Enter Ferdinand, and Roſania.</stage>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Ferd.</speaker>
               <l>Was this the Ladies Meſſage? does the Queen</l>
               <l>Take thee into ſuch favour?</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Roſa.</speaker>
               <l>I tell truth,</l>
               <l>And though it ſound but ill on the Queens part,</l>
               <l>Becauſe ſhe thinks me what I ſeem my Lord,</l>
               <pb n="42" facs="tcp:153589:26"/>
               <l>You need not to wear one Cloud upon your Face</l>
               <l>When you remember who I am, my fears</l>
               <l>Are thick upon my Heart, how to ſecure</l>
               <l>This ſhadow any longer.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Ferd.</speaker>
               <l>That afflicts</l>
               <l>Me moſt <hi>Roſania,</hi> for it pleaſes me</l>
               <l>To hear ſhe can affect thee; but what way</l>
               <l>To keep her expectation high, and thee</l>
               <l>(My deareſt) ſafe? her paſſions may be violent.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Roſa.</speaker>
               <l>They are already Sir, if I miſtake not;</l>
               <l>I wiſh to Heaven that you were reconcil'd</l>
               <l>To do the office of a Husband to her,</l>
               <l>That peace would keep her Boſom clear, and I</l>
               <l>Should live to all the World except your ſelf</l>
               <l>A ſtranger ſtill.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Ferd.</speaker>
               <l>What language ſpeaks <hi>Roſania?</hi>
               </l>
               <l>Ther's death in every ſyllable; ſhould I</l>
               <l>Obey what thou deſir'ſt, and do the office</l>
               <l>Of a Husband, ha?</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Roſa.</speaker>
               <l>I'l wait upon you ſtill,</l>
               <l>And hope you will vouchſafe me now and then</l>
               <l>A harmleſs ſmile; her beauty will deſerve</l>
               <l>Your whole heart, and ther's ſomething in the memory</l>
               <l>Of what ſhe has advanc'd you to, will help</l>
               <l>To make you kind.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Ferd.</speaker>
               <l>Should I injoy the Queen?</l>
               <l>Becauſe the miſery of my fate compeld</l>
               <l>A ceremonious ſin? ſhall I betray</l>
               <l>The eſſence of my faith, and leave a curſe,</l>
               <l>When thou art known, upon my name for ever?</l>
               <l>If thou haſt taken new reſolves againſt me,</l>
               <l>Puniſh my heart ſome other way; had ſhe</l>
               <l>More ornament than ever met in woman,</l>
               <l>Miſtreſs of more perfection than Poets</l>
               <l>Invented for the Queen of love, to this</l>
               <l>Were the proud Empire of the World her own,</l>
               <pb n="43" facs="tcp:153589:26"/>
               <l>And ſhe would make me Lord of her, and theſe,</l>
               <l>It would not buy me to the pleaſure of</l>
               <l>One Nights embrace, my body ſhall not carry</l>
               <l>My ſoul ſo far aſtray; the Man condemnd</l>
               <l>To live in a perpetuall Snow, hath not</l>
               <l>A purer Froſt within his blood.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Roſa.</speaker>
               <l>This but</l>
               <l>Ingenders a new grief although it bind</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Roſanias</hi> Heart there is yet one way left</l>
               <l>And that ere I pronounce you muſt forgive;</l>
               <l>There is a trembling in my tongue and I</l>
               <l>Already feel ſuch Winter in my breath,</l>
               <l>My timorous Lips do wither.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Ferd.</speaker>
               <l>Do not fright</l>
               <l>My Soul too much ther's ſomething threatens me</l>
               <l>So like a loſs of theſe, that I am left</l>
               <l>A peece of ſhaking Earth, death cannot look</l>
               <l>To make me tremble ſo; canſt thou forſake me?</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Roſ.</speaker>
               <l>Not in my Heart but give my body leave</l>
               <l>To ſeek ſome other place my Lord to dwell in.</l>
               <l>When I am gone into ſome wilderneſs,</l>
               <l>You will find eaſe at Heart, and love the Queen,</l>
               <l>And perfect all; I'l pray you may live happy.</l>
               <l>And hold Intelligence with ſome gentle Winds</l>
               <l>That ſhall convey my wiſhes and return</l>
               <l>What joys do follow you; the purling Rivers</l>
               <l>I'l teach your name and they which g<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ide this way</l>
               <l>Shall bring thee ſomething <hi>Ferdinand</hi> of mine;</l>
               <l>My tears I know will not be loſt, which I</l>
               <l>Will ſend thee daily by the courteous ſtream,</l>
               <l>Clear pledges of my faith; conſent my Lord</l>
               <l>I may depart and you ſhall chooſe your way,</l>
               <l>To every bleſſing here.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Ferd.</speaker>
               <l>Not till we meet</l>
               <l>With one embrace, and take our flight together;</l>
               <l>And I have thought a way to perfect it,</l>
               <pb n="44" facs="tcp:153589:27"/>
               <l>Obſerve my ſweet <hi>Roſania,</hi> the Queen</l>
               <l>Thou ſayſt affects thee, cheriſh it, with all</l>
               <l>The ſoftneſs of her creature; if ſhe allow,</l>
               <l>Kiſs her, and promiſe what young lovers doe,</l>
               <l>Examine not, but by thy love to me</l>
               <l>Be free in amorous language, if ſhe have</l>
               <l>Heat to a private meeting in her Chamber,</l>
               <l>Obey, this ſhall ſecure our loves ambition.</l>
               <l>Enquire not, but reſolve, and let me know</l>
               <l>The time.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Roſ.</speaker>
               <l>You will attempt no violence</l>
               <l>Upon the Queen?</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Ferd.</speaker>
               <l>By this—</l>
               <stage>Kiſſes her.</stage>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Roſ.</speaker>
               <l>What if ſhe have commanded me</l>
               <l>This Night?</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Ferd.</speaker>
               <l>To meet?</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Roſ.</speaker>
               <l>In het Bed-Chamber.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Ferd.</speaker>
               <l>Ha! obey it.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Roſ.</speaker>
               <l>At a late hour.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Ferd.</speaker>
               <l>It ſhall beget our comfort</l>
               <l>If thou conſent.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Roſa.</speaker>
               <l>But ſhall I not expoſe</l>
               <l>My ſelf to danger, if her love perſue</l>
               <l>Immodeſt ends, ſince you adviſe I ſhould</l>
               <l>Apply my ſelf to her deſires?</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Ferd.</speaker>
               <l>If ſhe</l>
               <l>Take too much flame, by ſome ſoft art delay her,</l>
               <l>Till I come to cloſe all; keep ſtill thy perſon</l>
               <l>Secret, the leaſt diſcovery will deſtroy</l>
               <l>Us both; the Evening with much haſt prepares</l>
               <l>Thy viſit and our happineſs.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Roſa.</speaker>
               <l>I'l obey,</l>
               <l>But be you ſure to come.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Ferd.</speaker>
               <l>Loſe thou no time</l>
               <l>Now to indear thee to her, let us part</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Love will find balm to cure the wounded Heart.</hi>
               </l>
            </sp>
            <stage>Exeunt ſeverally</stage>
            <pb n="45" facs="tcp:153589:27"/>
            <stage>A Table, and Lights, ſet out, then Enter Queen, and Violinda.</stage>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Que.</speaker>
               <l>Was he not cheerfull when he promis'd thee?</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Viol.</speaker>
               <l>He was, and he was not.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Que.</speaker>
               <l>I have a ſtrange apprehenſion, and this doth feed it.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Viol.</speaker>
               <l>I told him 'twas an honour worth his joyfull</l>
               <l>entertainment.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Que.</speaker>
               <l>If it ſhould prove ſuccesfull, my revenge</l>
               <l>Were perfect, I'm reſolute to perſue—</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Viol.</speaker>
               <l>It makes well</l>
               <l>For your contrivement that the King and you do</l>
               <l>Lodge at diſtance—ſtay, I hear a tread.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Que.</speaker>
               <l>I hope 'tis he.</l>
            </sp>
            <stage>Enter Leonario.</stage>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Viol.</speaker>
               <l>Prince <hi>Leonario</hi> Madam.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Que.</speaker>
               <l>What comes he for?</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Leon.</speaker>
               <l>Although I have ſmall expectation</l>
               <l>For my own ſake, that you can pardon Madain</l>
               <l>This bold acceſs, and at ſo dark an hour,</l>
               <l>Yet when you have heard my buſineſs, You will know</l>
               <l>Your ſelf ſo much concern'd, I'l not deſpair</l>
               <l>To find your mercy.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Que.</speaker>
               <l>You prepare me for</l>
               <l>Something of conſequence.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Leon.</speaker>
               <l>Pleaſe you to diſmiſs</l>
               <l>Your Ladie, I have ſomething to deliver</l>
               <l>Wo'not become her knowledge.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Que.</speaker>
               <l>Leave us—now,</l>
               <stage>Ex. Violinda.</stage>
               <l>Our conference is free, your Graces pleaſure?</l>
               <l>It muſt be matter of much eſſence, that</l>
               <l>Could not expect till morning, but y'ar welcome.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Leon.</speaker>
               <l>This time and darkneſs Madam beſt becomes him,</l>
               <l>Who for your ſake bluſhes to ſee the Day,</l>
               <l>But I came not to chide my wrongs have learn'd</l>
               <l>A modeſt ſilence, my approach is not</l>
               <pb n="46" facs="tcp:153589:28"/>
               <l>To name a ſuffering of mine but to</l>
               <l>Diſcover what already is prepar'd</l>
               <l>Againſt your peace and honour.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Que.</speaker>
               <l>Is it treaſon?</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Leon.</speaker>
               <l>It is, but threatens not your life, you may</l>
               <l>Live many years upon the wound.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Que.</speaker>
               <l>You fright me.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Leon.</speaker>
               <l>Loſe not the beauty of your cheek ſo ſoon,</l>
               <l>Hide not beneath that cold and killing Snow,</l>
               <l>One Roſie bluſh, and yet that pale would ſhew</l>
               <l>Like Innocence which you have loſt; oh Madam</l>
               <l>Had you not made a forfet of your truth</l>
               <l>To me no ſtorm could ſhake you but your ſoul</l>
               <l>That made no change could know no fear; I come</l>
               <l>To tell you what juſt providence hath done</l>
               <l>In my revenge, your breach of vow is puniſh'd</l>
               <l>With loſs of faith in him to whom you gave</l>
               <l>The Heart you promis'd me, the King, whoſe pride</l>
               <l>You built on my diſhonour, is as falſe,</l>
               <l>As you were.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Que.</speaker>
               <l>This is paſſion but be</l>
               <l>Not yet too raſh in cenſuring him. Whom I</l>
               <l>Have plac'd ſo neer, I muſt defend, nor will</l>
               <l>He need my ſtrength, to make their blood account</l>
               <l>That dare traduce his honour; he has a Heart—</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Leon.</speaker>
               <l>A falſe one. I was born without a fear,</l>
               <l>And dare upon his boſom (wear he worth</l>
               <l>The manly conteſtation,) write him perjur'd.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Que.</speaker>
               <l>I would this were not envy; but admit</l>
               <l>He be thus guiltie, 'tis a fault in him.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Leon.</speaker>
               <l>No Madam, it is yours; that ſin that poyſond</l>
               <l>The expectation of my joys in you,</l>
               <l>Hath made him falſe, and will excuſe his ſtorie,</l>
               <l>When you are nam'd that broke your faith to me;</l>
               <l>I can have no hope now to be repair'd,</l>
               <l>But if it be worth memorie to know</l>
               <pb n="47" facs="tcp:153589:28"/>
               <l>The triumph waits on Innocence, the World</l>
               <l>Shall ſay the Queen deſerv'd to meet a ſcorn</l>
               <l>Deep as her wrongs to me.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Que.</speaker>
               <l>It cannot be.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Leon.</speaker>
               <l>Think ſo, and help to make the revenge greater,</l>
               <l>Till the winds catch the black report and multiply</l>
               <l>The ſhame, by ſcattering it about the Kingdom,</l>
               <l>Sit ſtill, and careleſs of your fame, incourage</l>
               <l>His private luſt, his Miſtreſs now in Court.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Que.</speaker>
               <l>A Miſtriſs in the Court?</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Leon.</speaker>
               <l>Yes Madam, in the Court.</l>
               <l>And may one day think any ſecond place</l>
               <l>Too narrow to contain her greatneſs, ſhe —</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Que.</speaker>
               <l>As y'ar a Prince no more; I have done ill,</l>
               <l>And find the penance here It does agree</l>
               <l>With his neglects, and addes new flame to my</l>
               <l>Young jealouſie; I feel a tempeſt riſing;</l>
               <l>By all your goodneſs leave me Sir; I cannot</l>
               <l>Now right you more than mourn, and give belief to you.</l>
               <l>No more I pray you, by all your love to honour.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Leon.</speaker>
               <l>I ha' done,</l>
               <l>And take my leave, my everlaſting leave,</l>
               <l>'Tis time; how like the day, that flatterd us</l>
               <l>With cheerfull light, are my deſires fled hence,</l>
               <l>And left me here a prodigie of darkneſs,</l>
               <l>A walking Herſe, hung round about with night,</l>
               <l>Whoſe wings muſt one day cover all? farewell.</l>
               <l>If any Star look forth, it is to call</l>
               <l>Me hence, and light me to another World.</l>
               <l>Our Lips are never like to meet agen.</l>
               <stage>Kiſſes Exit.</stage>
               <l>Farewell, if I but ſtay, I ſhall forgive her.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Que.</speaker>
               <l>A Miſtreſs in the Court? ſomething is buſie</l>
               <l>About my Heart.</l>
            </sp>
            <stage>Enter Violinda.</stage>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Viol.</speaker>
               <l>The Prince is gone.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Que.</speaker>
               <l>No matter.</l>
               <pb n="48" facs="tcp:153589:29"/>
               <l>Affronted thus? but I forgot to ask</l>
               <l>Her name that rivals me; how this paſſion</l>
               <l>Befools our underſtanding, and prevents</l>
               <l>The knowledge, and the cure of what afflicts us!</l>
               <l>The Morning will aſſure all; but ſhall this</l>
               <l>Strike me to aſhes? I may find a way</l>
               <l>To my revenge.</l>
            </sp>
            <stage>Enter Violinda.</stage>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Viol.</speaker>
               <l>
                  <hi>Tiberio</hi> is come Madam.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Que.</speaker>
               <l>Wait carefully.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Viol.</speaker>
               <l>I know my dutie.</l>
            </sp>
            <stage>Enter Roſania: (Kneels and Kiſſes her Hand.)</stage>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Que.</speaker>
               <l>Riſe,</l>
               <l>This meeting was not meant for ceremony,</l>
               <l>Ther's ſomething in this preſence will deſerve</l>
               <l>We ſhould put off all ſtate, and ſpeak like friends.</l>
               <l>You muſt be cover'd too. I'l have it ſo.</l>
               <l>We are private now.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Roſa.</speaker>
               <l>Theſe graces will</l>
               <l>Undoe a youth, whoſe birth, and careleſs Stars</l>
               <l>Ordain'd him to be humble, and with dutie</l>
               <l>Wait on your meaneſt ſervant.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Que.</speaker>
               <l>Thou ſhalt ſoon have cauſe</l>
               <l>To think thy Stars are carefull of thee, if</l>
               <l>Thou canſt be wiſe.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Roſa.</speaker>
               <l>Alas! my years are few.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Que.</speaker>
               <l>Thy knowledge is not wanting to diſtinguiſh</l>
               <l>Whoſe favours Court thee, and apply thy ſelf</l>
               <l>To underſtand, and thank the kind beſtower;</l>
               <l>'Tis in my power to make thee great.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Roſa.</speaker>
               <l>You may</l>
               <l>Advance this worthleſs walking ſhadow Madam,</l>
               <l>And when you like the free and bounteous Sun</l>
               <l>Have bleſt me with your rayes, it is but like</l>
               <pb n="49" facs="tcp:153589:29"/>
               <l>His glorious warmth beſtow'd upon a peece</l>
               <l>Of rude and barren Earth, which takes not from</l>
               <l>The luſtre of your Beams, but ſhews more clearly,</l>
               <l>By your own light, what poverty you ſhin'd on.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Quee.</speaker>
               <l>This modeſty becomes you not, look in</l>
               <l>My eie, and read what's there.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Roſa.</speaker>
               <l>Some thing like anger,</l>
               <l>Enough to ſtrike me dead.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Quee.</speaker>
               <l>What now?</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Roſa.</speaker>
               <l>A ſmile,</l>
               <l>And ſuch attending ſweetneſs—</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Quee.</speaker>
               <l>Thus it ſhall</l>
               <l>Invite thee ſtill to gaze, and love, <hi>Tiberio,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>No frown ſhall point on thee; I finde my eyes</l>
               <l>Were meant for thee, and all they grac'd before,</l>
               <l>But objects of miſtake. Here, here, O turn</l>
               <l>Thy lovely face away, left I be ſeen</l>
               <l>To bluſh, my heart hath choſe to place my love</l>
               <l>And the reward; this would become thy tongue</l>
               <l>A great deal better, Come ſit down <hi>Tiberio.</hi>
               </l>
               <l>What ſtill an Infants underſtanding? Think</l>
               <l>I am the man, and learn a little better,</l>
               <l>What beauty dwells upon this hand, What ſoftneſs,</l>
               <l>How like the Snow, or Innocence it ſhews,</l>
               <l>yet fires my heart with every gentle touch.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Roſa.</speaker>
               <l>Dear Madam; would the King would come.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Que.</speaker>
               <l>This is a happineſs that Kings ſhould ſue for,</l>
               <l>And yet there are poor comforts in theſe Kiſſes;</l>
               <l>Let hands preſerve Societie with hands,</l>
               <l>And with there change of whiteneſs, and of Balm,</l>
               <l>Make wealthy one another: But let what</l>
               <l>Was mean't for kiſſes meet, and finde out pleaſure</l>
               <l>By warm exchange of ſouls from our ſoft lips.
<stage>Kiſſes.</stage>
               </l>
               <l>Madam, how like you this?</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Roſa.</speaker>
               <l>Madam.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Que.</speaker>
               <l>I ſuppoſe you a Lady all this while,</l>
               <pb n="50" facs="tcp:153589:30"/>
               <l>And I the man, our lips muſt meet again,</l>
               <l>Will this inſtruct thee nothing?</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Roſ.</speaker>
               <l>Gracious Madam.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Que.</speaker>
               <l>And yet this recreation comes ſhort,</l>
               <l>Dear Lady, of what love might well allow us.</l>
               <l>Admit you are a Queen, you are not bound</l>
               <l>To th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>n your Royal Blood with froſt, but as</l>
               <l>Your power, your pleaſure ſhould exceed; nay graut</l>
               <l>You have a man (a man ſaid I) that can</l>
               <l>Keep love alive, and warm a yielding boſom,</l>
               <l>Yet where from the invitement of your eie,</l>
               <l>And amorous choice, I am become your ſervant,</l>
               <l>You may be a little kinder.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Roſa.</speaker>
               <l>Madam, I know not</l>
               <l>How with the ſafetie of my ſelf, my dutie,</l>
               <l>And your own name and power, to underſtand you,</l>
               <l>(Yet this to ſome would need but little Comment)</l>
               <l>Can you place ſuch a value on a thing</l>
               <l>That not deſerves to breath your name? Or ſhould</l>
               <l>I hope theſe charms of Language you have ſpred</l>
               <l>To catch my heart which hath no wings, but where</l>
               <l>It can believe; For you trauſcend ſo much</l>
               <l>In wonder of your love, a willing Faith</l>
               <l>Not eaſily can reach it. But dear Madam,</l>
               <l>I know all this is but to try my duty,</l>
               <l>And you have pleas'd to chooſe me forth, to make</l>
               <l>Theſe ſilent hours more grateful, by the mirth</l>
               <l>My weak replies may raiſe you,</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Que.</speaker>
               <l>Miracle!</l>
               <l>I but imagin'd thee a woman, now</l>
               <l>I ſhall believe thee one indeed; this coldneſs</l>
               <l>Becomes no maſculine habit. Come, we'll in,</l>
               <l>And change our Sexes; Thou ſhalt wear my clothes,</l>
               <l>And I will put on theſe, help on with thine,</l>
               <l>And I will dreſs thee handſomely, and then</l>
               <l>We'll act again.</l>
            </sp>
            <pb n="51" facs="tcp:153589:30"/>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Roſ.</speaker>
               <l>Not for the world dear Madam, Not yet come?</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Que.</speaker>
               <l>The world? This confirms my jealouſie.</l>
               <l>I'll ſearch you to the ſoul, <hi>Adonis</hi> come,</l>
               <l>I'll call thee ſo, and court thee with more charm</l>
               <l>Than <hi>Venus</hi> did, when in the <hi>Idalian</hi> Groves</l>
               <l>To buy a kiſs, ſhe offer'd the proud Boy</l>
               <l>Her flaming Chariot, and her Doves of Snow.</l>
               <l>'Tis in thy power to make thy fate and heart</l>
               <l>More happy by conſent to meet with mine;</l>
               <l>Tempt not the anger of a Queen deſpis'd,</l>
               <l>Whoſe breath can like a whirl-wind ſnatch thee up,</l>
               <l>And drop thee in a Wilderneſs, where with ſorrow</l>
               <l>For thy neglect, thou by degrees maiſt ſigh</l>
               <l>Thy ſelf into a Miſt, which no Sun-beam</l>
               <l>Shall pitie or take up into a Cloud.</l>
               <l>But love me, and compoſe thy heart to mine,</l>
               <l>Wee'l live with more delight, than fancie can</l>
               <l>Inrich <hi>Elizium</hi> with. The ſoft hours ſhall ſtay</l>
               <l>Till we allow 'em Wings, and while we kiſs</l>
               <l>And on each others Lips breath Incenſe thus,</l>
               <l>Wee'l have ten thouſand <hi>Cupids</hi> for our guard,</l>
               <l>Whoſe Bows ſhall awe the deſtinies, and we write</l>
               <l>The King and Queen of Fate.</l>
            </sp>
            <stage>
               <hi>Enter</hi> Ferdinand, Leandro, Rodriguez, Erneſto, <hi>Captain, Guard.</hi>
            </stage>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Ferd.</speaker>
               <l>Will this deſerve your faith?</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Leand.</speaker>
               <l>We muſt believe.</l>
            </sp>
            <stage>Enter Violinda.</stage>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Viol.</speaker>
               <l>We are undone, the King.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Que.</speaker>
               <l>Falſe Keys?</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Roſa.</speaker>
               <l>'Twas time to come.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Ferd.</speaker>
               <l>Had I not cauſe, my Lords, to appear ſad,</l>
               <l>When I ſuſpected this ſo great affront?</l>
               <l>My melancholy all this while was but</l>
               <pb n="52" facs="tcp:153589:31"/>
               <l>A mourning for this ſhame: Look but my Lords</l>
               <l>Into your ſelves, and make this ſuffering yours.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Viol.</speaker>
               <l>Madam be rais'd again, I have an art</l>
               <l>To fetch you off with honor, and the youth too.</l>
               <l>I will perſwade him there can be no cure</l>
               <l>In this extream. but to pretend himſelf</l>
               <l>A woman; I will dreſs him in your Gown</l>
               <l>Before they can be ware on't; they all know</l>
               <l>This way he cannot flie, mean time put on</l>
               <l>A confidence, and <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>et them know you are</l>
               <l>The Queen, not to be ſhaken with their power;</l>
               <l>This will gain time.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Que.</speaker>
               <l>Proſper in this.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Viol.</speaker>
               <l>I will</l>
               <l>Redeem my fault, or never ſleep again.</l>
            </sp>
            <stage>Exit with Roſania.</stage>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Ferd.</speaker>
               <l>She bluſhes not.</l>
               <l>Were ſhe nor Queen, what names could we beſtow</l>
               <l>Upon this want of modeſty?</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Leand.</speaker>
               <l>'Tis plain.</l>
               <l>We came in time.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Ferd.</speaker>
               <l>Moſt happily to prevent</l>
               <l>Some further act of ſhame; can ſhe look on us</l>
               <l>Without a bluſh?</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Que.</speaker>
               <l>I ſee no ſuch attraction</l>
               <l>In your ſtate faces, that I ſhould deſire</l>
               <l>Much to look on 'em. Who made you King I pray?</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Ferd.</speaker>
               <l>Your power I dare not call it love, preſuming</l>
               <l>That I was fit to be your property,</l>
               <l>Without a ſoul to ſee, or have a ſenſe</l>
               <l>Of theſe diſhonors; This rank heat of blood,</l>
               <l>Madam, what penitence can make this clear?</l>
               <l>Admit your thoughts were wanton, and your flame,</l>
               <l>Too great to be ſuppreſt, could you finde none</l>
               <pb n="53" facs="tcp:153589:31"/>
               <l>For your adulterate embrace, but one</l>
               <l>That was my ſervant? my own hound devour me?</l>
               <l>As if your luſt had not enough of ſhame</l>
               <l>And miſchief to me, but your malice muſt</l>
               <l>Appear in't too; with what ſecuritie</l>
               <l>Can I expect to live, when ſhe begins</l>
               <l>So ſoon to poyſon me?</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Leand.</speaker>
               <l>We heard her ſay</l>
               <l>They two would write themſelves the King and Queen,</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Rod.</speaker>
               <l>So we did all.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Ferd.</speaker>
               <l>You may conſider theſe.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Leand.</speaker>
               <l>'Tis impious</l>
               <l>Madam with what grief do we</l>
               <l>Remember now that Law you made</l>
               <l>After your Corronation to preſerve</l>
               <l>The name of your ſex chaſt which gave our Hearts</l>
               <l>Hope of your bleſſed progreſs; you made it death</l>
               <l>To ſtain the Marriage-bed; where ſhall we expect</l>
               <l>The life of that good act, when you begin</l>
               <l>A breach of chaſtitie by ſo black example?</l>
               <l>If the King urge an Execution</l>
               <l>Of what our vote confirm'd by yours impos'd</l>
               <l>Upon the kingdom, you ſhould prove your ſelf</l>
               <l>More innocent or give us cauſe to mourn</l>
               <l>This fall from virtue</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Er.</speaker>
               <l>Madam we grieve for you.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Que</speaker>
               <l>So, ſo, have your great wiſdoms ſaid all yet?</l>
               <l>I laugh at you (poor things) and am ſo far</l>
               <l>From trembling at your thunder, that I pitty you;</l>
               <l>And firſt I'l let you know you ſelves, you are</l>
               <l>I take it all my ſubjects, I will not</l>
               <l>Exempt you Sir, ſince Marriage takes not off</l>
               <l>My Intereſt, and Eſſence here all ſtrength</l>
               <l>Flowing from me, and your Derivative ſhine</l>
               <l>Extinct, when I frown you to darkneſs; by</l>
               <l>What power dare you take an accompt of me?</l>
               <pb n="54" facs="tcp:153589:32"/>
               <l>That am above your Laws, which muſt obey</l>
               <l>Me, as their Soul, and Dye when I forſake 'em?</l>
               <l>But I will reaſon coolely, and admit</l>
               <l>They live in force; 'gainſt whom? are you ſo ſhallow,</l>
               <l>To think we that created, and decreed 'em</l>
               <l>For vulgar reformation, muſt be ſquard</l>
               <l>And Levell'd by 'em, as we meant to loſe</l>
               <l>Our Character and diſtinction, and ſtoop</l>
               <l>Toth' common file of ſubjects? this were policy!</l>
               <l>I ſpeak not this with ſenſe of any guilt,</l>
               <l>So to decline it, for I here defie you,</l>
               <l>And bring an Innocence ſhall ſtrike a bluſh</l>
               <l>Upon your Souls; that ſinn'd in my ſuſpition.</l>
            </sp>
            <stage>Aſide.</stage>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Ferd.</speaker>
               <l>Where is the Boy? <hi>Erneſto</hi> take him to</l>
               <l>Your cuſtodie, and bid him not deſpair,</l>
               <l>I have contriv'd the reſt.</l>
            </sp>
            <stage>Enter Roſania (like a Woman) and Violinda.</stage>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Er.</speaker>
               <l>He's here.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Viol.</speaker>
               <l>Take it upon you, if it come to ſearching</l>
               <l>Wee'l find a Jurie.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Capt.</speaker>
               <l>You are deceiv'd my Lord, with your good pardon, He is not here.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Er.</speaker>
               <l>Who is not here?</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Capt.</speaker>
               <l>The he you do expect;</l>
               <l>And your Officious Ladyſhip might well</l>
               <l>Have ſpar'd your pains, to put on all this trim.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Ferd.</speaker>
               <l>What means the fellow?</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Capt.</speaker>
               <l>'Tis no news to your Sir.</l>
               <l>I could have told the Queen before and you</l>
               <l>My honourable Lords, this was no Boy,</l>
               <l>Though now he would but ſeem o'th' tother ſex,</l>
               <l>I knew her name.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Roſ.</speaker>
               <l>My name?</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Capt.</speaker>
               <l>Are not you call'd <hi>Roſania?</hi>
               </l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Ferd.</speaker>
               <l>Ha! betraid?</l>
            </sp>
            <pb n="55" facs="tcp:153589:32"/>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Capt.</speaker>
               <l>Yes indeed is ſhe, you were preſent Sir</l>
               <l>I'th' Garden when this fine Hermophrodite</l>
               <l>Declar'd what ſex was hid behind the Breeches,</l>
               <l>And this I certified the Prince before.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Que.</speaker>
               <l>Now 'tis clear.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Capt.</speaker>
               <l>There are ſome tokens too I can remember,</l>
               <l>As kiſſes, and excuſe for marrying with</l>
               <l>The Queen, a Virgin ſtill, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
               </l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Omnes.</speaker>
               <l>A Woman?</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Viol.</speaker>
               <l>But are you a Woman indeed?</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Capt.</speaker>
               <l>And now my Lords, if you have Hearts that are</l>
               <l>Honeſt and daring come about agen,</l>
               <l>For this is but a cunning piece of treaſon,</l>
               <l>Againſt your Faith, and the Queens honour.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Ferd.</speaker>
               <l>We are both loſt <hi>Roſania.</hi>
               </l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Capt.</speaker>
               <l>'Tis truth, or take my Head off.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Que.</speaker>
               <l>You do believe this transformation,</l>
               <l>And know this Ladie, my good Lord, I did</l>
               <l>Suſpect before the cauſe of your neglects,</l>
               <l>And meeting with ſome dark Intelligence</l>
               <l>From the Prince, to perfect this diſcovery,</l>
               <l>Did in my Chamber wooe with apteſt forms</l>
               <l>Of Love, to trie how long the ſex would be</l>
               <l>Conceal'd; you heard a part, and ſee us kiſs,</l>
               <l>And came in time with theſe wiſe Noblemen</l>
               <l>To prevent further acts of ſhame.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Rodri.</speaker>
               <l>I'ſt poſſible?</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Roſa.</speaker>
               <l>It was an ill contrivement to make me</l>
               <l>Proof of the Queens diſhonour.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Er.</speaker>
               <l>An apparent Plot</l>
               <l>Againſt the life and honour of the Queen,</l>
               <l>Since he would urge that Law maliciouſly</l>
               <l>Againſt her, knowing this to be a Woman,</l>
               <l>And his cloſe ſtrumpet.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Rodri.</speaker>
               <l>The ſame Law muſt be</l>
               <l>Their tryall.</l>
            </sp>
            <pb n="65" facs="tcp:153589:33"/>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Leand.</speaker>
               <l>What a change is here already?</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Que.</speaker>
               <l>You muſt not Lords deny me Juſtice.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Rodri.</speaker>
               <l>'Tis inſufferable</l>
               <l>Againſt a common perſon.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Er.</speaker>
               <l>Let his firſt</l>
               <l>Treaſon, if you think good Madam, be urg'd</l>
               <l>In accuſation.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Leand.</speaker>
               <l>So, ſo.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Que.</speaker>
               <l>You did us ſervice Captain.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Capt.</speaker>
               <l>I am bound too't, heres more news for the Prince.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Que.</speaker>
               <l>Uſe your pleaſures.</l>
            </sp>
            <stage>Exit.</stage>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Rod.</speaker>
               <l>What need we circu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſtance, let him dye to morrow.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Que.</speaker>
               <l>Death will be mercie to ſo much ingratitude,</l>
               <l>Command them both to ſeverall cuſtodies.</l>
               <l>The morning ſhall behold 'em dead—</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Roſ.</speaker>
               <l>Now more loſt then ever.</l>
            </sp>
            <stage>Exeunt. Manent. Ferd: Roſ. &amp; Guard.</stage>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Ferd.</speaker>
               <l>Pray lets take</l>
               <l>Short leave of one another, 'tis in vain</l>
               <l>To reaſon againſt providence, or ſay</l>
               <l>We might ha' liv'd; though I muſt dye, and after</l>
               <l>Be hid in my obſcureſt name, and ſhade,</l>
               <l>I muſt declare whoſe blood they will profane</l>
               <l>In bleeding thee; farewell, our laſt, laſt kiſs.</l>
               <l>My heart would fain come to thee, I will make it</l>
               <l>My humble ſute with my laſt breath it may</l>
               <l>Be quickly ſent thee.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Roſa.</speaker>
               <l>We ſhall both meet, when</l>
               <l>This duſt falls off, and our ſouls kiſs agen.</l>
            </sp>
            <stage>Excunt.</stage>
         </div>
         <div n="5" type="act">
            <pb n="57" facs="tcp:153589:33"/>
            <head>ACT. V.</head>
            <stage>Enter Leandro, Rodriguez, Erneſto, Servants with Lights.</stage>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Er.</speaker>
               <l>MY Lord you tell us wonders, 'tis high time</l>
               <l>To open ſuch a myſterie.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Rodri.</speaker>
               <l>This change</l>
               <l>Will exceed all, and ſo convincing are</l>
               <l>The circumſtances of this great diſcovery</l>
               <l>They do command our faith.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Er.</speaker>
               <l>And you ſhall ſteer us.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Leand.</speaker>
               <l>Then let us loſe no time; oh my good Lords,</l>
               <l>Did you but feel the torment of my boſome,</l>
               <l>Till I diſcharge the duty, which ſo long</l>
               <l>Hath ſlept in his concealment, you would call</l>
               <l>For wings to flye, and think all motion tedious;</l>
               <l>For Heavens ſake lets make haſt, that we prevent</l>
               <l>The morning, which will riſe upon this knowledge</l>
               <l>With cheerfull beams, and put on all his glory.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Er.</speaker>
               <l>Moſt gladly we attend.</l>
            </sp>
            <stage>Exeunt.</stage>
            <stage>A Table and Taper ſet out. Enter Ferdinand (with a book in his Hand.)</stage>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Ferd.</speaker>
               <l>I have no Heart to think of any thing</l>
               <l>But my <hi>Roſania,</hi> all devotion,</l>
               <l>When I remember her, flyes off, and leaves</l>
               <l>My ſoul no contemplation but her ſafety;</l>
               <l>They were too cruell to divide us, night</l>
               <l>It ſelf looks now more black by this dim taper;</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Roſania's</hi> eyes would brighten all, but they</l>
               <l>Weigh'd down with ſleep, and ſorrow, are perhaps</l>
               <l>At reſt, a thouſand Angels watch about 'em;</l>
               <l>And let ſome one whoſe office is to wait</l>
               <pb n="58" facs="tcp:153589:34"/>
               <l>On harmleſs love, preſent me to her dreams;</l>
               <l>O let her hear me often call upon her,</l>
               <l>As I am led to death, and when the ſtroke</l>
               <l>Divides me from my ſelf, and from the World,</l>
               <l>My Heart ſhall pay her tribute, and my blood</l>
               <l>Do miracles, when every Crimſon drop</l>
               <l>My Body bleeds, ſhall not in vain be wept,</l>
               <l>But fall into ſome Letter of her name,</l>
               <l>To keep alive our ſtory.</l>
               <stage>Enter two Servants (with Torches) Leandro, Erneſto, Rodriguez.</stage>
               <l>What lights are theſe?</l>
               <l>This place ſure is not wont to be thus viſited.</l>
               <l>They are ſpirits, ha! yet if I have a memory</l>
               <l>Thoſe Faces were but late familiar to me.</l>
               <stage>They Kneel.</stage>
               <l>What mockery is this? if you be ſubſtances</l>
               <l>Of things I know, go tell the Tyrant Queen</l>
               <l>She might allow me death without this ſcorn,</l>
               <l>This jeering Antimaſque.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Omnes.</speaker>
               <l>Long live the King.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Ferd.</speaker>
               <l>What King?</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Omnes.</speaker>
               <l>Long live <hi>Ferdinand</hi> King of <hi>Murcia.</hi>
               </l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Ferd.</speaker>
               <l>A dream, a golden dream. What fancies wait</l>
               <l>Upon our ſleep? and yet I wake, they are</l>
               <l>Apparitions, I'l ſhut my eyes, and loſe 'em.</l>
               <l>They wo'not vaniſh <hi>Leandro, Rodriguez, Erneſto?</hi>
               </l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Omnes.</speaker>
               <l>All your ſubjects.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Leand.</speaker>
               <l>Collect your ſcatterd thoughts my Lord, and be</l>
               <l>Aſſur'd, we now pay reall duties to you,</l>
               <l>You are our King, and muſt be.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Ferd.</speaker>
               <l>Who ſays ſo?</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Leand.</speaker>
               <l>I, whoſe cold fear, and frailty,</l>
               <l>When fate of Wat had made you Priſoner,</l>
               <l>Conceal'd the truth, and Juſtice of your title,</l>
               <pb n="59" facs="tcp:153589:34"/>
               <l>'Twas I that ſav'd you from your Uncles ſury</l>
               <l>And ſent you to <hi>Valentia,</hi> while I cozen'd</l>
               <l>The kingdom with your death, till time might ripen</l>
               <l>Your challenge to the ſcepter; if you can</l>
               <l>Find mercy to a treaſon, great as this,</l>
               <l>I'l live, and ſtudy how to merit pardon.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Ferd.</speaker>
               <l>Riſe, riſe all,</l>
               <l>And if you be <hi>Leandro,</hi> pray come neerer.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Rod.</speaker>
               <l>Pray Heav'n this unexpected happineſs</l>
               <l>Meet with no extaſie, all ſenſes are</l>
               <l>Not arm'd for ſuch extremes of Joy.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Er.</speaker>
               <l>The Queen,</l>
               <l>When ſhe finds this, will fall into a Feaver,</l>
               <l>By inſtinct her Head muſt ake this very minute.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Rod.</speaker>
               <l>And ſhake too, for the Crown is tottering.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Ferd.</speaker>
               <l>Pardon? thou ſhouldſt divide the kingdom with me.</l>
               <l>But do all theſe believe it, will you not,</l>
               <l>When I make ſecond claim, deny me agen?</l>
               <l>Call me Impoſtor?</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Leand.</speaker>
               <l>Sir forgive that firſt,</l>
               <l>And I'l not ask Heaven pardon for my next</l>
               <l>Deniall, let death threaten all his ſtings;</l>
               <l>And I have ſatisfied theſe Lords ſo well,</l>
               <l>They are confirm'd in your juſt claim, and perſon.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Rod Er.</speaker>
               <l>We lay our lives and fortunes at your feet.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Ferd.</speaker>
               <l>I may command you then, fetch me <hi>Roſania;</hi>
               </l>
               <l>I'l be no King without her; do not ſtay</l>
               <l>To hear how much I love her 'bove the Crown,</l>
               <l>And all the glories wait upon it, ſhe</l>
               <l>That was my Page, my fellow Priſoner, <hi>Roſania.</hi>
               </l>
               <stage>Exit Rodrig.</stage>
               <l>'Tis that name next to Heaven I bow too.</l>
               <l>Good my Lord follow him, and if ſhe be</l>
               <l>Awake, oh drop it gently by degrees,</l>
               <l>(The joy is mighty, ſhe a ſad weak Virgin)</l>
               <pb n="60" facs="tcp:153589:35"/>
               <l>That I ſhall live to make her Queen.</l>
               <stage>Exit Erneſt</stage>
               <l>Stay you, and if I play too much the wanton with</l>
               <l>My fate, or ſwell with expectation,</l>
               <l>Speak ſomething to allay my hopes, and ſay</l>
               <l>There may be croſſes yet, the Queen may want</l>
               <l>Faith or conſent, or put caſe the people</l>
               <l>(A dangerous torrent to oppoſe) like not</l>
               <l>This Innovation, where is the King then?</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Leand.</speaker>
               <l>Doubt not their Loves, you had thei<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
               </l>
               <l>Hearts before;</l>
               <l>Let nothing ſhake you.</l>
            </sp>
            <stage>Enter Roſania, Erneſto, Rodriguez.</stage>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Ferd.</speaker>
               <l>Th'art my better Angell.</l>
               <l>Why then if my <hi>Roſania</hi> will be Queen,</l>
               <l>The kingdoms ours agen; ſhe comes, ſhe comes.</l>
               <l>Thou mak'ſt too little haſt to be a Queen.</l>
               <l>I am my ſelf agen, my name is found,</l>
               <l>I ſhall live to, thus to embrace <hi>Roſania</hi>
               </l>
               <l>Without a fear, theſe Lords are all thy ſubjects,</l>
               <l>I am a King.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Leand.</speaker>
               <l>You are.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Ferd.</speaker>
               <l>Then what muſt my</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Roſania</hi> be?</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Roſ.</speaker>
               <l>Happy, if this be more</l>
               <l>Than dream, my tears and ſufferings are all paid for</l>
               <l>If this be true.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Leand.</speaker>
               <l>Moſt true.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Roſ.</speaker>
               <l>What a ſtrong arm</l>
               <l>Hath Heaven?</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Ferd.</speaker>
               <l>See how the Day hath made</l>
               <l>Haſt to ſalute <hi>Roſania,</hi> and to wait</l>
               <l>Upon thy triumph, bluſhes like a Maid</l>
               <l>When ſhe is told ſhe is in Love, the Stars</l>
               <l>Are gone to tell the other World, thy beauty,</l>
               <l>Till now Ecclips'd with ſorrow, hath thrown off</l>
               <pb n="61" facs="tcp:153589:35"/>
               <l>The impriſoning veil, and ſhines above their bright<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs.</l>
               <l>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ut how ſhall we <hi>Leandro</hi> now contrive</l>
               <l>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>or our Court entertainment, where the Queens</l>
               <l>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>repar'd to hear our Tragedy?</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Leand.</speaker>
               <l>Leave me</l>
               <l>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>o order your appearance; but firſt Sir,</l>
               <l>We muſt ſecure this Fort.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Er.</speaker>
               <l>The Captain is</l>
               <l>My creature.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Ferd.</speaker>
               <l>Thou ſhalt be all our direction.</l>
               <l>Come my <hi>Roſania,</hi> time hath turn'd a gen</l>
               <l>Our Glaſs, and his keen ſith this comfort brings,</l>
               <l>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>t cuts no ſcepters down but to make Kings.</l>
            </sp>
            <stage>Excunt.</stage>
            <stage>Enter Leonario (reading a Letter,) and Soldier.</stage>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Leon.</speaker>
               <l>So neer?</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Sold.</speaker>
               <l>We heard before of your affront</l>
               <l>My Lord, and were prepar'd.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Leon.</speaker>
               <l>It hath outſtrip'd my expectation,</l>
               <l>Theſe Letters ſay</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Mendoza</hi> is their Generall new return'd</l>
               <l>With victory from the <hi>Moores;</hi> his fame I honour,</l>
               <l>My knowledge never reach'd his perſon.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Sold.</speaker>
               <l>Sir, he brings old Soldiers with him, the Commanders</l>
               <l>Are ſuch, whoſe faith and valor in thoſe Wars</l>
               <l>Already tried, he durſt name to the King</l>
               <l>To be employ'd here in your highneſs cauſe.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Leand.</speaker>
               <l>We will to Horſe immediatly. I long</l>
               <l>To ſalute the Army.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Sold.</speaker>
               <l>Which but wants your perſon</l>
               <l>The Soul of their deſign; you may ſoon reach 'em.</l>
            </sp>
            <stage>Enter Captain.</stage>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Leon.</speaker>
               <l>I will.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Capt.</speaker>
               <l>Your Grace.</l>
            </sp>
            <pb n="62" facs="tcp:153589:36"/>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Leon.</speaker>
               <l>That we had wings, away, to Horſe to Horſe</l>
            </sp>
            <stage>Exeunt Leon. Sold</stage>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Capt.</speaker>
               <l>Speed, and you be ſo hot o'th' ſpur, my buſineſs</l>
               <l>Is but breath, and your deſign it ſeems rides poſt.</l>
               <stage>Enter Lieutenant and Antient.</stage>
               <l>The Earth runs upon wheels; whom do I ſpy?</l>
               <l>My extraordinaries, I'l ha' ſport with them,</l>
               <l>But firſt obſerve 'em.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Lieut.</speaker>
               <l>I ſee no profit in theſe offices</l>
               <l>That we ha' brought.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Ant.</speaker>
               <l>Not extraordinary, as the name did promiſe</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Capt.</speaker>
               <l>The Rogues are poor, and now repent.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Ant.</speaker>
               <l>We were told by the cheating Captain</l>
               <l>That we ſhould want Men to tell our money.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Lieut.</speaker>
               <l>This 'tis to deal with <hi>Soldades.</hi>
               </l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Ant.</speaker>
               <l>We ſhould command the Ladies too, and we</l>
               <l>Were bountifull, a ſmall Pox take their beauties,</l>
               <l>'Tis the greater curſe, I have undone</l>
               <l>My ſelf in giving away enameld Rings</l>
               <l>And Bracelets.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Lieut.</speaker>
               <l>Well, if I truſt a Captain agen.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Ant.</speaker>
               <l>Or I.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Capt.</speaker>
               <l>I'm glad they are payd; I wo'not leave 'em</l>
               <l>I feel my antipathy ſtrong yet.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Ant.</speaker>
               <l>I would venture half my ſoul to be reveng'd</l>
               <l>If I knew how.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Capt.</speaker>
               <l>True Raſcals!</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Lieut.</speaker>
               <l>The Ladies love him.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Ant.</speaker>
               <l>They all Love Men of War.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Lieu.</speaker>
               <l>Would his poop were a fire.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Ant.</speaker>
               <l>And Battels in Bed naturally.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Lieu.</speaker>
               <p>Well, what Ladies give him hereafter to bu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> new Feathers, may his body compell him to beſtow upon a Surgeon.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Ant.</speaker>
               <l>May Diſeaſes undermine his Fleſh like Gun powder,</l>
               <pb n="63" facs="tcp:153589:36"/>
               <l>And blow all his skin up into bliſters.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Lieu.</speaker>
               <p>May they that look for his Noſe, go about for want of a <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ridge, and let him wear no Legs but what he buyes from the Carpenter.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Ant.</speaker>
               <p>May his face break out, and undo him in taf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fata, and may the patches at the laſt be ſo many, till his skin be inviſible, and his goggle eyes look through a Mask.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Lieu.</speaker>
               <p>May he live to be as much coward as we ha' been, and be beaten!</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Ant.</speaker>
               <p>Abominably beaten, and may the miracle be on our ſide, that we may be valiant, and be the Men to doe it, oh I would have no more mercy.—</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Capt.</speaker>
               <p>Save you Gallants, ſave you Courtiers.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Both.</speaker>
               <p>My noble Captain.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Ant.</speaker>
               <p>It may be he did not hear us.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Capt.</speaker>
               <p>Hark you, what purchaſe have you two made lately?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Both.</speaker>
               <p>Of what?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Capt.</speaker>
               <l>Of Lands and loggerheads, Lordſhips I would ſay,</l>
               <l>I know you are both rich, you cannot chooſe,</l>
               <l>But I will borrow no more o' you, faith beſatisfied</l>
               <l>and leave off in time with the wealth you have.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Lieu.</speaker>
               <l>Where is it Captain?</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Ant.</speaker>
               <p>Can you tell where we may borrow as much money upon our extraordinary places, as will ſet up ſhop agen? For this Court trade wo' not do.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Capt.</speaker>
               <p>How?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Lieu.</speaker>
               <p>No indeed Captain we ha' made little benefit ſince we came to be extraordinaries.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Capt.</speaker>
               <p>Ye took not the right way then.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Ant.</speaker>
               <p>That may be.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Capt.</speaker>
               <p>Why, cannot you lie, and ſwear, and pawn your ſouls for ſix pence, the Devill could not furniſh <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>he City with two more hopefull <hi>Borachios.</hi> You have a Carrot-colourd Beard, and that never fails, and your worſhips face is a prognoſtication of preferment</p>
               <pb n="64" facs="tcp:153589:37"/>
               <l>Is a Prognoſtication of preferment, where</l>
               <l>Beſide Dominicall Letters you have all the</l>
               <l>Conjuring Characters of the Planets.</l>
               <l>But all this is your cunning, to diſſemble your eſtates.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Lieu.</speaker>
               <p>By this empty pocket, I have but one Shirt</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Capt.</speaker>
               <p>You jeaſt y'ſaith.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Ant.</speaker>
               <p>And by all my no money, I have but half a one left</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Capt.</speaker>
               <p>Come, come, you took up linnen lately, I heard You did.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Ant.</speaker>
               <p>I, ſmocks.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Capt.</speaker>
               <p>Why they are in faſhion with extraordina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry Courtiers.</p>
               <l>But if you be in earneſt, I can tell, where you</l>
               <l>May furniſh your ſelves richly.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Both.</speaker>
               <p>Where? where?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Capt.</speaker>
               <p>W'y in the Shops for ready money, but you would Save charges.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Ant.</speaker>
               <p>I marry Captain.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Capt.</speaker>
               <l>Venture to rob a hedge, it is but hanging,</l>
               <l>And whats that to men extraordinary?</l>
               <l>But if your wants be reall, be not dejected,</l>
               <l>I'l ſet you up agen my ſelf, I have been</l>
               <l>Beholding to you two for your good words</l>
               <l>And wiſhes Gentlemen.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Lieu.</speaker>
               <l>It pleaſes you to ſay ſo, I begin</l>
               <l>To ſmell.—</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Ant.</speaker>
               <p>Not to us Captain, we have been beholding to you.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Capt.</speaker>
               <p>And it happens, as if fortune had made you miſerable</p>
               <p>A purpoſe to bleſs you both with ſuch a preferment, as wo'not be offerd agen in a Coronation.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Lieu.</speaker>
               <p>On good Captain, for we are extraordinary miſerable.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Capt.</speaker>
               <p>Then obſerve; you are not ignorant how things go at Court, the King is in priſon.</p>
            </sp>
            <pb n="65" facs="tcp:153589:37"/>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Ant.</speaker>
               <p>So.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Capt.</speaker>
               <p>And his wench with him that walk'd in Breeches; The Queen reſolves they ſhall both dye.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Ant.</speaker>
               <p>Good.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Capt.</speaker>
               <p>This morning too; now in regard the King is a perſon of qualitie—</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Lieu.</speaker>
               <p>I think he be.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Capt.</speaker>
               <p>And the tother a Lady, as ſome imagine, you two may do very well to undertake now—</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Both.</speaker>
               <p>Any thing.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Capt.</speaker>
               <p>To be a couple of Hangmen: d'ee mark? to diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>patch the Queens enemies in what horrid way, her coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſell ſhall think convenient, you will do ſervice to the State, and have extraordinary rewards; beſides the honour and reputation of your places; what ſay? 'tis my pure love to make this firſt offer to you.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Ant.</speaker>
               <p>Do we look like a couple of Hangmen?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Capt.</speaker>
               <p>No you ha' not ſo good a complexion; and now I think on't you ſha'not live to have that preferment come, draw you that wear your Sword like a Bum-baly, do as I bid you, and that quickly.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Ant.</speaker>
               <p>It wo'not come out Sir—</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Cap.</speaker>
               <p>No.—this ſhall in then—</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Ant.</speaker>
               <p>I will put more ſtrength to'c.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Capt.</speaker>
               <p>So, now, d'ee mark—kill one another.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Both.</speaker>
               <p>Kill one another?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Capt.</speaker>
               <p>Yes and doo't religiouſly, with as much alacrity as you would devour an Orphan: and do't hanſomly, that you may not be hangd when you are dead.</p>
               <l>I'l ſee't done, he that is dull ſhall have my goad to quicken</l>
               <l>him: —</l>
               <stage>They fight.</stage>
               <l>So, good, good agen, well offer'd—they fight by theſe Hilts</l>
               <l>Furiouſly, now cou'd I forgive 'em—ſo, enough.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Lieu.</speaker>
               <p>This is very fine ſport.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Capt.</speaker>
               <p>Neceſſity has taught 'em the noble ſcience, come. if all fail, you ſhall fight challenges; ther's mony and
<pb n="66" facs="tcp:153589:38"/>broken Pates to be got that way, you can make legs, and gape like Gudgins for benevolence, cut ſcurvy capers, to ſhew your Legs are well, when your Head bleeds; farewell; ſtay, you want money, I had forgot, there is twelve pence apiece for you.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Both.</speaker>
               <p>How Captain? I hope not.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Capt.</speaker>
               <p>They are not hearty yet, they think I ſerve 'em with Preſs money agen; no, tis my pure bounne. Go, ſet up agen, and truſt Souldiers, without impertinent asking for your debts; they I pay you.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Ant.</speaker>
               <p>As you ha' done.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Capt.</speaker>
               <p>I'l hearken how you behave you ſelves farewell. When you are rich, I'l viſit you agen, and borrow money.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Lieu.</speaker>
               <p>Too much is too much; humh.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Ant.</speaker>
               <p>Now have I a great mind to fight with your Captainſhip.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Lieu.</speaker>
               <p>So have I, now my Hands in, methinks 'tis nothing.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Capt.</speaker>
               <p>You are not deſperate?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Ant.</speaker>
               <p>We are a little better, as good be Hang'd for kil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling of you Captain, as live after the rate of our diſgrace. I am reſolv'd.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Capt.</speaker>
               <l>Two Maſtives at once may worry me. I am put too't.</l>
               <stage>They fight.</stage>
               <l>Muſt we have tother 'bout.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Ant.</speaker>
               <p>This is enough at once we may come too't in time.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Capt.</speaker>
               <p>Why now I love you, love you, as well as you do Law.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Ant.</speaker>
               <p>Upon good terms we love you too.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Capt.</speaker>
               <p>Let's ſhake Hands, you ſha'not to your vomit agen. Now you dare ſight, I'l tell you a hundred wayes to get moneys, come, wee'l drink and divide fortunes, Run not back into cows agen.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Ant.</speaker>
               <p>I'l be Antient now agen.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Lieu.</speaker>
               <p>And I Lieutenant.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Capt.</speaker>
               <p>Both my own Boyes.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Ant.</speaker>
               <p>'Tis not ſo hard to fight I ſee, if a Man be but deſperate, and give his mind too't.</p>
            </sp>
            <pb n="67" facs="tcp:153589:38"/>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Lieu.</speaker>
               <p>Pox a Cowards; come Captain.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Capt.</speaker>
               <p>Let me hug ye my brace of <hi>Mirmidons,</hi> And drink a Tun of Wine to this converſion.</p>
            </sp>
            <stage>Exeunt.</stage>
            <stage>Enter Queen, Violinda.</stage>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Que.</speaker>
               <l>The Prince ſo early met upon the way</l>
               <l>This morning ſayſt? and with a Souldier?</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Vio.</speaker>
               <l>And in that haſt too, Madam, I was told</l>
               <l>The ſpeed of Wings was ſlow, their fiery Horſe</l>
               <l>Bathing in foam, yet fled as if they meant</l>
               <l>To leave the Wind, and Clouds behind 'em.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Que.</speaker>
               <l>Strange!</l>
               <l>I could have wiſh'd him with leſs diſcontent</l>
               <l>To have left us, but my ſtubborn fate deſign'd it;</l>
               <l>Having thus ſnatch'd away himſelf, it will</l>
               <l>Become us to compoſe, and make the beſt</l>
               <l>Of our State game; I ſent a Meſſenger</l>
               <l>With our command, to th' Governor of the Fort,</l>
               <l>He ſhould attend the King by the Water-gate</l>
               <l>Leads to the Garden, we do purpoſe conference;</l>
               <l>If <hi>Ferdinand</hi> wiſely conſent to break</l>
               <l>The Magick that ſo chains his Heart to that</l>
               <l>Idoll <hi>Roſania,</hi> wee'l be reconcil'd,</l>
               <l>And Peace ſhall marry once agen our Hearts.</l>
               <stage>Enter Courtier.</stage>
               <l>Me thinks our Lords are cold in their attendance,</l>
               <l>Where be our train of Ladies?—nay permit 'em,</l>
               <l>A ſolitude becomes this ſullen Day.</l>
               <l>And our own thoughts; methinks thou doſt not look</l>
               <l>With thy own face upon me.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Vio.</speaker>
               <l>Not I Madam?</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Que.</speaker>
               <l>My eyes have loſt their virtue, all I look on</l>
               <l>Have not the ſhape and colour they preſented.</l>
               <l>What whiſpers that? ha'?</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Viol.</speaker>
               <l>Here was none Madam.</l>
            </sp>
            <pb n="68" facs="tcp:153589:39"/>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Que.</speaker>
               <l>I could be jealous of the Wind methinks,</l>
               <l>And quarrell with the poſtures of thoſe very</l>
               <l>Shapes i'th' Arras; fie <hi>Olivia,</hi> call home thy reaſon.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Court.</speaker>
               <l>O Madam!</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Que.</speaker>
               <l>What horror's in that voice? I ſee a treaſon</l>
               <l>In's looks.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Court.</speaker>
               <l>O Madam, I beſeech your pardon.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Que.</speaker>
               <l>Why? art a traitor?</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Court.</speaker>
               <l>Not I, but there are practices I fear</l>
               <l>Againſt your royal perſon; the Court gates</l>
               <l>Are ſhut, all's in confuſion within,</l>
               <l>And I could hear abroad loud acclamations</l>
               <l>And triumph for the King, as he were new proclam'd.</l>
            </sp>
            <stage>Enter Captain.</stage>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Que.</speaker>
               <l>Which way comeſt thou?</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Cap.</speaker>
               <l>Over the Wall Madam; the gates are ſhut,</l>
               <l>I'l tell you news; young <hi>Fordinand</hi> your Husband</l>
               <l>Is in all ſtate attended, and proclam'd</l>
               <l>King in his own right, he is prov'd to be</l>
               <l>What he did firſt pretend himſelf, <hi>Leandro,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>And all the Lords confirm't, the Governor</l>
               <l>Hath given him up the Fort, the wiſe City</l>
               <l>Her Keys, and every officer on's knees</l>
               <l>Is praying and drinking the Kings health,</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Que.</speaker>
               <l>Away and let thy face be ſeen no more,</l>
               <l>But when the fatall noiſe of fire, ſome blood,</l>
               <l>Or buriall calls thee forth.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Capt.</speaker>
               <l>This my reward</l>
               <l>For bringing news the King's alive? take heed,</l>
               <l>Do not talk treaſon in your own defence,—hark</l>
            </sp>
            <stage>Enter (in ſtate) Rodriguez, Erneſto, Leandro, Ferdinand, (who takes the Throne) Attendants.</stage>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Que.</speaker>
               <l>From what an expectation am I faln!</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Omnes.</speaker>
               <l>Long live <hi>Ferdinand</hi> King.</l>
            </sp>
            <pb n="69" facs="tcp:153589:39"/>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Ferd.</speaker>
               <l>We thank you; and will ſtudy to be worth</l>
               <l>Your prayers and dutie; Madam the Chancelor</l>
               <l>Can cleer, and bring your faith to allow the wonder,</l>
               <l>We are no Impoſtor now, nor need we borrow</l>
               <l>A beam from you to make us ſhine yet ſtill</l>
               <l>You are our Coſen, fair <hi>Olivia,</hi>
               </l>
               <stage>Enter Roſania and Ladies.</stage>
               <l>The Husband was a title long ſince due</l>
               <l>To my <hi>Roſania,</hi> may it proſper here.</l>
               <l>Our love and years grew up together, and</l>
               <l>Our Souls by holy contract tied, when in</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Alfonzo</hi>'s Houſe, her Father, and my Guardian</l>
               <l>(To whoſe truſt I was ſent an Infant by <hi>Leandro</hi>)</l>
               <l>We plighted faith; it is no blemiſh</l>
               <l>To fair <hi>Olivia</hi> ſtill to be a Virgin,</l>
               <l>Though ſhe have loſt the Queen, ſhe is a Princeſs.</l>
               <l>And hath now found a Kinſman, that ſhall ſtudy</l>
               <l>What ſhall become his love, her blood, and honour.</l>
               <l>Upon your Lip I print this fair aſſurance.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Roſa.</speaker>
               <l>And mine ſhall be to do you ſervice Madam.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Que.</speaker>
               <l>If this be true, you muſt command my dutie.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Ferd.</speaker>
               <l>We hear Prince <hi>Leonario</hi> is departed,</l>
               <l>When he ſhall know the progreſs of our fortunes</l>
               <l>Hee'l quit his Stars, that hid their golden Heads</l>
               <l>To mock him with a ſmall Eclipſe, o' purpoſe</l>
               <l>To light him with more glorie to his happineſs. <hi>Soft Alarum</hi>
               </l>
               <l>Ha? what clamors that? the frightfull noiſe increaſes.</l>
            </sp>
            <stage>Enter firſt Guard.</stage>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Guard.</speaker>
               <p>Flie, and ſave your ſelves the Fort's ſurpris'd By the Prince of <hi>Arragon,</hi> whoſe troups have ſeiz'd the City, reeling with Wine, and careleſs of their ſtrength, in their joyes for you Sir.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Ferd.</speaker>
               <l>The Prince of <hi>Arragon?</hi> the fates cannot</l>
               <l>Be ſo injuſt, ſo envious of our bleſſing,</l>
               <pb n="70" facs="tcp:153589:40"/>
               <l>To ſnatch it from us in a minute; ha?</l>
               <l>Help, help, quarter.</l>
            </sp>
            <stage>Divers within cry.</stage>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Ferd.</speaker>
               <l>They are i'th' Court already.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Leand.</speaker>
               <l>We are all undone,</l>
               <l>Lets yield, and ask conditions honourable.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Ferd.</speaker>
               <l>Dye he, that dares but think ſo yeeld? no, <hi>Ferdinand</hi>
               </l>
               <l>Was here too late a Priſoner; let us ſell</l>
               <l>Our lives at glorious rates, the Evening puts</l>
               <l>A Mask upon the horror, follow me.</l>
            </sp>
            <stage>Exit.</stage>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Leand.</speaker>
               <l>To certain death; Ladies ſtay you, the danger</l>
               <l>Will meet us here to ſoon, and yet your perſons</l>
               <l>In honour challenge ſafety.</l>
            </sp>
            <stage>Ex. Lords.</stage>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Que.</speaker>
               <l>Is there no end of my diſtractions?</l>
               <l>Or hath my folly yet deſerv'd more vengeance?</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Roſa.</speaker>
               <l>It cannot be Heaven will ſo ſoon deſtroy</l>
               <l>The bleſſing it beſtow'd if thus you puniſh</l>
               <l>Whom you advance, who will believe your gifts</l>
               <l>Are more than flattery to betray our Peace?</l>
            </sp>
            <stage>Enter Leonario Alfonſo, Ferdinand, (Priſoner,) Rodriguez, Erneſto, Souldiers.</stage>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Leon.</speaker>
               <l>This Ladie is my prize.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Que.</speaker>
               <l>How Sir, your prize?</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Leon.</speaker>
               <l>Miſtake me not, ther's no diſhonour meant</l>
               <l>Your perſon; yet I boldly may pronounce</l>
               <l>You are, and muſt be mine. I am not ignorant</l>
               <l>You are a Virgin all but name, be wiſe</l>
               <l>As you are fair, and I forget what's paſt,</l>
               <l>And take this ſatisfaction; if I meet</l>
               <l>Contempt, where I with honour once more Court you,</l>
               <l>You will create a flame ſhall never dye</l>
               <l>But in the Kingdoms aſhes; you were mine</l>
               <l>Firſt by your own election, ſeal'd above,</l>
               <l>If I muſt loſe what Heaven beſtow'd upon me</l>
               <l>The quarrell is not mine</l>
               <l>But virtues, whoſe right Hand is arm'd with Juſtice.</l>
               <pb n="71" facs="tcp:153589:40"/>
               <stage>Enter Captain.</stage>
               <l>Puniſh not where you owe your Heart, but let</l>
               <l>Both our revenges meet in that Impoſtor;</l>
               <l>I find your noble Soul return; Lord Generall</l>
               <l>While I retire with this fair Queen whom not</l>
               <l>One violent accent ſhall affright, much leſs</l>
               <l>A rude attempt, take hence that counterfet,</l>
               <l>And cut his Head off.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Roſ.</speaker>
               <l>O my deareſt Lord?</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Leon.</speaker>
               <l>The reſt may if they pleaſe find mercy.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Capt.</speaker>
               <l>I were beſt be o' this ſide.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Leon.</speaker>
               <l>Away with him.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Ferd.</speaker>
               <l>Inſulting Prince, thou dareſt not.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Leon.</speaker>
               <l>How Sir, dare not?</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Ferd.</speaker>
               <l>I ſaid it,</l>
               <l>Thy better, being a King in my own right,</l>
               <l>Without her charitie, proclam'd and juſtified,</l>
               <l>By Birth a Prince.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Leand.</speaker>
               <l>All this is truth Sir.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Leon.</speaker>
               <l>You muſt not Cozen thus my faith, away;</l>
               <l>Cut off his Head.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Alfon.</speaker>
               <l>Diſpatch you with the Queen,</l>
               <l>Let me alone to make his Head ſecure.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Leand.</speaker>
               <l>Nay take mine too. I'l wait on him in death,</l>
               <l>It ſhall begin my ſervice.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Roſ.</speaker>
               <l>Cruell Prince.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Que.</speaker>
               <l>What fate muſt I obey?</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Roſ.</speaker>
               <l>My death will adde ſome lines</l>
               <l>Unto thy bloody Chronicle; pray let us dy together.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Leon.</speaker>
               <l>You ſhall ſpeak, her ſentence Madam.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Que.</speaker>
               <l>She muſt live then.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Leon.</speaker>
               <l>To all we offer mercie, but to <hi>Ferdinand,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>His doom is fixt; come Madam.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Que.</speaker>
               <l>Whither Sir?</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Leon.</speaker>
               <l>I know the way to your Chappel, he that loves us</l>
               <l>Make haſt, and bring the Prieſt.</l>
            </sp>
            <pb n="72" facs="tcp:153589:41"/>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Capt.</speaker>
               <l>That's I, I know</l>
               <l>Her Chaplains, they are my friends, and all good fellows.</l>
            </sp>
            <stage>Exit.</stage>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Ferd.</speaker>
               <l>Pray can you tell me, where, or what I am</l>
               <l>Or what I muſt do next?</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Alfon.</speaker>
               <l>Yes, you muſt dye.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Ferd.</speaker>
               <l>Let not that grieve you Gentlemen, 'tis nothing</l>
               <l>To part with life, and if but my <hi>Roſania</hi> would not weep</l>
               <l>Methinks I could ſhake off this duſt, and leap</l>
               <l>To Immortality without a guide,</l>
               <l>And in that cheerfull flight prepare the bleſt</l>
               <l>With ſo much praiſe and wonder of thy virtue,</l>
               <l>They ſhall be more in love with thee, than I,</l>
               <l>And double all their prayers to bring thee to 'em.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Roſ.</speaker>
               <l>No, we will dye together.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Alf.</speaker>
               <l>You ſhall.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Ferd.</speaker>
               <l>How?</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Alf.</speaker>
               <l>Both live, and love, and bleſs my age the witneſs.</l>
               <l>D'ee know me?</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Roſa.</speaker>
               <l>Father?</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Ferd.</speaker>
               <l>Guardian.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Leand.</speaker>
               <l>
                  <hi>Alfonſo,</hi> my noble Kinſman.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Alf.</speaker>
               <l>How joyes flow in my Heart, to ſee this conſtancy!</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Ferd.</speaker>
               <l>How came you to be his?</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Alf.</speaker>
               <l>I have deceiv'd the Prince our forces are <hi>Valentia</hi>'s,</l>
               <l>Not <hi>Arragons,</hi> which he by Letters ſent for</l>
               <l>In his revenge, but we met the Intelligence</l>
               <l>And arriv'd ſooner to pretend our ſelves</l>
               <l>The Armie he expected; you ſhall know more hereafter.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Ferd.</speaker>
               <l>I want a knowledge where to begin my gratitude,</l>
               <l>The joyes you bring are mighty, and overcome us.</l>
               <l>O my <hi>Roſania?</hi>
               </l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Roſ.</speaker>
               <l>This was beyond hope.</l>
            </sp>
            <stage>Enter Captain.</stage>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Capt.</speaker>
               <l>So, ſo, 'tis done, he has mumbled up the ceremony;</l>
               <pb n="73" facs="tcp:153589:41"/>
               <l>A compendious Prieſt may do much in few words;</l>
               <l>They are faſt enough; the Queen was wiſe to take him;</l>
               <l>You are onely like to be a loſer Sir; they come.</l>
            </sp>
            <stage>Enter Leonario, Queen.</stage>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Alfon.</speaker>
               <l>All joyes to the Prince of <hi>Arragon,</hi> and the fair <hi>Olivia.</hi>
               </l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Leon.</speaker>
               <l>Why not the Queen <hi>Olivia?</hi>
               </l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Alfon.</speaker>
               <l>Not while this Gentleman's Head is on, believe it.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Leon.</speaker>
               <l>Where is <hi>Mendoza?</hi>
               </l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Alfon.</speaker>
               <l>Hid within this buſh—</l>
               <l>But here's <hi>Alfonſo</hi> Generall of the Army</l>
               <l>Sent from <hi>Valentia</hi> to aſſiſt King <hi>Ferdinand</hi>
               </l>
               <l>To his native right.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Leon.</speaker>
               <l>
                  <hi>Valentia?</hi>
               </l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Alfon.</speaker>
               <l>My Maſter having faild in his firſt aids</l>
               <l>To <hi>Ferdinand,</hi> intended not ſit down</l>
               <l>With ſo much loſs, but rais'd another Army,</l>
               <l>Which in our march conſulted our ſecurity</l>
               <l>By Interception of all paſſages;</l>
               <l>Your meſſenger by a party was ſurpriz'd,</l>
               <l>Him, ſtubborn to diſcover what he was,</l>
               <l>Imperfect in his anſwer, we Interpreted</l>
               <l>Some ſpie, and ſearching found your Letters fraught</l>
               <l>With miſchief and revenge, theſe ſent to our King</l>
               <l>We had command to haſten our deſign,</l>
               <l>And ſteer our courſe by Sea to <hi>Carthagena,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>How after we arriv'd, we gaind your faith</l>
               <l>And purpoſes, Your highneſs knows.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Leon.</speaker>
               <l>Betrayd?</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Alfon.</speaker>
               <l>Sir, be a Prince, and juſt to your own honour,</l>
               <l>And having perfected your fair deſires</l>
               <l>With her, we hope you will account your ſelf</l>
               <l>Moſt happy that you miſt a power to ſerve</l>
               <l>Further revenge upon a lawfull Prince,</l>
               <l>My Soldiers will obey me now, although</l>
               <pb n="74" facs="tcp:153589:42"/>
               <l>To help your Marriage I appear'd no friend</l>
               <l>To <hi>Ferdinand.</hi>
               </l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Leand.</speaker>
               <l>Who was the Prince preſerv'd</l>
               <l>By me, and ſent an Infant to this Lord,</l>
               <l>My noble Kinſman.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Alfon.</speaker>
               <l>Him I bred, till time</l>
               <l>And ſtrength might arm him to return, and claim</l>
               <l>His own.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Leon.</speaker>
               <l>
                  <hi>Leandro</hi> denied this before.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Leand.</speaker>
               <l>To my diſhonour, 'twas a coward fear</l>
               <l>To loſe my ſelf unprofitably</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Leon.</speaker>
               <l>I apprehend with wonder.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Ferd.</speaker>
               <l>If you repent not-love and our alliance,</l>
               <l>She ſhall be worth your beſt embrace, and we</l>
               <l>Forgetfull of your paſſion, entertain you</l>
               <l>With all affection to our blood.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Leon.</speaker>
               <l>I meet it,</l>
               <l>And ſatisfied in this ſtory, Joy I was</l>
               <l>Prevented; I congratulate your Stars Sir;</l>
               <l>Nor is this treaſure of leſs price to me</l>
               <l>Than when her Temples were enchac'd with Empire.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Que.</speaker>
               <l>This love will give my ſoul another form.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Ferd.</speaker>
               <l>Our ſtorie hath been full of change, but love</l>
               <l>Hath met a glorious victory, and tied</l>
               <l>Our ſouls together with moſt firm embraces.</l>
               <l>My Lord <hi>Leandro</hi> you ſhall to <hi>Valentia,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>With our beſt thanks and greeting to the King;</l>
               <l>His Armies charge is ours, beſide what elſe</l>
               <l>We owe his Royall bountie. Once more welcome</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Alfonſo</hi> now my Father, witneſs I</l>
               <l>Preſerve my faith to my <hi>Roſania,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>I hear the Prieſt call us to other rites,</l>
               <l>His Altar doth expect another pair,</l>
               <l>Make haſt to light his Tapers with thine eyes</l>
               <l>And make our hearts each others Sacrifice.</l>
            </sp>
            <stage>Exeunt Omnes.</stage>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
         <div type="epilogue">
            <pb facs="tcp:153589:42"/>
            <head>Epilogue, Captain.</head>
            <opener>
               <salute>Gentlemen,</salute>
            </opener>
            <l>
               <hi>I</hi> Am no Epilogue, I come to pray</l>
            <l>You'd tell me your opinion of the Play,</l>
            <l>Is the Plot current? may we truſt the wit</l>
            <l>Without a Say-Maſter to autoriſe it?</l>
            <l>Are the lines Sterling? do they hold conceit?</l>
            <l>And every peece with your allowance, weight?</l>
            <l>That when you come abroad, you'l not report</l>
            <l>You are ſorry to have given white money for't?</l>
            <l>So, ſo, I know your meaning, now pray tell</l>
            <l>How did the action pleaſe ye, was it well?</l>
            <l>How did King <hi>Stephen</hi> do, and tother Prince?</l>
            <l>Enough, enough, I apprehend, and ſince</l>
            <l>I am at queſtions w'ee, tell me faith</l>
            <l>How do you like the Captain? ha? he ſaith,</l>
            <l>I'l tell you, y'are my friends, none here, he knows,</l>
            <l>I mean you o'the Gentry, t'whom he ows</l>
            <l>No money, will enter a falſe action,</l>
            <l>And let the reſt look too't, if there be one,</l>
            <l>Among his City creditors, that dares,</l>
            <l>He hath vow'd to preſs, and ſend him to the Wars.</l>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
            <pb facs="tcp:153589:43"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:153589:43"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:153589:44"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:153589:44"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:153589:45"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:153589:45" rendition="simple:additions"/>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
