<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Electra of Sophocles presented to Her Highnesse the Lady Elizabeth; with an epilogue, shewing the parallell in two poems, the return, and the restauration. By C.W.</title>
            <title>Electra. English</title>
            <author>Sophocles.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1649</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 179 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 57 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2012-10">2012-10 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A93563</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing S4690</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Thomason E1216_2</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R203592</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99863502</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99863502</idno>
            <idno type="VID">115706</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A93563)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 115706)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Thomason Tracts ; 169:E1216[2])</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>Electra of Sophocles presented to Her Highnesse the Lady Elizabeth; with an epilogue, shewing the parallell in two poems, the return, and the restauration. By C.W.</title>
                  <title>Electra. English</title>
                  <author>Sophocles.</author>
                  <author>Wase, Christopher, 1625?-1690.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[24], 57, [3], 12 p., [2] plates : ports., ill. (woodcuts)  </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>for Sam Brown,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>At the Hague :</pubPlace>
                  <date>MDCXLIX. [1649]</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>C.W. = Christopher Wase.</note>
                  <note>In verse.</note>
                  <note>Title pages in red and black.</note>
                  <note>Annotation on Thomason copy: "Aprill 5"; to the right of initials C.W."ase".</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the British Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Sophocles --  Translations into English --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Greek drama --  Translations into English --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2011-07</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-07</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-09</date>
            <label>Taryn Hakala</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-09</date>
            <label>Taryn Hakala</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-05</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:115706:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>ELECTRA OF <hi>SOPHOCLES:</hi> PRESENTED TO HER HIGHNESSE THE LADY ELIZABETH; With an EPILOGUE, Shewing the Parallell in two Poems, <hi>THE RET<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>RN,</hi> and <hi>THE RESTA<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>RATION.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>By <hi>C. W.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>At the <hi>Hague,</hi> for <hi>Sam. Brown,</hi> MDCXLIX.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="dedication">
            <pb facs="tcp:115706:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:115706:2"/>
            <head>TO THE MOST HIGH AND MOST VERTUOUS PRINCESSE THE LADY ELIZABETH.</head>
            <opener>
               <salute>Madam,</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>THeſe rude and uncompos'd Airs aſpire into your preſence, that from your Touch they may receive Time and Laws. If you ſhall gra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciouſly vouchſafe to read them, they will Live and Breath. It pleaſed our Renowned Lady, Queen <hi>Elizabeth,</hi> to preferre the learned Authour to the choiſe honour of her Favourite, and to conferre with him in his Naturall language. Neither doth that Moſt Illuſtrious Name, reſt on your High<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe without a deſigne of Provi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence, ſince it ſpeaks in you her
<pb facs="tcp:115706:3"/>Piety, and Early Bonds, and whatſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever Shee wore of greater Value then her Crown. May it pleaſe you here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in to countenance the Parallell. One<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly accept the Endeavours of the un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>worthy Tranſlatour, and give them Admiſsion to your Vertuous Hand, not valuing the Preſent, but receiving the Homage: For the Authoritie of your Judgement is ſo pregnant, of ſo Royall and Early Growth, and ſo he<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reditary, that Verſes licens'd by your Approbation, like ſealed Meaſures, are juſtifi'd againſt Inferiour cenſures by their mark.</p>
            <p>Playes are the Mirrours wherein Mens actions are reflected to their own view. Which, perhaps, is the true cauſe, that ſome, privy to the Uglineſſe of their own guilt, have iſſued out Warrants, for the break<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing all thoſe Looking-glaſſes; leſt their deformities recoyl, and become
<pb facs="tcp:115706:3"/>an eye-ſore unto themſelves. This dim Chryſtall (fully'd with An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiquitie, and a long voyage) will return upon your Highneſſe ſome Lines and Shadows of that Pie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie to your deceaſed Father, which ſeats you above the Age, and beyond your Years: Which makes you better then your Countrey, and higher then your Enemies: Which lodges you in our Eye as our Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ample, and in our Heart as our Treaſure.</p>
            <p>Be ſecure (moſt illuſtrious Prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſe) you are not ſo much guard<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed from flattery, by the Acts and Vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gilancy of the States, as by the Tran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcendencie of your own Merits. The Hiſtorie of your Name ſhall be an Academie, whence obſequi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous Rhetorick ſhall draw forth En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>comiums to bleach the defects of unaccompliſht Queens.</p>
            <pb facs="tcp:115706:4"/>
            <p>MADAM, Your Vertues com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mand: Let Your Clemen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cie favour the dutie of my ambition, Which is, to be</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>The most humble Honourer of Your Highneſſe, C. W.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="encomia">
            <div type="encomium">
               <pb facs="tcp:115706:4"/>
               <head>TO THE MOST EXCELLENT PRIN<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>CESSE THE LADY <hi>ELIZABETH,</hi> On my Friends Dedication of <hi>ELECTRA.</hi>
               </head>
               <opener>
                  <salute>GREAT MADAM,</salute>
               </opener>
               <l>All the Muſes humbly bow,</l>
               <l>And kneel (not to the Ordinance) but You:</l>
               <l>And mine ſtoops low, as <hi>Perſians</hi> to the sky,</l>
               <l>Low as their arrogance is bold and high</l>
               <l>Who have enacted, that the Hat and Knee</l>
               <l>The Hinge of Honour be forgot to thee.</l>
               <l>Now though You are depos'd in thoſe poor parts,</l>
               <l>You're ſtill the ſame <hi>Great Princeſſe</hi> in our hearts.</l>
               <l>Souls make your Train and Court, which is no leſſe</l>
               <l>Now, than when all Your Pallace was a preſſe.</l>
               <l>State, Pomp, obſequious throngs, and ſuch gay things</l>
               <l>Are Complements, and make but tapſtry Kings.</l>
               <pb facs="tcp:115706:5"/>
               <l>Spare Scepters, Crowns, nay blood, ſtill there remains</l>
               <l>The Princeſſe, not ſo by the Fathers Veyns</l>
               <l>Alone, but Virtues, which are ſuch they'l Wooe</l>
               <l>You Realms and Subjects where ſo er'e you go.</l>
               <l>You own a Word, a Look, a Touch will ſmooth,</l>
               <l>Unfiled <hi>Indians</hi> to Obedient Love.</l>
               <l>See Forreign Princes Crowd, and preſſe to lay</l>
               <l>Their Kingdoms by thy ſide, and next age may,</l>
               <l>See the ſcore of thy Royall Parents wrongs,</l>
               <l>Reveng'd by Kings which now ſleep in thy Loynes.</l>
               <l>You and the <hi>Duke</hi> are all our Hold and Fort,</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Henry</hi> preſents the Camp, and You the Court.</l>
               <l>The Royall Widow with her beauteous Sky</l>
               <l>Of Lady's, are Seen in Your Cheek and Eye:</l>
               <l>And in Great <hi>Glo'ſters</hi> little ſelf Alone,</l>
               <l>The Father breaths, and Brother is at Home.</l>
               <l>Then leave us not, Dear pair, leaſt that we throw</l>
               <l>Our ſelves down where dead plumbets uſe to go.</l>
               <l>It is your innocence does Counter-mand</l>
               <l>Deſtruction, and bids Fire and Brimſtone, Stand;</l>
               <l>And when the rowling Mountains would come On,</l>
               <l>You like thoſe little Seeds bid e'm, Be gone.</l>
               <pb facs="tcp:115706:5"/>
               <l>On the Account too that it is your ray,</l>
               <l>Madam, alone, keeps green up in the Bay;</l>
               <l>The Poet here preſents <hi>Electra's</hi> eye</l>
               <l>A Chriſtall for to dreſſe your Cypreſſe by,</l>
               <l>To ſet your Veyl, and ſighs, and what you wear</l>
               <l>Inſtead of Pearl, each Orientall tear.</l>
               <l>And while you ſit in thoſe ſhades of your dreſſe,</l>
               <l>And Gloom of your attyre, a Tragick verſe:</l>
               <l>Moving with penſive gate, and reverend feet,</l>
               <l>May to your eye a ſmooth admittance Meet:</l>
               <l>If that it paſſe the Guard, and die not there,</l>
               <l>For Forreign Spy, or <hi>CHARLES</hi>'es Meſſenger.</l>
               <signed>H. P.</signed>
            </div>
            <div type="encomium">
               <pb facs="tcp:115706:6"/>
               <head>To my learned Friend on his apt <hi>choice and ſeaſonable tranſlation of</hi> ELECTRA in <hi>SOPHOCLES.</hi>
               </head>
               <lg>
                  <l>THe <hi>Calender</hi> that's ſtampt for <hi>fourty nine</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>Surts not the <hi>Year</hi> more, then thy <hi>Book</hi> the <hi>time:</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>Which comes forth in <hi>ſuch</hi> day, that it <hi>before</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>Had been <hi>clean Verſe,</hi> and <hi>Engliſh,</hi> but <hi>no more.</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>Now 'tis <hi>Deſigne,</hi> and <hi>Plot,</hi> and may be ſaid</l>
                  <l>Nor to bring onely <hi>forreign Wit,</hi> but <hi>Aid:</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>It ſpeaks our <hi>Land,</hi> as well as <hi>Tongue,</hi> and <hi>cares</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>Not onely for our <hi>Words,</hi> but our <hi>Affayrs.</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>You make him to <hi>invade</hi> the State, and ſeek,</l>
                  <l>Not to <hi>tranſlate,</hi> but to <hi>tranſport</hi> the <hi>Greek;</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>As if you had <hi>Commiſſion</hi> to <hi>lie</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Agent</hi> in <hi>forreign tongues,</hi> and <hi>Poeſie:</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>And when the King wants troops of valiant Verſ,</l>
                  <l>To <hi>beat</hi> your <hi>drums</hi> up through the <hi>Languages.</hi>
                  </l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>And it is <hi>Counſel</hi> now to fight the times,</l>
                  <l>Not in <hi>pitcht Proſe,</hi> but <hi>Verſe,</hi> and <hi>flying rymes.</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>'Tis ſafe too: For the Poet (as Men ſay)</l>
                  <l>Can forfeit nothing but ſome <hi>woods</hi> of <hi>Bay.</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>An old Lute, broken harp, torn wreath, or all</l>
                  <l>Such <hi>Goods</hi> and <hi>Chattels</hi> mere <hi>Poeticall.</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>Here I might praiſe the <hi>Wiſdome</hi> of thy <hi>Wit,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>Who gain'ſt the <hi>Croop</hi> of <hi>danger</hi> too in it:</l>
                  <l>For 'tis but <hi>Sophocles</hi> repeated, and</l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Eccho</hi> cannot be <hi>guilty</hi> or <hi>arraign</hi>'d.</l>
                  <pb facs="tcp:115706:6"/>
                  <l>Thus by <hi>ſlight</hi> of <hi>tranſlation</hi> you make</l>
                  <l>Him <hi>libell</hi>'em, who is <hi>ten ages</hi> back</l>
                  <l>Out of their reach: and lay your ambuſh ſo,</l>
                  <l>They ſee not who 'tis hurts e'm. <hi>He</hi> or <hi>You.</hi>
                  </l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>Yet each page of your book affrights 'em more,</l>
                  <l>Then the <hi>loud</hi> Citie-prentices at <hi>doore.</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>They tremble at their own <hi>red</hi> actions paſt,</l>
                  <l>(For 'tis their <hi>Chronicle,</hi> but writ in <hi>hast.</hi>)</l>
                  <l>And then to ſee the Puniſhment they ſhake,</l>
                  <l>Reading their <hi>Shambles,</hi> and <hi>themſelves</hi> in <hi>ſtakes.</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>When <hi>Egiſt</hi> groans, they ſtart, as if the ſteel</l>
                  <l>Reacht at their <hi>ſouls,</hi> and when He <hi>falls,</hi> They <hi>reel.</hi>
                  </l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>Thus it <hi>ſows ſpears</hi> and <hi>Agues</hi> in ſome breaſts,</l>
                  <l>But fills us with the joy of <hi>Wine</hi> and <hi>Feasts,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>And <hi>Hopes</hi> to ſee it dub'd by Victorie,</l>
                  <l>And bid, <hi>Riſe up a perfect Prophecie.</hi>
                  </l>
               </lg>
            </div>
            <div type="encomium">
               <pb facs="tcp:115706:7"/>
               <head>To his learned Friend on his ingeni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous choice and tranſlation of <hi>Sophocle's Electra,</hi> Repreſenting Allegorically theſe Times.</head>
               <l>WHat? 's aged <hi>Sophocles</hi> ſtill infant? how</l>
               <l>Comes it to paſſe he learns to ſpeak but now?</l>
               <l>His lines before were but half truth; his ſtyle</l>
               <l>Againſt this age thy wit doth whet and file.</l>
               <l>Me thinks this were a perfect Prophecie,</l>
               <l>But that there wants ſtill the Cataſtrophe:</l>
               <l>Here guilt with guilt is parallel'd; the rime</l>
               <l>Of vengeance too may be compleat in time.</l>
               <l>Our <hi>Agamemnon</hi>'s dead, <hi>Electra</hi> grieves,</l>
               <l>The onely hope is that <hi>Oreſtes</hi> lives.</l>
               <l>Others can onely books tranſlate; but thou</l>
               <l>Tranſlat'ſt the Poeme, and the Poet too,</l>
               <l>And mak'ſt him Prophet; as with double face,</l>
               <l>He ſee's behind him by thy looking-glaſſe.</l>
               <l>Poets themſelves were ne're transform'd; but here</l>
               <l>In one twy-forkt <hi>Parnaſſus</hi> doth appear.</l>
               <l>Theſe times were typifi'd by thoſe; and he</l>
               <l>I'le boldly adde, was but a type of thee.</l>
               <signed>W. G.</signed>
            </div>
            <div type="encomium">
               <pb facs="tcp:115706:7"/>
               <head>To my moſt intimate <hi>C. F. C. W. On his ELECTRA,</hi> Tranſlated out of the <hi>Greek,</hi> and laid at the feet of her Highneſſe the Lady ELIZABETH.</head>
               <opener>
                  <salute>BOld Friend,</salute>
               </opener>
               <lg>
                  <l>Thou haſt ſpoke words, and thou muſt look</l>
                  <l>To be indited for thy per'lous Book;</l>
                  <l>Twelve honeſt men of <hi>Mycens</hi> ſhall debate</l>
                  <l>About the Symptomes of thy fooliſh Fate.</l>
                  <l>How wilt thou look when thou ſhalt be attaqu'd.</l>
                  <l>For having broke Lord <hi>Egiſts</hi> new made Act?</l>
                  <l>O for a Limber then with grace to hint</l>
                  <l>Thy wan complexion and thy face in print!</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>Is it a cheap offence to have diſplay'd</l>
                  <l>The Myſterie of the Thanksgiving-trade,</l>
                  <l>That you Humiliations too muſt mock,</l>
                  <l>It's dear Co-partner, that drives on one ſtock?</l>
               </lg>
               <pb facs="tcp:115706:8"/>
               <lg>
                  <l>Thou ſweet <hi>Electra</hi> haſt with ſighs reliev'd;</l>
                  <l>Thou haſt with her in all her ſorrows griev'd.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>And when 'twas Ordered that ſhe be array'd</l>
                  <l>In the caſt gown of ſome ſtale Chamber-maid;</l>
                  <l>Thou from remoteſt Iſles Attire haſt brought</l>
                  <l>Of pureſt gold, with curious phanſie wrought,</l>
                  <l>Unfolded from the Ward-robe of thy Wit.</l>
                  <l>Rich as the Veſts aboard her Fathers fleet,</l>
                  <l>When <hi>Aſian</hi> Robes, and coſtly <hi>Phrygian</hi> Vayls,</l>
                  <l>Over the Victour ſpred their ſilken ſayles</l>
                  <l>Nor were they Webs of an inſeriour Grain</l>
                  <l>By rude and Needy Vulgar knit for Gain:</l>
                  <l>There fifty Princeſſes in ſtately grace,</l>
                  <l>With equall Princes match'd, great <hi>Priams</hi> race,</l>
                  <l>On Ivory Couches in ſoft Cuſhions plac'd,</l>
                  <l>(The lofty Gallery's with gold enchac'd)</l>
                  <l>Their Needles ply: each Madams nimble clue</l>
                  <l>The younger Dames and honour'd Maids purſue,</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>When <hi>Egiſt</hi> too had her confinement charg'd</l>
                  <l>By thee thus richly clad ſhe is enlarg'd,</l>
                  <l>And by a Princeſſe plac'd, whoſe each aſpect</l>
                  <l>Will an enriched Ray of grief reflect:</l>
                  <l>See how they kindle tears, how by conſent</l>
                  <l>They now themſelves, each other now lament.</l>
                  <pb facs="tcp:115706:8"/>
                  <l>Mark their thick Tears, and fair dejected Head,</l>
                  <l>As heavie Lilly's honey-riv'lets ſhed.</l>
                  <l>Then they look up, and if but thin drops ſhoot,</l>
                  <l>At th' others Eie their watry Hoſt recruit.</l>
                  <l>The ſtreams fall in and mix. Pale ſorrow rides</l>
                  <l>In ſilent depths, and unimpeached tides.</l>
                  <l>Now Tears they vie, and in the place contend,</l>
                  <l>Each is a Duelliſt, and not a Friend:</l>
                  <l>Till on the precious pavement this rich vein</l>
                  <l>Is loſt in that, and ſo they cloſe again:</l>
                  <l>Now in full force they march, joyn hand in hand,</l>
                  <l>And Grief no Champion is, but a full Band.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>But I muſt adde one word, before we end,</l>
                  <l>To expiate my having been thy friend.</l>
                  <l>Had I thee known a <hi>Greek,</hi> or that way given,</l>
                  <l>From this foul fault long ſince I had been driven.</l>
                  <l>I'd fled at diſtance, and a farre off feard</l>
                  <l>Thy paſtbord ſtomacher and goodly Beard.</l>
                  <l>But theſe are all inviſible in thee,</l>
                  <l>Inviſible as is the <hi>Greek</hi> to me.</l>
                  <l>But ſince thou tell'ſt me it, Hold, take theſe Alms,</l>
                  <l>This Verſ that wil ſcarce go, theſe with'red Palms.</l>
               </lg>
               <signed>E. F.</signed>
            </div>
         </div>
         <div type="dramatis_personae">
            <pb facs="tcp:115706:9"/>
            <head>The Perſons of the Enterlude.</head>
            <list>
               <item>The <hi>Tutour</hi> and Foſter.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Oreſtes,</hi> the Prince.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Electra,</hi> the Princeſſe Royall.</item>
               <item>The <hi>Quirre</hi> of Maids of Honour dwelling neare the Palace.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Chryſotheame,</hi> the Siſter of <hi>Electra.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Clytemneſtra,</hi> the unnaturall Spouſe of <hi>Aga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>memnon,</hi> who conſpired againſt him.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Egiſt,</hi> the Paramour of <hi>Clytemnestra,</hi> and</item>
               <item>Conſpiratour againſt the King.</item>
            </list>
         </div>
         <div type="explanation_of_marginalia">
            <pb facs="tcp:115706:9"/>
            <head>The Signification of the References.</head>
            <p>THe Alphabeticall letter relates to the mana<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ging of the Scene, it ſhew's the Poſtures and Motions, with the Carriage of the Action.</p>
            <p>The Smaller Figures referres to the Interpreta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of ſome difficult places, and vindicating them from Obſcurity or Miſtake.</p>
            <p>The Larger Figures in the Head of ſome files of Verſes, is that which contains the moſt No<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>velty. We muſt know, that the Ancient Quire of the Greek Tragedians in the time of <hi>Sophocles,</hi> conſisted of Fifteen, ſeated by fives upon three Forms, or by threes upon five Forms. And in that Number were their Approaches and Returns, one ſpeaking for the reſt, being the fore party of the Quire. Muſick ſtill attended their Speeches and Dancing. Now theſe Stanzas prick'd out by Numbers, are moſt exactly anſwer'd by an en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſuing Stanza, either immediately enſuing, or ſo enterwoven, that the third anſwers the firſt, and the fourth the ſecond. Every ſuch Stanza ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving 'its Counterpart, and every Member though of different Meeter, being exactly commenſurate with the Member following in the ſame Num<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber of the Counterpart. It is ſuspicious that of theſe Songs, the former referr'd to a Leading up of the Dance in ſet Paces, and the Latter to a Returning in equall Steps. Onely this kind of Dancing ſeems to have fall'n even in the Ro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man
<pb facs="tcp:115706:10"/>Tragedy's, though I hardly know any thing to have been more magnificent in the very flower and height of their Empire, then their Sumptu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous Theaters and Amphitheaters. This long diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uſe hath tranſmitted us a very obſcure notion of thoſe rarityes in Muſick wherein the Ancient Greeks ſeem to have excell'd. So that it may be excuſable, if I am not clear enough in delivering that, of which the injury of Time hath ſcarce left a ſhadow.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="historical_background">
            <pb facs="tcp:115706:10"/>
            <head>A ſhort extract of the Hiſtory about <hi>the deſtruction of TROY.</hi>
            </head>
            <p>BEcauſe this confident Eſſay hath adventur'd to go out, under the ſilken Banner of Her Highneſſe, and being a piece which proceeded from an Authour, in the Originall, whoſe character it is ſtill to have done right to vertuous Lady's; It may poſſibly be engag'd (though Naturally Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deſt) in the Attendance of ſome of that ſex. Now it were indiſcretion to think their fair hands can afford to be ſoyl'd with the duſtie records of Time, or impertinent Hiſtory, further then the Arras can inſtruct, or then may be underſtood by one who is well-verſ'd in the Ward-robe. Therefore I ſhall take it for a needfull part of my duty here, to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcribe briefly the Heads of this Story, ſo familiarly intimated in the Poem.</p>
            <p>The voiage to <hi>Troy</hi> happened in the MCXCIIII yeare, before the Incarnation of our Saviour, about the time that <hi>Jair</hi> judg'd <hi>Iſrael.</hi> Upon this Quar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rell. <hi>Paris</hi> the ſonne of <hi>Priam</hi> (King of <hi>Troy</hi>) ſail'd over to <hi>Peloponneſus,</hi> where <hi>Menelaus</hi> reign'd; having for his Queen <hi>Helen</hi> the great beauty of her age. <hi>Paris</hi> lodg'd in the Court of <hi>Menelaus,</hi> in whoſe abſence he carries away <hi>He<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>len</hi> (againſt the Laws of her Wedlock, and his Hoſpitality) over to <hi>Troy</hi> with him. <hi>Menelaus</hi> returning, demands her, and is repuls'd. Where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>upon he invites his Brother <hi>Agamemnon,</hi> then King of <hi>Argos,</hi> to aſſiſt him in the recovery of
<pb facs="tcp:115706:11"/>her by arm's. So both the Kings with the other neighbour Princes, levying the whole ſtrength of <hi>Greece,</hi> fell down towards <hi>Aulis</hi> an Iſland in <hi>Boeotia;</hi> where they entred into confederacie, not to return till either <hi>Troy</hi> were ras'd, or they pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſhed in the enterpriſe. But when they ſhould have put out, the Navie lay becalm'd, till accord<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to the anſwer of the Oracle which they con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſulted, <hi>Agamemnon</hi> had ſacrific'd his daughter <hi>Iphigenia.</hi> About xxvii years after this <hi>Jephthe</hi> ſacrificed his daughter: ſo that ſome think this of <hi>Iphigenia</hi> a fiction, and that uncertain tradition huddled up both times together, and that the La<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dyes right name was <hi>Iphtigenia.</hi> This warre laſted ten years, till the prime and ableſt Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manders being cut off on both ſides, the Victorie fell to the Greeks, whoſe cauſe was the juſter; <hi>Troy</hi> being taken by the treachery of <hi>Aeneas</hi> and <hi>An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tenor,</hi> &amp; ſack'd, and burnt. Yet it far'd little better with the Conquerours in their return, then it had with the conquered, moſt of them being weather<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>beaten, and caſt away. As for <hi>Agamemnon,</hi> he was ſlain in his own houſe by wicked <hi>Egiſt,</hi> through the complotment of <hi>Clytemneſtra:</hi> which unnaturall treaſon, <hi>Oreſtes</hi> with the aſſiſtance of <hi>Electra</hi> reveng'd: Heaven, as it were, rewarding this affection of <hi>Oreſtes,</hi> by length of dayes, and happineſſe of Government; for he lived ninetie years, &amp; reigned ſeventy, match'd with <hi>Hermione.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The Tyrannicall uſurpation of the <hi>Mycenian</hi> Kingdome, with the Affliction and Oppreſſion of the Royall Children, and the Deſtruction of the
<pb facs="tcp:115706:11"/>Conſpiratours, the Enthroning of <hi>Oreſtes,</hi> with the Deliverance of the Royall Family, make up this work.</p>
            <p>It was written by <hi>Sophocles,</hi> who was born in the CCCCXCV yeare before the Incarnation of our Saviour, and lived XC years.</p>
            <p>So that this Action was performed little leſſe then MMM years ago; and repreſented in this Tragedie ſomewhat more then MM.</p>
            <p>This Abridgement of that famous Hiſtory, is ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tracted (for the generality) out of <hi>Petavius,</hi> a moſt exact Chronologer, though with ſome change and addition.</p>
            <p>The reſt will be ſupply'd by the Notes.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="prologue">
            <pb facs="tcp:115706:12"/>
            <head>The Hiſtoricall and Morall Plot of the Tragedy.</head>
            <lg>
               <l>EXil'd <hi>Oreſtes</hi> is return'd, though late,</l>
               <l>His Royall Fathers blood to expiate:</l>
               <l>That Blood from which War and the bold ſword ſhrunk</l>
               <l>Yet was by Treaſon, and the cold Ax drunk.</l>
               <l>Safe is he entred, but yet unrevea'ld,</l>
               <l>By Night and darker policy conceal'd.</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Electra</hi> here a Generous Defyer,</l>
               <l>In vain to comfort woo'd by the kind Quire,</l>
               <l>Chides <hi>Chryſotheame</hi> a white-liver'd Complyer:</l>
               <l>Who was with Offering by her Mother ſent</l>
               <l>To bribe the dead, and Seape the puniſhment.</l>
               <l>She intercepts the gifts, the Oyles ſhe ſpills,</l>
               <l>And with a ſmoaking Curſe her Cenſer fills.</l>
               <l>The <hi>Cannon</hi>'s turn, and this revolting prayer,</l>
               <l>Went forth a Treaſure, but returns a ſnare.</l>
               <l>But <hi>Clytemneſtra</hi> pleads the fact was Juſt,</l>
               <l>The Bill was Murder, where the Judge was Luſt.</l>
               <l>Yet though th' out-faced Noon ſhe down may beat,</l>
               <l>The Dark brings Viſion, and the Silence threat,</l>
               <l>Laſh'd by pale dreams, the Hobs of night, ſhe runs</l>
               <l>To flattering Humiliations.</l>
               <pb facs="tcp:115706:12"/>
               <l>Thinking thoſe angry Beadles to diſarm,</l>
               <l>With ſtrumpet Incenſe and Religious charm.</l>
               <l>But hypocriticall Devotions dreſſe,</l>
               <l>A Pageant ſafety, and a Mock of peace:</l>
               <l>For ſcarce her prayers are cool'd and downward bending</l>
               <l>When their return is at the door attending.</l>
               <l>A Poſt in neat Romance <hi>Oreſtes</hi> ſlayes,</l>
               <l>Secures the field, and ſo the field betrayes.</l>
               <l>Now ſad <hi>Electra</hi> at the diſmall news</l>
               <l>Diſſolves, and ſcatters into pious Dews.</l>
               <l>The Quire Companions of her grief ſhe ſlights,</l>
               <l>Nor in her Sisters joyfull words delights.</l>
               <l>Who ſees large offerings at the Sepulchre,</l>
               <l>And thence her Brothers hand doth right inferre.</l>
               <l>Built on much reaſon: but we leſſe ſet by</l>
               <l>Weak-grounded truth, then a bold hear-ſay ly<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
               </l>
               <l>Hence raging grief into hard valour knits,</l>
               <l>(For both are elevate beyond our wits)</l>
               <l>Her Sister ſhe invites to mutuall Aid,</l>
               <l>With hands combin'd the Traytor to invade,</l>
               <l>And is repuls'd, yet ſhe reſolves alone</l>
               <l>To execute her reſolution.</l>
               <l>Thoſe who Compound led captive by tame Eaſe,</l>
               <l>Seldome on dangerous Honour dare to Seize.</l>
               <pb facs="tcp:115706:13"/>
               <l>Poor loyalty, how low now art thou laid</l>
               <l>By Enemies deſtroy'd, by friends betray'd!</l>
               <l>What valiant wiſdome will appear at once,</l>
               <l>To break thy foes, and heal thy Factions?</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Oreſtes</hi> is at door; his Urn he ſhews,</l>
               <l>Meets with <hi>Electra</hi> and confirms her woes.</l>
               <l>The dear Impoſture ſhe muſt ſee and hold,</l>
               <l>And to her Brother all her cares unfold.</l>
               <l>In dolefull accents her ſweet paſſions ſound,</l>
               <l>Which in a precious deluge ſtreight are drown'd.</l>
               <l>The happy witneſſe of thoſe pious throws.</l>
               <l>Cannot forbear his perſon to diſcloſe.</l>
               <l>Their Joyes ſwell high, but at a quick ſurprize,</l>
               <l>Firſt <hi>Clytemneſtra,</hi> and then <hi>Egiſt</hi> dy's.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Thus Loyall ſorrow in high triumph ends,</l>
               <l>While rebell Joy Eternall Black attends.</l>
            </lg>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="play">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:115706:13"/>
            <head>ELECTRA <hi>OF</hi> SOPHOCLES.</head>
            <sp>
               <speaker> The Tutour.</speaker>
               <stage n="a" place="margin">
                  <hi>The Tu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tour</hi> and <hi>O<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reſtes</hi> are brought in upon the way to <hi>Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gos,</hi> newly coming in by break of day; and the old man tels him all the places as he comes by, &amp; where he is: For it is preſum'd, that he being about ten years old at his departure had not before the wiſdome to take notice of them. The entrance is pert and live<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, being quickned by frequent pointing at ſights, and alteration of poſture: it is alſo ſtately, opening into various Scenes, and being beautified with a proſpect upon objects, full both of delight and magnificence. Beſides that delicate paſſion which is inſinuated into us, to ſee an Exile entring his Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trey, which he was forc'd to leave very young; and to heare thoſe places repeat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed as he paſſes along, whoſe bare names cannot but raiſe in him a Naturall endearment.</stage>
               <l>SOn of great <hi>Agamemnon,</hi> he who late</l>
               <l>Led the <hi>Greek</hi> hoſt againſt the Trojan State;</l>
               <l>Now may thine eyes their wiſhed objects read:</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>This</hi> is old <hi>Argos</hi> you ſtill long'd to tread.</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Yon</hi> grove is
<note n="1" place="bottom">
                     <hi>Io</hi> the daughter of <hi>Inachus,</hi> raviſhed by <hi>Jupiter,</hi> was upon the ſurpri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſall of jealous <hi>Juno,</hi> for ſecreſie, transformd into a cow: <hi>Juno</hi> ſuſpecting this, creates the Ox-flie, and ſets it upon her; with whoſe ſting ſhe was ſo vehemently infeſted, that ſhe runne mad: but was afterward by <hi>Jupiter</hi> pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerred to a goddeſſe, &amp; worſhipped with conſecrated groves by the <hi>Athenians.</hi>
                  </note> 
                  <hi>horn-mad Inachi's</hi> abode:</l>
               <l>And <hi>this, Oreſtes,</hi>
                  <note n="2" place="bottom">
                     <hi>Apollo</hi> the guardian of flocks: which care in deſtroying Wolves, was al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wayes much magnified in countreys of great paſturage.</note> the wolf-ſlaying god</l>
               <l>Wolf-Court hath nam'd: But <hi>on the left</hi> her fanes</l>
               <l>The proud
<note n="3" place="bottom">
                     <hi>Junoes</hi> Temple, about two miles diſtant from <hi>Mycens.</hi>
                  </note> 
                  <hi>Heraeum's</hi> ſpiring tops advance:</l>
               <pb n="2" facs="tcp:115706:14"/>
               <l>
                  <hi>Mycens</hi> the wealthy <hi>here</hi> her Treaſures ſhow's,</l>
               <l>
                  <stage n="b" place="margin">They make a ſtand at the door of the royal hall, and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bate.</stage> And <hi>this</hi> the
<note n="4" place="margin">The ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lamitous ſeat of the <hi>Argive</hi> Kings: w<hi rend="sup">ch</hi> were <hi>Pelops</hi> matchdwith <hi>Hippoda<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mia,</hi> daugh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter to <hi>Oe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nomaus</hi> King of the <hi>Eleans.</hi> After whom ſucceeded <hi>Atreus,</hi> matchd with <hi>Aeropes</hi> He had a brother <hi>Thyeſtes:</hi> this brother inceſtuouſly conſotted with <hi>Aerope,</hi> which made <hi>Atreus,</hi> to aſſert his nuptiall honour, enter on this high-flown revenge: he invites him to a feaſt, wherein he caters his own inceſtuous brood for his entertainment. <hi>Thyeſtes</hi> after the ſupper underſtanding of this, conſulted the Oracle, how he might recompenſe the cruelty, and according to the anſwer, devirginates his own daughter <hi>Pelopera,</hi> by which inceſt was be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>got <hi>Egiſt.</hi> After <hi>Atreus, Agamemnon</hi> reigned, that matched with <hi>Clytem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſtra:</hi> he after the ten years ſiege of <hi>Troy</hi> returning in conqueſt, was ſlain by <hi>Egiſt,</hi> who in his abſence had wonn great authority in the kingdom. This he compaſſed by ſcaling the bed of <hi>Clytemneſtra,</hi> who was left Regent of <hi>Mycens</hi> in the time of the voyage.</note> infamous <hi>Pelopeian</hi> houſe,</l>
               <l>Whence I thee, as thy Father freſh was ſlain,</l>
               <l>From thy dear ſiſters ſweet embraces ta'ne</l>
               <l>Reſcu'd and ſav'd, and to this bigneſſe bred</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Avenger of thy Royall Fathers head.</hi>
               </l>
               <l>Now then, <hi>Orestes,</hi> and thou deareſt friend</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Pylade,</hi> diſpatch we that that we intend.</l>
               <l>For birds with chirping Mattins call from bed</l>
               <l>The woken Suns already riſing head,</l>
               <l>And ſable night of all her ſtarrs is rid:</l>
               <l>Wherefore e're any out of doores ſhall ſtirre,</l>
               <l>Conferre your thoughts. No time now to <hi>demur,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>But forward action <hi>ripen'd</hi> is to height.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Oreſt.</speaker>
               <l>Deareſt of my attendants, now I ſee't</l>
               <l>How kind thou art to us it plain appears,</l>
               <l>For as ſome <hi>mettel'd</hi> ſteed, though <hi>ſtruck in years,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>In hotteſt ſervice nought of heart lets go,</l>
               <l>But ſtands with ear erect; you even ſo</l>
               <l>Both ſpur us on, and march your ſelf i'ch front:</l>
               <l>I<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>'e tell you my reſolve, attend you on't:</l>
               <pb n="3" facs="tcp:115706:14"/>
               <l>And if ought unadvis'd eſcape, amend.</l>
               <l>When I the <hi>Pythian</hi> curtain did attend</l>
               <l>Conſulting how my Fathers murder, I</l>
               <l>On th' executioners might ſatisfie,</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Phoebus</hi> this anſwer gave, mark the reply:</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Without or buckler or an armies guard</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>By ſtealth procure the murders just reward,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>Since then the holy voice directs us thus,</l>
               <l>As firſt occaſion ſerv's, get in this houſe,</l>
               <l>And mark what e're is done, &amp; when you know,</l>
               <l>Make us acquainted how all actions go:</l>
               <l>For they'll ne're ſpie nor once ſuſpect your ſhew,</l>
               <l>With age diſguis'd, long abſence, and this hiew:</l>
               <l>And make your tale this wiſe; A Forreiner</l>
               <l>Of <hi>Phoce,</hi> ſent by noble <hi>Phanot</hi> there,</l>
               <l>(For he and they in neareſt league combine)</l>
               <l>You come to tell (thereto a deep oath joyn)</l>
               <l>How that <hi>Oreſtes</hi> came t'untimely end</l>
               <l>As in the <hi>Pythian</hi> matches they contend,</l>
               <l>Struck from the hurrying eoach: This ſtory paſſe.</l>
               <l>Mean while my Fathers tombe in the firſt place</l>
               <l>(As was appointed then) with locks new ſhorn,</l>
               <l>And hallowed liquours we forth with adorn:</l>
               <l>Then we return, and carrying in our hands</l>
               <l>The pot which midſt the thicket you know ſtands</l>
               <l>To hide the tale, the ſweet news you have ſe'd</l>
               <l>Wee'll bring them word of, how that I am dead;</l>
               <l>My body in the funerall pile <hi>calcin'd,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>To the few aſhes in this urn confin'd:</l>
               <l>For what great harm if but <hi>reported</hi> ſlain,</l>
               <l>In <hi>truth</hi> I live, and great <hi>renown</hi> obtain.</l>
               <l>I'me of the mind no words that <hi>gain</hi> are nought:</l>
               <pb n="4" facs="tcp:115706:15"/>
               <l>Thus have I oft ſeen
<note n="5" place="margin">The Po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>et ſeems to have had an eye upon <hi>Lycurgus</hi> and <hi>Pytha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>goras,</hi> yet a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>voids that miſtake of anticipati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of hiſto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry, while he onely names an action which might have been common to former ages, &amp; conceals thoſe actors which were long after the time of <hi>Oreſtes.</hi>
                  </note> Sages carry'd out</l>
               <l>I th' <hi>empty coffin</hi> of a falſe report,</l>
               <l>Yet ſafe come home and double honour'd for 't;</l>
               <l>So truſt I from this fame alive to <hi>riſe,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>Like a <hi>bright ſtar</hi> upon my enemies.</l>
               <l>O Countrey ſoil and <hi>Greeces</hi> guardian powers,</l>
               <l>Send me a bleſſed journey to theſe Towers;</l>
               <l>And you my Fathers Hall, for you I come</l>
               <l>To expiate you, led by heav'nly doom:</l>
               <l>Nor ſend me with diſgrace out of theſe ports,</l>
               <l>But <hi>Lord</hi> of <hi>wealth,</hi> but <hi>Founder</hi> of great <hi>Courts.</hi>
               </l>
               <l>Well, I have done: but you, <hi>grave Sir,</hi> beware</l>
               <l>To what our Counſel charg'd upon your care:</l>
               <l>And we away, 'Tis time, for alway's this</l>
               <l>Grand <hi>Over-ſeer</hi> of all actions is.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>El.</speaker>
               <p>Ay me, unhappy me!</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Tut.</speaker>
               <l>Methinks within door, child, I ſeemd to heare</l>
               <l>One of the maidens keep a groaning there.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Or.</speaker>
               <l>'Tis poore Electra, is 't not, prithee fain</l>
               <l>I'ld ſtay a while, and heare the plaint again.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Tut,</speaker>
               <l>By no means, nought before <hi>Phoebus</hi> ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vice</l>
               <l>Aſſay to do: Thence take our Action riſe.</l>
               <l>Go, poure your offerings on your Fathers tombe,</l>
               <l>For Triumph hence, and might for Service come:
<stage n="c" place="margin">
                     <hi>Oreſtes</hi> &amp; <hi>Pylades</hi> (a mute companion of <hi>Orestes)</hi> go away from before the gate, to the tombe of <hi>Agamemnon,</hi> and <hi>the Tu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tour</hi> goes away, but parts from them.</stage>
               </l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>El.</speaker>
               <l>
                  <stage n="d" place="bottom">
                     <hi>Electra</hi> newly up, and wayling walks out to the gate.</stage> Sacred light, earth-bounding aire,</l>
               <l>Nurſes privy to my care,</l>
               <pb n="5" facs="tcp:115706:15"/>
               <l>You my Dirges witneſſe beſt,</l>
               <l>You how I ply my bruiſed breſt,</l>
               <l>When the gloomy Shade, is ceaſt;</l>
               <l>But my Night grones ring aloof,</l>
               <l>In the ſad Courts wicked roof,</l>
               <l>While I my poor Father mean,</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Whom in Barbarous Region</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Bloudy</hi> Mars <hi>had let alone,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <note n="6" place="margin">Here may not unpro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perly be urg'd the old caution, that ſimilitudes run not upon all foure: Yet may this be a fit pourtraiture of an accu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mulative or aggregative Lady, the queen politick, which hath trull'd it in the lewd embraces of the ſouldiery, and to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſummare the ſcandall, ſhall have conſpired with it, &amp; together hainouſly upon agreement, deſtroys her juſt and undoubted Lord.</note> But my Mother and her Mate</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Egiſt,</hi> as ſtrong Swains lie at</l>
               <l>A ſturdy Oak to fell down flat,</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>His head with bloudy Pol-ax cleave:</hi>
               </l>
               <l>Nor any but I at this grieve</l>
               <l>That thou, Father, thus ſhouldſt come</l>
               <l>To a ſad unworthy <hi>doom.</hi>
               </l>
               <l>But moan I <hi>will</hi> and cry,</l>
               <l>While I the glittering ſtars eſpy,</l>
               <l>While I the day diſcover</l>
               <l>My plaint I'le nere give over,</l>
               <l>But as a robd Nightingall</l>
               <l>Will my ſorrows tune, and all</l>
               <l>Shall heare my moan before this gate;</l>
               <l>O <hi>Pluto's</hi> and <hi>Proſerpines</hi> ſtate!</l>
               <l>O <hi>Mercury</hi> and curſe that ſure is!</l>
               <l>O ſtern god-begotten Fury's!</l>
               <l>You Crowners of the murdred, heare</l>
               <l>You Watchers of th' Adulterer!</l>
               <l>Come ye, help ye, venge ye all</l>
               <l>Our Fathers fall:</l>
               <l>And my brother home me call.</l>
               <l>My ſelf no longer can weigh down</l>
               <l>My overbearing moan.</l>
            </sp>
            <pb n="6" facs="tcp:115706:16"/>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Quir.</speaker>
               <l n="1">1 Child,
<stage n="c" place="margin">The La<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy's dwel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling hard by, come to her that they may comfort her.</stage> child <hi>Electra,</hi> of a mother</l>
               <l n="2">2 Unlucky'ſt of all other</l>
               <l n="3">3 Why alwayes thus dripping away</l>
               <l n="4">4 In tears that can find no allay,</l>
               <l n="5">5 For <hi>Agamemnon</hi> long ſince ſlain</l>
               <l n="6">6 By the ungodly wily Quain,</l>
               <l n="7">7 And betrayd by wicked train.</l>
               <l n="8">8 O that he who did this contrive</l>
               <l n="9">9 (If I may ſay't) may he nere thrive!</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>El.</speaker>
               <l n="1">1 Iſſues of noble parentage,</l>
               <l n="2">2 You come my ſorrow to aſſwage,</l>
               <l n="3">3 I ſee and know it, nor deceive</l>
               <l n="4">4 You me, yet never by your leave</l>
               <l n="5">5 Will I ſurceaſe with ſobbing cries</l>
               <l n="6">6 To mourn my Fathers obſequies:</l>
               <l n="7">7 Wherefore ſweet Damſels ever kind,</l>
               <l n="8">8 Let me this favour from you find,</l>
               <l n="9">9 Let me alone,</l>
               <l n="10">10 Alwayes, alack, alack to groan.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Quir.</speaker>
               <l n="1">1 Why from deaths Catholick Meere you'l never</l>
               <l n="2">2 Though moſt you moan, deliver</l>
               <l n="3">3 Your Father back: or cry, or pray,</l>
               <l n="4">4 You onely caſt your ſelf away:</l>
               <l n="5">5 While you improve and give more weight</l>
               <l n="6">6 To ſorrows load, which elſe were light;</l>
               <l n="7">7 Nor can releaſe come by 't</l>
               <l n="8">8 From the ſad preſſure of your wo:</l>
               <l n="9">9 Why long you then your ſelf t' undo.</l>
            </sp>
            <pb n="7" facs="tcp:115706:16"/>
            <sp>
               <speaker>El.</speaker>
               <l n="1">1 Fooliſh they who in ſilence ſheath</l>
               <l n="2">2 Their parents brought to wretched death.</l>
               <l n="3">3 But me
<note n="7" place="margin">
                     <hi>Progne,</hi> feignd by the Poets to have been tranſlated into a Swallow, or Robbin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red-breſt; She to revenge up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on her husband <hi>Tereus,</hi> the inceſtuous rape of her ſiſter <hi>Philomel,</hi> murthers his ſonne <hi>Itys,</hi> and ſtews and ſets him on the board to her husband, which in ſupper-time, to com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pleat the cruelty, ſhe diſcovers; and wingd with ſudden flight, is converted into a Bird, whoſe breaſt is all ſtaind with gore. She is ſaid continually to lament this prodigious effect of her high-wrought paſſion.</note> the dolefull one contents</l>
               <l n="4">4 Which <hi>Itys</hi> ſtill, <hi>Itys</hi> laments:</l>
               <l n="5">5 Afflicted bird, <hi>Joves</hi> Meſſenger,</l>
               <l n="6">6 Sent for the Summers Harbinger.</l>
               <l n="7">7 But, O diſtreſſed
<note n="7" place="bottom">
                     <hi>Niobe</hi> after the loſſe of her numerous and flouriſhing progeny, which cauſed her diſcontented husband to make away himſelf, being reduc'd from proſperous and proud, to a childleſſe widow, through exceſſive ſorrow, is ſaid to have congeald into an entire rock, onely her tears reſervd <hi>See both theſe Fables at large in Sandys Ovid. Metam.</hi> book. 6.</note> 
                  <hi>Niobe!</hi>
               </l>
               <l n="8">8 I thee adore my Deity,</l>
               <l n="9">9 Which weepeſt ſtill,</l>
               <l n="10">10 From rocky tombe a teary rill.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Quir,</speaker>
               <l>You are not, Madam, th' onely ſhee</l>
               <l>VVho in this grief plead property,</l>
               <l>VVhy you ſo loud 'bove them within</l>
               <l>I'th ſame degree of bloud akin</l>
               <l>As <hi>Chryſotheame</hi> and <hi>Iphianaſſe</hi> both,</l>
               <l>And he who griev's in hidden growth?</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>El.</speaker>
               <l>Happy whom nor yet long hence</l>
               <l>Fam'd <hi>Mycens</hi> land ſhall bear, <hi>brave Prince;</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Oreſtes</hi> ſent by <hi>Joves</hi> decree;</l>
               <l>Whom I unweary'd wait to ſee;</l>
               <l>Childleſſe, piteous, husbandleſſe,</l>
               <l>Pining away with wretchedneſſe,</l>
               <l>Waſting in teares, nor can be found</l>
               <l>What may give my ſorrows bound,</l>
               <pb n="8" facs="tcp:115706:17"/>
               <l>While he forgets both what's him done,</l>
               <l>And what him taught, falſe rumours runne:</l>
               <l>Fain would he e're.</l>
               <l>Yet though he'ld fain do's not appear.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Qu.</speaker>
               <l>Madam chear up, come chear,</l>
               <l>In heaven great <hi>Jove</hi> reſides</l>
               <l>Who all things ſees and guides.</l>
               <l>To whom <hi>exceſſive</hi> paſſions leaving</l>
               <l>Nor <hi>ſenſeleſſe</hi> be, nor <hi>overgrieving,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>Time is a gentle god, nor yet</l>
               <l>Doe's <hi>Agamemnons</hi> youth <hi>forget</hi>
               </l>
               <l>To come unto his native land</l>
               <l>Though now in <hi>Criſa's</hi> fertile ſtrand.</l>
               <l>Nor who the world <hi>controlls</hi> below,</l>
               <l>Will <hi>murther</hi> ſee <hi>unpuniſh't</hi> go.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>El.</speaker>
               <l>But I mean while <hi>ſans hope</hi> perceive</l>
               <l>My tender Age poor me to leave,</l>
               <l>Nor can I longer ſtay</l>
               <l>Which without Parents fade away:</l>
               <l>Nor have a Friend my part to take,</l>
               <l>But <hi>Pilgrim-like</hi> whom all forſake;</l>
               <l>At home in theſe <hi>poor cloths</hi> muſt ſpread,</l>
               <l>My Fathers empty <hi>Bord</hi> and <hi>Bed.</hi>
               </l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Qui.</speaker>
               <l n="1">1 Wretched coming, to remember!</l>
               <l n="2">2 Wretched blow giv'n in the chamber!</l>
               <l n="3">3 Where with the <hi>broad ſteel-faced Cleaver</hi>
               </l>
               <l n="4">4 <hi>The Royall Temples they diſſever.</hi>
               </l>
               <l n="5">5 <hi>Treaſon</hi> was <hi>Privy-counſellour,</hi>
               </l>
               <l n="6">6 <hi>Luſt</hi> was the <hi>Executioner.</hi>
               </l>
               <l n="7">7 Dreadfull they a dreadfull ſight</l>
               <l n="8">8 Wrought, were it god or mortall wight,</l>
               <l n="9">9 That acted it.</l>
            </sp>
            <pb n="9" facs="tcp:115706:17"/>
            <sp>
               <speaker>El.</speaker>
               <l n="1">1 O Day, Curſe of my Kalender!</l>
               <l n="2">2 O night! O Suppers horrid Chear!</l>
               <l n="3">3 Cracking my loaded Heart.</l>
               <l n="4">4 When unworthy Fate did part</l>
               <l n="5">5 By baſe Conſpirators my Father</l>
               <l n="6">6 Who took, who ſtroy'd my life together.</l>
               <l n="7">7 With whom the great God ruling heav'n</l>
               <l n="8">8 In vengeance over weight be ev'n.</l>
               <l n="9">9 Nor may they e're enjoy their ſtate,</l>
               <l n="10">10 Purchas'd at Treaſons rate.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Qui.</speaker>
               <l n="1">1 Huſh, pray not too loud, for know you</l>
               <l n="2">2 What harm ſtorming thus may do you?</l>
               <l n="3">3 Endangering your preſent fortune,</l>
               <l n="4">4 Your own deſtruction you importune;</l>
               <l n="5">5 And much of needleſſe ill will gain</l>
               <l n="6">6 While ſtill you ſtubbornely complain,</l>
               <l n="7">7 To raiſe ſtrife: forbear; 'Tis Art,</l>
               <l n="8">8 Oppoſe not the prevayling part,</l>
               <l n="9">9 But yoke your heart.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>El.</speaker>
               <l n="1">1 I am provok'd: I ſee it, and</l>
               <l n="2">2 My impatience underſtand;</l>
               <l n="3">3 But at this fact to grieve</l>
               <l n="4">4 I'll not ceaſe, till ceaſe to live.</l>
               <l n="5">5 For who would ſpeak well of me, ſhould I?</l>
               <l n="6">6 VVho that or Honour know's or duty?</l>
               <l n="7">7 Comforters leave, leave me alone</l>
               <l n="8">8 For this grief muſt no meaſure own.</l>
               <l n="9">9 Ne're will I from my labours ceaſe,</l>
               <l n="10">10 But ſtill my tears increaſe.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Qui.</speaker>
               <l>'Tis meere good will all that I preſſe,</l>
               <l>Like to ſome tender Mother;</l>
               <l>Breed not griefs one of another.</l>
            </sp>
            <pb n="10" facs="tcp:115706:18"/>
            <sp>
               <speaker>El.</speaker>
               <l>Tell me what bounds my woes confine,</l>
               <l>I'ſt fit the Dead in ſcorn t' enſhrine?</l>
               <l>VVhat man doth nature bring up ſo?</l>
               <l>May I ne're in their favour grow.</l>
               <l>Nor if I match, ſome worthy Lord</l>
               <l>To live <hi>demure</hi> will I afford;</l>
               <l>But my ſad devotions pay</l>
               <l>At my Fathers grave will lay.</l>
               <l>For if the dead and rotten</l>
               <l>Like <hi>earth</hi> and <hi>nought</hi> forgotten</l>
               <l>Muſt lie along,</l>
               <l>And they the wrong</l>
               <l>Not rue, who did the ſame,</l>
               <l>Farewell Vertue, Farewel ſhame,</l>
               <l>And all the gods reputed name.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Qui.</speaker>
               <l>
                  <stage n="f" place="margin">One of the Ladies coming after the reſt.</stage> Brought, Madam,
<stage n="g" place="margin">Both that I may coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſell you not to exaſperate your enemies by the oppo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſition of per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>petuall com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plaints, and that I may approve my ſelf a faith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full friend in coming in to your comfort</stage> both for yours and my own ſake</l>
               <l>Hither Im'e with all this eare betake:</l>
               <l>And if I prove other then right to ſay</l>
               <l>VVe ſtraight ſubmit our wills, yours be the day.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>El.</speaker>
               <lg>
                  <l>Lady's, I am aſham'd in your eſteem</l>
                  <l>That I though ne're ſo ſad, too penſive ſeem.</l>
                  <l>But to this life I am perforce enclin'd:</l>
                  <l>Pardon, how can a Maid of generous mind,</l>
                  <l>Seeing her Fathers wrongs do otherwiſe</l>
                  <l>Then I, who moan abed, moan when I riſe?</l>
                  <l>Nor waynes my grief, but ſtill encreaſes more.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>For firſt 'tis my own mother who me bore</l>
                  <l>Hates me, then they who made away my Father</l>
                  <l>VVith me in mine own Palace, live together.</l>
                  <l>They are my <hi>Governours,</hi> and they me <hi>feed,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>From whom then be ſupply'd, I'd rather <hi>need.</hi>
                  </l>
                  <pb n="11" facs="tcp:115706:18"/>
                  <l>Beſides, what life I lead pray do you count,</l>
                  <l>VVhen I ſee haughty <hi>Egiſt</hi> perching mount</l>
                  <l>My Fathers Throne, the ſelf ſame robes behold</l>
                  <l>Him wear, my ſlaughter'd Father wore of old.</l>
                  <l>And in thoſe very rooms where he his Hands</l>
                  <l>Embrew'd, attone the houſhold Guardians.</l>
                  <l>And that which gives my utmoſt wo full ſtature,</l>
                  <l>My Fathers ſheets are made to hold the Traytor</l>
                  <l>VVith my lewd mother, if't be fit at all</l>
                  <l>That I his <hi>bedfellow</hi> ſhould <hi>Mother</hi> call;</l>
                  <l>And ſhe thus baſe lodg'd by the murderer,</l>
                  <l>Of haunting ghoſts ner'e ſtands one whit in fear,</l>
                  <l>But as ſhe at the fact made merry, when</l>
                  <l>She finds the day is come about agen,</l>
                  <l>In which by guile ſhe made our Sire away,</l>
                  <l>Then ſhe doth mask it, then moneth offerings ſlay</l>
                  <l>To ſaviour-gods, on her <hi>thanksgiving day:</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>Mean while, poore I, 'bout houſe looking thereon</l>
                  <l>Cry, fret, and make a lamentable moan,</l>
                  <l>My Fathers diſmall feaſt to think upon,</l>
                  <l>All by my ſelf alone; nor can I ſtil</l>
                  <l>Continuall weeper, ever weep my fill.</l>
                  <l>Then the well-ſpoken gentle-woman for'c,</l>
                  <l>VVith ſuch like curbing girds takes me up ſhort;</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Hate of the gods, to you, forſooth, alone</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Your Father's dead, none elſe makes any moan;</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>An ill end ſeize on thee, and this doom purſue,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Hell after death thy leaſe of grief renue.</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>Thus taunts ſhee. But when any meſſage brings</l>
                  <l>How that <hi>Oreſtes</hi> comes: then out ſhe flings</l>
                  <l>Like a rude Bedlam, and with rampant voice,</l>
                  <l>Cryes, <hi>This your doings is, all this you cauſe</hi>
                  </l>
                  <pb n="12" facs="tcp:115706:19"/>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Which out of my arms reach</hi> Oreſtes <hi>get:</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>But know that thou ſhalt dearly pay the ſhot.</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>Thus ſnaps ſhe, and her fine companion</l>
                  <l>Standing cloſe by her elbow, eggs her on:</l>
                  <l>That ſneaks in grain, that piece made up of ſcorn,</l>
                  <l>That Champion to Lady-duells born.</l>
                  <l>But I <hi>Oreſtes</hi> ſtill expecting, who</l>
                  <l>Should ſet me free, mean while decay with wo.</l>
                  <l>For while he ſtands contriving, he deſtroyes</l>
                  <l>At once my preſent <hi>hopes,</hi> and future <hi>joyes:</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>Nor can I whilſt things ſtand this wiſe with me,</l>
                  <l>Lady's or <hi>patient</hi> or <hi>religious</hi> be:</l>
                  <l>For <hi>deep afflicting evils burden forces</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>The beſt that are to fall on evil courſes.</hi>
                  </l>
               </lg>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Quir.</speaker>
               <l>Tel's one thing, Madam, is <hi>Egiſt</hi> abroad,</l>
               <l>Or here, while you your paſſion thus unload?</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>El.</speaker>
               <l>Abroad you may be ſure: were he in town,</l>
               <l>I durſt not peep: he's now to th' countrey gone.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Quir.</speaker>
               <l>Nay, if 't be ſo I dare ſomewhat more free</l>
               <l>Own your acceſſe, and talk more ventrouſly.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>El.</speaker>
               <p>He is from home, your mind you need not ſmother.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Qu.</speaker>
               <l>Then <hi>I</hi>'le adventure: VVhat news from your Brother?</l>
               <l>Comes he, or ſtay's he? pray for certain tell's.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>El.</speaker>
               <p>He promiſes to come, but nothing elſe.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Qu.</speaker>
               <p>Men on great enterprizes move but ſlow.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>El.</speaker>
               <p>I'me ſure in ſaving him I did not ſo.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Qu.</speaker>
               <p>Fear not, he's one will ne're deſert his friend</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>El.</speaker>
               <p>No: if I ſhould my life were at an end.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Qu.</speaker>
               <l>Not a word more; I eſpie <hi>Chryſotheame,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>Your ſiſter of one ſire and mothers ſtemme,</l>
               <pb n="13" facs="tcp:115706:19"/>
               <l>Come out of doors; with gifts in hands whoſe rites</l>
               <l>Are proper to appeaſe deceaſed ſprights.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Chr.</speaker>
               <l>VVhat a complaining, ſiſter, at the gate</l>
               <l>Do you make, after your accuſtom'd rate?</l>
               <l>VVill you ne're be adviſed to refrain</l>
               <l>From idle paſſion, but ſtill give it rein?</l>
               <l>VVhy now thus much I by mine own ſelf know</l>
               <l>I vex at heart things ſhould be carri'd ſo:</l>
               <l>And were but my good wil with ſtrength protected</l>
               <l>They ſoon ſhould know w<hi rend="sup">ch</hi> way I ſtand affected:</l>
               <l>But in a ſtorm I ſafely ſtrike my ſayles,</l>
               <l>Nor ſeem to act, when action nought avayles.</l>
               <l>Il'd have you too, Dear Siſter, tread this way:</l>
               <l>'Tis true, that Juſtice is not what I ſay,</l>
               <l>But what you do; yet if my Liberty</l>
               <l>I'll have, I muſt with thoſe in power comply.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>El.</speaker>
               <l>Sad caſe that you his child whom you pretend</l>
               <l>Slighting your Sire, ſhould to your Mother bend.</l>
               <l>For all thoſe wholſome counſels you preferre</l>
               <l>Are none of them your own, but taught by her;</l>
               <l>Wherefore chuſe one o'th two; or mad be ſtil'd,</l>
               <l>Or in your wits but an unnaturall child.</l>
               <l>For you that fitly ſay, wer't in place where</l>
               <l>Your deteſtation of them you'ld declare.</l>
               <l>Yet when I ſeek to right my Fathers ſhade</l>
               <l>Help'ſt nothing, nay do'ſt me that would diſſwade:</l>
               <l>Do's not this Cowardiſe to ſorrow adde?</l>
               <l>Wherefore or teach me, or elſe from me learn,</l>
               <l>Could I leave off my moan what ſhould I earn?</l>
               <l>I live now, <hi>poor</hi> you'll ſay; Well, <hi>yet content:</hi>
               </l>
               <l>And while I vex their hearts, at leaſt this rent</l>
               <l>(If ought the Dead can pleaſe) the dead preſent.</l>
               <pb n="14" facs="tcp:115706:20"/>
               <l>But you that hate them, hate them <hi>ſore</hi> in word,</l>
               <l>Yet to converſe with them you can afford</l>
               <l>That murde'rd your dear Sire: Il'd ne're abide it</l>
               <l>Though hir'd with all the knacks in which you pride it;</l>
               <l>To crouch to their commands. <hi>Enjoy you ſtill</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>A table richly furniſh'd, wealth your fill:</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Give me but food which nature doth require,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>And to your Gallantry I'll ne're aspire.</hi>
               </l>
               <l>Nor would you were you but your ſelf, for when</l>
               <l>You might be call'd, <hi>Daughter to'th beſt of men,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>Your Mothers be, ſo ſhall't be to you laid</l>
               <l>You your dead Father and your Friends <hi>betray'd.</hi>
               </l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Qui.</speaker>
               <l>Nothing in anger for all loves: 'Tis right</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Each</hi> of you ſay's, and <hi>each</hi> may profit by't.</l>
               <l>Would you endure but to be rul'd by her,</l>
               <l>And ſhe but learn to be your follower.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Chry.</speaker>
               <l>I am Dear Lady's in a manner uſ'd</l>
               <l>To theſe term's from her, and had now refuſ'd</l>
               <l>To ſpeak, but that a buſineſſe I diſcover,</l>
               <l>Will make her all her wayling ſoon give over.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>El.</speaker>
               <l>Tells that great buſineſſe, come; and if 't outvy</l>
               <l>My grief, I'll forthwith with your will comply.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Chry.</speaker>
               <l>Well I'll acquaint you then with what I can:</l>
               <l>They mean 'leſſe you your puling leave, anon</l>
               <l>To turn you thither where no <hi>curteous</hi> Sun</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Beſtow's</hi> a <hi>Viſit</hi> on the Dungeon.</l>
               <l>Where in griefs loneſome <hi>Peſt-houſe</hi> ſhut up cloſe</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Farre from</hi> this <hi>Land</hi> you may tune out your woes.</l>
               <pb n="15" facs="tcp:115706:20"/>
               <l>Wherefore <hi>conform,</hi> for now 'tis time to do it,</l>
               <l>And blame me not too late, if you ſhall rue it.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>El.</speaker>
               <p>But are you ſure 'gainſt me this is their doom?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Ch.</speaker>
               <p>Moſt ſure I am when <hi>Egiſt</hi> back ſhal come.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>El.</speaker>
               <p>Now therefore would for me he'ld come a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>way!</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>El.</speaker>
               <p>O wretch, what wicked thing is 't you did pray?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>El,</speaker>
               <p>That he would come, if it be thus decreed.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Ch.</speaker>
               <p>To do you miſchief? Are you mad indeed?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>El.</speaker>
               <p>To rid me from among you all far hence.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Ch.</speaker>
               <p>What, of your preſent life have you no ſenſe?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>El.</speaker>
               <p>O mine a heavenly life, moſt wondrous ſweet!</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Ch.</speaker>
               <p>At leaſt, it might be, if you 'ld be <hi>diſcreet</hi>
               </p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>El.</speaker>
               <p>Teach me not my deceas'd friend to forget.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Ch.</speaker>
               <p>I teach you not, but <hi>to power to ſubmit.</hi>
               </p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>El.</speaker>
               <p>
                  <hi>You flatter,</hi> with my Nature it ne're ſtood.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Ch.</speaker>
               <p>Yet to fall through <hi>raſhneſſe</hi> 't is not good.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>El.</speaker>
               <p>Wee'll fall, if need, t' avenge our Fathers <hi>blood.</hi>
               </p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Ch.</speaker>
               <p>Our Father, he I know with this <hi>diſpenſes.</hi>
               </p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>El.</speaker>
               <p>Such words are ſlothfull <hi>Cowards</hi> baſe <hi>pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tences.</hi>
               </p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Ch.</speaker>
               <p>You'l not be rul'd then, nor with me agree?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>El.</speaker>
               <p>No truly, ne're may I ſo ſenſeleſſe be.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Ch.</speaker>
               <p>I'me haſting thither where my errand lyes.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>El.</speaker>
               <p>Whither away? whoſe is this ſacrifice?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Ch.</speaker>
               <p>My Fathers, whom my Mother ſends this gift,</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>El.</speaker>
               <p>What him the odiouſeſt that ever liv'd?</p>
            </sp>
            <pb n="16" facs="tcp:115706:21"/>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Ch.</speaker>
               <p>Him that ſhe kill'd, your meaning's that I know.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>El,</speaker>
               <p>What friend advis'd her? who would coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſel ſo?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Ch.</speaker>
               <p>'T was ſome night-apparition as I caſt.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>El.</speaker>
               <p>Now Fathers holy Angels help at laſt!</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Ch.</speaker>
               <p>Have y' any ground of hopes rais'd from this fright?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>El.</speaker>
               <p>I'll tell you if you'l tell's what was the ſight.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Ch.</speaker>
               <p>I know it not: onely one little glance.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>El.</speaker>
               <l>That little tell's, <hi>A word ofttimes may chance</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>To cast the high down, and the low advance.</hi>
               </l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Ch.</speaker>
               <l>There is a ſpeech, that <hi>with a ſecond greet,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Your and my Father was ſeen her to meet</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Riſen to light: his Royall Staff then rear's,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>And plants, which late himſelf now <hi>Egiſt</hi> bear's,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>From whoſe Crown ſhot forth ſuch a verdant Bough,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>All</hi> Mycens <hi>roosted in its ſhady Brow.</hi>
               </l>
               <l>Thus much I heard one telling, who was there</l>
               <l>When ſhe did to the Sun her dream declare:</l>
               <l>Farther then this I know not, but that ſhe</l>
               <l>Upon that fright this Meſſage ſendeth me.</l>
               <l>Wherefore I by thy Fathers gods thee pray,</l>
               <l>Be rul'd by me, nor caſt thy ſelf away.</l>
               <l>But thou 'rt ſtill loſt, if thou ſhalt diſobey.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>El.</speaker>
               <l>Hold Siſter: none of thoſe things in your hands</l>
               <l>Muſt <hi>touch</hi> the Tombe, Juſtice it ſelf withſtands,</l>
               <l>And Piety; you ſhould our Father carry</l>
               <pb n="17" facs="tcp:115706:21"/>
               <l>Cleanſings and offerings from his Adverſary.</l>
               <l>Wherefore i'th winds or ſome <hi>deep-mined</hi> cave</l>
               <l>Hide 'em where they may ne're <hi>admiſſion</hi> have,</l>
               <l>Into the <hi>preſence-chamber</hi> of his grave.</l>
               <l>But let 'em there be ſav'd a <hi>goodly</hi> prize,</l>
               <l>For her own <hi>precious</hi> ſelf againſt ſhe dies.</l>
               <l>For were ſhe not, the moſt ungodly ſhe</l>
               <l>E're breath'd, theſe hoſtile off'rings could not be</l>
               <l>From her the <hi>Murdereſſe</hi> to him that <hi>fell:</hi>
               </l>
               <l>Now judge your ſelf, how can the enter'd take wel</l>
               <l>Theſe honours at thoſe hands by which he di'd</l>
               <l>In <hi>vile</hi> diſgrace, like a plain foe defi'd:</l>
               <l>Which
<note n="10" place="margin">It was a ſuperſtiti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons humour of the An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cients, after they had committed any murder, to cut the ſinews a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bout the arm-pits of the corſe, fondly (as far as I can reach) ſuppoſing that they did thereby en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feable the arms of the injured ſpright, and diſable it from purſuing them with its crooked taſons, or returning any due ſatisfaction: yet the ordinary ſewer of interpretations runs into this ſenſe, that they were wont to cut off the tipps of the body, as the ears, and noſe, and the like, and ſtring them, and ſo wear them for an amulet caſt about their neck, &amp; brought about to their armholes.</note> 
                  <hi>arm-string'd</hi> him, and to ſcoure off the gore,</l>
               <l>In cleanſing
<note n="11" place="margin">Another wiſe ceremony after murder, to ſcoure the bloud of the decea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed, upon this deſigne, that thereby they might wipe off all anger.</note> 
                  <hi>rinc'd</hi> the <hi>lopt</hi> head o're and o're.</l>
               <l>Are not theſe rather expiations ſpent,</l>
               <l>To <hi>compound</hi> for the murders puniſhment?</l>
               <l>It muſt not be; wherefore go ſet 'em down,</l>
               <l>And
<note n="12" place="margin">The cuſtome of offering locks of hair at the tombe of deceaſed friends, is ancient and frequent: Foc a plain probable reaſon of it, (if any reaſon can be given of the encroachmentts of ſuperſtition, or any eye ſo vigilant to ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerve them) I ſhould ſuppoſe that as the Heathens were wont to exalt their paſsions into Deities; ſo thoſe actions which are the effects of theſe perturbati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons might in proceſſe of time paſſe into forms of worſhip Tearing the hair is a'genuine iſſue of a ſqualid and diſcheveld'd ſorrow upon the loſſe of ſome inward friend. This might have ſet the copy to thoſe funerall raſures and baldneſſes for the dead, prohibited <hi>Lev.</hi> xix. 27, 28. xxi. 5. <hi>Deut.</hi> xii. 1.</note> crop a lock or two from your own crown,</l>
               <pb n="18" facs="tcp:115706:22"/>
               <l>And from unhappy mine. Alas! poore <hi>ſhifts,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>Yet my <hi>ſmall ſtock</hi> affords no better gifts.</l>
               <l>Preſent him with this Hair uncomb'd
<note n="13" place="margin">The Greek is <hi>unnnointed,</hi> for in our countreys the <hi>Puff</hi> is more known then the <hi>Box</hi> of <hi>oynt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment,</hi> nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther do I think any want of proportion betwixt <hi>Anoint thy head,</hi> and <hi>Pouder thy hair.</hi>
                  </note> 
                  <hi>unpouderd,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>Preſent him with this Girdle unimbroyder'd;</l>
               <l>And falling on your knees, beg that <hi>he would</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Be our Aſsiſtant, to revenge his bloud,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>And that his child</hi> Oreſtes <hi>come home ſafe,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Or's enemies the upper hand may have;</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>That ſo with richer hands for time to come</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Then now we're able, we may crown his Tombe.</hi>
               </l>
               <l>I know, I know he thinks on our conditions,</l>
               <l>That thus he ſends her theſe ill boding viſions.</l>
               <l>Wherefore, ſweet ſiſter, underhand beſtow</l>
               <l>Upon <hi>your ſelf</hi> and <hi>me</hi> this favour too,</l>
               <l>And <hi>him</hi> who both of us our being gave,</l>
               <l>Deareſt of ſouls, though now laid in the grave.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Qu.</speaker>
               <l>'T is all religion that ſhe ſay's, and you,</l>
               <l>Lady, if wiſe, will as ſhe bids you do.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Ch.</speaker>
               <l>I will: For <hi>naked truth needs no diſpute</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>To quarrell for 't, but readineſſe to do 't.</hi>
               </l>
               <l>But while I this exploit aſſay, be ſure</l>
               <l>You keep my counſel, friends, I you conjure:</l>
               <l>For if it chance to reach my mothers ear,</l>
               <l>I ſhall attempt a work will coſt me dear.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Qu.</speaker>
               <l n="1">1 Unleſſe I be much deceived,</l>
               <l n="2">2 And of reaſon quite bereaved,</l>
               <l n="3">3 Before is come the Harbinger,</l>
               <l n="4">4 <hi>Juſtice</hi> ſelf at hand is near,</l>
               <l n="5">5 And will ſhew her dreadfull pow'rs</l>
               <l n="6">6 E're time ſpin out many houres;</l>
               <l n="7">7 Some hope there ſeems</l>
               <l n="8">8 When I hear theſe pleaſant dreams.</l>
               <pb n="19" facs="tcp:115706:22"/>
               <l n="9">9 Nor will <hi>Greeces</hi> nat'rall Father</l>
               <l n="10">10 Ever be forgetfull,
<note n="14" place="margin">The Greek Scho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liaſt confeſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feth this place to contain a hard expreſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion, that the very inſtrument ſhould not be unmindfull of that act. But he reſolvsit into this meaning, that the very Ax ows Traytours a grudge.</note> neither</l>
               <l n="11">11 Th' ancient <hi>Poll-ax Raſor-edg'd</hi>
               </l>
               <l n="12">12 <hi>With ſteel</hi>
                  <note n="15" place="margin">
                     <p>Anſwerable to this is the <hi>Latine</hi> name <hi>bipennis,</hi> however <hi>Quintilian</hi> deviſes ſome other fetch. <hi>Simmias</hi> the <hi>Rhodian</hi> hath deſcribed the figure of that Ax, wherewith <hi>Epêus</hi> built the <hi>Trojan</hi> horſe. The generation of an Hat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chet, is by the concourſe of two circles, contingent in the centre uf a third oequall circle: as in this figure is plain to the eye.</p>
                     <figure>
                        <figDesc>diagram of circle and hatchet</figDesc>
                     </figure>
                     <p>Take a plate of iron infinite, and deſcribe in it a circle at adventures, which let A B C be from any point at any diſtance: Let the Diameter be drawn, whoſe extreams let A B be, the Centre D. At the point A, and diſtance A D, pare off F D E: Again, at the point B, and diſtance B D, pare off G D H, ſuperfluous cantles of iron, the reſidue preſents you the figure of the double headed Battel-ax. The Helve muſt be drawn thorough the de of the centre D, and proportion'd to the circle A B C.</p>
                  </note> 
                  <hi>wing on both ſides fledg'd,</hi>
               </l>
               <l n="13">13 Which with <hi>opprobrious</hi> ſtroke,</l>
               <l n="14">14 Off <hi>its Sovereigne took.</hi>
               </l>
               <pb n="20" facs="tcp:115706:23"/>
               <l n="1">1 And Ir'n hoofd <hi>Erinnys</hi> couching</l>
               <l n="2">2 In dread Ambuſh is approching,</l>
               <l n="3">3 With many a foot, and many a hand,</l>
               <l n="4">4 For without or Law or Band</l>
               <l n="5">5 In the twice polluted ſheets,</l>
               <l n="6">6 Lawleſſe ſhe loves combate meets:</l>
               <l n="7">7 Wherefore I gueſſe</l>
               <l n="8">8 This dream will, will find ſucceſſe;</l>
               <l n="9">9 Both on the Actors and Conſenters;</l>
               <l n="10">10 <hi>Elſe all dreams come at adventures,</hi>
               </l>
               <l n="11">11 <hi>And no meahing carrie, though</hi>
               </l>
               <l n="12">12 <hi>Full of terrour they may ſhow;</hi>
               </l>
               <l n="13">13 <hi>And Oracles are tales,</hi>
               </l>
               <l n="14">14 <hi>If this viſion fails.</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <note n="16" place="margin">
                     <hi>Pelops</hi> won his La<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>die at the match with her father <hi>Oenomaus</hi> by the deceit of <hi>Myrtill</hi> his chariot<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er: For the Father un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtanding from the O<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>racle, that his ſonne in Law ſhould ſlay him, propoſed, not to let any one wed her, unleſſe he over<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come his fleet chariot-horſes. <hi>Pelops</hi> arriving at <hi>Piſa,</hi> brib's <hi>Myrtill</hi> to leave out the Axle-pin: So in the way the chariot overthrew, <hi>Oenomaus</hi> fell, and committing the revenge of his treacherous man to his ſonne, expired. <hi>Pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lops</hi> having wonne <hi>Hippodamia,</hi> in lieu of reward, caſts the perfidious <hi>Myr<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>till</hi> into the <hi>Myrtean</hi> (as the <hi>Greeks</hi> feign, deriving from him that name.</note> O <hi>Pelops!</hi> in ill weather</l>
               <l>Thy Coach came hither;</l>
               <l>Thou drov'ſt with an ill hand</l>
               <l>To this ſame land:</l>
               <l>For ſince <hi>Myrtill</hi> was laid aſleep,</l>
               <l>Thrown in the deep,</l>
               <l>With cruel baſe reproch</l>
               <l>Or'ethrown with's Coach</l>
               <l>Emboſs'd with beaten gold,</l>
               <l>Wo within wo enroll'd,</l>
               <l>Hath dogg'd cloſe</l>
               <l>This ſad Houſe.</l>
            </sp>
            <pb n="21" facs="tcp:115706:23"/>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Clyt.</speaker>
               <l>You now it ſeems are gadding forth agen,</l>
               <l>Now <hi>Egist</hi> is from home, who kept you in,</l>
               <l>Leſt you abroad your friends ſhould load with lies.</l>
               <l>But now he's out o'th way, you me deſpiſe.</l>
               <l>And many folks you many tales have told,</l>
               <l>How I, harſh and outragious cruel, hold</l>
               <l>You and yours under, doing you great wrong:</l>
               <l>No wrong; I give bad words to a bad tongue.</l>
               <l>Now for your Father (that's all you pretend</l>
               <l>Alwayes) how he by me came to his end.</l>
               <l>By me? I know it well, and will it own,</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>But Juſtice took him off, not I alone;</hi>
               </l>
               <l>To whom, if wiſe, your helping hand y' had lent:</l>
               <l>For this your Father whom you ſtill lament,</l>
               <l>Onely of all the <hi>Grecians</hi> muſt proffer</l>
               <l>Your ſiſter to the angry gods to offer,</l>
               <l>Having in the begetting her not known</l>
               <l>My pangs in a hard labour undergone.</l>
               <l>Come on now, ſatisfie me for whoſe ſake</l>
               <l>Offer'd he her. The <hi>Greeks,</hi> you I anſwer make.</l>
               <l>Now, what had they to do my child to kill?</l>
               <l>Or to comply with <hi>Menelaus</hi> will?</l>
               <l>Should he ſlay mine, and look I ſhould ſit ſtill?</l>
               <l>
                  <note n="17" place="margin">
                     <hi>Hermi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>one</hi> and <hi>Ni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>coſtratus</hi> children of <hi>Menclaus</hi> by <hi>Helena.</hi>
                  </note> And had not th' other two, more fitting far</l>
               <l>Both of them, to be ſacrific'd then her?</l>
               <l>Of father born and mother, for whoſe ſake</l>
               <l>They did the expedition undertake:</l>
               <l>Or did Death long, and had an eager mind,</l>
               <l>On mine to <hi>banquet,</hi> and leave hers behind?</l>
               <l>Or did not your baſe father rather this,</l>
               <l>Hate her by me, and <hi>Menelaus</hi> lov'd his?</l>
               <l>Do's not this Sire the <hi>fool</hi> and <hi>vile</hi> bewray?</l>
               <pb n="22" facs="tcp:115706:24"/>
               <l>I think he doth, however you ſay, Nay.</l>
               <l>And the dead, could ſhe ſpeak ſhe would conſent:</l>
               <l>I therefore at what's done do not repent:</l>
               <l>And if I ſeem to you to think amiſſe,</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Do well</hi> to load your friends with calumny's.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>El.</speaker>
               <l>You'l not ſay now that I firſt went about,</l>
               <l>To move your <hi>heat,</hi> and <hi>drew</hi> this paſſion out:</l>
               <l>But if you'l give me leave, I'le tell you true</l>
               <l>Of my dead Father, and my ſiſter too.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Cly.</speaker>
               <l>I give you leave. This <hi>modest</hi> dialect</l>
               <l>Still us'd, our <hi>ready</hi> audience might expect.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>El.</speaker>
               <l>I tell you then. Your felf profeſſe you ſpilt</l>
               <l>My Fathers bloud. A word of blackeſt guilt,</l>
               <l>Were it by right or not, yet I'le aſſert</l>
               <l>It was not Right, but Love did you pervert</l>
               <l>To that lewd Paramour, with whom y'are nought.</l>
               <l>Now ask the Huntreſſe <hi>Dian,</hi> for whoſe fault</l>
               <l>She in calm <hi>Aulis</hi> ſtaid the <hi>wind-bound</hi> Fleet.</l>
               <l>Or I'le reply: for her we cannot meet.</l>
               <l>My Father once (as I have heard it talk'd)</l>
               <l>Sporting i'th holy Grove, rous'd as he walk'd</l>
               <l>A ſpotted, well-brancht Stag, which having kil'd,</l>
               <l>And boaſting of't by chance, ſome words he ſpild,</l>
               <l>At which <hi>Latona's</hi> daughter took offence,</l>
               <l>And ſtop'd the <hi>Greeks,</hi> nor let them ſtir from thence,</l>
               <l>Till he his Child gave her Beaſts recompence.</l>
               <l>Thus ſhe was given, nor could the Army come,</l>
               <l>On other terms back, or to <hi>Ilium:</hi>
               </l>
               <l>So that unwilling, when he could no other,</l>
               <l>He offered her, and not to pleaſe his brother.</l>
               <l>But grant it were (as you auerre) to further</l>
               <pb n="23" facs="tcp:115706:24"/>
               <l>His brother, muſt he therefore merit murder</l>
               <l>At your hands to be executed? By what order?</l>
               <l>Take heed leſt while you make a new-found Law</l>
               <l>You on your felf <hi>wo</hi> and <hi>repentance</hi> draw:</l>
               <l>For if bloud muſt with bloud <hi>aſſoyled</hi> be,</l>
               <l>Vou muſt die firſt to <hi>ſeal</hi> your own decree.</l>
               <l>But ſee if you <hi>coyn</hi> not a vain excuſe,</l>
               <l>For if you pleaſe, reſolve me why you chuſe</l>
               <l>Your life in fowl debauchments to abuſe,</l>
               <l>Which with that Murd'rer lie, with whom together</l>
               <l>Plotting before, you made away my Father,</l>
               <l>And <hi>gendrest</hi> with him, but us out doſt throw,</l>
               <l>The <hi>honest</hi> iſſue of a <hi>pious</hi> vow.</l>
               <l>Can I commend you here? is't your pretence,</l>
               <l>This too is for your child to make amends?</l>
               <l>Fowl anſwer if it be. No law allows</l>
               <l>You ſhould t' avenge a child, a foe eſpouſe:</l>
               <l>Nor may we our <hi>advice</hi> preſent, but ſtill</l>
               <l>Incens'd you cry, our Mother we revile.</l>
               <l>But I in your deportment to us find,</l>
               <l>More of the Miſtris <hi>harſh,</hi> then Mother <hi>kind:</hi>
               </l>
               <l>Which lead ſad dayes, and old acquaintance date</l>
               <l>With woes by you occaſion'd, and your Mate.</l>
               <l>But poor <hi>Oreſtes</hi> now in forreign lands,</l>
               <l>That life with which he hardly ſcap't your hands,</l>
               <l>Clo'yd with diſtreſſe, conſumes; who<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> you complain</l>
               <l>I for your executioner maintain.</l>
               <l>Which, were I able, be aſſur'd I wou'd:</l>
               <l>And therefore give it out, if you think good,</l>
               <l>That I'me ill natur'd, or unbridled ſcold,</l>
               <l>Or to the depth of impudence am bold:</l>
               <l>For if theſe vertuous qualities I ſhew,</l>
               <pb n="24" facs="tcp:115706:25"/>
               <l>I do not much degenerate from you.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Qui.</speaker>
               <l>I ſee her mov'd but whether juſtly ſo</l>
               <l>'Tis not within my Judgements <hi>Verge</hi> to know.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Clyt.</speaker>
               <l>What Courſe now can I take with her that thus</l>
               <l>Is not aſham'd her Mother to abuſe?</l>
               <l>
                  <note n="18" place="margin">
                     <hi>Electra</hi> was proba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bly 28. or 30. yeers old as may be gather d from the of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fices of re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcuing and ſaving her Brother mentioned in her la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mentation over the Urne that followes.</note> And that at theſe years too? ſeem's ſhe not bent,</l>
               <l>For all <hi>bold</hi> miſchiefs a <hi>fit</hi> inſtrument?</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>El.</speaker>
               <l>Aſſure your ſelf I feel an inward ſhame,</l>
               <l>How e're you think: I am advis'd, and blame</l>
               <l>My Carriage fit nor for the time, nor me.</l>
               <l>But your curſt uſage and your deeds they be</l>
               <l>Malgre my ſelf me to this paſſe have wrought</l>
               <l>For by lewd company, lewd tricks are taught.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Clyt.</speaker>
               <l>O ye Bold Beaſt, do I or words of mine</l>
               <l>Or my deeds you to talk at large encline?</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>El.</speaker>
               <l>'Tis you talk ſo not I: you do the deed,</l>
               <l>And Deeds by words are but interpreted.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Clyt.</speaker>
               <l>Now by our Lady <hi>Dian,</hi> you ſhall mourn</l>
               <l>For your bold Tongue when <hi>Egiſt</hi> do's return.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>El.</speaker>
               <l>See you're enrag'd for all I had your leave</l>
               <l>To ſpeak my Mind, nor will attention give.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Clyt.</speaker>
               <l>I ſhall not offer then for you in Peace,</l>
               <l>Since I conſented to your tongues <hi>releaſe.</hi>
               </l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>El.</speaker>
               <l>You may, you ſhall; Offer, nor blame my Noyſe,</l>
               <l>For hear I'll put a period to my Voice.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Clyt.</speaker>
               <l>You that attend take the fruit offerings thence,</l>
               <l>That I to th' King may make my Orizens,</l>
               <l>To eaſe my ſoul, my ſoul of it's oppreſſing fear</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Phoebus</hi> great Preſident of <hi>Mycens</hi> hear.</l>
               <pb n="25" facs="tcp:115706:25"/>
               <l>Me ſoftly pray, for enemy's ſtand by,</l>
               <l>Nor may I ſpeak all out while ſhe is nigh.</l>
               <l>Leſt ſhe with clamours loud and Mind perverſe</l>
               <l>An idle tale through all the town diſperſe,</l>
               <l>Thus hear thou: thus my praiers conceald prevent:</l>
               <l>The apparitions laſt night did preſent</l>
               <l>In both my dreams, <hi>Lycean</hi> King, for theſe</l>
               <l>If they be lucky, crown them with ſucceſſe</l>
               <l>On me; if Hoſtile, on my Enemy's:</l>
               <l>Nor if ſome <hi>ill-affected</hi> ſhall contrive</l>
               <l>My ruine from this hight, do thou connive:</l>
               <l>But in ſafe <hi>Channell</hi> glide my peacefull dayes</l>
               <l>Holding the royall Halls and royall Mace.</l>
               <l>And with the friends I have may I ſtill reſt,</l>
               <l>Bathing in eaſe, with my dear pledges bleſt.</l>
               <l>(Bate thoſe <hi>Maligne</hi> my peace, and ſweets infeſt)</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Lycean Phoebus</hi> to theſe prayers lend</l>
               <l>An open ear, and a propitious End;</l>
               <l>And all things elſe, though not expreſs'd by me,</l>
               <l>Which unto you a god muſt naked be,</l>
               <l>For fit it is <hi>Joves</hi> ſeed ſhould all things ſee.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Tut.</speaker>
               <l>Who can enform one, Lady's, I intreat</l>
               <l>If this be Royall <hi>Egiſts</hi> Princely ſeat.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Qui.</speaker>
               <p>This gentle ſtranger 'tis: Right is your aim.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Tut.</speaker>
               <l>At this his Conſort aim I too as nigh?</l>
               <l>Her <hi>preſence</hi> perſonates a <hi>Majeſtie.</hi>
               </l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Qui.</speaker>
               <p>Reſolve you this great Lady is the ſame.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Tut.</speaker>
               <l>Hail gratious Queen, ſweet tidings I commend</l>
               <l>From one to you and <hi>Egiſt</hi> a near Friend.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Clyt.</speaker>
               <l>Succeed the news, but firſt acquaint me this,</l>
               <pb n="26" facs="tcp:115706:26"/>
               <l>What Maſter ſent you with theſe Embaſſy's.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Tut.</speaker>
               <p>
                  <hi>Phanot</hi> the <hi>Phoceſe.</hi> High concernment 'tis.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Clyt.</speaker>
               <l>Friend ſpeak it out, you come from a good King,</l>
               <l>And a good Meſſage without doubt you bring.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Tut.</speaker>
               <p>
                  <hi>Oreſtes</hi> death in one word take it all.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>El.</speaker>
               <p>Wo to me wretch, this day compleats my fall.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Clyt.</speaker>
               <p>What is't? what is't my Friend? her cry's ne're heed.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Tut.</speaker>
               <p>
                  <hi>Oreſtes,</hi> then and now I ſay, is dead.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>El.</speaker>
               <p>Loſt and forlorn I am: I am no more.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Clyt.</speaker>
               <l>Get you about your buſineſſe, but kind friend</l>
               <l>Tell me the certain <hi>manner</hi> of his end.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Tut.</speaker>
               <l>I'll tell you all: my Journey was there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore.</l>
               <l>Arriv'd at <hi>Greeces</hi> high renowned Came,</l>
               <l>To enter in the <hi>Delphick</hi> liſts he came:</l>
               <l>Where firſt the cryer with ſhrill voyce proclaim'd</l>
               <l>The race on Foot: This was the foremoſt nam'd,</l>
               <l>He enters brave: th' amazed Cirque look on,</l>
               <l>Nor by his perſon was his power out-done.</l>
               <l>But fleet he ſcoures the lazy road, and meets</l>
               <l>The forward Goal. The Crown his conqueſt greets</l>
               <l>Of many facts, I can relate but few</l>
               <l>Who neither his exploits nor Proweſſe knew,</l>
               <l>Onely take this: When ever race was wag'd,</l>
               <l>Or in the
<note n="19" place="margin">
                     <p>There were 5. more eminent <hi>Greek</hi> exerciſes, which are reckon'd up in the latter verſe of this Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtick in the <hi>Greek</hi> Epigrams by <hi>Simonides.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Iſthmians</hi> and <hi>Pythians Diophon Philo's ſon,</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>At Race, Dart, Quoyt, Jumping and Wreſtling won.</l>
                  </note> five-encounters Men engag'd:</l>
               <pb n="27" facs="tcp:115706:26"/>
               <l>One from the reſt to bear away the Day</l>
               <l>Was ſtill cry'd up: An <hi>Argive</hi> as they ſay,</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Oreſtes</hi> nam'd; great <hi>Agamemnons</hi> ſonne,</l>
               <l>Who levy'd the <hi>Greek</hi> hoſt of late renown,</l>
               <l>Thus farre 'twas ſo; but if God rayſe his arm,</l>
               <l>No ſtrength is Heaven-proof to ſtand the harm.</l>
               <l>For he one day when of ſwift
<note n="20" place="margin">Chario<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tery is one of the antiqua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted Modes of Chivalry. Heretofore as it was us'd in Triumphs ſo in field-ſervice and games. This uſe may well go con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>joyn'd: For ordinarily publike ſports, either by the policy of the Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſters, or the propenſion of mens affe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctions main<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain a reſem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>blance with the Deeds of Arms, of their reſpective Country's. In the field Chariots of Iron ſometimes were uſed, ſo denominated from their hooked Fauchions or Sythes ſpeating out of the Axeltree. Thoſe Ammunition Coaches were ſmall as to hold but two, and light timberd Ours are of a heavie bulk, and alwayes employ'd either for ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſary portation from place to place, or ſtately oftentation in ſolemn proceſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons and Masks.</note> charriot-horſe,</l>
               <l>By early Sunne they made a ſpeedy Courſe</l>
               <l>Ent'red the Stage with many chariotiers,</l>
               <l>An <hi>Achive one:</hi> from <hi>Spartaeone</hi> appears;</l>
               <l>Their harneſt <hi>Barbary's two Lybians</hi> driv'd,</l>
               <l>(And among them he was himſelf) <hi>a fifth,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>Laſht his <hi>Theſſalick</hi> Mares: a <hi>ſixth</hi> one jolts</l>
               <l>His ratling Coach with bay <hi>Etolian</hi> colts.</l>
               <l>The <hi>ſeventh</hi> a <hi>Magneſian:</hi> In th' <hi>eighth</hi> place,</l>
               <l>One with white horſe, an <hi>Enian</hi> by race.</l>
               <l>The <hi>ninth</hi> frow <hi>Athens,</hi> heav'n built was come:</l>
               <l>Laſt, a <hi>Boeotian</hi> coach fill'd the tenth room.</l>
               <l>Standing where by the lot the Maſters find,</l>
               <l>What rank ſhould to each chariot be aſſign'd,</l>
               <l>At brazen Trump they ſtart, each chiding backs</l>
               <l>His ſlothfull Steeds, the waving rein each ſhak's:</l>
               <l>The plains are <hi>deafned</hi> by the ratling wheels,</l>
               <l>And <hi>clouds</hi> of duſt riſe from the horſes heels:</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Pell Mell</hi> they drive: None ſpare for ſting: while each,</l>
               <l>At t' others ſpokes and panting noſtrils reach,</l>
               <pb n="28" facs="tcp:115706:27"/>
               <l>While they put on, the hindmoſt Courſer laves</l>
               <l>That's <hi>Back,</hi> and that the <hi>Rut</hi> with foamy waves,</l>
               <l>But he his outmoſt axle alwayes led,</l>
               <l>Cloſe to the columnes ſide, and giving head</l>
               <l>To the right forehorſe, held his fellow ſtreight:</l>
               <l>Still all the <hi>ſteady</hi> chariots ſtood upright,</l>
               <l>When th' <hi>Enians</hi> hard-mouth'd ſteeds in furious ſort,</l>
               <l>Set on a running, and then turning ſhort,</l>
               <l>After the ſixth and ſeventh <hi>ſtage</hi> complete,</l>
               <l>Their foreheads on che
<note n="21" place="margin">That is, <hi>Lybian.</hi>
                  </note> 
                  <hi>Barcian</hi> Coaches beat,</l>
               <l>And as <hi>miſchances never go alone,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>One by another's broke and overthrown:</l>
               <l>All the <hi>Criſean</hi> heath did cover'd lie.</l>
               <l>With ſhatter'd <hi>limbs</hi> of <hi>ſhip-wrackt</hi> Chivalry.</l>
               <l>This he of <hi>Athens</hi> ſhrowd at's rein eſpies,</l>
               <l>And gently draws aſide, ſo by there flyes</l>
               <l>The harnes'd <hi>Cataract,</hi> tumbling all in heaps.</l>
               <l>He drives i'th rear; but ſtill <hi>Oreſtes</hi> keeps</l>
               <l>His horſes laſt, relying on the end.</l>
               <l>But when he ſees him onely left behind,</l>
               <l>With a <hi>ſhrill</hi> laſh his nimble ſteeds revive,</l>
               <l>Purſuing ſwift, and <hi>pole</hi> by <hi>pole</hi> they drive,</l>
               <l>Poys'd is the game; and if one overlook,</l>
               <l>By t' others foreward head he 's overtook.</l>
               <l>Th' unhappy Prince, theſe <hi>Poſts</hi> unoverthrown,</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>pright</hi> in <hi>upright</hi> chariot ſafe had gone,</l>
               <l>When he his left rein ſlackt, and turning <hi>Pole,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>Fell unawares upon the Column foul;</l>
               <l>The <hi>Nave</hi> aſunder ſplits, and on the Wheels</l>
               <l>He <hi>pitches</hi> down, and drags his <hi>hamperd</hi> heels</l>
               <pb n="29" facs="tcp:115706:27"/>
               <l>I'th following Tire, and as he fell along,</l>
               <l>The <hi>plunging</hi> horſes through the champion flong:</l>
               <l>But when the ring beheld the ſweet youth ſlide</l>
               <l>Down from the box, with a ſhrill ſhriek they cri'd,</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>How brave a Prince how bad a fate doth ſhare!</hi>
               </l>
               <l>Dragg'd on the ground, then toſſing in the aire</l>
               <l>His hurri'd legs, till the kind chariotiers</l>
               <l>With much ado ſtopping their mad carriers,</l>
               <l>Looſen the bloudy corps, ſo torn as none</l>
               <l>Their friends <hi>disfigured</hi> countenance could own.</l>
               <l>Then forth with certain <hi>Phocians</hi> order'd, burn</l>
               <l>His limbs; and in a <hi>little</hi> brazen urn,</l>
               <l>Conduct the <hi>einders</hi> of that <hi>mighty Name,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>That in his <hi>Countrey</hi> he may <hi>buriall claim.</hi>
               </l>
               <l>You have it all. Piteous it is to tell:</l>
               <l>But had you bin, as we, at th' Spectacle,</l>
               <l>In my ſight ne're ſo ſad a thing befell.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Qu.</speaker>
               <l>Wo, wo, our ancient Maſters forward hope</l>
               <l>Wholly, it ſeems, is <hi>Root and Branch stockt up.</hi>
               </l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Clyt.</speaker>
               <l>O <hi>Jove!</hi> what's here! is 't Curſedneſſe or Bliſſe?</l>
               <l>'Tis gain, I grant; yet grievous joy it is,</l>
               <l>If mine own ſorrows muſt my life protect.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Tut.</speaker>
               <p>Why Lady, do's this Meſſage you deject?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Clyt.</speaker>
               <l>
                  <hi>Child-birth is ſharp,</hi> and though he prove ungrate,</l>
               <l>A Mother yet cannot her own <hi>pangs</hi> hate.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Tut.</speaker>
               <p>We on an <hi>idle</hi> errand come, I ſee.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Clyt.</speaker>
               <l>Not <hi>idle</hi> neither, how can't <hi>idle</hi> be,</l>
               <l>That you of his deceaſe ſure ſignes have brought,</l>
               <l>Who when he was of mine own <hi>ſoul</hi> begot,</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Revolting</hi> from my dugs and nurture, run</l>
               <pb n="30" facs="tcp:115706:28"/>
               <l>To forreigne Realms; and ſince he firſt was gone,</l>
               <l>Ne're ſaw me, but his Fathers murder charg'd</l>
               <l>On me, and cruel threatnings hath enlarg'd;</l>
               <l>So that nor day, nor night, my <hi>ſleeps</hi> were <hi>ſweet,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>But the next houre I lookt my death to meet;</l>
               <l>But now this day is my <hi>deliverer</hi>
               </l>
               <l>From all my fears of <hi>him,</hi> my fears of <hi>her.</hi>
               </l>
               <l>'Twas <hi>ſhe,</hi> a worſe and <hi>inmate</hi> grief I hous'd,</l>
               <l>Which <hi>gnaw'd</hi> my bones, and my heart-bloud <hi>carous'd.</hi>
               </l>
               <l>But now, our <hi>quiet</hi> dayes, without <hi>annoy</hi>
               </l>
               <l>Survive, nor ſhall her threats <hi>impeach</hi> our joy.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>El.</speaker>
               <l>Wo's me poor wretch! 't is time thy fall to mourn,</l>
               <l>My dear <hi>Oreſtes,</hi> who art yet a ſcorn</l>
               <l>To thy reviling Mother; well is this?</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Clyt.</speaker>
               <p>No, not with <hi>you;</hi> but well with <hi>him</hi> it is.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>El.</speaker>
               <p>Give eare, O <hi>Juſtice,</hi> and revenge the dead.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Cly.</speaker>
               <p>She <hi>hath</hi> given eare aright, &amp; wel decreed.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>El.</speaker>
               <p>Mock on, for your proſperity now flaunts.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Cly.</speaker>
               <p>You and <hi>Oreſtes</hi> ne're will leave theſe taunts.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>El.</speaker>
               <p>Yes, we have left, but cannot make you leave</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Clyt.</speaker>
               <l>Good ſtranger, mayſt thou all reward re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive,</l>
               <l>That thou haſt freed us from her brawling tone.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Tut.</speaker>
               <p>Well, I am going then, ſince that is done.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Clyt.</speaker>
               <l>By no means, Sir, that thought do's nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther ſuit</l>
               <l>With your great Lords <hi>reſpect,</hi> nor my <hi>repute:</hi>
               </l>
               <l>But enter in, and let her without door,</l>
               <pb n="31" facs="tcp:115706:28"/>
               <l>
                  <hi>Her own</hi> diſtreſſes, and <hi>her friends</hi> deplore
<stage n="g" place="margin">
                     <hi>Clytem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſtra</hi> car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries the <hi>Tu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tour</hi> off the ſtage, to en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tertain him in her Court</stage>
.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>El.</speaker>
               <l>Do not you mark how <hi>paſsionate,</hi> how <hi>wild</hi>
               </l>
               <l>Diſtreſſed Lady ſhe bewayls her child?</l>
               <l>That he <hi>is dead,</hi> and that he <hi>thus</hi> ſhould <hi>die?</hi>
               </l>
               <l>No: ſhe <hi>unnat'rall</hi> laughs. Unhappy I!</l>
               <l>I, who <hi>deare Brother,</hi> periſh in thy fall,</l>
               <l>While thou haſt <hi>bury'd</hi> at thy <hi>Funerall,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>My remnant of <hi>low</hi> hopes to ſee the day,</l>
               <l>When thy juſt hand full vengeance ſhould <hi>diſplay,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>A <hi>Fathers death,</hi> and <hi>Siſters wrongs</hi> to pay.</l>
               <l>Now where ſhall I my dolefull footſteps turn,</l>
               <l>Who am all deſolate, and <hi>twice</hi> forlorn?</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Brotherleſſe Orphan.</hi> Once more to their check</l>
               <l>Whom I moſt hate, I muſt ſubmit my neck,</l>
               <l>My <hi>Fathers Headſmen</hi> ſerve. With me is 't well?</l>
               <l>But 't is reſolv'd, I will no longer dwell</l>
               <l>In theſe curs'd walls,
<stage n="h" place="margin">
                     <hi>Electra</hi> layes her down be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore the gate.</stage> but here before this gate</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Laying</hi> me <hi>down,</hi> will fade diſconſolate,</l>
               <l>And let them, if they take this ill within</l>
               <l>Kill me, my ſlaughter were a <hi>courteous ſinne,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>To <hi>live</hi> is <hi>pain,</hi> the light I hate to <hi>ſpinne.</hi>
               </l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Quir.</speaker>
               <l n="1">1 Where be <hi>Joves</hi> thunders fled,</l>
               <l n="2">2 And <hi>Phoebus</hi> burniſht head,</l>
               <l n="3">3 If this they eye,</l>
               <l n="4">4 Like <hi>ſtanders by?</hi>
               </l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>El.</speaker>
               <l n="5">5 Ah! wo!</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Quir.</speaker>
               <l n="6">6 Lady, why this lament?</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>El.</speaker>
               <l n="7">7 Oh!</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Quir.</speaker>
               <l n="8">8 Be not too vehement.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>El.</speaker>
               <l n="9">9 You kill me.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Qu.</speaker>
               <l n="10">10 How?</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>El.</speaker>
               <l n="11">11 If you with hopes beguil me,</l>
               <pb n="32" facs="tcp:115706:29"/>
               <l n="12">12 Of thoſe whom plain we know,</l>
               <l n="13">13 Fled to deaths region below:</l>
               <l n="14">14 My <hi>dying</hi> light,</l>
               <l n="15">15 You even quench <hi>out-right.</hi>
               </l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Qu.</speaker>
               <l n="1">1 Why th'
<note n="22" place="margin">The <hi>Quire</hi> en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deavours to comfort her by the ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ample of <hi>Amphiarus</hi> who was in like manner betray'd to death by his wife <hi>E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riphyle.</hi> For he being a footh-ſayer fore-knew that if he went to the <hi>Thebane</hi> warre, he ſhould there die, and hid himſelf: But <hi>Adraſtus</hi> enticed his wife with the gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving her a precious chain, to a diſcovery of him: And ſo going againſt <hi>Thebes,</hi> with the other Princes, was ſwallowed up the firſt day, with his coach and foure horſes, by an opening of the earth. Which lewdneſſe of his mother, <hi>Alcmaeon</hi> being brought up to age, expiated, by executing her.</note> 
                  <hi>Argive</hi> Bard I knew,</l>
               <l n="2">2 Whom the gold Bracelet ſlew,</l>
               <l n="3">3 Firſt hid in 's cave.</l>
               <l n="4">4 And now in 's grave.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>El</speaker>
               <l n="5">5 Ah! wo!</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Qu.</speaker>
               <l n="6">6 He's Sovereigne of the dead.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>El.</speaker>
               <l n="7">7 Oh!</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Qu.</speaker>
               <l n="8">8 Oh truly! for tis ſad.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>El.</speaker>
               <l n="9">9 He periſht.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Qu.</speaker>
               <l n="10">10 Yes.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>El.</speaker>
               <l n="11">11 True, true: for a friend cheriſht</l>
               <l n="12">12 His <hi>Orphan</hi> at 's deceaſe;</l>
               <l n="13">13 But none vouchſafes my grief to <hi>eaſe:</hi>
               </l>
               <l n="14">14 And he that wou'd,</l>
               <l n="15">15 Is blaſted in the bud.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Qui.</speaker>
               <l n="1">1 Sad Lady you ſad things indure.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>El.</speaker>
               <l n="2">2 I know't, I know't too ſure:</l>
               <l n="3">3 Sorrow's crowding, overflowing,</l>
               <l n="4">4 Never fading, ever growing.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Qui.</speaker>
               <l n="5">5 We all bear witneſſe to your Cry.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>El.</speaker>
               <l n="6">O <hi>then</hi> look you no more</l>
               <pb n="33" facs="tcp:115706:29"/>
               <l n="7">7 <hi>Entice</hi> me to <hi>give o're.</hi>
               </l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Qui.</speaker>
               <l n="8">8 What ſay you?</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>El.</speaker>
               <l n="8 (cont.)">
                  <note n="23" place="margin">That exploit now comes into her mind, which ſhe afterwards invites her ſiſter too.</note> Yet I ſpy</l>
               <l n="9">9 Helpers beſide,</l>
               <l n="10">10 <hi>Hopes of blood royall near ally'd.</hi>
               </l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Qu.</speaker>
               <l n="1">1 All mortalls death muſt undergo.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>El.</speaker>
               <l n="2">2 In cruel <hi>racing</hi> too?</l>
               <l n="3">3 As, unhappy, he was <hi>mangled,</hi>
               </l>
               <l n="4">4 In the winding <hi>traces</hi> tangled.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Qui.</speaker>
               <l n="5">5 It was an <hi>unſeen</hi> miſery.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>El.</speaker>
               <l n="6">6 Yes, for in <hi>forreigne</hi> land,</l>
               <l n="7">7 Without my carefull hand.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Qu.</speaker>
               <l n="8">8 Alas now!</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>El.</speaker>
               <l n="8 (cont.)">He muſt <hi>lie,</hi>
               </l>
               <l n="9">9 Nor <hi>buried,</hi>
               </l>
               <l n="10">10 Nor with my <hi>tears</hi> upon him <hi>ſhed.</hi>
               </l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Chry.</speaker>
               <l>
                  <hi>Wingd</hi> with delight, and by ſweet plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure <hi>chac't,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>Quitting all <hi>decent gate,</hi> I hither haſt:</l>
               <l>For <hi>joyfull</hi> news I bring, and <hi>ſure</hi> repoſe</l>
               <l>From the long <hi>burden</hi> of your <hi>preſſing</hi> woes.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>El.</speaker>
               <l>Whence can you find a <hi>balſome</hi> for my heart,</l>
               <l>Whoſe wounds are paſt the <hi>ſlender</hi> cure of art?</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Chry.</speaker>
               <l>
                  <hi>Oreſte's</hi> come: take it from me, &amp; know,</l>
               <l>'Tis ſure as that thou <hi>ſtrangely</hi> eye me now.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>El.</speaker>
               <l>Art mad poor wretch: or doſt thou this de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſigne,</l>
               <l>To laugh at <hi>thine own</hi> miſeries and <hi>mine?</hi>
               </l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Chry.</speaker>
               <l>No, houſhold <hi>Veſta</hi> help me, as no jeer</l>
               <l>I mean at all: but he is certain here.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>El.</speaker>
               <l>Ah me unhappy! on what <hi>mortals breath</hi>
               </l>
               <l>Builds thy <hi>aſſurance</hi> it's <hi>unerring faith?</hi>
               </l>
            </sp>
            <pb n="34" facs="tcp:115706:30"/>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Chr.</speaker>
               <l>Mine &amp; none others <hi>eies</hi> my <hi>authors</hi> were,</l>
               <l>Sure ſignes I <hi>ſaw,</hi> and a <hi>true meſſage</hi> bear.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>El.</speaker>
               <l>Poor heart, what ſurety ſaw'ſt thou? from what <hi>aim</hi>
               </l>
               <l>Striv'ſt thou to <hi>fan</hi> my breaſts <hi>expiring</hi> flame?</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Chr.</speaker>
               <l>Now for the gods ſakes heark, and as you find</l>
               <l>Repute me henceforth <hi>ſound</hi> or <hi>weak in mind.</hi>
               </l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>El.</speaker>
               <p>
                  <hi>Tell</hi> on then, if you pleaſure take to <hi>tell.</hi>
               </p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Chr.</speaker>
               <l>I will, and nothing that I know conceal.</l>
               <l>When I approcht my Fathers ancient ſtone,</l>
               <l>Freſh riv'lets of new milk run trickling down</l>
               <l>From th' hillock I deſcry: and a ſweet rownd</l>
               <l>Of ſev'rall flowers my Fathers aſhes crownd.</l>
               <l>Seeing I wonder, and I wondring ſtand</l>
               <l>To ſee <hi>the Authour,</hi> if he were at hand:</l>
               <l>But when I viewd the coaſt on all ſides clear,</l>
               <l>Nearer the tombe I ſtole: whoſe brinks appear</l>
               <l>Strowd all about with locks of new-ſhorn hair:</l>
               <l>Which when, <hi>poore wretch,</hi> I ſaw, my active thought</l>
               <l>A <hi>face</hi> well known unto my <hi>fanſie</hi> brought:</l>
               <l>I ſtraight preſag'd no hand but that alone</l>
               <l>Of dear <hi>Oreſtes</hi> could this office own.</l>
               <l>Taking them up, no <hi>blaſting curſe</hi> I band,</l>
               <l>But <hi>tears</hi> of <hi>joy</hi> in my warm ey-lids ſtand;</l>
               <l>So that both then, and now, I firmly know,</l>
               <l>That theſe devotions none but him can ſhow:</l>
               <l>For, bating <hi>us,</hi> to <hi>whom</hi> does this pertain?</l>
               <l>Now that <hi>my</hi> act 'tis not <hi>I</hi> witneſſe can;</l>
               <l>Nor is it <hi>yours:</hi> for how could you eſcape,</l>
               <l>Which rue it if but out to Church you <hi>ſtep?</hi>
               </l>
               <pb n="35" facs="tcp:115706:30"/>
               <l>Nor does <hi>my mothers</hi> heart delight to act</l>
               <l>Such works, nor had ſhe carried it untrack'd.</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Orestes</hi> 'tis; theſe Honours muſt deſigne.</l>
               <l>Then, <hi>dear,</hi> courage: Alwayes the <hi>face divine</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Views not the ſame with the ſame conſtant ſhine;</hi>
               </l>
               <l>It <hi>yet</hi> hath <hi>frownd</hi> on us, and who can tell,</l>
               <l>Whether <hi>this day</hi> much <hi>happineſſe</hi> may <hi>ſeal?</hi>
               </l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>El.</speaker>
               <p>
                  <hi>Poore fool!</hi> I pitie thee ev'n all the way.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Ch.</speaker>
               <p>What's this? rejoyce you not at what I ſay?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>El.</speaker>
               <p>Thou knowſt not where thou <hi>ſtand'ſt,</hi> nor what's thy <hi>thought.</hi>
               </p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Ch.</speaker>
               <p>How know I not that which mine <hi>eyes</hi> me <hi>taught?</hi>
               </p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>El.</speaker>
               <l>
                  <hi>He</hi>'s dead, <hi>poore wretch,</hi> thy hopes are at an <hi>end,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>Of aid <hi>from him,</hi> no more <hi>on him</hi> depend.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Ch.</speaker>
               <p>Unhappy me! of whom did you this hear?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>El.</speaker>
               <p>Of one which <hi>when</hi> he fell, <hi>himſelf</hi> was <hi>near.</hi>
               </p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Ch.</speaker>
               <p>And where is he? amazement ſtrikes my breaſt.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>El.</speaker>
               <p>Bout houſe; <hi>my mothers dear</hi> and welcome gueſt.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Ch.</speaker>
               <l>Unhappy me! vvho vvas he then that gave</l>
               <l>Thoſe lib'rall off rings at my Fathers grave?</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>El.</speaker>
               <l>I am perſvvaded ſome kind hand hath paid</l>
               <l>Thoſe ſad devotions to <hi>Oreſtes</hi> ſhade.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Ch.</speaker>
               <l>Diſtreſſed me! but I vvith joy ſurprizd</l>
               <l>Haſtned to bring this vvord, nor once ſurmizd</l>
               <l>In vvhat ſad caſe vve are, but coming vievv,</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>My ancient Bill of care enflamd with new.</hi>
               </l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>El.</speaker>
               <l>Thus ſtands your caſe, but if you'l hear my mind,</l>
               <pb n="36" facs="tcp:115706:31"/>
               <l>This preſſing <hi>load</hi> of grief you ſhall <hi>unbind.</hi>
               </l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Ch.</speaker>
               <p>Can I the dead <hi>to life raiſe</hi> up <hi>again?</hi>
               </p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>El.</speaker>
               <p>There's no ſuch need: I was not ſure ſo vain.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Ch.</speaker>
               <p>What other <hi>action</hi> can my <hi>ſtrength</hi> effect?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>El.</speaker>
               <p>
                  <hi>Dare</hi> but to <hi>move</hi> as I ſhall you <hi>direct.</hi>
               </p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Ch.</speaker>
               <p>Why if 't be good, I vvill not come be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hind.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>El.</speaker>
               <p>See, <hi>without pains nothing ſucceſſe can find.</hi>
               </p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Ch.</speaker>
               <p>I ſee: and vvill contribute too my <hi>All.</hi>
               </p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>El.</speaker>
               <l>Heark then vvhich vvay my reſolutions fal.</l>
               <l>Our <hi>ſtore</hi> of friends, you knovv that <hi>none</hi> vve have</l>
               <l>But all are ſvvallovv'd by the rav'nous grave.</l>
               <l>And onely vve diſtreſſed pair ſurvive.</l>
               <l>Novv vvhile I heard my brother vvas alive</l>
               <l>And flouriſht, ſtill, one day, my hopes did reſt,</l>
               <l>He for his <hi>Fathers bloud</hi> vvould make <hi>inqueſt.</hi>
               </l>
               <l>But ſince <hi>he</hi>'s gone, <hi>to you</hi> I turn <hi>my eyes,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>That vvith your ſiſter joyning enterpriſe,</l>
               <l>You ſhould not novv to <hi>execute</hi> deferre</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Egiſt</hi> our Fathers executioner:</l>
               <l>For nought it boots longer my thoughts to ſtop,</l>
               <l>And till vvhen vvill you ſlug? upon vvhat hope</l>
               <l>Not ſleighted look you? You indeed may moan.</l>
               <l>Of your <hi>revenue robd</hi> and <hi>portion:</hi>
               </l>
               <l>And you may grieve vvhich to this ancient day</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Unbedded</hi> and <hi>unwedded</hi> wear avvay.</l>
               <l>Nay, never muſt you look theſe joyes to meet:</l>
               <l>For think not <hi>Egiſt</hi> is ſo <hi>indiſereet,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>To ſuffer once <hi>your ſtock</hi> or <hi>mine</hi> to <hi>flouriſh,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>Which vvere his <hi>open overthrow</hi> to <hi>nouriſh.</hi>
               </l>
               <l>But if you vvill my earneſt counſel truſt,</l>
               <l>Firſt to our Fathers and our Brothers duſt,</l>
               <pb n="37" facs="tcp:115706:31"/>
               <l>Perform the Ceremony's of the Dead,</l>
               <l>Then as thou'rt <hi>nobly born,</hi> and <hi>nobly bred,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Aſſert</hi> thy Name, &amp; thou a <hi>Match</hi> ſhalt find</l>
               <l>Of <hi>worth,</hi> for <hi>all to vertue are enclin'd.</hi>
               </l>
               <l>But as for <hi>fame,</hi> you know not what <hi>reſpect,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>Obeying me, on us both you reffect.</l>
               <l>For who or <hi>Friend</hi> or <hi>Stranger</hi> ſhall us meet,</l>
               <l>But will us with this commendation greet?</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Mark Dear Companions thoſe two Sisters: thoſe</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Who from the Duſt redeem'd their Fathers houſe.</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Who when Victorious Treaſon higheſt flew,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Spar'd not for life, but the bold rebell ſlew:</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Theſe we muſt love: theſe we muſt reverence all:</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>And for their Spirit at Feaſts and publik Hall,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Receive with Honour Epidemicall.</hi>
               </l>
               <l>Thus ſhall all living us with praiſes Crown,</l>
               <l>So that nor <hi>Life,</hi> nor <hi>Death</hi> ſhall want renown.</l>
               <l>Wherefore <hi>Dear ſoul</hi> be rul'd your <hi>Sire</hi> relieve,</l>
               <l>Aſſiſt <hi>your Brother,</hi> reſcue <hi>me</hi> from grief.</l>
               <l>Reſcue <hi>your ſelf:</hi> Aſſur'd of this, <hi>'tis baſe</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Well to be born and live in foul diſgrace.</hi>
               </l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Qui.</speaker>
               <l>In ſuch affairs <hi>Advice</hi> were a good Friend,</l>
               <l>To <hi>them that Counſell,</hi> and <hi>them that atend.</hi>
               </l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Chry.</speaker>
               <l>Now e're ſhe ſpoke, Lady's, had <hi>Vertue</hi> reign'd,</l>
               <l>She <hi>Modeſty</hi> had kept which now is <hi>ſtain'd.</hi>
               </l>
               <l>For on what grounds in <hi>desp'rat boldneſſe</hi> yet</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Dreſſe</hi> you your Heart and fain would me <hi>abet?</hi>
               </l>
               <l>Nor count how you are <hi>Woman</hi> born not <hi>Man,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Inferiour</hi> is our <hi>Sex,</hi> and leſſer can;</l>
               <l>Then their Proſperity in <hi>Spring-tides flow'th,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>Ours back is <hi>Eb'd</hi> and <hi>parcheth</hi> into <hi>Drouth.</hi>
               </l>
               <pb n="38" facs="tcp:115706:32"/>
               <l>Who then ſhall plot to ſtricke off ſuch a Head,</l>
               <l>And think to carry it unpuniſhed?</l>
               <l>See then leſt Bad enough to Worſe advance;</l>
               <l>If any <hi>Ear</hi> on theſe our Counſells <hi>glance.</hi>
               </l>
               <l>For nought it helps us, nor our ſtare amends,</l>
               <l>To gain good Names, and come to ſhameful End<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>.</l>
               <l>For Death is not the worſt, but Death to will.</l>
               <l>Nor to be able this Will to fulfill.</l>
               <l>Now I beſeech you e're you <hi>root</hi> us out</l>
               <l>At once, and bring your Family to <hi>nought,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Aſſwage</hi> your <hi>heat:</hi> and all which hath been ſaid;</l>
               <l>Unſpoke, Undone, ſhall <hi>ſafely</hi> up be laid.</l>
               <l>Onely your Spirit <hi>check,</hi> and learn at length</l>
               <l>How <hi>weak</hi> you are, and then <hi>ſubmit</hi> to <hi>ſtrength.</hi>
               </l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Qui.</speaker>
               <l>Be rul'd: <hi>No treaſure Man enjoy's ſo great</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>As is a wiſe Forecaſt, and mind diſere<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>s.</hi>
               </l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>El.</speaker>
               <l>All this before I look't for: I expected</l>
               <l>That all which was <hi>apply'd</hi> ſhould be <hi>rejected:</hi>
               </l>
               <l>But with my Hand this work alone will I</l>
               <l>Archieve: nor will we let out counſells die.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Chry.</speaker>
               <l>Oh—</l>
               <l>Would when my Father dy'd your Mind had been</l>
               <l>Thus firmly bent; you all had finiſh't then.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>El.</speaker>
               <p>Why then my <hi>will</hi> was <hi>good,</hi> but <hi>loſſe</hi> my <hi>wit.</hi>
               </p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Chry.</speaker>
               <p>Strive that your wit ſtand alwayes at that height.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>El.</speaker>
               <p>You then <hi>inſtruct</hi> me but wil nothing <hi>Aid.</hi>
               </p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Chry.</speaker>
               <p>Why it will bring us <hi>ruine</hi> if <hi>aſſay'd.</hi>
               </p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>El.</speaker>
               <p>I praiſe your wondrous <hi>Wit,</hi> but hate your <hi>fear.</hi>
               </p>
            </sp>
            <pb n="39" facs="tcp:115706:32"/>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Chry.</speaker>
               <p>When you ſhall thank me for it I'll give ear.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>El.</speaker>
               <p>Never expect to find me in that <hi>Note.</hi>
               </p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Chry.</speaker>
               <p>Of that Hereafter gives the ſurer Vote.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>El.</speaker>
               <p>Away, for <hi>thou</hi> art one wil't nothing <hi>do.</hi>
               </p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Chry.</speaker>
               <p>I would, but <hi>thou</hi> art one wilt nothing <hi>know.</hi>
               </p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>El.</speaker>
               <p>Go tell your Mother the diſcourſe w'have had.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Chry.</speaker>
               <p>No, Siſter, yet I love you not ſo bad.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>El.</speaker>
               <p>Know you to great <hi>diſgrace</hi> draw me aſide.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Chry.</speaker>
               <p>To no <hi>diſgrace,</hi> but <hi>wiſedom</hi> I you <hi>guide.</hi>
               </p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>El.</speaker>
               <p>I <hi>follow</hi> muſt what you for <hi>Juſtice</hi> read.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Chry.</speaker>
               <p>When you with <hi>Judgement</hi> joyn, then you ſhall lead.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>El.</speaker>
               <p>Pity one ſpeaks ſo <hi>well,</hi> and ſpeaks ſo <hi>wide.</hi>
               </p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Chry.</speaker>
               <p>Right ſaid you that, to your own ſpeech appli'd.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>El.</speaker>
               <p>What ſeem I not with <hi>Juſtice</hi> to combine?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Chry.</speaker>
               <p>Yes but ſometime <hi>Juſtice</hi> with <hi>Harm</hi> may Joyn.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>El.</speaker>
               <p>I'll never to theſe lawes Alleagiance pay.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Chry.</speaker>
               <p>But if you <hi>do,</hi> you'l thank me for't one Day.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>El.</speaker>
               <p>Yes I <hi>will do,</hi> nor will at all you dread.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Chry.</speaker>
               <p>Is 't true? nor will you ſecond Counſell read?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>El.</speaker>
               <p>No: for of Bads, the Worſt Bad Counſell is.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Chry.</speaker>
               <p>All I have ſaid you underſtand amiſſe.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>El.</speaker>
               <p>Long fixt is this reſolve; no ſudden Motion.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Chry.</speaker>
               <l>Then I am gone, for on my <hi>words attend.</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>You will</hi> not, nor <hi>can-I</hi> your <hi>works commend.</hi>
               </l>
            </sp>
            <pb n="40" facs="tcp:115706:33"/>
            <sp>
               <speaker>El</speaker>
               <l>Go in: ne're will I be at your devotion,</l>
               <l>Though moſt you wiſh it; for 'tis fooliſh pains,</l>
               <l>If we Content purſue, where none remains.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Chry,</speaker>
               <l>
                  <stage n="i" place="margin">This ſhee ſpeaks as ſhe is walking away.</stage> Why if you think you <hi>are</hi> ſo, <hi>ſtill</hi> be wiſe;</l>
               <l>But when you <hi>feel it,</hi> you'll praiſe my <hi>Advice.</hi>
               </l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Qui.</speaker>
               <l n="1">1 Why mark vve the vviſe fowl, Above,</l>
               <l n="2">2 In Countrey and in Nat'rall love;</l>
               <l n="3">3 Where the <hi>Dam</hi> looks to be fed,</l>
               <l n="4">4 Of thoſe ſhe hath <hi>born</hi> and <hi>bred;</hi>
               </l>
               <l n="5">5 Nor do like Tribute pay.</l>
               <l n="6">6 But if <hi>Jove</hi> thunder hath,</l>
               <l n="7">7 And heavenly <hi>Themis</hi> wrath;</l>
               <l n="8">8 They Carry't not Avvay.</l>
               <l n="9">9 Fame dovvnvvard ſpring,</l>
               <l n="10">10 And this dolefull Meſſage ring:</l>
               <l n="11">11 In the Dead <hi>Atrida's</hi> hearings</l>
               <l n="12">12 Of theſe cruell
<note n="24" place="margin">This Metaphor is elegantly put to expreſſe a Bickering betwixt friends en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gag'd in one common Cauſe that ſhould tread in equalſteps, and hear the ſame Burden. It is taken from the beſt Author of Engliſh, our late Sov<gap reason="illegible" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>
                     <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raign of E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ternall Me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mory, in his Cabinet broke open; pag xxxviii. Numer. to the Queen xxxvii.</note> 
                  <hi>interferings,</hi>
               </l>
               <l n="1">1 Their Houſe-affairs have long been weak,</l>
               <l n="2">2 Their children now in quarrels break:</l>
               <l n="3">3 Nor doth long converſe as yet</l>
               <l n="4">4 Their Diviſions Umpire ſet.</l>
               <l n="5">5 <hi>Electra</hi> ſtill doth float:</l>
               <l n="6">6 Poore ſhe betrayd alone,</l>
               <l n="7">7 Alwayes her Sire doth moan,</l>
               <l n="8">8 I'th Nightingals ſad note:</l>
               <l n="9">9 Nor cares for Death;</l>
               <l n="10">10 But provides to <hi>morgage</hi> breath,</l>
               <l n="11">11 While ſhe thoſe <hi>twin-imps</hi> deſtroyeth.</l>
               <l n="12">12 In ſuch life what Lady joyeth?</l>
               <pb n="41" facs="tcp:115706:33"/>
               <l n="1">1 None low of means, and high of place,</l>
               <l n="2">2 Endure their honours to debaſe</l>
               <l n="3">3 With ſcorn. <hi>Great Lady, thus</hi>
               </l>
               <l n="4">4 <hi>You hard afflictions chuſe</hi>
               </l>
               <l n="5">5 <hi>Companions of your Age.</hi>
               </l>
               <l n="5">5 <hi>Oppoſing Treaſons Rage.</hi>
               </l>
               <l n="7">7 <hi>At once with double honour crownd,</hi>
               </l>
               <l n="8">8 <hi>A child both wiſe and vertuous found.</hi>
               </l>
               <l n="1">1 <hi>O mayſt thou live in wealth and ſtrength</hi>
               </l>
               <l n="2">2 <hi>Above thine enemies at length,</hi>
               </l>
               <l n="3">3 <hi>More then thou dost Below!</hi>
               </l>
               <l n="4">4 <hi>I thee entirely know;</hi>
               </l>
               <l n="5">5 <hi>Afflicted thou heldſt forth</hi>
               </l>
               <l n="6">6 <hi>High principles of worth:</hi>
               </l>
               <l n="7">7 <hi>Thou alwayes didst for Pilot own</hi>
               </l>
               <l n="8">8 <hi>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nmoveable Religion.</hi>
               </l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Or.</speaker>
               <l>Have we <hi>Deare Lady's,</hi> been directed right,</l>
               <l>And do we on our purpos'd journey hit?</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Qu.</speaker>
               <p>What is your ſearch? and whether your deſire?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Or.</speaker>
               <p>For <hi>Egiſt,</hi> where he dwells I long enquire.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Qu.</speaker>
               <p>You're right, and
<note n="25" place="margin">The <hi>Attick</hi> laws enjoyned to ſhew a ſtranger the way: as <hi>Pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>titus</hi> in the laſt Chap. And <hi>Buzyges</hi> orderd it to be put into their Commination, that thoſe who turned ſtrangers out of their way, ſhould be curſ'd publickly through the ci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, amongſt them that were guilty of other hainous offences.</note> 
                  <hi>harmleſſe</hi> your dire<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctour <hi>ſave.</hi>
               </p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Or.</speaker>
               <l>Who then to thoſe within this errand car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries,</l>
               <l>That here a welcome meſſage for them tarries?</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Qu.</speaker>
               <p>Here 's one. if of her Brother news ſhe have.</p>
            </sp>
            <pb n="42" facs="tcp:115706:34"/>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Or.</speaker>
               <l>Go, Maiden, them within acquaint; At gate</l>
               <l>Some men of <hi>Phocia</hi> for <hi>Egist</hi> wait.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Qu.</speaker>
               <l>Unhappy me! You come not to evince,</l>
               <l>The late report we had by certain ſignes</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Or.</speaker>
               <l>Your talk I know not: But ſome weigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty thing</l>
               <l>Touching <hi>Oreſtes,</hi> from old <hi>Strophius</hi> bring.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Qu.</speaker>
               <p>What is it friend? I feel a chilling fear.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Or.</speaker>
               <l>We in ſmall Urn theſe Funerall reliques bear</l>
               <l>In hand, behold it, of <hi>Oreſtes here.</hi>
               </l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>El.</speaker>
               <l>Ay wretched me! Now plain before mine eie,</l>
               <l>I ſee the <hi>weight,</hi> and feel the <hi>miſery.</hi>
               </l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Or.</speaker>
               <l>If for <hi>Oreſtes</hi> you a tear let ſlide,</l>
               <l>Know that this pitcher doth his Body <hi>hide.</hi>
               </l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>El.</speaker>
               <l>Friend, give me leave, for th' gods ſake I am bold,</l>
               <l>To take this in my hand, if this him hold:</l>
               <l>That o're theſe aſhes I may wail and moan</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>My ſelf,</hi> and <hi>all my family</hi> undone.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Or.</speaker>
               <l>Come reach it her, who e're ſhe be, for ſure</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>I'll will would never this requeſt precure:</hi>
               </l>
               <l>But or ſome <hi>Friend,</hi> or elſe in <hi>bloud</hi> ſhe's <hi>neare.</hi>
               </l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>El.</speaker>
               <l>O thou his monument, who was moſt dear</l>
               <l>The <hi>remnant</hi> of <hi>Oreſtes</hi> ſoul: how wide</l>
               <l>Thy <hi>ſettings-forth,</hi> and thy <hi>return's</hi> divide?</l>
               <l>For now my hands can poyſe thy empty load,</l>
               <l>But, child, I ſent thee glorious abroad.</l>
               <l>Would I had breath'd my laſt e're I thee left</l>
               <l>To <hi>forreigne</hi> lands, and ſav'd thy life by <hi>theft!</hi>
               </l>
               <pb n="43" facs="tcp:115706:34"/>
               <l>Then hadſt thou with thy Sire that day deſtroy'd,</l>
               <l>As Death <hi>with</hi> Death, ſo Grave <hi>by</hi> grave enjoy'd.</l>
               <l>But now <hi>from home,</hi> and <hi>vagrant</hi> in <hi>ſtrange</hi> coaſt,</l>
               <l>Without thy <hi>Sister,</hi> thou art <hi>ſadly</hi> loſt.</l>
               <l>Nor did with <hi>tender</hi> hands <hi>unhappy</hi> I,</l>
               <l>Thy <hi>loved</hi> corſe in Barhings <hi>purifie:</hi>
               </l>
               <l>Nor did I take, as <hi>decent</hi> rites require.</l>
               <l>The <hi>dolefull</hi> burden from the <hi>ſolemn</hi> fire:</l>
               <l>But by <hi>strange</hi> hands laid out, thou doſt return</l>
               <l>The <hi>eaſie</hi> meaſure of a <hi>ſhallow</hi> Urn.</l>
               <l>Wretched me! Oh my feeding thee of old</l>
               <l>Now comes to nought! For oft I thee did hold,</l>
               <l>Nurſing with peaſant trouble. Thou wert ſtil'd</l>
               <l>Not more at all <hi>thy Mothers,</hi> then <hi>my</hi> child.</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>I</hi> was thy Nurſe, not <hi>they within</hi> reputed.</l>
               <l>And I thy ſiſter alwayes <hi>was</hi> ſaluted.</l>
               <l>But all theſe comforts in one day are dead,</l>
               <l>With thee <hi>expiring:</hi> thou with them art fled.</l>
               <l>Thou like a <hi>whirl-wind</hi> ruſh'dſt: Faln is <hi>my Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther:</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>I</hi> from thee periſhr: <hi>Thou</hi> deſtroy'd together.</l>
               <l>The <hi>euemy</hi> laughs, and wild with joy doth rant</l>
               <l>Thy <hi>Stop-dame-Mother;</hi> which <hi>lewd miſcreant</hi>
               </l>
               <l>Thou oft to me in private meſſage ſent,</l>
               <l>That thou wouldſt bring to <hi>condigne</hi> puniſhment.</l>
               <l>But all thoſe <hi>just</hi> reſolves, and <hi>vews</hi> repeated,</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Thine,</hi> and <hi>my</hi> angry Angel have defeated,</l>
               <l>Which thus to me hath in ſad wiſe convey'd</l>
               <l>For thy <hi>ſweat Face,</hi> this <hi>dust</hi> and <hi>uſeleſſe ſhade.</hi>
               </l>
               <l>O me! O me!</l>
               <l>O Dolefull corſe! Ay! Ay!</l>
               <l>O how diſmall! Oh me! O me!</l>
               <pb n="44" facs="tcp:115706:35"/>
               <l>A <hi>journey</hi> tookſt thou, Deareſt, to <hi>my</hi> death,</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Thy Siſters</hi> death, O ſoul more dear then breath.</l>
               <l>Wherefore thou <hi>Me to Thee</hi> take in this room,</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Nothing to nothing:</hi> ſo for time to come</l>
               <l>I'll lodge with thee Below: for <hi>thou</hi> Above</l>
               <l>And <hi>I</hi> did alwayes equall fortunes prove.</l>
               <l>And now I <hi>long</hi> thy Death and Urn to ſhare:</l>
               <l>For I perceive not that the dead take care.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Qu.</speaker>
               <l>
                  <hi>Electra,</hi> think a <hi>Mortall Sire</hi> you had,</l>
               <l>And <hi>Mortall Brother</hi> too, nor grieve too bad,</l>
               <l>For we are <hi>out-law'd</hi> all till Death be <hi>paid.</hi>
               </l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Or.</speaker>
               <l>Oh! oh! what ſhall I ſay? what ſtrange addreſſe</l>
               <l>Contrive? nor can I longer me ſuppreſſe.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>El.</speaker>
               <p>What is your grief? what may this lan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guage ſound?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Or.</speaker>
               <p>Is yours <hi>Electra's</hi> viſage ſo renown'd?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>El.</speaker>
               <p>This is the ſame, and in <hi>full grievous</hi> plight.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Or.</speaker>
               <p>Alas! how <hi>ſad</hi> and <hi>pitifull</hi> a ſight!</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>El.</speaker>
               <p>Why <hi>Stranger,</hi> do you thus for me lament?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Or.</speaker>
               <p>O Body <hi>wickedly</hi> and <hi>baſely</hi> rent!</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>El.</speaker>
               <p>I, gentle <hi>Stranger,</hi> am the ſame you moan,</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Or.</speaker>
               <p>O ſad unwedded deſolation!</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>El.</speaker>
               <p>Why, <hi>Stranger, look</hi> you thus on me, &amp; ſigh?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Or.</speaker>
               <p>Of all my ſorrows I ne're knew the tithe.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>El.</speaker>
               <p>How know you that from ought hath <hi>now</hi> been ſpoken?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Or.</speaker>
               <p>In <hi>ſeeing</hi> you with many troubles broken.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>El.</speaker>
               <p>Few of my troubles are <hi>to ſight</hi> diſclos'd.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Or.</speaker>
               <p>And how can worſe then theſe be once <hi>ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pos</hi>'d?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>El.</speaker>
               <p>Becauſe I ſtill with <hi>murderers</hi> converſe.</p>
            </sp>
            <pb n="45" facs="tcp:115706:35"/>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Or.</speaker>
               <p>Murdrers? of whom? ſtrange grief thou doſt rehearſe.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>El.</speaker>
               <p>
                  <hi>My Fathers Murdrers;</hi> and am made their drudge.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Or.</speaker>
               <p>What mortall doth thee to this bondage judge?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>El.</speaker>
               <p>One Mother <hi>cald,</hi> but nothing <hi>Mother-like.</hi>
               </p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Or.</speaker>
               <p>And by what means? Doth ſhe thee ſtarve or ſtrike?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>El.</speaker>
               <p>Both ſtarvs and ſtrikes, and all hard uſage tries.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Or.</speaker>
               <p>And does no <hi>Helper,</hi> no <hi>Defender</hi> riſe?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>El.</speaker>
               <p>None, and my <hi>One</hi> that was is in your urn.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Or.</speaker>
               <p>Poore heart, I pity all along thy turn.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>El.</speaker>
               <p>Know you are th' onely He hath done <hi>thus much.</hi>
               </p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Or.</speaker>
               <p>For I am th'onely He your troubles touch.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>El.</speaker>
               <p>You are not any way to us ally'd?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Or.</speaker>
               <p>I'ld you reſolve, might I in theſe <hi>confide.</hi>
               </p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>El.</speaker>
               <p>You may; with honeſt Lady's you conferre,</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Or.</speaker>
               <p>Let go the Pot then, and the buſineſſe heare.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>El.</speaker>
               <p>Uſe me not, <hi>Stranger,</hi> for the gods ſake ſo.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Or.</speaker>
               <p>Obey my words and you aright ſhall go.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>El.</speaker>
               <p>Not for all <hi>dears:</hi> rob me not of my trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Or.</speaker>
               <p>I can you not excuſe.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>El.</speaker>
               <l>Hard is my mea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure</l>
               <l>If I thy duſt, <hi>Oreſtes,</hi> muſt let go.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Or.</speaker>
               <p>Good words. Thoſe grones no lawfull war<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rant ſhew.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>El.</speaker>
               <p>No warrant, when I grone for my dead brother?</p>
            </sp>
            <pb n="46" facs="tcp:115706:36"/>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Or.</speaker>
               <p>Thoſe words do not become you, but ſome other.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>El.</speaker>
               <p>Am I ſo of the deads inſeriours?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Or.</speaker>
               <p>Inferiour you of none: nor is this yours.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>El.</speaker>
               <p>If this <hi>Oreſtes</hi> body be, I poyſe.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Or.</speaker>
               <p>Its no <hi>Oreſtes,</hi> but a coyn'd device,</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>El.</speaker>
               <p>Where then, unhappy, is his tombe indeed?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Or.</speaker>
               <p>No where: For men alive no tombe do need.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>El.</speaker>
               <p>What ſaieſt thou man?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Or.</speaker>
               <p>No lie I do contrive.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>El.</speaker>
               <p>And does he breath?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Or.</speaker>
               <p>As ſure as I'me alive.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>El,</speaker>
               <p>You are not he?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Or.</speaker>
               <l>See this my Fathers <hi>Seal,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>And lern if I other then truth reveal,</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>El.</speaker>
               <p>O deareſt fuce!</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Or.</speaker>
               <p>Deareſt I witnes bear.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>El.</speaker>
               <p>O voyce art come?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Or.</speaker>
               <p>No other ſeek to hear.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>El.</speaker>
               <p>I thee embrace.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Or.</speaker>
               <p>O mayſt thou <hi>e're</hi> from hence!</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>El.</speaker>
               <l>Deareſt companions, fellow citizens;</l>
               <l>Behold <hi>Orestes</hi> by a fiction ſlain,</l>
               <l>And by that fiction ſafely brought again.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Qu.</speaker>
               <l>Lady, we ſee. And all our grief to heal.</l>
               <l>A tear of joy down from our eyes doth ſteal.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>El.</speaker>
               <l n="1">1 O Nobleſt, Nobleſt Progeny</l>
               <l n="2">2 Of the moſt Reverend, to me</l>
               <l n="3">3 At length brought back;</l>
               <l n="4">4 You come, you find, you ſee thoſe whom you you lack,</l>
            </sp>
            <pb n="47" facs="tcp:115706:36"/>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Or.</speaker>
               <l n="1">1 W'are come: But o're us let ſtill ſilence hover.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>El.</speaker>
               <l n="2">2 What is the buſineſſe?</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Or.</speaker>
               <l n="3">3 <hi>Silence</hi> were beſt, leſt they within <hi>diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cover.</hi>
               </l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>El.</speaker>
               <l n="1">1 Now <hi>Dian</hi> aid,</l>
               <l n="2">2 Eternall maid,</l>
               <l n="3">3 Of that be ne're afraid.</l>
               <l n="4">4 While ſuch a female ſwarm</l>
               <l n="5">5 Still in the houſe, <hi>ring</hi> their <hi>alarm.</hi>
               </l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Or.</speaker>
               <l n="1">1 Beware, for women too can warre aſſay:</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>El.</speaker>
               <l n="1">1 O joyfull day!</l>
               <l n="2">2 Thou haft <hi>restord</hi> our light,</l>
               <l n="3">3 <hi>Wrapt</hi> up in conſtant night,</l>
               <l n="4">4 In <hi>one</hi> continu'd Weſt,</l>
               <l n="5">5 So were our hearts diſtreſt.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Or.</speaker>
               <l n="1">1 I know this too; but <hi>then we</hi> will re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>flect</l>
               <l n="2">2 On theſe affairs, <hi>when ſeaſon</hi> ſhall direct,</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>El.</speaker>
               <l n="1">1 All time, all time I do repute</l>
               <l n="2">2 My preſent joyfulneſſe to ſuit,</l>
               <l n="3">3 So juſt, ſo fit;</l>
               <l n="4">4 For never could I <hi>ſpeak</hi> with <hi>freedome</hi> yet.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Or.</speaker>
               <l n="1">1 <hi>There</hi> I conſent. Wherefore now keep it <hi>ſafer.</hi>
               </l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>El.</speaker>
               <l n="2">2 By what endeauours?</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Or.</speaker>
               <l n="3">3 By not <hi>enlarging,</hi> while time does not favour.</l>
            </sp>
            <pb n="48" facs="tcp:115706:37"/>
            <sp>
               <speaker>El.</speaker>
               <l n="1">1 Upon what fear</l>
               <l n="2">2 Now you appear</l>
               <l n="3">3 Can I to ſpeak forbear,</l>
               <l n="4">4 When unwarn'd, unadvis'd,</l>
               <l n="5">5 I ſee thee hither come diſguis'd?</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Or.</speaker>
               <l n="1">1 Thou ſeeſt me when the <hi>Gods</hi> decree'd my way.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>El.</speaker>
               <l n="1">1 Bleſt news you ſay,</l>
               <l n="2">2 Greater then yet I knew,</l>
               <l n="3">3 You tell a joy that's new;</l>
               <l n="4">4 <hi>If God did guide,</hi> I ſay</l>
               <l n="5">5 <hi>Auſpictous is your way.</hi>
               </l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Or.</speaker>
               <l n="1">1 Full loth I am to <hi>check</hi> your joy, but <hi>yet</hi>
               </l>
               <l n="2">2
<note n="26" place="margin">The 14. following verſes which are full of Female paſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſions, depend upon an un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kindneſſe which <hi>Ele<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctra</hi> takes at this expreſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion.</note> I fear <hi>to pleaſure</hi> you too much <hi>ſubmit.</hi>
               </l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>El.</speaker>
               <l>Thou who didſt pleaſe though held by long demurre</l>
               <l>This pleaſant voyage to preferre</l>
               <l>Me ſpouſe of ſorrows do not thou—</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Or.</speaker>
               <p>What ſhould I not?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>El.</speaker>
               <l>Do not me <hi>diſallow</hi>
               </l>
               <l>The <hi>pleaſure</hi> of thy <hi>preſence</hi> to declare</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Or.</speaker>
               <p>With others I'ld be angry ſhould they dare.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>El.</speaker>
               <p>You like me then!</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Or.</speaker>
               <p>Why ſhould I o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>therwiſe</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>El.</speaker>
               <l>O friends a voice</l>
               <l>Which I exſpected not I heard,</l>
               <l>My anger ſpeechleſſe was,</l>
               <l>And I to cry aloud afeard;</l>
               <l>But now I hugge thee; on thy face</l>
               <l>A pleaſant <hi>ſhine</hi> doth ſit</l>
               <l>Which I though full of care ſhould ne're <hi>forget.</hi>
               </l>
            </sp>
            <pb n="49" facs="tcp:115706:37"/>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Or.</speaker>
               <l>From all <hi>impertinent</hi> diſcourſes ceaſe:</l>
               <l>Nor teach me that <hi>debancht</hi> my <hi>mother</hi> is;</l>
               <l>That <hi>Egiſt</hi> all our Fathers <hi>coffers</hi> ſpends;</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Wast's</hi> ſome <hi>himſelf,</hi> and <hi>ſhares</hi> ſome with his <hi>Friends.</hi>
               </l>
               <l>The time would paſſe ſhould we <hi>diſcourſing</hi> ſtand</l>
               <l>But what may further the deſigne in hand</l>
               <l>Tell me, how in an <hi>hid</hi> or <hi>ouvert</hi> way,</l>
               <l>My coming may my laughing foes <hi>allay.</hi>
               </l>
               <l>And when we enter hold a watchfull eye,</l>
               <l>Leſt you with <hi>chearfull</hi> looks your Mother ſpy,</l>
               <l>But to the t<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>le of grief a grone <hi>let flie:</hi>
               </l>
               <l>For, <hi>when our labours have obtain'd the goal,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Then we may laugh and joy without controll.</hi>
               </l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>El.</speaker>
               <l>Well Brother, what may make to your <hi>content</hi>
               </l>
               <l>Shall be my <hi>care:</hi> for all my joyes I <hi>rent</hi>
               </l>
               <l>Deriv'd from you, nor can my <hi>Free-hold</hi> call;</l>
               <l>Wherefore I would not, to your grief though <hi>ſmall.</hi>
               </l>
               <l>A <hi>great</hi> advantage reap: For I full ill</l>
               <l>Should hearken to my preſent <hi>Angels</hi> will.</l>
               <l>Nor can you otherwiſe but know the ſumme</l>
               <l>Of our affairs: How <hi>Egiſt</hi> is from home;</l>
               <l>But here within my Mother, whom ne're doubt</l>
               <l>Leſt ſhe my <hi>merry</hi> countenance find out:</l>
               <l>For both in ancient <hi>feud</hi> I with her burn;</l>
               <l>And ſeeing the pleaſure of your ſafe return,</l>
               <l>To drop my <hi>liquid</hi> joy in plenteous <hi>ſhower,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>Nor ever <hi>will</hi> deſiſt, nor <hi>have</hi> the <hi>power:</hi>
               </l>
               <l>For I have the<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <hi>dead</hi> and <hi>alive</hi> beheld</l>
               <l>At <hi>ene</hi> approch, and wonders <hi>reconcil'd:</hi>
               </l>
               <pb n="50" facs="tcp:115706:38"/>
               <l>So that ſhould I my <hi>Father</hi> meet <hi>alive,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>Faith <hi>unaſtoniſht</hi> to the ſight I'ld give:</l>
               <l>Wherefore your own way, ſince you are arriv'd.</l>
               <l>Lead on; for I had this alone archiev'd,</l>
               <l>I had not miſs'd what ſtill was in my eye,</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Bravely</hi> to <hi>quit my ſelf,</hi> or <hi>bravely die.</hi>
               </l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Or.</speaker>
               <l>Silence I you advis'd. Some from within</l>
               <l>I hear is coming forth.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>El.</speaker>
               <l>
                  <hi>Come,</hi> Strangers, in;</l>
               <l>For what you bring, can neither <hi>forth</hi> be kept,</l>
               <l>Nor can the taker with <hi>delight</hi> accept.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Tut.</speaker>
               <l>O Men moſt vain, and of all wit bereft,</l>
               <l>What, of your lives have you no value left?</l>
               <l>Or have you not of common ſenſe a taſt,</l>
               <l>Who do not once conceive how you are plac'd,</l>
               <l>Not at the <hi>Brink.</hi> but in wide hazzards <hi>deep!</hi>
               </l>
               <l>For had not I light in the houſe to keep</l>
               <l>A faithfull ward, into the inmoſt room</l>
               <l>Before your <hi>perſons,</hi> your <hi>deſignes</hi> had come.</l>
               <l>But now a <hi>ſure</hi> proviſion I have made:</l>
               <l>Wherefore aſide all <hi>long diſcourſes</hi> laid,</l>
               <l>And <hi>dangerous</hi> joy by <hi>laviſh</hi> ſhouts bewrayd,</l>
               <l>Enter the houſe: for <hi>perill tracks delay,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>And expedition here muſt win the Day.</hi>
               </l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Or.</speaker>
               <p>How at my entrance are things manag'd there?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Tut.</speaker>
               <p>Right well: for none will know you who you are.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Or.</speaker>
               <p>You then have of my death reporter been?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Tut,</speaker>
               <p>Know you are <hi>one</hi> of <hi>t' other world</hi> with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Or.</speaker>
               <p>And are they glad thereat? what words are giv'n?</p>
            </sp>
            <pb n="51" facs="tcp:115706:38"/>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Tut.</speaker>
               <l>When <hi>all</hi> is <hi>done</hi> I'll anſwer: But <hi>untill</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>All's</hi> there, ev'n that which is not well, is <hi>well.</hi>
               </l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>El.</speaker>
               <p>Brother, I beg, reſolve me what's this man?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Or.</speaker>
               <p>Know you him not?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>El.</speaker>
               <p>Nor yet imagine can.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Or.</speaker>
               <p>Know you not whom you gave me in his hands?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>El.</speaker>
               <p>Whom? what d' you mean?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Or.</speaker>
               <l>Who to the <hi>Phocian</hi> lands</l>
               <l>Convey'd me ſecretly, ſent by your order.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>El,</speaker>
               <l>Is this that man, the onely He of all</l>
               <l>Whom I found faithfull at my Fathers fall?</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Or.</speaker>
               <p>The ſame it is: <hi>examine</hi> me no <hi>further.</hi>
               </p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>El.</speaker>
               <l>O deareſt face! O onely <hi>ranſomer</hi>
               </l>
               <l>Of <hi>Agamemnons</hi> houſe! how camſt thou here?</l>
               <l>Art thou He which from <hi>Death</hi> haſt <hi>him</hi> ſet free,</l>
               <l>And <hi>me</hi> from odious <hi>captivity?</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Deareſt,</hi> thoſe <hi>hands,</hi> and thoſe <hi>beloved feet</hi>
               </l>
               <l>A ſweet embaſſage bear! Nor did I heed</l>
               <l>Thy <hi>neere</hi> converſe, nor wouldſt <hi>diſcloſe;</hi> but flew'ſt</l>
               <l>Me with thy words, when truth moſt dear, thou knewſt.</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Hail</hi> Father! for methinks I ſee my <hi>Father.</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Hail,</hi> and know, thee moſt of all men together,</l>
               <l>In one dayes compaſſe I did <hi>hate</hi> and <hi>favour.</hi>
               </l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Tut.</speaker>
               <l>Enough: for theſe diſcourſes made at plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure,</l>
               <l>The <hi>wheeling</hi> Nights, with <hi>equall</hi> Dayes may meaſure:</l>
               <l>Which you <hi>Electra</hi> thus ſhall entertain.</l>
               <l>But you that here attend, I tell you plain,</l>
               <pb n="52" facs="tcp:115706:39"/>
               <l>
                  <hi>Now</hi> action fits: <hi>Now</hi> the Queen's all alone.</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Now</hi> there's no <hi>man</hi> within: But if you drone</l>
               <l>Conſider how <hi>with theſe,</hi> and <hi>wiſer farre,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>Beeing <hi>more then theſe,</hi> you muſt engage in War.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Or.</speaker>
               <l>
                  <hi>Pylade,</hi> this work no further long delay</l>
               <l>Requires, but in we with all ſpeed we may.</l>
               <l>And let's our <hi>homage</hi> offer to the gods</l>
               <l>Which in this entrance take up their abodes.
<stage n="k" place="margin">
                     <hi>Pylade</hi> and <hi>Orêſtes</hi> kneel down and pray. <hi>Electra</hi> kneels down too in the Court of the houſe with them.</stage>
               </l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>El.</speaker>
               <l>
                  <note n="27" place="margin">Here let it not be thought an impertinen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cie, to annex theſe Corollaryes. That firſt as the Heathens ſcatter'd their gods through all high-wayes, and faſtened a devotion upon almoſt every ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ject; ſo their adorations were not retir'd from publick view. And again, their ſhrines were ordinarily in the bounds of places, ſuch as are Borders of Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>treys, Havens, Corners of ſtreets, and Portals of houſes, by which they par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>celd forth the Ubiquity of God, and endeavoured to piece out that Omni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſence which exceeds the meaſure of finite capacities, with the raggs of ſucceſſive ſhifting of places. A third obſervation is which follows.</note> Sovereigne <hi>Apollo,</hi> them with favour heare,</l>
               <l>And me with them: for I did ſtill appear.</l>
               <l>With hand enlarg'd,
<note n="28" place="margin">The comparing this, with her preſents <hi>Pag.</hi> 18. and her mothers, <hi>Pag.</hi> 24. ſhews a ſweet contemplation drawn from the Law of Nature, and entire Reaſon, that the mites of a diſtreſſed innocent are more acceptable, then the Baskets of fruits, the Baſons of Spies, Gumms and Incenſe, the Boxes of Oyls, with flagons of Wine, and all other pompous blandiſhments which diſſembling oppreſſours offer.</note> 
                  <hi>according</hi> to my <hi>power.</hi>
               </l>
               <l>And now, <hi>Lycean</hi> King, I bring my ſtore,</l>
               <l>I <hi>pray,</hi> I <hi>prostrate me,</hi> I <hi>beg.</hi> Combine</l>
               <l>Thy aid <hi>propitious</hi> in this great <hi>deſigne.</hi>
               </l>
               <l>And then the <hi>unbelieving</hi> world ſhall ſee,</l>
               <l>What <hi>due</hi> rewards the <hi>gods</hi> to <hi>vice</hi> decree.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Qu.</speaker>
               <l n="1">1 See how <hi>Mars</hi> breathing hoſtile blood,</l>
               <l n="2">2 Before is taſting of his food,</l>
               <pb n="53" facs="tcp:115706:39"/>
               <l n="3">3 And enter'd <hi>rove</hi> within the houſe</l>
               <l n="4">4 The <hi>chaſers</hi> of facts <hi>villaxous</hi>
               </l>
               <l n="5">5 The <hi>Hounds</hi> below!</l>
               <l n="6">6 So that not farre <hi>behind</hi> doth <hi>go</hi>
               </l>
               <l n="7">7 That which my mind did long <hi>fore-know.</hi>
               </l>
               <l n="1">1 For in the houſe brought from the dead,</l>
               <l n="2">2 The Judge in a diſguiſe doth tread,</l>
               <l n="3">3 His Fathers <hi>rich</hi> and <hi>ancient</hi> ſeat,</l>
               <l n="4">4 <hi>Graſping</hi> in hand his <hi>blade</hi> new <hi>whet:</hi>
               </l>
               <l n="5">5 And <hi>Maia's</hi> ſon,</l>
               <l n="6">6 Cloſe <hi>Merc'ry</hi> leads them, putting on</l>
               <l n="7">7 A myſt to th' laſt, nor tarry's till <hi>anon.</hi>
               </l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>El.</speaker>
               <l>Lady's moſt dear, The men within diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpatch</l>
               <l>The bus'neſſe, here do you with ſilence watch.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Qu.</speaker>
               <p>How? Now what do they?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>El.</speaker>
               <l>While ſhe do's provide</l>
               <l>A cauldron for the dead, they <hi>ſtand beſide.</hi>
               </l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Qu.</speaker>
               <p>And why did you come out?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>El.</speaker>
               <l>To ſtand a guard,</l>
               <l>Leſt <hi>Egist</hi> enter in and ne're be heard.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Clyt.</speaker>
               <l>Ah! Ah! Wo! the Houſe</l>
               <l>Widow'd of Friends, and ſeiz'd upon by Fiends!</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>El.</speaker>
               <p>One cri's within, do you not hear my friends?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Qu.</speaker>
               <l n="1">1 I a diſmall hearing heard,</l>
               <l n="2">2 Made unhappy me afeard.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Clyt.</speaker>
               <l n="1">1 O me forlorn! <hi>Egiſt,</hi> where art thou? gone.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>El.</speaker>
               <l n="2">2 Look, one cri's out again.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Clyt.</speaker>
               <l>O ſon! O ſon!</l>
               <l n="3">3 Pity thy <hi>Mother.</hi>
               </l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>El.</speaker>
               <l>But I'me ſure nor <hi>He,</hi>
               </l>
               <l n="4">4 Nor <hi>his own Father,</hi> pity'd were by thee.</l>
            </sp>
            <pb n="54" facs="tcp:115706:40"/>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Qui.</speaker>
               <l n="1">1 Wretched City; wretched Houſe,</l>
               <l n="2">2 Now the Fate of <hi>old</hi> thine own</l>
               <l n="3">3 Thee into waſte ruines throw's</l>
               <l n="4">4 Down, Down.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>1 <hi>Clyt.</hi>
               </speaker>
               <p>Oh! I am ſtab'd!</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>El.</speaker>
               <p>Courage and mend your blow.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Clyt.</speaker>
               <p>Oh! and again!</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>El.</speaker>
               <p>Would <hi>Egiſt</hi> were ſo too!</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Qui.</speaker>
               <l n="1">1 The Curſes prove. They breath</l>
               <l n="2">2 Whom Earth had lodg'd beneath:</l>
               <l n="3">3 For he which long ago was dead, now <hi>drains,</hi>
               </l>
               <l n="4">4 <hi>Channels</hi> of Blood from out the Murderers <hi>veyns.</hi>
               </l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>El.</speaker>
               <l n="1">1 So they come forth, his <hi>Crimſon</hi> hand doth <hi>wreak</hi>
               </l>
               <l n="2">2 With <hi>Wars oblation;</hi> But I cannot ſpeak</l>
               <l n="3">3 <hi>How are things carry'd?</hi>
               </l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Or.</speaker>
               <l>Things with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in are wrought</l>
               <l n="4">4 <hi>Well</hi> if <hi>Apollos</hi> wiſedom well hath <hi>taught,</hi>
               </l>
               <l n="5">5 The <hi>Wretch</hi> is <hi>Dead;</hi> Henceforth all Fear diſplace,</l>
               <l n="6">6 Your Mothers ſpight ne're ſhall you more diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>grace.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Qui.</speaker>
               <l n="1">1 Peace! for I diſcover cleare,</l>
               <l n="2">2 <hi>Egiſt</hi> do's in ſight appear.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>El.</speaker>
               <l n="1">1 Lady's, what not retire?</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Or.</speaker>
               <l>Do you perceive</l>
               <l n="2">2 The Man at Hand?</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>El.</speaker>
               <l>He doth the ſuburbs leave</l>
               <pb n="55" facs="tcp:115706:40"/>
               <l n="3">3 With <hi>Jocond</hi> pace —</l>
               <l n="4">4 —</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Qui.</speaker>
               <l n="1">1 In the Houſe: go Ambuſh'd ſit,</l>
               <l n="2">2 With all preſent ſpeedineſſe:</l>
               <l n="3">3 Thoſe things hitherto have hit</l>
               <l n="4">4 May theſe!</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Or.</speaker>
               <l n="1">1 Reſt quiet we perform your will.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>El.</speaker>
               <p>Then haſt.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Or.</speaker>
               <l n="2">2 I'me lodg'd.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>El.</speaker>
               <p>My charge be o're theſe actions plac'd</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Qui.</speaker>
               <l n="1">1 'Twere beſt a while <hi>picquere,</hi>
               </l>
               <l n="2">2 And <hi>buzze</hi> into his <hi>ear</hi>
               </l>
               <l n="3">3 Some <hi>idle</hi> tale; and <hi>play the fiſh,</hi> that ſo</l>
               <l n="4">4 He <hi>unawares</hi> may <hi>ruſh</hi> on judgements blow.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Egiſt.</speaker>
               <l n="1">1 The <hi>Phocian</hi> ſtrangers which of you can ſhew's</l>
               <l n="2">2 Who of <hi>Oreſtes</hi> death they ſay bring news,</l>
               <l n="3">3 That he was caſt away i'th <hi>Chariet-wrecks?</hi>
               </l>
               <l n="4">4 Can you? or you? or can <hi>you</hi> I muſt ask</l>
               <l n="5">5 That were ſo <hi>fierce</hi> before: for you I take</l>
               <l n="6">6 Here moſt <hi>concern'd,</hi> and beſt <hi>report</hi> can make.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>El.</speaker>
               <l>
                  <note n="26" place="margin">
                     <hi>Electra</hi> in all heran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwers now onely mocks with a dou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble meaning play's upon hisignorance to baffle him while things are ſet in or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der with in.</note> Know it! how ſhould I leſſe? or I ſhould An utter <hi>Alien</hi> to my <hi>deareſt grief.</hi>
               </l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Eg.</speaker>
               <p>Reſolve me where one may the ſtrangers live find</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>El.</speaker>
               <p>Within: for they've met with their Hoſtes kind.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Eg.</speaker>
               <p>And did they ſay for <hi>certain</hi> he was <hi>Dead?</hi>
               </p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>El.</speaker>
               <p>No, (but they <hi>ſhew'd him too</hi>) <hi>not onely ſaid.</hi>
               </p>
            </sp>
            <pb n="56" facs="tcp:115706:41"/>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Eg.</speaker>
               <p>And may we ſee this plain convincing light?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>El.</speaker>
               <p>You may: <hi>your ſelf</hi> will <hi>pity</hi> much the <hi>ſight.</hi>
               </p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Eg.</speaker>
               <p>Much joy thou tell'ſt me of beſides thy wont.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>El.</speaker>
               <p>
                  <hi>Encreaſe</hi> your <hi>joy</hi> if <hi>this</hi> for joy you count!</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Eg.</speaker>
               <l>Silence I will you, and the Gates unfold,</l>
               <l>That <hi>Argives</hi> and <hi>Mycenians</hi> may behold:</l>
               <l>That ſo if any with preſumption ſpread,</l>
               <l>Hath ſtuff't his Sayles, ſeeing <hi>the Prince</hi> is dead</l>
               <l>He may <hi>my</hi> Curb endure, and henceforth fear</l>
               <l>Leaſt condemn, his <hi>haughty</hi> Head to rear.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>El.</speaker>
               <l>My duty is perform'd: for I late wit</l>
               <l>Have got, and can to power <hi>now</hi> ſubmit.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Eg.</speaker>
               <l>
                  <stage n="l" place="margin">The Body of ſlain <hi>Cly<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>temneſtra</hi> is drawn forth vayled into the Stage, re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſented to <hi>Egiſt</hi> as the Corſe of <hi>O<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>restes.</hi>
                  </stage> O <hi>Jove!</hi> A ſight I ſee with ſorrow clo'yd,</l>
               <l>But whether judgements hand I not decide.</l>
               <l>Withdraw the Vayle that even I may ſhed,</l>
               <l>A tear upon my <hi>Kinſman</hi> that is dead.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Or.</speaker>
               <l>Take it <hi>your ſelf.</hi> 'Tis <hi>not mine</hi> but <hi>your own</hi>
               </l>
               <l>To <hi>look upon,</hi> and with kind words to <hi>mean.</hi>
               </l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Eg,</speaker>
               <l>'Tis right, I will: But ſome of you 'bout Houſe</l>
               <l>Go <hi>Clytemneſtra</hi> hither call to us.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Or.</speaker>
               <p>She is hard by you; look no further for her.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Eg.</speaker>
               <p>
                  <stage n="m" place="margin">He diſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>velops it.</stage> Oh! what ſee I?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Or.</speaker>
               <p>Whom look you on <hi>with horrour?</hi>
               </p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Eg.</speaker>
               <l>What <hi>Men</hi> have me within their <hi>nots en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clos'd</hi>
               </l>
               <l>At unawares?</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Or.</speaker>
               <l>Have you not that <hi>ſuppos'd,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>How you <hi>alive</hi> talk with the <hi>Dead</hi> thus free?</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Eg.</speaker>
               <l>Alack, I <hi>take the</hi> word. It cannot <hi>be,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>But this <hi>Oreſtes</hi> is, who talks with me.</l>
            </sp>
            <pb n="57" facs="tcp:115706:41"/>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Or.</speaker>
               <p>You <hi>out</hi> ſo long and ſuch A <hi>Cunning</hi> Man!</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Eg.</speaker>
               <l>Wretch I am loſt: yet let me <hi>this</hi> obtain</l>
               <l>Hear <hi>one</hi> word.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>El.</speaker>
               <l>Brother, <hi>do not,</hi> I beſeech</l>
               <l>Let him <hi>go on,</hi> and <hi>ſpin</hi> a <hi>teadious</hi> ſpeech.</l>
               <l>For wherein is a Dying Man reliev'd</l>
               <l>If he one grievous Minute be repriev'd?</l>
               <l>But kill him out of <hi>hand,</hi> and being kil'd,</l>
               <l>Give him the Bury all of the <hi>open</hi> field</l>
               <l>Out of our ſight: for onely this will <hi>loſe</hi>
               </l>
               <l>The <hi>ſad remembrance</hi> of my ancient woes.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Or.</speaker>
               <l>Get you in quickly: For you now <hi>Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mence</hi>
               </l>
               <l>An <hi>Execution</hi> and no <hi>defence.</hi>
               </l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Eg.</speaker>
               <l>Why do you <hi>hale</hi> me in? if this be <hi>fair</hi>
               </l>
               <l>Why <hi>lacks</hi> it <hi>Night,</hi> and <hi>dreads</hi> the <hi>open</hi> Air?</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Or.</speaker>
               <l>
                  <hi>Appoint</hi> you not. But to the <hi>Chamber</hi> hy</l>
               <l>Where you my Father kil'd and there <hi>Come</hi> die.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Eg.</speaker>
               <l>Is it ordein'd that that <hi>ſame</hi> Room muſt ſee</l>
               <l>The <hi>Pelops</hi> Ills that are, and Are to be.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Or.</speaker>
               <p>It muſt <hi>yours.</hi> I of that give a <hi>ſhrowd</hi> gueſſe.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Eg.</speaker>
               <p>Your Fathers <hi>honour</hi> you do not <hi>profeſſe.</hi>
               </p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Or.</speaker>
               <l>You much <hi>dispute,</hi> but <hi>go</hi> but ſlowly on.</l>
               <l>Advance.</l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Eg.</speaker>
               <p>Go firſt.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Or.</speaker>
               <p>No you muſt <hi>lead</hi> the <hi>van.</hi>
               </p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Eg.</speaker>
               <p>Shall I not <hi>ſcape</hi> you.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Or.</speaker>
               <l>I muſt now beware</l>
               <l>All <hi>eaſe</hi> that you a <hi>bitter</hi> death may ſhare.</l>
               <l>'Twere fit this <hi>Martiall</hi> law did ſtill prevail,</l>
               <l>That who ſo durſt tranſgreſſe the ſtatutes <hi>pale,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>Might <hi>ſtreight</hi> be kild, for <hi>villains</hi> ſoon would <hi>fail.</hi>
               </l>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Qui.</speaker>
               <l>
                  <hi>Atreus ſeed</hi> how <hi>hard</hi> oppreſt,</l>
               <l>Art thou <hi>at length</hi> arriv'd at reſt</l>
               <l>by <hi>this Aſſay</hi> redreſt!</l>
            </sp>
            <trailer>THE END.</trailer>
         </div>
         <div type="epilogue">
            <pb facs="tcp:115706:42"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:115706:42"/>
            <head>THE EPILOGUE: Shewing the Parallell in two Poems, <hi>THE RET<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>RN,</hi> and <hi>THE REST A<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>RATION, Addreſſed to her Highneſſe,</hi> the Lady ELIZABETH. MDCXLIX.</head>
            <div type="poem">
               <pb facs="tcp:115706:43"/>
               <pb n="1" facs="tcp:115706:43"/>
               <head>
                  <hi>THE RET<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>RN.</hi> To Her Highneſſe, the Ladie ELIZABETH.</head>
               <opener>
                  <salute>BRight Saint,</salute>
               </opener>
               <l>Juſt Heaven hath ſeen thy Tears:</l>
               <l>Thy Brother on our Iſles appears.</l>
               <l>Requeſt and Sorrow now leave off,</l>
               <l>When glad Enjoyment ſayes, Enough.</l>
               <l>Let no ſad Thought take from the grace</l>
               <l>Of a ſerene and full-blown Praiſe.</l>
               <l>Looks over-caſt but ill do ſuit,</l>
               <l>The Royall Stranger to ſalute.</l>
               <l>Honour with mirth now reconciles:</l>
               <l>Reject not thoſe officious ſmiles</l>
               <l>Which hover yet aloof, and ſeek</l>
               <l>To perch upon your lovely cheek.</l>
            </div>
            <div type="poem">
               <pb n="2" facs="tcp:115706:44"/>
               <opener>
                  <salute>MADAM,</salute>
               </opener>
               <lg>
                  <l>Lift up your pleaſant eye,</l>
                  <l>In yonder Nook ſits Majeſtie.</l>
                  <l>Our Sov'reigne at that Spot begun</l>
                  <l>Three Kingdoms juſt Poſſeſsion.</l>
                  <l>Thus a received Turf doth yield,</l>
                  <l>Full ſeiſin of its native Field;</l>
                  <l>And from that ſtreight and diſtant ſphear,</l>
                  <l>Weighs and directs his free Carier.</l>
                  <l>As firſt the early point of Day,</l>
                  <l>Aloof does but the Earth ſurvey,</l>
                  <l>But ſtreight the dark profound invades,</l>
                  <l>And chaſes out the flying ſhades.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>There he debates what ready way,</l>
                  <l>A glorious Entrance to aſsay.</l>
                  <l>The num'rous ſinners he deſcry's</l>
                  <l>Parted by Seas and Enmiti's.</l>
                  <l>He ſees, and ſo do the ſage States,</l>
                  <l>That as their Fear, their Love abates:</l>
                  <l>Becauſe, though their grim Horſemen tread</l>
                  <l>Upon the quaking Countreys head;</l>
                  <pb n="3" facs="tcp:115706:44"/>
                  <l>Though they our lives hang at their beck,</l>
                  <l>And a ſtiff yoke about our neck;</l>
                  <l>Though they can ſpoil without Conſent,</l>
                  <l>Yet e're they rule we muſt Indent:</l>
                  <l>Force can but in a Rape engage,</l>
                  <l>'T is Choice muſt make it Marriage.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>Hence a Conveyance they contrive,</l>
                  <l>Which muſt on us their Cauſe derive:</l>
                  <l>This muſt attaque, what holds out ſtill,</l>
                  <l>And is impregnable, the Will.</l>
                  <l>This muſt enchant our conſcious hands,</l>
                  <l>To ſlumber in like guilty bands,</l>
                  <l>While like the froward Miltoniſt,</l>
                  <l>We our old Nuptiall knot untwiſt:</l>
                  <l>And with the hands, late faith did joyn,</l>
                  <l>This Bill of plain Divorce now ſigne.</l>
                  <l>Here their New Kingdom muſt commence,</l>
                  <l>And Sinne conſpire with Conſcience.</l>
                  <l>This ſpills our Bloud loſt in juſt warrs,</l>
                  <l>And brands with Shame our honeſt Scarrs:</l>
                  <l>His Fathers murder this commends,</l>
                  <l>And crowns it with its plotted ends.</l>
                  <pb n="4" facs="tcp:115706:45"/>
                  <l>His Sacred Perſon this aſſayles,</l>
                  <l>And the dire Regicide entayles.</l>
                  <l>He, the bold Blank defi'd diſcerns,</l>
                  <l>And Malice but his Laughter earns;</l>
                  <l>So what they for freſh liſts deviſe,</l>
                  <l>Into their thin ſhort Kingdome pry's.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>Next he the Realm views in all parts</l>
                  <l>Shut on Him, but the Peoples hearts.</l>
                  <l>While his approach new warmth doth ſhed</l>
                  <l>On thoſe Deſire had maſſacred.</l>
                  <l>His double Righteouſnes all draws</l>
                  <l>That of Himſelf, that of his Cauſe:</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>His Perſon Signatures preſents</l>
                  <l>Where King and Conqueſt pitch their tents;</l>
                  <l>Taller, then Palms, whoſe humble Top,</l>
                  <l>Do's to his lofty Temples ſtoop.</l>
                  <l>And pays a tributary Bough;</l>
                  <l>To bind on his Victorious Brow.</l>
                  <l>Then Beacons plac'd on Mountains, thoſe</l>
                  <l>Mountains which HER late Prince outgrows</l>
                  <pb n="5" facs="tcp:115706:45"/>
                  <l>A valiant Black his Brow doth wear,</l>
                  <l>Our reverence; but Traytours fear:</l>
                  <l>His look ſpeaks out, it was deſign'd,</l>
                  <l>Subjects to conquer, not to find.</l>
                  <l>Which Heat, leſt we ſhould fear his Ray's,</l>
                  <l>The Fathers Clemency allay's;</l>
                  <l>See how our heaving Souls enlarge!</l>
                  <l>See how freſh Spirits our ſtrength ſurcharge!</l>
                  <l>Till in his Banner wrapp'd we prove,</l>
                  <l>Nothing ſo ſtrong as loyall Love:</l>
                  <l>And touch'd from Heaven with holy flame</l>
                  <l>His Throne we plant, his Foes we tame.</l>
               </lg>
            </div>
            <div type="poem">
               <pb facs="tcp:115706:46"/>
               <pb n="7" facs="tcp:115706:46"/>
               <head>
                  <hi>THE REST A<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>RATION.</hi> To Her ſaid Highneſſe,</head>
               <opener>
                  <salute>GReat Princeſſe,</salute>
               </opener>
               <lg>
                  <l>Then the Royall Nun,</l>
                  <l>Shall find her Husband in her Son.</l>
                  <l>And take, ſince mourning weeds muſt ceaſe</l>
                  <l>Beauty and Honour for her dreſſe.</l>
                  <l>Her love impregnable did ſtand,</l>
                  <l>Againſt the Sea, againſt the Land.</l>
                  <l>While her Lord griev'd, ſhe ſcorn'd delight,</l>
                  <l>Companion of his Bed and Flight.</l>
                  <l>She thought it Dutifull to claim</l>
                  <l>A Portion in her Husbands ſhame.</l>
                  <l>Wherefore our ſtreets when ſhe ſhall paſſe,</l>
                  <l>Proud Matrons ſhall empale the wayes:</l>
                  <l>And as ſhe walks her pious Ey's,</l>
                  <l>Our eaſie Dames will Catechize.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>Thy Priſon too ſhall then fly ope,</l>
                  <l>And ripe deliverance kiſſe Hope.</l>
               </lg>
               <pb n="8" facs="tcp:115706:47"/>
               <lg>
                  <l>Here Thy free ſight at large ſhall rove,</l>
                  <l>And Thou if but look up Above,</l>
                  <l>Thy Brother in his Throne ſhalt eye</l>
                  <l>Burniſh't in a full Majeſtie.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>About his Seat at each juſt Hand,</l>
                  <l>A bright Array of Peers ſhall ſtand.</l>
                  <l>Not ſuch who take up their high Name,</l>
                  <l>On credit of ſome dalliant Dame:</l>
                  <l>Theſe in mean Luſts ſpend their cheap Age,</l>
                  <l>Nor ought degen'rate from the Page.</l>
                  <l>Hence, they at rates low as their wit,</l>
                  <l>Can their uſurped Honour quit.</l>
                  <l>For though an Apparition gay,</l>
                  <l>May ruffle in the milky way.</l>
                  <l>Taking acquaintance with the ſtar's,</l>
                  <l>Like one of their familiar Peers:</l>
                  <l>Nay may rant down the leſſer fry,</l>
                  <l>Like Younger Brothers of the sky;</l>
                  <l>And boaſting of his richer light,</l>
                  <l>Firſt Cozen to the Sun ſhould write:</l>
                  <l>Yet if he ſhall his Orb reſigne;</l>
                  <l>Shut up his Windows; ceaſe to ſhine;</l>
                  <pb n="9" facs="tcp:115706:47"/>
                  <l>If his aſſumed Beauty's ſmoot;</l>
                  <l>And through the empty Hollow ſhoot;</l>
                  <l>Scattering all along the air,</l>
                  <l>His periwig of yellow hair;</l>
                  <l>Till he the lower Region plough,</l>
                  <l>And takes his bed up in a ſlough:</l>
                  <l>The Gazer that did late admire</l>
                  <l>His flagrant robes, and Tiſſue fire,</l>
                  <l>That then the Gallant did reherſe</l>
                  <l>Amidſt the ſparkling Courtiers,</l>
                  <l>When he perceivs his borrow'd Lamp</l>
                  <l>With its exhauſted Oyl to damp;</l>
                  <l>Soon tracks the Cheaters ſordid birth</l>
                  <l>From ſome dull Commoner of earth.</l>
                  <l>This Arm o'th ſea of light miſtook,</l>
                  <l>Dry'd up, proves Land-waters and Brook.</l>
                  <l>Our Lords their own clear line make good,</l>
                  <l>Mark'd out by loyall Parents blood,</l>
                  <l>Which the unſpotted Plumes doth lave,</l>
                  <l>That on their Crowned Temples wave:</l>
                  <l>They vouch their True and High Extraction,</l>
                  <l>By conſtant Faith, by noble Action.</l>
               </lg>
               <pb n="10" facs="tcp:115706:48"/>
               <lg>
                  <l>Then let thy meek Affection bow,</l>
                  <l>To view and glad our Realm Below.</l>
                  <l>Here from a Popular bondage freed</l>
                  <l>The Countrey ſhall liſt up her head;</l>
                  <l>The Whip and Yoke now under hoof,</l>
                  <l>She kiſsing the ſoſt rein of love,</l>
                  <l>VVith thankfull mirth aloud ſhall ring,</l>
                  <l>Preferr'd to ſerve her gracious King.</l>
                  <l>Thou ſhalt one ſpotleſſe joy behold,</l>
                  <l>By no allaying ſigh controll'd.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>Thus mark in Halls of great reſort,</l>
                  <l>At Penſhurſt, or ſome Princes Court,</l>
                  <l>If my Lords angry Gentlemen</l>
                  <l>(The Upper Houſe of his great train)</l>
                  <l>Or ſome big Steward ſhall cruſh down</l>
                  <l>His Fellows with perpetuall frown;</l>
                  <l>The Houſe, becauſe he domineers,</l>
                  <l>And Takes upon him o're his Peers,</l>
                  <l>Think the Yoke too hard to be born;</l>
                  <l>Not for the Burden, but the Scorn.</l>
                  <l>When if the wiſer Lady ſoon</l>
                  <l>Spy and remove the grief, anon</l>
                  <pb n="11" facs="tcp:115706:48"/>
                  <l>You may a chearfull duty ſee,</l>
                  <l>Flit through the buſie Family.</l>
                  <l>No Monſter is ſo much abhorr'd,</l>
                  <l>As an Inferiour ſurly lord.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>The Villagers their knees ſhall bow,</l>
                  <l>Not aw'd by a ſtern troopers brow:</l>
                  <l>As Larks upon their Peſtles ſquat,</l>
                  <l>If but one daring Hobby bayt.</l>
                  <l>Nor ſhall this Care their gladnes ſpoyl,</l>
                  <l>How they to be undone muſt toyl.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>The VVealthy Citie ſhall give thanks</l>
                  <l>In decent State, and Rev'rend ranks:</l>
                  <l>Not offring up conſtrained Rites,</l>
                  <l>Amidſt Church-driven Proſelytes.</l>
                  <l>No lip a faint Amen ſhall ſay,</l>
                  <l>VVhile the Recuſant Heart would, Nay.</l>
                  <l>The Heart whoſe penſive ſtrings are wrackt,</l>
                  <l>VVith ſtock decay'd, and credit crackt:</l>
                  <l>For draining taxes more unſluce</l>
                  <l>Their gains, then doth blood-thirſty Uſe.</l>
                  <l>VVhile they a thin ſubſiſtence beat,</l>
                  <l>Manur'd by Perjury and Sweat,</l>
                  <pb n="12" facs="tcp:115706:49"/>
                  <l>Tacking a fortune up, untill</l>
                  <l>Themſelves, the laſt of VVares they ſell,</l>
                  <l>For unſeen ſtarres and Countreys bound,</l>
                  <l>VVhere no Wiſe Parliament is found;</l>
                  <l>For where the ſavage Ethiop fries,</l>
                  <l>No pineond Dragon is ſo Wiſe.</l>
                  <l>Our welcome Exiles home ſhall flee:</l>
                  <l>Our waiting Captives be ſet free.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>From obſcure Denns, from untrackd Caves</l>
                  <l>The retir'd Clere ſhall break their graves:</l>
                  <l>And from Contempt reformd put on</l>
                  <l>Glory and reſurrection.</l>
                  <l>The Sons of VViſdome ſhall releaſe</l>
                  <l>Their patient Spirits into meek peace;</l>
                  <l>Each reaſsuming his old Care,</l>
                  <l>Seated in a becoming Chair;</l>
                  <l>Hoary their Heads, their Tongue diſcreet,</l>
                  <l>Open their Hands, ſpotleſſe their Feet.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>When thou beholdeſt this rich Joy,</l>
                  <l>Embaſed by no ſad Alloy;</l>
                  <l>Then mix thy Note and with one Quire,</l>
                  <l>Let our free Souls in Praiſe aſpire.</l>
               </lg>
            </div>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
      <back>
         <div type="publishers_advertisement">
            <pb facs="tcp:115706:49"/>
            <head>Courteous Reader, Theſe Books following are printed for <hi>Humphrey Moſeley,</hi> and are to be ſold at his Shop at the <hi>Prince's Armes</hi> in St. <hi>Paul</hi>'s Church-yard.</head>
            <div type="list">
               <head>Various Hiſtories, with curious Diſcourſes in Humane Learning, &amp;c.</head>
               <list>
                  <item>1. <hi>DE Bello Belgico,</hi> The Hiſtory of the Low-Country-Warrs, written in La<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tine by <hi>Famianus Strada,</hi> in Engliſh by Sir <hi>Robert Stapylton;</hi> illuſtrated with divers fi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gures, newly printed, in Folio.</item>
                  <item>2. The Hiſtory of the <hi>Baniſhed Virgin,</hi> a Romance, tranſlated by <hi>I. H.</hi> Eſquire, in Fol.</item>
                  <item>3. The Hiſtorie of <hi>Pokxander,</hi> a Romance, Engliſhed by <hi>William Brown</hi> Gent. Printed for <hi>T. W.</hi> and are to bee ſold by <hi>Humphrey Moſeley,</hi> in Fol.</item>
                  <item>4. The uſe of Paſſions, written by <hi>I. F. Senalt,</hi> and put into Engliſh by <hi>Henry</hi> Earl of <hi>Monmouth,</hi> in 8<hi rend="sup">o</hi>.</item>
                  <item>5. Letters between the Lord <hi>George Digby,</hi> and Sir <hi>Kenelm Digby</hi> Knight, concerning Religion, newly printed in 8<hi rend="sup">o</hi>.</item>
                  <item>6. Judicious and Select Eſſaies, and Ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſervations, written by the Renowned and learned Knight, Sir <hi>Walter Raleigh,</hi> with his
<pb facs="tcp:115706:50"/>Apology for his Voyage to <hi>Guiana,</hi> in 8<hi rend="sup">o</hi> newly Printed.</item>
                  <item>7. Vnheard-of Curioſities concerning the Talismanicall Sculpture of the Perſians, the Horoſcope of the Patriarkes and the Judge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of the Starres, by <hi>James Gaffarel;</hi> Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſhed by <hi>Edm. Chilmead,</hi> Ch. Ch <hi>Oxon,</hi> newly printed in 8<hi rend="sup">o</hi>.</item>
                  <item>8. The Compleat Horſeman, and Expert Farrier, in two Books, by <hi>Thomas de Gray</hi> Eſquire, newly printed with Additions, in 4<hi rend="sup">o</hi>.</item>
                  <item>9. Mr. <hi>Iames Howels</hi> Hiſtory of <hi>Lewis</hi> the Thirteenth, King of <hi>France</hi> with the life of his <hi>Cardinall de Richelieu,</hi> in Fol.</item>
                  <item>10. Mr. <hi>Howels Epiſtolae Ho-Elianae,</hi> Fami<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liar Letters, Domeſtick and Forren, in ſix Sections, partly Hiſtoricall, Politicall, Philo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſophicall, the firſt Volume with Additions, in 8<hi rend="sup">o</hi>.</item>
                  <item>11. Mr. <hi>Howels</hi> New volume of Familiar Letters, partly Hiſtoricall, Politicall, Philo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſophicall, the ſecond Volume with many Additions, in 8<hi rend="sup">o</hi>.</item>
                  <item>12. Mr. <hi>Howels</hi> Third Volume of Additional Letters of a freſher date, never before publi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhed, in 8<hi rend="sup">o</hi>.</item>
                  <item>13. Mr. <hi>Howels Dodona's Grove,</hi> ort he <hi>Vo<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>call Foreſt,</hi> the firſt part, in 12<hi rend="sup">o</hi> with many Ad<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ditions.</item>
                  <pb facs="tcp:115706:50"/>
                  <item>14. Mr. <hi>Howels Dodona's Grove,</hi> or the <hi>
                        <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ocall Fo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reſt,</hi> the ſecond part, in 8<hi rend="sup">o</hi> never printed before.</item>
                  <item>15. Mr. <hi>Howels Englands Teares</hi> for the preſent wars.</item>
                  <item>16. Mr. <hi>Howel</hi> of the <hi>Pre-eminence</hi> and Pedegree of Parliament, in 12<hi rend="sup">o</hi>.</item>
                  <item>17. Mr <hi>Howels</hi> Inſtructions and Directions for For<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ren Travels, in 12<hi rend="sup">o</hi> with divers Additions for Travel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling into Turky, and the Levant parts.</item>
                  <item>18. Mr. <hi>Howels</hi> Vote, or a Poem Royall preſented to his Majeſty, in 4<hi rend="sup">o</hi>.</item>
                  <item>19. Mr. <hi>Howels Angliae Suſpiria &amp; lachrymae,</hi> in 12<hi rend="sup">o</hi>.</item>
                  <item>20. <hi>Policy unveiled,</hi> or <hi>Maximes of State,</hi> done into Engliſh by the Tranſlator of <hi>Guſman,</hi> in 4<hi rend="sup">o</hi>.</item>
                  <item>21. The Hiſtory of the <hi>Inquiſition,</hi> compoſed by the <hi>R. F. Paul Servita,</hi> the compiler of the Hiſtory of the. Councill of Trent, in 4<hi rend="sup">o</hi>. tranſlated out of Italian.</item>
                  <item>22. <hi>Biathanatos,</hi> a Paradox of ſelf-homicide, by Dr <hi>Jo: Donne,</hi> Dean of St <hi>Pauls</hi> London, in 4<hi rend="sup">o</hi>.</item>
                  <item>23. <hi>Marques Virgilio Malvezzi</hi>'s <hi>Romulus</hi> and <hi>Tar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quin,</hi> Engliſhed by <hi>Hen.</hi> Eail of <hi>Menmouth,</hi> in 12<hi rend="sup">o</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>24. <hi>Marques Virgilio Malvezzi</hi>'s <hi>David</hi> perſecuted, Engliſhed by <hi>Ro. Aſhley.</hi> Gent. in 12<hi rend="sup">o</hi>.</item>
                  <item>25. <hi>Marques Virgilio Malvezzi,</hi> of the ſucceſs and chief events of the Monarchy of Spain, in the year 1639. of the revolt of the Catalonians from the King of Spain. Engliſhed by <hi>Rob. Gentilis</hi> Gent. in 12<hi rend="sup">o</hi>.</item>
                  <item>26. <hi>Marques Virgilio Malvezzi</hi>'s conſiderations on the lives of <hi>Alcibiades,</hi> and <hi>Coriolanus,</hi> Two famous Roman Commanders Engliſhed by <hi>Rob. Gentilis</hi> Gent. in 12<hi rend="sup">o</hi> newly printed.</item>
                  <item>27. Gracious privileges granted by the King of Spain to our Engliſh Merchants, in 4<hi rend="sup">o</hi>.</item>
                  <item>28. The Hiſtory of Life and Death, or the prolon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gation of Life, written by <hi>Francis</hi> Lord <hi>
                        <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>erulam,</hi> Viſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>count St. <hi>Albans</hi> in 12<hi rend="sup">o</hi>.</item>
                  <pb facs="tcp:115706:51"/>
                  <item>29. The Antipathy between the <hi>French</hi> and the <hi>Spanyard,</hi> an ingenious tranſlation out of Spaniſh, in 12<hi rend="sup">o</hi>.</item>
                  <item>30. Mr. <hi>Birds</hi> grounds of Grammer, in 8<hi rend="sup">o</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>31. Mr. <hi>Bulwers</hi> Philocophus, or the Deaf and Dumb mans friend, in 12<hi rend="sup">o</hi>.</item>
                  <item>32. Mr <hi>Bulwers</hi> Pathomyotomia, or the Diſſection of the ſignificative Muſcles of the Affections of the Mind, in 12<hi rend="sup">o</hi>.</item>
                  <item>33. An Itinerary contayning a voyage made through Italy in the yeares 1646, 1647. illuſtrated with divers Figures of Antiquity, never before pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſhed, by <hi>John Raymond,</hi> Gent in 12<hi rend="sup">o</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>34. A Diſcovery of Subterraneal Treaſure, <hi>viz</hi> of all manner of Mines and Minerals, from the Gold, to the Coal, with plain Directions and Rules for the finding of them in all Kingdoms, and Countreys, written by <hi>Gabriel Plat.</hi> Printed for <hi>I. E.</hi> and are to be ſold by <hi>Humphrey Moſeley,</hi> newly printed. 1653.</item>
               </list>
            </div>
            <div type="list">
               <head>Severall Sermons, with other excellent Tracts in Divinity, written by ſome moſt eminent and learned Biſhops, and Orthodox Divines.</head>
               <list>
                  <item>35 A <hi>Manuall</hi> of private Devotions and Meditations for every day in the week, by the right reverend Father in God, <hi>Lancelet Andrews</hi> late Lord Biſhop of <hi>Wincheſter,</hi> in 24<hi rend="sup">o</hi>. newly printed.</item>
                  <item>36. A <hi>Manuall</hi> of Directions for the Sick, with ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny ſweet Meditations and Devotions, by the right reverend Father in God, <hi>Lancelot Andrews,</hi> late Lord Biſhop of <hi>Wincheſter,</hi> in 24<hi rend="sup">o</hi>, newly printed.</item>
                  <item>37. Ten Sermons upon ſeverall occaſions, preached at St <hi>Pauls Croſs,</hi> and elſwhere, by the right reverend
<pb facs="tcp:115706:51"/>Father in God, <hi>Arthur Lake,</hi> late Lord Biſhop of Bath and Wells, in 4<hi rend="sup">o</hi>.</item>
                  <item>38. Six Sermons upon ſeverall occaſions, preached at Court before the Kings Majeſty, and elſewhere, by that late learned and reverend Divine, <hi>John Donne;</hi> Dr. in Divinity, and Dean of St. <hi>Pauls London,</hi> in 4<hi rend="sup">o</hi>.</item>
                  <item>39 A Key to the Key of Scripture, or an expoſition with notes upon the Epiſtle to the Romans, the three firſt chapters, by <hi>William Sclater,</hi> Dr. in Divinity and Miniſter of the word of God at <hi>Pitmiſter</hi> in <hi>So<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>merſetſhire,</hi> in 4<hi rend="sup">o</hi>.</item>
                  <item>40. Pretious promiſes and priviledges of the faith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full, written by <hi>Richard Sibbs,</hi> Dr in Divinity, late Maſter of <hi>Katharine Hall</hi> in <hi>Cambridge,</hi> and Preacher of <hi>Grayes Inne London,</hi> in 12<hi rend="sup">o</hi>.</item>
                  <item>41. <hi>Sarah</hi> and <hi>Hagar,</hi> or the ſixteenth Chapter of Geneſis opened in nineteen Sermons, being the firſt legitimate Eſſay of the pious labours of that learned, Orthodox, and indefatigable Preacher of the Goſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pell, Mr. <hi>Joſias Shute.</hi> B. D. and above 33 yeares Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctor of St <hi>Mary Woolnoth in Lombardſtreet,</hi> in Folio.</item>
                  <item>42. Chriſts Teares with his love and affection to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards Jeruſalem, delivered in ſundry Sermons upon <hi>Luke</hi> 19. <hi>v.</hi> 41, 42. by <hi>Richard Maden,</hi> B.D. Preacher of the Word of God, late of <hi>Magdalen Colledge in Camb.</hi> in 4<hi rend="sup">o</hi>.</item>
                  <item>43. Ten Sermons preached upon ſeverall Sundays, and Saints dayes, by <hi>Peter Hauſted</hi> Mr. in Arts, and Curate at <hi>
                        <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ppingham</hi> in <hi>Rutland, in</hi> 4<hi rend="sup">o</hi>.</item>
                  <item>44. Eighteen Sermons preached upon the Incar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nation and Nativity of our bleſſed Lord and Savi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>our Jeſus Chriſt, wherein the greateſt myſteries of Godlines are unfolded, to the capacity of the Weak<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eſt Chriſtian, by <hi>John Dawſon <hi>Own.</hi>
                     </hi> in 4<hi rend="sup">o</hi>.</item>
                  <item>45. The Hiſtory of the Defenders of the Faith, diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>courſing the ſtate of Religion in England during
<pb facs="tcp:115706:52"/>the Reign of King <hi>Henry</hi> 8. <hi>Edward</hi> 6. Queen <hi>Mary,</hi> and Queen <hi>Elizabeth.</hi> by <hi>C.L.</hi> in 4<hi rend="sup">o</hi>.</item>
                  <item>46. Chriſtian Divinity, written by <hi>Edmund Reeve</hi> Batchelour in Divinity, in 4<hi rend="sup">o</hi>.</item>
                  <item>47. The Communion-Book Catechiſm expounded by <hi>Edmund Reeve</hi> Batchelour in Divinity, in 4<hi rend="sup">o</hi>.</item>
                  <item>48. The true and abſolute Biſhop, wherein is ſhew<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed how Chriſt is our only Shepheard and Biſhop of our ſoules, by <hi>Nicholas Darton,</hi> Maſter in Arts, in 4<hi rend="sup">o</hi>.</item>
                  <item>49. A deſcription of the New-born Chriſtian, or a lively pattern of the Saint militant, child of God, wrirten by <hi>Nicholas Hunt,</hi> Maſter in Arts, in 4<hi rend="sup">o</hi>.</item>
                  <item>50. Divine Meditations upon the 91. Pſalm, and on The Hiſtory of <hi>Agag</hi> King of <hi>Amalek,</hi> with an Eſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſay of Friendſhip written by an honourable perſon, in 12<hi rend="sup">o</hi>.</item>
                  <item>51. An Hiſtoricall Anatomy of Chriſtian Melan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>choly, by <hi>Edmund Gregory. Oxon.</hi> in 8<hi rend="sup">o</hi>.</item>
                  <item>52. <hi>Lazarus</hi> his Reſt, a Sermon preached at the Funerall of that pious, learned, and Orthodox Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vine, Mr. <hi>Ephraim <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>dall,</hi> by <hi>Thomas Reeve,</hi> Batchelour in Divinity, in 4<hi rend="sup">o</hi>.</item>
                  <item>53. The Survey of Man, in a Sermon as it was delivered by Mr. <hi>John Biſhop</hi> at his Fathers funeral, in 4<hi rend="sup">o</hi>. Printed 1652.</item>
               </list>
            </div>
            <div type="list">
               <head>Choice Poems, with excellent Tranſlations, and incomparable Comedies and Tragedies, written by ſeverall ingenious Authors.</head>
               <list>
                  <item>54 COmedies and Tragedies written by <hi>Francis Beaumont,</hi> and <hi>John Fletcher,</hi> never printed before, and now publiſhed by the Authors Originall Copies, containing 34 plays, and a Maſque, in Fol.</item>
                  <item>55. Epigrammata <hi>Thomae Mori</hi> Angli, in 16<hi rend="sup">o</hi>.</item>
                  <item>56. <hi>Fragmenta Aurea,</hi> A Collection of the incom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>parable
<pb facs="tcp:115706:52"/>Pieces, written by Sr. <hi>John Suckling</hi> Kt. in 8<hi rend="sup">o</hi>.</item>
                  <item>57. All <hi>Juvenals</hi> 16 Satyrs tranſlated by Sr, <hi>Robert Stapylton</hi> wherein is contained a ſurvey of the man<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ners &amp; actions of mankind, with Annotations, in 8<hi rend="sup">o</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>58. <hi>Muſaeus</hi> on the loves of <hi>Hero</hi> and <hi>Leander,</hi> with <hi>Leanders</hi> letter to <hi>Hero,</hi> &amp; her anſwer, taken out of <hi>Ovid,</hi> with Annotations by Sir <hi>Rob. Stapylton,</hi> in 8<hi rend="sup">o</hi>.</item>
                  <item>59. Poems, &amp;c. written by Mr. <hi>Edward Waller</hi> of <hi>Beconsfield</hi> Esq; in 8<hi rend="sup">o</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>60. <hi>Paſtor Fido,</hi> the faithfull Shepheard, a Paſtoral, newly tranſlated out of the Original, by Mr. <hi>Rich. Fanſhaw,</hi> Eſq; in 4<hi rend="sup">o</hi>.</item>
                  <item>61. Poems, with a diſcovery of the Civil Warres of <hi>Rome</hi> by, Mr. <hi>Richard Fanſhaw,</hi> Eſq; in 4<hi rend="sup">o</hi>.</item>
                  <item>62. <hi>Aurora, Iſmenia,</hi> and the Prince, with <hi>Oronta</hi> the Cyprian Virgin, tranſlated by <hi>Thomas Stanly</hi> Eſq; the 2<hi rend="sup">d</hi> Edition corrected and amended, in 8<hi rend="sup">o</hi>.</item>
                  <item>63. <hi>Europa, Cupid</hi> crucified, <hi>Venus</hi> Vigils, with Anno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tations, by <hi>Thomas Stanly,</hi> Eſq; in 8<hi rend="sup">o</hi>.</item>
                  <item>64. <hi>Medea,</hi> a Tragedy written in Latine by <hi>Lucius Annaeus Seneca,</hi> Engliſhed by Mr. <hi>Edward Sherburn</hi> Eſq; with Annotations, in 8<hi rend="sup">o</hi>.</item>
                  <item>65. <hi>Seneca's</hi> anſwer to <hi>Lucilius</hi> his Quaere, why good men ſuffer misfortunes, ſeeing there is a Divine providence, tranſlated into Engliſh verſe by Mr <hi>Ed<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward Sherburn</hi> Eſq; in 8<hi rend="sup">o</hi>.</item>
                  <item>66. Poems of Mr <hi>John Milton,</hi> with a Maſque pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſented at <hi>Ludlow</hi> Caſtle before the Earle of <hi>Bridge-water,</hi> then preſident of <hi>Wales,</hi> in 8<hi rend="sup">o</hi>.</item>
                  <item>67. Poems, &amp;c. with a Maſque called The Triumph of Beauty, by <hi>James Shirley,</hi> Gent. in 8<hi rend="sup">o</hi>.</item>
                  <item>68. Divine Poems, written by <hi>Francis Quarles,</hi> in 8<hi rend="sup">o</hi>.</item>
                  <item>69. The Odes of <hi>Caſimire,</hi> tranſlated by Mr. <hi>George Hills</hi> of <hi>Newark,</hi> in 12<hi rend="sup">o</hi>.</item>
                  <pb facs="tcp:115706:53"/>
                  <item>70. Steps to the Temple, Sacred Poems with the Delights of the Muſes upon ſeveral occaſions, by <hi>Ri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chard Craſhaw</hi> of Cambridge, in 12<hi rend="sup">o</hi>.</item>
                  <item>71. The Miſtris, or ſeveral Copies of Love verſes written by Mr. <hi>Abraham Cowley,</hi> in 8<hi rend="sup">o</hi>.</item>
                  <item>72. <hi>Arnalte</hi> and <hi>Lucenda,</hi> or the melan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>choly Knight, a Poem tranſlated by <hi>L. Lau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rence,</hi> in 4<hi rend="sup">o</hi>.</item>
                  <item>73. The Sophiſter, a Comedy in 4<hi rend="sup">o</hi>. by Dr. <hi>S.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>74. The Woman-hater, or, the Hungry Gourtier, a Comedy written by <hi>Francis Beau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mont,</hi> and <hi>John Fletcher,</hi> Gent. in 4<hi rend="sup">o</hi>.</item>
                  <item>75. The Tragedy of <hi>Thierry</hi> King of <hi>France,</hi> and his brother <hi>Theodoret,</hi> written by <hi>Francis Beaumont,</hi> and <hi>John Fletcher,</hi> Gent. in 4<hi rend="sup">o</hi>.</item>
                  <item>76. The Elder Brother, a Comedy written by <hi>Fran. Beaumont,</hi> &amp; <hi>John Fletcher,</hi> Gent. in 4<hi rend="sup">o</hi>.</item>
                  <item>77. The Scornfull Lady, a Comedy writ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten by <hi>Francis Beaumont,</hi> and <hi>John Fletcher,</hi> Gent. in 4<hi rend="sup">o</hi>.</item>
                  <item>78. <hi>Cupids</hi> Revenge, a Tragedy written by <hi>Francis Beaumont,</hi> and <hi>John Fletcher,</hi> Gent. in 4<hi rend="sup">o</hi>.</item>
                  <item>79. <hi>Monſieur Thomas,</hi> a Comedy written by <hi>Francis Beaumont,</hi> and <hi>John Fletcher,</hi> Gent. in 4<hi rend="sup">o</hi>.</item>
                  <item>80. The two noble Kinſmen, a Comedy written by <hi>Francis Beaumont,</hi> and <hi>John Fletcher,</hi> Gent. in 4<hi rend="sup">o</hi>.</item>
                  <item>81. The Tragedy of <hi>Albovine</hi> King of the
<pb facs="tcp:115706:53"/>
                     <hi>Lombards,</hi> written by <hi>William Davenant,</hi> in 4<hi rend="sup">o</hi>.</item>
                  <item>82. The Juſt <hi>Italian,</hi> written by <hi>VVilliam Davenant,</hi> in 4<hi rend="sup">o</hi>.</item>
                  <item>83. The Cruel Brother, a Tragedy written by <hi>William Davenant,</hi> in 4<hi rend="sup">o</hi>.</item>
                  <item>84. The Unfortunate Lovers, a Tragedy written by <hi>VVilliam Davenant,</hi> in 4<hi rend="sup">o</hi>.</item>
                  <item>85. Love and Honor, a Comedy written by <hi>William Davenant,</hi> in 4<hi rend="sup">o</hi>.</item>
                  <item>86. Madagaſcar, with other Poems, written by <hi>William Davenant,</hi> in 12<hi rend="sup">o</hi>.</item>
                  <item>87. The Countrey Captain, and the Varie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie, two Comedies written by a Perſon of Honour, in 12<hi rend="sup">o</hi>.</item>
                  <item>88. The Contention for Honor and Riches, a Maſque written by <hi>James Shirley,</hi> Gent. in 4<hi rend="sup">o</hi>.</item>
                  <item>89. The Triumph of Peace, a Maſque pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſented by the four honourable Houſes of Inns of Court before the <hi>King,</hi> and <hi>Queens</hi> Maje<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſty at <hi>Whitehall,</hi> 1633, written by <hi>James Shir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ley,</hi> Gent. in 4<hi rend="sup">o</hi>.</item>
                  <item>90. The Dutcheſs of <hi>Malfy,</hi> a Tragedy written by <hi>John Webſter,</hi> Gent. in 4<hi rend="sup">o</hi>.</item>
                  <item>91. Poems written by Mr. <hi>William Shake<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpear,</hi> Gent. in 8<hi rend="sup">o</hi>.</item>
                  <item>92. The Cid, a Tragi-Comedy, tranſlated out of French by <hi>Joſeph Rutter,</hi> Gent. in 12<hi rend="sup">o</hi>.</item>
                  <pb facs="tcp:115706:54"/>
                  <item>93. Allarum to Poets by <hi>I. L.</hi> in 4<hi rend="sup">o</hi>.</item>
                  <item>94. <hi>Fragmenta Poetica,</hi> or Miſcellanies of Poeticall Muſings, by <hi>Nich. Murford,</hi> Gent. in 12<hi rend="sup">o</hi>.</item>
                  <item>95. <hi>Hymnus Tobaci Authore</hi> Raphaele Tho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rio, in 8<hi rend="sup">o</hi>.</item>
                  <item>96. <hi>Hymnus Tobaci,</hi> a Poem in Honour of Tobacco, heroically compoſed by <hi>Raphael Thorius,</hi> made Engliſh by <hi>Peter Hauſted,</hi> Mr. of Arts <hi>Camb.</hi> newly printed in 8<hi rend="sup">o</hi>.</item>
                  <item>97. The Sophy, a Tragedy written by Mr. <hi>Iohn Denham</hi> Eſquire.</item>
                  <item>98. Coopers Hill, a Poem written by Mr. <hi>Iohn Denham</hi> Eſq; The ſecond Edition in 4<hi rend="sup">o</hi>. with Additions.</item>
                  <item>99. Poems, with a Maſque, by <hi>Thomas Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rew</hi> Eſquire, Gentleman of the Privy Cham<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber to his late Majeſty, revived and inlarged with Additions. in 8<hi rend="sup">o</hi>.</item>
                  <item>100. Comedies and Tragedies, with other excellent Poems, by Mr. <hi>William Cartwright,</hi> late Student of Chriſt-Church in <hi>Oxford,</hi> and Proctor of the Univerſity. The Ayres and Songs ſet by Mr. <hi>Henry Laws</hi> ſervant to his late Majeſty in his publick and private Mu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſick, newly printed in 8<hi rend="sup">o</hi>.</item>
                  <item>101. <hi>Claraſtolla,</hi> with other occaſionall Poems, Elegies, Epigrams and Satyrs, written by <hi>R. Heath,</hi> Eſq; in 12<hi rend="sup">o</hi>.</item>
                  <pb facs="tcp:115706:54"/>
                  <item>102. <hi>Olor Iſcanus,</hi> a Collection of ſome ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lect Poems, and Tranſlations, written by Mr. <hi>Henry Vaughan</hi> Siluriſt, newly printed in 8<hi rend="sup">o</hi>.</item>
                  <item>103. The Academy of Complements, wherein Ladies, Gentlewomen, Scholars, and Strangers may accommodate their Courtly practiſe, with Gentile Ceremonies, Comple<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mentall, Amorous, high Expreſſions, and Forms of ſpeaking, or writing of Letters, moſt in faſhion, with Additions of many witty Poems, &amp; pleaſant new Songs, newly printed.</item>
               </list>
            </div>
            <div type="list">
               <head>Books newly printed this preſent year for <hi>Humphrey Moſeley.</hi>
               </head>
               <list>
                  <item>104. THe Pſalms of <hi>David</hi> from the new Tranſlation of the Bible, turned into Metre, to be ſung after the old Tunes uſed in the Churches, by the Right Reverend Father in God, <hi>Henry King</hi> Biſhop of <hi>Chiche<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter,</hi> in 12<hi rend="sup">o</hi>.</item>
                  <item>105. The Life of the moſt Learned Father <hi>Paul,</hi> Author of the Hiſtory of the Council of <hi>Trent,</hi> tranſlated out of <hi>Italian</hi> by a perſon of Quality, in 8<hi rend="sup">o</hi>.</item>
                  <item>106. Choice Muſick for three Voices, and a Thorough Baſe, compoſed by Mr. <hi>Henry,</hi> and Mr. <hi>William Lawes,</hi> brothers, and ſervants to
<pb facs="tcp:115706:55"/>his late Majeſty; with divers Elegies ſet in Muſick by ſeverall Friends upon the death of Mr. <hi>William Lawes,</hi> in 4<hi rend="sup">o</hi>.</item>
                  <item>107. Artificiall Arithmetick, containing the Quinteſſence of the Golden Rule, the true valuation of all Annuities, alſo to finde the diſtance at one ſtation; an Art never till now publiſhed; uſeful for Gunners, Seamen, and Surveyors, by <hi>Rob. Jager,</hi> Gent. in 8<hi rend="sup">o</hi>.</item>
                  <item>108. <hi>Caſſandra,</hi> the fam'd Romance, the three firſt Books written originally in French, &amp; now elegantly rendred into Engliſh by the right honorable the Lord <hi>George Digby,</hi> in 8<hi rend="sup">o</hi>.</item>
                  <item>109. The Hiſtory of <hi>Philoxipes</hi> and <hi>Pol<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>crite,</hi> taken out of <hi>Artamene,</hi> or the Grand <hi>Cyrus;</hi> made Engliſh by an honorable Perſon, in 8<hi rend="sup">o</hi>.</item>
                  <item>110. The Hiſtory of <hi>Don Feniſe,</hi> a new Ro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mance, written in Spaniſh by <hi>Franciſco de las-Coveras,</hi> treating the Severall effects of Love, and Fortune, Engliſhed by a Perſon of Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour, in 8<hi rend="sup">o</hi>.</item>
                  <item>111. <hi>La Stratonica,</hi> or the unfortunate Queen, a new Romance, written in Italian, and now Engliſhed by <hi>I. B.</hi> Gent. in 4<hi rend="sup">o</hi>.</item>
                  <item>112. <hi>Ibrahim,</hi> or the <hi>Illuſtrious Baſſa,</hi> an Excellent new Romance, the Whole Work in four parts, written in <hi>French</hi> by Mounſier <hi>de Scudery,</hi> and now Engliſhed by <hi>Henry C<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>
                        <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gan.</hi> Gent. in Fol.</item>
                  <pb facs="tcp:115706:55"/>
                  <item>113. <hi>Caſſandra,</hi> the fam'd Romance, the whole Work in five parts, written originally in <hi>French,</hi> and now Elegantly rendred into Engliſh by a Perſon of quality, in Fol.</item>
                  <item>114. <hi>Cleopatra,</hi> a new Romance, written in <hi>French</hi> by the Fam'd Author of <hi>Caſsandra,</hi> and now Engliſhed by a Gen. of the Inner Temple</item>
                  <item>115. The Wild-Gooſe-Chaſe, a Comedy written by <hi>Fran. Beaumont</hi> &amp; <hi>I. Fletcher,</hi> Gent.</item>
                  <item>116. The Widow, a Comedy written by <hi>Een. Johnſon, Iohn Fletcher,</hi> &amp; <hi>Thomas Midleton.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>117. The Soveraignty of the Britiſh Seas, written by that learned Knight Sir <hi>John Bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>roughes</hi> Keeper of the Records in the <hi>Tower.</hi>
                  </item>
               </list>
            </div>
            <div type="list">
               <head>Books printed this Tearm for <hi>Humphrey Moſeley.</hi>
               </head>
               <list>
                  <item>118. Poems and tranſlations, the Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pleat Workes of <hi>Thomas Stanley</hi> Eſquire, in 8<hi rend="sup">o</hi>. 1653.</item>
                  <item>119. Herodian of <hi>Alexandria</hi> his Imperial Hiſtory of twenty Roman <hi>Caeſars</hi> and <hi>Empe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rors</hi> of his time, firſt written in <hi>Greek,</hi> now converted into an Heroick Poem by <hi>C. B. Stapleton</hi> in 4<hi rend="sup">o</hi>. 1653.</item>
                  <item>120. <hi>Grammatica Burleſa,</hi> or a new Engliſh Grammer, made plain and eaſie for Teacher and Scholar, compoſed by <hi>Edward Burles</hi> Mr. of Arts and School-maſter at <hi>Eaſt-Acton</hi> in Midleſex, in 12<hi rend="sup">o</hi>. 1653.</item>
                  <pb facs="tcp:115706:56"/>
                  <item>121. <hi>Sions Proſpect</hi> in its firſt view, preſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted in a Summary of Divine truths, conſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting with the faith profeſſed by the <hi>Church</hi> of <hi>England,</hi> confirmed from Scripture and Reaſon, compoſed by Mr. <hi>Ro. Moſſom</hi> Miniſter.</item>
                  <item>122. <hi>Quaeſtio Quodlibetica,</hi> or a diſcourſe whether it be lawfull to take <hi>
                        <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ſe</hi> for <hi>Money,</hi> by <hi>R. F.</hi> Knight in 12<hi rend="sup">o</hi>. 1653.</item>
                  <item>123. Hiſtorical Relations of the Vnited Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vinces of <hi>Flanders,</hi> written in <hi>Italian</hi> by <hi>Car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinall Bentivoglio,</hi> and now rendred into Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſh by the Right Honorable <hi>Henry</hi> Earl of <hi>Monmouth,</hi> in Fol. 1653.</item>
                  <item>124. Choice Novels and Amorous <hi>Tales,</hi> written by the moſt refined witts of <hi>Italy,</hi> newly tranſlated into Engliſh by a Perſon of Quality, in 8<hi rend="sup">o</hi>. 1653.</item>
                  <item>125. <hi>Niſſena,</hi> an excellent new Romance, written Orignally in <hi>Italian,</hi> and now Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſhed by an Honorable Perſon, in 8<hi rend="sup">o</hi>. 1653.</item>
                  <item>126. The Changeling, written by <hi>Thomas Middleton</hi> and <hi>W. Rowley,</hi> Gent. in 4<hi rend="sup">o</hi>. 1653.</item>
                  <item>127. Paradoxes, Problems, Characters &amp;c. by Dr. <hi>Donne</hi> D. of St. <hi>Paul's,</hi> to which is added a Book of Epigrams, written in Latin by the ſame Author; tranſlated by <hi>Jaſper Main D. D.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>128. <hi>Ignatius</hi> his Conclave a Satyr written by Dr. <hi>Donne</hi> Dean of St <hi>Paules.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>129. Eſſayes in Divinity by Dr. <hi>Donne</hi> D. of St. <hi>Paul's,</hi> before he entred into <hi>holy Orders.</hi>
                  </item>
               </list>
            </div>
            <div type="list">
               <pb facs="tcp:115706:56"/>
               <head>Theſe Books I have now in the Preſſe, ready to come forth.</head>
               <list>
                  <item>130. Six new Playes, <hi>viz.</hi>
                     <list>
                        <item>The BROTHERS.</item>
                        <item>The SISTERS.</item>
                        <item>The DOUBTFULL HEIR.</item>
                        <item>The IMPOSTURE.</item>
                        <item>The CARDINALL.</item>
                        <item>The COURT SECRET.</item>
                     </list> By <hi>James Shirley,</hi> Gent. in 8<hi rend="sup">o</hi>. Being all that ever the Author made for the Private houſe in <hi>Black-Fryers.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>131. The Sinners Teares in Meditations and Prayers, by <hi>Thomas Fettiplace</hi> of <hi>Peterhouſe Cam<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>.</hi> in 12<hi rend="sup">o</hi>.</item>
                  <item>132. The Naturall and experimentall <hi>Hi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtory</hi> of <hi>Winds</hi> written in Latine by the right Honorable <hi>Francis Lord Verulam Viſcount St. Alban,</hi> tranſlated into Engliſh by an admirer of the learned Author, in 12<hi rend="sup">o</hi>.</item>
                  <item>133. The Card of Courtſhip, or the Lan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>grees, Sexes, and Conditions, in 12<hi rend="sup">o</hi>. 1653. guage of Love, fitted to the Humors of all De-</item>
                  <item>134. <hi>Renatus des Cartes's</hi> Excellent Compen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dium of Muſick with Neceſſary and Judici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous Animadverſions Thereupon by a Perſon of Honor, <hi>Illuſtrated with divers figures.</hi> 1653.</item>
                  <item>135. Naturall &amp; divine Contemplations of the Paſſions and facultyes of the ſoul of man in three books, written by <hi>Nicholas, Moſley</hi> Eſq;</item>
               </list>
            </div>
            <div type="list">
               <pb facs="tcp:115706:57"/>
               <head>Theſe Bookes I doe purpoſe to Print very Speedily.</head>
               <list>
                  <item>136. THe Hiſtory of the Warres of the Emperour <hi>Iuſtinian</hi> with the <hi>Perſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans, Goths,</hi> and <hi>Vandalls,</hi> written in Greek by <hi>Procopius</hi> of <hi>Caeſarea,</hi> in eight books, tranſla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted into Engliſh by Sir <hi>Henry Holtcraft,</hi> Kt.</item>
                  <item>137. The Hiſtory of the Kingdome of <hi>Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ples,</hi> with a large and exact Deſcription of the Scituation, Quality, &amp; nature of the Country, the Manners and Conditions of the People, with the famous Antiquityes, and the worthy men that have lived therein, &amp;c. Compoſed by the moſt Elaborate care of <hi>Sampſon Len<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nard,</hi> Eſquier.</item>
                  <item>138. <hi>Poemata Graeca &amp; Latina, à Gulielmo Cartwright, è</hi> C. C. <hi>Oxon.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>139. <hi>Le Chemin Abrege,</hi> or a Diſcourſe for the attaining of Sciences in a ſhort time, with the Statutes of the <hi>Academy</hi> of the <hi>Cardinall Richelieu,</hi> tranſlated out of French.</item>
                  <item>140. The Secretary in <hi>Faſhion,</hi> or a Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pendious and refined way of Expreſſion in all manner of <hi>Letters,</hi> compoſed in <hi>French</hi> by <hi>P. Sr. de la Serre</hi> augmented with inſtructions how to write Letters, moreover a Collection of 26 <hi>Choice moral Letters,</hi> written by the moſt <hi>refined wits</hi> of this <hi>age,</hi> alſo the Complements of the <hi>French tongue</hi> newly tranſlated into <hi>En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gliſh</hi> by a Perſon of Quality.</item>
               </list>
               <pb facs="tcp:115706:57"/>
            </div>
         </div>
      </back>
   </text>
</TEI>
