<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Aminta: the famous pastoral. / Written in Italian by Signor' Torquato Tasso. And translated into English verse by John Dancer. Together with divers ingenious poems.</title>
            <title>Aminta. English</title>
            <author>Tasso, Torquato, 1544-1595.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1660</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 183 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 78 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2012-10">2012-10 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A94684</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing T172</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Thomason E1836_2</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R203743</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99863579</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99863579</idno>
            <idno type="VID">115787</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A94684)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 115787)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Thomason Tracts ; 229:E1836[2])</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>Aminta: the famous pastoral. / Written in Italian by Signor' Torquato Tasso. And translated into English verse by John Dancer. Together with divers ingenious poems.</title>
                  <title>Aminta. English</title>
                  <author>Tasso, Torquato, 1544-1595.</author>
                  <author>Dancer, John, fl. 1660-1675.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[16], 134, [10] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed for John Starkey, at the Miter, near the Middle Temple-gate in Fleet-street.,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London, :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1660.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>In verse.</note>
                  <note>The first leaf is blank.</note>
                  <note>With four final advertisement leaves; the last leaf is blank.</note>
                  <note>Annotation on Thomason copy: "June".</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the British Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Tasso, Torquato, 1544-1595. --  Aminta. --  Translations into English.</term>
               <term>Italian poetry --  16th century --  Translations.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2011-10</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-10</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-12</date>
            <label>Louis Goldberg</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-12</date>
            <label>Louis Goldberg</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-05</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:115787:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>AMINTA: The <hi>FAMOUS PASTORAL.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Written in Italian BY <hi>Signor Torquato Taſſo.</hi> And Tranſlated into Engliſh Verſe BY <hi>John Dancer.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Together with divers Ingenious POEMS.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON,</hi> Printed for <hi>John Starkey,</hi> at the Miter, near the Middle Temple-gate in <hi>Fleet-ſtreet.</hi> 1660.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="dedication">
            <pb facs="tcp:115787:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:115787:2"/>
            <head>TO My much Honoured, AND Truely Noble Friend, Mr. <hi>R. B.</hi>
            </head>
            <opener>
               <salute>Worthy Sir,</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>ANcient cuſtom, and the <hi>genius</hi> of the preſent times admit a dedication of thoſe works which we eſteem
<pb facs="tcp:115787:3"/>either <hi>profitable</hi> or <hi>pleaſant</hi> to thoſe we <hi>love</hi> or <hi>honour,</hi> this though it pretend little to profit, and as little to pleaſure without your <hi>pleaſing aſpect,</hi> yet is intended as a <hi>demonſtration</hi> of that <hi>honor</hi> and <hi>reſpect</hi> I bear your <hi>worth:</hi> which your favours to me have <hi>condignly</hi> merited.</p>
            <p>And to whom indeed ſhould I <hi>dedicate</hi> both my ſelf and labours? but to you, who have ſeemed to <hi>dedicate</hi> your ſelf wholly to my welfare? to whom ſhould I preſent theſe effects of my <hi>leiſure?</hi> but to you, by and from whom I recei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved ſo comfortable an <hi>olium?</hi> to whom ſhould I addreſs, or whoſe
<pb facs="tcp:115787:3"/>
               <hi>protection</hi> ſhould I crave for this work of mine? but his under whoſe <hi>protection I</hi> effected it?</p>
            <p>Yet pretend <hi>I</hi> not at all by this the <hi>least</hi> requital of your unlimited favours, which have encompaſſed me round like an <hi>Ocean,</hi> but onely manifeſt to you, what <hi>I</hi> am almoſt con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fident you already believe; that, were my <hi>fortunes</hi> anſwer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able to my <hi>deſires,</hi> though your <hi>retorted</hi> Graces might, and would ſtill keep me out of the <hi>haven,</hi> yet ſhould <hi>I</hi> uſe my utmoſt ſtrength and en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deavours to arrive at the <hi>Port</hi> of a wiſh'd for gratitude.</p>
            <pb facs="tcp:115787:4"/>
            <p>In the mean time, pleaſe Sir to accept of this poor pledge of my <hi>weak,</hi> though <hi>willing,</hi> endeavours; and in thanks for your acceptance, this I really aſſure you, That though your <hi>protection</hi> ſhould not render it more <hi>acceptable</hi> to others, yet will it more and more <hi>oblige</hi> me, and like a <hi>Cypher</hi> added to a <hi>figure,</hi> double, if not treble, the <hi>ſcore</hi> of your favours.</p>
            <p>For the work it ſelf, let me make this Apologie, <hi>That you know it to be the firſt that ever I un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dertook:</hi> ſo, for thoſe faults which you may very probably find in it, I ſhal only implore that wonted
<pb facs="tcp:115787:4"/>Candour and Generoſity where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>with you have oft been pleaſ'd to paſs by leſſe pardonable errors.</p>
            <p>I am ſorry your <hi>Commands con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceale</hi> your Name, and muſt needs herein accuſe you of ſome <hi>Inju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtice,</hi> both to <hi>my ſelfe</hi> and the <hi>World;</hi> to my ſelfe, in not gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving my Pen the Honour to <hi>Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>claime,</hi> not only yours, but the Virtues of your <hi>Thrice Noble</hi> Family; And to the World, in not permitting them to be <hi>Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nourers</hi> and <hi>Admirers</hi> of ſo rare a Pattern of <hi>Unparallel'd</hi> Freind<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip.</p>
            <p>To conclude. That the <hi>God of Heaven</hi> would plentifully poure
<pb facs="tcp:115787:5"/>down the choiſeſt of his bleſſings upon you and your Worthy Conſort, and enable you to the <hi>Continuance</hi> of your favours to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards me; and me to ſome way to <hi>Merit,</hi> or meanes to <hi>Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quite them.</hi> Is the earneſt Prayer of</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>Your Devoted Servant John Dancer.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="to_the_reader">
            <pb facs="tcp:115787:5"/>
            <head>To The READER:</head>
            <opener>
               <salute>Curteous Reader,</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>
               <hi>I</hi> Here preſent to thy view, a Work of that Excellent <hi>I<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>talian</hi> Poet's, <hi>Torquato Taſſo,</hi> Whoſe ſweet and Melli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fluous ſtraines, made him not on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly eſteem'd the <hi>Apollo</hi> of his
<pb facs="tcp:115787:6"/>Nation, but thought worthy that Honour by Frreign Wits. This is his <hi>Aminta;</hi> a Piece Valued by themoſt Refined Judge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments above all his other <hi>Po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ems:</hi> and ſo much Valued, That the admired <hi>Baptiſta Guarini</hi> confeſſes himſelfe its Imitator, in his Famous, and ſo much Adored <hi>Paſtor Fido.</hi> If it have ſuffered by my Tranſlati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, I am ſorry. I muſt con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſe I envyed, but cannot fancy to have reach'd the Happineſſe of <hi>Fanſhaw</hi>'s Stile. 'Tis the firſt Work ever I undertook, ſo, though there may be errors, condemn me not for the firſt fault, the
<pb facs="tcp:115787:6"/>next may be better; hower accept this, as it is, but Friendly, and I have enough.</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>J. D.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="prologue">
            <pb facs="tcp:115787:7"/>
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:115787:7"/>
            <head>Prologue.</head>
            <lg>
               <head>Cupid in Paſtoral habit.</head>
               <l>HOw could it enter into mortall breaſt:</l>
               <l>That under humane ſhape, and paſt'ral veſt,</l>
               <l>Lay hid a god? nay more, no god o'th woods,</l>
               <l>Or one of the inferiour rank of gods,</l>
               <l>A god Celeſtial: who doth juſtly claim,</l>
               <l>Among the greateſt the moſt powerful name:</l>
               <l>Who often makes victorious <hi>Mars</hi> to lay</l>
               <l>His conquering ſword, and bloody ſpear away.</l>
               <l>Great <hi>Neptune</hi> who ſo fils the world with wonder,</l>
               <l>Yeilds him his trident; <hi>Jove</hi> himſelf his thunder.</l>
               <l>Sure with this aſpect, in this habit clad,</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Venus</hi> can ne're diſcern her ſmooth-fac'd lad,</l>
               <l>Or know him thus transform'd. I'm forc'd to fly,</l>
               <l>And hide my ſelf from her, becauſe that I</l>
               <pb n="2" facs="tcp:115787:8"/>
               <l>Scorn for to be her ſubject, or my darts</l>
               <l>Should be her ſlaves: and only wound thoſe hearts</l>
               <l>They're levell'd at by her, and what's that vain,</l>
               <l>Ambitious woman dare my ſhafts reſtrain?</l>
               <l>At Kings and Princes Courts ſhe only will</l>
               <l>That 'mongſt great Ladies I employ my skill,</l>
               <l>And to my lower Miniſters conceads</l>
               <l>To practice theirs amongſt the woods and Meads,</l>
               <l>In ruſtick breaſts. I though you may me deem</l>
               <l>A boy, am none, and will, as beſt ſhall ſeem</l>
               <l>To me, diſpoſe my ſhafts, ſince mine of old</l>
               <l>Are both th'omnipotent torch, and bow of gold:</l>
               <l>Wherefore (to hide my ſelf and to fly from</l>
               <l>Her force, not, but her prayrs ſtrong when they come</l>
               <l>From an importunate mother) in theſe plains,</l>
               <l>I refuge ſeek amongſt the rurall ſwains,</l>
               <l>And my ſelf ſhelter in theſe woods, but ſhe</l>
               <l>Ceaſes nor day nor night to follow me,</l>
               <l>Promiſing thoſe would tell her where I were</l>
               <l>Or kiſſes ſweet, or what's than them more dear:</l>
               <l>As if that ſhe my giving too could bar</l>
               <l>Of kiſſes ſweet, or what's more pleaſant far,</l>
               <l>To thoſe that hide me from her, this at leaſt;</l>
               <l>I know my kiſſes will be counted beſt:</l>
               <l>(If I that love am of love underſtand)</l>
               <l>So that ſhe oft ſeeks for me vainly, and</l>
               <l>Looſes her pains: Since none ſo fooliſh are,</l>
               <l>As to diſcloſe or tell her where I were.</l>
               <l>But leaſt by counter ſigns ſhe ſhould me know,</l>
               <l>My wings, my dart, my quiver, and my bow,</l>
               <pb n="3" facs="tcp:115787:8"/>
               <l>I have laid by, yet come not I diſarm'd,</l>
               <l>Or weaponleſſe, for ſee how I have charm'd</l>
               <l>My torch into this rod; which has the ſame</l>
               <l>Force it had firſt, and burns though with a flame</l>
               <l>Inviſible, this likewiſe is my old</l>
               <l>Dart that I uſ'd, which though its head of gold</l>
               <l>Be chang'd, yet this of divine temper'd ſteel</l>
               <l>Who er'e it pierces makes loves flames to feel.</l>
               <l>This day I'l make the triall; and my dart</l>
               <l>Shall ſhew its divine power o're the heart.</l>
               <l>Leſſe boſome of the cruel'ſt nymph before</l>
               <l>This time that ever followed <hi>Dians</hi> Chore,</l>
               <l>And chaſteſt <hi>Silvia</hi>'s plague ſhall be the ſame,</l>
               <l>(For that's of this hard-hearted Nymph the name,)</l>
               <l>As that of fam'd <hi>Aminta,</hi> who did feel</l>
               <l>Long ſince, the pow'r of my Divineſt ſteel;</l>
               <l>When he and ſhe both tender us'd to ſport,</l>
               <l>In the chaſt pleaſures of bright <hi>Cynthia</hi>'s Court.</l>
               <l>But cauſe the wound ſhall be more inward, I</l>
               <l>Will ſtay untill ſome pitie mollifie</l>
               <l>That ſo hard froſt which round about her heart</l>
               <l>Her virgin-pride hath fix'd, then I'l my dart</l>
               <l>Let fly with it's full force; and cauſe I'l pleaſe</l>
               <l>My ſelf in doing it, and do't with eaſe,</l>
               <l>I'l mix my ſelf among the ſhepheards crew</l>
               <l>Which paſſed by juſt now, who alwaies do</l>
               <l>On holydayes make ſport within this plain,</l>
               <l>And to be one of them my ſelf I'l fain;</l>
               <l>Then with the best occaſion give the blow,</l>
               <l>So ſlyly, as no mortall eye ſhal't know.</l>
               <pb n="4" facs="tcp:115787:9"/>
               <l>In a ſtrange manner ſhall theſe woods, to day,</l>
               <l>Be heard of love to reaſon, that it may,</l>
               <l>Clearly (my ſacred Deity is here)</l>
               <l>(And not my under Miniſters) appear.</l>
               <l>Theſe ruſtick <hi>Silvane</hi> breſts I will endue</l>
               <l>With divine ſences, teach them how to wooe</l>
               <l>In lofty language, that it may be known</l>
               <l>That love where e're he is, is alwaies one,</l>
               <l>Whether he pleaſes for to make his neſt</l>
               <l>Or in a Swains, or in a Hero's breaſt.</l>
               <l>Then if my beauteous mother, who ha's tride</l>
               <l>Her utmoſt art to know where I abide</l>
               <l>By theſe feats know not, ſhe's more blind then I</l>
               <l>For blind by wrong, men call my Deity.</l>
            </lg>
         </div>
         <div type="play">
            <pb n="5" facs="tcp:115787:9"/>
            <head>TASSO'S AMINTA.</head>
            <div type="act">
               <head>Act. 1.</head>
               <div n="1" type="scene">
                  <head>Scen. I.</head>
                  <stage>
                     <hi>Daphne</hi> and <hi>Silvia.</hi>
                  </stage>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Daph.</speaker>
                     <l>ARt thou reſolv'd then <hi>Silvia</hi> to conſume</l>
                     <l>Thy faireſt youth? can't thy heart find a room</l>
                     <l>For <hi>Venus</hi> pleaſures? wilt not know thoſe joy's</l>
                     <l>A Mother takes to ſport with her ſweet boyes?</l>
                     <l>Shall ſo much beauty be to woods confin'd?</l>
                     <pb n="6" facs="tcp:115787:10"/>
                     <l>Change, fondling that thou art, change, change thy mind.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Sil.</speaker>
                     <l>Let others follow loves delights for me,</l>
                     <l>If that in love any delight there be.</l>
                     <l>This life me pleaſes beſt; Nor do I know</l>
                     <l>Ought I take pleaſure in, but in my bow;</l>
                     <l>This is my chiefeſt comfort, for to follow</l>
                     <l>The wild beaſts in the chaſe, hear huntſmen hollow:</l>
                     <l>Nor do I fear ſuch ſports will wanting be.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Da.</speaker>
                     <l>More ſottiſh ſports, more ſottiſh life, doſt ſee?</l>
                     <l>This life thee pleaſes cauſe thou haſt not prov'd</l>
                     <l>As yet another, cauſe thou haſt not lov'd.</l>
                     <l>"So in the infant world, and when as yet,</l>
                     <l>"The ſimple people knew no better meat,</l>
                     <l>"Acorns and water, were accounted ſweet:</l>
                     <l>"But when th'earth did abound with corn and wine,</l>
                     <l>"Acorns and water then were food for ſwine.</l>
                     <l>So ſhouldſt thou taſte but one poor thouſand part</l>
                     <l>Of the ſweet joys of love, thou'dſt ſay, dear heart,</l>
                     <l>Why didſt thou ſix my pleaſure on ſuch toyes</l>
                     <l>And leave me widow to more reall joyes?</l>
                     <l>Thou'lt ſorrowfull repent the loſt time paſt</l>
                     <l>And curſe it now for running on ſo faſt.</l>
                     <l>How many a widow night, how many a day</l>
                     <l>I've ignorantly ſpent! thou'lt ſighing ſay.</l>
                     <l>Change then, ſond fool, change change thy mind I pray,</l>
                     <l>Leſt when'ts too late thou do repent in vain</l>
                  </sp>
                  <pb n="7" facs="tcp:115787:10"/>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Sil.</speaker>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Daphne,</hi> when I repent or o're again</l>
                     <l>Repeat theſe words of thine, w<hi rend="sup">ch</hi> thou doſt feign'</l>
                     <l>Juſt as thou liſt, then let the rivers turn</l>
                     <l>Back to their fountains; let the Ocean burn,</l>
                     <l>The wolves fly from the tender lamo, the hares</l>
                     <l>Purſue the greyhounds; then let the fierce bears,</l>
                     <l>Inhabit waters: and let dolphins range</l>
                     <l>The fields, whenever I my mind do change.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Daph.</speaker>
                     <l>This is meer childiſhneſs, Siſter, as thou</l>
                     <l>Art, I was once. (Alas!) although that now</l>
                     <l>I'me chang'd by age, even juſt ſo neat, ſo fair</l>
                     <l>My count'nance was, ſo golden was my hair,</l>
                     <l>Juſt ſuch a cherry lip, juſt ſuch a Roſe,</l>
                     <l>I did in th'middle of my cheek diſcloſe;</l>
                     <l>'Twas my delight, then, Silvia, (now I find</l>
                     <l>A fooliſh one it was) to hunt the Hind,</l>
                     <l>Follow the footſteps of wild beaſts, my net</l>
                     <l>Spread to untrap the birds, take care to whet</l>
                     <l>My dart; and if I did but chance to ſpy</l>
                     <l>Some youthfull Shepheard caſt an am'rous eye,</l>
                     <l>I looked down with ſcorn, and with diſdain,</l>
                     <l>Counting what was my grace to be my pain,</l>
                     <l>And nought was more diſpleaſing unto me</l>
                     <l>Then ſee me pleaſing unto others be:</l>
                     <l>But yet at length, time and th'importunate</l>
                     <l>Pray'rs of my faithful lover, did abate</l>
                     <l>That Virgin froſt, Siſter, I was (and bleſſe</l>
                     <l>The hour) o'recome at laſt, I do confeſſe,</l>
                     <l>And in one night's black ſhade I did learn more</l>
                     <l>Then I had done in all my life before:</l>
                     <pb n="8" facs="tcp:115787:11"/>
                     <l>So now I did my former folly know,</l>
                     <l>I quite renounc'd both <hi>Cynthia</hi>'s; life and bow:</l>
                     <l>And ſo I hope thou wilt too, and at laſt</l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Aminta</hi>'s ſighs may melt thy flinty breaſt.</l>
                     <l>How canſt thou chooſe but love him? canſt deny</l>
                     <l>He's handſom? then pray tell the reaſon, why?</l>
                     <l>Thinkſt thou he loves thee not? or does love any</l>
                     <l>Better than thee, though he be lov'd by many?</l>
                     <l>If ſo, why do's he ſo thy love purſue?</l>
                     <l>Think'ſt him not enough noble? if thou do</l>
                     <l>Though from this Rivers god the third thou be,</l>
                     <l>Third from great <hi>Pan</hi> the ſhepherds god is he.</l>
                     <l>Why then deſpi'ſt thou him? thinkſt thou the lilies</l>
                     <l>Of the fair cheeks of faireſt <hi>Amarillis,</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>Are not as beautiful as thine? yet he</l>
                     <l>Thou ſeeſt deſpiſeth her, and follows thee;</l>
                     <l>She follows him and ſeeks his love, and thou,</l>
                     <l>Though he ſeeks thine, refuſeſt his; pray now</l>
                     <l>Imagine, he, thus croſt by thy diſdain</l>
                     <l>(God grant th'imagination be but vain)</l>
                     <l>Should leave thee and take her, I fain would know</l>
                     <l>Whether it would not grieve thee yea or no?</l>
                     <l>'Tis better to accept him then, by half,</l>
                     <l>Then taking her both at thy folly laugh.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Sil.</speaker>
                     <l>Let <hi>'minta</hi> and his loves diſpoſed be,</l>
                     <l>As beſt him pleaſeth little't imports me:</l>
                     <l>Nor who his love has, ſo I do it miſſe,</l>
                     <l>Care I, mine he can't be, ſince I'me not his:</l>
                     <l>And though he mine were, his I would not be.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <pb n="9" facs="tcp:115787:11"/>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Daph.</speaker>
                     <l>From whence proceeds this hatred now from thee?</l>
                     <l>If I were thee I'd ſtrive to love him rather.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Sil.</speaker>
                     <l>It's from his love.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Daph.</speaker>
                     <l>Strange child of ſuch a Father,</l>
                     <l>When was fierce tyger born of gentle lamb?</l>
                     <l>Or when from Swan's egge a black crow e're came?</l>
                     <l>Siſter thou cheateſt or thy ſelf or me.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Sil.</speaker>
                     <l>I hate his love, cauſe he my honeſty:</l>
                     <l>And I ſhould love him while he would not crave</l>
                     <l>Ought elſe of me but what my ſelf would have,</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Daph.</speaker>
                     <l>Thou onely wil'ſt thy hurt, he only would</l>
                     <l>Wiſh that to thee which wiſh himſelf he ſhould:</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Sil.</speaker>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Daphne,</hi> or talk of ſomewhat elſe, or hold</l>
                     <l>Thy peace I pray.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Daph.</speaker>
                     <l>O gods! do but behold</l>
                     <l>This perverſe wench! but prethee Siſter do,</l>
                     <l>But anſwer this, If that another ſue</l>
                     <l>Should for thy love, would'ſt thus requite his pain?</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Sil.</speaker>
                     <l>Who would entrap my chaſtity, the ſame</l>
                     <l>Requite ſhould find from me, what e're he be,</l>
                     <l>Whom thou ſtil'ſt lover, I am enemy.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Daph.</speaker>
                     <l>The Ram unto the ewe doſt thou eſteem</l>
                     <l>Or to the tender heifer the bull deem,</l>
                     <l>En'mies to be, or doth the Turtle dove</l>
                     <l>Reject her mate, becauſe he doth her love:</l>
                     <l>Seeſt thou the fragrant ſeaſon of the year,</l>
                     <l>How every thing doth ſweet and green appear?</l>
                     <l>This pleaſant verdure covering o're the plains,</l>
                     <pb n="10" facs="tcp:115787:12"/>
                     <l>Invites, alas, not only nymphs and Swains,</l>
                     <l>But very beaſts to love, and doſt not ſee,</l>
                     <l>How all things in the world inamoured be?</l>
                     <l>See how thoſe two doves whiſper, with what willing,</l>
                     <l>And joynt conſent as 'twere they two are billing!</l>
                     <l>You Nightingale which hops from grove to grove</l>
                     <l>Still as ſhe hops, ſhe ſings, I love, I love;</l>
                     <l>The cruell Adder who doth ſtop his ears.</l>
                     <l>And having ſtung, will not be charm'd by tears,</l>
                     <l>Or cries, is charm'd by ſweeteſt love: 'ith woods</l>
                     <l>The tigers love, the fiſhes in the floods</l>
                     <l>Love too, but thou more cruel then a beaſt</l>
                     <l>Denyeſt ſweet love an entrance in thy breaſt;</l>
                     <l>But what talk I of beaſts; ſeeſt thou each tree</l>
                     <l>In this vaſt forreſt? they inamoured be.</l>
                     <l>Behold with what a ſweet embrace the vine</l>
                     <l>Does her dear conſort lovingly intwine,</l>
                     <l>The firr doth love the firr, the pine the pine;</l>
                     <l>You ſtubborn oak, which ſcarce the wind can move,</l>
                     <l>Is mov'd by th'power of divineſt love,</l>
                     <l>Hadſt thou a ſpir't of love, or if of ſtone,</l>
                     <l>Were not thy heart, thou'dſt hear it ſigh and groan,</l>
                     <l>And utter forth it's am'rous plaints: yet thou</l>
                     <l>For all this art not mov'd to love, why now</l>
                     <l>Wilt thou than plants or beaſts be more unkind?</l>
                     <l>Change, fondling that thou art, change, change thy mind:</l>
                  </sp>
                  <pb n="11" facs="tcp:115787:12"/>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Sil.</speaker>
                     <l>When I of plants the am'rous ſighs ſhal hear</l>
                     <l>I'l likewiſe be in love, til then forbear.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Daph.</speaker>
                     <l>Well though thou now laugh at, and doſt diſdain</l>
                     <l>My faithful counſels; know that to thy pain</l>
                     <l>Thou wilt repent, thou doſt not while thou may</l>
                     <l>Them follow; for be ſure there comes a day,</l>
                     <l>When what's to thee a pleaſure and delight,</l>
                     <l>Shall be thy greateſt grief, thy greateſt ſpight;</l>
                     <l>And as thou now diſdaineſt others, ſo,</l>
                     <l>Thou'lt then deſpiſe thy very ſelf; and know</l>
                     <l>Thoſe ſo clear ſprings in which thou oft doſt uſe</l>
                     <l>Thy moſt reſplendent beauty to peruſe,</l>
                     <l>Thou'lt leave forſaken and neglected now,</l>
                     <l>Or ſtand amazed at thy wrinkled brow</l>
                     <l>But why ſpeak I of this? ſince 'tis a ſure</l>
                     <l>And common evil we muſt all endure:</l>
                     <l>I'l tell thee more, and mark me what I ſay,</l>
                     <l>'Tis what the ſage <hi>Elpino</hi> t'other day</l>
                     <l>Recounted unto <hi>Licoris</hi> the fair</l>
                     <l>The gentile <hi>Licoris:</hi> whoſe beauty rare,</l>
                     <l>Has ſuch pow'r o're <hi>Elpino,</hi> as his art</l>
                     <l>In ſinging ought t'have o're her pliant heart;</l>
                     <l>If there be any debt in love. He told</l>
                     <l>It before am'rous <hi>Thir</hi>'s and <hi>Battus</hi> old,</l>
                     <l>Juſt at the entrance of <hi>Aurora</hi>'s cave,</l>
                     <l>Where writ in golden Characters you have;</l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>All you that are profane depart from hence,</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>And ſaid that it was told to him long ſince</l>
                     <l>By the grand Poet, who ſo high did ſing</l>
                     <pb facs="tcp:115787:13"/>
                     <l>The life of many a Heroe, many a King,</l>
                     <l>Who dying did leave him his pipe, There is</l>
                     <l>Sayes he, at bottom o'th profound abyſſe,</l>
                     <l>A horrid cave, vomiting ſmoak with fire,</l>
                     <l>And a moſt conſtant ſtink out of the dire</l>
                     <l>Fornace of <hi>Acheronta,</hi> where do lie,</l>
                     <l>In torments dark, and that eternally</l>
                     <l>Thoſe women; who perſwaded here above,</l>
                     <l>Neither by pray'rs, nor tears, could be to love:</l>
                     <l>And 'tis a juſt, and well deſerved law,</l>
                     <l>Smoak ſhould force tears, which pity could not draw:</l>
                     <l>Then if thou thus thy cruelty continue,</l>
                     <l>Look to be conſort with that curſt retinue.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Sil.</speaker>
                     <l>But what ſaid <hi>Licoris</hi> to this, and how</l>
                     <l>Anſwer'd ſhe him;</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Daph.</speaker>
                     <l>Why ſee! thou fain wouldſt know</l>
                     <l>Others affairs, but car'ſt not for thine own:</l>
                     <l>She anſwered with her eyes.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Sil.</speaker>
                     <l>With eys alone</l>
                     <l>How could ſhe anſwer him?</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Dap.</speaker>
                     <l>Thoſe very ey's</l>
                     <l>Were, as 'twere, meſſengers, or rather ſpies;</l>
                     <l>Which mix'd with pleaſant ſmiles to him made known,</l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Licoris</hi> and her heart were now his own:</l>
                     <l>Except he did believe, faith was as rare</l>
                     <l>In them as beauty; ſhe as falſe as fair.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Sil.</speaker>
                     <l>Why ſhould he ſo believe?</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Daph.</speaker>
                     <l>knowſt thou what <hi>Thir's,</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>That famous Maſter both of Love and Verſe,</l>
                     <l>Did write, when burning with the flames of love</l>
                     <pb n="13" facs="tcp:115787:13"/>
                     <l>He wandring through the forreſt, did both move</l>
                     <l>The nimphs &amp; ſwains to laughter? but though he</l>
                     <l>Did things worth laughter, yet his writings be</l>
                     <l>Not to be jeer'd; this in a tree he writ,</l>
                     <l>With th'tree it grew, and there I oft read it:</l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>The looking-glaſſes of falſe hearts your eyes</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Are; and in them all deceit hidden lies,</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>But what avails't ſince ſhun them love denies:</hi>
                     </l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Sil.</speaker>
                     <l>I here in pratling caſt my time away,</l>
                     <l>And had forgot this is th'appointed day,</l>
                     <l>In which we ought to go, as we were wont,</l>
                     <l>In <hi>Eliceto</hi> for to raiſe the Hunt.</l>
                     <l>Prethee do thou ſtay for me while i'th nigh</l>
                     <l>Fountain I cleanſe the ſweat, and duſt which I,</l>
                     <l>Got yeſterday by hunting of a Deer,</l>
                     <l>Which at the laſt I kil'd;</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Daph.</speaker>
                     <l>I'l ſtay thee here</l>
                     <l>Perhaps I'l bath me too, but firſt my gate,</l>
                     <l>I'l homewards bend for it's not yet ſo late</l>
                     <l>As't ſeems, and thou at home for me mayſt ſtay:</l>
                     <l>But in the mean time think of that, I pray,</l>
                     <l>Concerns thee more then hunting, and ſay I</l>
                     <l>Bid thee take a fools counſel, ſo god bu'y.</l>
                  </sp>
               </div>
               <div n="2" type="scene">
                  <pb n="14" facs="tcp:115787:14"/>
                  <head>Act. 1. Scen. 2.</head>
                  <stage>
                     <hi>Aminta</hi> and <hi>Thirſis.</hi>
                  </stage>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>A.</speaker>
                     <l>I have with my laments, my ſighs, my groans</l>
                     <l>To pity moved, both the rocks and ſtones;</l>
                     <l>But mov'd I have not nor can hope to move</l>
                     <l>Her I adore, to pity or to love:</l>
                     <l>Remorſeleſs Nymph, I know not which I beſt</l>
                     <l>May ſtile thee, or a woman; or fierce beaſt</l>
                     <l>For thou to be a woman doſt deny,</l>
                     <l>Since more than beſt'al is thy cruelty.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Thir.</speaker>
                     <l>The lambs on tender graſſe, wolves on lambs feed,</l>
                     <l>And both do ſatisfie their hungry need:</l>
                     <l>But though love feed on tears, the more it have</l>
                     <l>Of tears and ſighs, it ſtill the more doth crave;</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Amin.</speaker>
                     <l>Alas! alas! love long ſince with the food</l>
                     <l>Of my tears ſatiate is, now for my blood</l>
                     <pb n="15" facs="tcp:115787:14"/>
                     <l>It onely thirſts, and therefore to the eyes</l>
                     <l>Of it and that cru'l nymph I'l mak't a prize:</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Thir.</speaker>
                     <l>Why talkſt thou thus <hi>Aminta?</hi> if unkind</l>
                     <l>And cruel ſhe be, thou'lt another find.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Amin.</speaker>
                     <l>How can I find another, when that I</l>
                     <l>Can't find my very ſelf, or pray whereby</l>
                     <l>Can one loſt to himſelf e're pleaſure gain?</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Thir.</speaker>
                     <l>Do not deſpair, at length thou mayſt obtain</l>
                     <l>This cruel fair; time teaches men to check,</l>
                     <l>Lions, and bring fierce tygers to their beck:</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Amin.</speaker>
                     <l>But whilſt that I wait out this long delay,</l>
                     <l>I ſhall with grief be quite conſum'd away:</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Thir.</speaker>
                     <l>Short the delay will be, for the diſdain</l>
                     <l>Of woman's kindled ſoon, ſoon quench't again:</l>
                     <l>They're moveable by nature, nor the wind,</l>
                     <l>Can breath more changes then a womans mind:</l>
                     <l>Lighter than feathers, and will readier bow,</l>
                     <l>Then ripened ears before a ſtorm; but thou,</l>
                     <l>Of thy condition farther let me know,</l>
                     <l>And the hard fortune of thy love, for though</l>
                     <l>Thou long ſince toldſt me that thou waſt in love,</l>
                     <l>Yet thou hidſt from me, who it was could move</l>
                     <l>In thee this am'rous fire, although that faith,</l>
                     <l>And ever conſtant friendſhip 'twixt us hath</l>
                     <l>Oblig'd thee to diſcover that to me,</l>
                     <l>Which unto others might concealed be.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Amin.</speaker>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Thirſis,</hi> I am content to tell thee what</l>
                     <l>The woods and mountains know, but men know not,</l>
                     <l>And 'tis but juſt that I being now ſo nigh,</l>
                     <pb n="16" facs="tcp:115787:15"/>
                     <l>My death, ſhould leave the reaſon why I die</l>
                     <l>To ſome dear friend, who may when I am gone</l>
                     <l>Report it, or may grav't in tree or ſtone,</l>
                     <l>Near the place where my bloodleſſe corps ſhall lie,</l>
                     <l>That if that pit'leſſe Nymph chance to paſs by.</l>
                     <l>She may ſtamp on't with her proud foot, and boaſt,</l>
                     <l>That her dire cruelty my life me coſt;</l>
                     <l>And that ſhe may rejoyce to ſee me lie,</l>
                     <l>There as a trophee of her victory.</l>
                     <l>Perhaps at laſt ſhe may (but things above</l>
                     <l>Deſert I hope) both pity then and love</l>
                     <l>Him dead, who living by her hate was ſlain,</l>
                     <l>And with ſalt tears may wiſh me back again;</l>
                     <l>But liſten now.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Thir.</speaker>
                     <l>Proceed; I wel thee mind,</l>
                     <l>And am to help thee at thy need inclin'd.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Amin.</speaker>
                     <l>I was as yet a child &amp; ſcarce could crop</l>
                     <l>Thoſe fruits the willing trees did ſeem to drop,</l>
                     <l>From their full loaden branches near the earth,</l>
                     <l>When full of jollity and harmleſſe mirth,</l>
                     <l>Not knowing love, or caring it to know,</l>
                     <l>With th' ſweeteſt nymph I did familiar grow,</l>
                     <l>That in the wind e're ſpread a golden hair,</l>
                     <l>It was the rich <hi>Cidippe</hi>'s daughter fair;</l>
                     <l>Grandchild unto the great <hi>Montan,</hi> whoſe flocks</l>
                     <l>And mighty heards fill both the woods and rocks,</l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Silvia,</hi> the glory of the woods, the fire</l>
                     <l>Of every heart, of all ſouls the deſire:</l>
                     <pb n="17" facs="tcp:115787:15"/>
                     <l>With her I kept ſuch faithful company,</l>
                     <l>That 'twixt two Turtles ne're the like could be;</l>
                     <l>Nothing to me than <hi>Silvia</hi> was dearer,</l>
                     <l>Near were our houſes, but our hearts were nearer:</l>
                     <l>Her age was equal almoſt with my own,</l>
                     <l>But 'twixt our thoughts, there was no diff'rence known;</l>
                     <l>With her I often us'd to ſpread the ſnares,</l>
                     <l>To catch the ſimple birds, or fearful hares:</l>
                     <l>With her I us'd to force ſwift Does to flight,</l>
                     <l>Equal the prey was, equal the delight;</l>
                     <l>But whilſt we thus made prize of beaſts: a prize</l>
                     <l>My ſelf was made to her all-conqu'ring eyes;</l>
                     <l>And like a weed which of it ſelf doth grow,</l>
                     <l>So grew there in my boſom, from I know</l>
                     <l>Not yet what root, a ſtrange and unknown fire,</l>
                     <l>Which made me <hi>Silvia</hi>'s preſence more deſire:</l>
                     <l>Her eyes were food to me, ſweet, but did leave</l>
                     <l>A bitter; did me of all joyes bereave:</l>
                     <l>And though my ſighs, alas, now were not few,</l>
                     <l>Yet of thoſe many ſighs no cauſe I knew.</l>
                     <l>Thus was I, e're that I could it diſcover,</l>
                     <l>By her fair ey's forc'd to becoem a lover:</l>
                     <l>But how I came to know't at laſt, do thou</l>
                     <l>Take notice pray.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Thir.</speaker>
                     <l>Proceed and tell me how.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Amin.</speaker>
                     <l>When <hi>Phoebus</hi> bright his hotteſt beams diſplai'd,</l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Silvi'</hi> and <hi>Phillis</hi> once chanc't' ſeek a ſhade</l>
                     <pb n="18" facs="tcp:115787:16"/>
                     <l>Under a ſpreading beech, when, lo, a Bee</l>
                     <l>Buzzing about <hi>Phillis</hi> fair cheeks chanc'd ſee</l>
                     <l>The lovely red ſhe did in them diſcloſe,</l>
                     <l>Did make the Bee miſtake them for a Roſe,</l>
                     <l>And think to gather honey from that ſweet,</l>
                     <l>She lights: but with too harſh ſalute did greet</l>
                     <l>Thoſe roſean cheeks, and <hi>Phillis</hi> with the pain,</l>
                     <l>Of the ſharp ſting moſt ſadly did complain;</l>
                     <l>When my Dear <hi>Silvia</hi> told her: <hi>Phillis</hi> pray</l>
                     <l>Lament not thus, I ſoon will take away</l>
                     <l>Thy pain with an inchantment, which I learn'd</l>
                     <l>Of the ſage <hi>Areſia,</hi> and I earn'd</l>
                     <l>It well, for in requital of it I</l>
                     <l>Gave unto her my horn of Ivory,</l>
                     <l>VVhich was adorn'd with gold. Thus having ſaid</l>
                     <l>Her ſweeter lips to <hi>Phillis</hi> cheek ſhe laid:</l>
                     <l>Juſt where the Bee had ſtung her, and ſhe there</l>
                     <l>Muttred ſome words which well I could not hear:</l>
                     <l>But O moſt wonderful! <hi>Phillis</hi> had eaſe</l>
                     <l>Immediately, and all her pain did ceaſe.</l>
                     <l>VVhether it was her Magick art or no,</l>
                     <l>That ſo ſoon wrought the cure I don't well know,</l>
                     <l>But I believe in her ſweet mouth was ſuch</l>
                     <l>Vertue that it did heal all it did touch.</l>
                     <l>I, that before had ſo reſtrain'd the fire</l>
                     <l>Of love, that nothing elſe I did deſire,</l>
                     <l>But <hi>Silvia</hi>'s preſence, and a paradice</l>
                     <l>It was to feaſt my ſelf on her fair ey's,</l>
                     <pb n="19" facs="tcp:115787:16"/>
                     <l>Or hear the ſweet tunes of her warbling voice,</l>
                     <l>More pleaſing far to me than was the noiſe,</l>
                     <l>The little pibbles make in murm'ring ſloods,</l>
                     <l>Or than the wind when't ſings among the woods</l>
                     <l>Was now by an ambitious ſpirit inclin'd,</l>
                     <l>To a deſire which wiſh'd my lips were join'd</l>
                     <l>To hers. This amorous deſire me taught,</l>
                     <l>A very ſubtile craft which at length brought</l>
                     <l>Me wiſh'd ſucceſſe (do but obſerve how love</l>
                     <l>Makes mens ingenio's nimbly for to move)</l>
                     <l>Her wondrous cure on <hi>Phillis</hi> I did ſee,</l>
                     <l>The ſight of that taught me to feign a Bee</l>
                     <l>Had bit my under lip, and though her pray</l>
                     <l>I durſt not for to take my pain away</l>
                     <l>By her inchantment, yet did my lament</l>
                     <l>Expreſſe as 'twere to her my hearts intent;</l>
                     <l>She harmleſſe ſoul pittying the grief that I</l>
                     <l>Made ſhew of, proffered freely to apply</l>
                     <l>Her cure to my feign'd wound, which added fuel,</l>
                     <l>To my hearts wound, and made it far more cruel.</l>
                     <l>Oh <hi>Thirſis!</hi> never Bee did ſuck from Roſe,</l>
                     <l>Honey ſo ſweet as I did ſuck from thoſe</l>
                     <l>Sweet cherries of her lips, though every kiſſe,</l>
                     <l>Me thought did yet want ſome part of its bliſſe,</l>
                     <l>For though I had a ful deſire, yet I</l>
                     <l>Was or reſtrain'd by fear, or modeſty:</l>
                     <l>But whilſt this honey mixt with gall deſcended</l>
                     <l>Thus to my heart, I ſorry ſo ſoon ended</l>
                     <pb n="20" facs="tcp:115787:17"/>
                     <l>Should be my bliſſe, feign'd that her charms did eaſe</l>
                     <l>Me ſomewhat, but not quite the pain ſurceaſe;</l>
                     <l>Which made her willingly to take the trouble,</l>
                     <l>That to me ſweet inchantment to redouble;</l>
                     <l>Thus ſo increaſ'd this love within my breaſt,</l>
                     <l>That at the laſt 'twas forced to leave its neſt:</l>
                     <l>Nor would it be kept ſecret, ſo one day,</l>
                     <l>When we were ſit as we were wont to play;</l>
                     <l>Shepherds and Nymphs together on the graſſe,</l>
                     <l>Each lad ſome ſecrets whiſpering to his laſſe:</l>
                     <l>I <hi>Silvia</hi> told, <hi>Silvia,</hi> I burn for thee,</l>
                     <l>And ſure ſhal die unleſſe thou helpeſt me;</l>
                     <l>Strait at my words there in her face aroſe</l>
                     <l>A bluſh both ſhame and anger did diſcloſe:</l>
                     <l>Bow'd to the ground her fair face was, and ſhe</l>
                     <l>With nought but an harſh ſilence anſwer'd me,</l>
                     <l>And from me turn'd, nor ever would ſhe deign,</l>
                     <l>Since that to ſee or hear me ſpeak again,</l>
                     <l>Though ful three years are paſt and I have tri'd</l>
                     <l>All means I could to get her pacifi'd,</l>
                     <l>Except my death; and could but that appeaſe</l>
                     <l>Her anger, I methinks could die with eaſe,</l>
                     <l>And ſhould account it highly worth my pain,</l>
                     <l>If I by death her pity could obtain,</l>
                     <l>And for my faith would deem it recompence,</l>
                     <l>Should ſhe lament me when I'm gone from hence;</l>
                     <l>But why ſhould I wiſh grief unto that breaſt,</l>
                     <l>In which I fixed have my joy, my reſt?</l>
                  </sp>
                  <pb n="21" facs="tcp:115787:17"/>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Thir.</speaker>
                     <l>But is it poſſible if ſhe ſhould hear</l>
                     <l>Thee ſay thus much? ſhe longer could forbear,</l>
                     <l>This true love to requite?</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Amin.</speaker>
                     <l>That know not I,</l>
                     <l>But when I'd ſpeak ſhe more my words doth fly,</l>
                     <l>Than doth an aſpe the charmer.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Thir.</speaker>
                     <l>Truſt to me,</l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Aminta,</hi> and I will procure that ſhe</l>
                     <l>Shal hearken to thee.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Amin.</speaker>
                     <l>Nothing from her can you,</l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Thirſis,</hi> procure, or if procure you do</l>
                     <l>That I ſpeak to her, yet alas in vain</l>
                     <l>Will be my ſpeech, and I ſhall nothing gain:</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Thir.</speaker>
                     <l>Why doſt deſpair ſo?</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Amin.</speaker>
                     <l>Juſt oc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>caſion I</l>
                     <l>Have to deſpair, nay rather for to die;</l>
                     <l>For the wiſe <hi>Mopſu</hi>'s long ſince did foreſhow</l>
                     <l>This my hard fortune. <hi>Mopſus,</hi> who doth know</l>
                     <l>The vertue of all herbs, and talk of birds.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Thir.</speaker>
                     <l>Which <hi>Mopſus</hi> ſpeakſt thou of? of him whoſe words</l>
                     <l>Are honi'd, and who has a friendly ſmile</l>
                     <l>In's face, but in his heart has nought but guile:</l>
                     <l>Be of good cheer, <hi>Aminta,</hi> do not fear,</l>
                     <l>Thoſe uncouth propheſies he ſels ſo dear</l>
                     <l>To unadviſed perſons, I reject</l>
                     <l>As fooliſh, for they never have effect;</l>
                     <l>This know I by experience, and I,</l>
                     <l>Cauſe he hath thus foretold, do hope thereby</l>
                     <pb n="22" facs="tcp:115787:18"/>
                     <l>That in thy love all things wil ſucceed wel,</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Amin.</speaker>
                     <l>If by experience thou canſt ought me tell</l>
                     <l>Which comfort may my hope, pray don't it hide,</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Thir.</speaker>
                     <l>When I came hither firſt for to a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bide</l>
                     <l>Within theſe woods, I knew and did eſteem,</l>
                     <l>This <hi>Mopſus</hi> ſuch as thou doſt now him deem;</l>
                     <l>I had by chance occaſion for to go</l>
                     <l>To the great Citie; which I let him know</l>
                     <l>As hoping his advice, when thus to me</l>
                     <l>He ſpake, To the great land thou go'ſt, ſaid he,</l>
                     <l>Where the ſly Citizens and thoſe o'th Court</l>
                     <l>Of ſimple ruſticks make a ſcoffing ſport;</l>
                     <l>Therefore be ſure this counſel take of mine,</l>
                     <l>Come not near thoſe whom thou ſhalt ſee to ſhine</l>
                     <l>With gold and ſtones, and other vain devices,</l>
                     <l>But above all (and ſlight not my advices)</l>
                     <l>Beware, leaſt thou be led by thy ill fate,</l>
                     <l>Or youthful curioſ'ty to the gate</l>
                     <l>O'th magazine of pratlers. Then ſtrait I</l>
                     <l>Demanded of him, what that place might be?</l>
                     <l>In this place Sorcereſſes live, ſaid he;</l>
                     <l>Who by inchantments do all things unvail,</l>
                     <l>What to thee ſeems pure gold, to them is pale</l>
                     <l>And ſordid braſſe, thoſe arches thou with trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure</l>
                     <l>Deemſt fil'd, are dirt and mire out of meaſure;</l>
                     <pb n="23" facs="tcp:115787:18"/>
                     <l>There are the wals built with great art, and do</l>
                     <l>Speak themſelves, and to ſpeakers anſwer too:</l>
                     <l>Nor do they anſwer a dumb voice alone,</l>
                     <l>As Eccho here, but in words one by one,</l>
                     <l>Tables and ſtools and all go tittle tattle,</l>
                     <l>And ſhould a dumb man enter here he'd prattle.</l>
                     <l>But ther's worſe evil yet, here maiſt thou be</l>
                     <l>Chang'd into water, fier, or a tree,</l>
                     <l>Water of tears, and fire of ſighs: content,</l>
                     <l>With this fond foreſight I to th'City went,</l>
                     <l>Where guided by bleſt fate I chanc'd to ſpy</l>
                     <l>The happy lodge, as I was paſſing by;</l>
                     <l>With curious eye expecting ſomething worth</l>
                     <l>My ſight, I chanc'd to hear at length come forth</l>
                     <l>Out of the gate ſuch pleaſant murm'ring noiſes,</l>
                     <l>Of nymphs and Sirens the harmonious voices,</l>
                     <l>As made me ſtand aſtonied with delight,</l>
                     <l>The object pleaſ'd ſo both my ears and ſight.</l>
                     <l>Juſt by the gate as guard to things ſo good,</l>
                     <l>A man of a magnan'mous aſpect ſtood;</l>
                     <l>To whom I do not wel know which I were</l>
                     <l>Beſt give that ſtile of Duke, or Cavalier,</l>
                     <l>He with benign and grave aſpect together,</l>
                     <l>Invited great and ſmal to come in thither,</l>
                     <l>Nor did he me poor ſimple ſoul deſpiſe;</l>
                     <l>O gods what did I ſee there! near mine eyes</l>
                     <l>Enjoy'd ſuch bleſſed ſights, nymphs ful as fair,</l>
                     <l>As heavenly goddeſſes, or far more rare:</l>
                     <l>Beauties more bright then glittering <hi>Phaebus</hi> beams,</l>
                     <pb n="24" facs="tcp:115787:19"/>
                     <l>When, at his riſe he guild's the eaſtern ſtreams;</l>
                     <l>There ſate <hi>Apollo,</hi> and the Muſes nine,</l>
                     <l>Shining in all their Graces, ſo Divine;</l>
                     <l>And, 'mongſt the Muſes, ſate the ſage <hi>Elpin.</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>Then was I raviſhed, with a high deſire,</l>
                     <l>Then, firſt I flam'd with a Poetick fire;</l>
                     <l>I ſang the lives of Kings, oth 'ancient times,</l>
                     <l>Scorning a mean verſe, or paſtorall rimes;</l>
                     <l>And, though again I to theſe woods return'd,</l>
                     <l>By my ill deſtiny: yet ſtill I burn'd</l>
                     <l>With ſome part of that fire: yet did abound,</l>
                     <l>My Pipe, ſtill, with a more then rurall ſound.</l>
                     <l>But, envious <hi>Mopſus,</hi> chancing me to ſpy,</l>
                     <l>One day caſt at me a Malignant eye:</l>
                     <l>Whereby, I hoarſe became, and then long time</l>
                     <l>I ſilent was, and ſung no more in rime.</l>
                     <l>Seen by the Wolfe, Paſtors ſuppoſed me,</l>
                     <l>Which cauſ'd my ſilence: but that wolfe was he;</l>
                     <l>This I have told thee, that thou maiſt perceive,</l>
                     <l>How willing is this Mopſo to deceive,</l>
                     <l>And void of faith, and therefore cauſe he will</l>
                     <l>Thee void of hope, I'd have thee hope more ſtill.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Amin.</speaker>
                     <l>It pleaſes me extreamly, for to heare</l>
                     <l>What thou haſt told, then of my life the care</l>
                     <l>To thee I do commit.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Thir.</speaker>
                     <l>Let me alone,</l>
                     <l>I care will take of it, as of my own;</l>
                     <l>Ile go ſee what for thee I can prevaile,</l>
                     <l>Then in an houre to meet me do not faile.</l>
                  </sp>
               </div>
               <div type="chorus">
                  <pb n="25" facs="tcp:115787:19"/>
                  <head>CHORUS.</head>
                  <lg>
                     <l>MOſt bleſſed age of gold! not cauſe the floods</l>
                     <l>Stream'd down pure ſnow, white milk: nor cauſe the woods</l>
                     <l>Diſtill'd ſweet hony, or, the free earth bore</l>
                     <l>Her fruits untouch't, nor had her bowells tore;</l>
                     <l>As yet by th' labr'ing ploughman, lambs might erre</l>
                     <l>Through the thick forreſts, without noiſe or fear;</l>
                     <l>Nor yet becauſe no winters clouds begun</l>
                     <l>T 'ecclipſe that Radiant Splendor of the Sun,</l>
                     <l>With which it's warme and pleaſant beames did bring</l>
                     <l>The wiſh'd-for happ'neſſe of a conſtant ſpring;</l>
                     <l>Nor wandring pines did yet, with ſails unfold,</l>
                     <l>For warr or gain compaſs the late known world.</l>
                     <l>But, only cauſe that fooliſh, and that vain,</l>
                     <l>Idol of errors, and deceit, that name</l>
                     <l>So without ſubſtance, which the Vulgar, mad,</l>
                     <l>Did afterwards call <hi>Honour,</hi> as yet had</l>
                     <l>No Power to play the Tyrant, or controule</l>
                     <l>The Peace and Freedome of a joviall ſoule.</l>
                     <pb n="26" facs="tcp:115787:20"/>
                     <l>But nymphs and paſtors ſweetly liv'd, nor knew</l>
                     <l>Any delight, but what from freedom grew,</l>
                     <l>Not ſubject, but to law perform'd with eaſe</l>
                     <l>Which nature writ; <hi>Is lawful if it pleaſe.</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>No need there was of <hi>Cupids</hi> torch to move</l>
                     <l>Or ſhafts to force the Nymphs and Swains to love,</l>
                     <l>Their very ſports inflam'd them and their ſmiles</l>
                     <l>They mix with their ſweet words, and then e're while,</l>
                     <l>Both with their ſweeter kiſſes then the roſe,</l>
                     <l>Of her fair cheeks the Virgin did diſcloſe</l>
                     <l>Freely to all; which now alas are blown,</l>
                     <l>To the delight and pleaſure but of one;</l>
                     <l>Then often by the waters of a bright</l>
                     <l>Spring, lovers us'd to take their full delight.</l>
                     <l>But thou perverſeſt <hi>honour</hi> firſt didſt ſhade</l>
                     <l>This fountain of delight, and thou firſt made</l>
                     <l>This freedom ceaſe, and thou didſt firſt deny</l>
                     <l>Water to quench his thirſt whom love made dry;</l>
                     <l>Thou taught'ſt thoſe ſplendant beauties firſt to lie,</l>
                     <l>Vail'd and obſcur'd from every am'rous eye;</l>
                     <l>Their all gold ſhining hair thou didſt reſtrain,</l>
                     <l>Into a net, and thou haſt put a rein</l>
                     <l>To all ſweet dear laſcivious acts, and we</l>
                     <l>Think now that theft which us'd loves gift to be,</l>
                     <l>And all theſe acts of thine turn to our pain:</l>
                     <pb n="27" facs="tcp:115787:20"/>
                     <l>But thou great <hi>Jove</hi> who with thy power doſt reign,</l>
                     <l>O're love and nature with a word, can'ſt tame</l>
                     <l>The greateſt Monarchs and whoſe very name</l>
                     <l>Strikes terrour, why alas doſt take delight,</l>
                     <l>To diſturb us poor miſcreants? kings of might</l>
                     <l>And power beſt fit thy thoughts, diſturb their peace,</l>
                     <l>And grant great god that we may live at eaſe,</l>
                     <l>And by thy divine providence be hurl'd</l>
                     <l>Into the golden—oth' ancient world.</l>
                     <l>We'l hope, ſince there's no joy, when once one dies</l>
                     <l>We'l hope; that as we have ſeen with our eies</l>
                     <l>The Sun to ſet, ſo we may ſee it riſe.</l>
                  </lg>
               </div>
               <pb n="28" facs="tcp:115787:21"/>
            </div>
            <div type="act">
               <head>Act. 2.</head>
               <div n="1" type="scene">
                  <head>Scen. 1.</head>
                  <stage>
                     <hi>Satyre</hi> alone.</stage>
                  <lg>
                     <l>SMall is the Bee, much ſmaller is her ſting,</l>
                     <l>Yet doth its wound both pain &amp; ſorrow bring,</l>
                     <l>But what's more ſmal then love? ſince it conceals</l>
                     <l>It ſelf within ſuch minute parts, and ſteals</l>
                     <l>Into the ſmalleſt ſpaces, now it reſts</l>
                     <l>Within the valley of two alp-like breaſts:</l>
                     <l>Now creeps and hides it ſelf within the fair</l>
                     <l>And curled treſſes of a golden hair:</l>
                     <l>Now under twinkling eye-brows, now i'th' ſleek</l>
                     <l>And roſie dimples of a laughing cheek;</l>
                     <l>Yet are it's wounds, it's plagues, ſo ſad, ſo ſore,</l>
                     <l>That nought can be imagin'd torment more.</l>
                     <l>Ah me! my very bowels and my heart</l>
                     <l>Boil o're with blood, and like a cruel dart,</l>
                     <l>So <hi>Silvia</hi>'s fair ey's pierce me, I may ſay</l>
                     <l>Cruel Love; but far more cruel <hi>Silvia,</hi>
                     </l>
                     <pb n="29" facs="tcp:115787:21"/>
                     <l>Cru'ler then woods, Oh! how wel doth agree</l>
                     <l>Thy nature with thy name, wel did he ſee</l>
                     <l>That it impos'd thee, woods in their green brakes</l>
                     <l>Do hide fierce lions, tigers, wolves and ſnakes,</l>
                     <l>Thou under covert of thy ſaireſt breaſt,</l>
                     <l>Hid'ſt anger, hatred and diſdain, which beaſts</l>
                     <l>Are worſe by much (alas) than thoſe of prey,</l>
                     <l>As lions, tygers, wolves or ſnakes; for they</l>
                     <l>May be appeaſed, but ay me! theſe are</l>
                     <l>Such, as will not be charm'd by gift or pray'r;</l>
                     <l>Thou ſlights the flowr w<hi rend="sup">ch</hi> from the fields I choſe</l>
                     <l>Becauſe thy cheek flowers much fairer ſhowes.</l>
                     <l>I from the orchards bring thee apples fair,</l>
                     <l>Which thou rejectſt diſdainful, cauſe there are</l>
                     <l>In thy fair boſome apples far more rare.</l>
                     <l>I bring thee ſweeteſt honey, even ſuch</l>
                     <l>From hives I ſtole thou, deignſt it not to touch</l>
                     <l>Cauſe on thy ſweet lips ſweeter ther's by much;</l>
                     <l>But if my poverty permits me not</l>
                     <l>To give unto thee any thing but what</l>
                     <l>In thee's more ſweet and fair, my ſelf then take;</l>
                     <l>Unjuſt, why ſhouldſt thou ſuch a gift forſake?</l>
                     <l>I'm not to be deſpiſed, no, for I</l>
                     <l>Saw my ſelf in the ſea when it did lie</l>
                     <l>Becalm'd &amp; free from waves, this my fierce, ſtern</l>
                     <l>And ſanguine look, theſe ſhoulders large, this arm</l>
                     <l>So ſtrong and nervous, this rough ſhaggy breaſt,</l>
                     <l>Theſe big-bon'd thighs of mine, and all my reſt</l>
                     <l>So well knit members, are a ſign that I</l>
                     <l>Am ſtrong and luſty, if believ'ſt not, try;</l>
                     <pb n="30" facs="tcp:115787:22"/>
                     <l>What wil't do with theſe tender fooles, whoſe ſleek</l>
                     <l>Face, ſcarce allowes them down upon their cheek?</l>
                     <l>Women, in ſhow, and Workes they be, nor are</l>
                     <l>Skill'd in ought elſe, but to diſpoſe each haire,</l>
                     <l>In it's due order; ther's not one that dare</l>
                     <l>Follow thee through the woods, to hunt the Bear,</l>
                     <l>Or, durſt encounter wilde Boares for thy ſake.</l>
                     <l>I'me not ſo ugly, no: nor doſt forſake</l>
                     <l>Me, 'cauſe I am thus form'd, alas, but why?</l>
                     <l>Becauſe I'm poor, thou doſt thy love deny.</l>
                     <l>Alas, the Villages do follow now</l>
                     <l>The cuſtom of the Mighty Cities: how</l>
                     <l>Well may the golden age this called be,</l>
                     <l>Since gold alone Commands imperiouſly?</l>
                     <l>O! thou, who firſt didſt teach the way, to ſell</l>
                     <l>Divineſt love, may torments, worſe then hell,</l>
                     <l>Still waite and tend upon thee; maiſt thou dy</l>
                     <l>Unpitied let thy cold aſhes ly</l>
                     <l>Unburied; let Nimphs and Shepherds ceaſe</l>
                     <l>Paſſing to ſay, <hi>Soule, do thou reſt in Peace;</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>Let the raine wet thee, move thee may the wind;</l>
                     <l>Let flocks and ſtrangers too, be ſo unkind,</l>
                     <l>As for to trample on thee, thou firſt ſham'd</l>
                     <l>The Nobility of love, not to be nam'd;</l>
                     <l>Horrid and Monſtrous, 'tis not to be told,</l>
                     <pb n="31" facs="tcp:115787:22"/>
                     <l>How Love is made the Price of abject Gold.</l>
                     <l>But, why in vaine lament I? ſince I ſee,</l>
                     <l>Beaſts, for their ſafety, uſe thoſe Armes, which be,</l>
                     <l>Allotted them by Nature, Tigers paw's</l>
                     <l>Uſe for defence, Lions their teeth and claw's;</l>
                     <l>The Stag does for her ſafety uſe to fly,</l>
                     <l>A womans weapon is her Beauty. Why?</l>
                     <l>(Then ſince all theſe do uſe their nat'ral armes</l>
                     <l>To conquer foes, or ſave themſelves from harms)</l>
                     <l>Should not I when that nature ha's me made</l>
                     <l>Apt for to raviſh, make uſe of the trade?</l>
                     <l>I'l force, I'l raviſh what ſhe me denies,</l>
                     <l>Nor will be moved with her pray'rs nor cries.</l>
                     <l>Not long ago I told was by a Swain,</l>
                     <l>That in the fountain lies in yonder plain;</l>
                     <l>She often baths her ſelf, there I intend</l>
                     <l>To hide me in the buſhes, to the end</l>
                     <l>That when ſhe comes I may be ſure to take</l>
                     <l>Hold on her; what reſiſtance can ſhe make</l>
                     <l>'Gainſt me, poor tender ſoule? and for her cries,</l>
                     <l>I'l neither them nor of her beauty prize</l>
                     <l>The power. Oh if I can but once entwine,</l>
                     <l>This hand within her locks, why then ſhe's mine,</l>
                     <l>Nor ſhal the gods releaſe her, til that I</l>
                     <l>For my revenge my armes in blood do dy.</l>
                  </lg>
               </div>
               <div n="2" type="scene">
                  <pb n="32" facs="tcp:115787:23"/>
                  <head>Act. 2. Scen. 2.</head>
                  <stage>
                     <hi>Daphne</hi> and <hi>Thirſis.</hi>
                  </stage>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Daph.</speaker>
                     <l>
                        <hi>THirſis,</hi> as I thee told, I long ſince thought,</l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Amintas</hi> did love <hi>Silvia,</hi> and have ſought,</l>
                     <l>God knows, all way's to further this his love,</l>
                     <l>And ſhall the more, ſince thou art pleas'd to move</l>
                     <l>Me in it: but I rather had by far</l>
                     <l>Chuſe for to tame a lion, or fierce bear,</l>
                     <l>Then ſuch a ſimple girle, who does not know</l>
                     <l>How piercing be her beauties armes, and though</l>
                     <l>She others kils, yet is her ſelf ſtil ſound,</l>
                     <l>And wounding others knows, not how to wound.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Thir.</speaker>
                     <l>And where's that child ſo ſimple han't a mind,</l>
                     <l>As ſoon as out of ſwathling bands, to find</l>
                     <pb n="33" facs="tcp:115787:23"/>
                     <l>Arts to ſeem handſom and to make her pleaſe?</l>
                     <l>And how to kil with pleaſing? and with eaſe</l>
                     <l>Can tell what armes they be cauſe death? nay more,</l>
                     <l>What armes they be which life again re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtore:</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Daph.</speaker>
                     <l>Who miſtreſſe is of ſo much art?</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Thir.</speaker>
                     <l>As though</l>
                     <l>Thou knewſt not <hi>Daphne,</hi> 'tis the ſame doth ſhew</l>
                     <l>Flight to the winged birds, and doth infuſe</l>
                     <l>Swimming to fiſhes, teaches Buls to uſe</l>
                     <l>Their hornes, and makes <hi>Juno</hi>'s proud bird to ſpread</l>
                     <l>Her <hi>Argus</hi>-eye-deckt feathers o're his head:</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Daph.</speaker>
                     <l>I'd very fain know how you cal this ſame</l>
                     <l>Miſtreſs of arts?</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Thir.</speaker>
                     <l>Why <hi>Daphne</hi> is her name.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Daph.</speaker>
                     <l>Out filthy liar that thou art.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Thir.</speaker>
                     <l>why fool</l>
                     <l>Art thou not able then to keep at ſchool</l>
                     <l>A thouſand girls, although no need there is</l>
                     <l>In this ſame Art of Love of Miſtreſſes,</l>
                     <l>For nature is their miſtreſſe, though, 'tis true,</l>
                     <l>The mother and the nurſe bear a ſhare too.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Daph.</speaker>
                     <l>Come, thou too knaviſh art, in ſum I'l tel</l>
                     <l>Thee that I am not yet reſolved well,</l>
                     <l>If <hi>Silvia</hi> be ſo ſimple as ſhe feigns</l>
                     <l>Her ſelf to be; for down in yonder plains</l>
                     <l>Where the clear waters of the ſilent lake</l>
                     <l>Incircled round a pretty Iſland make,</l>
                     <l>I t'other day ſaw <hi>Silvia</hi> counſel take,</l>
                     <pb n="34" facs="tcp:115787:24"/>
                     <l>How ſhe the golden treſſes of her head</l>
                     <l>In pretty curls might o're her forehead ſpread,</l>
                     <l>And then how ſhe might fitteſt o're them place</l>
                     <l>Her ſnow-white vail, o're that with better grace</l>
                     <l>Order ſome fragrant flowers, with lilies fair</l>
                     <l>Her white neck ſhe'd adorn; and ſo compare</l>
                     <l>Which was the whiteſt, now a lovely roſe,</l>
                     <l>To her ſweet cheeks to ſee which did diſcloſe</l>
                     <l>The livelieſt hue; then with delight would ſhe</l>
                     <l>Smile, as 'twere boaſting of the victory:</l>
                     <l>Methought ſhe ſeem'd to ſay, I onely do</l>
                     <l>For your diſgrace baſe flowers carry you,</l>
                     <l>Not for my ornament, ſince all may ſee</l>
                     <l>How much in beauty you muſt yeild to me;</l>
                     <l>But whilſt ſhe flatt'red thus her ſelf, her eye</l>
                     <l>By chance ſhe turn'd, and turning did eſpie</l>
                     <l>That I ſat laughing in th'adjacent bowers,</l>
                     <l>At which ſhe bluſh'd, and ſtrait let fall her flowers;</l>
                     <l>When laugh the more to ſee her bluſh did I,</l>
                     <l>Which her cheeks tinged in a deeper dy;</l>
                     <l>But cauſe that onely on one ſide her head</l>
                     <l>Her hair was gathered, on the other ſpread;</l>
                     <l>She fearful I ſhould ſee again, poor ſoule,</l>
                     <l>As 'twere from the clear fountain counſel ſtole,</l>
                     <l>And though ſhe were undreſt, yet pleas'd was ſhe</l>
                     <l>That, ſo undreſt, ſhe look'd ſo handſomely:</l>
                     <pb n="35" facs="tcp:115787:24"/>
                     <l>I ſaw it and was ſilent.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Thir.</speaker>
                     <l>Thou doſt tell</l>
                     <l>What I before told thee; gueſt I not well?</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Daph.</speaker>
                     <l>Well didſt thou gueſſe, but I have been told how</l>
                     <l>Paſtors and nymphs were not ſo ſly as now</l>
                     <l>In former times, nor young was I ſo bold:</l>
                     <l>The world do's grow more wicked, as more old.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Thir.</speaker>
                     <l>'Tis true that then Citizens us'd not ſo</l>
                     <l>Oft in the Countrey come, nor Ruſticks go</l>
                     <l>Unto the City; now their crafty race</l>
                     <l>As well as cuſtomes do with us take place;</l>
                     <l>But to our purpoſe canſt not thou procure,</l>
                     <l>That the hard-hearted <hi>Silvia</hi> may endure</l>
                     <l>To hear <hi>Amintas</hi> ſpeak alone, or't leaſt</l>
                     <l>In company with thee, which ſhe'l think beſt.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Daph.</speaker>
                     <l>I'l tell thee, <hi>Silvia</hi> now ſo coy doth grow</l>
                     <l>That well how to obtain it I don't know.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Thir.</speaker>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Amintas</hi> too reſpectfully is nice.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Daph.</speaker>
                     <l>True ſayſt thou <hi>Thirſis;</hi> there can no worſe vice</l>
                     <l>In lovers be; he that would learn the art</l>
                     <l>Of divine love muſt lay reſpect apart,</l>
                     <l>Muſt dare demand, ſolicite, importune;</l>
                     <l>And if by theſe means he can't overcome,</l>
                     <l>Muſt raviſh too: <hi>Thirſis,</hi> thou knowſt ſo well,</l>
                     <l>That I am ſure there's none need thee to tell,</l>
                     <l>The nature of a woman, if ſhe flies</l>
                     <l>'Tis cauſe ſhe'd be purſu'd; if ſhe deny's,</l>
                     <pb n="36" facs="tcp:115787:25"/>
                     <l>Alas 'tis onely cauſe that ſhe would have</l>
                     <l>Men to force that which firſt they did but crave,</l>
                     <l>She fights to be o'recome: laugh not at me</l>
                     <l>That I ſpeak thus in conſidence to thee,</l>
                     <l>And that I ſpeak in rimes, but thou knowſt, <hi>Thirſis,</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>I can for rimes return thee more than verſes.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Thir.</speaker>
                     <l>Thou haſt no reaſon to ſuſpect that I</l>
                     <l>Should e'r tell ought againſt thy modeſty.</l>
                     <l>But I conjure thee, <hi>Daphne,</hi> by the dear</l>
                     <l>Remembrance of thy youth that thou wilt here</l>
                     <l>Lend thy aſſiſtance with me for relief</l>
                     <l>Of poor <hi>Amintas,</hi> who elſe dies with grief.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Daph.</speaker>
                     <l>How neatly he conjures me, by the joy</l>
                     <l>Of mine that's paſt, and by my preſent'noy?</l>
                     <l>But what wilt have me do?</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Thir.</speaker>
                     <l>Judgement and skil</l>
                     <l>I know thou haſt, then onely, that thou will.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Daph.</speaker>
                     <l>In ſum I'l tell thee then <hi>Silvi'</hi> and I</l>
                     <l>This day at <hi>Dians</hi> well, which is hard by,</l>
                     <l>Intend to waſh, where an inviting ſhade</l>
                     <l>For nymphs and ſhepherds by a beech is made;</l>
                     <l>And there ſhe'l naked bath her tender waſt.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Thir.</speaker>
                     <l>What then?</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Daph.</speaker>
                     <l>What then! if thou haſt wit thou maiſt</l>
                     <l>Gueſs at the reſt.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Thir.</speaker>
                     <l>I gueſs, but do not know</l>
                     <l>Whether he'l have the heart to come or no.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Daph.</speaker>
                     <l>If come he wo'n't, for ought that I can ſay,</l>
                     <l>Stay until ſhe looks after him he may.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <pb n="37" facs="tcp:115787:25"/>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Thir.</speaker>
                     <l>He ſo deſerves.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Daph.</speaker>
                     <l>But, <hi>Thirſis,</hi> may not we</l>
                     <l>(At leiſure now) talk ſomewhat too of thee?</l>
                     <l>Why doſt not thou a ſweet-heart get? Alas</l>
                     <l>Thou'rt yet but young! and ſcarce doſt four years paſſe</l>
                     <l>Of the fifth luſtre (and full well do I</l>
                     <l>Know when theſe arms have danc't thee lullaby)</l>
                     <l>Why wilt neglected live, and void of joy?</l>
                     <l>Since without love there's no delight (my boy)</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Thir.</speaker>
                     <l>A man may ſhun fond love, and yet not faſt</l>
                     <l>From <hi>Venus</hi> pleaſures, he the ſweet do's taſte</l>
                     <l>Without the bitter.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Daph.</speaker>
                     <l>Moſt unſavorie 'tis:</l>
                     <l>The ſweet's not ſeaſoned with ſome bitterneſſe</l>
                     <l>Soon ſatiate.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Thir.</speaker>
                     <l>Better once ſatisfide:</l>
                     <l>Then before meat and after to abide</l>
                     <l>Stil hungry.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Daph.</speaker>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Thirſis,</hi> if the meat you have</l>
                     <l>doth pleaſe; the more you taſt, the more you crave</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Thir.</speaker>
                     <l>But who can alwaies preſent have that food</l>
                     <l>Which, though he's hungry, to his taſte is good.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Daph.</speaker>
                     <l>Who ſeeks no good ſhal find none.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Thir.</speaker>
                     <l>There's no eaſe</l>
                     <l>In ſeeking that, which found, 'tis true doth pleaſe;</l>
                     <l>But if not found when ſought torments us more.</l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Thirſis</hi> wil ne'r a lover be, before</l>
                     <l>That cruel love ſhal leave it's company</l>
                     <l>Of ſighs and tears, enough already I</l>
                     <l>Have ſigh'd and wept.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Daph.</speaker>
                     <l>Enough enjoyed though</l>
                     <l>Perhaps thou haſt not.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Thir.</speaker>
                     <l>Nor deſire, if ſo</l>
                     <pb n="38" facs="tcp:115787:26"/>
                     <l>Dear I muſt buy it.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Daph.</speaker>
                     <l>Well if nothing move</l>
                     <l>Thee can, at length thou wilt be forc'd to love:</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Th.</speaker>
                     <l>Love cannot force who's out of his command.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Dap.</speaker>
                     <l>But who is't can out of loves empire ſtand?</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Thir.</speaker>
                     <l>Who fears his witching charms and flies away.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Daph.</speaker>
                     <l>Where wilt thou fly if love his wings diſplay?</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Thir.</speaker>
                     <l>But love when young ha's his wings ſhort, and ſo</l>
                     <l>Can't overtake the man will from him go.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Daph.</speaker>
                     <l>The birth of love, there's no man can diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cry,</l>
                     <l>And when diſcri'd, his wings grown great, he'l fly.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Thir.</speaker>
                     <l>Some by experience his firſt birth can tel.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Dap.</speaker>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Thirſis,</hi> ſince thou pretendſt to know ſo wel</l>
                     <l>That Art, we'l ſee if thou canſt from him run,</l>
                     <l>This I proteſt to thee, I'l not be won</l>
                     <l>A hand, a foot, or eye-brow for to move,</l>
                     <l>Either to help or aid thee in thy love.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Thir.</speaker>
                     <l>Fy cruel one then couldſt thou dead me ſee?</l>
                     <l>If thou wilt have me love, why, love thou me.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Daph.</speaker>
                     <l>Why doſt thou mock me, <hi>Thirſis?</hi> perhaps thou</l>
                     <l>Doſt not deſerve ſo fine a miſtreſſe; how</l>
                     <l>Many a colour'd and ſmooth face be guiles.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Thir.</speaker>
                     <l>I do not mock thee; no, but thou mean<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>whiles</l>
                     <l>With this pretext my love doſt not accept;</l>
                     <l>This is the common trick: but if reject</l>
                     <pb n="39" facs="tcp:115787:26"/>
                     <l>My love thou doſt, I without love will live.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Daph.</speaker>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Thirſis,</hi> maiſt thou contently live and thrive,</l>
                     <l>More then e're yet thou didſt, maiſt live in eaſe</l>
                     <l>And leiſure, without which love ne're doth pleaſe.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Thir.</speaker>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Daphne,</hi> this leiſure god hath granted me,</l>
                     <l>One who a god may here eſteemed be;</l>
                     <l>To whom on verdant plains and cliffy rocks,</l>
                     <l>From ſea to ſea we feed our herds and flocks:</l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Thirſis,</hi> ſaid he, let others take a care,</l>
                     <l>To chaſe the wolves, and thieves, let others ſhare</l>
                     <l>Rewards unto the ſervants; others guard</l>
                     <l>My wal'd-in ſheep; thou (from theſe labours bar'd,)</l>
                     <l>Shalt ſing: then juſt it is my pipe ſhould move,</l>
                     <l>Not in fond fancies of a worldly love;</l>
                     <l>But that in higher ſtrains it onely hollow</l>
                     <l>The anceſtors of my <hi>Jove,</hi> or <hi>Apollo.</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>(For which of thoſe to call him well, in troth,</l>
                     <l>I know not, ſince he do's reſemble both)</l>
                     <l>Progenitors of greater worth by far,</l>
                     <l>Then or bright <hi>Saturn</hi> or the Heavens are;</l>
                     <l>(Low Muſe to ſuch a merit,) but yet he,</l>
                     <l>Sing I or clear or hoarſe, rejects not me;</l>
                     <l>His praiſe I dare not chant, nor well can I</l>
                     <l>Worthily honour him, but ſilently,</l>
                     <l>And with due reverence; but his altars ne'r</l>
                     <l>Without my flowers or ſweet perfumes yet were:</l>
                     <l>And when I do forget him to adore,</l>
                     <l>Or worſhip; then let <hi>Thirſis</hi> be no more:</l>
                     <pb n="40" facs="tcp:115787:27"/>
                     <l>Let Rivers change their beds, the <hi>Soane</hi> ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vance</l>
                     <l>To waſh the <hi>Perſian</hi> banks, the <hi>Tigris France.</hi>
                     </l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Daph.</speaker>
                     <l>High ho, thou'rt flown too high, prethee deſcend</l>
                     <l>Unto our purpoſe.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Thir.</speaker>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Daphne,</hi> I intend,</l>
                     <l>That thou ſhouldſt as thou go'ſt along the way</l>
                     <l>Endeavour for to ſoften <hi>Silvia;</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>I'l procure that he come, this task of mine</l>
                     <l>I doubt will harder be by far than thine,</l>
                     <l>Then go thy waies:</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Daph.</speaker>
                     <l>I do, but I did mean</l>
                     <l>By this talk part of which thou didſt not dream;</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Thir.</speaker>
                     <l>If I can wel diſcern him by the face,</l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Aminta</hi> 'tis appears in yonder place.</l>
                  </sp>
               </div>
               <div n="3" type="scene">
                  <pb n="41" facs="tcp:115787:27"/>
                  <head>Act. 2. Scen. 3.</head>
                  <stage>Aminta Thirſis.</stage>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Amin.</speaker>
                     <l>I'Le ſee what <hi>Thirſis</hi> may have done for me,</l>
                     <l>In what to do he promiſ'd; but if he</l>
                     <l>Have nothing done, why then, before that I</l>
                     <l>Will be conſum'd to nothing, I will die</l>
                     <l>Before the rigid <hi>Silvia;</hi> that abate</l>
                     <l>My death, may ſomewhat of her cruell hate,</l>
                     <l>She (that ſo pleaſ'd is with that plague, the Dart</l>
                     <l>Of her fair ey's ha's gi'n my love-ſick heart)</l>
                     <l>Wil with that wound which my breſt ſhal endure</l>
                     <l>From mine own hands be doubly pleaſ'd I'm ſure.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Thir.</speaker>
                     <l>I new's of comfort bring thee, and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tent,</l>
                     <l>Then deare <hi>Aminta,</hi> ceaſe thus to lament.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Amin.</speaker>
                     <l>What ſay'ſt thou <hi>Thirſis,</hi> muſt I live or die?</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Thir.</speaker>
                     <l>I bring thee life and ſafety, for if I</l>
                     <pb n="42" facs="tcp:115787:28"/>
                     <l>The other had, I'd not it bring, but need</l>
                     <l>There is of courage, man, and that with ſpeed?</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Amin.</speaker>
                     <l>What need is there of courage, pray. and where</l>
                     <l>Muſt I employ it?</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Thir.</speaker>
                     <l>If thy <hi>Silvia</hi> were</l>
                     <l>Within a wood, encompaſſ'd round with rocks,</l>
                     <l>Where lions and fierce Tigers by whole flocks</l>
                     <l>Did range, no way to ſcape by ſtrength or art,</l>
                     <l>To go to reſcue her, would'ſt have the heart?</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Amin.</speaker>
                     <l>More joyfull farr then on a holy day,</l>
                     <l>A Countrey wench doth run to dance or play.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Thir.</speaker>
                     <l>If ſhe 'mongſt murd'rers were, I fain would know,</l>
                     <l>Whether thou dar'ſt unto her reſcue go.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Amin.</speaker>
                     <l>I'd go more readier then the Stag does fly</l>
                     <l>To the long-wiſh'd-for fountain, when he's dry.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Thir.</speaker>
                     <l>But greater proofes more courage do require.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Amin.</speaker>
                     <l>I would for <hi>Silvia's</hi> ſake paſſe through the fire,</l>
                     <l>Or through the floods, when down the Moun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tains throw,</l>
                     <l>With a full torrent, their diſſolved ſnow;</l>
                     <l>I'd go to hell it ſelfe, if hell could be,</l>
                     <l>Where there is one ſo fair ſo good as ſhe;</l>
                     <l>But tell me pray, where is't?</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Thir.</speaker>
                     <l>Hark then.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Amin.</speaker>
                     <l>Go on.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Thir.</speaker>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Silvia</hi> attends thee naked and alone,</l>
                     <l>At that ſame fountain call'd <hi>Diana</hi>'s well;</l>
                     <pb n="43" facs="tcp:115787:28"/>
                     <l>Dar'ſt thou to go.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Amin.</speaker>
                     <l>Alas! what doſt thou tell</l>
                     <l>Me, <hi>Thirſis?</hi> naked and alone do's ſhe</l>
                     <l>Stay for me, ſayſt thou?</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Thir.</speaker>
                     <l>Unleſſe <hi>Daphne</hi> be</l>
                     <l>There (who of our ſide is) alone I ſay.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Amin.</speaker>
                     <l>But naked prethee do's ſhe for me ſtay?</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Thir.</speaker>
                     <l>I ſay ſhe there ſtayes naked for thee, but-</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Amin.</speaker>
                     <l>But what? thou kilſt me if that word thou put.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Thir.</speaker>
                     <l>But I can't tel if thou hadſt beſt to go.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Amin.</speaker>
                     <l>Oh hard concluſion! which all the forego-</l>
                     <l>Ing ſweetneſſe doth imbitter: with what art</l>
                     <l>Doſt ſtrive to wound my almoſt bloodleſſe heart?</l>
                     <l>Is't not enough that thus unhappy I</l>
                     <l>Am, but thou wilt increaſe my miſery?</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Thir.</speaker>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Aminta,</hi> if thou wilt my counſel take,</l>
                     <l>Thou mayſt be happy:</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Amin.</speaker>
                     <l>What, for the gods ſake,</l>
                     <l>Doſt thou adviſe me;</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Thir.</speaker>
                     <l>What! That thou be bold,</l>
                     <l>And on what fortune thee preſents lay hold.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Amin.</speaker>
                     <l>The gods I hope will keep me that I may</l>
                     <l>Ne're think a thought to diſpleaſe <hi>Silvia:</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>I ne're diſpleas'd her yet, but by my love,</l>
                     <l>Nor was't my fault, her beauties power did move</l>
                     <l>Me to't: but let me when I ceaſe to ſtrive</l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Silvia</hi> to pleaſe, no longer care to live.</l>
                     <pb n="44" facs="tcp:115787:29"/>
                     <l>Anſwer me now, If in thy Pow'r it were</l>
                     <l>To leave her love, wouldſt do't to ple aſure her</l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Love</hi> lets me not ſay ſo, nay 't does deny</l>
                     <l>That I ſhould think to leave her love, though I</l>
                     <l>Could do't.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Thir.</speaker>
                     <l>Why then though leave her? love thou could'ſt;</l>
                     <l>Yet, in deſpight of her, love her thou would'ſt.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Amin.</speaker>
                     <l>Not in deſpight, but yet I'd love her ſtill.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Thir.</speaker>
                     <l>Why then thou love her would'ſt a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt her will.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Amin.</speaker>
                     <l>Yes, certainly I ſhould.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Thir.</speaker>
                     <l>Then dar'ſt thou not</l>
                     <l>Againſt her will (fool as thou art) take what</l>
                     <l>At firſt may hard and heavy ſeem, once paſt</l>
                     <l>Sweeter and ſweeter growes unto the laſt.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Amin.</speaker>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Thirſis,</hi> love for me anſwers, and my heart</l>
                     <l>Know's it's own means, but cannot them impart,</l>
                     <l>Thee conſtant uſe ha's skil'd in loves great Art,</l>
                     <l>But that ha's bound my tongue which bound my heart.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Thir.</speaker>
                     <l>Why then we wil not go.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Amin.</speaker>
                     <l>Yes go wil I:</l>
                     <l>But not where thou doſt deem.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Thir.</speaker>
                     <l>Whither?</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Amin.</speaker>
                     <l>To die;</l>
                     <l>To die alas I'l go, if this be all</l>
                     <l>The favour thou haſt done me.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Thir.</speaker>
                     <l>Think'ſt it ſmall?</l>
                     <l>Think'ſt <hi>Daphne</hi> counſel would to go, if find</l>
                     <pb n="45" facs="tcp:115787:29"/>
                     <l>In part ſhe did not that 'twas <hi>Silvia</hi>'s mind?</l>
                     <l>And who can tell, it may be <hi>Silvia</hi> too</l>
                     <l>Know's it her ſelfe, but would not have that you</l>
                     <l>Should know ſhe knows it; now, if thou doſt crave</l>
                     <l>Her full conſent, thou do'ſt deſire to have</l>
                     <l>What would diſpleaſe her moſt, and then (foole) where</l>
                     <l>Is that deſire of thine to pleaſure her?</l>
                     <l>Or if ſhe would that thy injoyment were</l>
                     <l>Thy theft, and not her gift, what need'ſt thou care?</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Amin.</speaker>
                     <l>But who aſſures me ſuch is her deſire?</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Thir.</speaker>
                     <l>Why ſee? thou do'ſt that certainty re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quire,</l>
                     <l>Which does and ought diſpleaſe her, and which thou</l>
                     <l>Ought'ſt not to ſeek: but pray imagine now</l>
                     <l>That ſuch were her deſire, and thou not go,</l>
                     <l>Equal the doubt is, the loſſe equal; ſo,</l>
                     <l>I think it better that couragiouſly</l>
                     <l>Thou like a man, than like a coward, die</l>
                     <l>Ar't ſilent? thou'rt o'recome, confeſſe I pray</l>
                     <l>This love <hi>Aminta;</hi> it occaſion may</l>
                     <l>Thy greater Vict'ry; let's go then.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Amin.</speaker>
                     <l>I pray.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Thir.</speaker>
                     <l>What, ſtay! ſeeſt not how faſt the time does run?</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Amin.</speaker>
                     <l>Pray let us think firſt w<hi rend="sup">ht</hi> is to be done.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Thir.</speaker>
                     <l>We by the way wil think the reſt, but who</l>
                     <l>Do's too much think things, ſeldom wel doth do.</l>
                  </sp>
               </div>
               <div type="chorus">
                  <pb n="46" facs="tcp:115787:30"/>
                  <head>CHORUS.</head>
                  <lg>
                     <l>
                        <hi>LOve,</hi> who can teach us thy myſterious art?</l>
                     <l>Who thy divineſt fancies can impart?</l>
                     <l>Where may we learne them? who can them diſplay?</l>
                     <l>Since (though the mind them comprehend) a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>way?</l>
                     <l>Arm'd with thy wing'd prowes, they ſoare a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bove,</l>
                     <l>Not learned <hi>Athens</hi> ere the art of love</l>
                     <l>Could teach, nor its <hi>Liceo</hi> could it ſhew,</l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Phaebus</hi> in <hi>Helicon</hi> thy art ne'r knew;</l>
                     <l>He could diſcourſe of love, 'tis true, but ſo,</l>
                     <l>As if he did thy art but blindly know,</l>
                     <l>Or were a learner, cold were his deſires,</l>
                     <l>Nor did his voice burn with celeſtiall fires,</l>
                     <l>As ſits thy power, nor could his thoughts ariſe</l>
                     <l>To comprehend thy ſacred myſteries;</l>
                     <l>Thou only, <hi>Love,</hi> a worthy maſter art,</l>
                     <l>In thy ſublime, and more then heav'nly art;</l>
                     <l>To ruſtick breſts thou mak'ſt known thoſe Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vine</l>
                     <l>And moſt Celeſtiall Characters of thine,</l>
                     <pb n="47" facs="tcp:115787:30"/>
                     <l>Writ by thine own hand in anothers eye,</l>
                     <l>Thy faithfull ſervants tongues thou doſt untie:</l>
                     <l>And mak'ſt them glide in pure and nobler ſtream's,</l>
                     <l>Then ever iſſu'd from Poetick veines;</l>
                     <l>By thee divineſt love there's more expreſt</l>
                     <l>In broken words and ſpeeches, then the beſt</l>
                     <l>Of Orators can do, and more doth move</l>
                     <l>Thy ſilence, then their Rhetorick, to love:</l>
                     <l>Heart-conquering <hi>Love</hi> to others, leave will I</l>
                     <l>To learn thy art in blind philoſophy,</l>
                     <l>Or from the learned ſchooles: I only will</l>
                     <l>In faire ey's ſtudy this myſterious skill;</l>
                     <l>And their high ſtiles and Poetry will leſſe,</l>
                     <l>Then ſhall my rough or ruſtick times, expreſs:</l>
                  </lg>
               </div>
               <pb n="48" facs="tcp:115787:31"/>
            </div>
            <div type="act">
               <head>Act. 3</head>
               <div n="1" type="scene">
                  <head>Scen. 1.</head>
                  <stage>
                     <hi>Thirſis Chorus</hi> of <hi>Shepherds.</hi>
                  </stage>
                  <lg>
                     <l>O Horrid cruelty! unheard! unſeen!</l>
                     <l>Or ever yet remembred to have been</l>
                     <l>In humane breſt; three hundred times, nay four</l>
                     <l>Ingratefull ſex; thou nymph ingrateful more.</l>
                     <l>Why didſt thou, Nature, ſhow thy utmoſt art,</l>
                     <l>Thus in adorning womans outward part?</l>
                     <l>Why did'ſt her beaut'ous countenance indue</l>
                     <l>With ſuch a ſun-like ſoul-bewitching hue?</l>
                     <l>And didſt afford to grace her mind within</l>
                     <l>Nothing but falſeneſſe, cruelty, and ſin.</l>
                     <l>Negligent <hi>Miſtreſſe!</hi> But ay me, my dear</l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Aminta</hi> will have ſlain himſelf, I fear;</l>
                     <l>'Tis full three houres that round about the ground,</l>
                     <pb n="49" facs="tcp:115787:31"/>
                     <l>Where I him left I ſought him, but have found</l>
                     <l>Nor him, nor yet his footſteps, 'tis too plain</l>
                     <l>I clearly ſee that he himſelf hath ſlain;</l>
                     <l>But ſtay, perhaps thoſe ſhepherds yonder be</l>
                     <l>May tell me news of him, friends did you ſee</l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Aminta</hi> or hear of him?</l>
                  </lg>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Chor.</speaker>
                     <l>Thou doſt ſhow</l>
                     <l>So troubled; that the cauſe we fain would know</l>
                     <l>Of this thy grief; from whence proceeds this ſweat?</l>
                     <l>This ſorrow; tel us if thou think'ſt it meet.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Thir.</speaker>
                     <l>I fear <hi>Aminta</hi>'s ill, did you him ſee?</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Chor.</speaker>
                     <l>No him we have not ſeen, ſince that from thee</l>
                     <l>Long ſince he parted; but pray tell us plain</l>
                     <l>What doſt thou fear?</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Thir.</speaker>
                     <l>Leſt he himſelf have ſlain.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Chor.</speaker>
                     <l>That he ha's ſlain himſelf! but what could move</l>
                     <l>Him ſuch an act to do?</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Thir.</speaker>
                     <l>Hatred and love.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Chor.</speaker>
                     <l>Who two ſuch potent enemies don't fear?</l>
                     <l>What can't they do? but tel us pray more clear.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Thir.</speaker>
                     <l>His great love of a nymph, and her no ſmal</l>
                     <l>Hatred of him.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Chor.</speaker>
                     <l>Nay prethee tell us all;</l>
                     <l>This is a place of paſſage, and whilſt you</l>
                     <l>Relate it, news may brought be; perhaps too</l>
                     <l>Himſelf may come mean-while.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Thir.</speaker>
                     <l>I wil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lingly</l>
                     <l>Recount it wil, that the juſt infamy</l>
                     <l>Of ſuch a ſtrange ingratitude may reſt</l>
                     <pb n="50" facs="tcp:115787:32"/>
                     <l>Upon that cruel and remorſeleſs breaſt;</l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Aminta</hi> told was (I alas was he</l>
                     <l>That told it him and he was led by me,</l>
                     <l>Now I repent me) that his <hi>Silvia</hi> dear</l>
                     <l>This day with <hi>Daphne</hi> in a fountain clear</l>
                     <l>Would bath her naked limbs, he thither went</l>
                     <l>Not mov'd by his deſire, but to content</l>
                     <l>My importunities: oft back have gone</l>
                     <l>He would; but that I ſtill did thruſt him on;</l>
                     <l>Now when we come were to the fountain nigh;</l>
                     <l>We thought we heard a womans woefull cry,</l>
                     <l>And not far off we <hi>Daphne</hi> ſaw, her ey's</l>
                     <l>Swollen with tears, when ſhe ſaw us, her cries</l>
                     <l>Did pierce the heav'ns, run and make haſte, ſaid ſhe,</l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Silvia</hi> is forc'd. <hi>Amintas</hi> preſently,</l>
                     <l>Not ſtaying to hear more, flew away ſo</l>
                     <l>Swift as I never yet ſaw ſwifter Do:</l>
                     <l>I followed him; when, lo, we ſtraightway ſee</l>
                     <l>The beauteous <hi>Silvia</hi> ti'd unto a tree;</l>
                     <l>The rope to tie her was her brighteſt hair,</l>
                     <l>Which in a thouſand knots intangled were</l>
                     <l>About the plant; that girdle us'd to be</l>
                     <l>The former warder of her chaſtitie,</l>
                     <l>Was us'd now to her rape, and ſerv'd to bind</l>
                     <pb n="51" facs="tcp:115787:32"/>
                     <l>Unto the tree her ſnow-white hands behind.</l>
                     <l>The very plant it ſelf did condeſcend</l>
                     <l>To this foule act, and ſeem'd as 'twere to lend</l>
                     <l>It's ful aſſiſtance to the rape; for round</l>
                     <l>About her legs two pliant twigs were bound;</l>
                     <l>Juſt before her a cruel <hi>Satyre</hi> ſtood,</l>
                     <l>With looks denoting villany and blood,</l>
                     <l>Who finiſht had to bind her; ſhe poor heart</l>
                     <l>Did ſtrive with all her force and all her art,</l>
                     <l>But what (alas!) could all her force or skil</l>
                     <l>Prevail 'gainſt him who had ſuch ſtrength at will;</l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Aminta</hi> with his ſharp wel-brandiſh'd dart</l>
                     <l>Aim'd at, but miſt, the curſed <hi>Satyres</hi> heart;</l>
                     <l>I gather'd up what ſtones I could, but he</l>
                     <l>Seeing us two, thought it was beſt to flee:</l>
                     <l>We him purſu'd, <hi>Aminta</hi> as his flight</l>
                     <l>Gave leave, turn'd back his ey's to have the ſight</l>
                     <l>Of her fair members, which more ſoft by far</l>
                     <l>Seem'd than Swans down, and whiter much than are</l>
                     <l>The ſnow-deck'd <hi>Alpes,</hi> but when we had in vain</l>
                     <l>Purſu'd the rogue, he turning back again</l>
                     <l>Accoſts her thus, Pardon, O <hi>Silvia</hi> fair,</l>
                     <l>Theſe hands of mine, which with ſuch boldneſs dare</l>
                     <l>Approach thy members, for they're forc'd to looſe</l>
                     <pb n="52" facs="tcp:115787:33"/>
                     <l>Theſe knots which miniſtred to thy abuſe;</l>
                     <l>Then ſince that fortune has been pleas'd to ſend</l>
                     <l>Them ſuch a bliſſe, let it not thee offend.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Chor.</speaker>
                     <l>Words that would mollifie a heart of ſtone!</l>
                     <l>What anſwer did ſhe give him then?</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Thir.</speaker>
                     <l>Why none:</l>
                     <l>But looking down diſdainfully, ſhe tride,</l>
                     <l>All that ſhe could, her faireſt breaſts to hide;</l>
                     <l>He from the tree begins her hair to looſe;</l>
                     <l>And thus he ſeem'd to ſay, Durſt thou abuſe</l>
                     <l>Theſe golden curls, baſe plant? which do to thee</l>
                     <l>So great an honour, ah, unworthy be</l>
                     <l>Thy branches of ſuch knots; what vantage pray</l>
                     <l>Can we poor Lovers boaſt of? Since trees may</l>
                     <l>Enjoy thoſe comforts which we want, en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>twine</l>
                     <l>By force thoſe locks which bleſſe theſe hands of mine</l>
                     <l>By their bare touch; this done he from be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hind</l>
                     <l>Unties the knot, and does her hands unbind;</l>
                     <l>In manner ſo as if he ſeem'd to fear</l>
                     <l>Their touch, and yet to touch could not forbear;</l>
                     <l>Then ſtoops that he might looſe her feet, but ſhe</l>
                     <l>Finding her hands were now at libertie,</l>
                     <l>Looks on him ſcornfully, ſays touch not, I</l>
                     <pb n="53" facs="tcp:115787:33"/>
                     <l>Am <hi>Dians</hi> nymph. I can my feet untie</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Chor.</speaker>
                     <l>Can ſo much pride reign in ſo fair a heart?</l>
                     <l>O for ſo good an act ingrateful part!,</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Thir.</speaker>
                     <l>He did reſpectfully himſelf retire</l>
                     <l>Not looking on her, though he did deſire,</l>
                     <l>Deny'd himſelf that pleaſure, which on trial</l>
                     <l>He fear'd would give her trouble of de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nial;</l>
                     <l>I heard and ſaw all this, and hid did lie,</l>
                     <l>And though about to check her cruelty;</l>
                     <l>Yet I with-held: but heare the moſt unkind</l>
                     <l>Part of all yet; ſhe did at length unbind</l>
                     <l>Her ſelf, ſcarce looſe, nor bidding him adieu,</l>
                     <l>Faſter then fleeteſt Stag away ſhe flew;</l>
                     <l>And yet to fear I'm ſure ſhe cauſe had none,</l>
                     <l>For his reſpect to her was ful wel known.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Chor.</speaker>
                     <l>Why did ſhe fly then?</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Thir.</speaker>
                     <l>She would of her rape</l>
                     <l>The reſcue attribute to her eſcape,</l>
                     <l>Not to his modeſt love.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Chor.</speaker>
                     <l>Ingrateful too</l>
                     <l>In this! but what ſaid he? what did he do?</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Thir.</speaker>
                     <l>I know not, I vext at her rigor, ran</l>
                     <l>To overtake and hold her but in vain;</l>
                     <l>For ſoon I loſt her track, then turning, where</l>
                     <l>I left <hi>Aminta,</hi> could not find him there;</l>
                     <l>My heart preſages ill, for this I'm ſure</l>
                     <l>He'd rather die than this ſad chance endure:</l>
                  </sp>
                  <pb n="54" facs="tcp:115787:34"/>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Cho.</speaker>
                     <l>The cuſtom 'tis (we know) of thoſe that are</l>
                     <l>In love, to threaten death, but very rare</l>
                     <l>Are thoſe effect it.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Thir.</speaker>
                     <l>But pray god that he</l>
                     <l>One of thoſe rare ones be not:</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Cho.</speaker>
                     <l>He won't be</l>
                     <l>So fooliſh, fear not.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Thir.</speaker>
                     <l>I'l go to the cave</l>
                     <l>Of ſage <hi>Elpino,</hi> where I ſure ſhal have</l>
                     <l>News of him if he lives, for that's his hant;</l>
                     <l>There on his oaten pipe he us'd to chant</l>
                     <l>Sweet ſongs, and there lament him of his love,</l>
                     <l>And make the very rocks and mountains move;</l>
                     <l>The Rivers ſtop their courſe to hear his layes,</l>
                     <l>The trees incline, and wild beaſts leave their preys.</l>
                  </sp>
               </div>
               <div n="2" type="scene">
                  <pb n="55" facs="tcp:115787:34"/>
                  <head>Act. 3. Scen. 2.</head>
                  <stage>Amintas Daphne Nerina.</stage>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Amin.</speaker>
                     <l>PItileſſe pity <hi>Daphne</hi> ſure was thine,</l>
                     <l>When thou with-heldſt this hand, this dart of mine;</l>
                     <l>That ſo my death being delay'd by fate</l>
                     <l>Might be more bitter by how much more late;</l>
                     <l>And why doſt trace me thus? or thinkſt to force</l>
                     <l>Hope into me by this thy vain diſcourſe:</l>
                     <l>What doſt thou fear? that I my ſelf ſhould ſlay,</l>
                     <l>Thou fear'ſt my good; then prethee goe away;</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Daph.</speaker>
                     <l>Deſpair not thus <hi>Aminta,</hi> for if I</l>
                     <pb n="56" facs="tcp:115787:35"/>
                     <l>Know <hi>Silvia</hi> wel, 'twas ſhame that made her fly,</l>
                     <l>Not cruelty.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Amin.</speaker>
                     <l>Alas! there is for me</l>
                     <l>No way but to deſpair, ſince hope wil be</l>
                     <l>As't ha's been yet my ruine, ſtil I find</l>
                     <l>It ſtrives as 'twere to bloſſom in my mind;</l>
                     <l>And whiſpers to me live, and can ought be</l>
                     <l>Worſe then a life, to ſuch a wretch as me?</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Daph.</speaker>
                     <l>Live wretch, live ſtil I ſay, and let this be</l>
                     <l>Support unto thee in thy miſery;</l>
                     <l>That if thy hope in life do but maintain thee,</l>
                     <l>At length thar naked fair one it will gain thee.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Amin.</speaker>
                     <l>Both love and fortune, though that at the brink</l>
                     <l>Of wretchedneſſe I was, yet did not think</l>
                     <l>Me yet forlorn enough, until that I</l>
                     <l>Had fully ſeen what fully both denie.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Ner.</speaker>
                     <l>Muſt I then alwaies have the luck to be</l>
                     <l>The meſſenger of ſuch ſad news? ay me!</l>
                     <l>Wretched <hi>Mantano!</hi> what ſad heart wil thine</l>
                     <l>Be when thou com'ſt to hear this newes of mine?</l>
                     <l>O ſad and des'late father thou, nay rather,</l>
                     <l>By loſſe of thy dear <hi>Silvia,</hi> no more Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther!</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Daph.</speaker>
                     <l>I a ſad voice do hear.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Amin.</speaker>
                     <l>And I hear ſound</l>
                     <l>The name of <hi>Silvia,</hi> which my heart do's wound,</l>
                     <pb n="57" facs="tcp:115787:35"/>
                     <l>Who is it names her?</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Daph.</speaker>
                     <l>it ſeemes at firſt ſight</l>
                     <l>To be <hi>Nerina, Cynthia's</hi> cheife delight,</l>
                     <l>Who ha's ſo ſweet comportment, ſo fair face,</l>
                     <l>Such charming ey's, ſuch a bewitching Grace.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Ner.</speaker>
                     <l>And yet alas, I'm forc'd to let him know</l>
                     <l>Of this moſt fatal chance of thine, that ſo</l>
                     <l>He may ſeek thoſe unhappy bones, if no</l>
                     <l>More reſts of thee; oh! my deare <hi>Silvia,</hi> oh!</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Amin.</speaker>
                     <l>Ay me, what ſay's ſhe!</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Ner.</speaker>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Daphne,</hi>
                     </l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Daph.</speaker>
                     <l>what, and why</l>
                     <l>Do'ſt to thy ſelf name <hi>Silvia,</hi> and then cry.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Ner.</speaker>
                     <l>Alas! with reaſon I lament her ſad</l>
                     <l>And cruel fate;</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Amin.</speaker>
                     <l>What fate can be ſo bad</l>
                     <l>To make thee thus lament? Ay me, I feele</l>
                     <l>My heart a dying, as though pierc'd with ſteele,</l>
                     <l>Is ſhe alive?</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Daph.</speaker>
                     <l>Prethee to us relate</l>
                     <l>What thus thou mutter'ſt of her deſp'rate fate.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Ner.</speaker>
                     <l>Ye Gods! why am I meſſenger? yet I</l>
                     <l>Muſt tel't: did ſhe, you know the reaſon why</l>
                     <l>Come e'n now naked to my Lodg, and there</l>
                     <l>Re-cloath'd her ſelfe again; ſhe by her pray'r</l>
                     <l>Prevail'd with me, that I would with her go</l>
                     <l>In <hi>Eliceto</hi> for to hunt a Do.</l>
                     <l>I pleaſ'd her, and we went when, neer the ground,</l>
                     <pb n="58" facs="tcp:115787:36"/>
                     <l>Gather'd together many Nymphs we found;</l>
                     <l>Scarce had we ſpoke to them, when lo we ſee</l>
                     <l>A mighty wolfe ſtart from behind a tree,</l>
                     <l>Great out of meaſure was he, and with blood</l>
                     <l>His noſe was di'd, he fiercely looking ſtood;</l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Silvia</hi> ſtreight to her bow an arrow fits,</l>
                     <l>And ſhe nere uſ'd to miſſe; ſo now ſhe hits</l>
                     <l>Him juſt upon the head, he fly's again</l>
                     <l>Into the wood, ſhe followes him amaine:</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Amin.</speaker>
                     <l>O ſad beginning, which do's pierce my heart!</l>
                     <l>What end wilt have?</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Ner.</speaker>
                     <l>I with another dart</l>
                     <l>Follow'd her track, but at great diſtance, ſince</l>
                     <l>She was i'th wood ere I could move me thence,</l>
                     <l>Yet I her footſteps made a ſhift to trace,</l>
                     <l>Until I came to the moſt deſert place</l>
                     <l>Of all the wood, where, lo, by chance I found</l>
                     <l>My deareſt <hi>Silvia's</hi> dart upon the ground,</l>
                     <l>And not farr off from it I did eſpy</l>
                     <l>That ſnow-white vaile, which I my ſelfe did ty</l>
                     <l>Upon her head, which as you ſee is di'd</l>
                     <l>With crimſon gore, and looking round I ſpi'd</l>
                     <l>Seven fierce wolves, which ſeem'd to lick the blood</l>
                     <l>Of a nak'd body, about which they ſtood,</l>
                     <l>Such was my hap, and ſo intent they were</l>
                     <l>Upon their prey, they ſaw not I was there;</l>
                     <l>So I return'd, and this is the full tale</l>
                     <l>I tell of <hi>Silvia</hi> can, ſee here the vaile.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <pb n="47" facs="tcp:115787:36"/>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Amin.</speaker>
                     <l>Th'aſt told too much, this vaile, and this blood be</l>
                     <l>Sure tokens of her death.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Daf.</speaker>
                     <l>Ah poore wretch! he</l>
                     <l>Is dead with greife too.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Ner.</speaker>
                     <l>No, he breathes, revives,</l>
                     <l>'Tis but a ſudden fainting, ſee he lives.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Amin.</speaker>
                     <l>Greife, why? (alas!) do'ſt thou tor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment me ſo,</l>
                     <l>And do'ſt not kill outright? if thou too ſlow</l>
                     <l>Beeſt, or wouldſt have my hand the inſtrument</l>
                     <l>To do't, to this I'me very well content;</l>
                     <l>And it ſhal execute that death which thou</l>
                     <l>Refuſeſt, or to do, or know'ſt not how;</l>
                     <l>Then ſince the certainty of this we know,</l>
                     <l>And nothing wants now to augment my woe;</l>
                     <l>Why ſhould I longer ſtay? oh <hi>Daphne!</hi> why</l>
                     <l>Did'ſt not permit me, when I would, to die?</l>
                     <l>To this ſad end reſerv'dſt thou me? to this!</l>
                     <l>Sure ſweet my death had been, nay more a bliſſe,</l>
                     <l>And greateſt happineſſe, had but that dart,</l>
                     <l>Which cruel thou withheldeſt, pierc'd my heart.</l>
                     <l>But heav'ns deni'd it, and did feare leaſt that</l>
                     <l>I by my ſudden death forerun ſhould, what</l>
                     <l>They had ordain'd me, now my utmoſt ill</l>
                     <l>They executed have, permit they will</l>
                     <l>To make the full ſumme of their cruel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty:</l>
                     <pb n="60" facs="tcp:115787:37"/>
                     <l>And thou permi too muſt) that I may dy.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Daph.</speaker>
                     <l>Reſtrain this frantick humour of thy youth,</l>
                     <l>Until we do heare further of the truth.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Amin.</speaker>
                     <l>Why do'ſt thou ſtrive to keep me off with ſuch</l>
                     <l>Delay's? I've ſtaid too long, and heard too much.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Ner.</speaker>
                     <l>I would I had been dumb.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Amin.</speaker>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Nymph,</hi> pray beſtow</l>
                     <l>On me that blood-beſpotted Vail; that ſo</l>
                     <l>Small, but whole relique of my <hi>Silvia;</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>That ſince no more there reſts of her, it may</l>
                     <l>Witneſſe my death, and if there ought can be</l>
                     <l>To do't may ſerve t' augment my miſery;</l>
                     <l>Though, I confeſs, 'tis not ſo ſmall that I</l>
                     <l>Need to increaſe it, to perſwade me dy.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Ner.</speaker>
                     <l>Had I beſt giv't him, or deny't him? I</l>
                     <l>Think for th' occaſion I were beſt deny.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Amin.</speaker>
                     <l>What cruell one! ſo ſmall a gift to me,</l>
                     <l>Who am reſolv'd nere to ask more of thee?</l>
                     <l>In this too wretched fate, I yeeld with you,</l>
                     <l>Then let the Vaile remain, and ſo adieu;</l>
                     <l>I go to turn no more.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Daph.</speaker>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Aminta,</hi> ſtay,</l>
                     <l>Gods! with what fury do's he fly away?</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Ner.</speaker>
                     <l>He flies ſo faſt, that it will be in vaine</l>
                     <l>To follow him, I down in yonder plaine</l>
                     <pb n="61" facs="tcp:115787:37"/>
                     <l>Wil ſeek <hi>Montano,</hi> but I do not know</l>
                     <l>If I were beſt to tell the newes or no.</l>
                  </sp>
               </div>
               <div type="chorus">
                  <head>CHORUS.</head>
                  <lg>
                     <l>THere is no cauſe, which death may move</l>
                     <l>To bind him, ha's a noble heart;</l>
                     <l>His faith's enough firſt, then his love,</l>
                     <l>Nor is ſo hard of love the art.</l>
                     <l>By him alone that loves wel, love is ſought,</l>
                     <l>And like a Merchandiſe by love is bought;</l>
                     <l>And ſeeking love we often find</l>
                     <l>A Glory, which we leave behind.</l>
                  </lg>
               </div>
               <pb n="63" facs="tcp:115787:38"/>
            </div>
            <div type="act">
               <head>Act. 4.</head>
               <div n="1" type="scene">
                  <head>Scen: 1.</head>
                  <stage>
                     <hi>Daphne, Silvia</hi> and <hi>Chore</hi> of <hi>Shepherds.</hi>
                  </stage>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Daph.</speaker>
                     <l>THat wind that brought the ſad new's of thy death,</l>
                     <l>Brought with it likewiſe in the ſelfe ſame breath</l>
                     <l>Thy preſent and thy future ill, but thou</l>
                     <l>(Thanks be to God) art live and well, when now</l>
                     <l>I deem'd thee dead; <hi>Nerina</hi> with ſuch greife</l>
                     <l>It told: had ſhe been dumb, or others deaf.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Sil.</speaker>
                     <l>The danger ſure was great, and ſhe in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deed</l>
                     <l>Had juſt occaſion to ſuſpect me dead.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Daph.</speaker>
                     <l>A juſt occaſion for to tell it, though,</l>
                     <l>She had not, but let me thy danger know,</l>
                     <l>And how thou ſcap'dſt.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Sil.</speaker>
                     <l>I'l tell thee, I, in chaſe</l>
                     <pb n="62" facs="tcp:115787:38"/>
                     <l>Of a fierce wolf, unto the thickeſt place</l>
                     <l>Came of the wood, ſo that I quite the track</l>
                     <l>Did of his footſteps looſe, but turning back</l>
                     <l>Again, I ſpi'd him; by my ſhaft I knew</l>
                     <l>That 'twas the ſame wolf firſt before me flew.</l>
                     <l>He with ſome others feeding was amain,</l>
                     <l>On a dead carkaſe they had newly ſlain;</l>
                     <l>Of what I could not well diſcern, but he</l>
                     <l>Leaving his prey came running after me.</l>
                     <l>I ſtood him; with intent to make him feel,</l>
                     <l>My dart than arrow was the ſharper ſteel;</l>
                     <l>And thou knowſt well I'm miſtreſſe of the art,</l>
                     <l>Of brandiſhing and lancing wel a dart;</l>
                     <l>I ſeldom uſe to miſſe, and ſo, when nigh</l>
                     <l>Enough I thought him, I my dart let fly,</l>
                     <l>But was it fault of fortune, or of me,</l>
                     <l>I miſt the wolf, and ſtuck it in a tree:</l>
                     <l>The Wolf more fiercely at me runs, and I,</l>
                     <l>Seeing 'twas vain to uſe my bow, did fly:</l>
                     <l>He follows me, (now hear a chance,) my vail</l>
                     <l>Hap'd to untie, and with the murm'ring gale</l>
                     <l>Came through the woods, blew up and down, at laſt</l>
                     <l>A bot a bough tangled it ſelf ſo faſt,</l>
                     <l>That though my force redoubled was, my ſtrength</l>
                     <l>Could not prevail a reſcue, but at length,</l>
                     <l>Seeing no way to'ſcape, I thought it beſt</l>
                     <l>Quite to untie it, and there <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>et it reſt;</l>
                     <l>Which done, I ran again with all my might,</l>
                     <pb n="64" facs="tcp:115787:39"/>
                     <l>Feare adding thouſand wings unto my flight,</l>
                     <l>That he nere joyn'd me, and I came out ſafe</l>
                     <l>Unto my lodge, where firſt of all I have</l>
                     <l>Encountred thee, and wondred much to ſee</l>
                     <l>Thee ſtand amaz'd, and wondring ſo at me.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Daph.</speaker>
                     <l>Thou liv'ſt, alas! but others not.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Sil.</speaker>
                     <l>doth't greive</l>
                     <l>Thee <hi>Daphne</hi> then that I am ſtill alive?</l>
                     <l>Hat'ſt thou me ſo?</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Daph.</speaker>
                     <l>no <hi>Silvia,</hi> I'm full glad</l>
                     <l>Thou liv'ſt, anothers death 'tis makes me ſad.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Sil.</speaker>
                     <l>Whoſe death?</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Daph.</speaker>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Aminta's.</hi>
                     </l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Sil.</speaker>
                     <l>Is he dead, and how?</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Daph.</speaker>
                     <l>Well how I cannot tell, nor do I know</l>
                     <l>If it be certain.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Sil.</speaker>
                     <l>Strange! but can'ſt di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vine</l>
                     <l>What was the occaſion of his death?</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Daph.</speaker>
                     <l>why? thine.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Sil.</speaker>
                     <l>I underſtand thee not.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Daph.</speaker>
                     <l>The ti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dings ſad</l>
                     <l>Brought of thy wretched death, ſuch power had</l>
                     <l>O're him, poore foul, and o're his wearied life,</l>
                     <l>That I beleive 'thas brought him cord or knife.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Sil.</speaker>
                     <l>I hope that vaine will this ſuſpect of thine</l>
                     <l>Be of his death, as vain was that of mine;</l>
                     <l>For when men come to the effect, they ſtrive</l>
                     <pb n="49" facs="tcp:115787:39"/>
                     <l>(Let them boaſt what they wil before) to live.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Daph.</speaker>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Silvia,</hi> thou know'ſt not what the fire of love</l>
                     <l>Can in a heart that's not of marble move,</l>
                     <l>But thine's more hard than ſtone, elſe thou be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieve</l>
                     <l>Would'ſt him, for whom thou yet ſeem'ſt not to grieve;</l>
                     <l>And would'ſt have lov'd him who far more did prize</l>
                     <l>Thy love, than the dear apples of her ey's.</l>
                     <l>I wel believ'd him, knew, and ſaw't, when he</l>
                     <l>Having unloos'd the (Tigreſſe) from the tree,</l>
                     <l>An act that would have forc'd thee him to love,</l>
                     <l>Had'ſt had a heart; but what is't thee can move?</l>
                     <l>I ſay I ſaw him there reverſe his dart</l>
                     <l>And with his ful force ſtrive to pierce his heart;</l>
                     <l>Nor did repent him, though at firſt he di'd</l>
                     <l>It in his crimſon gore; but once more tri'd</l>
                     <l>To make it enter farther, and he ſure</l>
                     <l>Had pierc'd his heart, but I could not endure</l>
                     <l>To ſee't, ſo ſtaid him; yet believe the rage</l>
                     <l>Of that ſmal wound did not at all aſſwage</l>
                     <l>His deſp'rate conſtancy, but onely made</l>
                     <l>A freer paſſage for his thirſty blade.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Sil.</speaker>
                     <l>What doſt thou tell?</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Daph.</speaker>
                     <l>I ſaw him too when he</l>
                     <l>Firſt underſtood news of the death of thee</l>
                     <l>To ſwound for grief; reviv'd, he fled away</l>
                     <l>In fury with intent himſelf to ſlay:</l>
                     <pb n="66" facs="tcp:115787:40"/>
                     <l>And he'l have done it ſurely.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Sil.</speaker>
                     <l>Think'ſt thou ſo.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Daph.</speaker>
                     <l>I cannot doubt it.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Sil.</speaker>
                     <l>Oh my <hi>Daphne,</hi> oh</l>
                     <l>Why followedſt not to hinder him, with me</l>
                     <l>Come now and ſeek to find him; for if he,</l>
                     <l>Thinking me dead, reſolv'd himſelf to kill,</l>
                     <l>Sure now I live, remain in life he will.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Daph.</speaker>
                     <l>I follow'd him, and ſought him, but in vain,</l>
                     <l>For when he once got out of ſight, again</l>
                     <l>I could not find him, nor his footſteps; thou</l>
                     <l>Then whither, prethee, wilt go ſeek him now?</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Sil.</speaker>
                     <l>Alas let's go however, for if we</l>
                     <l>Don't ſtay him, he will his own murd'rer be.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Daph.</speaker>
                     <l>Perhaps it grieves thee then that any one</l>
                     <l>Should boaſt of killing him, but thee alone;</l>
                     <l>Or cruel one doſt think it ſcorn, his heart</l>
                     <l>Should wounded be by any, but thy dart?</l>
                     <l>Content thy ſelf, how e're he dies, yet he</l>
                     <l>Dies for thy ſake, thou wilt his murd'rer be.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Sil.</speaker>
                     <l>Ay me! thy comfort's harſh, but now I find</l>
                     <l>That grief of heart, which overſwayes my mind;</l>
                     <l>For his ſad chance imbittered is the more,</l>
                     <l>By how much I was rigorous before,</l>
                     <l>And the remembrance of my cruelty</l>
                     <l>Torments me now, I call'd it honeſty,</l>
                     <l>And ſo it was, but too ſevere by far,</l>
                     <l>Too cruel ſince it did all pity bar;</l>
                     <pb n="67" facs="tcp:115787:40"/>
                     <l>Now I repent me.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Daph.</speaker>
                     <l>Strange! what do I hear?</l>
                     <l>Pitiful thou? what can thy flint heart bear</l>
                     <l>The leaſt impreſſ'on? weep'ſt thou? what can move</l>
                     <l>Theſe tears? are they of pity or of love?</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Sil.</speaker>
                     <l>They tears of love not, but of pity, are.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Daph.</speaker>
                     <l>Pity to love is alwaies meſſenger,</l>
                     <l>As lightning to the thunder.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Chor.</speaker>
                     <l>Oft when reſt</l>
                     <l>He hidden ſeeks within a virgins breaſt,</l>
                     <l>Who had with too ſtrict honeſty before,</l>
                     <l>Againſt his ſly charms ſhut and barr'd the door:</l>
                     <l>He of mild pitie his fond ſervant takes</l>
                     <l>The ſhape and habit, and ſo entrance makes.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Daph.</speaker>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Silvia,</hi> theſe tears of love be, 'tis too plain</l>
                     <l>Art ſilent? doſt thou love? thou lov'ſt in vain:</l>
                     <l>O divine force of love! how juſtly thou</l>
                     <l>Chaſtiſeſt thoſe who don't thy pow'r avow!</l>
                     <l>Wretched <hi>Aminta!</hi> like the Bee who leaves</l>
                     <l>Sorrow to him he ſtings, but yet bereaves</l>
                     <l>Himſelf of life: ſo now thou victor art,</l>
                     <l>And dying wounded haſt that ſtony heart</l>
                     <l>Which living thou ne'r couldſt, and if thou be</l>
                     <l>A wandring ſpir't, as I believe, then ſee</l>
                     <l>Her tears, and though to thee all joy be paſt,</l>
                     <l>Rejoyce that thou haſt overcome at laſt.</l>
                     <l>Lover in life, belov'd in death; if thy</l>
                     <pb n="52" facs="tcp:115787:41"/>
                     <l>Eate 'twere not to be lov'd til thou didſt die,</l>
                     <l>Or if this cruel one at no leſſe price</l>
                     <l>Would ſell her love, then to him for it dies;</l>
                     <l>See thou haſt given her the price ſhe ſought,</l>
                     <l>And with thy early death, her love haſt bought.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Chor.</speaker>
                     <l>Dear price to him that gave it, but more griev-</l>
                     <l>Ous far (alas) to her did it receive.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Sil.</speaker>
                     <l>Could I but with my love his life re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gain,</l>
                     <l>Or with my life call him from death again!</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Daph.</speaker>
                     <l>Ah pitiful too late! and too late wiſe,</l>
                     <l>Pity aſſiſts not where fate help denies.</l>
                  </sp>
               </div>
               <div n="2" type="scene">
                  <pb n="53" facs="tcp:115787:41"/>
                  <head>Act. 4. Scen. 2.</head>
                  <stage>
                     <hi>Ergaſto Chore</hi> of <hi>Shepherds Silvia Daphne.</hi>
                  </stage>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Erg.</speaker>
                     <l>SO full my breaſt of pity is, and ſo</l>
                     <l>Clogd up with horror, that I do not know</l>
                     <l>Whither to turn me, nothing comes to ſight,</l>
                     <l>Nothing I hear, which doth not me affright.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Chor.</speaker>
                     <l>What newes brings our <hi>Ergaſto?</hi> ſure 'tis bad,</l>
                     <l>His countenance and accent both are ſad.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Erg.</speaker>
                     <l>I bring the ſad news of <hi>Aminta</hi>'s death:</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Sil.</speaker>
                     <l>Ay me!</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Erg.</speaker>
                     <l>The nobleſt ſhepherd that did breath</l>
                     <l>Within theſe woods; whoſe ſweet comport<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments were</l>
                     <l>Unto the nymphs, and muſes both, ſo dear.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Chor.</speaker>
                     <l>And is he dead? and how? relate that we</l>
                     <l>May his untimely end lament with thee.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Sil.</speaker>
                     <l>I dare not liſten to this ſad diſcourſe,</l>
                     <pb n="70" facs="tcp:115787:42"/>
                     <l>Nor yet go near to hear it, though of force</l>
                     <l>Hear it I muſt, wicked relentleſſe heart</l>
                     <l>Of mine, what fear'ſt thou? go receive that dart</l>
                     <l>Which he brings in his tongue; that ſo there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by</l>
                     <l>May be made known thy heartleſſe cruelty.</l>
                     <l>Shepherd I come a partner here to be</l>
                     <l>Of that grief, which thou promiſt's others, me</l>
                     <l>Perhaps it more concerns, and as a due</l>
                     <l>Debt of my rigor I receiv't from you.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Erg.</speaker>
                     <l>Nymph, I believe thee well; for at his death</l>
                     <l>He with thy name gave up his lateſt breath.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Daph.</speaker>
                     <l>Now begin this ſad ſtory.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Erg.</speaker>
                     <l>I ſurround</l>
                     <l>The Mount did with ſome nets, ſpread on the ground,</l>
                     <l>When, lo, <hi>Amintas</hi> paſſed by, and he</l>
                     <l>Was too much chang'd from what he us'd to be,</l>
                     <l>Too troubled, and too ſad; I ran and ſtaid</l>
                     <l>Him, though with much ado; he to me ſaid:</l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Ergaſto</hi> I'd intreat a courteſie</l>
                     <l>Of thee, 'tis this, to come along with me,</l>
                     <l>And be a witneſſe of what I ſhal do,</l>
                     <l>But this I ſhal requier firſt of you,</l>
                     <l>That by ſtreight oath your firmeſt faith you bind,</l>
                     <pb n="71" facs="tcp:115787:42"/>
                     <l>Neither to hinder nor oppoſe my mind;</l>
                     <l>I (for who could have thought ſo ſtrange a caſe,</l>
                     <l>Or ſuch mad fury?) let his will take place</l>
                     <l>And did conjure, <hi>Pan, Pales, Priapus,</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>And all thoſe gods are honour'd moſt by us;</l>
                     <l>He at my oaths went forward, and me led</l>
                     <l>There where the cliffy rock hangs o're it's head:</l>
                     <l>Road it was none, for there no path at all,</l>
                     <l>But from the mount, a precipice doth fall</l>
                     <l>Into th'adjacent valley; here a ſtop</l>
                     <l>We made, when I with looking from the top,</l>
                     <l>Such was the height, ſo level to the ground,</l>
                     <l>That with a giddineſſe my head turn'd round;</l>
                     <l>I ſtarted back, he ſmil'd to ſee me ſtart,</l>
                     <l>Which too much did aſſure my fearleſſe heart:</l>
                     <l>Then to me ſaid, <hi>Ergaſto,</hi> I'd have thee</l>
                     <l>Recount to Nymphs and Paſtors what thou'lt ſee,</l>
                     <l>So looking down began—
<q>
                           <l>
                              <hi>Had I here ready to my will,</hi>
                           </l>
                           <l>
                              <hi>The teeth of rav'nous wolves to ſpill</hi>
                           </l>
                           <l>
                              <hi>My blood, I'd onely chooſe that death,</hi>
                           </l>
                           <l>
                              <hi>By which ſhe di'd who was my breath:</hi>
                           </l>
                           <l>
                              <hi>They tear this body ſhould of mine,</hi>
                           </l>
                           <l>
                              <hi>As they did that fair corps of thine;</hi>
                           </l>
                           <l>
                              <hi>But ſince that heav'n is ſo unjuſt</hi>
                           </l>
                           <l>
                              <hi>As to deny, (though die I muſt)</hi>
                           </l>
                           <pb n="56" facs="tcp:115787:43"/>
                           <l>
                              <hi>My death deſired, nor will ſend</hi>
                           </l>
                           <l>
                              <hi>Fierce beaſts to help me to my end;</hi>
                           </l>
                           <l>
                              <hi>I'l find a death though not the due,</hi>
                           </l>
                           <l>
                              <hi>Shall end my life as ſoon as you.</hi>
                           </l>
                           <l>Silvia <hi>I come, I come to thee,</hi>
                           </l>
                           <l>
                              <hi>Diſdain not then my company;</hi>
                           </l>
                           <l>
                              <hi>Contentedly I ſhall endure</hi>
                           </l>
                           <l>
                              <hi>The ſharpeſt death, were I but ſure</hi>
                           </l>
                           <l>
                              <hi>'T would not again begin our ſtrife,</hi>
                           </l>
                           <l>
                              <hi>Thy anger ceas'd were with thy life.</hi>
                           </l>
                        </q>
                     </l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Silvia</speaker>
                     <l>I come, this ſaid: he in a trice</l>
                     <l>Threw himſelf down; I frozen ſtood like Ice.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Daph.</speaker>
                     <l>Wretched <hi>Aminta!</hi>
                     </l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Sil.</speaker>
                     <l>Ay poor me!</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Chor.</speaker>
                     <l>But why</l>
                     <l>Some way to hinder him didſt thou not try?</l>
                     <l>Perhaps thy promis'd oath did thee reſtrain.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Erg.</speaker>
                     <l>No; for, rejecting oaths in that caſe vain,</l>
                     <l>When I diſcern'd his purpoſe, though too late,</l>
                     <l>I ran to ſtay him; ſuch was his hard fate,</l>
                     <l>I onely caught this ſilken girdle here,</l>
                     <l>But he went with ſuch force it could not bear</l>
                     <l>His body's weight, and ſo it did remain</l>
                     <l>Thus broken in my hands.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Chor.</speaker>
                     <l>But what became</l>
                     <l>Of the unhappy corps?</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Erg.</speaker>
                     <l>That know not I,</l>
                     <l>I had not heart enough to ſee it lie:</l>
                     <pb n="57" facs="tcp:115787:43"/>
                     <l>(Pity and horror having fill'd the place)</l>
                     <l>So ſhattred into peeces.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Chor.</speaker>
                     <l>O ſtrange caſe!</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Sil.</speaker>
                     <l>If this newes kil's not me, my heart's of ſtone,</l>
                     <l>Or rather I believe that I have none;</l>
                     <l>Shall the falſe rumour of my death have ſuch</l>
                     <l>Power o're his life, whom I did hate ſo much?</l>
                     <l>And ſhall not his true death, who life did leave</l>
                     <l>For love of me, me of my life bereave?</l>
                     <l>It ſhall: and if that griefe can't do't, a knife,</l>
                     <l>Or elſe this girdle ſhall command my life;</l>
                     <l>This girdle left behind, alone to be</l>
                     <l>The juſt revenger of my cruelty;</l>
                     <l>Unhappy girdle of a Maſter farr</l>
                     <l>Unhappier, diſdaine not that you are</l>
                     <l>Lodg'd in this juſtly to thee hatefull breſt,</l>
                     <l>Since there thou as an inſtrument do'ſt reſt</l>
                     <l>Of that revenge, which is in juſtice due</l>
                     <l>To your ſo hapleſſe Maſter, and to you;</l>
                     <l>For ſince twas by my cruelty deni'd</l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Aminta</hi> ſhould my conſort here abide,</l>
                     <l>'Tis juſt I ſhould by work of thine be made</l>
                     <l>His conſort, in the ſweet <hi>Elizian</hi> ſhade.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Chor.</speaker>
                     <l>Comfort thy ſelfe poore wretch, thou fault haſt none</l>
                     <l>In this, but fault of fortune 'tis alone.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Sil.</speaker>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Shepherds,</hi> weep not for me, your tears you looſe,</l>
                     <pb n="74" facs="tcp:115787:44"/>
                     <l>Thoſe pity don't deſerve, who none did uſe,</l>
                     <l>Or if ye weep, his loſſe ye weep in vain,</l>
                     <l>Since that deſerves a far more dolefull ſtreine;</l>
                     <l>And thou too, <hi>Daphne,</hi> dry thoſe teares of thine,</l>
                     <l>If from no other cauſe they come than mine;</l>
                     <l>This ſ'd intreat thee do, not for my ſake,</l>
                     <l>But for his worthy was, the pains to take,</l>
                     <l>To go with me to ſee thoſe wretched bones,</l>
                     <l>I feare me, cruſh'd among the rocks and ſtones,</l>
                     <l>And helpe to bury them, and when that I</l>
                     <l>Have perform'd this, what ſhould I do but dy?</l>
                     <l>This office I'l repay him, ſince no more,</l>
                     <l>I can, for that great love which he me bore;</l>
                     <l>And though theſe hands of mine contami<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nate</l>
                     <l>Will this good work: yet ſince pernicious fate</l>
                     <l>Permits me only to do this; I know</l>
                     <l>It will be deare to him, he lov'd me ſo.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Daph.</speaker>
                     <l>Who would their help to ſuch a work deny?</l>
                     <l>But afterwards thou muſt not think to dy.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Sil.</speaker>
                     <l>Till now I liv'd, have to my ſelfe a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lone,</l>
                     <l>And to my cruelty, what reſts, to none</l>
                     <l>I'l live but to <hi>Aminta:</hi> and if fade,</l>
                     <l>My hopes do there, I'l live to his cold ſhade,</l>
                     <l>So long I'l live, till in one point can I</l>
                     <l>Finiſh his ſaddeſt obſequies, and dy;</l>
                     <pb n="75" facs="tcp:115787:44"/>
                     <l>Shepherd direct me, that I may not faile</l>
                     <l>To find the way which leads unto the vale;</l>
                     <l>Where ends that curſed precipice.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Erg.</speaker>
                     <l>You are</l>
                     <l>Juſt in the way, nor is it very far.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Daph.</speaker>
                     <l>Come, I'l go with thee, thou my foot-ſteps trace,</l>
                     <l>And I'l thee lead directly to the place.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Sil.</speaker>
                     <l>Then Shepherds, Nimphs, Meadows, and Plaines adieu;</l>
                     <l>Woods, Rivers, Fountains, all farewell to you.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Erg.</speaker>
                     <l>Alas! ſhe takes her leave with ſighs ſo ſore,</l>
                     <l>As if ſhe were reſolv'd to turn no more.</l>
                  </sp>
               </div>
               <div type="chorus">
                  <pb n="60" facs="tcp:115787:45"/>
                  <head>CHORUS.</head>
                  <lg>
                     <l>WHat death muſt yeeld, that love retains,</l>
                     <l>Thou peace's friend, he wars unkind,</l>
                     <l>Ever his triumphs, vaunts and reignes;</l>
                     <l>And whil'ſt thoudo'ſt twofair ſouls bind;</l>
                     <l>Thou rendr'ſt earth ſo like the heavenly ſphear,</l>
                     <l>That thou thy ſelfe deign'ſt to inhabit here;</l>
                     <l>There is no anger there above</l>
                     <l>And thou haſt mortal breſts inclin'd</l>
                     <l>By thy divineſt art of love;</l>
                     <l>To put all hatred out of mind;</l>
                     <l>And with a pow'r exceeding earthly Kings</l>
                     <l>Thou here below doſt govern mortall things.</l>
                  </lg>
               </div>
               <pb n="61" facs="tcp:115787:45"/>
            </div>
            <div type="act">
               <head>Act. 5.</head>
               <div n="1" type="scene">
                  <head>Scen. 1.</head>
                  <stage>
                     <hi>Elpine Chorus</hi> of <hi>Shepherds.</hi>
                  </stage>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Elp.</speaker>
                     <l>IN truth, the divine law by which love ſway's</l>
                     <l>His ſacred Empire is not hard nor ſtray's</l>
                     <l>In oblique paths, ſage providence the guide</l>
                     <l>Is of his workes, and all his actions glide</l>
                     <l>In deepeſt myſteries, ſee by what art</l>
                     <l>By what ſtrange uncouth meanes he leads a heart</l>
                     <l>To happineſſe! and when man thinks that he</l>
                     <l>Is now arriv'd at th' depth of miſery</l>
                     <l>And wretchedneſſe, why then the winged boy</l>
                     <l>Tranſports him to the paradiſe of joy:</l>
                     <l>Behold <hi>Aminta,</hi> by his fall aſcends</l>
                     <l>To his long wiſh'd-for, and deſired ends;</l>
                     <l>Happy <hi>Aminta,</hi> happy ſo much more,</l>
                     <l>By how much more miſ'rable thou before;</l>
                     <pb n="78" facs="tcp:115787:46"/>
                     <l>By thy example why ſhould I deſpaire,</l>
                     <l>But rather hope that cruell one, though faire,</l>
                     <l>Who under ſmiles of pity doth conceale</l>
                     <l>Her mortall rigor, now at length may heale</l>
                     <l>My wounded heart, and may true pity have</l>
                     <l>To cure that wound, her feigned pity gave.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Chor.</speaker>
                     <l>ſee how the ſage <hi>Elpino</hi> yonder walkes,</l>
                     <l>And to himſelfe of poor <hi>Aminta</hi> talkes,</l>
                     <l>As though he living were; he fortunate</l>
                     <l>And happy calls him, O the ſad eſtate</l>
                     <l>Of lovers! is his judgement ſo miſled,</l>
                     <l>To call thoſe happy, who find pity dead?</l>
                     <l>Is this the paradiſe of joy? is this</l>
                     <l>His wiſh'd contentment, his deſired bliſſe?</l>
                     <l>Is this the great reward, the greateſt eaſe</l>
                     <l>Love gives his ſervants? can this ſo much pleaſe?</l>
                     <l>Can this ſuffice? <hi>Elpino,</hi> is ſo bad,</l>
                     <l>Thy luck, that thou ſtil'ſt ſprtunate the ſad</l>
                     <l>Death of <hi>Aminta?</hi> ſuch an end do'ſt crave?</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Elp.</speaker>
                     <l>No Shepherds, no; but let your ſorrows have</l>
                     <l>An end; falſe the report is, he was dead.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Chor.</speaker>
                     <l>O! how much comfort hath this good new's bred?</l>
                     <l>Did he not then himſelfe precipitate?</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Elp.</speaker>
                     <l>He did, but his more than thrice bleſſed fate</l>
                     <l>Under deaths dolefull image did him give</l>
                     <pb n="79" facs="tcp:115787:46"/>
                     <l>Both life and joy: ſhepherds, he ſtill doth live,</l>
                     <l>And lives content; for now his head doth reſt</l>
                     <l>On his deare <hi>Nymphs</hi> ſo much deſired breſt;</l>
                     <l>She whom before, nor tears, nor ſighs could move</l>
                     <l>To pity him, is now as full of love,</l>
                     <l>Is now as mercifull; and from his ey's</l>
                     <l>With her own mouth his teares of joy ſhe dry's.</l>
                     <l>I go to ſeek her father, old <hi>Montane,</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>And to conduct him unto yonder plaine</l>
                     <l>Where they two be, for nothing to the ſill</l>
                     <l>Of their content there wants, but his good will.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Chor.</speaker>
                     <l>Equal their birth is, equal are their years</l>
                     <l>Their wills agree, and good <hi>Montane,</hi> who bears</l>
                     <l>Deſiers to have nephews, and to fence,</l>
                     <l>His drooping age with ſuch a ſweet defence,</l>
                     <l>Will make his will be theirs; but dear <hi>Elpine</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>Relate to us what fate, what god divine</l>
                     <l>Could of our poor <hi>Aminta</hi> ſuch care have</l>
                     <l>As might in that ſame deſp'rate fall him ſave.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Elp.</speaker>
                     <l>I am content to tell it, and no man</l>
                     <l>I'm ſure can tell it better then I can.</l>
                     <l>Juſt at the entrance of my cave ſtood I,</l>
                     <l>Which you know well at the hils foot doth lie;</l>
                     <l>I reaſoning was of her, who in a net</l>
                     <l>Firſt <hi>Thirſis</hi> caught, and after me, and yet</l>
                     <pb n="64" facs="tcp:115787:47"/>
                     <l>I did my thraldom far prefer above</l>
                     <l>His life of freedom, or his flight from love,</l>
                     <l>When a ſtrange voice our ears and ey's did call</l>
                     <l>Up to the top, from whence to ſee one fall,</l>
                     <l>And ſee him on a buſh of briers light,</l>
                     <l>Which ſtood in the mid-way, was all one ſight;</l>
                     <l>Nature had planted on the mountain's ſide</l>
                     <l>A ſett of thornes, ſo thick, that they ſeem'd ti'd,</l>
                     <l>Or wove together, here at firſt he fell,</l>
                     <l>Which, though 'twas like a net, yet could not well</l>
                     <l>His bodi's weight ſuſteine, but let him go</l>
                     <l>Quite through, that at our feet he fell; yet ſo</l>
                     <l>Much of the force and ſhock it took away,</l>
                     <l>That 'twas not mortall, only there he lay</l>
                     <l>Aſtoniſhed, and void of ſence. Amaz'd</l>
                     <l>We at the ſad chance ſtood, but when we gaz'd</l>
                     <l>More neerly on, and knew him, then our trouble,</l>
                     <l>Our ſorrow, and our anguiſh did redouble;</l>
                     <l>But to our griefe it was ſome ſmall repreive</l>
                     <l>That he was not quite dead, perhaps might live;</l>
                     <l>Then <hi>Thirſis</hi> t' me the ſecrets did diſco<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver</l>
                     <pb n="81" facs="tcp:115787:47"/>
                     <l>Of this diſconſolate and deſp'rate lover</l>
                     <l>We knowing 'twas in vain him to lament</l>
                     <l>Bethought a remedy; and while we ſent</l>
                     <l>For learned <hi>Eſculapius,</hi> whom <hi>Apollo</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>Taught, Phyſicks art when he him us'd to fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low:</l>
                     <l>At the ſame time he did on me beſtow</l>
                     <l>The skil to tune a harp, and bend a bow.</l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Silvia</hi> and <hi>Daphne</hi> thither ſeeking came</l>
                     <l>That body which they did believe was ſlain;</l>
                     <l>When <hi>Silvia</hi> ſaw <hi>Aminta</hi>'s cheeks once fair</l>
                     <l>Now void of life, now grown ſo pallid were,</l>
                     <l>So wan that the bleak violet diſplay's</l>
                     <l>Not half that paleneſſe ſcorch'd by <hi>Phoebus</hi> rayes:</l>
                     <l>She ſtupifi'd neer void of ſenſe doth reſt</l>
                     <l>Lamenting, crying, beating her fair breaſt</l>
                     <l>She on him falls, to take her lateſt kiſſe,</l>
                     <l>And joyn'd his face to hers, her mouth to his.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Chor.</speaker>
                     <l>Could ſhe that was ſo coy, now not re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrain</l>
                     <l>Her paſſion but extend the bounds of ſhame.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Elp.</speaker>
                     <l>Weak love is held by ſhame, but love grows bold</l>
                     <l>As ſtrong, what is it then can it with-hold:</l>
                     <l>She as though in her ey's ſhe did contain</l>
                     <l>Fountains of tears, did with ſuch plenty rain</l>
                     <l>Them on his cheeks, and they ſuch vertue had,</l>
                     <l>That it reviv'd again the breathleſſe lad;</l>
                     <l>His ey's he weakly opens, and he ſends</l>
                     <pb n="82" facs="tcp:115787:48"/>
                     <l>From his afflicted ſoule a ſigh, which ends</l>
                     <l>In his dear <hi>Silvia</hi>'s ſpirit, by her ſweet</l>
                     <l>Mouth it was catch't and ſeem'd with it to meet;</l>
                     <l>Her Echo quite enliv'ned him, but who</l>
                     <l>Could now declare the joy poſſeſt theſe two;</l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Aminta</hi> thought 'twas more then heav'nly charms,</l>
                     <l>That thus enclaſp'd him in his <hi>Silvia</hi>'s armes;</l>
                     <l>He that loves ſervant is, perhaps may gueſſe</l>
                     <l>Their bliſſe; but none there is can it expreſſe.</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Chor.</speaker>
                     <l>And is <hi>Aminta</hi> fully cur'd canſt tell?</l>
                     <l>No danger of his life?</l>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Elp.</speaker>
                     <l>He's fully well:</l>
                     <l>'Tis true he's ſomewhat bruis'd, but nothing he</l>
                     <l>Do's it account, and nothing it will be;</l>
                     <l>Thrice happy he who did ſo fully prove</l>
                     <l>Love's worſt, and now doth taſt the ſweets of love;</l>
                     <l>His ſufferings and his torments onely be</l>
                     <l>Sweet ſeaſonings of his felicitie.</l>
                     <l>Shepherds farewel. For I muſt once again</l>
                     <l>Make haſte to find out the good old <hi>Montane.</hi>
                     </l>
                  </sp>
               </div>
               <div type="chorus">
                  <pb n="83" facs="tcp:115787:48"/>
                  <head>CHORUS.</head>
                  <lg>
                     <l>CAn that Martyrdom he prov'd,</l>
                     <l>While he ſerv'd, and while he lov'd,</l>
                     <l>While he hop'd, while he diſpair'd,</l>
                     <l>While he ſigh'd, and while he car'd,</l>
                     <l>Ever recompenſed be</l>
                     <l>Though with joy's eternally?</l>
                     <l>What if ſweet things ſweeter more</l>
                     <l>Are when bitter go before?</l>
                     <l>What if good things better will</l>
                     <l>Be, if ſavour'd with ſome ill?</l>
                     <l>Yet <hi>Love</hi> I pray give me the leſſe</l>
                     <l>Not this greater bleſſedneſſe.</l>
                     <l>If thou wilt, bleſſe others ſo,</l>
                     <l>Who this full bliſſe crave to know:</l>
                     <l>But let me my nymph enjoy,</l>
                     <l>For a word or for a toy,</l>
                     <l>Without ſighs, and without care,</l>
                     <l>Without tears, without diſpair.</l>
                     <pb n="84" facs="tcp:115787:49"/>
                     <l>Let the ſeaſon'ngs of our love,</l>
                     <l>Such be as may onely move,</l>
                     <l>(Not ſuch torments or ſuch pain)</l>
                     <l>Sweet repulſes, ſweet diſdain;</l>
                     <l>To which kind kiſſes may ſucceed,</l>
                     <l>To ſhow our hearts are ſtill agreed.</l>
                  </lg>
                  <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
               </div>
            </div>
         </div>
         <div type="poems">
            <pb n="85" facs="tcp:115787:49"/>
            <head>Poems.</head>
            <div type="poem">
               <head>Lucretia (<hi>raviſhed by</hi> Sextus Tarquine) <hi>to her Husband</hi> Collatine <hi>and her Friends.</hi>
               </head>
               <lg>
                  <l>TO whom ſhould poor <hi>Lucretia</hi> bemoan,</l>
                  <l>Thoſe wrongs, that outrage ſhe has under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gon</l>
                  <l>But to the <hi>Collatine?</hi> no more ah me!</l>
                  <l>No more, no more! thy faithful ſpouſe is ſhe:</l>
                  <l>Since <hi>Sextus</hi> did my innocence invade,</l>
                  <l>And our chaſt bed a luſtful ſtew hath made;</l>
                  <l>If't be a ſin to ſuffer this; if't be</l>
                  <l>A fault to yield to forcing Tyranny,</l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Rome</hi> judge me guilty: but if will alone</l>
                  <l>In crimes be argu'd: then <hi>Lucrece</hi> has none;</l>
                  <l>My body onely he defil'd, but ſtil</l>
                  <l>My purer mind reſts guiltleſſe from the ill;</l>
                  <l>Nor ever did my noble ſoul yet move</l>
                  <l>One footſtep from it's loyal conſtant love;</l>
                  <l>I ne'r had thought to nuptial rights unjuſt,</l>
                  <l>Nor ever did invite proud <hi>Tarquins</hi> luſt;</l>
                  <l>Nor ſought he like a lover to prevail,</l>
                  <l>But like a bloody Tyrant did aſſaile</l>
                  <pb n="86" facs="tcp:115787:50"/>
                  <l>My chaſtity: I him eſteem'd a foe</l>
                  <l>But yet did pleaſe him whe'r I would or no:</l>
                  <l>The <hi>Graecian</hi> Dames lamented <hi>Helens</hi> fate,</l>
                  <l>Curſ'd him that ſacred bed did violate:</l>
                  <l>You <hi>Latine</hi> matrons my hard hap bemoan,</l>
                  <l>We have a <hi>Roman Paris;</hi> nor alone</l>
                  <l>Is <hi>Troy</hi> of ſuch faults guilty, great mens crimes</l>
                  <l>Grow ſtill and follow'd are by future times.</l>
                  <l>What ſhall I do? no longer ſhal I be</l>
                  <l>Now fam'd amongſt the Dames for chaſtity.</l>
                  <l>I may be ſtil'd a Matron, but no more,</l>
                  <l>An undefiled Matron, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>s before:</l>
                  <l>Yet I am guiltleſſe: and his force made foul</l>
                  <l>My body onely, but ne'r touch't my ſoul.</l>
                  <l>Doubt not ye <hi>Romans;</hi> for you ſtreight ſhal ſee</l>
                  <l>A certain token of my conſtancy;</l>
                  <l>I'l give you a ſure ſign, for ſince deprive</l>
                  <l>His force did me of fame, I will not live;</l>
                  <l>But by my own hands dying will proclaim</l>
                  <l>His horrid wickedneſſe and my juſt fame.</l>
                  <l>They ſhan't point at <hi>Lucretia;</hi> ne'r will I</l>
                  <l>Leave to the <hi>Roman</hi> Dames a memory</l>
                  <l>That ſhal reproach them, nor can I give way</l>
                  <l>To let ſuſpicion feign what ere ſhe may;</l>
                  <l>This my magnanimous right hand ſhal be</l>
                  <l>The ſteerer of my faith, my chaſtity;</l>
                  <l>The Princes ſtrong hand and his violent armes</l>
                  <l>Infolded me in theſe reproachful harms;</l>
                  <l>My violent hand ſhal my redeemer be,</l>
                  <l>And this ſharp ſteel ſhal from them ſet me free:</l>
                  <pb n="87" facs="tcp:115787:50"/>
                  <l>We'l not unto our Country be a ſtain,</l>
                  <l>Nor give the wicked ſamples to profane</l>
                  <l>The ſacred mariage rites, never from me</l>
                  <l>Shall <hi>Rome</hi> a ſad example take to be</l>
                  <l>Subject to willing Tyranny: nay more</l>
                  <l>Perhaps my rape her freedom may reſtore;</l>
                  <l>When ages yet to come ſhall praiſe my name,</l>
                  <l>And if not patient, noble me proclaim:</l>
                  <l>In Brothers blood the firſt of Tyrants dies</l>
                  <l>His wals. this offers as a Sacrifice</l>
                  <l>A raviſh'd ſpouſes blood, that <hi>Tibers</hi> ſhore</l>
                  <l>May ſtain'd be both with male and female gore;</l>
                  <l>Thou Father take in hand thy dart, thou <hi>Brute</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>No more refuſe to act, no more be mute,</l>
                  <l>Nor let unpuniſh'd go ſuch curſed crimes,</l>
                  <l>But like a man revenge them; now the times</l>
                  <l>Of thy feign'd madneſſe ceaſe: he whoſe ſtrong hand</l>
                  <l>Could overcome a woman, yet can't ſtand</l>
                  <l>Before you armed men, thus onely eaſe</l>
                  <l>And thus alone dear <hi>Collatine</hi> appeaſe</l>
                  <l>Thou maiſt my ghoſt; let not th' adult'rer ſcape</l>
                  <l>The juſt reward of his moſt horrid rape;</l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Theſtiad's</hi> ſword was by <hi>Oreſtes</hi> head</l>
                  <l>Made famous: he defil'd his fathers bed.</l>
                  <l>I guiltleſſe liv'd, and in that title die,</l>
                  <l>Yet my fame loſt no longer live will I.</l>
               </lg>
            </div>
            <div type="poem">
               <pb n="88" facs="tcp:115787:51"/>
               <head>Vetruria <hi>to her Son,</hi> Cn. Martius Coriolanus, <hi>about to raiſe civil war againſt his Countrey.</hi>
               </head>
               <lg>
                  <l>WHat horrid madneſs do's thy brains infeſt,</l>
                  <l>Thus to diſturb thy countries quiet reſt</l>
                  <l>With hoſtile arms? what! canſt thou think it good</l>
                  <l>To die a <hi>Latian</hi> dart in <hi>Roman</hi> blood?</l>
                  <l>Or canſt imagine <hi>Romes</hi> injurious hate</l>
                  <l>Deſerves to be reveng'd at ſuch a rate?</l>
                  <l>Conſider, <hi>Martius,</hi> by this diſmal ſtrife,</l>
                  <l>Thou cut'ſt the thred of thy <hi>Volumnia</hi>'s life;</l>
                  <l>And whilſt thou doſt revenge thy private ill</l>
                  <l>Thou her who firſt gave life to thee doſt kil;</l>
                  <l>What can thy fury make ſo foul a breach?</l>
                  <l>Can envy, hatred, malice, thus far reach?</l>
                  <l>And can that venerable name of <hi>Rome</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>Now in thy heart find no reſpectful room?</l>
                  <l>Wilt turn ſon to an en'my, make me ſhare,</l>
                  <l>To be a conſort in this bloody war?</l>
                  <l>Thoſe Cities thou deſtroy'ſt are ours, each field</l>
                  <l>W<hi rend="sup">ch</hi> thou laiſt waſt doth us our comforts yeild;</l>
                  <l>Thoſe wals which thou ſeekſt todeface are mine,</l>
                  <l>Thy wif's, thy childrens, friends, nay very thine;</l>
                  <pb n="89" facs="tcp:115787:51"/>
                  <l>Let great <hi>Romes</hi> people guilty be, who did</l>
                  <l>Baniſh the man had been their glorious head;</l>
                  <l>The matrons guiltleſſe are; with one accord</l>
                  <l>They damn'd the wickedneſſe: and all afford</l>
                  <l>Curſes to thoſe baſe <hi>Tribunes</hi> which ſhe ſent</l>
                  <l>To exile, and in vain theſe wars lament.</l>
                  <l>Conſider yet, theſe, thy wife, children, I,</l>
                  <l>Amongſt thy unjuſt foes intangled lie;</l>
                  <l>Thou with our danger ſeek'ſt revenge: and we</l>
                  <l>Though not in guilt, in it muſt partners be;</l>
                  <l>Seekſt thou thus to embrace me? thus entwine</l>
                  <l>Me in thine arms? alas! they are not thine</l>
                  <l>They are my foes: and now thy mother I</l>
                  <l>By thee ſhal led be to Captivitie:</l>
                  <l>I for thy triumphs am deſign'd, and round</l>
                  <l>About thy armed bands muſt be led bound.</l>
                  <l>Thoſe armes that us'd to reach the dug to thee,</l>
                  <l>By hoſtile armes muſt now inforced be.</l>
                  <l>Thoſe houſhold gods thou uſed'ſt to adore,</l>
                  <l>By armed fury wil be trampled o're;</l>
                  <l>The harmleſs child muſt with the reſt be flain,</l>
                  <l>The guiltleſs receive part o'th'guilty's pain;</l>
                  <l>For this brought I thee forth (ah luckleſs day)</l>
                  <l>That thou mighteſt to the <hi>Volſcians</hi> us betray?</l>
                  <l>Am I cauſe of this evil? muſt my name,</l>
                  <l>Great <hi>Romulus?</hi> eclipſe thy Empires fame,</l>
                  <l>Since from my bowels iſſued that fierce boy,</l>
                  <l>Who ſeeks his native Country to deſtroy:</l>
                  <l>Wil't make me guilty of this, <hi>Martius?</hi> why</l>
                  <l>Shouldſt thou thus ſtrive to make me baſely die?</l>
                  <pb n="90" facs="tcp:115787:52"/>
                  <l>Nay this thy crime being by thy Country laid</l>
                  <l>Unto my charge will ſure diſturb my ſhade;</l>
                  <l>Were I an exul too! 'twould ne'r grieve me,</l>
                  <l>To die by any one but onely ſhe:</l>
                  <l>Disband dear <hi>Martius</hi> yet thy mighty powers</l>
                  <l>And be pleas'd with us: ſee thoſe lofty towers</l>
                  <l>Long ſince by <hi>Romulus</hi> erected: ſee</l>
                  <l>Thoſe ſtately Temples; reliques: let theſe be</l>
                  <l>Thy ſweet appeaſers, but if they won't move</l>
                  <l>Thee, yet think once more of thy kindreds love;</l>
                  <l>'Twill be a ſhame to thee if thou ſhouldſt have</l>
                  <l>Her to thy wife who will be then thy ſlave;</l>
                  <l>Or what great honor thinkſt thou wilt thou gain,</l>
                  <l>When thy dear mother captive doth remain:</l>
                  <l>Be wiſe, though angry, let not fury throw</l>
                  <l>Thee on deſigns whereby no praiſe doth grow;</l>
                  <l>If nothing elſe, yet let our tears thee move,</l>
                  <l>Mans ſuppl'ant tears will bend the mighty <hi>Jove;</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>But if my ſighs and cries can't thee ſuſpend</l>
                  <l>From ſuch vile act'ons: if thy wife contemn'd</l>
                  <l>Be by thee; if thy gods get no reſpect;</l>
                  <l>Or if thy Countries name thou doſt reject:</l>
                  <l>Turn thy ſword in my bowels, let me feel</l>
                  <l>The ſharpeſt force of thy revenging ſteel.</l>
                  <l>Thoſe who before the mighty <hi>Rome</hi> did fear,</l>
                  <l>(The <hi>Vejans</hi> and <hi>Faliſc ans</hi>) now will jeer;</l>
                  <l>How will the <hi>Samnites</hi> laugh to ſee that none</l>
                  <l>Can overcome great <hi>Rome,</hi> but ſhe alone?</l>
                  <l>How willingly ſhal I conſent to die,</l>
                  <l>Rather than ſee my Countries miſery.</l>
               </lg>
            </div>
            <div type="poem">
               <pb n="91" facs="tcp:115787:52"/>
               <head>Cataline <hi>Exhorting his Souldiers to fight with</hi> Anthony.</head>
               <lg>
                  <l>HEre ſtand we fortune: nor haſt thou us gi'n</l>
                  <l>A Captain who hath dull or ſloathful bin;</l>
                  <l>What though the <hi>Romans</hi> are content to ſerve;</l>
                  <l>And from their ancient noble tenents ſwerve?</l>
                  <l>I by theſe wars chooſe rather to proclaim,</l>
                  <l>My man-like ſoule craves liberty or fame;</l>
                  <l>He onely ha's true honour who dare die</l>
                  <l>Rather than live in endleſſe ſlavery;</l>
                  <l>And dying thus to ſhun a ſervile ſhame,</l>
                  <l>Looſing his life wins honour to his name.</l>
                  <l>What though my harder fortune may deny</l>
                  <l>To my full hopes ſucceſſe or victory:</l>
                  <l>My daring and illuſtrious ſoul ſhall be,</l>
                  <l>For ever famous to poſteritie;</l>
                  <l>Then let our onely hope of triumph rear</l>
                  <l>Our free-born ſouls and make them void of fear;</l>
                  <l>Why ſhould we tremble at the <hi>Conſuls</hi> ſword,</l>
                  <l>Or be obedient to the <hi>Senates</hi> word,</l>
                  <l>Since we maintain that they no <hi>Senate</hi> be,</l>
                  <l>But meer uſurpers of our liberty:</l>
                  <l>Why ſhould the mighty <hi>Rome</hi> fear <hi>Cato?</hi> why</l>
                  <pb n="92" facs="tcp:115787:53"/>
                  <l>Should it to <hi>Piſo Craſſus</hi> ſubject lie?</l>
                  <l>W'are <hi>Romans</hi> too, and from the ſelf ſame race</l>
                  <l>The footſteps of the fam'd <hi>Aeneas</hi> trace:</l>
                  <l>They'are not alone <hi>Quirinus</hi> off-ſpring, nor</l>
                  <l>Are they alone ſprung from the god of war;</l>
                  <l>We from the ſame ſtock do deſcend, and claim</l>
                  <l>Right in the glories of our grandſires name:</l>
                  <l>Why ſhould they ful with gold their treaſures make?</l>
                  <l>Why we oppreſt with poverty? they rake</l>
                  <l>And ſqueeze the people to increaſe their gains,</l>
                  <l>Our riches are the fruits due to our pains;</l>
                  <l>They with their prouder faces do command,</l>
                  <l>And boaſt dominion o'r both ſea and land;</l>
                  <l>Are we by birth or courage leſſe then they?</l>
                  <l>Or have we no ſoul left but to obey?</l>
                  <l>Why ſhould not they to us obedience ſhew,</l>
                  <l>Or why ſhould they deſpiſe me thus? why you?</l>
                  <l>Are we thy laughing-ſtock proud <hi>Rome?</hi> muſt we</l>
                  <l>Be thus neglected and contemn'd by thee?</l>
                  <l>Whilſt ſome with an inſulting ſtate do go</l>
                  <l>Bearing the mace before um, others flow</l>
                  <l>With heapt-upriches, theſe uſurp the Laws,</l>
                  <l>And at their pleaſure deal in every cauſe;</l>
                  <l>Such is their pride: the <hi>Conſul</hi> ſeems to be</l>
                  <l>Subject unto the <hi>Tribunes</hi> tyranny;</l>
                  <l>When we like Cyphers ſtand, and void of ſtate</l>
                  <l>Neglected lie like minds degenerate:</l>
                  <l>Theſe live in ſtately marble ſtructures, we</l>
                  <l>Muſt with poor cottages contented be,</l>
                  <l>Theſe ſtrive their Empire ſtil to magnifie,</l>
                  <pb n="93" facs="tcp:115787:53"/>
                  <l>And ſtretch their vaſt dominions to the sky;</l>
                  <l>We wanting all things miſerably poor,</l>
                  <l>Are forc'd both cold and hungry to endure;</l>
                  <l>For this did nature us produce? or thus</l>
                  <l>To live? is this the fate aſſigned us?</l>
                  <l>Muſt we thus ſuffer? No, it ſhal not be</l>
                  <l>Our ſwords from what the gods themſelves de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cree</l>
                  <l>Shal free us: he who bears a noble ſoul,</l>
                  <l>May deſtiny and fate it ſelf controul;</l>
                  <l>Fortune aſſiſts the bold: let's not incite</l>
                  <l>It's frowns, nor our own ſlavery invite</l>
                  <l>By coward-minds; nor looſe by our vain ſloth,</l>
                  <l>The gaining <hi>Rome,</hi> or liberty, or both.</l>
                  <l>The hopes of gold imbolden ſome mens breaſts,</l>
                  <l>Which an inſatiate cov'touſueſſe infeſts;</l>
                  <l>But let your courage ſpring from thoughts more high</l>
                  <l>It is your own; your country's liberty</l>
                  <l>You crave and fight for; here you nobly gain</l>
                  <l>Honour which truly do's requite your pain;</l>
                  <l>I'l be both Souldier, and your General,</l>
                  <l>Nor me Commander but Companion call;</l>
                  <l>To <hi>Roman</hi> tyrants I'l their pride make known,</l>
                  <l>And wil revenge, hers, your wrongs, and my own</l>
                  <l>This hand devoted to my Countries health</l>
                  <l>Shal fight for you; this ſhal reſtore your wealth:</l>
                  <l>Revenge the altars of the gods through death</l>
                  <l>And ſlaughters, give <hi>Rome</hi> new &amp; freeborn breath</l>
                  <l>Go then, and with couragious minds aſſaile,</l>
                  <l>The <hi>Conſuls</hi> tents, and doubt not to prevail.</l>
                  <l>Hope in the Victor-gods: now only force</l>
                  <pb n="94" facs="tcp:115787:54"/>
                  <l>Convenes, ſloth hurts, nor muſt ye have remorſe,</l>
                  <l>Or being <hi>Romans, Romans</hi> fear to kil.</l>
                  <l>Pity's good after fight, before 'tis ill.</l>
                  <l>Unbridled fury now of all helps beſt;</l>
                  <l>And fear to kil, denotes too baſe a breaſt;</l>
                  <l>But whoſoe'r he be that fears to die,</l>
                  <l>Half dead already is, to death more nigh;</l>
                  <l>There is no hope in flight, a double hoſt</l>
                  <l>With all their pow'r on each ſide doth accoſt</l>
                  <l>Our tents: the <hi>Alpes</hi> encompaſſe us half round,</l>
                  <l>The <hi>Conſul</hi> is poſſeſſ'd of yonder ground;</l>
                  <l>That ſide preſents <hi>Metellus</hi> to our ſight,</l>
                  <l>There is no way of ſafety but by fight:</l>
                  <l>Go on then bravely let your ſharp ſwords find</l>
                  <l>A paſſage through them, he that ha's a mind</l>
                  <l>To fight may ſcape, at leaſt he'l nobly die,</l>
                  <l>Not like a carcaſe unrevenged lie:</l>
                  <l>Then let not fear ſurpriſe your hearts, be bold,</l>
                  <l>The <hi>Roman</hi> people ſhal as wel behold</l>
                  <l>The ſlaughter of their own, as ours, and he</l>
                  <l>That drinks this blood with his 't ſhal mixed be;</l>
                  <l>And though they Victors are, they ſhal not boaſt,</l>
                  <l>But rather weep the bloody conqueſts coſt.</l>
               </lg>
            </div>
            <div type="poem">
               <pb n="95" facs="tcp:115787:54"/>
               <head>Mutius Scaevola <hi>to</hi> Porſenna, <hi>when killing his Secretary inſtead of him be was taken.</hi>
               </head>
               <lg>
                  <l>BEhold grim Tyrant, here before thee ſtands,</l>
                  <l>A man had been thy death, had not theſe hands</l>
                  <l>Prov'd Traitors to my mind: had made that grave</l>
                  <l>Been thine; which now's prepared for thy ſlave.</l>
                  <l>If <hi>Scaevola</hi> muſt undergo deaths doom,</l>
                  <l>There's none but will write guiltleſſe on his tomb:</l>
                  <l>I ſet upon with fearleſſe courage thoſe</l>
                  <l>Who were our Capitols, our Countries foes;</l>
                  <l>Why are the heav'ns then thus againſt me bent?</l>
                  <l>And not propit'ous to my brave intent?</l>
                  <l>What! are the gods aſham'd to lend their aid?</l>
                  <l>Or are they of this Tyrants pow'r afraid?</l>
                  <l>Or have the fates reſerved him that he</l>
                  <l>In future triumphs might a trophie be?</l>
                  <pb n="96" facs="tcp:115787:55"/>
                  <l>What e'r 'twas made them thus 'gainſt me con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpire,</l>
                  <l>It grieves my ſoul it had not it's deſire;</l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Etruria</hi> ſee what ſouls the <hi>Romans</hi> bear,</l>
                  <l>Admire the noble acts the <hi>Latians</hi> dare;</l>
                  <l>Long after me that wil this fact yet do</l>
                  <l>There comes another and another too;</l>
                  <l>There want not thoſe who hope to ſay they wore</l>
                  <l>A lawrel died in thy crimſon gore:</l>
                  <l>What though thy Camp lies free from our alarms,</l>
                  <l>And ſpoils our fields with unrevenged harms;</l>
                  <l>We ſcorn with baſer blood to ſtain a dart,</l>
                  <l>O King, that's onely level'd at thy heart:</l>
                  <l>Our nobler ſwords wil drink the blood of none,</l>
                  <l>But thy heart blood, <hi>Porſenna,</hi> thine alone;</l>
                  <l>Thoſe who their hands wil ſtrait in it imbrue,</l>
                  <l>Walk intermixed with thy armed crew.</l>
                  <l>Methinks I ſee at preſent one thee note,</l>
                  <l>Who ſtrait wil hide his weapon in thy throat;</l>
                  <l>Hence therfore think each hower of thy breath,</l>
                  <l>To be the aſſured hower of thy death;</l>
                  <l>Thou doſt with warlike troups our wals ſur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>round,</l>
                  <l>Hoping to lay them level with the ground,</l>
                  <l>And think'ſt to famiſh us whilſt o'r thy head</l>
                  <l>Hangs a revengeful arm wilſtrike thee dead;</l>
                  <l>That glorious Diadem which now I ſee</l>
                  <l>Circles thy brow was hop'd a ſpoil by me;</l>
                  <l>That purple robe inveſts thy loins ſhal lie,</l>
                  <pb n="97" facs="tcp:115787:55"/>
                  <l>Thy blood be tinged in a deeper dy;</l>
                  <l>That very ſcepter which thy hand ſuſtains,</l>
                  <l>Shal, turn'd a club, daſh out thy curſed brains;</l>
                  <l>Now Rule, now Lord and King it, with this fate</l>
                  <l>Expecting ſtill the period of thy date.</l>
                  <l>Methinks I ſee how on thy curled brow,</l>
                  <l>Self-rendring vengeance ſits inthron'd, and how</l>
                  <l>Thy thoughts already tear me; yet I feel</l>
                  <l>No horror, nor my frighted body reel,</l>
                  <l>No trembling in my joynts: know, King, I can</l>
                  <l>Both do and ſuffer 'bove the reach of man:</l>
                  <l>In freeborn ſouls pale terror never ſtood</l>
                  <l>In competition with thier Countries good;</l>
                  <l>Thoſe ſouls in whom aſpiring fame her ſphear</l>
                  <l>Hath plac't, neglect the precipice of fear.</l>
                  <l>This ſacred Altar, theſe pure fires ſhal be</l>
                  <l>Witneſſe of our undaunted conſtancy;</l>
                  <l>This hand to <hi>Roman</hi> freedom ſo unjuſt,</l>
                  <l>Shal for it's pennance be conſum'd to duſt;</l>
                  <l>Nor is it cruel, but moſt right it's doom,</l>
                  <l>Since liberty it could not yeild to <hi>Rome.</hi>
                  </l>
               </lg>
            </div>
            <div type="poem">
               <pb n="98" facs="tcp:115787:56"/>
               <head>On a Lady ſick of the ſmal pox.</head>
               <lg>
                  <l>LEt thoſe whoſe tow'ring thoughts can from the ſpring</l>
                  <l>Of <hi>Helicon</hi> their high-flown fancies bring,</l>
                  <l>Invoke their muſe, and in their loftier ſtrains</l>
                  <l>Diſtill thoſe ſtreams that flow from nobler veins,</l>
                  <l>My grov'ling muſe ne'r knew what meant the fire</l>
                  <l>Of a Poetick rapture, till mine ire,</l>
                  <l>When envious ſickneſſe ſeiſ'd ſo fair a frame,</l>
                  <l>Conſtrain'd me thus to burſt into a flame:</l>
                  <l>And ſhall baſe ſcab I at thy malice chide,</l>
                  <l>Or thy poor ſilly impudence deride?</l>
                  <l>Alas! becauſe that of't thoſe roſean buds,</l>
                  <l>Which ſooner then the reſt throw off their hoods</l>
                  <l>To ſhew their native beauty, and diſplay</l>
                  <l>Their modeſt bluſhes to the early <hi>May,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>Are nipt by ſuddain froſts like thoſe that meet,</l>
                  <l>When freed from ſwathling bands, their winding ſheet</l>
                  <l>Doſt think therfore that thy malicious ſpite</l>
                  <l>Can check the dawnings of her beauteous light?</l>
                  <l>Which ſhines eradiant as the day when born,</l>
                  <l>On the wing'd ſhoulders of a clearer morn;</l>
                  <pb n="99" facs="tcp:115787:56"/>
                  <l>Hadſt thou attempted on ſome meaner face,</l>
                  <l>Where beauties luſtre ſhone with common grace;</l>
                  <l>It might have yeilded when thou didſt aſſaile:</l>
                  <l>But here thy poyſon can no more prevaile</l>
                  <l>Than can that ſable mantle, which the night</l>
                  <l>Draws o'r the world, and ſo preſents our ſight,</l>
                  <l>Thoſe leſſer fires not ceaſe to be no more,</l>
                  <l>When glitt'ring <hi>Phaebus</hi> guilds the Eaſtern ſhore:</l>
                  <l>But ſtay, perhaps it was not malice made</l>
                  <l>Thy noxious heat thus boldly to invade</l>
                  <l>Such matchleſſe beauty. <hi>Sol</hi> himſelf began</l>
                  <l>With anxious envy to look pale and wan,</l>
                  <l>And fearing leſt hereafter ſhould ariſe</l>
                  <l>Such ſplendor from the ſun-ſhine of her ey's,</l>
                  <l>As ſhould obſcure and dark his glory, ſent</l>
                  <l>Strait out of policy an inſtrument,</l>
                  <l>To damp that brightneſs and eclipſe thoſe raies,</l>
                  <l>Which he foreſaw would rob him of his bayes;</l>
                  <l>'Twas wiſely done! could that judicious head</l>
                  <l>Which comprehends all wit be thus miſ-led?</l>
                  <l>Sure he forgot how that his beams do uſe</l>
                  <l>To clear thoſe miſts which oft do circunfuſe</l>
                  <l>His ſplendid orb, and dart with greater light</l>
                  <l>Through darkneſs would obſcure the day with night:</l>
                  <l>So having clear'd thoſe miſts ſhe will appear,</l>
                  <l>A Sun more bright in beauties Hemiſphear.</l>
               </lg>
            </div>
            <div type="poem">
               <pb n="100" facs="tcp:115787:57"/>
               <head>In praiſe of a Conſtable.</head>
               <lg>
                  <l>ALas alas! ſee how my muſe</l>
                  <l>Ha's broke her ham-ſtrings, ſlipt her nooſe,</l>
                  <l>Her fancy tow'rs aloft, nor will</l>
                  <l>A common ſubject pleaſe her quill;</l>
                  <l>She's like thoſe rev'rend Sirs which preach</l>
                  <l>What's far above their wiſdoms reach,</l>
                  <l>As if their nonſenſe had the merit,</l>
                  <l>To have it father'd on ſome ſpirit:</l>
                  <l>She'l ſing a theme'bove what ſhe's able,</l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>John Petty Tyrant the Conſtable:</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>But ſee alas ſhe's big with doubt,</l>
                  <l>Some zealous mid-wife help her out,</l>
                  <l>That ſhe may firſt be brought to bed</l>
                  <l>Of his light horn, or his light head;</l>
                  <l>Thanks Sir, it's done, nor thinks ſhe ſcorn</l>
                  <l>In the firſt file to rank his horn;</l>
                  <l>In hopes ſhe may be the Recorder,</l>
                  <l>That he's dub'd knight o'th' forked order;</l>
                  <l>Hail then, Sir <hi>John,</hi> and think't no wipe,</l>
                  <l>You ſhal have th'pot, your wife the pipe,</l>
                  <l>What would you roſt your noſe and ey's,</l>
                  <l>And have her freeze between the thighs?</l>
                  <pb n="101" facs="tcp:115787:57"/>
                  <l>You'l repreſent his Highneſſe grace,</l>
                  <l>Let ſome Sir then ſupply your place.</l>
                  <l>But hark methinks the clocks go twelve,</l>
                  <l>Let's up and ſeek thoſe fairy elves</l>
                  <l>Which us'd to riot in the night,</l>
                  <l>Becauſe by day their purſe is light,</l>
                  <l>Who (maids) do uſe to deal their knocks,</l>
                  <l>Not pinch your arms, but pick your locks:</l>
                  <l>Hobgoblins which do uſe to ſcare</l>
                  <l>A miſer worſe than Bull or Bear;</l>
                  <l>He's up and like a brave Commander,</l>
                  <l>Who's wit would ſhame my Grandams gander;</l>
                  <l>Firſt with the choiceſt of his crew</l>
                  <l>He mans his fort, ſets ſome perdieu;</l>
                  <l>Then ranks the reſt, and ſo they go</l>
                  <l>As ſtout as hares to ſtart the foe;</l>
                  <l>Thus they march, but by his ſide,</l>
                  <l>A brave Eſquire of mickle pride,</l>
                  <l>Who with quick eye and prickt-up ear,</l>
                  <l>Firſt finds out what doth cauſe their fear.</l>
                  <l>'Twas this <hi>Lynceus</hi> piercing eye,</l>
                  <l>A hideous Monſter doth eſpie,</l>
                  <l>Which he beholds with ſtart up hairs</l>
                  <l>Devoutly falling to his pray'rs.</l>
                  <l>And then almoſt half dead cries out,</l>
                  <l>Unto the reſt of the bold rout:</l>
                  <l>Oh Sirs we're dead, ha'ye made your wils?</l>
                  <l>Oh diſmal night, prepare your bils,</l>
                  <l>The Monſter looks moſt wrath and wood,</l>
                  <l>As if he meant to ſuck your blood;</l>
                  <pb n="102" facs="tcp:115787:58"/>
                  <l>We better had fierce Lions meet,</l>
                  <l>It's dire <hi>Sir Backbite many feet,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>What ſhall we do alack, alack,</l>
                  <l>He ha's th' Conſtable by the back,</l>
                  <l>At which words their ſtout Generall</l>
                  <l>Through valour lets his weapon fall,</l>
                  <l>Being of a couragious mind</l>
                  <l>Diſcharg'd a Lulloim behind,</l>
                  <l>Which miſt the foe, my muſe ſuppoſes,</l>
                  <l>And yet aſſailed all their noſes;</l>
                  <l>Some cri'd the gun was foul and ſtank,</l>
                  <l>Becauſe the powder was too dank,</l>
                  <l>By his quick fall my muſe ſtil boaded,</l>
                  <l>That he the gun had overloaded;</l>
                  <l>Which ſo recoiled at the blow,</l>
                  <l>It made him fall beneath the foe,</l>
                  <l>At which their fear redoubled, and</l>
                  <l>Like men bereft of ſenſe they ſtand,</l>
                  <l>Till at the length one ſtout as ſteel</l>
                  <l>Doth pluck his heart out of his heel;</l>
                  <l>And apprehends the foe, their cries</l>
                  <l>In his applauſe ſtrait rend the skies:</l>
                  <l>Some ſaid he was Sir <hi>George</hi> alone,</l>
                  <l>Some the ſev'n Champions all in one,</l>
                  <l>No living man, they all agree,</l>
                  <l>Could do ſuch feats of Chivalry;</l>
                  <l>Whilſt thus they echo out his praiſe,</l>
                  <l>One charitably ſeeks to raiſe</l>
                  <l>Their leader, who, he ſtrait doth find,</l>
                  <l>Ha's ſhot before and eke behind:</l>
                  <pb n="103" facs="tcp:115787:58"/>
                  <l>He then with kind words doth him greet,</l>
                  <l>But finds his heart ſtuck in his teeth;</l>
                  <l>Amazed then he puls in haſte</l>
                  <l>A bottle from beneath his waſte;</l>
                  <l>Unſtops and dext'rouſly let flies</l>
                  <l>Streams of ſtrong-waters in his eyes,</l>
                  <l>And ſo recall'd his fleeting ſoul,</l>
                  <l>Their joy then ſounds without controul;</l>
                  <l>They now march back to th' Cittadel,</l>
                  <l>And on the pris'ners quarters fell;</l>
                  <l>Some would condemn him to the jaile,</l>
                  <l>Some ſhow their teeth, and ſome their naile;</l>
                  <l>Their Gen'ral, who had art at will,</l>
                  <l>Would have him thruſt through with a bill;</l>
                  <l>They all concluded with a ſhout,</l>
                  <l>He had the wiſeſt judgement out,</l>
                  <l>So ſtrait they choſe from out the reſt</l>
                  <l>One whom they did eſteem the beſt,</l>
                  <l>For he had long be a tride fighter,</l>
                  <l>And had deſtroy'd Sir <hi>Skip Backbiter,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>This monſter Couſin <hi>Germain,</hi> and</l>
                  <l>Now takes his lance into his hand,</l>
                  <l>Shakes it, and with career doth run</l>
                  <l>More fierce than e'r did knight o'th' Sun,</l>
                  <l>And with the ſhock o'rethrows the foe, who lies</l>
                  <l>Rowling o'th' ground, gives up the ghoſt &amp; dies;</l>
                  <l>And now, my friends, 'twas my intent,</l>
                  <l>But that the night is ſo far ſpent,</l>
                  <l>T' interr the monſter, and to write</l>
                  <l>A full relation of the fight,</l>
                  <pb n="104" facs="tcp:115787:59"/>
                  <l>On's tomb; but hearken it doth chime,</l>
                  <l>The Clock tels four, it is full time,</l>
                  <l>That ſick Sir <hi>John</hi> were brought to's home,</l>
                  <l>Whither at length he being come,</l>
                  <l>Found that's wife, pitying his caſe,</l>
                  <l>Had got a friend to warm his place;</l>
                  <l>Here then they leave him and think beſt,</l>
                  <l>That all repair unto their reſt;</l>
                  <l>And my muſe ſo benum'd ſhe ſcarce could creep,</l>
                  <l>Is at the length crawl'd home and fal'n aſleep.</l>
               </lg>
            </div>
            <div type="poem">
               <head>A voyage from Egypt.</head>
               <lg>
                  <l>NOt of thoſe giants great I ſing,</l>
                  <l>That did hils top o't'other fling</l>
                  <l>For to climb up to Heaven;</l>
                  <l>Nor yet of <hi>Theſeus</hi> noble facts,</l>
                  <l>Or <hi>Hercules</hi> his valiant acts,</l>
                  <l>Or the worlds wonders ſeven:</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <head>2.</head>
                  <l>I ſing not of thoſe <hi>Trojan</hi> wars,</l>
                  <l>VVhoſe fame already mounts the ſtars,</l>
                  <l>Or vict'ry of the <hi>Greeks;</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>Nor yet will I employ my muſe</l>
                  <pb n="105" facs="tcp:115787:59"/>
                  <l>To tell you how they fed the Jews</l>
                  <l>With garlick and with leeks.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <head>3.</head>
                  <l>But yet the beſt I can I'l tell</l>
                  <l>What in a voyage me befell</l>
                  <l>Made from a land of <hi>Moors:</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>A land of aſſes well you wot</l>
                  <l>I left, but yet I'l tell you what,</l>
                  <l>I chanc'd to light 'mongſt
<note n="*" place="margin">
                        <hi>I</hi> came on a Flemiſh ſhip.</note> bores.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <head>4.</head>
                  <l>I never thought beaſts of that race</l>
                  <l>Did uſe the ſurging ſeas to trace;</l>
                  <l>Their brawn is good at feaſts,</l>
                  <l>But yet I'l tell you I might gueſſe</l>
                  <l>Both lands were low, ſo more or leſſe</l>
                  <l>Both people might be beaſts.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <head>5.</head>
                  <l>Good god! ſhould I give you account</l>
                  <l>Of all my labours, they'd ſurmount</l>
                  <l>Great <hi>Hercules</hi> his
<note n="*" place="margin">I had occaſion of no more.</note> ſeven;</l>
                  <l>For I believe theſe bores are ſo</l>
                  <l>Much like the <hi>Turks,</hi> they think to go,</l>
                  <l>By beſtialities to Heaven.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <head>6.</head>
                  <l>Firſt come aboard with a great ſtir,</l>
                  <l>They gruntled out, You'r welcome Sir?</l>
                  <l>I ſtar'd and was half daunted:</l>
                  <l>They grin'd and grunted ſo together,</l>
                  <l>That what with that, and the foul weather,</l>
                  <l>I fear'd I was inchanted.</l>
               </lg>
               <pb n="106" facs="tcp:115787:60"/>
               <lg>
                  <head>7.</head>
                  <l>The Captain ſtrait me carries in,</l>
                  <l>And drinks to me in my own wine,</l>
                  <l>'Tis true I tell you now,</l>
                  <l>And faith I judg'd it well as yet,</l>
                  <l>If I amongſt theſe Bores could get</l>
                  <l>A pig of my own ſow.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <head>8.</head>
                  <l>But when we came to dinner, oh,</l>
                  <l>My mouth with water 'gan to flow</l>
                  <l>You never ſaw the like:</l>
                  <l>For I believe that ſuch pure meat,</l>
                  <l>So ſluttiſh dreſt, was never eat</l>
                  <l>By any <hi>Iriſh</hi> Tike.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <head>9.</head>
                  <l>I now 'gan to repent in vain,</l>
                  <l>And wiſh'd my ſelf aſhore again</l>
                  <l>To feed there like an aſſe,</l>
                  <l>But all alas would not prevail,</l>
                  <l>For now our ſhip was under ſail,</l>
                  <l>I wiſht't had been on graſſe.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <head>10.</head>
                  <l>But come, I will obſerve ſome order,</l>
                  <l>Though they had none in all their larder,</l>
                  <l>And tell you of their diet;</l>
                  <l>I do beleive you'l think it good,</l>
                  <l>But this adviſe you that you wou'd</l>
                  <l>Ne'r venture for to try it.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <head>11.</head>
                  <l>Firſt enter then a bowl of beans,</l>
                  <pb n="107" facs="tcp:115787:60"/>
                  <l>Boil'd juſt to maſh, and ſwims with ſtreams</l>
                  <l>Of greaſe as black as hell:</l>
                  <l>'Tis good ſea meat, you need not chew it,</l>
                  <l>And if you're ſick with eaſe you ſpew it,</l>
                  <l>And this I think likes well.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <head>12.</head>
                  <l>The next is lentils which they boil</l>
                  <l>With a commixtion of whales oyl,</l>
                  <l>With that a little brandy;</l>
                  <l>Then Devils Cook with all your tricks,</l>
                  <l>And boil the waters of black <hi>Stix,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>This diſh wil go beyond ye.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <head>13.</head>
                  <l>Then comes in Stock-fiſh ful as tough</l>
                  <l>As Bacon rind, and twice as rough,</l>
                  <l>They'l take no pains to beat it;</l>
                  <l>And I'l beſworn can I get hay</l>
                  <l>That feed but like a horſe I may,</l>
                  <l>I'l take no pains to eat it.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <head>14.</head>
                  <l>To ſee the maggots in the Cheeſe</l>
                  <l>Is that which beſt of all doth pleaſe,</l>
                  <l>How monſtrouſly they ſhew;</l>
                  <l>A vomit or a ſtool to urge,</l>
                  <l>You need no gliſter nor a purge,</l>
                  <l>Ne'r fear but this will do.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <head>15.</head>
                  <l>But if on Sundays we did get</l>
                  <l>A piece of powder'd beef, why it</l>
                  <l>Was monſtrous rare and fine,</l>
                  <pb n="108" facs="tcp:115787:61"/>
                  <l>O then you'd ſee them flaſh and ſlay,</l>
                  <l>And ſwear by th' Sacrament that they</l>
                  <l>Like <hi>Hogon Mogons</hi> dine.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <head>16</head>
                  <l>'Tis true the fleſh a <hi>hogo</hi> has</l>
                  <l>But yet with them it well doth paſſe</l>
                  <l>For wonderous good fare,</l>
                  <l>And now I've told you of their meat,</l>
                  <l>I'l tell you who they were it eat,</l>
                  <l>You'l judge what Bores they are.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <head>17.</head>
                  <l>Then firſt the Captain mounts the ſtage,</l>
                  <l>And he appears a Saint of age</l>
                  <l>Although he be not old;</l>
                  <l>Yet ſo his grace his age outſtript,</l>
                  <l>That full nine years ſince he was dipt,</l>
                  <l>As I have oft been told.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <head>18</head>
                  <l>O 'tis a fatted Boar I'l ſwear,</l>
                  <l>That with his briſtles and his hair,</l>
                  <l>He's full ten foot about,</l>
                  <l>And faith when firſt I did him ſee,</l>
                  <l>I thought <hi>Golias</hi> ſuch as he</l>
                  <l>Though this wa'n't half ſo ſtout.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <head>19.</head>
                  <l>Had you but ſeen with how much pains</l>
                  <l>He'd wallow down the meat like grains,</l>
                  <l>'T would put you in a fear;</l>
                  <l>For if you ſeek the whole world round</l>
                  <l>Scarce ſuch another would be found,</l>
                  <l>Unleſſ't a <hi>Marriot</hi> were.</l>
               </lg>
               <pb n="109" facs="tcp:115787:61"/>
               <lg>
                  <head>20.</head>
                  <l>I wondred much how he could ſtay,</l>
                  <l>To hear grace ſaid, or rather pray-re</l>
                  <l>For 'twas not he that ſaid it,</l>
                  <l>But if you underſtand aright,</l>
                  <l>It did but whet his appetite,</l>
                  <l>God! how he after paid it.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <head>21.</head>
                  <l>Next mounts the mate our holy brother,</l>
                  <l>The world affords not ſuch another;</l>
                  <l>'Tis a moſt precious Saint,</l>
                  <l>O you might hear him preach and pray,</l>
                  <l>Till quite his breath was gone away,</l>
                  <l>I'm ſure til I did faint.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <head>22.</head>
                  <l>O what a piece of carrion 'twas,</l>
                  <l>As lean as any ſtraw-fed Aſſe,</l>
                  <l>A pox upon his lungs,</l>
                  <l>For had you heard his tittle tattle</l>
                  <l>You would have ſworn by his prattle,</l>
                  <l>He had had twenty tongues.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <head>23.</head>
                  <l>You'l judge the reſt of this foul rabble,</l>
                  <l>And put me to no further trouble;</l>
                  <l>That I felt there was ſore,</l>
                  <l>And I imagine all like me,</l>
                  <l>That were they caught but once, they'd be</l>
                  <l>Intrapped by them no more.</l>
               </lg>
               <pb n="110" facs="tcp:115787:62"/>
               <lg>
                  <head>24.</head>
                  <l>I do believe theſe are the ſwine,</l>
                  <l>With whom the prodigal did dine,</l>
                  <l>At leaſt like them they be:</l>
                  <l>But if his whores were of this kind,</l>
                  <l>He had a dev'liſh luſtful mind,</l>
                  <l>Faith he ſhould—for me.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <head>25.</head>
                  <l>But all this while we under ſaile</l>
                  <l>Endured many a bitter gale,</l>
                  <l>And yet I wiſht for more;</l>
                  <l>I was ſo tired with hard fare,</l>
                  <l>That in good troth I did not care</l>
                  <l>Though I came wet aſhore.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <head>26.</head>
                  <l>At length we reach'd <hi>Meſſina;</hi> here</l>
                  <l>The <hi>Spaniſh</hi> Boyes did ſcold and jeer,</l>
                  <l>And cal'd me <hi>Engliſh</hi> dog,</l>
                  <l>I thought they with more reaſon might,</l>
                  <l>Againſt the Captain vent their ſpite,</l>
                  <l>And call him <hi>Flemiſh</hi> hog.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <head>27.</head>
                  <l>Wel, here I ſome refreſhment got,</l>
                  <l>I after wiſh'd I had it not,</l>
                  <l>It made my grief the more;</l>
                  <l>For all my hate to Boriſh diet,</l>
                  <l>Yet I was forc'd again to try it,</l>
                  <l>Which worſe was than before.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <head>28.</head>
                  <l>Scarce gotten from <hi>Meſſina</hi> well,</l>
                  <pb n="111" facs="tcp:115787:62"/>
                  <l>Becalm'd before the gates of hel</l>
                  <l>Full fourteen dayes we lay;</l>
                  <l>Judge now in what a caſe we were,</l>
                  <l>They call it <hi>Strombello,</hi> and here</l>
                  <l>The Devil dwels they ſay.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <head>29.</head>
                  <l>I think the Dee'l had a deſire,</l>
                  <l>To Cook a whole Bore at his fire,</l>
                  <l>But none were good enough;</l>
                  <l>'Twas well for them they wa'n't in caſe,</l>
                  <l>And though the Captains burly face,</l>
                  <l>Yet he was found too tough.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <head>30.</head>
                  <l>At laſt we reach'd unto our port,</l>
                  <l>Which made my heart begin to ſport,</l>
                  <l>I thought I was in heaven,</l>
                  <l>This voyage taught me how to preach,</l>
                  <l>But all the doctrine that I teach,</l>
                  <l>Is w'are the <hi>Flemings</hi> leaven.</l>
               </lg>
            </div>
            <div type="poem">
               <pb n="112" facs="tcp:115787:63"/>
               <head>Dom. Baudii. Gno. Iamb. lib. primus.</head>
               <lg>
                  <l>WHo bears a manlike ſoul, or valiant breaſt</l>
                  <l>Provokes not dangers to diſturb his reſt,</l>
                  <l>Nor is ſo prodigal on every cauſe,</l>
                  <l>Too light to ſpend his ſtrength, but when the lawes</l>
                  <l>The true Religion, or his Countries good</l>
                  <l>Crave his aſſiſtance, freely ſpils his blood;</l>
                  <l>To caſt away our life denotes a fear,</l>
                  <l>Who throws not off that load he cannot bear?</l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Cato</hi> or <hi>Caſſius</hi> ſcarce deſerv'd a room</l>
                  <l>In fame, and vertue groan'd to raiſe their tomb:</l>
                  <l>We might more juſtly praiſe to <hi>Otho</hi> lend,</l>
                  <l>Who liv'd a woman; like a man did end.</l>
               </lg>
            </div>
            <div type="poem">
               <pb n="113" facs="tcp:115787:63"/>
               <head>The Defiance.</head>
               <lg>
                  <head>1.</head>
                  <l>NO more, no more, no more fond love will I</l>
                  <l>Own thee to be a deity,</l>
                  <l>No longer fear thy bow or dart,</l>
                  <l>Or think th' haſt pow'r to wound a heart,</l>
                  <l>There's none but fools are ſubject to thy skil,</l>
                  <l>I'l ſcorn thy force, and love but where I will;</l>
                  <l>Let dotards hold thou canſt controul</l>
                  <l>The motions of a noble ſoul,</l>
                  <l>I'l never fear to be thy ſlave,</l>
                  <l>Or think that o'r my heart thou pow'r canſt have.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <head>2.</head>
                  <l>Then childiſh boy, go let thy weaker darts</l>
                  <l>Pierce ſottiſh fools or mad-mens hearts,</l>
                  <l>In vain, in vain they here are thrown,</l>
                  <l>Think not with ſteel to pierce a heart of ſtone:</l>
                  <l>No, thou maiſt ſooner move the firmament,</l>
                  <l>Make the poles meet, than make my heart relent;</l>
                  <pb n="114" facs="tcp:115787:64"/>
                  <l>Tis too too firm, nor will it be</l>
                  <l>Bound to ſo baſe a ſlavery,</l>
                  <l>Nor can my noble conſtant mind</l>
                  <l>To any force or power be confin'd.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <head>3.</head>
                  <l>Nay I'l not onely not be ſlave to thee,</l>
                  <l>But thou ſhalt be a ſlave to me,</l>
                  <l>I will uſurp thy pow<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>r and find</l>
                  <l>Ways to ſubject a female mind,</l>
                  <l>Which thou fond boy couldſt never boaſt to know,</l>
                  <l>And not inſnare, but fairly force my foe,</l>
                  <l>Whilſt thou ſhalt pine becauſe</l>
                  <l>My power exceeds thy laws,</l>
                  <l>And ſhalt be forc'd to yeild to me</l>
                  <l>Thy bow, thy dart, thy very deity.</l>
               </lg>
            </div>
            <div type="poem">
               <pb n="115" facs="tcp:115787:64"/>
               <head>The wonder.</head>
               <lg>
                  <head>1.</head>
                  <l>I Can't deviſe what Devil 'tis can move</l>
                  <l>Men to this fond, this fooliſh paſſion love,</l>
                  <l>In the beſt woman I ſpy not one part,</l>
                  <l>Worthy to wound a noble heart,</l>
                  <l>Nor can the beauties of a face,</l>
                  <l>A comely carri'ge or a grace,</l>
                  <l>Wit or diſcourſe, in my poor ſoule take place.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <head>2.</head>
                  <l>'Tis true in beauty I find ſome delight,</l>
                  <l>But yet no farther than to pleaſe my ſight,</l>
                  <l>I love fair eyes, I love a Roſie cheek,</l>
                  <l>I love a skin that's ſmooth and ſleek,</l>
                  <l>I love ſoft breaſts: but of all theſe</l>
                  <l>There's none that with my heart agrees,</l>
                  <l>They onely ſerve my outward ſenſe to pleaſe.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <head>3.</head>
                  <l>Strange that mensſouls ſhould be bewitcht and <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap>
                  </l>
                  <l>Subject to darting of a female eye,</l>
                  <pb n="116" facs="tcp:115787:65"/>
                  <l>No ſoule's ſure ſo ignoble to take fire,</l>
                  <l>From ſuch a low baſe-born deſire,</l>
                  <l>They're made our ſervants, and ſhal we</l>
                  <l>By loving them, make them to be</l>
                  <l>Equal? nay grant them ſuperioritie?</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <head>4.</head>
                  <l>There may be witchcraft in a comely grace,</l>
                  <l>There may be witchcraft in a beauteous face,</l>
                  <l>But I for ever that pow'r in love diſ-own,</l>
                  <l>That makes me others ſlave then's own,</l>
                  <l>'Tis worſe than <hi>Turkiſh</hi> Tyranny,</l>
                  <l>In love for him to make me be</l>
                  <l>To her that is my ſlave in ſlavery.</l>
               </lg>
            </div>
            <div type="poem">
               <head>The Compoſition.</head>
               <lg>
                  <l>THreat'ſt thou to wound me? fool thou threat'ſt in vain,</l>
                  <l>Thou maiſt ſhake heav'n with leſſer pain,</l>
                  <l>Or make the mountains plain,</l>
                  <l>The Northern pole go move,</l>
                  <l>Go bring the bright Sun from above,</l>
                  <l>And then come boaſt th'haſt forc'd me love.</l>
               </lg>
               <pb n="117" facs="tcp:115787:65"/>
               <lg>
                  <head>2.</head>
                  <l>I'd have thee know I have a flinty heart,</l>
                  <l>That ſcorns thy utmoſt power or art,</l>
                  <l>Nay thy all-piercing dart,</l>
                  <l>Go and let it's ſteely head</l>
                  <l>Imprint it ſelf on hearts of lead,</l>
                  <l>None break a flint but on a feather-bed.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <head>3.</head>
                  <l>I dare thy fooliſh threats, but hadſt thou come</l>
                  <l>With pray'rs and humbly ſought a room</l>
                  <l>Perhaps I had gi'n thee ſome,</l>
                  <l>Strong <hi>Rhodes</hi> was found</l>
                  <l>'Gainſt <hi>Turkiſh</hi> force to keep her ground,</l>
                  <l>But fair conditions offer'd, did compound.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <head>4.</head>
                  <l>Then if that laying by thy bow and dart,</l>
                  <l>By league thou wilt ſecure my heart,</l>
                  <l>Let's thus conditions part;</l>
                  <l>I'l leave that whole to thee</l>
                  <l>But thou muſt let me ſtill go free,</l>
                  <l>With bag and baggage both from it and thee.</l>
               </lg>
            </div>
            <div type="poem">
               <pb n="118" facs="tcp:115787:66"/>
               <head>The Conqueſt.</head>
               <lg>
                  <l>GEntly kind love reſtrain, reſtrain thy hand,</l>
                  <l>Keep back thy cruel pricking dart</l>
                  <l>Leſt it not wound but kill my heart;</l>
                  <l>I yeild, who dare reſiſt if thou command;</l>
                  <l>O let it be enough for thee,</l>
                  <l>That thou haſt gain'd o'r me the victory,</l>
                  <l>Do not inſult upon my miſery.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <head>2.</head>
                  <l>Shouldſt thou continue ſtill to conquer me,</l>
                  <l>And ſhould'ſt not to my o'reflown grief</l>
                  <l>Send ſome ſmall comfort or relief,</l>
                  <l>Death would at laſt of both have victory;</l>
                  <l>Be merciful and let me live,</l>
                  <l>Leſt while t'inlarge thy power thou doſt ſtrive,</l>
                  <l>Thy cruelty Subjects of life deprive.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <head>3.</head>
                  <l>I ask no more, but ſo far pity me</l>
                  <l>As with the ſelf ſame dart</l>
                  <l>To wound her frozen heart,</l>
                  <pb n="119" facs="tcp:115787:66"/>
                  <l>That ſo ſhe may no more relentleſſe be,</l>
                  <l>And thus ſhalt thou two ſubjects gain,</l>
                  <l>Who will this victory of thine proclaim,</l>
                  <l>And ever honour thy all-conquering name.</l>
               </lg>
            </div>
            <div type="poem">
               <head>Reaſon in Love.</head>
               <lg>
                  <l>TIs not the luſtre of thy darting eye</l>
                  <l>Which ſhines ſo gloriouſly,</l>
                  <l>Nor is't thy twin-born milk-white breaſts which ſhew</l>
                  <l>Like mounts of purer ſnow,</l>
                  <l>'Tis not thy cherry lip or golden hair,</l>
                  <l>Which makes me judge thee fair,</l>
                  <l>Nor is't thy pleaſant ſweet diſcourſe or wit,</l>
                  <l>Nor what proceeds from it,</l>
                  <l>Thy comely carriage or thy grace, can move</l>
                  <l>Me to adore or love.</l>
                  <l>But 'tis thy purer ſoul which ſtill I find</l>
                  <l>Compliant to my mind;</l>
                  <l>In all things but what would moſt pleaſant be</l>
                  <l>That is thy loving me,</l>
                  <l>Wer't then fair <hi>Hellen</hi> fairer, couldſt thou boaſt</l>
                  <l>Thy beauty o'r the moſt.</l>
                  <pb n="120" facs="tcp:115787:67"/>
                  <l>Didſt thou in all mens judgments where thou'rt ſeen</l>
                  <l>Exceed the ſea-born Queen;</l>
                  <l>If the leaſt falſeneſſe in thy ſoul I ſee,</l>
                  <l>Thou'dſt ſeem moſt foule to me:</l>
                  <l>Were thy mind blemiſht with the ſmalleſt blot,</l>
                  <l>Or the leaſt faithleſſe ſpot,</l>
                  <l>The blackeſt ill-look'd <hi>Indian</hi> would appear</l>
                  <l>To me than thee more rare;</l>
                  <l>'Tis the bright ſoul that darting out it's light</l>
                  <l>Makes beauty a delight,</l>
                  <l>Which elſe like the inclouded Sun would be</l>
                  <l>Gloomy and dark to me:</l>
                  <l>'Tis that alone which me thy ſlave can make,</l>
                  <l>And love thy body for thy fair ſouls ſake.</l>
               </lg>
            </div>
            <div type="poem">
               <head>Beauty.</head>
               <lg>
                  <head>1.</head>
                  <l>THou ſoul-bewitching devil, at firſt made</l>
                  <l>Mens inward ſenſes to invade,</l>
                  <l>That haſt the power to invite</l>
                  <l>Mans purer mind unto a feign'd delight:</l>
                  <l>That firſt doſt conquer with thy flatt'ring eye,</l>
                  <l>And then inſult'ſt upon our miſery.</l>
               </lg>
               <pb n="121" facs="tcp:115787:67"/>
               <lg>
                  <head>2.</head>
                  <l>Thou heart-entrapping witch, which do'ſt de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prive,</l>
                  <l>Men firſt of ſenſe, and then of life;</l>
                  <l>Thou ſnake that li'ſt'mongſt faireſt flower</l>
                  <l>Raiſ'd by the moiſture of ſweet <hi>Aprill</hi> ſhowers;</l>
                  <l>And ſo with greater eaſe do'ſt work our harmes,</l>
                  <l>Regarding none but only thy own charmes.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <head>3.</head>
                  <l>Thou meere conceit of mans imagination,</l>
                  <l>Blown up and down, fixt to no ſtation;</l>
                  <l>Which haſt no more in thee of bliſſe,</l>
                  <l>Then what by his fond ſoule imagin'd is;</l>
                  <l>So, if a <hi>Chaos</hi> by him deemed be,</l>
                  <l>Faire 'tis, by much more beautifull then ſhe.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <head>4.</head>
                  <l>Thou painted garniſh'd flower, only made</l>
                  <l>To flatter men, and then to fade:</l>
                  <l>That ſo they puniſhed may be,</l>
                  <l>Like <hi>Tantalus,</hi> not to enjoy, but ſee;</l>
                  <l>Mounting them up, firſt to a promiſ'd bliſſe,</l>
                  <l>To let them fall to more unhappineſſe.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <head>5.</head>
                  <l>Thou fruit, like curſed <hi>Sodoms,</hi> which do'ſt lie</l>
                  <l>Delighfull pleaſing to the eye:</l>
                  <l>But if once toucht like them thou'rt found,</l>
                  <pb n="122" facs="tcp:115787:68"/>
                  <l>But onely fair without, within unſound</l>
                  <l>Like ſummer pears, a pleaſant outward part,</l>
                  <l>But if once cut, found rotten at the heart.</l>
               </lg>
            </div>
            <div type="poem">
               <head>The Variety.</head>
               <lg>
                  <l>THou ſaiſt I ſwore I lov'd thee beſt,</l>
                  <l>And that my heart liv'd in thy breaſt,</l>
                  <l>And now thou wondreſt much that I</l>
                  <l>Should what I ſwore then, now deny,</l>
                  <l>And upon this thou taxeſt me</l>
                  <l>With faithleſſeneſſe, inconſtancy:</l>
                  <l>Thou haſt no reaſon ſo to do,</l>
                  <l>Who can't diſſemble ne'r muſt wooe.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <head>2.</head>
                  <l>That ſo I lov'd thee 'tis confeſt,</l>
                  <l>But 'twas becauſe I judg'd thee beſt,</l>
                  <l>For then I thought that thou alone</l>
                  <l>Waſt vertues, beauties paragon:</l>
                  <l>But now that the deceit I find,</l>
                  <l>To love thee ſtill were to be blind,</l>
                  <l>And I muſt needs confeſſe to thee</l>
                  <l>I love in love variety.</l>
               </lg>
               <pb n="123" facs="tcp:115787:68"/>
               <lg>
                  <head>3.</head>
                  <l>Alas! ſhould I love thee alone,</l>
                  <l>In a ſhort time I ſhould love none;</l>
                  <l>Who on one well lov'd feeds, yet,</l>
                  <l>Once being cloy'd, of all, loaths it;</l>
                  <l>Would'ſt thou be ſubject to a fate</l>
                  <l>To make me change my love, to hate?</l>
                  <l>Blame me not then, ſince 'tis for love</l>
                  <l>Of thee, that I inconſtant prove.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <head>4.</head>
                  <l>And yet in truth 'tis conſtancy,</l>
                  <l>For which I am accuſ'd by thee;</l>
                  <l>To nature thoſe inconſtant are,</l>
                  <l>Who fix their love on one that's faire;</l>
                  <l>Why did ſhe, but for our delight,</l>
                  <l>Preſent ſuch numbers to our ſight;</l>
                  <l>'Mongſt all the earthly Kings, theres none</l>
                  <l>Contented with one Crown alone.</l>
               </lg>
            </div>
            <div type="poem">
               <pb n="124" facs="tcp:115787:69"/>
               <head>She inconſtant.</head>
               <lg>
                  <l>HA! now you think y'have cheated me, oh no,</l>
                  <l>I did believe you would do ſo:</l>
                  <l>Who ever did the various wind</l>
                  <l>Still conſtant to one corner find?</l>
                  <l>Whenever did the changling air</l>
                  <l>Show it ſelf ſtil ſerene and fair?</l>
                  <l>Yet we might ſooner hope theſe thus ſhould be,</l>
                  <l>Than think to find in woman conſtancy.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <head>2.</head>
                  <l>We may as well command the Sun not move,</l>
                  <l>As you with conſtancy to love,</l>
                  <l>Or bid the ſea be free from waves,</l>
                  <l>When ſtormy bluſtring <hi>Boreas</hi> raves,</l>
                  <l>Nay we as well the Moon might wooe,</l>
                  <l>To leave her weekly change as you:</l>
                  <l>Your nature 'tis, and ſhould you conſtant be,</l>
                  <l>I fear you'd prove unnatural to me.</l>
               </lg>
               <pb n="125" facs="tcp:115787:69"/>
               <lg>
                  <head>3.</head>
                  <l>You lighter much than feathers are, and ſo</l>
                  <l>Muſt move with whar e'r wind doth blow,</l>
                  <l>Hurried about, now here, now there,</l>
                  <l>Now yonder; but yet fixt no where.</l>
                  <l>Perhaps at length a guſt may be</l>
                  <l>To bring you back once more to me;</l>
                  <l>But <hi>Jove</hi> forbid: for yet I fear thou'dſt move</l>
                  <l>My enſnar'd ſoule to ruine in thy love.</l>
               </lg>
            </div>
            <div type="poem">
               <head>The Reſolution.</head>
               <lg>
                  <head>1.</head>
                  <l>NOw by that beauty I ſo much adore,</l>
                  <l>I am reſolv'd to dote no more,</l>
                  <l>No longer ſhall my paſſions ſtrive</l>
                  <l>Me of my reaſon to deprive,</l>
                  <l>No longer will I ſubject be,</l>
                  <l>But nobly ſet my heart at liberty.</l>
               </lg>
               <pb n="126" facs="tcp:115787:70"/>
               <lg>
                  <head>2.</head>
                  <l>Then go dear heart, and be no more confin'd</l>
                  <l>To a womans changling mind;</l>
                  <l>Why ſhould'ſt thou a ſubject be</l>
                  <l>To their ſelfe-will'd tyranny;</l>
                  <l>Break, break thy bands and fetters, know,</l>
                  <l>Subject to her, thou'rt ſubject to a foe.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <head>3.</head>
                  <l>Theres nought in her that thee her ſlave hath made,</l>
                  <l>'Tis thou that haſt thy ſelfe betraid,</l>
                  <l>By fanc'ing that her beauties ſhine</l>
                  <l>Like ſomething more then halfe divine:</l>
                  <l>Think then thy ſelfe deceiv'd to be,</l>
                  <l>Thou'rt undeceiv'd, and art than thought more free.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <head>4:</head>
                  <l>'Tis men alone that womens Empire raiſe,</l>
                  <l>By wooing them with fancied praiſe;</l>
                  <l>When, if we would their maſters be,</l>
                  <l>They muſt grant Superiority:</l>
                  <l>Nay, did we ceaſe to flatter thus,</l>
                  <l>'Twould not be long ere they would flatter us.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <head>5:</head>
                  <l>Ceaſe then my heart, and dote no more in vain,</l>
                  <l>Thou never thus the fort wilt gain;</l>
                  <l>No more upon entreaties ſtand,</l>
                  <l>But learn like her how to command;</l>
                  <l>Thoſe Caſtles which find no remorſe,</l>
                  <l>On ſummons muſt be taken in by force.</l>
               </lg>
            </div>
            <div type="poem">
               <pb n="127" facs="tcp:115787:70"/>
               <head>She Weeping.</head>
               <lg>
                  <head>1.</head>
                  <l>SEe how ſhe weepes, with what a grace</l>
                  <l>Sorrow it ſelfe ſhowes in her face;</l>
                  <l>See how her ey's ſtill dart their beams,</l>
                  <l>Nothing ecclipſed by thoſe ſtreams;</l>
                  <l>See how thoſe teares ſprung from her eye,</l>
                  <l>Like pearles enchaſ'd on rubies lie.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <head>2.</head>
                  <l>So have I ſeen the clouds diſtill,</l>
                  <l>Their heat drops, yet the Sun ſhine ſtill:</l>
                  <l>Which only ſome refreſhment yield</l>
                  <l>To the before Sun-ſcorched field;</l>
                  <l>Ah! precious teares, might you but be</l>
                  <l>Of halfe that comfort unto me,</l>
                  <l>Then ſhould I deeme them far more rare,</l>
                  <l>Then all the Ocean jewells are;</l>
                  <l>But what avails it, ſince in vaine,</l>
                  <l>I hope they ſhould refreſh my pain?</l>
                  <l>Since, Ah poore me! I plainly ſee</l>
                  <l>They tears of greife, not pity be:</l>
               </lg>
            </div>
            <div type="poem">
               <pb n="128" facs="tcp:115787:71"/>
               <head>The Wiſh.</head>
               <lg>
                  <head>1.</head>
                  <l>NO: my deſires are limited; nor expand,</l>
                  <l>They halfe ſo far: I do not crave,</l>
                  <l>To have dominion o're a mighty land,</l>
                  <l>Nor <hi>Creſſue</hi> riches would I have;</l>
                  <l>The <hi>Grecian</hi> Empire would not be,</l>
                  <l>Of any comfort or content to me.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <head>2.</head>
                  <l>While ſhe, deare ſhe, deigns not to caſt an eye,</l>
                  <l>Of pity, or regard my greife,</l>
                  <l>Rather inſults upon my miſery;</l>
                  <l>So far, ſo far! ſhee's from releife;</l>
                  <l>Ah faireſt Nymph, all that I crave,</l>
                  <l>Is that one look of pity I might have.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <head>3.</head>
                  <l>Would'ſt thou be pleaſ'd but once to ſmile on me,</l>
                  <l>For that ſmile I'd the <hi>Indies</hi> ſlight,</l>
                  <l>In them there could not halfe that comfort be;</l>
                  <pb n="129" facs="tcp:115787:71"/>
                  <l>Not half that pleaſure or delight:</l>
                  <l>No, the whole world to me would ſeem</l>
                  <l>For ſuch a favour of too ſmal eſteem.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <head>4.</head>
                  <l>One ſmile I wiſh, nor would I have thee be</l>
                  <l>Too laviſh of ſuch boons as thoſe,</l>
                  <l>Ah! how much would poor one recomfort me,</l>
                  <l>One ſmile enough thy pity ſhowe:</l>
                  <l>And ſhould'ſt thou not it then with-hold.</l>
                  <l>With joy I die, or elſe grow over-bold.</l>
               </lg>
            </div>
            <div type="poem">
               <head>Deſpair.</head>
               <lg>
                  <head>1.</head>
                  <l>AH me! my tears and ſighs I waſte in vain,</l>
                  <l>In vain of her I beg releif,</l>
                  <l>Who neither pity's nor regards my pain,</l>
                  <l>Nor will yeild comfort to my grief.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <head>2.</head>
                  <l>No more, no more in vain to thee I'l cry,</l>
                  <l>No thou my ſighs no more ſhalt hear,</l>
                  <l>But to ſome lone ſhade I'l retire and lie,</l>
                  <l>Lamenting my hard fortune there.</l>
               </lg>
               <pb n="130" facs="tcp:115787:72"/>
               <lg>
                  <head>3.</head>
                  <l>Where the kind Echo from th'incloſed air</l>
                  <l>Shall grant to me what e'r I ſay,</l>
                  <l>And from the hollow rocks anſwer my pray'r,</l>
                  <l>Nor ever, like thee, ſay me nay.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <head>4.</head>
                  <l>But yet I fear leſt while I here impart,</l>
                  <l>And tell my griefs unto each tree;</l>
                  <l>My boſome be not left without a heart,</l>
                  <l>'Twil ſtil burſt out and fly to thee.</l>
               </lg>
            </div>
            <div type="poem">
               <head>Love or no Love.</head>
               <lg>
                  <l>I Think I lov'd but for paſtime, or ſo,</l>
                  <l>Nor can I well tell if I lov'd or no,</l>
                  <l>Sure, <hi>Love,</hi> I did but jeer thee: for I find</l>
                  <l>Thou haſt left no impreſſion on my mind;</l>
                  <l>Thy ſhafts ne'r yet touch'd me, nor did thy dart</l>
                  <l>That I was ſenſible, e'r wound my heart,</l>
                  <l>Yet I can love without thee, nor canſt thou</l>
                  <l>Subject that heart will ſooner break than bow.</l>
                  <pb n="131" facs="tcp:115787:72"/>
                  <l>Strange! that men ſhould be cauſers of their woe,</l>
                  <l>And fancy paſſions when they are not ſo,</l>
                  <l>Thou haſt no pow'r to conquer; but what we</l>
                  <l>By fancying a ſubjection give to thee.</l>
                  <l>I can love ſo that neither my deſire</l>
                  <l>Can mount ſo high as to be term'd a fire,</l>
                  <l>And I can ceaſe to love when e'r I pleaſe,</l>
                  <l>Nor one, nor t'other ſhall diſturb my eaſe.</l>
                  <l>Go then fond boy, and break thy feebler darts,</l>
                  <l>And boaſt no more thy pow'r to conquer hearts,</l>
                  <l>Since I have learn'd to fool thy pow'r and thee,</l>
                  <l>And love, or not love with Tranquillity.</l>
               </lg>
            </div>
            <div type="poem">
               <head>Gold.</head>
               <lg>
                  <head>1.</head>
                  <l>BAſe ſottiſh Idol, which doſt vainly boaſt,</l>
                  <l>T' extend thy pow'r from coaſt to coaſt,</l>
                  <l>Vaunting that there Temples be</l>
                  <l>Rear'd in every heart to thee,</l>
                  <l>Boaſt no more, for thou ſhalt find</l>
                  <l>No altars ſmoaking in my mind.</l>
               </lg>
               <pb n="132" facs="tcp:115787:73"/>
               <lg>
                  <head>2.</head>
                  <l>What though the greateſt kings thy ſubjects be,</l>
                  <l>I'l not ſacrifice to thee,</l>
                  <l>Nor will ſpend one idle hower</l>
                  <l>To adore thy flatt'ring power,</l>
                  <l>Fools! to adore a god will be</l>
                  <l>Falſe to um in neceſſity.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <head>3.</head>
                  <l>Let the curs'd Tyrant new inventions find,</l>
                  <l>To pleaſe his never glutted mind,</l>
                  <l>Let him his Subjects ſqueeze and rake,</l>
                  <l>And ful with gold his checquer make,</l>
                  <l>Yet at the end he ſhal confeſſe</l>
                  <l>Mine is the greater happineſſe.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <head>4.</head>
                  <l>Let the fond merchant ſeek the <hi>Indian</hi> ſhore,</l>
                  <l>To find out treaſures more and more,</l>
                  <l>And venture life and libertie,</l>
                  <l>Nay wife and children all for thee,</l>
                  <l>Having done what he can invent,</l>
                  <l>He'l find that I live more content.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <head>5.</head>
                  <l>Let the learn'd Chymiſt ſtriving to extract</l>
                  <l>Thee from his fancies, or compact</l>
                  <l>The <hi>Elixar</hi> to encreaſe his gains,</l>
                  <l>Looſe both his treaſure and his pains,</l>
                  <pb n="133" facs="tcp:115787:73"/>
                  <l>And then he wil confeſſe that I</l>
                  <l>Have liv'd by much more happily.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <head>6.</head>
                  <l>Let the extorting Us'rer carp and care,</l>
                  <l>And pinch his guts his god to ſpare,</l>
                  <l>And let him unknown wayes invent</l>
                  <l>To raiſe, or elſe to rack his rent,</l>
                  <l>To leave his gold he'l make more moan,</l>
                  <l>Than ever I did to have none.</l>
               </lg>
            </div>
            <div type="poem">
               <head>The Farewel.</head>
               <lg>
                  <head>1.</head>
                  <l>NOw perverſe world I'l bid thee quite fare<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wel,</l>
                  <l>What is there in thee that can pleaſe?</l>
                  <l>Thy greateſt joy's diſturb our eaſe,</l>
                  <l>Thy favours thou at too dear rate doſt ſell,</l>
                  <l>No, I'l thy ſlave no longer be,</l>
                  <l>But quite retreat my ſelf from thee,</l>
                  <l>Or to ſome pleaſant ſhade, or to a gloomy Cell.</l>
               </lg>
               <pb n="134" facs="tcp:115787:74"/>
               <lg>
                  <head>2.</head>
                  <l>There in dull ſilence will I ſpend my dayes,</l>
                  <l>Slighting thy favours and my fame,</l>
                  <l>In vain men ſeek to get a name,</l>
                  <l>Or their falſe glory in thy crouds to raiſe,</l>
                  <l>Since that their living trophees muſt</l>
                  <l>By time or fate conſume to duſt,</l>
                  <l>And then what reſts there of their toil-got praiſe?</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <head>3.</head>
                  <l>Yet in deſpite of thee my name ſhall be</l>
                  <l>The talk of ages yet to come,</l>
                  <l>In every time there ſhall be ſome,</l>
                  <l>Which ſhall applaud me more for leaving thee,</l>
                  <l>Then thoſe fond ſimple fools who do</l>
                  <l>Imbrace thy woes and honours too,</l>
                  <l>And make me famous to poſteritie.</l>
               </lg>
               <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
            </div>
         </div>
      </body>
      <back>
         <div type="publishers_advertisement">
            <pb facs="tcp:115787:74"/>
            <p>BOOKS Printed for <hi>JOHN STARKEY</hi> At the ſign of the MITER, near the middle <hi>TEMPLE-GATE in Fleetſtreet.</hi>
            </p>
         </div>
         <div type="to_the_reader">
            <pb facs="tcp:115787:75"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:115787:75"/>
            <opener>
               <salute>Courteous Reader.</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>
               <hi>Theſe Books following are printed for, and ſold by</hi> John Starkey, <hi>at his ſhop at the Miter, near the Middle Temple-gate in Fleet-ſtreet.</hi>
            </p>
            <div type="section">
               <head>Books in Divinity.</head>
               <p n="1">1. MR. <hi>Thomas Hall</hi>'s Practical and Polemical Commentary, or, Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſition upon the third and fourth Chapters of the latter Epiſtle of St. <hi>Paul</hi> to <hi>Timothy,</hi> wherein the Text is explained, fome Controverſies diſcuſſed, ſundry Caſes of Conſcience are cleared, many Common Places are ſuccinctly handled, and divers Uſeful, and ſeaſonable Obſervations raiſed. fol.</p>
               <pb facs="tcp:115787:76"/>
               <p n="2">2. M<hi rend="sup">r.</hi> 
                  <hi>Thomas Halls Homeſus Enervatus,</hi> or a Confutation of the <hi>Millenarian</hi> Opinion, plain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly ſhewing that <hi>Chriſt</hi> will not Raign with the Saints for 1000. yeares on Earth, with a <hi>Word</hi> to our fifth <hi>Monarchy</hi> men, in octavo.</p>
               <p n="3">3. M<hi rend="sup">r.</hi> 
                  <hi>Thomas Halls Apologia pro Miniſterio Evangelico, in quà planè &amp; plenè oſtenditur ejus neceſſitas, dignitas, Efficacia &amp; <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>tilitas;</hi> in 8<hi rend="sup">o</hi>.</p>
               <p n="4">4. M<hi rend="sup">r.</hi> 
                  <hi>Richard Baxters</hi> Directions, and Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwaſions to a ſound Converſion, for prevention of that deceipt and Damnation of Soules; and of thoſe ſcandalls, hereſies, and deſperate apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtaſies, that are the conſequents of a counterfeit or ſuperficiall Change, this being the ſecond Part of the Call to the <hi>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nconverted,</hi> in octavo.</p>
               <p n="5">5. M<hi rend="sup">r:</hi> 
                  <hi>Richard Baxter.</hi> The <hi>Grotian</hi> Religion diſcovered at the Invitation of Mr. <hi>Thomas Pierce</hi> in his Vindication, with a Vindication of the <hi>Synod</hi> of <hi>Dort,</hi> from the Calumnies of the New <hi>Tylenus,</hi> and the <hi>Puritanes</hi> from the cen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure of Mr. <hi>Pierce,</hi> in octavo.</p>
               <p n="6">6. M<hi rend="sup">r.</hi> 
                  <hi>Richard Baxter</hi> of Saving Faith, that it is not only Gradually, but Specifically diſtinct from all common Faith, being a Treatiſe in an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwer to Mr. <hi>Barlow</hi> of <hi>Oxford,</hi> in quarto.</p>
               <p n="7">7. D<hi rend="sup">r.</hi> 
                  <hi>Thomas Goodwin Opuſcula Theologica,</hi> in octavo.</p>
               <p n="8">8. M<hi rend="sup">r.</hi> 
                  <hi>Thomas Gataker,</hi> Gods Eye on his <hi>Iſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rael;</hi> being an Expoſition on <hi>Numbers</hi> 23.21. in quarto.</p>
               <pb facs="tcp:115787:76"/>
               <p n="9">9. M<hi rend="sup">r.</hi> 
                  <hi>Thomas Gataker, de Juſtificatione, &amp; de Dipthongis,</hi> in twelves.</p>
               <p n="10">10. M<hi rend="sup">r.</hi> 
                  <hi>William Cartwright</hi> of <hi>Oxford,</hi> his Sermon of the Paſſion of <hi>Chriſt,</hi> in octavo.</p>
               <p n="11">11. M<hi rend="sup">r.</hi> 
                  <hi>Thomas Warrens</hi> Juſtification Juſtifi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, or a Treatiſe of Juſtification by Faith, in octavo.</p>
               <p n="12">12. M<hi rend="sup">r.</hi> 
                  <hi>Thomas Coopers</hi> Act of Giving, or a Guide to Charity, in octavo.</p>
               <p n="13">13. M<hi rend="sup">r.</hi> 
                  <hi>John Phillips</hi> Chriſtian Alphabet, Containing Grounds of Knowledge unto Salva<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, in twelves.</p>
               <p n="14">14. M<hi rend="sup">r.</hi> 
                  <hi>Adam Harſnets</hi> Gods Summons into a Generall Repentance, in twelves.</p>
               <p n="15">15. M<hi rend="sup">r.</hi> 
                  <hi>Thomas Hooker</hi> of <hi>New-England,</hi> his Miſcelanies, containing five Excellent Treatiſes in Divinity, in twelves.</p>
               <p n="16">16. M<hi rend="sup">r.</hi> 
                  <hi>Richard Sedgwick.</hi> The Synopſis of Chriſtianity, in an Expoſition of the Commande<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments, Lords Prayer, and the Creed, in octavo.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="section">
               <pb facs="tcp:115787:77"/>
               <head>Books of Hiſtory and Humanity.</head>
               <p n="17">17. LEtters of Affaires, Love, and Court<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip, written to ſeverall Perſons of Honour and Quality, by the Exquifite Pen of <hi>Monſieur de Voiture,</hi> Engliſhed by <hi>J. D.</hi> in octavo.</p>
               <p n="18">18. M<hi rend="sup">r.</hi> 
                  <hi>Walter Mountague</hi> his Shepherds Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>radiſe, a Comedy privately acted before the late King <hi>Charles,</hi> by the Queens Majeſty, and her Ladies of Honour, whoſe names are pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fixt, in octavo.</p>
               <p n="19">19. M<hi rend="sup">r.</hi> 
                  <hi>Thomas Halls Phaetons</hi> Folly, being a Tranſlation of the ſecond Book of <hi>Ovids Meta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>morphoſts,</hi> Paraphraſtically and Grammatically; with an Eſſay on <hi>Ovid de Triſtibus,</hi> in octavo.</p>
               <p n="20">20. M<hi rend="sup">r.</hi> 
                  <hi>Agricola Carpentars</hi> Magical Deſcrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of the ſoule, in octavo.</p>
               <p n="21">21. M<hi rend="sup">r.</hi> 
                  <hi>John Hayes</hi> Compleat <hi>Tradeſman,</hi> or a <hi>Guide</hi> for the true Stating of Intereſt, at <hi>Six per Cent. per. Annum,</hi> with other uſefull Tables, in twelves.</p>
               <p n="22">22. A Relation of the Life of the Famous <hi>Chriſtina,</hi> Queen of <hi>Sweden,</hi> whereunto is added
<pb facs="tcp:115787:77"/>her <hi>Genius,</hi> Tranſlated out of <hi>French</hi> by <hi>J. H.</hi> in quarto.</p>
               <p n="23">23. <hi>France</hi> no friend to <hi>England,</hi> or the Ro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſentments of the <hi>French,</hi> upon the ſucceſſe of the <hi>Engliſh,</hi> as it is expreſſed in a <hi>Remonſtrance</hi> to the King of <hi>France,</hi> upon the ſurrendering of <hi>Dunkirke</hi> into the hands of the <hi>Engliſh,</hi> where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in much of the private Tranſactions between <hi>Cardinall Mazarine,</hi> and the late <hi>Protector, Oli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver,</hi> are diſcovered, Tranſlated out of <hi>French,</hi> in quarto.</p>
               <p n="24">24. M<hi rend="sup">r.</hi> 
                  <hi>Henery Praſhams Truth</hi> of <hi>Time,</hi> Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vealed, in twelves.</p>
               <p n="25">25. <hi>Aminta,</hi> the Famous <hi>Paſtorall,</hi> written in <hi>Italian,</hi> by <hi>Signoir Torquato Taſſo,</hi> and Tranſla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted into <hi>Engliſh</hi> Verſe by <hi>John Dancer;</hi> to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether with divers Ingenuous <hi>Poems,</hi> in octavo.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="section">
               <head>In the Preſſe.</head>
               <p>A Rare Piece, Intitled, the <hi>World Surveyed,</hi> or the Famous <hi>Voyages</hi> and <hi>Travells</hi> of <hi>Monſieur Vincent Le Blanc, Alias, White,</hi> a <hi>Frenchman</hi> of <hi>Marſeilles,</hi> who, from the age of twelve yeares
<pb facs="tcp:115787:78"/>to threeſcore, travelled through the <hi>Eaſt</hi> and <hi>Weſt-Indies,</hi> and moſt habitable Parts of the World: with a Deſcription of all thoſe Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tries he paſt through; the whole Work enrich<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed with many pleaſant Hiſtories, Tranſlated out of <hi>French</hi> into <hi>Engliſh,</hi> by <hi>W. P.</hi> folio.</p>
               <pb facs="tcp:115787:78"/>
            </div>
         </div>
      </back>
   </text>
</TEI>
