<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>The tragedie of Chabot admirall of France as it vvas presented by her Majesties Servants, at the private house in Drury Lane. Written by George Chapman, and Iames Shirly.</title>
            <title>Chabot</title>
            <author>Chapman, George, 1559?-1634.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1639</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 152 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 36 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2014-11">2014-11 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">B12027</idno>
            <idno type="STC">STC 4996</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC S107727</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99843423</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99843423</idno>
            <idno type="VID">177674</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online text creation partnership.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. B12027)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 177674)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 1132:5)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>The tragedie of Chabot admirall of France as it vvas presented by her Majesties Servants, at the private house in Drury Lane. Written by George Chapman, and Iames Shirly.</title>
                  <title>Chabot</title>
                  <author>Chapman, George, 1559?-1634.</author>
                  <author>Shirley, James, 1596-1666. aut</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[72] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed by Tho. Cotes, for Andrew Crooke, and William Cooke,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1639.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>The authors' names are bracketed together on title page.</note>
                  <note>Signatures: A-I⁴.</note>
                  <note>Running title reads: The admirall of France.</note>
                  <note>The last leaf is blank.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the Henry E. Huntington Library and Art Gallery.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Chabot, Philippe, 1480-1543 --  Drama --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2013-12</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-12</date>
            <label>Apex CoVantage</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2014-02</date>
            <label>Olivia Bottum</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2014-02</date>
            <label>Olivia Bottum</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2014-03</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:177674:1"/>
            <p>THE TRAGEDIE OF CHABOT ADMIRALL OF FRANCE: As it vvas preſented by her Majeſties Servants, at the private Houſe in <hi>Drury</hi> Lane.</p>
            <list>
               <label>Written by</label>
               <item>
                  <list>
                     <item>
                        <hi>George Chapman,</hi> and</item>
                     <item>
                        <hi>James Shirly.</hi>
                     </item>
                  </list>
               </item>
            </list>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON,</hi> Printed by <hi>Tho. Cotes,</hi> for <hi>Andrew Crooke,</hi> and <hi>William Cooke.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>1639.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="dramatis_personae">
            <pb facs="tcp:177674:2"/>
            <head>Speakers.</head>
            <list>
               <item>ASall.</item>
               <item>Allegre.</item>
               <item>King.</item>
               <item>Queene.</item>
               <item>Treaſuror.</item>
               <item>Chancellor.</item>
               <item>Admirall.</item>
               <item>Father.</item>
               <item>Generall.</item>
               <item>Chabot.</item>
               <item>Iudges.</item>
               <item>Officers.</item>
               <item>Secretary.</item>
               <item>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ſhers.</item>
               <item>Conſtable.</item>
               <item>Courtiers.</item>
               <item>Porter.</item>
               <item>Guard.</item>
            </list>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="play">
            <pb facs="tcp:177674:2"/>
            <head>THE TRAGEDIE OF PHILIP CHABOT, ADMIRALL of FRANCE.</head>
            <div n="1" type="act">
               <head>Actus Primus.</head>
               <stage>Enter Aſall, and Allegre.</stage>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Aſall.</speaker>
                  <l>
                     <seg rend="decorInit">N</seg>Ow <hi>Phillip Chabot,</hi> Admirall of <hi>France,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>The great, and onely famous Favorite</l>
                  <l>To <hi>Francis</hi> firſt of that Imperiall name,</l>
                  <l>Hath found a freſh competitor in glory,</l>
                  <l>(Duke <hi>Montmorancie,</hi> Conſtable of <hi>France</hi>)</l>
                  <l>Who drinkes as deepe as he of the ſtreame Royall,</l>
                  <l>And may in little time convert the ſtrength</l>
                  <l>To raiſe his ſpring, and blow the others fall.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Al.</speaker>
                  <l>The world would wiſh it ſo, that will not patiently</l>
                  <l>Endure the due riſe of a vertuous man.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Aſ.</speaker>
                  <l>If he be vertuous, what is the reaſon</l>
                  <l>That men affect him not, why is he loſt</l>
                  <pb facs="tcp:177674:3"/>
                  <l>Toth' generall opinion, and become</l>
                  <l>Rather their hate than love?</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Al.</speaker>
                  <l>I wonder you</l>
                  <l>Will queſtion it, aske a ground or reaſon</l>
                  <l>Of men bred in this vile degenerate age;</l>
                  <l>The moſt men are not good, and it agrees not</l>
                  <l>With impious natures to allow whats honeſt,</l>
                  <l>Tis an offence enough to be exalted</l>
                  <l>To regall favours, great men are not ſafe</l>
                  <l>In their owne vice, where good men by the hand</l>
                  <l>Of Kings are planted to ſurvey their workings;</l>
                  <l>What man was ever fixt 'ith Sphere of honour,</l>
                  <l>And precious to his Soveraigne, whoſe actions,</l>
                  <l>Nay very ſoule was not expos'd to every</l>
                  <l>Common and baſe diſſection? and not onely</l>
                  <l>That which in Nature hath excuſe, and in</l>
                  <l>Themſelves is priviledg'd by name of frailtie,</l>
                  <l>But even Vertues are made crimes, and doom'd</l>
                  <l>Toth' fate of Treaſon.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Aſ.</speaker>
                  <l>A bad age the while,</l>
                  <l>I aske your pardon Sir, but thinkes your judgement,</l>
                  <l>His love to Juſtice, and Corruptions hate</l>
                  <l>Are true and hearty?</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Al.</speaker>
                  <l>Iudge your ſelfe by this</l>
                  <l>One argument, his hearty truth to all,</l>
                  <l>For in the heart hath anger his wiſeſt ſeate,</l>
                  <l>And gainſt unjuſt ſuites ſuch brave anger fires him,</l>
                  <l>That when they ſeeke to paſſe his place and power,</l>
                  <l>Though mov'd, and urg'd by the other minion,</l>
                  <l>Or by his greateſt friends, and even the King</l>
                  <l>Leade them to his allowance with his hand,</l>
                  <l>Firſt given in Bill, aſſign'd, even then his ſpirit,</l>
                  <l>(In nature calme as any Summers evening)</l>
                  <l>Puts up his Whole powers like a Winters ſea,</l>
                  <l>His bloud boyles over, and his heart even cracks</l>
                  <l>At the injuſtice, and he teares the Bill,</l>
                  <l>And would doe, were he for't to be torne in pe<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ces.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Aſ.</speaker>
                  <l>Tis brave I ſweare.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <pb facs="tcp:177674:3"/>
                  <speaker>Al.</speaker>
                  <l>Nay it is worthy your wonder</l>
                  <l>That I muſt tell you further, there no Needle</l>
                  <l>In a Sunne Diall plac'd upon his ſteele</l>
                  <l>In ſuch a tender poſture, that doth tremble</l>
                  <l>The timely Diall being held amiſſe,</l>
                  <l>And will ſhake ever, till you hold it right</l>
                  <l>More tender than himſefe in any thing</l>
                  <l>That he concludes in Iuſtice for the State:</l>
                  <l>For as a fever held him, hee will ſhake</l>
                  <l>When he is ſigning any things of weight,</l>
                  <l>Leaſt humane frailty ſhould miſguide his juſtice.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Aſ.</speaker>
                  <l>You have declar'd him a moſt noble <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>uſticer.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Al.</speaker>
                  <l>He truely weighes and feeles Sir, what a charge</l>
                  <l>The ſubjects livings are (being even their lives</l>
                  <l>Laid on the hand of power,) which abus'd</l>
                  <l>Though ſeene, blood flow not from the juſtice ſeate,</l>
                  <l>Tis in true ſence as grievous, and horrid.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Aſ.</speaker>
                  <l>It argues nothing leſſe, but ſince your Lord</l>
                  <l>Is diverſly reported for his parts,</l>
                  <l>Whats your true c<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>nſure of his generall worth,</l>
                  <l>Vertue and Iudgement.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Al.</speaker>
                  <l>As of a Picture wrought to opticke reaſon,</l>
                  <l>That to all paſſers by, ſeemes as they move</l>
                  <l>Now woman, now a Monſter, now a Divell,</l>
                  <l>And till you ſtand, and in a right line view it,</l>
                  <l>You cannot well judge what the maine forme is,</l>
                  <l>So men that view him but in vulgar paſſes</l>
                  <l>Caſting but laterall, or partiall glances,</l>
                  <l>At what he is, ſuppoſe him weake, unjuſt,</l>
                  <l>Bloody, and monſtrous, but ſtand free and faſt,</l>
                  <l>And judge him by no more than what you know</l>
                  <l>Ingenuouſly, and by the right laid line</l>
                  <l>Of truth, he truely, will all ſtiles deſerve</l>
                  <l>Of wiſe, juſt, good, a man both ſoule and nerve.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Aſ.</speaker>
                  <l>Sir, I muſt joyne in juſt beleefe with you,</l>
                  <l>But whats his rivall the Lord high Conſtable?</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Al.</speaker>
                  <l>As juſt, and well inclin'd when hee's himſelfe,</l>
                  <l>(Not wrought on with the counſells, and opinions</l>
                  <pb facs="tcp:177674:4"/>
                  <l>Of other men) and the maine difference is,</l>
                  <l>The Admirall is not flexible nor wonne</l>
                  <l>To move one ſcruple, when he comprehends</l>
                  <l>The honeſt tract and juſtneſſe of a cauſe,</l>
                  <l>The Conſtable explores not ſo ſincerely</l>
                  <l>The courſe hee runnes, but takes the minde of others</l>
                  <l>(By name Iudiciall) for what his owne</l>
                  <l>Iudgement, and knowledge ſhould conclude.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Aſ.</speaker>
                  <l>A fault</l>
                  <l>In my apprehenſion, anothers knowledge</l>
                  <l>Applied to my inſtruction, cannot equall</l>
                  <l>My owne ſoules knowledge, how to informe Acts;</l>
                  <l>The Sunnes rich radiance ſhot through waves moſt faire,</l>
                  <l>Is but a ſhaddow to his beames ith' ayre,</l>
                  <l>His beames that in the ayre we ſo admire,</l>
                  <l>Is but a darkeneſſe to his flame in fire,</l>
                  <l>In fire his fervour but as vapour flies</l>
                  <l>To what his owne pure boſome rarifies:</l>
                  <l>And the Almighty wiſedom, having given</l>
                  <l>Each man within himſelfe an apter light</l>
                  <l>To guide his acts, than any light without him</l>
                  <l>(Creating nothing not in all things equall)</l>
                  <l>It ſeems a fault in any that depend</l>
                  <l>On others knowledge, and exile their owne.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Al.</speaker>
                  <l>Tis nobly argued, and exemplified,</l>
                  <l>But now I heare my Lord, and his young rivall</l>
                  <l>Are to be reconcil'd, and then one light</l>
                  <l>May ſerve to guide them both.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Aſ.</speaker>
                  <l>I wiſh it may, the King being made firſt mover</l>
                  <l>To forme their reconcilement, and enflame it</l>
                  <l>With all the ſweetneſſe of his praiſe and honour.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Al.</speaker>
                  <l>See, tis diſpatch'd I hope, the King doth grace it.</l>
               </sp>
               <stage>Loud Muſicke, and Enter Vſhers before, the Secretary, Treſuror, Chancellor, Admirall, Conſtable hand in hand, the King following, others attend.</stage>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Kin.</speaker>
                  <l>This doth expreſſe the nobleſt fruit of peace.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Cha.</speaker>
                  <l>Which when the great begin, the humble end</l>
                  <l>In joyfull imitation, all combining</l>
                  <pb facs="tcp:177674:4"/>
                  <l>A gardian beyond the <hi>Thrigian</hi> knot</l>
                  <l>Paſt wit to loſe it, or the ſword, be ſtill ſo.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Tre.</speaker>
                  <l>Tis certaine Sir, by concord leaſt things grow</l>
                  <l>Moſt great, and flouriſhing like trees that wrap</l>
                  <l>Their forehead in the skies, may theſe doe ſo.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Kin.</speaker>
                  <l>You heare my Lord, all that is ſpoke contends</l>
                  <l>To celebrate with pious vote the attonement</l>
                  <l>So lately, and ſo nobly made betweene you.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Ad.</speaker>
                  <l>Which for it ſelfe Sir, reſolve to keepe</l>
                  <l>Pure, and inviolable, needing none</l>
                  <l>To encourage or confirme it, but my owne</l>
                  <l>Love and allegiance to your ſacred counſell.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Kin.</speaker>
                  <l>Tis good, and pleaſes, like my deareſt health,</l>
                  <l>Stand you firme on that ſweete ſimplicitie.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Con.</speaker>
                  <l>Paſt all earth pollicie that would infringe it.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Kin.</speaker>
                  <l>Tis well, and anſwers all the doubts ſuſpected<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
                  </l>
                  <stage>Enter one that whiſpers with the Admirall.</stage>
                  <l>And what moves this cloſe meſſage <hi>Phillip?</hi>
                  </l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Adm.</speaker>
                  <l>My wives Father Sir, is cloſely come to Court.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>King.</speaker>
                  <l>Is he come to the Court, whoſe averſation</l>
                  <l>So much affects him, that he ſhunnes and flies it,</l>
                  <l>What's the ſtrange reaſon that he will not riſe</l>
                  <l>Above the middle region he was borne in?</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Adm.</speaker>
                  <l>He ſaith Sir, tis becauſe the extreame of height</l>
                  <l>Makes a man leſſe ſeeme to the imperfect eye</l>
                  <l>Then he is truely, his acts envied more,</l>
                  <l>And though he nothing cares for ſeeming, ſo</l>
                  <l>His being juſt ſtand firme twixt heaven and him,</l>
                  <l>Yet ſince in his ſoules jealouſie, hee feares</l>
                  <l>That he himſelfe advanced, would undervalue</l>
                  <l>Men placed beneath him, and their buſineſſe with him,</l>
                  <l>Since height of place oft dazles height of judgement,</l>
                  <l>He takes his toppe<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> ſaile downe in ſuch rough ſtormes,</l>
                  <l>And apts his ſailes to ayres more temperate.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Kin.</speaker>
                  <l>A moſt wiſe ſoule he has, how long ſhall King<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>
                  </l>
                  <l>Raiſe men that are not wiſe till they be high<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
                  </l>
                  <l>You haue our leave, but tell him <hi>Phillip</hi> wee</l>
                  <l>Would have him neerer.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <pb facs="tcp:177674:5"/>
                  <speaker>Con.</speaker>
                  <l>Your deſires attend you.</l>
               </sp>
               <stage>Enter another.</stage>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Kin.</speaker>
                  <l>We know from whence you come, ſay to the Queene<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
                  </l>
                  <l>We were comming to her, tis a day of love</l>
                  <l>And ſhe ſeales all perfection.</l>
               </sp>
               <stage>Exit</stage>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Tre.</speaker>
                  <l>My Lord,</l>
                  <l>We muſt beſeech your ſtay.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Con.</speaker>
                  <l>My ſtay?</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Cha.</speaker>
                  <l>Our Counſells</l>
                  <l>Have led you thus farre to your reconcilement,</l>
                  <l>And muſt remember you, to obſerve the end</l>
                  <l>At which in plaine I told you then wee aim'd at,</l>
                  <l>You know we all urg'd the attonement, rather</l>
                  <l>To enforce the broader difference betweene you,</l>
                  <l>Then to conclude your friendſhippe, which wiſe men</l>
                  <l>Know to be faſhionable, and priviledg'd pollicie<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
                  </l>
                  <l>And will ſucceede betwixt you, and the Admirall</l>
                  <l>As ſure as fate, if you pleaſe to get ſign'd</l>
                  <l>A ſute now to the King with all our hands,</l>
                  <l>Which will ſo much increaſe his preciſe juſtice,</l>
                  <l>That weighing not circumſtances of politicke State,</l>
                  <l>He will inſtantly oppoſe it, and complaine,</l>
                  <l>And urge in paſſion, what the King will ſooner</l>
                  <l>Puniſh than yeeld too, and ſo render you</l>
                  <l>In the Kings frowne on him, the onely darling<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
                  </l>
                  <l>And mediate power of <hi>France.</hi>
                  </l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Con.</speaker>
                  <l>My good Lord Chancellor,</l>
                  <l>Shall I ſo late atton'd, and by the Kings</l>
                  <l>Hearty and earneſt motion, fall in peeces?</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Cha.</speaker>
                  <l>Tis he, not you that breake.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Tre.</speaker>
                  <l>Ha not you patience</l>
                  <l>To let him burne himſelfe in the Kings flame?</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Cha.</speaker>
                  <l>Come, be not Sir infected with a ſpice</l>
                  <l>Of that too ſervile equitie, that renders</l>
                  <l>Men free borne ſlaves, and rid with bits like horſes,</l>
                  <l>When you muſt know my Lord, that even in nature</l>
                  <l>A man is <hi>Animall politicum,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>So that when he informes his actions ſimply</l>
                  <pb facs="tcp:177674:5"/>
                  <l>He does in both 'gainſt pollicie and nature,</l>
                  <l>And therefore our ſoule motion is affirm'd</l>
                  <l>To be like heavenly natures circular<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
                  </l>
                  <l>And circles being call'd ambitious lines,</l>
                  <l>We muſt like them become ambitious ever,</l>
                  <l>And endles in our circumventions;</l>
                  <l>No tough hides limiting our cheverill mindes.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Tre.</speaker>
                  <l>Tis learnedly, and paſt all anſwer argued,</l>
                  <l>Yare great, and muſt grow greater ſtill, and greater,</l>
                  <l>And not be like a dull and ſtanding lake,</l>
                  <l>That ſettles, putrifies, and chokes with mudde,</l>
                  <l>But like a river guſhing from the head,</l>
                  <l>That windes through the undervalles, what checkes ore flow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing</l>
                  <l>Gets ſtrength ſtill of his courſe,</l>
                  <l>Till with the Ocean meeting, even with him</l>
                  <l>In ſway, and title, his brave billowes move.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Con.</speaker>
                  <l>You ſpeake a ra<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>e affection, and high ſoules,</l>
                  <l>But give me leave great Lords, ſtill my juſt thankes</l>
                  <l>Remembred<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> 
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>o your counſells and direction,</l>
                  <l>I ſeeking this way to confirme my ſelfe</l>
                  <l>I undermine the columnes that ſupport</l>
                  <l>My hopefull glorious fortune, and at once</l>
                  <l>Provoke the tempeſt<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> though did drowne my envie,</l>
                  <l>With what aſſurance ſhall the King expect</l>
                  <l>My faith to him, that breake it for another,</l>
                  <l>He has engag'd our peace, and my revenge</l>
                  <l>Forfits my truſt with him, whoſe narrow <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ight</l>
                  <l>Will penetrate through all our miſts, could we</l>
                  <l>Vaile our deſigne with clouds blacker than night;</l>
                  <l>But grant this danger over, with what Iuſtice,</l>
                  <l>Or ſatisfaction to the inward Iudge,</l>
                  <l>Shall I be gultie of this good mans ruine,</l>
                  <l>Though I may ſtill the murmuring tongues without me,</l>
                  <l>Loud conſcience has a voyce to ſhadder greatneſſe<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
                  </l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Secr.</speaker>
                  <l>A name to fright, and terrifie young ſtatiſts,</l>
                  <l>There is neceſſitie my Lord, that you</l>
                  <l>Muſt loſe your light, if you ecclipſe not him,</l>
                  <l>Two ſtarres ſo Lucide cannot ſhine at once</l>
                  <pb facs="tcp:177674:36"/>
                  <l>In ſuch a firmament, and better you</l>
                  <l>Extinguiſh his fires, then be made his fuell,</l>
                  <l>And in your aſhes give his ſlame a Trophy.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Cha.</speaker>
                  <l>My Lord, the league that you have vow'd of friend<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip,</l>
                  <l>In a true underſtanding not confines you,</l>
                  <l>But makes you boundleſſe, turne not edge at ſuch</l>
                  <l>A liberty, but looke to your owne fortune;</l>
                  <l>Secure your honour, a Preciſian,</l>
                  <l>In ſtate, is a rideculous miracle</l>
                  <l>Friendſhip is but a viſor, beneath which</l>
                  <l>A wiſe man laughes to ſee whole families</l>
                  <l>Ruinde, upon whoſe miſerable pile</l>
                  <l>He mounts to glory, Sir you muſt reſolve</l>
                  <l>To uſe any advantage.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Con.</speaker>
                  <l>Miſery</l>
                  <l>Of riſing Stateſmen I muſt on, I ſee</l>
                  <l>That 'gainſt the politicke, and priviledg'd f<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ſhion,</l>
                  <l>All juſtice taſts but affectation.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Cha.</speaker>
                  <l>Why ſo? we ſhall do good on him ith' end.</l>
               </sp>
               <stage>Exeunt.</stage>
               <stage>Enter Father and the Admirall.</stage>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Adm.</speaker>
                  <l>You are moſt welcome.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Fa.</speaker>
                  <l>I wiſh your Lordſhips ſafetie<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
                  </l>
                  <l>Which whilſt I pray for, I muſt not forget</l>
                  <l>To urge agen the wayes to fixe you where</l>
                  <l>No danger has acceſſe to threaten you.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Adm.</speaker>
                  <l>Still your old argument, I owe your love fort.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Fa.</speaker>
                  <l>But fortified with new and pregnant reaſons,</l>
                  <l>That you ſhould leave the Court.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Ad.</speaker>
                  <l>I dare not Sir.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Fa.</speaker>
                  <l>You dare be undone then.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Ad.</speaker>
                  <l>I ſhould be ingratefull</l>
                  <l>To ſuch a maſter, as no ſubject boaſted</l>
                  <l>To leave his ſervice when they exact</l>
                  <l>My chiefeſt dutie, and attendance Sir.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Fa.</speaker>
                  <l>Would thou we<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>t leſſe degraded from thy titles,</l>
                  <l>And ſwelling offices, that will ith' end</l>
                  <l>Engulfe thee paſt a reſcue, I had not come</l>
                  <l>So farre to trouble you at this time, but that</l>
                  <l>I doe not like the loud tongues o'the world,</l>
                  <pb facs="tcp:177674:36"/>
                  <l>That ſay the King has tane another favorite,</l>
                  <l>The Conſtable a gay man, and a great,</l>
                  <l>With a hugh traine of faction too, the Queene,</l>
                  <l>Chancellor, Treaſurer, Secretary, and</l>
                  <l>An army of ſtate warriers<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> whoſe diſcipline</l>
                  <l>Is ſure, and ſubtile to confuſion,</l>
                  <l>I hope the rumour's falſe, thou art ſo calme.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Adm.</speaker>
                  <l>Report has not abus'd you Sir.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Fa.</speaker>
                  <l>It has not,</l>
                  <l>And you are pleas'd, then you doe meane to mixe</l>
                  <l>With unjuſt courſes, the great Conſtable</l>
                  <l>And you combining, that no ſuite may paſſe</l>
                  <l>One of the graples of your eithers rape,</l>
                  <l>I that abhorr'd, muſt I now entertaine</l>
                  <l>A thought, that your ſo ſtraight, and ſimple cuſtome</l>
                  <l>To render Iuſtice, and the common good,</l>
                  <l>Should now be patch'd with pollicy, and wreſted</l>
                  <l>From the ingenious ſtep you tooke,</l>
                  <l>And hang</l>
                  <l>Vpon the ſhoulders of your enemy</l>
                  <l>To beare you out in what you ſhame to act<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
                  </l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Adm.</speaker>
                  <l>Sir, We both are reconciled.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Fa.</speaker>
                  <l>It followes then that both the acts muſt beare</l>
                  <l>Like reconcilement, and if hee will now</l>
                  <l>Maligne and mallice you for croſſing him</l>
                  <l>Or any of his faction in their ſuites,</l>
                  <l>Being now atton'd, you muſt be one in all,</l>
                  <l>One in corruption, and twixt you two millſtones</l>
                  <l>New pickt, and put together, muſt the graine</l>
                  <l>Of good mens needfull meanes to live, be ground</l>
                  <l>Into your choking ſuperfluities;</l>
                  <l>You both too rich, they ruinde.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Adm.</speaker>
                  <l>I conceive Sir</l>
                  <l>Wee both may be enrich'd, and raiſe our fortunes</l>
                  <l>Even with our places in our Soveraignes favour:</l>
                  <l>Though paſt the height of others, yet within</l>
                  <l>The rules of Law and Iuſtice, and approove</l>
                  <l>Our actions white and innocent.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <pb facs="tcp:177674:6"/>
                  <speaker>Fa.</speaker>
                  <l>I doubt it</l>
                  <l>While inforc'd ſhew perhaps, which will I feare</l>
                  <l>Prove in true ſubſtance but a Millers whiteneſſe,</l>
                  <l>More ſticking in your clothes then conſcience.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Adm.</speaker>
                  <l>Your cenſure herein taſts ſome paſſion Sir,</l>
                  <l>And I beſeech you nouriſh better thoughts,</l>
                  <l>Then to imagine that the Kings meere grace</l>
                  <l>Suſtaines ſuch prejudice by thoſe it honours;</l>
                  <l>That of neceſſitie we muſt pervert it</l>
                  <l>With paſſionate enemies, and ambitious boundleſſe</l>
                  <l>Avarice, and every licence incident</l>
                  <l>To fortunate greatneſſe, and that all abuſe it</l>
                  <l>For the moſt impious avarice of ſome.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Fa.</speaker>
                  <l>As if the totall ſumme of favorites frailties</l>
                  <l>Affected not the full rule of their Kings</l>
                  <l>In their owne partially diſpoſed ambitions,</l>
                  <l>And that Kings doe no hazard infinitely</l>
                  <l>In their free realties of rights and honours,</l>
                  <l>Where they leave much for favourites powers to order.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Adm.</speaker>
                  <l>But wee have ſuch a maſter of our King</l>
                  <l>In the Imperiall art, that no power flies</l>
                  <l>Out of his favour, but his policie ties</l>
                  <l>A criance to it, to containe it ſtill;</l>
                  <l>And for the reconcilement of us Sir,</l>
                  <l>Never were two in favour, that were more,</l>
                  <l>One in all love of Iuſtice, and true honour,</l>
                  <l>Though in the act and pro<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ecution</l>
                  <l>Pehaps we differ. Howſoever yet</l>
                  <l>One beame us both creating, what ſhould let</l>
                  <l>That both our ſoules ſhould both one met<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>le beare,</l>
                  <l>And that one ſtampe, one word, one character.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Fa.</speaker>
                  <l>I could almoſt be won to be a Courtier,</l>
                  <l>Theres ſome thing more in's compoſition,</l>
                  <l>Then ever yet was favourites.</l>
                  <stage>Enter a Courtier.</stage>
                  <l>Whats hee?</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Cour.</speaker>
                  <l>I bring your Lordſhip a ſign'd bill, to <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ave</l>
                  <l>The addition of your honor'd hand, the counſell</l>
                  <pb facs="tcp:177674:6"/>
                  <l>Have all before ſubſcribed, and full prepar'd it.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Ad.</speaker>
                  <l>It ſeemes then they have weigh'd the importance of it,</l>
                  <l>And know the grant is juſt.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Cour.</speaker>
                  <l>No doubt my Lord,</l>
                  <l>Or elſe they take therein the Conſtables word,</l>
                  <l>It being his ſuite, and his power having wrought</l>
                  <l>The King already to appoſe his hand.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Adm.</speaker>
                  <l>I doe not like his working of the King,</l>
                  <l>For if it be a ſuite made knowne to him,</l>
                  <l>And fit to paſſe, he wrought himſelfe to it,</l>
                  <l>However my hand goes to no ſuch grant,</l>
                  <l>But firſt I'le know and cenſure it my ſelfe.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Cour.</speaker>
                  <l>A he, if thou beeſt goddeſſe of contention<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
                  </l>
                  <l>That <hi>Iove</hi> tooke by the haire, and hurl'd from heaven</l>
                  <l>Aſſume in earth thy empire, and this bill</l>
                  <l>Thy firebrand make to turne his love, thus tempted</l>
                  <l>Into a hate, as horrid as thy furies.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Adm.</speaker>
                  <l>Does this beare title of his Lordſhips ſuite?</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Cour.</speaker>
                  <l>It does my Lord, and therefore he beſeech'd</l>
                  <l>The rather your diſpatch.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Adm.</speaker>
                  <l>No thought the rather,</l>
                  <l>But now the rather all powers againſt it,</l>
                  <l>The ſuite being moſt injuſt, and he pretending</l>
                  <l>In all his actions juſtice, on the ſudden</l>
                  <l>After his ſo late vow not to violate it,</l>
                  <l>Is ſtrange and vile, and if the King himſelfe</l>
                  <l>Should owne and urge it, I would ſtay<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> and croſſe it,</l>
                  <l>For tis within the free power of my office,</l>
                  <l>And I ſhould ſtraine his kingdome if I paſt it,</l>
                  <l>I ſee their poore attempts, and giddy malice;</l>
                  <l>Is this the reconcilement that ſo lately</l>
                  <l>He vow'd in ſacred witneſſe of the King?</l>
                  <l>Aſſuring me, he never more would offer</l>
                  <l>To paſſe a ſuite unjuſt, which I well know</l>
                  <l>This is, above all, and have often beene urg'd</l>
                  <l>To give it paſſage, be you Sir the Judge.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Fa.</speaker>
                  <l>I wonot meddle</l>
                  <l>With any thing of ſtate, you knew long ſince.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <pb facs="tcp:177674:7"/>
                  <speaker>Adm.</speaker>
                  <l>Yet you may heare it Sir.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Fa.</speaker>
                  <l>You wonot urge</l>
                  <l>My opinion then, go to.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Adm.</speaker>
                  <l>An honeſt merchant</l>
                  <l>Preſuming on our league of <hi>France</hi> with <hi>Spaine,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>Brought into <hi>Spaine</hi> a wealthy ſhip, to vent</l>
                  <l>Her fit commodities to ſerve the country,</l>
                  <l>Which, in the place of ſuffering their ſaile</l>
                  <l>Were ſeas'd to recompence a <hi>Spaniſh</hi> ſhip</l>
                  <l>Priz'd by a <hi>French man,</hi> ere the league was made,</l>
                  <l>No ſuites, no letters of our Kings could gaine</l>
                  <l>Our merchants firſt right in it, but his letters</l>
                  <l>Vnreverently received, the Kings ſelfe ſcandall,</l>
                  <l>Beſide the leagues breach, and the foule injuſtice</l>
                  <l>Done to our honeſt merchant, who endured all,</l>
                  <l>Till ſome ſmall time ſince (authoris'd by our counſell,</l>
                  <l>Though not in open Court<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>) he made a ſhip out,</l>
                  <l>And tooke a <hi>Spaniard,</hi> brings all home, and ſues</l>
                  <l>To gaine his full prov'd loſſe, full recompence</l>
                  <l>Of his juſt prize, his prize is ſtaid and ceaz'd,</l>
                  <l>Yet for the Kings diſpoſure, and the <hi>Spaniard</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>Makes ſuite to be reſtor'd her, which this bill</l>
                  <l>Would f<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ine get granted, faining (as they hop'd)</l>
                  <l>With my allowance, and way given to make</l>
                  <l>Our Countrey mans in <hi>Spaine</hi> their abſolute prize.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Fa.</speaker>
                  <l>I were abſolute injuſtice.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Adm.</speaker>
                  <l>Should I paſſe it.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Fa.</speaker>
                  <l>Paſſe life, and ſtate before.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Adm.</speaker>
                  <l>If this would ſeeme</l>
                  <l>His Lordſhips ſuite, his love to me, and juſtice</l>
                  <l>Including plots upon me, while my ſimpleneſſe</l>
                  <l>Is ſeriouſly vow'd to reconcilement;</l>
                  <l>Love him good vulgars, and abhorre me ſtill,</l>
                  <l>For if I court your ſlatterie with my crimes,</l>
                  <l>Heavens love before me fly, till in my tombe</l>
                  <l>I ſticke purſuing it, and for this bill,</l>
                  <l>Thus ſay twas ſhiver'd, bleſſe us equall heaven!</l>
               </sp>
               <stage>Exit.</stage>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Fa.</speaker>
                  <l>This could I cheriſh, now above his loſſe,</l>
                  <pb facs="tcp:177674:7"/>
                  <l>You may report as much, the bill diſcharg'd Sir.</l>
               </sp>
               <stage>Exeunt.</stage>
            </div>
            <div n="2" type="act">
               <head>Actus Secundus.</head>
               <stage>Enter King and Queen, Secretary with the Torne bill.</stage>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Kin.</speaker>
                  <l>IS it en<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>
                     <g ref="char:punc">▪</g>ſo.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Que.</speaker>
                  <l>Good heaven how tame you are?</l>
                  <l>Doe Kings of <hi>France</hi> reward foule Traitors thus?</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Kin.</speaker>
                  <l>No Traitor, y'are too loude<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> 
                     <hi>Chabots</hi> no Traitor,</l>
                  <l>He has the paſſions of a man about him,</l>
                  <l>And multiplicitie of cares may make</l>
                  <l>Wiſe men forget themſelves, come be you patient.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Qu.</speaker>
                  <l>Can you be ſo, and ſee your ſelfe thus torne.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Kin.</speaker>
                  <l>Our ſelfe.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Qu.</speaker>
                  <l>There is ſome left, if yo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> dare owne,</l>
                  <l>Your royall character, is not this your name?</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Kin.</speaker>
                  <l>Tis <hi>Francis</hi> I confeſſe.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Qu.</speaker>
                  <l>Be but a name</l>
                  <l>If this ſtaine live upon't, affronted, by</l>
                  <l>Your ſubject, ſhall the ſacred name of King,</l>
                  <l>A word to make your nation bow and tremble,</l>
                  <l>Be thus profain'd, are lawes eſtabliſh'd</l>
                  <l>To puniſh the defacers of your image,</l>
                  <l>But dully ſet by the rude hand of others</l>
                  <l>Vpon your coine, and ſhall the character</l>
                  <l>That doth include the bleſſing of all <hi>France,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>Your name, thus written by your royall hand</l>
                  <l>Deſign'd for Juſtice, and your Kingdomes honour,</l>
                  <l>Not call up equall anger to reward it?</l>
                  <l>Your Counſellors of ſtate contemn'd, and ſlighted</l>
                  <l>As in this braine more circumſcrib'd all wiſedome,</l>
                  <l>And pollicy of Empire, and your power,</l>
                  <l>Subordinate and ſubject to his paſſion.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Kin.</speaker>
                  <l>Come, it concernes you not.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Qu.</speaker>
                  <l>Is this the conſequence</l>
                  <l>Of an attonement made ſo lately betweene<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
                  </l>
                  <pb facs="tcp:177674:8"/>
                  <l>The hopefull <hi>Mountmorencie,</hi> and his Lordſhip</l>
                  <l>Vrge by your ſelfe with ſuch a precious ſanction;</l>
                  <l>Come, he that dares doe this, wants not a heart,</l>
                  <l>But opportunitie.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Kin.</speaker>
                  <l>To doe what?</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Qu.</speaker>
                  <l>To teare your crowne off.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Kin.</speaker>
                  <l>Come your language doth taſte more</l>
                  <l>Of rage and womaniſh flame than ſolid reaſon</l>
                  <l>Againſt the Admirall, what commands of yours</l>
                  <l>Not to your expectation<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> obey'd</l>
                  <l>By him, is ground of your ſo keene diſpleaſure?</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Qu.</speaker>
                  <l>Commands of mine? he is too great, and powerfull</l>
                  <l>To ſtoope to my employment, <hi>a Coloſſus,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>And can ſtride from one Province to another</l>
                  <l>By the aſſiſtance o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> thoſe offices</l>
                  <l>You have moſt confidently impos'd upon him,</l>
                  <l>Tis he, not you take up the peoples eyes</l>
                  <l>And admiration, while his Princely wiſe.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Kin.</speaker>
                  <l>Nay then I reach the ſpring of your diſtaſte,</l>
                  <l>He has a wife,—</l>
               </sp>
               <stage>Enter Chancellor, Treaſurer, and whiſper with the King.</stage>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Qu.</speaker>
                  <l>Whom for her pride I love not,</l>
                  <l>And I but in her husbands ruine</l>
                  <l>Can triumph ore her greatneſſe.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>King.</speaker>
                  <l>Well, well, Ile thinke on't?</l>
               </sp>
               <stage>Exit.</stage>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Cha.</speaker>
                  <l>He beginnes to incline,</l>
                  <l>Madam you are the ſoule of our great worke.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Qu.</speaker>
                  <l>Ile follow, and imploy my powers upon him.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Tre.</speaker>
                  <l>We are confident you will prevaile at laſt,</l>
                  <l>And for the pious worke oblige the King to you.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Cha,</speaker>
                  <l>And us your humbleſt creatures.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Que.</speaker>
                  <l>Preſſe no further.</l>
                  <stage>Exit. Que.</stage>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Cha.</speaker>
                  <l>Lets ſeeke out my Lord Conſtable.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Tre.</speaker>
                  <l>And inflame him.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Cha.</speaker>
                  <l>To expoſtulate with <hi>Chabot,</hi> ſomething may</l>
                  <l>Ariſe from thence, <g ref="char:punc">▪</g>to pull more weight upon him.</l>
               </sp>
               <stage>Exeunt.</stage>
               <stage>Enter Father and Allegre.</stage>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Fa.</speaker>
                  <l>How ſorts the buſineſſe? how tooke the King</l>
                  <pb facs="tcp:177674:8"/>
                  <l>The tearing of his bill?</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Al.</speaker>
                  <l>Exceeding well,</l>
                  <l>And ſeem'd to ſmile at all their grimme complaints,</l>
                  <l>Gainſt all that outrage to his highneſſe hand,</l>
                  <l>And ſaid in plaine, he ſign'd it but to try</l>
                  <l>My Lords firme Iuſtice</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Fa.</speaker>
                  <l>What a ſweete King tis?</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Al.</speaker>
                  <l>But how his rivall the Lord Conſtable</l>
                  <l>Is labour'd by the Chancellor, and others to retort</l>
                  <l>His wrong with ten parts more upon my Lord,</l>
                  <l>Is monſtrous?</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Fa.</speaker>
                  <l>Neede hee their ſpurres?</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Al.</speaker>
                  <l>I Sir, for hees afraid</l>
                  <l>To beare himſelfe too boldly in his braves</l>
                  <l>Vpon the King (being newly entred Mynion)</l>
                  <l>Since tis but patience ſometime they thinke;</l>
                  <l>Becauſe the favor ſpending in two ſtreames,</l>
                  <l>One muſt runne low at length, till when he dare</l>
                  <l>Take fire in ſuch flame, as his faction wiſhes,</l>
                  <l>But with wiſe feare containes himſelfe, and ſo</l>
                  <l>Like a greene faggot in his kindling ſmoakes,</l>
                  <l>And where the Chancellor his chiefe Cyclops findes</l>
                  <l>The fire within him apt to take, he blowes,</l>
                  <l>And then the faggot flames, as never more</l>
                  <l>The bellowes needed, till the too ſoft greeneneſſe</l>
                  <l>Of his ſtate habit, ſhewes his ſappe ſtill flowes,</l>
                  <l>Above the ſolid timber, with which, then</l>
                  <l>His blaze ſhrinkes head, he cooles, and ſmoakes agen.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Fa.</speaker>
                  <l>Good man he would be, wod the bad not ſpoile him.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Al.</speaker>
                  <l>True ſir, but they ſtill ply him with their arts,</l>
                  <l>And as I heard have wrought him, perſonally</l>
                  <l>To queſtion my Lord with all the bitterneſſe</l>
                  <l>The galls of all their faction can powre in,</l>
                  <l>And ſuch an expectation hangs upon't,</l>
                  <l>Though all the Court as twere with child, and long'd</l>
                  <l>To make a mirror of my Lords cleare blood,</l>
                  <l>And therein ſee the full ebbe of his flood,</l>
                  <l>And therefore if you pleaſe to counſell him</l>
                  <pb facs="tcp:177674:9"/>
                  <l>You ſhall performe a fathers part.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Fa.</speaker>
                  <l>Nay ſince</l>
                  <l>Hees gone ſo farre, I wod not have him feare</l>
                  <l>But dare e'm, and yet ile not meddle int.</l>
                  <stage>Enter Admirall.</stage>
                  <l>Hoes here, if he have wit to like his cauſe,</l>
                  <l>His ſpiri<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> wonot be aſham'd to die int.</l>
               </sp>
               <stage>Exit.</stage>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Al.</speaker>
                  <l>My Lord retire, y'are way-laid in your walkes,</l>
                  <l>Your friendes are all fallen from you, all your ſervants</l>
                  <l>Suborn'd by all advantage to report</l>
                  <l>Each word you whiſper out, and to ſerve you</l>
                  <l>With hat and knee, while other have their hearts.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Adm.</speaker>
                  <l>Much profit may my foes make of ſuch ſervants,</l>
                  <l>I love no enemy I have ſo well,</l>
                  <l>To take ſo ill a bargaine from his hands.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Al.</speaker>
                  <l>Their other oddes yet ſhun, all being combinde,</l>
                  <l>And lodg'd in ambuſh ariv'd to doe you miſchiefe</l>
                  <l>By any meanes paſt feare of law, or ſoveraigne.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Adm.</speaker>
                  <l>I wa<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ke no deſart, yet goe arm'd with that,</l>
                  <l>That would give wildeſt beaſts inſtincts to reſcue,</l>
                  <l>Rather then offer any force to hurt me;</l>
                  <l>My innocence is, which is a conquering juſtice,</l>
                  <l>As weares a ſhield, that both defends and fights.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>All.</speaker>
                  <l>One againſt all the world.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Adm.</speaker>
                  <l>The more the oddes,</l>
                  <l>The leſſe the conqueſt, or if all the world</l>
                  <l>Be thought an army fit to employ gainſt one,</l>
                  <l>That one is argued fit to fight gainſt all;</l>
                  <l>If I fall under them, this breaſt ſhall beare</l>
                  <l>Their heape digeſted in my ſepulchre,</l>
                  <l>Death is the life of good men, let e'm come.</l>
               </sp>
               <stage>Enter Conſtable, Chancellor, Treaſurer, Secretary.</stage>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Con.</speaker>
                  <l>I thought my Lord our reconcilement perfect,</l>
                  <l>You have expreſt what ſea of gall flow'd in you,</l>
                  <l>In tearing of the bill I ſent to allow.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Adm.</speaker>
                  <l>Dare you confeſſe the ſending of that bill.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Con.</speaker>
                  <l>Dare, why not?</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Adm.</speaker>
                  <l>Becauſe it breake your oath</l>
                  <pb facs="tcp:177674:9"/>
                  <l>Made in our reconcilement, and betrayes</l>
                  <l>The honour, and the chiefe life of the King</l>
                  <l>Which is his juſtice.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Con.</speaker>
                  <l>Betraies?</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Adm.</speaker>
                  <l>No leſſe, and that Ile prove to him.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Omnes</speaker>
                  <l>You cannot.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Trea.</speaker>
                  <l>I would not wiſh you offer at an action</l>
                  <l>So moſt impoſſibly, and much againſt</l>
                  <l>The judgement, and favour of the King.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Adm.</speaker>
                  <l>His judgement nor his favour I reſpect,</l>
                  <l>So I preſerve his Iuſtice.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Cha.</speaker>
                  <l>Tis not Iuſtice,</l>
                  <l>Which I'le prove by law, and abſolute learning.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Adm.</speaker>
                  <l>All your great law, and learning are but words,</l>
                  <l>When I plead plainely, naked truth, and deedes,</l>
                  <l>Which though you ſeeke to fray with ſtate, and glory,</l>
                  <l>I'le ſhoote a ſhaft at all your globe of light,</l>
                  <l>If lightning ſplit it, yet twas high and right.</l>
               </sp>
               <stage>Exit:</stage>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Con.</speaker>
                  <l>Brave reſolution ſo his acts be juſt,</l>
                  <l>He cares for gaine not honour.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Chan.</speaker>
                  <l>How came he then</l>
                  <l>By all his infinite honour and his gaine?</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Tre.</speaker>
                  <l>Well ſaid my Lord.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Sec.</speaker>
                  <l>Anſwer but onely that.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Con.</speaker>
                  <l>By doing juſtice ſtill in all his actions.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Sec</speaker>
                  <l>But if this action prove unjuſt, will you</l>
                  <l>Say all his other may be ſo as well,</l>
                  <l>And thinke your owne courſe fitter farre than his.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Con,</speaker>
                  <l>I will—</l>
               </sp>
               <stage>Exit.</stage>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Cha.</speaker>
                  <l>He cooles, we muſt not leave him, we have no</l>
                  <l>Such engine to remove the Admirall.</l>
               </sp>
               <stage>Exeunt.</stage>
               <stage>Enter King and the Admirall.</stage>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Kin.</speaker>
                  <l>I prethee <hi>Philip</hi> be not ſo ſevere</l>
                  <l>To him I favour, tis an argument</l>
                  <l>That may ſerve one day to availe your ſelfe,</l>
                  <l>Nor Does it ſquare with your ſo gentle nature,</l>
                  <l>To give ſuch fires of envie to your bloud;</l>
                  <l>For howſoeuer out of love to Iuſtice,</l>
                  <pb facs="tcp:177674:10"/>
                  <l>Your Iealouſie of that doth ſo incenſe you,</l>
                  <l>Yet they that cenſure it will ſay tis envy.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Adm.</speaker>
                  <l>I ſerve not you for them, but for your ſelfe,</l>
                  <l>And that good in your Rule, that Iuſtice does you,</l>
                  <l>And care not this what others ſay, ſo you</l>
                  <l>Pleaſe but to doe me right for what you know.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>King.</speaker>
                  <l>You will not doe your ſelfe right, why ſhould I</l>
                  <l>Exceede you to your ſelfe?</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Adm.</speaker>
                  <l>My ſelfe am nothing</l>
                  <l>Compar'd to what I ſeeke, tis juſtice onely</l>
                  <l>The fount and flood, both of your ſtrength and kingdomes.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>King.</speaker>
                  <l>But who knowes not, that extreame juſtice is</l>
                  <l>(by all ruld lawes) the extreame of injurie,</l>
                  <l>And muſt to you be ſo, the perſons that</l>
                  <l>Your paſſionate heate calls into queſtion</l>
                  <l>Are great, and many, and may wrong in you</l>
                  <l>Your rights of kinde, and dignities of fortune,</l>
                  <l>And I advanc'd you not to heape on you</l>
                  <l>Honours, and fortunes, that by ſtrong hand now</l>
                  <l>Held up, and over you, when heaven takes off</l>
                  <l>That powerfull hand' ſhould thunder on your head,</l>
                  <l>And after you cruſh your ſurviving ſeedes.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Adm.</speaker>
                  <l>Sir, your regards to both are great, and ſacred,</l>
                  <l>But if the innocence, and right that rais'd me</l>
                  <l>And meanes for mine, can finde no friend hereafter</l>
                  <l>Of him that ever lives, and ever ſeconds</l>
                  <l>All Kings juſt bounties with defence, and refuge</l>
                  <l>In juſt mens races, let my fabricke ruine,</l>
                  <l>My ſtocke want ſap, my branches by the roote</l>
                  <l>Be <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>orne to death, and ſwept with whirlewindes out.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>King.</speaker>
                  <l>For my love no relenting.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Adm.</speaker>
                  <l>No my leige,</l>
                  <l>Tis for your love, and right that I ſtand out.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>King.</speaker>
                  <l>Be better yet advis'd.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Adm.</speaker>
                  <l>I cannot Sir</l>
                  <l>Should any Oracle become my counſell,</l>
                  <l>For that I ſtand not out, thus of ſet will,</l>
                  <l>Or pride of any ſingular conceite,</l>
                  <pb facs="tcp:177674:10"/>
                  <l>My e<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ne<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mies, and the world may clearely know,</l>
                  <l>I taſte no ſweetes to drowne in others gall,</l>
                  <l>And to affect in that which makes me lothed,</l>
                  <l>To leave my ſelfe and mine expos'd to all</l>
                  <l>The dangers you propos'd, my purchas'd honours,</l>
                  <l>And all my fortunes in an inſtant loſt,</l>
                  <l>That mony, cares, and paines, and yeares have gather'd,</l>
                  <l>How mad were I to rave thus in my wounds,</l>
                  <l>Vnleſſe my knowne health felt in theſe forc'd iſſues</l>
                  <l>Were ſound, and fit, and that I did not know</l>
                  <l>By moſt true proofes, that to become ſincere</l>
                  <l>With all mens hates, doth farre excëede their loves,</l>
                  <l>To be as they are, mixtures of corruption?</l>
                  <l>And that thoſe envies that I ſee purſue me</l>
                  <l>Of all true actions are the naturall conſequents</l>
                  <l>Which being my object, and my reſolute choiſe</l>
                  <l>Not for my good but yours, I will have juſtice.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>King.</speaker>
                  <l>You will have juſtice, is your will ſo ſtrong</l>
                  <l>Now againſt mine? your power being ſo weake</l>
                  <l>Before my favour gave them both their forces</l>
                  <l>Of all that ever ſhar'd in my free graces,</l>
                  <l>You <hi>Philip Chabot</hi> a meane Gentleman</l>
                  <l>Have not I-rais'd you to a ſupremeſt Lord,</l>
                  <l>And given you greater dignities than any?</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Adm.</speaker>
                  <l>You have ſo.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>King.</speaker>
                  <l>Well ſed, and to ſpurre your dulineſſe</l>
                  <l>With the particulars to which I rais'd you,</l>
                  <l>Have not I made you firſt a Knight of the Order<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>
                  </l>
                  <l>Then Admirall of <hi>France,</hi> then <hi>Count Byzanges,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>Lord, and Livetenant generall of all</l>
                  <l>My country, and command of <hi>Burgady;</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>Livetenant generall likewiſe of my ſonne</l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Daulphine,</hi> and heire, and of all <hi>Normandy,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>And of my chiefely honor'd privy Counſell,</l>
                  <l>And cannot all theſe powers weigh downe your will?</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Adm.</speaker>
                  <l>No Sir, they were not given me to that end,</l>
                  <l>But to uphold my will, my will being juſt.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>King.</speaker>
                  <l>And who ſhall judge that Juſtice, you or I?</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <pb facs="tcp:177674:11"/>
                  <speaker>Adm.</speaker>
                  <l>I Sir, in this caſe your royall thoughts are fitly</l>
                  <l>Exempt from every curious ſearch of one,</l>
                  <l>You have the generall charge with care of all.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Kin.</speaker>
                  <l>And doe not generalls include particulars?</l>
                  <l>May not I Iudge of any thing compriz'd</l>
                  <l>In your particular as well as you?</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Adm.</speaker>
                  <l>Farre be the miſery from you, that you may,</l>
                  <l>My cares, paines, broken ſleepe therein made more</l>
                  <l>Then yours ſhould make me ſee more, and my forces</l>
                  <l>Render of better judgement.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>King.</speaker>
                  <l>Well Sir, grant</l>
                  <l>Your force in this my odds in benefits</l>
                  <l>Paid for your paines, put in the other ſcale,</l>
                  <l>And any equall holder of the ballance</l>
                  <l>Will ſhew my merits hoiſt up yours to aire</l>
                  <l>In rule of any doubt or deed betwixt us.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Adm.</speaker>
                  <l>You merit not of me for benefits</l>
                  <l>More than my ſelfe of you for ſervices.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>King.</speaker>
                  <l>Iſt poſſible.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Adm.</speaker>
                  <l>Tis true.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>King.</speaker>
                  <l>Stand you on that?</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Adm.</speaker>
                  <l>I to the death and will approve to all men.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Kin.</speaker>
                  <l>I am deceiv'd, but I ſhall finde good Judges</l>
                  <l>That will finde difference.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Adm.</speaker>
                  <l>Finde them being good.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>King.</speaker>
                  <l>Still ſo? what if conferring</l>
                  <l>My bounties, and your ſervices to ſound them,</l>
                  <l>We fall foule on ſome licences of yours,</l>
                  <l>Nay, give me therein ſome advantage of you.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Adm.</speaker>
                  <l>They cannot.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>King.</speaker>
                  <l>Not in ſiſting their ſevere diſcharges</l>
                  <l>Of all your offices?</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Adm.</speaker>
                  <l>The more you ſift</l>
                  <l>The more you ſhall refine mee.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>King.</speaker>
                  <l>What if I</l>
                  <l>Grant out againſt you a commiſſion</l>
                  <l>Ioyn'd with an extraordinary proceſſe</l>
                  <l>To arreſt, and put you in lawes hands for triall.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <pb facs="tcp:177674:11"/>
                  <speaker>Adm.</speaker>
                  <l>Not with lawes uttermoſt.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>King.</speaker>
                  <l>Ile throw the dice.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Adm.</speaker>
                  <l>And Ile endure the chance,</l>
                  <l>The dice being ſquare.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Adm.</speaker>
                  <l>Repos'd in dreadleſſe confidence, and conſcience,</l>
                  <l>That all your moſt extreames ſhall never reach,</l>
                  <l>Or to my life, my goodes or honours breach.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>King.</speaker>
                  <l>Was ever heard ſo fine a confidence?</l>
                  <l>Muſt it not p<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ove preſumption, and can that</l>
                  <l>Scape brack<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>s and errors in your ſearch of law,</l>
                  <l>I prethee weigh yet, with more ſoule than danger,</l>
                  <l>And ſome leſſe paſſion.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Adm.</speaker>
                  <l>Witneſſe heaven, I cannot.</l>
                  <l>Were I diſſolv'd, and nothing elſe but ſoule.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>King.</speaker>
                  <l>Be ſhrew my blood, but his reſolves amaze me;</l>
                  <l>Was ever ſuch a Iuſtice in a ſubject<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
                  </l>
                  <l>Of ſo much office left to his owne ſwinge</l>
                  <l>That left to law thus, and his Soveraignes wrath,</l>
                  <l>Could ſtand cleare ſpight of both? let reaſon rule it</l>
                  <l>Before it come at law, a man ſo rare</l>
                  <l>In one thing cannot in the reſt be vulgar,</l>
                  <l>And who ſees you not in the broad high-way</l>
                  <l>The common duſt up in your owne eyes, beating</l>
                  <l>In queſt of riches, honours, offices,</l>
                  <l>As heartily in ſhew as moſt beleeve,</l>
                  <l>And he that can uſe actions with the vulgar,</l>
                  <l>Muſt needes embrace the ſame effects &amp; cannot informe him</l>
                  <l>Whatſoever he pretends, uſe them with ſuch</l>
                  <l>Free equitie, as fits one juſt and reall<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
                  </l>
                  <l>Even in the eyes of men, nor ſtand at all parts</l>
                  <l>So truly circular, ſo ſound, and ſolid,</l>
                  <l>But have his ſwellings out, his crackes and crannies,</l>
                  <l>And therefore in this reaſon, before law</l>
                  <l>Take you to h<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>r, leaſt you affect and flatter</l>
                  <l>Your ſelfe with mad opinions.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Adm.</speaker>
                  <l>I were mad</l>
                  <l>Directly Sir, if I were yet to know</l>
                  <l>Not the ſure danger, but the certaine ruine</l>
                  <pb facs="tcp:177674:12"/>
                  <l>Of men ſhot into law from Kings bent brow,</l>
                  <l>There being no dreame from the moſt muddie braine</l>
                  <l>Vpon the fouleſt fa<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>cie, that can forge</l>
                  <l>More horrour in the ſhaddowes of meere fame,</l>
                  <l>Then can ſome Lawyer in a man expos'd</l>
                  <l>To his interpretation by the King,</l>
                  <l>But theſe grave toyes I ſhall deſpiſe in death,</l>
                  <l>And while I live will lay them open ſo</l>
                  <l>(My inocence laid by them) that like foiles</l>
                  <l>They ſhall ſticke of my merits tenne times more,</l>
                  <l>And make your bounties nothing, for who gives</l>
                  <l>And hits ith teeth, himſelfe payes with the glory</l>
                  <l>For which he gave, as being his end of giving,</l>
                  <l>Not to crowne merits, or doe any good,</l>
                  <l>And ſo no thankes is due but to his glory.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>King.</speaker>
                  <l>Tis brave I ſweare.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Adm.</speaker>
                  <l>No Sir, tis plaine, and rude</l>
                  <l>But true, and ſpotleſſe, and where you object</l>
                  <l>My hearty, and groſſe vulgar love of riches,</l>
                  <l>Titles, and honours, I did never ſeeke them</l>
                  <l>For any love to them, but to that juſtice</l>
                  <l>You ought to uſe in their due gift to merits,</l>
                  <l>To ſhew you royall, and moſt open handed,</l>
                  <l>Not uſing for hands talons, pincers, grapples;</l>
                  <l>In whoſe gripes, and upon whoſe gord point,</l>
                  <l>Deſerts hang ſprawling out their vertuous limbs,</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>King.</speaker>
                  <l>Better and better.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Adm.</speaker>
                  <l>This your glory is</l>
                  <l>My deſerts wrought upon no wretched matter,</l>
                  <l>But ſhew'd your royall palmes as free, and moiſt,</l>
                  <l>As <hi>Ida,</hi> all enchaſt with ſilver ſprings,</l>
                  <l>And yet my merit ſtill their equall ſings.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>King.</speaker>
                  <l>Sing till thou ſigh thy ſoule out hence, and leave us.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Adm.</speaker>
                  <l>My perſon ſhall, my love and faith ſhall never.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>King.</speaker>
                  <l>Periſh thy love, and faith, and thee for ever;</l>
                  <l>Whoſe there?</l>
                  <stage>Enter Aſall.</stage>
                  <l>Let one goe for the Chancellor.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <pb facs="tcp:177674:12"/>
                  <speaker>Aſa.</speaker>
                  <l>He's here in Court Sir.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>King.</speaker>
                  <l>Haſte and ſend him hither,</l>
                  <l>This is an inſolence I never met with,</l>
                  <l>Can one ſo high as his degrees aſcend,</l>
                  <l>Clime all ſo free, and without ſtaine?</l>
                  <l>My Lord</l>
                  <stage>Enter Chancellor.</stage>
                  <l>Chancellor, I ſend for you about a ſervice</l>
                  <l>Of equall price to me, as if againe</l>
                  <l>My ranſome came to me from <hi>Pavian</hi> thraldome,</l>
                  <l>And more, as if from forth a ſubjects fetters,</l>
                  <l>The worſt of ſervitudes my life were reſcued.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Cha.</speaker>
                  <l>You fright me with a Prologue of much trouble<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
                  </l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>King.</speaker>
                  <l>Me thinkes it might be, tell me out of all</l>
                  <l>Your famous learning, was there ever ſubject</l>
                  <l>Rais'd by his Soveraignes free hand from the duſt,</l>
                  <l>Vp to a height above Ayres upper region,</l>
                  <l>That might compare with him in any merit</l>
                  <l>That ſo advanc'd him? and not ſhew in that</l>
                  <l>Groſſe over-weening worthy cauſe to thinke</l>
                  <l>There might be other over-ſights excepted</l>
                  <l>Of capitall nature in his ſifted greatneſſe.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Chan.</speaker>
                  <l>And paſt queſtion Sir, for one abſur'd thing granted,</l>
                  <l>A thouſand follow.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>King.</speaker>
                  <l>You muſt then employ</l>
                  <l>Your moſt exact, and curious art to explore</l>
                  <l>A man in place of greateſt truſt, and charge,</l>
                  <l>Whom I ſuſpect to have abus'd them all,</l>
                  <l>And in whom you may give ſuch proud veines vent,</l>
                  <l>As will bewray their boyling bloud corrupted</l>
                  <l>Both gainſt my crowne and life.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Cha.</speaker>
                  <l>And may my life</l>
                  <l>Be cruſt in every act,</l>
                  <l>If I explore him not to every finer.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>King.</speaker>
                  <l>It is my Admirall.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Cha.</speaker>
                  <l>Oh my good Leige</l>
                  <l>You tempt, not charge me with ſuch ſearch of him.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>King.</speaker>
                  <l>Doubt not my heartieſt meaning, all the troubles</l>
                  <l>That ever mov'd in a diſtracted King,</l>
                  <pb facs="tcp:177674:13"/>
                  <l>Put in juſt feare of his aſſaulted life</l>
                  <l>Are not above my ſufferings for <hi>Chabot.</hi>
                  </l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Cha.</speaker>
                  <l>Then I am glad, and proud that I can cure you,</l>
                  <l>For he's a man that I am ſtudied in,</l>
                  <l>And all his offices, and if you pleaſe</l>
                  <l>To give authoritie.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>King.</speaker>
                  <l>You ſhall not want it.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Cha.</speaker>
                  <l>If I diſcharge you not of that diſeaſe,</l>
                  <l>About your necke growne, by your ſtrange truſt in him,</l>
                  <l>With full diſcovery of the fouleſt treaſons.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>King.</speaker>
                  <l>But I muſt have all prov'd with that free juſtice.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Cha.</speaker>
                  <l>Beſeech your Majeſtie doe not queſtion it.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>King.</speaker>
                  <l>About it inſtantly, and take me wholly</l>
                  <l>Vpon your ſelfe.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Cha.</speaker>
                  <l>How much you grace your ſervant?</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>King.</speaker>
                  <l>Let it be fiery quicke.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Cha.</speaker>
                  <l>It ſhall have wings,</l>
                  <l>And every feather ſhew the ſlight of Kings.</l>
               </sp>
            </div>
            <div n="3" type="act">
               <head>Actus Tertius.</head>
               <stage>Enter Chancellor attended, the Proctor generall whiſpering in his eare. Two Iudges following. They paſt.</stage>
               <stage>Enter Chabot in his gowne, a gaurd about him, his father and his wife on each ſide, Allegre.</stage>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Adm.</speaker>
                  <l>ANd have they put my faithfull ſervant to the racke,</l>
                  <l>Heaven arme the honeſt man.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Fa.</speaker>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Allegre</hi> feeles the malice of the Chancellor.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Adm.</speaker>
                  <l>Many upon the torture have confeſt</l>
                  <l>Things againſt truth, and yet his paine ſits neerer</l>
                  <l>Than all my other feares, come don't weepe.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Wife</speaker>
                  <l>My Lord, I doe not grive out of a thought,</l>
                  <l>Or poore ſuſpition, they with all their malice</l>
                  <l>Can ſtaine your honour, but it troubles me,</l>
                  <l>The King ſhould grant this licence to your enemies,</l>
                  <l>As he were willing to heare <hi>Chabot</hi> guilty.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <pb facs="tcp:177674:13"/>
                  <speaker>Adm.</speaker>
                  <l>No more, the King is juſt, and by expoſing me</l>
                  <l>To this triall, meanes to render me</l>
                  <l>More happy to his ſubjects, and himſelfe</l>
                  <l>His ſacred will be obey'd, take thy owne ſpirit,</l>
                  <l>And let no thought in fringe thy peace for me,</l>
                  <l>I goe to have my honours all confirm'd;</l>
                  <l>Farewell thy lip, my cauſe has ſo much innocence,</l>
                  <l>It ſhanot neede thy prayer, I leave her yours</l>
                  <l>Till my returne; oh let me be a ſonne</l>
                  <l>Still in your thoughts, now Gentlemen ſet forward.</l>
               </sp>
               <stage>Exit.</stage>
               <stage>Manente Father and Wife.</stage>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Fa.</speaker>
                  <l>See you that truſt in greatneſſe, what ſuſtaines you,</l>
                  <l>Theſe hazards you muſt looke for, you that thruſt</l>
                  <l>Your heads into a cloud, where lie in ambuſh</l>
                  <l>The ſouldiers of ſtate in privy armes</l>
                  <l>Of yellow fire jealous, and mad at all</l>
                  <l>That ſhoote their foreheads up into their forges,</l>
                  <l>And pry into their gloomy Cabbinets;</l>
                  <l>You like vaine Citizens that muſt goe ſee</l>
                  <l>Thoſe ever burning furnaces, wherein</l>
                  <l>Your brittle glaſſes of eſtate are blowne;</l>
                  <l>Who knowes not you are all but puffe, and bubble</l>
                  <l>Of breath, and fume forg'd, your vile brittle natures</l>
                  <l>Cauſe of your deareneſſe? were you tough and laſting,</l>
                  <l>You would be cheape, and not worth halfe your face,</l>
                  <l>Now daughter Plannet ſtrooke.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Wif.</speaker>
                  <l>I am conſidering</l>
                  <l>What forme I ſhall put on, as beſt agreeing</l>
                  <l>With my Lords fortune.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Fa.</speaker>
                  <l>Habit doe you meane,</l>
                  <l>Of minde or body?</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Wif.</speaker>
                  <l>Both wod be apparell'd.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Fa.</speaker>
                  <l>In neither you have reaſon yet to mourne.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Wif.</speaker>
                  <l>Ile not accuſe my heart of ſo much weakeneſſe<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
                  </l>
                  <l>Twere a confeſſion gainſt my Lord. The Queene!</l>
                  <stage>Enter Queene, Conſtable, Treaſurer, Secretary.</stage>
                  <l>She has expreſt 'gainſt me ſome diſpleaſure.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Fa.</speaker>
                  <l>Lets this way through the Gallery.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <pb facs="tcp:177674:14"/>
                  <speaker>Qu.</speaker>
                  <l>Tis ſhe,</l>
                  <l>Doe you my Lord ſay I wo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> ſpeake with her?</l>
                  <l>And has <hi>Allegre,</hi> one of chiefeſt truſt with him</l>
                  <l>Suff<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>red the racke<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> the Chancellor is violent;</l>
                  <l>And whats c<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>nfeſt?</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Tre.</speaker>
                  <l>Nothing, he contemn'd all</l>
                  <l>That could with any cruelſt paine explore him,</l>
                  <l>As if his mind<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> had rob'd his nerves of ſence,</l>
                  <l>And through them diffusd fiery ſpirits above</l>
                  <l>All fleſh and blood; for as his limbs were ſtretch'd,</l>
                  <l>His contempts too extended.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Qu.</speaker>
                  <l>A ſtrange fortitude<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
                  </l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Tre.</speaker>
                  <l>But we ſhall loſe th' arraignement.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Qu.</speaker>
                  <l>The ſucceſſe</l>
                  <l>Will ſoone arrive.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Tre.</speaker>
                  <l>Youle not appeare, my Lord then?</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Con.</speaker>
                  <l>I deſire</l>
                  <l>Your Lordſhip wod excuſe me.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Tre.</speaker>
                  <l>We are your ſervants.</l>
               </sp>
               <stage>Exiunt. Tre. &amp; Sec.</stage>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Con.</speaker>
                  <l>She attends you Madam.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Qu.</speaker>
                  <l>This humbleneſſe proceedes not from your heart,</l>
                  <l>Why, you are a Queene your ſelfe in your owne thoughts,</l>
                  <l>The Admiralls wife of <hi>France</hi> cannot be leſſe,</l>
                  <l>You have not ſtate enough, you ſhold not move</l>
                  <l>Without a traine of friends and ſervants.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Wif.</speaker>
                  <l>There is ſome myſtery</l>
                  <l>Within your language Madam, I woud hope</l>
                  <l>You have more charitie than to imagine</l>
                  <l>My preſent condition worth your triumph,</l>
                  <l>In which I am not ſo loſt, but I have</l>
                  <l>Some friends and ſervants with proportion</l>
                  <l>To my Lords fortune, but none within the liſt</l>
                  <l>Of thoſe that obey mee can be more ready</l>
                  <l>To expreſſe their duties, than my heart to ſerve</l>
                  <l>Your juſt commands.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Qu.</speaker>
                  <l>Then pride will ebbe I ſee,</l>
                  <l>There is no conſtant flood of ſtate, and greatneſſe,</l>
                  <l>The prodigie is ceaſing when your Lord</l>
                  <pb facs="tcp:177674:14"/>
                  <l>Comes to the ballance, hee whoſe blazing fires,</l>
                  <l>Shot wonders through the Kingdome, will diſcover</l>
                  <l>What ſlying and corrupted matter ſed him.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Wif.</speaker>
                  <l>My Lord?</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Qu.</speaker>
                  <l>Your high and mighty Juſticer,</l>
                  <l>The man of conſcience, the Oracle</l>
                  <l>Of State, whoſe honorable titles</l>
                  <l>Would cracke an Elephants backe, is now turn'd mortall,</l>
                  <l>Muſt paſſe examination, and the teſt</l>
                  <l>Of Law, have all his offices rip<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>d up,</l>
                  <l>And his corrupt ſoule laid open to the ſubjects,</l>
                  <l>His bribes, oppreſſions, and cloſe ſinnes that made</l>
                  <l>So many grone, and curſe him, now ſhall finde</l>
                  <l>Their juſt reward, and all that love their country,</l>
                  <l>Bleſſe heaven, and the Kings Iuſtice, for removing</l>
                  <l>Such a devouring monſter.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Fa.</speaker>
                  <l>Sir your pardon</l>
                  <l>Madam you are the Queene, ſhe is my daughter,</l>
                  <l>And he that you have character'd ſo monſtrous,</l>
                  <l>My ſonne in Law, now gon to be arraign'd,</l>
                  <l>The King is juſt, and a good man, but't does not</l>
                  <l>Adde to the graces of your royall perſon</l>
                  <l>To tread upon a Lady thus dejected</l>
                  <l>By her owne griefe, her Lord's not yet found guilty,</l>
                  <l>Much leſſe condemn'd, though you have pleas'd to execute him.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Qu.</speaker>
                  <l>What ſaw<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>y fellow's this?</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Fa.</speaker>
                  <l>I muſt confeſſe</l>
                  <l>I am a man out of this element</l>
                  <l>No Courtier, yet I am a gentleman</l>
                  <l>That dare ſpeake honeſt truth to the Queenes care,</l>
                  <l>(A duty every ſubject wonot pay you)</l>
                  <l>And juſtifie it to all the world, there's nothing</l>
                  <l>Doth more ecclipſe the honours of our ſoule,</l>
                  <l>Than an ill grounded, and ill followed paſſion,</l>
                  <l>Let ſlie with noiſe, and licenſe againſt thoſe<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
                  </l>
                  <l>Whoſe hearts before are bleeding.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Con.</speaker>
                  <l>Brave old man.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Fa.</speaker>
                  <l>Cauſe<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> you are a Queene to trample ore a woman,</l>
                  <pb facs="tcp:177674:15"/>
                  <l>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap> tongue and faculties are all tied up,</l>
                  <l>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap> out a Lyons teeth, and pare his clawes,</l>
                  <l>And then a dwarfe may plucke him by the beard,</l>
                  <l>Tis a gay victory.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Qu,</speaker>
                  <l>Did you hëare my Lord?</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Fa.</speaker>
                  <l>I ha done.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Wif.</speaker>
                  <l>And it concernes me to beginne,</l>
                  <l>I have not made this pauſe through ſervile feare</l>
                  <l>Or guiltie apprehenſion of your rage,</l>
                  <l>But with juſt wonder of the heates, and wildneſſe</l>
                  <l>Has prepoſſeſt your nature gainſt our innocence,</l>
                  <l>You are my Queene, unto that title bowes</l>
                  <l>The humbleſt knee in <hi>France,</hi> my heart made lower</l>
                  <l>With my obedience, and proſtrate duty,</l>
                  <l>Nor have I powers created for my uſe,</l>
                  <l>When juſt commands of you expect their ſervice;</l>
                  <l>But were you Queene of all the world, or ſomething</l>
                  <l>To be thought greater, betwixt heaven and us</l>
                  <l>That I could reach you with my eyes and voyce,</l>
                  <l>I would ſhoote both up in defence of my</l>
                  <l>Abuſed honour, and ſtand all your lightning.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Qu.</speaker>
                  <l>So brave.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Wif.</speaker>
                  <l>So juſt and boldly innocent,</l>
                  <l>I cannot feare arm'd with a noble conſcience</l>
                  <l>The tempeſt of your frowne, were it more frightfull</l>
                  <l>Then every fury made a womans anger,</l>
                  <l>Prepar'd to kill with deaths moſt horrid ceremony,</l>
                  <l>Yet with what freedome of my ſoule I can</l>
                  <l>Forgive your accuſation of my pride.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Qu.</speaker>
                  <l>Forgive? what inſolence is like this language?</l>
                  <l>Can any action of ours be capable</l>
                  <l>Of thy forgiveneſſe? duſt! how I diſpiſe thee?</l>
                  <l>Can we ſinne to be object of thy mercie?</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Wif.</speaker>
                  <l>Yes, and have dont already, and no ſtaine</l>
                  <l>To your greatneſſe Madam, tis my charity</l>
                  <l>I can remit, when ſoveraigne Princes dare</l>
                  <l>Doe injury to thoſe that live beneath them,</l>
                  <l>They turne worth pitty, and their pray<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>rs, and tis</l>
                  <pb facs="tcp:177674:15"/>
                  <l>In the free power of thoſe whom they oppreſſe</l>
                  <l>To pardon e'm, each ſoule has a prerogative,</l>
                  <l>And priviledge royall that was ſign'd by heaven,</l>
                  <l>But though ith knowledge of my diſpoſition</l>
                  <l>Stranger to pride, and what you charge me with,</l>
                  <l>I can forgive the injuſtice done to me,</l>
                  <l>And ſtriking at my perſon, I have no</l>
                  <l>Commiſſion from my Lord to cleere you for</l>
                  <l>The wrongs you have done him, and ſtill he pardon</l>
                  <l>The wounding of his loyaltie, with which life</l>
                  <l>Can hold no ballance, I muſt talke juſt boldneſſe</l>
                  <l>To ſay—</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Fa</speaker>
                  <l>No more, now I muſt tell you daughter</l>
                  <l>Leaſt you forget your ſelfe, ſhe is the Queene,</l>
                  <l>And it becomes not you to vie with her</l>
                  <l>Paſſion for paſſion, if your Lord ſtand faſt</l>
                  <l>To the full ſearch of Law, Heaven will revenge him,</l>
                  <l>And give him up precious to good mens loves</l>
                  <l>If you attempt by theſe unruly wayes</l>
                  <l>To vindicate his juſtice, I me againſt you,</l>
                  <l>Deere as I wiſh your husbands life and fame,</l>
                  <l>Suffer are bound to ſuffer, not conteſt</l>
                  <l>With Princes, ſince their Will and Acts muſt be</l>
                  <l>Accounted one day to a Judge ſupreme.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Wif.</speaker>
                  <l>I ha done, if the devotion to my Lord,</l>
                  <l>Or pietie to his innocence have led me</l>
                  <l>Beyond the awfull limits to be obſerv'd</l>
                  <l>By one ſo much beneath your ſacred perſon,</l>
                  <l>I thus low crave your royall pardon Madam;</l>
                  <l>I know you will remember in your goodneſſe,</l>
                  <l>My life blood is concern'd while his leaſt veine</l>
                  <l>Shall runne blacke and polluted, my heart fed</l>
                  <l>With what keepes him alive, nor can there be</l>
                  <l>A greater wound than that which ſtrikes the life</l>
                  <l>Of our good name, ſo much above the bleeding</l>
                  <l>Of this rude pile wee carry, as the ſoule</l>
                  <l>Hath excellence above this earth-borne frailty:</l>
                  <l>My Lord, by the Kings will is lead already</l>
                  <pb facs="tcp:177674:16"/>
                  <l>To a ſevere arraignement, and to Iudges,</l>
                  <l>Will make no tender ſearch into his tract</l>
                  <l>Of life and ſtate, ſtay but a little while,</l>
                  <l>And <hi>
                        <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>ranc<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>
                     </hi> ſhall <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="3 letters">
                        <desc>•••</desc>
                     </gap>ho to his ſhame or innocence,</l>
                  <l>This ſuit I begge with teares, I ſhall have ſorrow</l>
                  <l>Enough to heare him cenſur'd foule and monſtrous,</l>
                  <l>Should you forbeare to antidate my ſufferings.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Qu.</speaker>
                  <l>Your conſcience comes about, and you incline</l>
                  <l>To feare he may be worth the lawes condemning.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Wif.</speaker>
                  <l>I ſooner will ſuſpect the ſtarres may loſe</l>
                  <l>Their way, and criſtall heaven returne to Chaos;</l>
                  <l>Truth <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>its not on her ſquare more firme than he;</l>
                  <l>Yet let me tell you Madam, were his life</l>
                  <l>And action ſo foule as you have character'd,</l>
                  <l>And the bad world expects, though as a wife</l>
                  <l>Twere duty I ſhould weepe my ſelfe to death,</l>
                  <l>To know him falne from vertue, yet ſo much</l>
                  <l>I a fraile woman love my King and Country,</l>
                  <l>I ſhould condemne him too, and think<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> all honours</l>
                  <l>The price of his loſt faith more fatall to me,</l>
                  <l>Than <hi>Cleopatra's</hi> aſpes warme in my boſome,</l>
                  <l>And as much boaſt their killing.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Qu.</speaker>
                  <l>This declares</l>
                  <l>Another ſoule than was deliver'd me,</l>
                  <l>My anger melts, and I beginne to pitty her,</l>
                  <l>How much a Princes eare may be abus'd?</l>
                  <l>Enjoy your happie confidence, at more leaſure</l>
                  <l>You may heare from us.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Wif.</speaker>
                  <l>Heaven preſerve the Queene,</l>
                  <l>And may her heart be charitable.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Fa.</speaker>
                  <l>You bleſſe and honour your unworthy ſervant.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Qu.</speaker>
                  <l>My Lord, did you obſerve this?</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Con.</speaker>
                  <l>Yes great Madam,</l>
                  <l>And read a noble ſpirit, which becomes</l>
                  <l>The wife of <hi>Chabot,</hi> their great ti<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> of m<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>rriage</l>
                  <l>I<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> not more ſtrong upon em, than their vertues.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Qu.</speaker>
                  <l>That your opinion? I thought your judgement</l>
                  <l>Againſt the Admi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>all, doe you thinke him honeſt?</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <pb facs="tcp:177674:16"/>
                  <speaker>Con.</speaker>
                  <l>Religiouſly, a true, moſt zealous Patrior,</l>
                  <l>And worth all royall favour.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Qu.</speaker>
                  <l>You amaze me,</l>
                  <l>Can you be juſt your ſelfe then, and advance</l>
                  <l>Your powers againſt him?</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Con.</speaker>
                  <l>Such a will be farre</l>
                  <l>From <hi>Montmoranzie,</hi> Pioners of ſtate</l>
                  <l>Have left no art to gaine me to their faction,</l>
                  <l>And tis my miſery to be plac'd in ſuch</l>
                  <l>A ſphere where I am whirl'd by violence</l>
                  <l>Of a fierce raging motion, and not what</l>
                  <l>My owne will would encline me. I ſhall make</l>
                  <l>This appeare Madam, if you pleaſe to ſecond</l>
                  <l>My free ſpeech with the King.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Qu.</speaker>
                  <l>Good heaven protect all,</l>
                  <l>Haſte to the King, Iuſtice her ſwift wing needes,</l>
                  <l>Tis high time to be good, when vertue bleedes.</l>
               </sp>
               <stage>Exeunt.</stage>
               <stage>Enter Officers before the Chancellor, Iudges, the Proctor generall, whiſpering with the Chancellor, they take their places.</stage>
               <p>To them</p>
               <stage>Enter Treaſures and Secretary who take their places prepared on one ſide of the Court.</stage>
               <p>To them</p>
               <stage>The Captaine of the Guard, the Admirall following, who is plac'd at the barre.</stage>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Cha.</speaker>
                  <l>Good Mr. Proctor generall begin.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Pro,</speaker>
                  <p>It is not unknowne to you my very good Lords the Iudges, and indeed to all the world, for I will make ſhort worke, ſince your honourable eares neede not to be enlarged, I ſpeake by a figure with prolixe ennumeration how infinitly the King hath favoured this ill favoured Traitor; and yet I may worthily too inſiſt and prove that no grace hath beene ſo large and voluminous, as this, that he hath appointed ſuch up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>right Iudges at this time, and the chiefe of this Triumvirie, our Chancellor by name <hi>Poyet,</hi> which deriveth from the Greeke his Etymology from <hi>Poyeni,</hi> which is to make, to create, to invent matter that was never extant in nature, from
<pb facs="tcp:177674:17"/> whence alſo is the name and dignitie of <hi>Poeta,</hi> which I will not inſiſt upon, in this place, although I am confident his Lordſhippe wanteth no facultie in making of Verſes: but what addition I ſay is it to the honour of this Delinquent, that he hath ſuch a Iudge, a man ſo learned, ſo full of equity, ſo noble, ſo notable in the progreſſe of his life, ſo innocent, in the manage of his office ſo incorrupt; in the paſſages of State ſo wiſe, in affection to his country ſo religious, in all his ſervices to the King ſo fortunate, and exploring, as envie it ſelfe cannot accuſe, or malice vitiate, whom all lippes will open to commend, but thoſe of <hi>Philip;</hi> and in their hearts will erect Altars, and Statues, Columnes, and Obeliſhes, Pillars and Pyramids, to the perpetuitie of his name and memory. What ſhall I ſay <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> but conclude for his ſo great and ſacred ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vice, both to our King and Kingdome, and for their everla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſting benefit, there may everlaſtingly be left here one of his loynes, one of his loynes ever remaine I ſay, and ſtay upon this Bench, to be the example of all Iuſtice, even while the North and South Starre ſhall continue.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Cha.</speaker>
                  <l>You expreſſe your Oratory Mr. Proctor,</l>
                  <l>I ray come preſen<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ly to the matter.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Pro.</speaker>
                  <p>Thus with your Lordſhips pardon, I proceede; and the firſt thing I ſhall glance at, will be worth your Lordſhips reflection, his ingratitude, and to whom? to no leſſe perſon than a King, and to what King, his owne, and our generall So<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veraigne <hi>Proh deum atque hominum fidem;</hi> a King, and ſuch a King, the health, life, and ſoule of us all, whoſe very mention drawes this ſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>lt water from my eyes; for hee indeede is our eye, who wakes and watches for us when we ſleepe, and who will not ſleep<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> for him, I meane not ſleepe, which the Philoſophers call, a naturall c<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ſſation of the common and conſequently<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> of all the exterior ſences, cauſed firſt and immediatly by a detenſion of ſpirits, which can have no communication, ſince the way is obſtructed, by which the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſe ſpirits ſhould commearce, by vapours aſcending from the ſtomacke to the head, by which evaporation the rootes of the nerves are filled, through which the annuall ſpirits, to be powred into the dwellings of the externall ſences; but ſleepe
<pb facs="tcp:177674:17"/> I take<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> for death, which all know to be <hi>
                        <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ltima linea,</hi> who will not ſleepe eternally for ſuch a King as wee enjoy? If there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore in generall as hee is King of us all, all ſharing and divi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding the benefits of this our Soveraigne: none ſhould be ſo in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gratefull as once to murm<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>re againſt him, what ſhall be ſaid of the ingratitude more monſtrous in this <hi>Chabot,</hi> for our <hi>Francis</hi> hath loved, not in generall in the croud with other ſubjects, but particularly this <hi>Ph<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>l<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>p</hi> advanc'd him to the ſupreme dig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nitie of a Statſman, lodg'd him in his very heart, yet <hi>Monſtrum horrendum;</hi> even to this <hi>Francis</hi> hath <hi>Philip</hi> beene ingratefull. <hi>Brutus</hi> the loved ſonne hath ſtabbed <hi>Caeſar</hi> with a Bodkin: Oh what brute may be compared to him? and in what parti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>culars may this crime be exemplified; hee hath, as wee ſay, chopt Logicke with the King, nay to the very teeth of his Soveraigne advance his owne Gnat-like merits, and juſtified with <hi>Luciferous</hi> pride, that his ſervices have deſerved more than all the bounty of our Munificent King hath paid him.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Cha.</speaker>
                  <p>O<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ſerve that my Lords.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Pro.</speaker>
                  <p>Nay he hath gone further, and moſt traitaerouſly hath commitred outrage and impiety to the Kings owne hand, and royall character, which preſented to him in a bill from the whole counſell, hee moſt violently did teare in peeces, and will doe the very body and perſon of your King, if our Juſtice make no timely prevention, and ſtrike out the Serpentine teeth of th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> high and more than ho<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>rible monſter.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Tr.</speaker>
                  <p>This was e<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>forced home.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Pro.</speaker>
                  <p>In the next place I will relate to your honours his moſt cruell exactions upon the ſubject, the old vantcurriers of rebellions. In the yeare 15. 6. and 37. This oppreſſour, and this extortioner, under pretext of his due taxation, being Ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mirall impo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>'d upon certaine Fiſhermen, (obſerve I beſeech you the circumſtance of their perſons, Fiſhermen) who poore <hi>Iohns</hi> were embarqued upon the coſt of <hi>Normandy,</hi> and fiſhing there for Herrings (which ſome ſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>y is the king of Fiſhes) he impos'd I ſay twenty <hi>ſouſe,</hi> and upon every boate ſixe <hi>liuers,</hi> oh intollerable exaction! enough not onely to alienate the hearts of theſe miſerable people from their King, which <hi>Ipſo facto</hi> is high treaſon, but an occaſion of a greater inconveni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence,
<pb facs="tcp:177674:18"/> for want of due proviſion of fiſh among the ſubjects, for by this might enſue a neceſſitie of mortall ſins, by breaking the religious faſt upon Vigils, Embers, and other dayes comman<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded by ſacred authority, beſides the miſerable rut that would follow, and perhaps contagion, when feaſting and fleſh ſhould be licenced for every carnall appetite.—I could urge ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny more particulars of his dangerous inſatiate and boundleſſe Avarice, but the improvement of his eſtate in ſo few yeares, from a private Gentlemans fortune, to a great Dukes reve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>newes, might ſave our ſoveraigne therein an Orator to en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>force and prove faulty even to gyantiſme againſt heaven.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Iudg.</speaker>
                  <p>This is but a noiſe of words.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Pro.</speaker>
                  <p>To the foule outrages ſo violent, let us adde his Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſſions granted out of his owne preſum'd authoritie, his Majeſtie neither infround or reſpected his diſloyalties, infide<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lities, contempts, oppreſſions, extortions, with innumerable abuſes, offences, and forfeits, both to his Majeſties moſt royall perſon, crowne, and dignitie, yet notwithſtanding all theſe injuſtices, this unmatchable, u<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>juſt delinquent affecteth to be thought inculpable, and incomparable juſt; but alas my moſt learned Lord, none knowes better than your ſelves, how eaſie the ſinceritie of Iuſtice is pretended, how hard it is to be per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formed, and how common it is for him that hath leaſt colour of title to it, to be thought the very ſubſtance and ſoule of it, he that was never true ſcholler in the leaſt degree, longs as a woman with child to be great with ſcholler ſhe that was ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver with child longs <hi>Omnibus vijs modis</hi> to be got with child, and will weare a cuſhion to ſeeme with child, and hee that was never juſt, will fly in the Kings face to be counted juſt, though for all he be nothing, but juſt, a Traytor.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Sec.</speaker>
                  <p>The Admirall ſmil<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>s.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Jud.</speaker>
                  <p>Anſwer your ſelfe my Lord.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Adm.</speaker>
                  <l>I ſhall, and briefely,</l>
                  <l>The furious eloquence of my accuſer hath</l>
                  <l>Branch'd my offences hainous to the King,</l>
                  <l>And then his ſubject, a moſt vaſt indictment,</l>
                  <l>That to the King I have juſtified my merit,</l>
                  <l>And ſervices; which conſcience of that truth,</l>
                  <pb facs="tcp:177674:18"/>
                  <l>That gave my actions life when they are queſtioned,</l>
                  <l>I ought to urge agen, and doe without</l>
                  <l>The leaſt part of injuſtice; for the Bill</l>
                  <l>A foule, and moſt unjuſt one, and prefer'd</l>
                  <l>Gainſt the Kings honour, and his ſubjects priviledge,</l>
                  <l>And with a policie to betray my office,</l>
                  <l>And faith to both, I doe confeſſe I tore it,</l>
                  <l>It being preſt immodeſtly, but without</l>
                  <l>A thought of diſobedience to his name,</l>
                  <l>To whoſe mention I bow, with humble reverence,</l>
                  <l>And dare appeale to the Kings knowledge of me,</l>
                  <l>How farre I am in ſoule from ſuch a rebell,</l>
                  <l>For the reſt my Lord, and you my honour'd Iudges,</l>
                  <l>Since all this mountaine all this time in labour</l>
                  <l>With more than mortall fury gainſt my life,</l>
                  <l>Hath brought forth nought but ſome ridiculous vermine,</l>
                  <l>I will not wrong my right, and innocence,</l>
                  <l>With any ſerious plea in my reply,</l>
                  <l>To fruſtrate breath, and fight with terrible ſhaddow</l>
                  <l>That have beene forg'd, and forc'd againſt my ſtate,</l>
                  <l>But leave all, with my life to your free cenſures;</l>
                  <l>Onely beſeeching all your learned judgements</l>
                  <l>Equall and pious conſcience to weigh.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Pro.</speaker>
                  <p>And how this great and mighty fortune hath exalted him to pride is apparant, not onely in his b<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>aves and bearings to the King, the fountaine of all this increaſe, but in his con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tempt and ſcorne of the ſubject, his vaſt expences in buil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dings, his private bounties, above royall to ſouldiers and ſchollers, that he may be the Generall and Patron, and prote<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctor of armes and arts; the number of domeſticke attendants, an army of Graſhoppers and gay Butterflies able to devoure the Spring; his glorious wardrobes, his ſtable of horſes that are prick'd with provender, and will enforce us to weede up our Vineyards to ſow Oates for ſupply of their proviſion, his caroches ſhining with gold, and more bright than the chariot of the Sunne, wearing out the pavements; nay, he is of late ſo tranſcendently proud, that men muſt be his Mules, and carry him up and downe as it were in a Proceſſion for men to gaze
<pb facs="tcp:177674:19"/> at him till their chines crackes with the weight of his inſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>portable pride, and who knowes but this may prove a faſhion? But who grones for this? the ſubject, who murmure, and are ready to beginne a rebellion, but the tumultuous ſaylers, and water-rats, who tunne up and downe the citie, like an over<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bearing tempeſt, curſing the Admirall, who in duty ought to undoe himſelf for the generall ſatisfaction of his countrymen.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Adm.</speaker>
                  <l>The varietie, and wonder now preſented</l>
                  <l>To your moſt noble notice, and the worlds,</l>
                  <l>That all my life and actions, and offices,</l>
                  <l>Explor'd with all the hundred eyes of Law</l>
                  <l>Lighted with lightning, ſhot out of the wrath</l>
                  <l>Of an incenſt, and commanding King,</l>
                  <l>And blowne with foes, with farre more bitter windes,</l>
                  <l>Then Winter from his Eaſterne cave exhailes,</l>
                  <l>Yeh nothing found, but what you all have heard,</l>
                  <l>And then conſider if a peere of State,</l>
                  <l>Should be expos'd to ſuch a wild arraignement</l>
                  <l>For poore complaints, his fame, faith, life, and honours</l>
                  <l>Rackt for no more.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Cha.</speaker>
                  <l>No more? good heaven, what ſay</l>
                  <l>My learned aſſiſtants.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>1 <hi>Iu.</hi>
                  </speaker>
                  <l>My Lord, the crimes urg'd here for us to cenſure</l>
                  <l>As capitall, and worth this high arraignement</l>
                  <l>To me ſeeme ſtrange, becauſe they doe not fall</l>
                  <l>In force of Law, to arraigne a Peere of State,</l>
                  <l>For all that Law can take into her power</l>
                  <l>To ſentence, is the exaction of the Fiſhermen.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>2 <hi>Iu.</hi>
                  </speaker>
                  <l>Here is no majeſty violated, I conſent to what my Brother has expreſt.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Cha.</speaker>
                  <l>Breake then in wonder,</l>
                  <l>My frighted words out of their forming powers,</l>
                  <l>That you no more collect, from all theſe forfeits</l>
                  <l>That Mr. Proctor generall hath opened,</l>
                  <l>With ſo apparant, and impulſive learning,</l>
                  <l>Againſt the rage and madneſſe of the offender,</l>
                  <l>And violate Majeſtie (my learned aſſiſtants)</l>
                  <l>When Majeſties affronted and deſied,</l>
                  <pb facs="tcp:177674:19"/>
                  <l>It being compar'd with? and in ſuch an onſet</l>
                  <l>As leap'd into his throate? his life affrighting?</l>
                  <l>Be juſtified in all inſolence, all ſubjects</l>
                  <l>If this be ſo conſidered, and inſult</l>
                  <l>Vpon your priviledg'd malice, is not Majeſtie</l>
                  <l>Poyſon'd in this wonder! and no felony ſet</l>
                  <l>Where royaltie is rob'd, and</l>
                  <l>Fie how it fights with Law, and grates upon</l>
                  <l>Her braine and ſoule, and all the powers of Reaſon,</l>
                  <l>Reporter of the proceſſe, ſhew the ſedule.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>No.</speaker>
                  <l>Here my good Lord.</l>
                  <l>1. No altering it in us.</l>
                  <l>2. Farre be it from us Sir.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Cha.</speaker>
                  <l>Heres ſilken Iuſtice,</l>
                  <l>It might be altered, mend your ſentences.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Both.</speaker>
                  <l>Not wee my Lord.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Cha.</speaker>
                  <l>Not you? The King ſhall know</l>
                  <l>You ſlight a duty to his will, and ſafety,</l>
                  <l>Give me your pen, it muſt be capitall.</l>
                  <l>1. Make what you pleaſe my Lord, our doome ſhall ſtand.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Cha.</speaker>
                  <l>Thus I ſubſcribe, now at your perills follow.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Both.</speaker>
                  <l>Perills my Lord? threates in the Kings free juſtice?</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Tre,</speaker>
                  <l>I am amaz'd they can be ſo remiſſe.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Sec.</speaker>
                  <l>Mercifull men, pittifull Iudges certaine.</l>
                  <l>1. Subſcribe, it matters nothing being conſtrain'd</l>
                  <l>On this ſide, and on this ſide, this capitall I,</l>
                  <l>Both which together put, import plaine <hi>Vi;</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>And witneſſe we are forc'd.</l>
                  <l>2. Enough,</l>
                  <l>It will acquit us when we make it knowne,</l>
                  <l>Our names are forc'd.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Cha.</speaker>
                  <l>If traiterous pride</l>
                  <l>Vpon the royall perſon of a King</l>
                  <l>Were ſentenc'd unfelloniouſly before,</l>
                  <l>Ile burne my Bookes and be a Iudge no more.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Both.</speaker>
                  <l>Here are our hands ſubſcrib'd.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Cha.</speaker>
                  <l>Why ſo, it joyes me,</l>
                  <l>You have reform'd your juſtice and your judgement,</l>
                  <pb facs="tcp:177674:20"/>
                  <l>Now have you done like Iudges and learned Lawyers,</l>
                  <l>The King ſhall thanke, and honour you for this.</l>
                  <l>Notary read.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>No.</speaker>
                  <l>We by his ſacred Majeſtie appointed</l>
                  <l>Judges, upon due triall, and examination</l>
                  <l>Of <hi>Philip Chabot</hi> Admirall of <hi>France</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>Declare him guiltie of high treaſons, &amp;c.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Cha.</speaker>
                  <l>Now Captaine of the gaurd, ſecure his perſon,</l>
                  <l>Till the King ſignifie</l>
                  <l>His pleaſure for his death, this day is happy</l>
                  <l>To <hi>France,</hi> thus reskued from the vile devourer.</l>
                  <stage>A ſhoute within.</stage>
                  <l>Harke how the votes applaud their bleſt deliverance,</l>
                  <l>You that ſo late did right and conſcience boaſt,</l>
                  <l>Heavens mercy now implore, the Kings is loſt.</l>
               </sp>
               <stage>Exeunt.</stage>
            </div>
            <div n="4" type="act">
               <head>Actus Quartus.</head>
               <stage>Enter King, Queene, and Conſtable.</stage>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Kin.</speaker>
                  <l>YOu raiſe my thoughrs to wonder, that you Madam,</l>
                  <l>And you my Lord, unite your force to pleade</l>
                  <l>Ith' Admiralls behalfe, this is not that</l>
                  <l>Language you did expreſſe, when the torne Bill</l>
                  <l>Was late pretended to us, it was then</l>
                  <l>Defiance to our high prerogative,</l>
                  <l>The act of him whoſe proud heart would rebell</l>
                  <l>And arm'd with faction, too ſoone attempt</l>
                  <l>To teare my crowne off.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Qu.</speaker>
                  <l>I was ignorant</l>
                  <l>Then of his worth, and heard but the report</l>
                  <l>Of his accuſers, and his enemies,</l>
                  <l>Who never mention in his character</l>
                  <l>Shadowes of any vertue in thoſe men,</l>
                  <l>They would depreſſe like Crowes, and carrion birds,</l>
                  <l>They ſly ore ſlowrie Meades, cleare Springs, faire Gardens,</l>
                  <l>And ſtoope at carcaſſes; for your owne honour</l>
                  <pb facs="tcp:177674:20"/>
                  <l>Pitty poore <hi>Chabot.</hi>
                  </l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>King.</speaker>
                  <l>Poore and a Coloſſus?</l>
                  <l>What could ſo lately ſtraddle ore a Province,</l>
                  <l>Can he be fallen ſo low, and miſerable,</l>
                  <l>To want my pitty, who breakes forth like day,</l>
                  <l>Takes up all peoples eyes, and admiration?</l>
                  <l>It cannot be, he hath a Princely wife too.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Qu.</speaker>
                  <l>I interpoſe not often Sir, or preſſe you</l>
                  <l>With unbecomming importunitie,</l>
                  <l>To ſerve the profitable ends of others</l>
                  <l>Conſcience, and duty to your ſelfe inforce</l>
                  <l>My preſent mediation, you have given</l>
                  <l>The health of your owne ſtate away, unleſſe</l>
                  <l>Wiſedome in time recover him.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>King.</speaker>
                  <l>If he proove</l>
                  <l>No adulterate gold, triall confirmes his value.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Qu.</speaker>
                  <l>Although it hold in mettle gracious Sir,</l>
                  <l>Such fiery examination, and the furnace</l>
                  <l>May waſt a heart thats faithfull, and together</l>
                  <l>With that you call the <hi>feces,</hi> ſomething of</l>
                  <l>The precious ſubſtance may be hazarded.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>King.</speaker>
                  <l>Why, you are the chiefe engine rais'd againſt him,</l>
                  <l>And in the worlds Creede labour moſt to ſinke him,</l>
                  <l>That in his fall, and abſence every beame</l>
                  <l>May ſhine on you, and onely guild your fortune,</l>
                  <l>Your difference is the ground of his arraignement,</l>
                  <l>Nor were we unſollicited by you,</l>
                  <l>To have your bill confirm'd, from that that ſpring</l>
                  <l>Came all theſe mighty and impetuous waves,</l>
                  <l>With which he now muſt wraſtle, if the ſtrength</l>
                  <l>Of his owne innocence can breake the ſtorme,</l>
                  <l>Truth wonot loſe her ſervant, her wings cover him,</l>
                  <l>He muſt obey his fate.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Con.</speaker>
                  <l>I would not have</l>
                  <l>It lie upon my fame, that I ſhould be</l>
                  <l>Mentioned in Story his unjuſt ſupplanter</l>
                  <l>For your whole Kingdome, I have beene abuſed,</l>
                  <l>And made beleeve my ſuite was juſt and neceſſary,</l>
                  <pb facs="tcp:177674:21"/>
                  <l>My walkes have not beene ſafe, my cloſet prayers,</l>
                  <l>But ſome plot has purſued me, by ſome great ones</l>
                  <l>Againſt your noble Admirall, they have frighted</l>
                  <l>My fancy into my dreames with their cloſe whiſpers,</l>
                  <l>How to uncement your affections,</l>
                  <l>And re<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>der him the fable, and the ſcorne</l>
                  <l>Of <hi>France.</hi>
                  </l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Qu.</speaker>
                  <l>Brave <hi>Montmorancie.</hi>
                  </l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>King.</speaker>
                  <l>Are you ſerious.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Con.</speaker>
                  <l>Have I a ſoule? or gratitude, to acknowledge</l>
                  <l>My ſelfe your creature, dignified and honor'd</l>
                  <l>By your high favours with an equall truth,</l>
                  <l>I muſt declare the juſtice of your Admirall</l>
                  <l>(In what my thoughts are conſcious) and will rather</l>
                  <l>Give up my claime to birth, title, and offices,</l>
                  <l>Be throwne from your warme ſmile, the top and crowne</l>
                  <l>Of ſubjects happineſſe, then be brib'd with all</l>
                  <l>Their glories to the guilt of <hi>Chabots</hi> ruine.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>King.</speaker>
                  <l>Come, come, you over act this paſſion,</l>
                  <l>And if it be not pollicie it taſts</l>
                  <l>Too greene, and wants ſome counſell to mature it,</l>
                  <l>His fall prepares your triumph.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Con.</speaker>
                  <l>It confirmes</l>
                  <l>My ſhame alive, and buried will corrupt</l>
                  <l>My very duſt, make our houſe-genious grone,</l>
                  <l>And fright the honeſt marble from my aſhes:</l>
                  <l>His fall prepare my triumph? turne me firſt</l>
                  <l>A naked exile to the world.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>King.</speaker>
                  <l>No more,</l>
                  <l>Take heede you baniſh not your ſelfe, be wiſe,</l>
                  <l>And let not too much zeale devoure your reaſon,</l>
               </sp>
               <stage>Enter Aſall.</stage>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Aſ.</speaker>
                  <l>Your Admirall</l>
                  <l>Is condemn'd Sir?</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>King.</speaker>
                  <l>Ha? ſtrange! no matter,</l>
                  <l>Leave us, a great man I ſee may be</l>
                  <l>As ſoone diſpatch'd, as a common ſubject<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
                  </l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Qu.</speaker>
                  <l>No mercy then for <hi>Chabot.</hi>
                  </l>
               </sp>
               <stage>
                  <pb facs="tcp:177674:21"/>Enter Wife and Father.</stage>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Wif.</speaker>
                  <l>From whence came</l>
                  <l>That ſound of <hi>Chabot?</hi> then we are all undone:</l>
                  <l>Oh doe not heare the Queene, ſhe is no friend</l>
                  <l>To my poore Lord, but made againſt his life,</l>
                  <l>Which hath too many enemies already.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Con.</speaker>
                  <l>Poore ſoule, ſhee thinkes the Queene is ſtill againſt him,</l>
                  <l>Who employeth all her powers to preſerve him.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Fa.</speaker>
                  <l>Say you ſo my Lord? daughter the Queen's our friend.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Wif.</speaker>
                  <l>Why doe you mocke my ſorrow! can you flatter</l>
                  <l>Your owne griefe ſo, be juſt, and heare me ſir,</l>
                  <l>And doe not ſacrifice a ſubjects blood</l>
                  <l>To appeaſe a wrathfull Queene, let mercy ſhine</l>
                  <l>Vpon your brow, and heaven will pay it backe</l>
                  <l>Vpon your ſoule, be deafe to all her prayers.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>King.</speaker>
                  <l>Poore heart, ſhe knowes not what ſhe has deſir'd.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Wif.</speaker>
                  <l>I begge my <hi>Chab<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>ts</hi> life, my ſorrowes yet</l>
                  <l>Have not deſtroid my reaſon.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>King.</speaker>
                  <l>He is in the power of my Lawes, not mine.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Wif.</speaker>
                  <l>Then you have no power,</l>
                  <l>And are but the emptie ſhadow of a King,</l>
                  <l>To whom is it reſign'd? where ſhall I begge</l>
                  <l>The forfeit life of one condemn<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>d by Lawes</l>
                  <l>To partiall doome?</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>King.</speaker>
                  <l>You heare he is condemn'd then?</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Fa.</speaker>
                  <l>My ſonne is condemn'd fit.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>King.</speaker>
                  <l>You know for what too.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Fa.</speaker>
                  <l>What the Iudges pleaſe to call it,</l>
                  <l>But they have given t<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> a name, Treaſon they ſay.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Qu.</speaker>
                  <l>I muſt not be denied.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>King.</speaker>
                  <l>I muſt deny you.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Wif.</speaker>
                  <l>Be<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>leſt for ever fort.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Qu.</speaker>
                  <l>Grant then to her.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>King.</speaker>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Chabot</hi> condemn'd by law?</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Fa.</speaker>
                  <l>But you have power</l>
                  <l>To change the rigor, in <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>our breaſt there is</l>
                  <l>A Chancellor above it, I nere had</l>
                  <l>A ſuite before, but my knees joyne with hers</l>
                  <pb facs="tcp:177674:22"/>
                  <l>To implore your royall mercy to her Lord,</l>
                  <l>And take his cauſe to your examination,</l>
                  <l>It cannot wrong your Iudges, if they have</l>
                  <l>Beene ſteer'd by conſcience.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Con.</speaker>
                  <l>It will fame your Iuſtice.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>King.</speaker>
                  <l>I cannot be preſcrib'd, you kneele in vaine,</l>
                  <l>You labour to betray me with your teares</l>
                  <l>To a treaſon above his, gainſt my owne Lawes,</l>
                  <l>Looke to the Lady—</l>
               </sp>
               <stage>Exeunt.</stage>
               <stage>Enter Aſall.</stage>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Aſ.</speaker>
                  <l>Sir the Chancellor.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>King.</speaker>
                  <l>Admit him, leave us all.</l>
                  <stage>Enter Chancellor.</stage>
                  <l>How now my Lord?</l>
                  <l>You have loſt no time, and how thrive the proceedings.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Cha.</speaker>
                  <l>Twas ſit my gracious Soveraigne, time ſhould leave</l>
                  <l>His motion made in all affaires beſide,</l>
                  <l>And ſpend his wings onely in ſpeed of this.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>King.</speaker>
                  <l>You have ſhew'd diligence, and whats become</l>
                  <l>Of our moſt curious Iuſticer, the Admirall?</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Cha.</speaker>
                  <l>Condemn'd ſir utterly, and all hands ſet</l>
                  <l>To his conviction.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>King.</speaker>
                  <l>And for faults moſt foule?</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Cha.</speaker>
                  <l>More than moſt impious, but the applauſive iſſue</l>
                  <l>Strooke by the concourſe of your raviſh'd ſubjects</l>
                  <l>For joy of your free Iuſtice, if there were</l>
                  <l>No other cauſe to aſſure the ſentence juſt</l>
                  <l>Were proofe convincing.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>King.</speaker>
                  <l>Now then he ſees cleerely</l>
                  <l>That men perceive how vaine his Iuſtice was,</l>
                  <l>And ſcorne him for the fooliſh net he wore</l>
                  <l>To hide his nakedneſſe; iſt not a wonder</l>
                  <l>That mens ambitions ſhould ſo blinde their reaſon</l>
                  <l>To affect ſhapes of honeſty, and take pride</l>
                  <l>Rather in ſeeming, then in being juſt.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Cha.</speaker>
                  <l>Seeming has better fortune to attend it</l>
                  <l>Then being ſound at heart, and vertuous.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>King.</speaker>
                  <l>Profeſſe all? nothing doe, like thoſe that live</l>
                  <pb facs="tcp:177674:22"/>
                  <l>By looking to the Lamps of holy Temples,</l>
                  <l>Who ſtill are buſie taking off their ſnuffes,</l>
                  <l>But for their profit ſake will adde no oyle;</l>
                  <l>So theſe will checke and ſentence every fame,</l>
                  <l>The blaze of riotous blood doth caſt in others,</l>
                  <l>And in themſelves leave the ſume moſt offenſive,</l>
                  <l>But he to doe this? more deceives my judgement</l>
                  <l>Than all the reſt whoſe nature I have ſounded.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Cha.</speaker>
                  <l>I know Sir, and have prov'd it.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>King.</speaker>
                  <l>Well my Lord</l>
                  <l>To omit circumſtance, I highly thanke you</l>
                  <l>For this late ſervice you have done me here,</l>
                  <l>Which is ſo great and meritorious</l>
                  <l>That with my ableſt power I ſcarce can quit you.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Cha.</speaker>
                  <l>Your ſole acceptance (my dread ſoveraigne)</l>
                  <l>I more rejoyce in, than in all the fortunes</l>
                  <l>That ever chanc'd me, but when may it pleaſe</l>
                  <l>Your Highneſſe to order the execution?</l>
                  <l>The haſte thus farre hath ſpar'd no pinions.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>King.</speaker>
                  <l>No my Lord, your care</l>
                  <l>Hath therein much deſerv'd.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Cha.</speaker>
                  <l>But where proportion</l>
                  <l>Is kept toth' end in things, at ſtart ſo happy</l>
                  <l>That end ſet on the crowne.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>King.</speaker>
                  <l>Ile ſpeede it therefore.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Cha.</speaker>
                  <l>Your thoughts direct it, they are wing'd.</l>
               </sp>
               <stage>Exit.</stage>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>King.</speaker>
                  <l>I joy this boldneſſe is condemn'd, that I may pardon,</l>
                  <l>And t<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>erein get ſome ground in his opinion</l>
                  <l>By ſo much bounty as ſave his life,</l>
                  <l>And me thinks that weigh'd more, ſhould ſway the ballance</l>
                  <l>Twixt me and him, held by his owne free Iuſtice,</l>
                  <l>For I could never finde him obſtinate</l>
                  <l>In any minde he held, when once he ſaw</l>
                  <l>Th' error with which he laboured, and ſince now</l>
                  <l>He needs muſt feele it, I admit no doubt,</l>
                  <l>But that his alteration will beget</l>
                  <l>Another ſence of things twixt him and me;</l>
                  <l>Whoſe there?</l>
                  <pb facs="tcp:177674:23"/>
                  <l>Goe to the Captaine of my <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>uard, and will him</l>
                  <l>To attend his condemn'd priſoner to me inſtantly.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Aſ.</speaker>
                  <l>I ſhall ſir</l>
               </sp>
               <stage>Ewer Treaſurer &amp; Secretary</stage>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>King.</speaker>
                  <l>My Lords, you were ſpectators of our Admirall.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Tre.</speaker>
                  <l>And hearers too of his moſt juſt conviction,</l>
                  <l>In which we witneſt over-weight enough</l>
                  <l>In your great bounties, and as they there were weigh'd</l>
                  <l>With all the feathers of his boaſted merits.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>King.</speaker>
                  <l>Has felt a ſcorching triall, and the teſt</l>
                  <l>(That holds fires utmoſt force) we muſt give mettalls</l>
                  <l>That will not with the hammer, and the melting</l>
                  <l>Confeſſe their truth, and this ſame ſence of feeling</l>
                  <l>(Being ground to all the ſences) hath one key</l>
                  <l>More than the reſt to let in through them all</l>
                  <l>The mindes true apprehenſion, that thence takes</l>
                  <l>Her firſt convey'd intelligence. I long</l>
                  <l>To ſee this man of conſidence agen:</l>
                  <l>How thinke you Lords, will <hi>Chabot</hi> looke on mee,</l>
                  <l>Now ſp<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ild of the integrity, he boaſted?</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Sec.</speaker>
                  <l>It were too much honour to vouchſafe your ſight.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Tr.</speaker>
                  <l>No doubt my Leigh, but he that hath offended</l>
                  <l>In ſuch a height againſt your crowne and perſon,</l>
                  <l>Will want no impudence to looke upon you.</l>
               </sp>
               <stage>Enter Aſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ll, Captaine, Admirall.</stage>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Cap.</speaker>
                  <l>Sir, I had charge given me by this Gentleman</l>
                  <l>To bring your condemn'd priſoner to your preſence.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>King.</speaker>
                  <l>You have done well, and tell the Queene, and our</l>
                  <l>Lord Conſtable we deſire their preſence, bid</l>
                  <l>Our Admiralls Lady, and her father too</l>
                  <l>Attend us here, they are but new withdrawne.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Aſ.</speaker>
                  <l>I ſhall ſir!</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Tre.</speaker>
                  <l>Doe you <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>ſerve this confidence?</l>
                  <l>He ſtands as all his triall were a dreame.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>S<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>c.</speaker>
                  <l>Hele finde the horrour waking the King's troubled;</l>
                  <l>Now for <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> thu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>der-clap: the Queene and Conſtable.</l>
               </sp>
               <stage>Enter Queene, Conſtable, Wiſe and Father.</stage>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Tr.</speaker>
                  <l>I doe not like their mixtu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>e.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>King,</speaker>
                  <l>My Lo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>d Admirall,</l>
                  <pb facs="tcp:177674:23"/>
                  <l>You made it your deſire to have this triall</l>
                  <l>That late hath paſt upon you;</l>
                  <l>And now you feele how vaine is too much faith</l>
                  <l>And flattery of your ſelfe, as if your breſt</l>
                  <l>Were proofe gainſt all invaſion, tis ſo ſlight</l>
                  <l>You ſee it lets in death, whats paſt, hath beene</l>
                  <l>To ſatisfie your inſolence, there remaines</l>
                  <l>That now we ſerve our owne free pleaſure, therefore</l>
                  <l>By th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>t moſt abſolute power, with which all right</l>
                  <l>Puts in my hands, theſe iſſues turnes, and changes,</l>
                  <l>I here in eare of all theſe, pardon all</l>
                  <l>Your faults and forfeits, whatſoever ſenſur'd,</l>
                  <l>Againe advancing, and eſtabliſhing</l>
                  <l>Your perſon in all fulneſſe of that ſtate</l>
                  <l>That ever you enjoy'd before th' attainder<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
                  </l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Tre.</speaker>
                  <l>Wonderfull, pardon'd!</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Wif.</speaker>
                  <l>Heaven preſerve the King.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Qu.</speaker>
                  <l>Who for this will deſerve all time to honour him.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Con.</speaker>
                  <l>And live Kings beſt example.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Fa.</speaker>
                  <l>Sonne yare pardon'd,</l>
                  <l>Be ſure you looke hereafter well about you.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Adm.</speaker>
                  <l>Vouchſafe great Sir to aſſure me what you ſaid,</l>
                  <l>You nam'd my pardon.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>King.</speaker>
                  <l>And agen declare it,</l>
                  <l>For all crimes paſt, of what nature ſoever.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Adm.</speaker>
                  <l>You cannot pardon me Sir.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>King.</speaker>
                  <l>How's that <hi>Philip?</hi>
                  </l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Adm.</speaker>
                  <l>It is a word carries too much relation</l>
                  <l>To an offence, of which I am not guilty,</l>
                  <l>And I muſt ſtill be bold where truth ſtill armes,</l>
                  <l>In ſpight of all thoſe frownes that would deject me</l>
                  <l>To ſay I neede no pardon.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>King.</speaker>
                  <l>Ha, howes this?</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Fa.</speaker>
                  <l>Hees mad with over-joy, and anſwers nonſence.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>King.</speaker>
                  <l>Why, tell me <hi>Chabot,</hi> are not you condemn'd?</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Adm.</speaker>
                  <l>Yes, and that juſtifies me much the more,</l>
                  <l>For whatſoever falſe report hath brought you,</l>
                  <l>I was condemn'd for nothing that could reach</l>
                  <pb facs="tcp:177674:24"/>
                  <l>To prejudice my life, my goods or honour,</l>
                  <l>As firſt in firmeneſſe of my conſcience,</l>
                  <l>I confidently told you, not alas</l>
                  <l>Preſuming on your ſlender thred of favour,</l>
                  <l>Or pride of fortunate and courtly boldneſſe,</l>
                  <l>But what my faith and juſtice bade me truſt too,</l>
                  <l>For none of all your learned aſſiſtant Judges,</l>
                  <l>With all the malice of my crimes could urge,</l>
                  <l>Or fel<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ny or hurt of ſacred power.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>King.</speaker>
                  <l>Doe any heare this, but my ſelfe? My Lords,</l>
                  <l>This man ſtill juſtifies his innocence,</l>
                  <l>What prodigies are theſe? have not our Lawes</l>
                  <l>Paſt on his actions, have not equall Iudges</l>
                  <l>Certified his arraignement, and him guilty</l>
                  <l>Of capitall Treaſon? and yet doe I heare</l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Chabot</hi> accuſe all theſe, and quit himſelfe.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Tr.</speaker>
                  <l>It does appeare diſtraction ſir.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>King.</speaker>
                  <l>Did we</l>
                  <l>Seeme ſo indulgent to propoſe our free</l>
                  <l>And royall pardon without ſuite or prayer,</l>
                  <l>To meete with his contempt?</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Sec.</speaker>
                  <l>Vnhea<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>'d of impudence!</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Ad.</speaker>
                  <l>I were malicious to my ſelfe, and deſperate</l>
                  <l>To force untruths upon my ſoule, and when</l>
                  <l>Tis cleare, to confeſſe a ſhame to exerciſe</l>
                  <l>Your pardon ſir, were I ſo foule and monſtrous</l>
                  <l>As I am given to you, you would commit</l>
                  <l>A ſinne next mine, by wronging your owne mercy</l>
                  <l>To let me draw out impious breath, it will</l>
                  <l>Releaſe your wonder, if you give command</l>
                  <l>To ſee your proceſſe, and if it prove other</l>
                  <l>Tha<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> I preſume to Informe, teare me in peeces.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>King.</speaker>
                  <l>Goe for the Proceſſe, and the Chancellor,</l>
                  <l>With the aſſiſtant Iudges. I thanke heaven</l>
                  <stage>Exit Aſ.</stage>
                  <l>That with all theſe inforcements of diſtraction</l>
                  <l>My reaſon ſtayes ſo cleare to heare, and anſwer,</l>
                  <l>And <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap> direct a meſſage. This inverſion</l>
                  <l>Of all the loyalties, and true deſerts</l>
                  <pb facs="tcp:177674:24"/>
                  <l>That I beleev'd I govern'd with, till now</l>
                  <l>In my choice Lawyers, and chiefe Counſellors</l>
                  <l>Is able to ſhake all my frame of reaſon.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Adm.</speaker>
                  <l>I am much griv'd.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>King.</speaker>
                  <l>No more, I doe incline</l>
                  <l>To thinke I am abus'd, my Lawes betrai'd</l>
                  <l>And wreſted to the purpoſe of my Judges,</l>
                  <l>This confidence in <hi>Chabot</hi> turnes my judgement,</l>
                  <l>This was too wilde away<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> to make his merits</l>
                  <l>Stoope and acknowledge my ſuperior bounties,</l>
                  <l>That it doth raiſe, and ſixe e'm paſt my art,</l>
                  <l>To ſhadow all the ſhame and forfeits mine.</l>
               </sp>
               <stage>Enter Aſall, Chancellor, Iudges.</stage>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Aſ.</speaker>
                  <l>The Chancellor and Judges Sir.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Tre.</speaker>
                  <l>I like not</l>
                  <l>This paſſion in the King, the Queene and Conſtable</l>
                  <l>Are of that ſide.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>King.</speaker>
                  <l>My Lord, you dare appeare then?</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Cha.</speaker>
                  <l>Dare Sir, I hope.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>King.</speaker>
                  <l>Well done, hope ſtill, and tell me,</l>
                  <l>Is not this man condemn'd?</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Cha.</speaker>
                  <l>Strange queſtion Sir,</l>
                  <l>The proceſſe will declare it, ſign'd with all</l>
                  <l>Theſe my aſſiſtant brothers reverend hands</l>
                  <l>To his conviction in a publike triall.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>King.</speaker>
                  <l>You ſaid for foule and monſtrous facts prov'd by <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap>
                  </l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Cha.</speaker>
                  <l>The very words are there ſir.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>King.</speaker>
                  <l>But the deedes</l>
                  <l>I looke for ſir, name me but one thats monſtrous?</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Cha.</speaker>
                  <l>His foule compariſons, and affronts of you,</l>
                  <l>To me ſeem'd monſtrous.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>King.</speaker>
                  <l>I told you them ſir,</l>
                  <l>Nor were they any that your ſo vaſt knowledge,</l>
                  <l>Being a man ſtudied in him, could produce</l>
                  <l>And prove as cleare as heaven, you warranted</l>
                  <l>To make appeare ſuch treaſons in the Admirall,</l>
                  <l>As never all Lawes, Volumes yet had ſentenc'd,</l>
                  <l>And <hi>France</hi> ſhould looke on, having ſcap'd with wonder</l>
                  <pb facs="tcp:177674:25"/>
                  <l>What in this nature hath beene cleerely prov'd</l>
                  <l>In his arraignement.</l>
                  <l>1. Nothing that we heard</l>
                  <l>In ſlendreſt touch urg'd by your Advocate.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>King.</speaker>
                  <l>Dare you affirme this too?</l>
                  <l>2. Moſt conſidently.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>King.</speaker>
                  <l>No baſe corruptions charg'd upon him.</l>
                  <l>1. None ſir.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Tr.</speaker>
                  <l>This argues <hi>Chabot</hi> has corrupted him.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Se<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>.</speaker>
                  <l>I doe not like this.</l>
                  <l>1. The ſumme of all</l>
                  <l>Was urg'd to prove your Admirall corrupt,</l>
                  <l>Was an exaction of his officers,</l>
                  <l>Of twenty <hi>ſouſe</hi> taken from the Fiſhermen</l>
                  <l>For every boate, and that fiſh'd the <hi>Normand</hi> coaſt.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>King.</speaker>
                  <l>And was this all</l>
                  <l>The mountaines, and the marvells promiſt me,</l>
                  <l>To be in cleere proofe made againſt the life.</l>
                  <l>Of our ſo hated Admirall.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Iud.</speaker>
                  <l>All ſir,</l>
                  <l>Vpon our lives and conſciences.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Cha.</speaker>
                  <l>I am blaſted.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>King.</speaker>
                  <l>How durſt you then ſubſcribe to his conviction.</l>
                  <l>1. For threats by my Lord Chancellor on the Bench,</l>
                  <l>Affirming that your Majeſtie would have it</l>
                  <l>Made capitall treaſon, or account us traitors.</l>
                  <l>2. Yet ſir, we did put to our names with this</l>
                  <l>Interpoſition of a note in ſecret</l>
                  <l>In theſe two letters <hi>
                        <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>,</hi> and <hi>I,</hi> to ſhew</l>
                  <l>Wee were enforc'd to what we did, which then</l>
                  <l>In Law is nothing.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Fa.</speaker>
                  <l>How doe you feele your Lordſhip,</l>
                  <l>Did you not finde ſome ſtuffing in your head,</l>
                  <l>Your braine ſhould have beene purg'd,</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Cha.</speaker>
                  <l>I fall to peeces,</l>
                  <l>Would they had rotted on the Bench.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>King.</speaker>
                  <l>And ſo you ſav'd the peace of that high Court.</l>
                  <l>Which otherwiſe his impious rage had broken,</l>
                  <l>But thus am I by his malicious arts</l>
                  <pb facs="tcp:177674:25"/>
                  <l>A parly rendred, and moſt tyrannous ſpurre</l>
                  <l>To all the open courſe of his baſe envies,</l>
                  <l>A forcer of my Iudges, and a thirſt</l>
                  <l>Of my nobilities blood, and all by one,</l>
                  <l>I truſted to make cleere my love of Iuſtice.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Cha.</speaker>
                  <l>I beſeech your Majeſtie, let all my zeale</l>
                  <l>To ſerve your vertues, with a ſacred value</l>
                  <l>Made of your royall ſtate, to which each leaſt</l>
                  <l>But ſhade of violence in any ſubject</l>
                  <l>Doth provoke certaine death.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>King.</speaker>
                  <l>Death on thy name</l>
                  <l>And memory for ever, one command</l>
                  <l>Our Advocate attend us preſently.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Aſ.</speaker>
                  <l>He waites here.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>King.</speaker>
                  <l>But ſingle death ſhall not excuſe, thy skinne</l>
                  <l>Torne ore thine eares, and what elſe can be inflicted<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>
                  </l>
                  <l>If thy life with the ſame ſeverity</l>
                  <l>Diſſected cannot ſtand ſo many fires.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Sec.</speaker>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Tre.</hi> Be mercifull great Sir.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>King.</speaker>
                  <l>Yet more amaze?</l>
                  <l>Is there a knee in all the world beſide</l>
                  <l>That any humane conſcience can let bow</l>
                  <l>For him, yare traitors all that pitty him.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Tr.</speaker>
                  <l>This is no time to move.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>King.</speaker>
                  <l>Yet twas my fault</l>
                  <l>To truſt this wretch, whom I knew fierce and proud</l>
                  <l>With formes of tongue and learning, what a priſoner</l>
                  <l>Is pride of the whole ſlood of man? for as</l>
                  <l>A humane ſeede is ſaid to be a mixture</l>
                  <l>And faire contemperature extracted from</l>
                  <l>All our beſt faculties, ſo the ſeede of all</l>
                  <l>Mans ſenſuall frailty, may be ſaid to abide,</l>
                  <l>And have their confluence in onely pride,</l>
                  <l>It ſtupifies mans reaſon ſo, and dulls</l>
                  <l>True ſence of any thing, but what may fall</l>
                  <l>In his owne glory, quenches all the ſpirits</l>
                  <l>That light a man to honour and true goodneſſe.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Aſ.</speaker>
                  <l>Your Advocate.</l>
               </sp>
               <stage>Enter Advocate.</stage>
               <sp>
                  <pb facs="tcp:177674:26"/>
                  <speaker>King.</speaker>
                  <l>Come hither.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Adv.</speaker>
                  <l>My moſt gracious Soveraigne.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Adm.</speaker>
                  <l>Madam you infinitely oblige our duty.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Qu.</speaker>
                  <l>I was too long ignorant of your worth my Lord,</l>
                  <l>And this ſweete Ladies vertue.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>W<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>f.</speaker>
                  <l>Both your ſervants.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Adm</speaker>
                  <l>I never had a feare of the Kings Iuſtice,</l>
                  <l>And yet I Know not what creepes ore my heart,</l>
                  <l>And leaves an ice beneath it, my Lord Chancellor,</l>
                  <l>You have my forgiveneſſe, but implore heavens pardon</l>
                  <l>For wrongs to equall juſtice, you ſhall want</l>
                  <l>No charitie of mine to mediate</l>
                  <l>To the King for you.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Cha.</speaker>
                  <l>Horrour of my ſoule</l>
                  <l>Confounds my gratitude.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Con.</speaker>
                  <l>To me now moſt welcome.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Adv.</speaker>
                  <l>It was my allegiance ſir, I did enforce,</l>
                  <l>But by directions of your Chancellor,</l>
                  <l>It was my office to advance your cauſe</l>
                  <l>Gainſt all the world, which when I leave to execute,</l>
                  <l>Flea me, and turne me out a moſt raw Advocate.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>King.</speaker>
                  <l>You ſee my Chancellor.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Adv.</speaker>
                  <l>He has an ill looke with him.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>King.</speaker>
                  <l>It ſhall be your province now, on our behalfe</l>
                  <l>To urge what can in juſtice be againſt him,</l>
                  <l>His riot on our Lawes, and corrupt actions</l>
                  <l>Will give you ſcope and field enough.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Adv.</speaker>
                  <l>And I</l>
                  <l>Will play my law prize, never feare it ſir.</l>
                  <l>He ſhall be guilty of what you pleaſe, I am ſtudied</l>
                  <l>In him ſir, I will ſqueeze his villan<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>es,</l>
                  <l>And urge his acts ſo whom into his bowells,</l>
                  <l>The force of it ſhall make him hang himſelfe,</l>
                  <l>And ſave the Lawes a labour.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>King.</speaker>
                  <l>Iudges, for all</l>
                  <l>The poiſonous outrage, that this viper ſpile</l>
                  <l>On all my royall freedome and my Empire,</l>
                  <l>As making all but ſervants to his malice,</l>
                  <pb facs="tcp:177674:26"/>
                  <l>I will have you reviſe the late arraignement,</l>
                  <l>And for thoſe worthy reaſons, that already</l>
                  <l>Affect you for my Admiralls acquitall</l>
                  <l>Employ your juſtice on this Chancellor, away with him,</l>
                  <l>Arreſt him Captaine of my guard to anſwer</l>
                  <l>All that due courſe of Law againſt him can</l>
                  <l>Charge both his Acts and life.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Cap.</speaker>
                  <l>I doe arreſt thee</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Poyet</speaker>
                  <l>Lord Chancellor in his Highneſſe name,</l>
                  <l>To anſwer all that equall courſe of Law</l>
                  <l>Can charge thy acts and life with.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Cha.</speaker>
                  <l>I Obey.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>King.</speaker>
                  <l>How falſe a heart corruption has, how baſe</l>
                  <l>Without true worth are all theſe earth-bred glories?</l>
                  <l>Oh bleſſed juſtice, by which all things ſtand,</l>
                  <l>That ſtills the thunder, and makes lightning finke</l>
                  <l>Twixt earth and heaven amaz'd, and cannot ſtrike,</l>
                  <l>Being prov'd ſo now in wonder of this man,</l>
                  <l>The object of mens hate, and heavens bright love;</l>
                  <l>And as in cloudy dayes, we ſee the Sunne</l>
                  <l>Glide over turrets, temples, richeſt fields,</l>
                  <l>All thoſe left darke, and ſlighted in his way,</l>
                  <l>And on the wretched plight of ſome poore ſhed,</l>
                  <l>Powres all the glories of his golden head;</l>
                  <l>So heavenly vertue, on this envied Lord,</l>
                  <l>Points all his graces, that I may dinſtinguiſh</l>
                  <l>Him better from the world.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Tre.</speaker>
                  <l>You doe him right.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>King.</speaker>
                  <l>But away Iudges, and purſue the afraignement</l>
                  <l>Of this polluted Chancellor with that ſwiftneſſe,</l>
                  <l>His fury wing'd againſt my Admirall,</l>
                  <l>And be you all, that ſate on him compurgators</l>
                  <l>Of me againſt this falſe Iudge.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Iud.</speaker>
                  <l>We are ſo.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>King.</speaker>
                  <l>Be you two joyn'd in the commiſſion,</l>
                  <l>And nothing urg'd but juſtly, of me learning</l>
                  <l>This one more leſſon out of the events</l>
                  <l>Of theſe affaires now paſt, that whatſoever</l>
                  <pb facs="tcp:177674:27"/>
                  <l>Charge or Commiſſion Iudges have from us,</l>
                  <l>They ever make their ayme ingenuous Iuſtice,</l>
                  <l>Not partiall for reward, or ſwelling favour,</l>
                  <l>To which if your King ſteere you, ſpare to obey;</l>
                  <l>For when his troubled blood is cleere, and calme,</l>
                  <l>He will repent that he purſued his rage,</l>
                  <l>Before his pious Law, and hold that Iudge</l>
                  <l>Vnworthy of his place, that lets his cenſure</l>
                  <l>Flote in the waves of an imagin'd favour,</l>
                  <l>This ſhipwracks in the haven, and but wounds</l>
                  <l>Their conſciences that ſooth the ſoone ebb'd humours</l>
                  <l>Of their incenſed King.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Con. Tre.</speaker>
                  <l>Royall and ſacred.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>King.</speaker>
                  <l>Come <hi>Philip,</hi> ſhine thy honour now for ever,</l>
                  <l>For this ſhort temporall ecclipſe it ſuffer'd</l>
                  <l>By th' interpos'd deſire I had to try thee,</l>
                  <l>Nor let the thought of what is paſt afflict thee,</l>
                  <l>For my unkindneſſe, live ſtill circled here,</l>
                  <l>The bright intelligence of our royall ſpheere.</l>
               </sp>
               <stage>Exeunt.</stage>
            </div>
            <div n="5" type="act">
               <head>Actus Quintus.</head>
               <stage>Enter Queene, Conſtable, Father.</stage>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Qu.</speaker>
                  <l>THe Admirall ſicke?</l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Fa.</hi> With danger at the h<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>rt,</l>
                  <l>I came to tell the King.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Con.</speaker>
                  <l>He never had</l>
                  <l>More reaſon in his ſoule, to entertaine</l>
                  <l>All the delights of health.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Fa.</speaker>
                  <l>I feare my Lord,</l>
                  <l>Some apprehenſion of the Kings unkindneſſe,</l>
                  <l>By giving up his perſon, and his offices</l>
                  <l>To the Lawes gripe and ſearch, is ground of his</l>
                  <l>Sad change, the greateſt foules are thus oft wounded,</l>
                  <l>If he vouchſafe his preſence, it may quicken</l>
                  <l>His faſt decaying ſpirits, and prevent</l>
                  <pb facs="tcp:177674:27"/>
                  <l>The haſty ebbe of life.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Qu.</speaker>
                  <l>The King is now</l>
                  <l>Fraught with the joy of his freſh preſervation,</l>
                  <l>The newes ſo violent, let into his eare,</l>
                  <l>May have ſome dangerous effect in him,</l>
                  <l>I wod not counſell ſir to that.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Fa.</speaker>
                  <l>With greater reaſon</l>
                  <l>I may ſuſpect they'le ſpread my Lord, and as</l>
                  <l>A river left his curl'd and impetuous waves</l>
                  <l>Over the bankes, by confluence of ſtreames</l>
                  <l>That fill and ſwell her channell, for by this time</l>
                  <l>He has the addition of <hi>Allegres</hi> ſuffering,</l>
                  <l>His honeſt ſervant, whom I met though feeble</l>
                  <l>And worne with torture, going to congratulatë</l>
                  <l>His Maſters ſafetie.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Qu.</speaker>
                  <l>It ſeemes he much</l>
                  <l>Affected that <hi>Allegre.</hi>
                  </l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Con.</speaker>
                  <l>There will be</l>
                  <l>But a ſad interview and dialogue.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Qu.</speaker>
                  <l>Does he keepe his bed?</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Fa.</speaker>
                  <l>In that alone</l>
                  <l>He ſhewes a fortitude, he will move, and walke</l>
                  <l>He ſayes while his owne ſtrength or others can</l>
                  <l>Support him, wiſhing he might ſtand and looke</l>
                  <l>His deſtiny in the face at the laſt ſummon,</l>
                  <l>Not ſluggiſhly exhaile his ſoule in bed,</l>
                  <l>With indulgence, and nice flattery of his limbs.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Qu.</speaker>
                  <l>Can he in this ſhew ſpirit, and want force</l>
                  <l>To wraſtle with a thought?</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Fa.</speaker>
                  <l>Oh Madam, Madam,</l>
                  <l>We may have proofe againſt thë ſword, and tyranny</l>
                  <l>Of boyſterous warre that threatens us, but when</l>
                  <l>Kings froune, a Cannon mounted in each eye,</l>
                  <l>Shoote death to apprehenſion, ere their fire</l>
                  <l>And force approach us.</l>
               </sp>
               <stage>Enter King.</stage>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Con.</speaker>
                  <l>Here's the King.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Qu.</speaker>
                  <l>No words</l>
                  <l>To interrupt his quiet,</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <pb facs="tcp:177674:28"/>
                  <speaker>Fa.</speaker>
                  <l>Ile begon then.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>King.</speaker>
                  <l>Our Admiralls father! call him backe.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Qu.</speaker>
                  <l>I w<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>not ſtay to heare e'm.</l>
               </sp>
               <stage>Exit.</stage>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Con.</speaker>
                  <l>Sir, be prudent,</l>
                  <l>And doe not for your ſonne fright the Kings health.</l>
               </sp>
               <stage>Exit.</stage>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>King.</speaker>
                  <l>What, ha they left us? how does my Admirall?</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Fa.</speaker>
                  <l>I am forbid to tell you ſir.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>King.</speaker>
                  <l>By whom.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Fa.</speaker>
                  <l>The Queene and my Lord Conſtable.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>King.</speaker>
                  <l>Are there</l>
                  <l>Remaining ſeedes of faction? have they ſoules</l>
                  <l>Not yet convinc'd ith truth of <hi>Chabots</hi> honour,</l>
                  <l>Cleare as the chriſtall heaven, and bove the reach</l>
                  <l>Of imitation.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Fa.</speaker>
                  <l>Tis their care of you,</l>
                  <l>And no thought prejudiciall to my ſonne.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>King.</speaker>
                  <l>Their care of me?</l>
                  <l>How can the knowledge of my Admiralls ſtate</l>
                  <l>Concerne their feares of me, I ſee their envie</l>
                  <l>Of <hi>Chabots</hi> happineſſe, whoſe joy to be</l>
                  <l>Rendr'd ſo pure and genuine to the world</l>
                  <l>Doth grate upon their conſcience and affright 'em;</l>
                  <l>But let 'em vexe, and bid my <hi>Chabot</hi> ſtill</l>
                  <l>Exalt his heart, and triumph, he ſhall havë</l>
                  <l>The acceſſe of ours, the kingdome ſhall put on</l>
                  <l>Such joyes for him as ſhe would boſt to celebratë</l>
                  <l>Her owne eſcape from ruine.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Fa.</speaker>
                  <l>He is not in ſtate to heare my ſad newes</l>
                  <l>I perceive.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>King.</speaker>
                  <l>That countenance is not right, it does not anſwë<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>
                  </l>
                  <l>What I expect,</l>
                  <l>Say, how is my Admirall?</l>
                  <l>The truth upon thy life.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Fa.</speaker>
                  <l>To ſecure his, I would you had.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>King</speaker>
                  <l>Ha? Who durſt oppoſe him?</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Fa.</speaker>
                  <l>One that hath power enough hath practiſed on him</l>
                  <l>And made his great heart ſtoope.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>King.</speaker>
                  <l>I will revenge it</l>
                  <pb facs="tcp:177674:28"/>
                  <l>With cruſhing, cruſhing that rebellious power to nothing.</l>
                  <l>Name him.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Fa.</speaker>
                  <l>He was his friend.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>King.</speaker>
                  <l>A friend to malice, his owne blacke impoſtume</l>
                  <l>Burne his blood up, what miſchiefe hath ingendred</l>
                  <l>New ſtormes?</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Fa.</speaker>
                  <l>Tis the old tempeſt.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>King.</speaker>
                  <l>Did not we</l>
                  <l>Appeaſe all horrors that look'd wilde upon him?</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Fa.</speaker>
                  <l>You dreſt his wounds I muſt confeſſe, but made</l>
                  <l>No cure, they bleede a freſh, pardon me ſir,</l>
                  <l>Although your conſcience have clos'd too ſoone,</l>
                  <l>He is in danger, and doth want new ſurgerie</l>
                  <l>Though he be right in fame, and your opinion,</l>
                  <l>He thinkes you were unkinde.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>King.</speaker>
                  <l>Alas poore <hi>Chabot,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>Doth that afflict him.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Fa.</speaker>
                  <l>So much, though he ſtrive</l>
                  <l>With moſt reſolv'd and Adamantine nerves,</l>
                  <l>As ever humane fire in fleſh and blood,</l>
                  <l>Forg'd for example, to beare all, ſo killing</l>
                  <l>The arrowes that you ſhot were (ſtill your pardon)</l>
                  <l>No Centaures blood could rancle ſo.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>King.</speaker>
                  <l>If this</l>
                  <l>Be all, ile cure him, Kings retaine</l>
                  <l>More Balſome in their ſoule them hurt in anger.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Fa.</speaker>
                  <l>Farre ſhort ſir, with one breath they uncreate,</l>
                  <l>And Kings with onely words more wounds can make</l>
                  <l>Then all their kingdome made in balme can heale,</l>
                  <l>Tis dangerous to play to wilde a deſcant</l>
                  <l>On numerous vertue, though it become Princes</l>
                  <l>To aſſure their adventures made in every thing,</l>
                  <l>Goodneſſe confin'd within poore fleſh and blood,</l>
                  <l>Hath but a queazie and ſtill ſickly ſtate,</l>
                  <l>A muſicall hand ſhould onely play on her</l>
                  <l>Fluent as ayre, yet every touch command.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>King.</speaker>
                  <l>No more,</l>
                  <l>Commend us to the Admirall, and ſay,</l>
                  <pb facs="tcp:177674:29"/>
                  <l>The King will viſite him, and bring health.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Fa.</speaker>
                  <l>I will not doubt that bleſſing, and ſhall move</l>
                  <l>Nimbly with this command.</l>
               </sp>
               <stage>Exeunt.</stage>
               <stage>Enter Officers before, Treaſurer, Secretary, and Iudges, at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tended by Petitioners, the Advocate alſo with many papers in his hand, they take their places. The Chancellor with a guard, and plac'd at the Barre.</stage>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Tre.</speaker>
                  <l>Did you beleeve the Chancellor had beene</l>
                  <l>So foule?</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Sec.</speaker>
                  <l>Hee's loſt toth' people, what contempts</l>
                  <l>They throw upon him? but we muſt be wiſe.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>1 <hi>Iud.</hi>
                  </speaker>
                  <l>Were there no other guilt, his malice ſhëw'd</l>
                  <l>Vpon the Admirall, in orebearing juſtice,</l>
                  <l>Would well deſerve a ſentence.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Tre.</speaker>
                  <l>And a deepe one.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>2 <hi>Iud.</hi>
                  </speaker>
                  <l>If pleaſe your Lordſhips to remember that</l>
                  <l>Was ſpecially commended by the King,</l>
                  <l>As being moſt blemiſh to his royall perſon,</l>
                  <l>And the free juſtice of his ſtate.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Tre.</speaker>
                  <l>Already</l>
                  <l>He has confeſt upon his examinations</l>
                  <l>Enough for ſenſure, yet to obey forme—</l>
                  <l>Mr. Advocate if you pleaſe—</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Adv.</speaker>
                  <p>I am ready for your Lordſhips: It hath beene ſaid, and will be ſaid agen, and may truely be juſtified, <hi>Omnia ex lite fieri.</hi> It was the poſition of Philoſophers, and now proved by a more Phyloſophycall ſect, the Lawyers, that <hi>Omnia ex lite fiant,</hi> we are all made by Law, made I ſay, and worthily if we be juſt, if we be un juſt, marr'd, though in marring ſome, there is neceſſitie of making others, for if one ſall by the Law, tenne to one but another is exalted by the execution of the Law, ſince the corruption of one muſt conclude the genera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of another, though not alwayes in the ſame profeſſion; the corruption of an Apothecary, may be the generation of a Doctor of Phyſicke; the corruption of a Citizen may beget a Courtier, &amp; a Courtier may very well beget an Alderman, the corruption of an Alderman may be the generation of a Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>try Iuſtice, whoſe corrupt ignorance eaſily may beget a tumult,
<pb facs="tcp:177674:29"/> a tumult may beget a Captaine, and the corruption of a Cap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine may beget a Gentleman-Vſher, and a Gentleman-Vſher may beget a Lord, whoſe wit may beget a Poet, and a Poet may get a thouſand pound a yeare, but nothing without cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ruption.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Tre.</speaker>
                  <p>Good Mr. Advocate be pleaſed to leave all digreſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, and ſpeake of the Chancellor.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Adv.</speaker>
                  <p>Your Lordſhip doth very ſeaſonably premoniſh, and I ſhall not neede to leave my ſubject corruption, while I diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>courſe of him, who is the very fenne and ſtigian abiſſe of it, five thouſand and odde hundred foule and impious corrupti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, for I will be briefe; have beene found by ſeverall exami<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nations, and by oathes prov'd againſt this odious and polluted Chancelor, a man of ſo tainted, and contagious a life, that it is a miracle any man enjoyeth his noſtrills, that hath lived with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in the ſent of his offices; he was borne with teeth in his head, by an affidavit of his Midwife, to note his devouring, and hath one toe on his left foote crooked, and in the forme of an Eagles talon, to foretell his rapacitie: What ſhall I ſay? branded, mark'd, and deſign'd in his birth for ſhame and oblo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quie, which appeareth further by a mole under his right eare, with only three Witches haires int, ſtrange and ominous pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dictions of nature.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Tre.</speaker>
                  <l>You have acquainted your ſelfe but very lately</l>
                  <l>With this intelligence, for as I remember</l>
                  <l>Your tongue was guilty of no ſuch character,</l>
                  <l>When hee ſat Iudge upon the Admirall,</l>
                  <l>A pious incorrupt man, a faithfull and fortunate</l>
                  <l>Servant to his King, and one of the greateſt</l>
                  <l>Honours that ever the Admirall received, was</l>
                  <l>That he had ſo noble and juſt a Iudge, this muſt</l>
                  <l>Imply a ſtrange volubilitie in your tongue, or</l>
                  <l>Conſcience, I ſpeake not to diſcountenance any</l>
                  <l>Evidence for the King, but to put you in minde,</l>
                  <l>Mr. Advocate that you had then a better opinion</l>
                  <l>Of my Lord Chancellor.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Adv.</speaker>
                  <p>Your Lordſhip hath moſt aptly interpos'd, and with a word I ſhall eaſily ſatisfie all your judgements; He was then
<pb facs="tcp:177674:30"/> a Judge, and in <hi>Cathedra,</hi> in which he could not erre; it may be your Lordſhips caſes, out of the chaire and ſeate of Iuſtice, he hath his frailties, is loos'ed and expos'd to the conditions of other humane natures; ſo every Iudge, your Lordſhips are not ignorant hath a kinde of priviledge while he is in his ſtate, office and being, and although hee may <hi>quoad ſe,</hi> internally and privately be guilty of bribery of Iuſtice, yet <hi>quoad nos,</hi> and in publike he is an upright and innocent Iudge, we are to take no notice, nay, we deſerved to ſuffer, if wee ſhould detect or ſtaine him; for in that we diſparage the Office, which is the Kings, and may be our owne, but once remov'd from his place by juſt diſhonour of the King, he is no more a Iudge but a common perſon, whom the law takes hold on, and wee are then to forget what hee hath beene, and without partialitie to ſtrip and lay him open to the world, a counterfeit and cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rupt Iudge, as for example, hee may and ought to flouriſh in his greatneſſe, and breake any mans necke, with as much faci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>litie as a jeaſt, but the caſe being altered, and hee downe, eve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry ſubject ſhall be heard, a Wolfe may be appareld in a Lamb<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>skinne; and if every man ſhould be afraid to ſpeake truth, nay and more than truth, if the good of the ſubject which are cli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ents ſometime require it, there would be no remove of Offi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cers, if no remove no motions<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> if no motion in Court no heate, and by conſequence but cold Termes; take away this moving, this removing of Iudges, the Law may bury it ſelfe in Buck<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ram, and the kingdome ſuffer for want of a due execution; and now I hope your Lordſhips are ſatisfied.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Tre.</speaker>
                  <p>Moſt learnedly concluded to acquity our ſelfe.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>1 <hi>Iud.</hi>
                  </speaker>
                  <l>Mr. Advocate, pleaſe you to urge for ſatisfaction</l>
                  <l>Of the world, and clearing the Kings honour, how</l>
                  <l>In juſtly he proceeded againſt the Admirall.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Adv.</speaker>
                  <p>I ſhall obey your Lordſhip—So v<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ſt ſo infi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nite hath beene the impudence of this Chancellor<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> not onely toward the ſubject, but even the ſacred perſon of the King, that I tremble as with a Palſie to remember it. This man, or rather this monſter, having power and commiſſion truſted for the examination of the Lord Admirall, a man perfect in all ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour and juſtice; indeede the very ornament and ſecond
<pb facs="tcp:177674:30"/> flower of <hi>France,</hi> for the <hi>Flower de lis,</hi> is ſacred and above all flowers, and indeede the beſt flower in our garden. Having uſed all wayes to circumvent his innocence by ſuborning and promiſing rewards to his betrayers, by compelling others by the cruelty of tortures, as namely Mounſieur <hi>Allegre</hi> a moſt ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſt and faithfull ſervant to his Lord, tearing and extending his ſinewes upon the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>acke to force a confeſſion to his purpoſe, and finding nothing prevaile upon the invincible vertue of the Admirall.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Sec.</speaker>
                  <p>How he would flatter him?</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Adv.</speaker>
                  <p>Yet moſt maliciouſly proceeded to arraigne him; to be ſhort againſt all colour of Iuſtice condemn'd him of high treaſons; oh thinke what the life of man is, that can never be recompenced; but the life of a juſt man, a man that is the vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gour and glory of our life and nation to be torne to death, and ſacrifis'd beyond the mallice of common perſecution. What Tiger of <hi>Hercanian</hi> breede could have beene ſo cruell? but this is not all? he was not guilty onely of murder, guilty I may ſay <hi>In foro co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſctieniae,</hi> though our good Admirall was miraculouſly preſerv'd, but unto this he added a moſt prodigious &amp; fearefull rape, a rape even upon Iuſtice it ſelf, the very ſoule of our ſtate, for the reſt of the Iudges upon the Bench, venerable images of <hi>Auſtria,</hi> he moſt tyranouſly compel'd to ſet their hands to his moſt unjuſt ſentence; did ever ſtory remember the like outr<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ge and injuſtice; what forfeit, what penalty can be enough to ſatisfie this tranſcendent offence? and yet my good Lords, this is but veniall to the ſacriledge which now followes, and by him committed, not content with this ſentence, not ſatisfied with horrid violence upon the ſacred Tribunall, but hee pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceedes and blaſphemes the very name and honour of the King himſelfe, obſerve that, making him the author and impulſive cauſe of all theſe rapines, juſtifying that he mov'd onely by his ſpeciall command to the death, nay the murder of his moſt faithfull ſubject, tranſlating all his owne blacke and damnable guilt upon the Kings heires, a traytor to his Country, firſt, he conſpires the death of one whom the King loves, and whom e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>very ſubject ought to honour, and then makes it no conſcience to proclaime it the Kings act, &amp; by conſequ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>nce declares him a
<pb facs="tcp:177674:31"/> murderer of his owne, and of his beſt ſubjects.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Within</speaker>
                  <l>An Advocate, an Advocate, teare him in peeces,</l>
                  <l>Teare the Chancellor in peeces.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Tre.</speaker>
                  <l>The people have deepe ſence of the Chancellors in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>juſtice.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Sec.</speaker>
                  <l>We muſt be carefull to prevent their mutiny.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> Iud.</speaker>
                  <l>It will become our wiſedomes to ſecure the court</l>
                  <l>And priſoner.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Tre.</speaker>
                  <l>Captaine of the guard.</l>
                  <l>2. What can you ſay for your ſelfe Lord Chancellor.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Cha.</speaker>
                  <l>Againe, I confeſſe all, and humbly fly to</l>
                  <l>The royall mercy of the King.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Tre.</speaker>
                  <l>And this ſubmiſſion is the way to purchaſe it.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Cha.</speaker>
                  <l>Heare me great Iudges, if you have not loſt</l>
                  <l>For my ſake all your charities, I beſeech you,</l>
                  <l>Let the King know my heart is full of penitence,</l>
                  <l>Calme his high-going ſea, or in that tempeſt</l>
                  <l>I ruine to eternitie, oh my Lords,</l>
                  <l>Conſider your owne places, and the helmes</l>
                  <l>You ſit at, while with all your providence</l>
                  <l>You ſteere, looke forth and ſee devouring quickſands,</l>
                  <l>My ambition now is puniſh'd, and my pride</l>
                  <l>Of ſtate and greatneſſe falling into nothing,</l>
                  <l>I that had never time through vaſt employments</l>
                  <l>To thinke of heaven, feele his revengefull wrath,</l>
                  <l>Boyling my blood, and ſcorching up my entrills,</l>
                  <l>There doomeſday is my conſcience blacke and horrid,</l>
                  <l>For my abuſe of Iuſtice, but no ſtings</l>
                  <l>Prickt with that terrour as the wounds I made</l>
                  <l>Vpon the pious Admirall, ſome good man</l>
                  <l>Beare my repentance thither, he is mercifull,</l>
                  <l>And may encline the King to ſtay his lightning</l>
                  <l>Which threatens my confuſion, that my free</l>
                  <l>Reſigne of title, office, and what elſe</l>
                  <l>My pride look'd at, would buy my poore lives ſafety,</l>
                  <l>For ever baniſh me the court, and let</l>
                  <l>Me waſte my life farre off in ſome Village.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Adv.</speaker>
                  <p>How? Did your Lordſhips note his requeſt to you, he would direct your ſentence to puniſh him with confining
<pb facs="tcp:177674:31"/> him to live in the country, like the Mouſe in the Fable, that having offended to deſerve death, beg'd he might be baniſhed into a Parmiſan. I hope your Lordſhips will be more juſt to the nature of his offences.</p>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Sec.</speaker>
                  <l>I could have wiſh'd him fall on ſofter ground</l>
                  <l>For his good parts.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Tre.</speaker>
                  <p>My Lord, this is your ſentence for you high miſde<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>meanours againſt his Majeſties Iudges, for your unjuſt ſentence of the moſt equall Lord Admirall, for many and foule corrup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions and abuſe of your office, and that infinite ſtaine of the Kings perſon, and honour, we in his Majeſties name, deprive you of your eſtate of Chancellor, &amp; declare you uncapeable of any judiciall office, &amp; beſides condemne you in the ſum of two hundred thouſand crownes; whereof one hundred thouſand to the King, and one hundred thouſand to the Lord Admirall, and what remaineth of your eſtate to goe to the reſtitution of thoſe you have injur'd, and to ſuffer perpetuall impriſonment in the Caſtle, ſo take him to your cuſtody. Your Lordſhips have beene mercifull in his ſentence.</p>
                  <stage>Exit.</stage>
                  <l>They have ſpar'd my life then, that ſome cure may bring,</l>
                  <l>I ſpend it in my prayers for the King.</l>
               </sp>
               <stage>Exeunt<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
               </stage>
               <stage>Enter Admirall in his Gowne and Cap, his Wife.</stage>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Adm.</speaker>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Allegre</hi> I am glad he hath ſo much ſtrength,</l>
                  <l>I prethee let me ſee him.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Wif.</speaker>
                  <l>It will but</l>
                  <l>Enlarge a paſſion—my Lord hee'le come</l>
                  <l>Another time and tender you his ſervice.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Adm.</speaker>
                  <l>Nay then—</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Wif.</speaker>
                  <l>Although I like it not, I muſt obey.</l>
               </sp>
               <stage>Exit.</stage>
               <stage>Enter Allegre ſupported.</stage>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Adm.</speaker>
                  <l>Welcome my injur'd ſervant, what a miſery</l>
                  <l>Ha they made on thee?</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Al.</speaker>
                  <l>Though ſome change appeare</l>
                  <l>Vpon my body, whoſe ſevere affliction</l>
                  <l>Hath brought it thus to be ſuſtained by others,</l>
                  <l>My hurt is ſtill the ſame in faith to you,</l>
                  <l>Not broken with their rage.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Adm.</speaker>
                  <l>Alas poore man!</l>
                  <pb facs="tcp:177674:32"/>
                  <l>Were all my joyes eſſentiall, and ſo mighty</l>
                  <l>As the affected world beleeves I taſte,</l>
                  <l>This object were enough to unſweeten all,</l>
                  <l>Though in thy abſence I had ſuffering,</l>
                  <l>And felt within me a ſtrong ſympathy,</l>
                  <l>While for my ſake their cruelty did vexe,</l>
                  <l>And fright thy nerves with horrour of thy ſence,</l>
                  <l>Yet in this ſpectacle I apprehend</l>
                  <l>More griefe than all my imagination</l>
                  <l>Could let before into me; didſt not curſe me</l>
                  <l>Vpon the torture?</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Al.</speaker>
                  <l>Good my Lord, let not</l>
                  <l>The thought of what I ſuffer'd dwell upon</l>
                  <l>Your memory, they could not puniſh more</l>
                  <l>Then what my duty did oblige to beare</l>
                  <l>For you and Iuſtice, but theres ſome thing in</l>
                  <l>Your lookes, preſents more feare than all the mallice</l>
                  <l>Of my tormentors could affect my ſoule with,</l>
                  <l>That paleneſſe, and the other formes you weare,</l>
                  <l>Would well become a guilty Admirall, and one</l>
                  <l>Loſt to his hopes and honour, not the man</l>
                  <l>Vpon whoſe life the fury of unjuſtice</l>
                  <l>Arm'd with fierce lightning, and the power of thunder,</l>
                  <l>Can make no breach, I was not rack'd till now,</l>
                  <l>Theres more death in that falling eye, than all</l>
                  <l>Rage ever yet brought forth, what accident ſir can blaſt,</l>
                  <l>Can be ſo blacke and fatall to diſtract</l>
                  <l>The calme? the triumph that ſhould ſit upon</l>
                  <l>Your noble brow, mi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>fortune could have no</l>
                  <l>Time to conſpire with fate, ſince you were reſcued</l>
                  <l>By the great arme of providence, nor can</l>
                  <l>Thoſe garlands that now grow about your forehead</l>
                  <l>With all the poyſon of the world be blaſted.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Adm.</speaker>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Allegre,</hi> thou doſt beare thy wounds upon thee,</l>
                  <l>In wide and ſpacious characters, but in</l>
                  <l>The volumne of my ſadneſſe thou doſt want</l>
                  <l>An eye to reade an open force, hath torne</l>
                  <l>Thy manly ſinewes which ſometime may cure</l>
                  <pb facs="tcp:177674:32"/>
                  <l>The engine is not ſeene that wounds thy Maſter,</l>
                  <l>Paſt all the remedy of art or time,</l>
                  <l>The flatteries of Court, of fame or honours,</l>
                  <l>Thus in the Sommer a tall flouriſhing tree,</l>
                  <l>Tranſplanted by ſtrong hand, with all her leaves</l>
                  <l>And blooming pride upon her makes a ſhew</l>
                  <l>Of Spring, tempting the eye with wanton bloſſome,</l>
                  <l>But not the Sunne with all her amorous ſmiles,</l>
                  <l>The dewes of mornings, or the teares of night,</l>
                  <l>Can roote her fibers in the earth agen,</l>
                  <l>Or make her boſome kinde, to growth and bearing,</l>
                  <l>But the tree withers, and thoſe very beames</l>
                  <l>That once were naturall warmth to her ſoft verdure</l>
                  <l>Dry up her ſap and ſhoote a feaver through</l>
                  <l>The barke and rinde, till ſhe becomes a burthen</l>
                  <l>To that which gave her life: ſo <hi>Chabot, Chabot.</hi>
                  </l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Al.</speaker>
                  <l>Wonder in apprehenſion, I muſt</l>
                  <l>Suſpect your health indeede.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Adm.</speaker>
                  <l>No no, thou ſhanot</l>
                  <l>Be troubled, I but ſtirr'd thee with a morrall,</l>
                  <l>Thats empty containes nothing, I am well,</l>
                  <l>See I can walke poore man, thou haſt not ſtrength yet.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Al.</speaker>
                  <l>What accident is ground of this diſtraction?</l>
               </sp>
               <stage>Enter Admirall.</stage>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Adm.</speaker>
                  <l>Thou haſt not heard yet whats become oth' Chancel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lor?</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Al.</speaker>
                  <l>Not yet my Lord.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Adm.</speaker>
                  <l>Poore gentleman, when I thinke</l>
                  <l>Vpon the King, I've balme enough to cure</l>
                  <l>A thouſand wounds, have I not <hi>Allegre?</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>Was ever bountious mercy read in ſtory,</l>
                  <l>Like his upon my life, condemn'd for ſacrifice</l>
                  <l>By Law, and ſnatch'd out of the flame unlooked for,</l>
                  <l>And unpetitioned? but his juſtice then</l>
                  <l>That wod not ſpare whom his owne love made great,</l>
                  <l>But give me up to the moſt cruell teſt</l>
                  <l>Of Iudges, for ſome boldneſſe in defence</l>
                  <l>Of my owne merits, and my honeſt faith to him</l>
                  <l>Was rare, paſt example.</l>
               </sp>
               <stage>
                  <pb facs="tcp:177674:33"/>Enter Father.</stage>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Fa.</speaker>
                  <l>Sir, the King</l>
                  <l>Is comming hither.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Al.</speaker>
                  <l>It will</l>
                  <l>Become my duty ſir to leave you now.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Adm,</speaker>
                  <l>Stay by all meanes <hi>Allegre,</hi> 'tſhall concerne<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> you,</l>
                  <l>I'me infinitely honor'd in his preſence.</l>
               </sp>
               <stage>Enter King, Queene, Conſtable, and Wife.</stage>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>King.</speaker>
                  <l>Madam be comforted, Ile be his Phiſitian.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Wif.</speaker>
                  <l>Pray heaven you may.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>King.</speaker>
                  <l>No ceremoniall knees,</l>
                  <l>Give me thy heart, my deare, my honeſt <hi>Chabot,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>And yet in vaine I chalenge that tis here</l>
                  <l>Already in my owne, and ſhall be cheriſh'd</l>
                  <l>With care of my beſt life, violence</l>
                  <l>Shall raviſh it from my poſſeſſion,</l>
                  <l>Not thoſe diſtempers that infirme my blood</l>
                  <l>And ſpirits ſhall betray it to a feare,</l>
                  <l>When time and nature joyne to diſpoſſeſſe</l>
                  <l>My body of a cold and languiſhing breath,</l>
                  <l>No ſtroake in all my arteries, but ſilence</l>
                  <l>In every faculty, yet diſſect me then,</l>
                  <l>And in my heart, the world ſhall read thee living,</l>
                  <l>And by the vertue of thy name write there,</l>
                  <l>That part of me ſhall never putrifie,</l>
                  <l>When I am loſt in all my other duſt.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Adm.</speaker>
                  <l>You too much honour your poore ſervant ſir,</l>
                  <l>My heart diſpares ſo rich a monument;</l>
                  <l>But when it dies—</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>King.</speaker>
                  <l>I wonot heare a ſound</l>
                  <l>Of any thing that trenched upon death,</l>
                  <l>He ſpeakes the funerall of my crowne that propheſies</l>
                  <l>So unkinde a fate, weele live and die together,</l>
                  <l>And by that duty which hath taught you hitherto,</l>
                  <l>All loyall and juſt ſervices I charge thee,</l>
                  <l>Preſerve thy heart for me and thy reward,</l>
                  <l>Which now ſhall crowne thy merits.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Adm.</speaker>
                  <l>I have found</l>
                  <pb facs="tcp:177674:33"/>
                  <l>A glorious harveſt in your ſavour ſir,</l>
                  <l>And by this overſlow of royall grace,</l>
                  <l>All my deſerts are ſhadowes and ſlie from mee,</l>
                  <l>I have not in the wealth of my deſires,</l>
                  <l>Enough to pay you now, yet you encourage me</l>
                  <l>To make one ſuite.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>King.</speaker>
                  <l>So ſoone as nam'd poſſeſſe it.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Adm.</speaker>
                  <l>You would be pleas'd take notice of this Gentleman,</l>
                  <l>A Secretary of mine.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Con.</speaker>
                  <l>Mounſieur <hi>Allegre,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>He that was rack'd ſir for your Admirall.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Adm.</speaker>
                  <l>His limbs want ſtrength to tender their full duty,</l>
                  <l>An honeſt man that ſuffers for my ſake.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>King.</speaker>
                  <l>He ſhall be deare to us, for what has paſt ſir</l>
                  <l>By the unjuſtice of our Chancellors power,</l>
                  <l>Weele ſtudy to recompence, ith' meane time that office</l>
                  <l>You exercis'd for <hi>Chabot</hi> we tranſlate</l>
                  <l>To our ſelfe, you ſhall be our Secretary.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Al.</speaker>
                  <l>This is</l>
                  <l>An honour above my weake deſert, and ſhall</l>
                  <l>Oblige the ſervice of my life to ſatisfie it.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Adm.</speaker>
                  <l>You are gracious, and in this act have put</l>
                  <l>All our complaints to ſilence, you <hi>Allegre,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <stage>Enter Treſuror, Secretary.</stage>
                  <l>Cheriſh your health, and feeble limbs which cannot</l>
                  <l>Without much prejudice be thus employ'd;</l>
                  <l>All my beſt wiſhes with thee.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Al.</speaker>
                  <l>All my prayers</l>
                  <l>Are duties to your Lordſhip—</l>
               </sp>
               <stage>Exit.</stage>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>King.</speaker>
                  <l>Tis too little,</l>
                  <l>Can forfeit of his place, wealth, and a laſting</l>
                  <l>Impriſonment purge his offences to</l>
                  <l>Our honeſt Admirall, had our perſon beene</l>
                  <l>Exempted from his mallice, he did perſecute</l>
                  <l>The life of <hi>Chabot</hi> with an equall wrath,</l>
                  <l>You ſhould have powr'd death on his treacherous head,</l>
                  <l>I revoke all your ſentences, and make</l>
                  <l>Him that was wrong'd full Maſter of his deſtiny,</l>
                  <pb facs="tcp:177674:34"/>
                  <l>Be thou his judge.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Adm.</speaker>
                  <l>O farre be ſuch injuſtice,</l>
                  <l>I know his doome is heavie, and I begge</l>
                  <l>Where mercy may be let into his ſentence</l>
                  <l>For my ſake you would ſoften it, I have</l>
                  <l>Glory enough to be ſet right in yours,</l>
                  <l>And my deare countries thought, and by an act</l>
                  <l>With ſuch apparent notice to the world.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>King.</speaker>
                  <l>Expreſſe it in ſome joy then.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Adm.</speaker>
                  <l>I will ſtrive</l>
                  <l>To ſhew that pious gratitude to you but—</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Kng.</speaker>
                  <l>But what</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Adm.</speaker>
                  <l>My frame hath lately ſir beene tane a peec<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>s,</l>
                  <l>And but now put together, the leaſt force</l>
                  <l>Of mirth will ſhake and unjoynt all my reaſon,</l>
                  <l>Your patience royall ſir.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>King.</speaker>
                  <l>Ile have no patience,</l>
                  <l>If thou forget the courage of a man.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Adm.</speaker>
                  <l>My ſtrength would <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>latter me.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>King.</speaker>
                  <l>Phiſitian<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>
                  </l>
                  <l>Now I begin to feare his apprehenſion,</l>
                  <l>Why how is <hi>Chabots</hi> ſpirit falne?</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Qu.</speaker>
                  <l>Twere beſt</l>
                  <l>He were conveid to his bed.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Wif.</speaker>
                  <l>How ſoone turn'd widdow.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Adm.</speaker>
                  <l>Who would not wiſh to live to ſerve your goodnes.</l>
                  <l>Stand from me, you betray me with your feares,</l>
                  <l>The plummets may fall off that hang upon</l>
                  <l>My heart, they were but thoughts at firſt, or if</l>
                  <l>They weigh me downe to death let not my eyes</l>
                  <l>Cloſe with another object then the King,</l>
                  <l>Let him be laſt I looke on.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>King.</speaker>
                  <l>I would not have him loſt for my whole Kingdome.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Con.</speaker>
                  <l>He may recover ſir.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>King.</speaker>
                  <l>I ſee it fall,</l>
                  <l>For Iuſtice being the proppe of every Kingdome</l>
                  <l>And mine broke, violating him that was</l>
                  <l>The knot and contract of it all in him,</l>
                  <l>It already falling in my eate,</l>
                  <pb facs="tcp:177674:34"/>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Pompey</hi> could heare it thunder, when the Senate</l>
                  <l>And Capitoll were deafe, ſo heavens loud chiding,</l>
                  <l>Ile have another ſentence for my Chancellor,</l>
                  <l>Vnleſſe my <hi>Chabot</hi> live,</l>
                  <l>In a Prince</l>
                  <l>What a ſwift executioner is a frowne,</l>
                  <l>Eſpecially of great and noble ſoules;</l>
                  <l>How is it with my <hi>Philip?</hi>
                  </l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Adm.</speaker>
                  <l>I muſt begge</l>
                  <l>One other boone.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>King.</speaker>
                  <l>Vpon condition</l>
                  <l>My <hi>Chabot</hi> will collect his ſcatter'd ſpirits,</l>
                  <l>And be himſelfe agen, he ſhall divide</l>
                  <l>My Kingdome with me.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Fa.</speaker>
                  <l>Sweete King.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Adm.</speaker>
                  <l>I obſerve</l>
                  <l>A fierce and killing wrath engendred in you;</l>
                  <l>For my ſake, as you wiſh me ſtrength to ſerve you,</l>
                  <l>Forgive your Chancellor, let not the ſtory</l>
                  <l>Of <hi>Philip Chabot</hi> read hereafter draw</l>
                  <l>A teare from any family, I beſeech</l>
                  <l>Your royall mercy on his life, and free</l>
                  <l>Remiſſion of all ſeaſure upon his ſtate,</l>
                  <l>I have no comfort elſe.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>King.</speaker>
                  <l>Endeavour</l>
                  <l>But thy owne health, and pronounce generall pardon</l>
                  <l>To all through <hi>France.</hi>
                  </l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Adm.</speaker>
                  <l>Sir I muſt kneele to thanke you,</l>
                  <l>It is not ſeal'd elſe, your bleſt hand live happy,</l>
                  <l>May all you truſt have no leſſe faith then <hi>Chabot,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>Oh.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Wif.</speaker>
                  <l>His heart is broken.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Fa.</speaker>
                  <l>And kneeling ſir,</l>
                  <l>As his ambition were in death to ſhew</l>
                  <l>The truth of his obedience.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Con.</speaker>
                  <l>I feard this iſſue.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Tre.</speaker>
                  <l>Hees paſt hope.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>King.</speaker>
                  <l>He has a victory ins death, this world</l>
                  <pb facs="tcp:177674:35"/>
                  <l>Deſerv'd him not, how ſoone he was tranſlated</l>
                  <l>To glorious eternitie, tis too late</l>
                  <l>To fright the ayre with words, my teare<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> embalme him.</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Wif.</speaker>
                  <l>What can become of me?</l>
               </sp>
               <sp>
                  <speaker>Qu.</speaker>
                  <l>Ile be your husband Madam, and with care</l>
                  <l>Supply your childrens father, to your father</l>
                  <l>Ile be a ſonne, in what ou<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> love or power</l>
                  <l>Can ſerve his friends, <hi>Chabot</hi> ſhall nere be wanting,</l>
                  <l>The greateſt loſſe is mine, paſt ſcale or recompence,</l>
                  <l>We will proceede no further gainſt the Chancellor,</l>
                  <l>To the charitie of our Admirall he owes</l>
                  <l>His life which ever baniſh'd to a priſon,</l>
                  <l>Shall not beget in us, or in the ſubject</l>
                  <l>N<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>w feares of his injuſtice, for his fortunes</l>
                  <l>Great and acquir'd corruptly, tis our will</l>
                  <l>They make juſt reſtitution for all wrongs</l>
                  <l>That ſhall within a yeare be prov'd againſt him;</l>
                  <l>O <hi>Chabot</hi> that ſhall boaſt as many monuments</l>
                  <l>As there be hearts in <hi>France,</hi> which as they grow,</l>
                  <l>Shall with more love enſhrine thee, Kings they ſay,</l>
                  <l>Die not, or ſtarve ſucceſſion, oh why</l>
                  <l>Should that ſtand firme, and Kings themſelves deſpaire,</l>
                  <l>To finde their ſubject ſtill in the next heire<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
                  </l>
               </sp>
               <stage>Exeunt.</stage>
            </div>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
